<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CMP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcmp</journal-id>
<journal-title>Conflict Management and Peace Science</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0738-8942</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1549-9219</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0738894212456951</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0738894212456951</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>No Good Deed Goes Unpunished: Refugees, Humanitarian Aid, and Terrorism</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Seung-Whan</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-0738894212456951">Department of Political Science, University of Illinois at Chicago</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Salehyan</surname><given-names>Idean</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-0738894212456951">Department of Political Science, University of North Texas</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0738894212456951">Idean Salehyan, University of North Texas, Denton, TX 76203, USA. Email: <email>idean@unt.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>30</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>53</fpage>
<lpage>75</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Peace Science Society (International)</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We examine the consequences of hosting refugees for domestic and international terrorism. In line with the old saying, “no good deed goes unpunished”, we argue that the infusion of aid resources provides militant groups with opportunities for looting and for attacking foreign targets. A cross-national, time-series data analysis of 154 countries for the years 1970–2007 shows evidence that countries with many refugees are more likely to experience both domestic and international terrorism. This finding implies that while the international community should strive to reduce the number of refugees by preventing the eruption of major conflict events, individual countries should find a way of maintaining the balance between humanitarianism toward refugees and providing safe, secure environments for refugees and those that assist them.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>humanitarian aid</kwd>
<kwd>refugees</kwd>
<kwd>terrorism</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Refugee crises are typically thought of in humanitarian terms. Men, women, and children are forced to flee their homes and livelihoods because of the traumatic experience of political violence and persecution. While the humanitarian dimensions of refugee flight are clearly important, a growing number of scholars have noted the security <italic>consequences</italic> of forced migration (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0738894212456951">Weiner, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0738894212456951">Lischer, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0738894212456951">Salehyan and Gleditsch, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0738894212456951">Salehyan, 2009</xref>). Refugees are certainly the victims of violence, but they can also spread conflict and instability to their host countries, particularly if hosts are unwilling or unable to contain security externalities. As one of the most dramatic examples, the protracted conflict in the Democratic Republic of the Congo was triggered by a large wave of migrants fleeing violence and instability in Rwanda (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0738894212456951">Prunier, 2008</xref>). Similarly, refugees from Darfur and associated cross-border violence have destabilized neighboring Chad.</p>
<p>The literature on transnational influences on violent conflict is relatively recent as most studies continue to focus on domestic variables. When existing studies examine the causes of political violence—i.e. terrorism, insurgency, and civil war—they often focus on domestic factors such as the state of the economy, regime type, ethnic cleavages, and physical terrain rather than the broader regional and international environment (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0738894212456951">Fearon and Laitin, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0738894212456951">Enders and Sandler, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0738894212456951">Piazza, 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0738894212456951">2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0738894212456951">LaFree and Ackerman, 2009</xref>). Although a few studies link refugee influxes to the spread of civil war (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0738894212456951">Salehyan and Gleditsch, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0738894212456951">Buhaug and Gleditsch, 2008</xref>), they neglect to explore lower-level political violence, such as sporadic terrorism and guerilla attacks. This is unfortunate given that such violence occurs frequently enough to threaten national security and it may evolve into large scale violence if not properly contained.</p>
<p>Even as previous research finds that refugees may contribute to the transnational diffusion of arms and combatants, studies overlook the question of whether the inflow of refugees induces terrorist attacks. The two recent surveys by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0738894212456951">Krieger and Meierrieks (2011)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0738894212456951">Gassebner and Luechinger (2011)</xref> indicate no previous studies that analyze the relationship between terrorism and refugee migration. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0738894212456951">Figure 1</xref>, there is a global trend in which terrorist events and refugee flows are related during the period from 1970 to 2007; an upward swing of terrorist attacks and refugee influxes took place until the early 1990s and then the former slowed down much more quickly than the latter. A simple correlation analysis shows that these two factors are correlated with each other (the correlation coefficient is 0.46). Nonetheless, such patterns warrant further systematic analysis.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0738894212456951" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Global Trend of Terrorism and Inflows of Refugees, 1970–2007.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0738894212456951-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>Our research examines how refugees are associated with domestic and international terrorism during the past four decades. While others have looked at the consequences of refugee flows for full-blown civil wars and insurgencies, sporadic violent attacks and terrorist incidents can contribute to general instability and can escalate to more severe crises. Sporadic attacks against refugees or aid workers may not be sufficient to be included in most civil war data, but they can have devastating effects on the communities in question and significantly disrupt humanitarian relief efforts. Militant groups can mobilize among refugee communities and migrants may be subject to anti-foreigner attacks. In addition, we argue that the infusion of aid workers, food, shelter, and other humanitarian supplies makes host countries more prone to terrorist attacks, as militants seek to exploit these resources. While refugee assistance is essential to forestall humanitarian catastrophes and should be lauded, without proper security measures in place, aid workers and the resources they provide are subject to attack.</p>
<p>To measure terrorist activities, this study utilizes the worldwide terrorism dataset recently compiled by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0738894212456951">Enders et al. (2011)</xref>, who systematically separated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0738894212456951">LaFree and Dugan’s (2007)</xref> Global Terrorism Database (GTD) into domestic and international terrorist incidents. To operationalize the influence of refugees, this study relies on the United States Committee for Refugees and Immigrants’ <italic>World Refugee Survey</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0738894212456951">Marshall, 2008</xref>). A cross-national, time-series data analysis of 154 countries during the period from 1970 to 2007 shows evidence that, <italic>ceteris paribus</italic>, countries with high numbers of refugees are more likely to experience both domestic and international terrorism. Our results are robust to a number of alternative modeling specifications. This finding implies that while the international community should strive to reduce the number of refugees by preventing the eruption of major conflict, humanitarian efforts must be accompanied by robust security provisions.</p>
<p>This study proceeds in several sections. The first section defines key terms of terrorism and refugees. The second section reviews the existing literature. The third section puts forward a conceptual linkage between refugees and terrorism. The fourth section explains the research design with statistical model building, operationalization, and data sources. The fifth section presents a discussion of the empirical results. The sixth section provides several illustrative examples of terrorist attacks on refugee aid resources. The last section sums up the main findings and presents policy implications.</p>
<sec id="section1-0738894212456951">
<title>Defining Terrorism and Refugees</title>
<p>Terrorism and refugees are contentious concepts that require clarification. Terrorism is often an ill-defined term and must be clearly delineated. This study follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0738894212456951">LaFree and Dugan’s (2007)</xref> definition of terrorism as an intentional act of violence or threat of violence by a non-state actor to attain political, economic, religious, or social goals. This is a very broad definition that encompasses many different types of groups and activities. LaFree and Dugan rely on this definition to compile the Global Terrorism Database (GTD) that combines domestic and international terrorism but excludes state terrorism.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0738894212456951">1</xref></sup> When the perpetrators and targets are from the same country, the act of violence is defined as domestic terrorism. An example is the Oklahoma City bombing committed by American-born Timothy McVeigh. International terrorism is a situation in which a terrorist incident in Country A involves perpetrators, victims, institutions, governments, or citizens of Country B (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0738894212456951">Enders and Sandler, 2006</xref>: 7; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0738894212456951">Dugan, 2010</xref>), such as Hezbollah’s attacks against American, French, and other allied troops in Lebanon in the 1980s.</p>
<p>It is important to note that the GTD’s broad definition of terrorism also includes attacks during “conventional” civil wars and insurgencies. For instance, violence by UNITA in Angola and the PKK in Turkey—even directed at state security forces—is included in the database. The advantage of using the GTD, as opposed to conventional measures of civil war, is that the former is not a dichotomous “state of affairs”. Most civil war datasets code a country as being in a civil war or not, based on some threshold for violence, such as 1,000 battle-deaths. The GTD encompasses attacks during civil wars, but also one-off events and low-level violence that does not meet the threshold for inclusion in other datasets. Moreover, such count measures of events rather than a binary classification enable researchers to gauge the frequency of violence incidents.</p>
<p>A refugee is defined by international law as one who, “owing to a well-founded fear of being persecuted for reasons of race, religion, nationality, membership of a particular social group, or political opinion, is outside the country of his nationality, and is unable to or, owing to such fear, is unwilling to avail himself of the protection of that country”.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0738894212456951">2</xref></sup> In practice, determining exactly who is a refugee can be difficult as people leave their homes for a variety of considerations including persecution, disaster, social unrest, and civil war. Most analysts and relief agencies (including the UN High Commissioner for Refugees) take a much broader view and consider anyone fleeing general violence, including civil war, genocide, and insurgent attacks—even if individual persecution cannot be ascertained—to be a refugee. We adopt this broader definition in our analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0738894212456951">
<title>Literature Review</title>
<p>Forced migration has a significant impact on states, international organizations, and non-governmental organizations due to humanitarian and security concerns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0738894212456951">Crisp, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0738894212456951">Lischer, 2005</xref>). However, the existing literature on refugees and security remains in its infancy, as international relations scholars have only recently considered the security implications of international migration (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0738894212456951">Weiner, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0738894212456951">Salehyan, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0738894212456951">Greenhill, 2010</xref>). Undoubtedly, the events of 11 September 2001 prompted researchers to review border security policies and the potential for terrorist networks to take advantage of immigration systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0738894212456951">Givens et al., 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Several studies document the framing of refugees as potential terrorist threats by numerous states in legislative and policy responses (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0738894212456951">Brouwer, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0738894212456951">Freilich et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0738894212456951">Nezer, 2006</xref>). Adelman (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0738894212456951">2002</xref>: 5) characterizes this trend as the “overlap between refugee and security concerns”. This overlap instigated changes in the way that asylum claims are handled, the number of asylum claims granted, and the detainment and exclusion of certain refugees on the basis of their region of origin, most notably from the Middle East and the South Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0738894212456951">Andreas and Biersteker, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0738894212456951">Brouwer, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0738894212456951">Sidebotham, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0738894212456951">Welch and Schuster, 2005</xref>). For example, after the Terrorism Act of 2000, Muslim refugees in Britain are increasingly being targeted as potential terrorist threats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0738894212456951">Fekete, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0738894212456951">Collyer, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0738894212456951">Nezer, 2006</xref>). On the contrary, some studies show no evidence for a direct relationship between forced migrants arriving in Europe and the risk of terrorism in the EU. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0738894212456951">Howard (2010)</xref> contends that there is no causal link despite post-9/11 fears (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0738894212456951">Guild, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>The literature that examines the relationship between refugees and security can be traced back to the period before the 9/11 terrorist attacks. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0738894212456951">Whitaker (1998)</xref> argues that “golden age” of generous refugee resettlement efforts by Western democracies was largely a by-product of Cold War security and propaganda. That is, in the ideological war between democracy and communism, refugees were a key component in this confrontation as defectors fleeing leftist regimes were greeted openly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0738894212456951">Jessen-Petersen, 1994</xref>: 1–2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0738894212456951">Rosenblum and Salehyan, 2004</xref>). However, the collapse of the former Soviet Union made many countries rethink their refugee policies. Selective refugee policies were characterized as less humanitarian and more concerned with granting asylum claims to, more or less, potential “ideal” citizens.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0738894212456951">3</xref></sup> Armed conflicts have also been linked to refugee flows. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0738894212456951">Dowty and Loescher (1996)</xref> assert that humanitarian aid and intervention were often invoked by the international community in the post-Cold War era on the grounds of preventing massive refugee flows and regional instability. For example, the US justified interventions in Haiti in 1994 and Kosovo in 1999 because of the large displacement of people and the regional externalities that they posed. These studies have mainly focused on refugees to developed countries, rather than a global analysis. More recently, studies have linked refugee flows to the transnational spread of civil and interstate war (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0738894212456951">Lischer, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0738894212456951">Salehyan and Gleditsch, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0738894212456951">Buhaug and Gleditsch, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0738894212456951">Salehyan, 2008</xref>). Yet, these studies focus on large-scale civil wars and state failure rather than sporadic political violence and terrorism, which do not necessarily target government forces.</p>
<p>Although these existing studies of refugees examine both security and humanitarian dimensions, they have neglected to address the possibility that refugees and the infusion of humanitarian resources may help attract terrorist attacks. This is an important issue since humanitarian activities such as the infusion of aid workers, food, and shelter may affect the internal security of host countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0738894212456951">Lischer, 2005</xref>), which then have less incentive to maintain humanitarian refugee policies. In the next section, we offer a more detailed theoretical argument on the refugee–terrorism connection.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0738894212456951">
<title>Why Hosting More Refugees Provokes Terrorist Incidents</title>
<p>There may exist numerous reasons why refugee crises invite terrorist attacks. First, the conflict from which the refugees fled may spill across borders as militants attack refugee encampments in order to punish or intimidate their political rivals. Second, insurgent groups and terrorist organizations may recruit from within the refugee camps. Previous studies have shown that poor young males with few economic opportunities are most likely to join violent factions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0738894212456951">Humphreys and Weinstein, 2008</xref>). Low opportunity costs for joining along with finding a sense of purpose may incline people to leave the camps and enlist in an armed group. Third, the presence of refugees and foreigners in general may prompt right-wing anti-immigrant groups to attack people who are ethnically and culturally different. These three factors are those most commonly discussed in the literature on refugees and the spread of conflict.</p>
<p>In this study, we propose an additional factor—humanitarian aid—that has not been discussed much among analysts. We argue that the infusion of aid resources during refugee crises—including food, medical supplies, and vehicles—provides opportunities for looting and theft by violent groups. In addition, relief workers are often targets of abduction, to be held for ransom. The rebellion-as-crime, or “greed”, literature in conflict research has primarily focused on the capture and sale of valuable commodities such as drugs and conflict diamonds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0738894212456951">Collier and Hoeffler, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0738894212456951">Lujala et al., 2005</xref>). Yet, aid resources, particularly in violent contexts, are often another prime target for theft and provide an easy opportunity for militants to acquire resources.</p>
<p>In addition to the theft of humanitarian resources and the abduction of aid workers for ransom, humanitarian workers may also become a target because of their ethnicity, nationality, or religion. Rather than travelling abroad to conduct attacks in their selected country, extremists can choose to target expatriates in their midst. For instance, following widespread outrage over the publication of offensive cartoons of the Prophet Muhammad by a Danish newspaper, aid agencies from Denmark operating in Muslim countries were put on alert (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0738894212456951">McLaughlin and Kilner, 2006</xref>). Refugee communities often attract workers from Western industrialized nations who work with non-governmental organizations, international relief organizations, or religious charities. Insurgents or terrorists seeking international targets may focus their attacks on such individuals.</p>
<p>Aid agencies are keenly aware of these risks. The International Committee of the Red Cross publishes a comprehensive set of safety guidelines for workers in conflict zones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0738894212456951">Roberts, 2006</xref>). Moreover, scholars are beginning to document and conduct analyses of attacks against aid workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0738894212456951">Fast, 2010</xref>); others have noted that humanitarian relief to refugees can inadvertently be channeled to militant groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0738894212456951">Lischer, 2005</xref>). Yet, to date, there has not been a systematic quantitative study of the link between refugee flows and terrorist attacks. We do not claim that one mechanism is more or less important than the others, but that there are several non-exclusive paths to violence. Thus, our main hypothesis is that: <italic>as the number of refugees increases in a country, the number of terrorist attacks will also increase</italic>. We note that this should apply to both domestic terrorism and international terrorism. Domestic militants may predate on refugee communities for purely local goals. Internationally-minded groups may begin to target foreign assets and individuals.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0738894212456951">
<title>Research Design</title>
<p>To test the refugee hypothesis, this study collects data on 154 countries during the period from 1970 to 2007 (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table7-0738894212456951">Appendix 1</xref> for the country list). This data collection makes the country-year the unit of analysis. We employ three different but related dependent variables. The first variable is a count measure that captures the total number of domestic and international terrorist incidents that occurred in a country per year. The second and third variables disaggregate the first measure into domestic and international terrorist incidents. The data come from the worldwide terrorism dataset of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0738894212456951">Enders et al. (2011)</xref>, who systematically separated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0738894212456951">LaFree and Dugan’s (2007)</xref> Global Terrorism Database (GTD)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0738894212456951">4</xref></sup> into domestic and international terrorist incidents. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0738894212456951">Enders et al. (2011</xref>: 3) underscore that “no other article provides such a complete partitioning of domestic and transnational incidents”.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0738894212456951">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>The main independent variable, refugees, records the number of refugees that a country receives from other countries. In order to correct the positive skew in the data and to avoid the mathematical problem of log-transforming zeros, this study takes the natural log of the number of refugees after adding 1 to the base. Data on refugee flows come from the <italic>World Refugee Survey</italic> from the Population Data Unit of the United States Committee for Refugees and Immigrants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0738894212456951">Marshall, 2008</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0738894212456951">6</xref></sup> Ideally, we would also like data on the number of aid workers and humanitarian supplies to refugees in a country, but unfortunately such data are not available for all countries during the time period.</p>
<p>To ensure the estimated results are not subject to omitted variable bias and thus flawed, this study includes six control variables: democracy, state failure, economic development, population, a post-Cold War indicator, and a lagged term for the dependent variable.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0738894212456951">7</xref></sup> Some studies show that democracy is inversely related to terrorism since democracy provides peaceful channels of conflict resolution (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0738894212456951">Schmid, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0738894212456951">Eyerman, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0738894212456951">Li, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0738894212456951">Choi, 2010</xref>). Conversely, other studies report that democracy allows more terrorist activity due to the commitment to individual freedoms which facilitates action (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0738894212456951">Eubank and Weinberg, 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0738894212456951">2001</xref>). We remain agnostic about the influence of democracy, since it is not our main variable of interest. The democracy variable is taken from the Polity dataset and is a 21-point variable ranging from pure autocracy (–10) to pure democracy (+10) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0738894212456951">Marshall and Jaggers, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Previous studies find empirical support for the positive relationship between failed states and terrorism (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0738894212456951">LaFree et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0738894212456951">Piazza, 2008</xref>). Since the political leadership of failed states is too weak to exercise legal authority over much of its territory, it is bound to attract a variety of terrorist activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0738894212456951">Rotberg, 2002</xref>). The failed state variable ranges from 0 to 17 by combining the severity of ethnic wars (0–4), revolutionary wars (0–4), adverse regime changes (0–4), and genocides and politicides (0–5). Data come from the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0738894212456951">Political Instability Task Force (2007)</xref>.</p>
<p>Several recent studies show that developed countries are more likely to experience terrorism since they are symbols of the political and economic status quo and because they provide more terrorist targets than less developed countries (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0738894212456951">Choi, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0738894212456951">Piazza, 2011</xref>). Economic success attracts more terrorist attacks because economic inequality is assessed globally in the form of poor versus rich countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0738894212456951">Krieger and Meierrieks, 2011</xref>; for a dissenting view, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0738894212456951">Krueger, 2007</xref>). This economic development variable is measured by the logged real GDP per capita, adjusted for purchasing power parity. Data for this variable are obtained from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0738894212456951">Gleditsch (2002)</xref> and are updated with base data from the new 6.3 version of the Penn World Tables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0738894212456951">Heston et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Since highly populated countries encounter more difficulty providing an adequate level of security to the entire population, they are at a greater risk of terrorist plots and attacks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0738894212456951">Eyerman, 1998</xref>). This positive correlation may also be due to a scale effect. More populous countries simply tend to experience more terrorism (in absolute numbers) because they harbor more terrorists and provide more targets than small countries. Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0738894212456951">Savun and Phillips (2009)</xref> are not the only ones who report the positive effect of population (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0738894212456951">Krieger and Meierrieks, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0738894212456951">Gassebner and Luechinger, 2011</xref>), they provide evidence that, irrespective of the type of terrorist attacks, highly populated countries experience more terrorist incidents than their smaller counterparts. With this in mind, the population variable, measured by the logged total population, is expected to increase terrorism. Data for this variable are taken from the US Census Bureau (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0738894212456951">2008</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0738894212456951">Enders and Sandler (2006)</xref> provide evidence that the total number of terrorist attacks has decreased with the end of Soviet funding of left-wing groups (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0738894212456951">Choi, 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0738894212456951">2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0738894212456951">Young and Findley, 2011</xref>). To account for a systemic decrease in terrorist activity after the end of the Cold War, a post-Cold War variable is included. The post-Cold War variable is coded 1 after 1991 and is otherwise coded 0.</p>
<p>This study also controls for the past history of terrorism by adding a lagged dependent variable on the right-hand side of the equation. Although the lagged dependent variable has the potential to “soak up” the explanatory power of theoretically interesting independent variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0738894212456951">Achen, 2000</xref>), it is theoretically appropriate because, as previous research demonstrates, countries with past incidents of terrorism are likely to be more vulnerable to terrorism in the present or in the future (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0738894212456951">Savun and Phillips, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0738894212456951">Young and Findlely, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Since the dependent variable is operationalized as the total number of terrorist events per year, this study employs a negative binomial maximum-likelihood regression model with Huber-White robust standard errors, clustered by country. This estimation method is chosen over Poisson regression as the variance of the terrorism data is much larger than its mean. Negative binomial regression adds a dispersion parameter to model the unobserved heterogeneity among observations, allowing the variance to exceed the mean, which essentially corrects for the over-dispersion found in Poisson regression models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0738894212456951">Long and Freese, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0738894212456951">Hilbe, 2007</xref>). Theoretically, it is unlikely that violent incidents will cause refugee <italic>inflows</italic> to the country concerned. However, all the predictors are lagged one year behind the outcome variable to ensure that the predictors cause the outcome variable rather than the other way around.</p>
<p>The terrorism data may be prone to the problem of excessive zero observations. Indeed, 56 percent of the cases are non-events. To assuage this potential problem, for robustness, this study turns to the rare event logit model developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0738894212456951">Tomz et al. (1999)</xref>, expanded upon by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0738894212456951">King and Zeng (2001)</xref>, and recently applied in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0738894212456951">Choi’s (2010)</xref> study on international terrorism and the rule of law.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0738894212456951">8</xref></sup> The rare event logit effectively addresses the issue of excessive zeros in the data. To run this logit technique, the event count dependent variable is converted into a binary measure, coded 1 if any attacks are recorded and 0 otherwise. To deal with temporal dependence in our data, we employ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0738894212456951">Carter and Signorino’s (2010)</xref> method of including the cubic polynomial of time.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0738894212456951">9</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0738894212456951">
<title>Empirical Results</title>
<p>We now turn to a discussion of our results. Model 1 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0738894212456951">Table 1</xref> employs negative binomial regression and serves as a base model in order to examine whether inflows of refugees are positively related with terrorism in general; Models 2 to 7 report various types of robustness tests. Model 1 presents results in which the refugee variable is statistically significant at the 0.001 level and in the hypothesized direction. It appears that as countries host more refugees, they are more likely to encounter terrorist incidents, domestic or international. Model 1 also indicates that all six control variables achieve significance, consistent with theoretical expectations. Democracy is positively associated with terrorism; failed states suffer from more terrorist incidents; developed countries experience more terrorism; highly populated countries are more likely to be plagued with terrorism; the post-Cold War period is exposed to less terrorism; and countries with a terrorist history are more vulnerable to terrorism.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-0738894212456951">10</xref></sup></p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0738894212456951" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The Effect of Refugees on Terrorism, 1970–2007.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0738894212456951" xlink:href="10.1177_0738894212456951-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">NB<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">†</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">REL<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">††</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">NB</th>
<th align="left">NB w/Region FE</th>
<th align="left">NB w/ Country FE</th>
<th align="left">NB w/Year FE<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">†††</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">GEEs<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">††††</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Incidents</th>
<th align="left">Binary</th>
<th align="left">Casualties</th>
<th align="left">Incidents</th>
<th align="left">Incidents</th>
<th align="left">Incidents</th>
<th align="left">Incidents</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">Model 1</th>
<th align="left">Model 2</th>
<th align="left">Model 3</th>
<th align="left">Model 4</th>
<th align="left">Model 5</th>
<th align="left">Model 6</th>
<th align="left">Model 7</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Refugee<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.079<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.108<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.081<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>0.075<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.092<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.064<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>0.088<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.021)</td>
<td>(0.018)</td>
<td>(0.033)</td>
<td>(0.022)</td>
<td>(0.011)</td>
<td>(0.030)</td>
<td>(0.031)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Democracy<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.041<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.042<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.037<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.041<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.038<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.050<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.036</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.007)</td>
<td>(0.005)</td>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td>(0.007)</td>
<td>(0.032)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>State Failure<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.162<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.243<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.215<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.159<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.136<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.175<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.511<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.018)</td>
<td>(0.027)</td>
<td>(0.023)</td>
<td>(0.018)</td>
<td>(0.011)</td>
<td>(0.023)</td>
<td>(0.054)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Econ Development<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.194<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.209<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.106<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>0.063</td>
<td>0.292<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.178<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.105</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.042)</td>
<td>(0.034)</td>
<td>(0.053)</td>
<td>(0.060)</td>
<td>(0.029)</td>
<td>(0.048)</td>
<td>(0.106)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Population<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.253<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.264<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.306<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.265<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.040<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>0.321<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.720<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.036)</td>
<td>(0.026)</td>
<td>(0.050)</td>
<td>(0.037)</td>
<td>(0.022)</td>
<td>(0.044)</td>
<td>(0.078)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Post-Cold War<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>−0.375<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.436<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.163</td>
<td>−0.366<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.299<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−18.684</td>
<td>−0.872<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.077)</td>
<td>(0.074)</td>
<td>(0.099)</td>
<td>(0.079)</td>
<td>(0.045)</td>
<td>not estimated</td>
<td>(0.215)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Terrorism<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.007<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>1.864<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.007<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.005<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td>(0.071)</td>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td>(0.001)</td>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Americas<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.023</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.224)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Europe<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−0.178</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.239)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Africa<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−0.696<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.233)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Asia<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−0.559<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.236)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Oceania<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−0.815<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.257)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>−2.352<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−5.451<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.487</td>
<td>−1.018</td>
<td>−4.197<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−2.055<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−6.140<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.483)</td>
<td>(0.370)</td>
<td>(0.604)</td>
<td>(0.645)</td>
<td>(0.327)</td>
<td>(0.555)</td>
<td>(0.922)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wald Chi<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>960.64</td>
<td/>
<td>357.55</td>
<td>1106.17</td>
<td>1053.59</td>
<td>not estimated</td>
<td>408.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prob &gt; Chi<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td/>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>not estimated</td>
<td>0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Log Likelihood</td>
<td>−10683.61</td>
<td/>
<td>−10864.79</td>
<td>−10596.90</td>
<td>−9089.16</td>
<td>−10639.90</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dispersion = 1</td>
<td>40.85</td>
<td/>
<td>555.89</td>
<td>39.76</td>
<td/>
<td>51.01</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Observations</td>
<td>5,259</td>
<td>5,259</td>
<td>5,040</td>
<td>5,258</td>
<td>5,162</td>
<td>5,259</td>
<td>5,259</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0738894212456951"><p>Robust standard errors are in parentheses. *p &lt; .05, **p &lt; .01, ***p &lt; .001, one-tailed tests. †Negative Binomial Regression, †† Rare Event Logit, ††† Fixed-Effect, †††† Generalized Estimating Equations.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Model 2 shows estimated results of the rare event logit model that deals with the issue of excess zeros in the terrorism data. Not surprisingly, the significance of the refugee variable remains the same along with all the control variables. Model 3 substitutes terrorist incidents with terrorist casualties as the dependent variable, which is an annual total of persons killed and wounded in terrorist attacks. This variable intends to capture a new phenomenon of terrorism that has replaced the “old terrorism” of the 1970s and 1980s: the number of incidents is on the decline but the lethality of incidents is rising (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0738894212456951">Frey and Luechinger, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0738894212456951">Crain and Crain, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0738894212456951">Frey et al., 2007</xref>). Thus, this variable is an alternative measure to total event counts because it can measure the unequal degree of severity in each terrorist incident rather than aggregate terrorist events of differing lethality. The estimated results in Model 3 indicate that countries with more refugees are more likely to be exposed to terrorist casualties. Models 4 to 6 replicate Model 1 after controlling for three different fixed-effects, namely region, country, and year.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-0738894212456951">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>In general, fixed-effects can control for omitted variables that differ between countries or time periods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0738894212456951">Green et al., 2001</xref>). Following the methodological insights of Green et al., we employ fixed-effects in three alternative ways: region, country, and year. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0738894212456951">Table 1</xref>, each of these fixed-effect negative binomial regression models still provides evidence that refugee inflows are a cause of increased terrorism. Model 7 employs generalized estimating equations (GEEs) that account for first-order correlation instead of negative binomial regression for estimation; the refugee variable is statistically significant with a positive sign. Therefore, our main result is robust to a number of modeling choices.</p>
<p>In our next set of models, we disaggregate terrorist incidents into two different types, namely domestic versus international. While Models 1 to 3 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0738894212456951">Table 2</xref> explain the causes of domestic terrorism, Models 4 to 6 look into the effect of refugees on international terrorism. As in Models 1 to 3 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0738894212456951">Table 1</xref>, these models are negative binomial regression, rare event logit, and negative binomial regression with terrorist casualties. As far as domestic terrorism is concerned, the hypothesis about refugees is supported across models except for casualties: refugees are a cause of domestic terrorism if not terrorist casualties. Models 4 to 6 report results that are obtained when the dependent variable is international terrorism; the results are consistent with those in the previous models. The impact of refugee flows on international terrorism is positive.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0738894212456951" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>The Effect of Refugees on Domestic and International Terrorism, 1970–2007.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0738894212456951" xlink:href="10.1177_0738894212456951-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Domestic Terrorism<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">International Terrorism<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">NB<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">†</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">REL<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">††</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">NB</th>
<th align="left">NB</th>
<th align="left">REL</th>
<th align="left">NB</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Incidents</th>
<th align="left">Binary</th>
<th align="left">Casualties</th>
<th align="left">Incidents</th>
<th align="left">Binary</th>
<th align="left">Casualties</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">Model 1</th>
<th align="left">Model 2</th>
<th align="left">Model 3</th>
<th align="left">Model 4</th>
<th align="left">Model 5</th>
<th align="left">Model 6</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Refugee<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.061<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>0.077<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.048</td>
<td>0.064<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>0.097<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.074<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.022)</td>
<td>(0.019)</td>
<td>(0.037)</td>
<td>(0.027)</td>
<td>(0.019)</td>
<td>(0.035)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Democracy<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.045<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.043<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.043<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.041<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.039<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.032<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.006)</td>
<td>(0.010)</td>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.006)</td>
<td>(0.010)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>State Failure<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.166<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.216<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.204<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.193<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.229<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.227<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.019)</td>
<td>(0.025)</td>
<td>(0.025)</td>
<td>(0.024)</td>
<td>(0.025)</td>
<td>(0.026)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Econ Development<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.150<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.132<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.029</td>
<td>0.230<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.244<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.217<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.048)</td>
<td>(0.036)</td>
<td>(0.060)</td>
<td>(0.053)</td>
<td>(0.036)</td>
<td>(0.058)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Population<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.284<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.274<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.332<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.256<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.277<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.300<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.038)</td>
<td>(0.027)</td>
<td>(0.049)</td>
<td>(0.041)</td>
<td>(0.026)</td>
<td>(0.052)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Post-Cold War<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>−0.188<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.173<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.073</td>
<td>−0.639<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.621<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.310<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.084)</td>
<td>(0.076)</td>
<td>(0.112)</td>
<td>(0.092)</td>
<td>(0.077)</td>
<td>(0.112)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Terrorism<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.008<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>1.999<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.030<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>1.718<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td>(0.074)</td>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td>(0.003)</td>
<td>(0.074)</td>
<td>(0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>−2.549<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−5.339<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.377</td>
<td>−4.124<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−6.151<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−2.830<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.517)</td>
<td>(0.393)</td>
<td>(0.630)</td>
<td>(0.575)</td>
<td>(0.390)</td>
<td>(0.764)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wald Chi<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>872.32</td>
<td/>
<td>328.52</td>
<td>427.72</td>
<td/>
<td>252.96</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prob &gt; Chi<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td/>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td/>
<td>0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Log Likelihood</td>
<td>−8993.00</td>
<td/>
<td>−9598.96</td>
<td>−6603.10</td>
<td/>
<td>−6148.48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dispersion = 1</td>
<td>47.22</td>
<td/>
<td>520.49</td>
<td>7.74</td>
<td/>
<td>192.87</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Observations</td>
<td>5,259</td>
<td>5,259</td>
<td>5,149</td>
<td>5,259</td>
<td>5,259</td>
<td>5,140</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0738894212456951"><p>Robust standard errors are in parentheses. *p &lt; .05, **p &lt; .01, ***p &lt; .001, one-tailed tests. †Negative Binomial Regression, †† Rare Event Logit.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Our empirical analysis has so far relied on the GTD data. Another widely used source of terrorist activity is the International Terrorism: Attributes of Terrorist Events (ITERATE) database from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0738894212456951">Mickolus et al. (2008)</xref>. As a way to check the robustness of our findings on international terrorism, we use the ITERATE dataset.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-0738894212456951">12</xref></sup> Model 1 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0738894212456951">Table 3</xref> show estimated coefficients and standard errors that are obtained from negative binomial regression. The results are quite similar to those shown with the GTD measure: the inflow of refugees is positively associated with international terrorism.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0738894212456951" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>The Effect of Refugees on International Terrorism, 1970–2007: ITERATE.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0738894212456951" xlink:href="10.1177_0738894212456951-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="8">Negative Binomial Regression<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">NB w/Cubic Polynomial of Time<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">1970–2007<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="7">1975–1997<hr/></th>
<th align="left">1970–2007<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">1975–1997<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">Model 1</th>
<th align="left">Model 2</th>
<th align="left">Model 3</th>
<th align="left">Model 4</th>
<th align="left">Model 5</th>
<th align="left">Model 6</th>
<th align="left">Model 7</th>
<th align="left">Model 8</th>
<th align="left">Model 9</th>
<th align="left">Model 10</th>
<th align="left">Model 11</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Refugee<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.078<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>0.066<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>0.058<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>0.049<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>0.053<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>0.065<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>0.057<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>0.059<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>0.062<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>0.056<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>0.061<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.027)</td>
<td>(0.028)</td>
<td>(0.025)</td>
<td>(0.025)</td>
<td>(0.026)</td>
<td>(0.023)</td>
<td>(0.024)</td>
<td>(0.024)</td>
<td>(0.024)</td>
<td>(0.024)</td>
<td>(0.024)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Democracy<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.031<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.040<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.035<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.033<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.038<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.034<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.031<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.037<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.029<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.027<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.027<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.009)</td>
<td>(0.009)</td>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.006)</td>
<td>(0.007)</td>
<td>(0.007)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>State Failure<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.187<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.193<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.188<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.184<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.197<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.146<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.149<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.161<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.137<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.141<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.113<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.023)</td>
<td>(0.028)</td>
<td>(0.023)</td>
<td>(0.021)</td>
<td>(0.024)</td>
<td>(0.023)</td>
<td>(0.021)</td>
<td>(0.025)</td>
<td>(0.027)</td>
<td>(0.028)</td>
<td>(0.032)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Econ Development<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.330<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.340<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.293<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.267<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.265<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.332<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.303<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.303<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.243<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.204<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.236<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.049)</td>
<td>(0.055)</td>
<td>(0.051)</td>
<td>(0.051)</td>
<td>(0.054)</td>
<td>(0.049)</td>
<td>(0.048)</td>
<td>(0.052)</td>
<td>(0.048)</td>
<td>(0.055)</td>
<td>(0.052)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Population<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.234<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.215<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.219<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.225<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.227<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.189<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.196<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.200<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.158<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.153<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.135<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.042)</td>
<td>(0.044)</td>
<td>(0.040)</td>
<td>(0.036)</td>
<td>(0.041)</td>
<td>(0.039)</td>
<td>(0.036)</td>
<td>(0.040)</td>
<td>(0.040)</td>
<td>(0.041)</td>
<td>(0.041)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Post-Cold War<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>−1.020<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.668<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.636<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.576<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.641<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.626<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.574<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.626<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.710<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.561<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.553<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.090)</td>
<td>(0.087)</td>
<td>(0.083)</td>
<td>(0.082)</td>
<td>(0.086)</td>
<td>(0.083)</td>
<td>(0.081)</td>
<td>(0.087)</td>
<td>(0.088)</td>
<td>(0.081)</td>
<td>(0.082)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Terrorism<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.021<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.018<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.015<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.018<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.016<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.015<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.018<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.016<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td>(0.005)</td>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hot Spot_Land<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.663<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.631<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.727<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.711<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.122)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.129)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.131)</td>
<td>(0.136)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hot Spot_Land and Sea<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.823<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.775<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.103)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.110)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hot Spot_950KM<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.648<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.606<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.102)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.112)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Interstate Dispute<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−0.038</td>
<td>−0.035</td>
<td>−0.172</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−0.035</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.113)</td>
<td>(0.106)</td>
<td>(0.143)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.105)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Civil Conflict<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.521<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.447<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.487<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.358<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.127)</td>
<td>(0.120)</td>
<td>(0.137)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.127)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>t</italic></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−0.596<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.545<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.527<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.048)</td>
<td>(0.062)</td>
<td>(0.061)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>t</italic><sup>2</sup></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.040<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.040<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.039<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.006)</td>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.008)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>t</italic><sup>2</sup></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−0.001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td>(0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>−4.443<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−4.443<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−4.318<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−3.965<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−3.945<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−4.214<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−4.098<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−4.099<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−1.872<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−1.666<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>−1.879<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.561)</td>
<td>(0.561)</td>
<td>(0.628)</td>
<td>(0.592)</td>
<td>(0.617)</td>
<td>(0.595)</td>
<td>(0.583)</td>
<td>(0.615)</td>
<td>(0.497)</td>
<td>(0.617)</td>
<td>(0.610)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wald Chi<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>439.61</td>
<td>298.84</td>
<td>452.88</td>
<td>715.90</td>
<td>373.11</td>
<td>584.87</td>
<td>798.89</td>
<td>507.38</td>
<td>735.56</td>
<td>665.64</td>
<td>786.12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prob &gt; Chi<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Log Likelihood</td>
<td>−7328.25</td>
<td>−5042.24</td>
<td>−4997.10</td>
<td>−4948.65</td>
<td>−4984.26</td>
<td>−4963.99</td>
<td>−4922.27</td>
<td>−4954.97</td>
<td>−7146.2</td>
<td>−4903.78</td>
<td>−4888.72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dispersion = 1</td>
<td>6.91</td>
<td>6.45</td>
<td>5.89</td>
<td>5.41</td>
<td>5.90</td>
<td>5.68</td>
<td>5.28</td>
<td>5.73</td>
<td>7.31</td>
<td>6.11</td>
<td>6.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Observations</td>
<td>5,150</td>
<td>3,054</td>
<td>3,054</td>
<td>3,054</td>
<td>3,054</td>
<td>3,054</td>
<td>3,054</td>
<td>3,054</td>
<td>5,150</td>
<td>3,054</td>
<td>3,054</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0738894212456951"><p>Robust standard errors are in parentheses. *p &lt; .05, **p &lt; .01, ***p &lt; .001, one-tailed tests.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Model 2 replicates Model 1 for a shorter time period that spans from 1975 to 1997. This model serves two purposes. One is to check whether the effect of refugees still remains robust to the shorter time period (i.e. sample selection bias) and another is to make it a base model for Models 3 to 8 in which additional variables of interest are introduced as controls. As far as the significance levels and the causal relationships are concerned, the results of Model 2 are nearly identical to Model 1.</p>
<p>Model 3 shows replicated results of Model 2 after adding a terrorism hot spot variable that is dichotomous: 1 for a country that is part of a hot spot neighborhood in a given year according to <italic>G<sub>i</sub>*</italic> statistics<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-0738894212456951">13</xref></sup> and 0 otherwise. “A terrorism hot spot is defined as a neighborhood of countries that experiences a larger number of terrorist incidents than one would expect of an average neighborhood in the international system according to a random process” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0738894212456951">Braithwaite and Li, 2007</xref>: 285). The reason we introduce such a spatial factor is to assuage the concern that neighboring an unstable country generates both international refugees and more terrorism events. The existence of spatial dependence causes potential problems, which are discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0738894212456951">Franzese and Hays (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0738894212456951">Plümper and Neumayer (2010)</xref>. It may be the case that the refugee variable simply captures a “neighborhood effect”, where being near a conflict hot spot also increases a country’s vulnerability to terrorism (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0738894212456951">Bapat, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0738894212456951">Braithwaite and Li, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0738894212456951">Braithwaite, 2010</xref>). However, this neighborhood effect does not need to come from the inflow of refugees, but from economic and political shocks that result from violence in the region. In order to isolate the direct effect of refugee presence from the broader influence of proximity to a terror hot spot, we include a measure of proximity to a terror hot spot as a control, as shown in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0738894212456951">Braithwaite and Li (2007)</xref>.</p>
<p>We employ three dichotomous measures of a terrorism hot spot based on geographic proximity: (1) direct land contiguity, (2) contiguity defined by shared land boundaries or those separated by not more than 150 km of sea, and (3) a minimum distance between countries of not more than 950 km. Model 3 uses the first measure of a terrorism hot spot; Model 4 relies on the second measure; and Model 4 adopts the third measure. All of these three models, in which spatial factors are accounted for, show the positive effect of refugees in a consistent manner. Our main results do not change with the inclusion of these variables.</p>
<p>The two recent studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0738894212456951">Krieger and Meierrieks (2011)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0738894212456951">Gassebner and Luechinger (2011)</xref> analyze which variables are robust correlates of terrorism. We have controlled for the “primary suspects” in our models reported above. However, it may be the case that the existence of a high-level armed conflict or an international war increases the level of violent attacks captured in our terrorism measures. Therefore, we include interstate dispute and civil conflict in our model specification.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-0738894212456951">14</xref></sup> Models 6 to 8 replicate Models 3 to 5 after including these two additional control variables. The results across models remain virtually the same.</p>
<p>To further test the robustness of the findings, Models 9 to 11 employ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0738894212456951">Carter and Signorino’s (2010)</xref> cubic polynomial of time. Model 9 replicates Model 1 after adding three time variables; Model 10 reruns Model 3 after accounting for the temporal dependence; and Model 11 replicates Model 6 after including the time factors. Regardless of the model specification, the three negative binomial regressions with the cubic polynomial of time confirm the previous findings: the inflow of refugees is a contributing factor in explaining acts of international terrorists.</p>
<p>It is important to estimate the substantive effects of variables in addition to their statistical significance. If the substantive effects are consistent with the statistical significance, the estimated results reported so far can be said to be meaningful. In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0738894212456951">Table 4</xref>, we look at the substantive effects of the refugee variables that appeared in Model 1 of <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0738894212456951">Table 1</xref>, and Models 1 and 4 of <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0738894212456951">Table 2</xref>. We find that the influx of refugees has a quite important impact on the number of experienced violent events. For all events combined, when a country experiences an increase of one and two standard deviations of refugees above their mean value, the frequency of terrorism incidents increases by 18% and 40%, respectively. The size of the effect is somewhat diminished when disaggregating among terrorism types. Nonetheless, the increase in predicted counts is a meaningful increase, which can have dramatic impacts on the countries in question.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0738894212456951" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>The Substantive Effect of Refugees.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0738894212456951" xlink:href="10.1177_0738894212456951-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Terrorism<hr/></th>
<th align="left">Domestic Terrorism<hr/></th>
<th align="left">International Terrorism<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable: Refugee<sub><italic>t</italic>–1</sub></th>
<th align="left">Model 1 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0738894212456951">Table 1</xref></th>
<th align="left">Model 1 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0738894212456951">Table 2</xref></th>
<th align="left">Model 4 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0738894212456951">Table 2</xref></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Increased by one standard deviation</td>
<td>18%</td>
<td>14%</td>
<td>15%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Increased by two standard deviations</td>
<td>40%</td>
<td>30%</td>
<td>31%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></table-wrap>
<p>Finally, one may suspect that our results may not be constant across all sample countries. In particular, strong states may be better able to integrate refugees and provide security to both the migrants and humanitarian workers. Weak states, on the other hand, are less able to provide security and ensure that conflicts do not spill over across national boundaries. Because of stronger bureaucratic capacity, improved ability to screen refugees, and enhanced security measures, the relationship between refugees and violence may be weaker in more developed countries. To account for this concern, we split our sample between OECD and non-OECD countries in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0738894212456951">Table 5</xref>. Although its significance levels weaken in the OECD countries, as compared to the non-OECD countries, the refugee variable turns out to be statistically significant across models except Model 6, which uses international terrorism as the dependent variable. The effects are weaker for strong states, but not nil. It appears that “strong” states suffer from “imported” violence as well (e.g. the PKK hit Turkish targets across Europe), or from right-wing/nationalist terrorism that develops in response to a “refugee problem” (e.g. there were attacks by far-right groups against migrants and refugees in Germany during the 1990s).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-0738894212456951">15</xref></sup> Attacks on aid supplies are likely to be of less concern in developed countries, however, as most refugees in these states do not reside in camps but are distributed across the country. Therefore, in terms of the causal mechanisms we discussed above, we believe that attacks on aid workers by organizations seeking foreign targets is less applicable to the OECD cases.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-0738894212456951" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>The Effect of Refugees on Terrorism, 1970–2007: Developing versus Developed Countries.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0738894212456951" xlink:href="10.1177_0738894212456951-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="6">Negative Binomial Regression<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Developing Countries<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Developed Countries<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">Terrorism
<break/>Model 1</th>
<th align="left">Domestic
<break/>Model 2</th>
<th align="left">International
<break/>Model 3</th>
<th align="left">Terrorism
<break/>Model 4</th>
<th align="left">Domestic
<break/>Model 5</th>
<th align="left">International
<break/>Model 6</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Refugee<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.087<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.082<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>0.074<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.068<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>0.101<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>0.041</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.022)</td>
<td>(0.031)</td>
<td>(0.023)</td>
<td>(0.035)</td>
<td>(0.044)</td>
<td>(0.038)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Democracy<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.049<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.047<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.055<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.032</td>
<td>0.027</td>
<td>0.055</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.010)</td>
<td>(0.009)</td>
<td>(0.031)</td>
<td>(0.029)</td>
<td>(0.055)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>State Failure<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.169<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.191<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.173<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.037</td>
<td>−0.087</td>
<td>0.145</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.018)</td>
<td>(0.023)</td>
<td>(0.018)</td>
<td>(0.157)</td>
<td>(0.171)</td>
<td>(0.168)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Econ Development<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.274<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.331<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.241<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.131</td>
<td>−0.240</td>
<td>−0.246</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.049)</td>
<td>(0.055)</td>
<td>(0.057)</td>
<td>(0.315)</td>
<td>(0.336)</td>
<td>(0.375)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Population<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.241<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.261<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.260<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.382<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.283<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.481<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.037)</td>
<td>(0.043)</td>
<td>(0.037)</td>
<td>(0.076)</td>
<td>(0.092)</td>
<td>(0.082)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Post-Cold War<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>−0.364<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.560<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.208<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.482<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.960<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.219</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.104)</td>
<td>(0.123)</td>
<td>(0.112)</td>
<td>(0.181)</td>
<td>(0.193)</td>
<td>(0.208)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Terrorism<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.007<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.032<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.008<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.013<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.028<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>0.017<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td>(0.005)</td>
<td>(0.000)</td>
<td>(0.001)</td>
<td>(0.005)</td>
<td>(0.002)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>−2.819<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−5.071<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−2.981<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0738894212456951">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.859</td>
<td>0.287</td>
<td>−1.341</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.538)</td>
<td>(0.596)</td>
<td>(0.588)</td>
<td>(2.926)</td>
<td>(3.186)</td>
<td>(3.509)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wald Chi<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>1032.63</td>
<td>374.34</td>
<td>961.13</td>
<td>591.59</td>
<td>218.19</td>
<td>345.91</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prob &gt; Chi<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Log Likelihood</td>
<td>−8442.90</td>
<td>−5062.69</td>
<td>−7160.70</td>
<td>−2151.20</td>
<td>−1497.41</td>
<td>−1746.71</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dispersion = 1</td>
<td>44.88</td>
<td>7.53</td>
<td>51.50</td>
<td>19.56</td>
<td>6.97</td>
<td>21.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Observations</td>
<td>4,424</td>
<td>4,424</td>
<td>4,424</td>
<td>835</td>
<td>835</td>
<td>835</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0738894212456951"><p>Robust standard errors are in parentheses. *p &lt; .05, **p &lt; .01, ***p &lt; .001, one-tailed tests.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0738894212456951">
<title>Illustrative Examples of Humanitarian Relief and Terrorism</title>
<p>We have argued above that humanitarian assistance, in the form of resources and aid workers, is a prime target for terrorist attacks. This is in addition to other causal mechanisms related to violent attacks, including anti-foreigner violence and refugee recruitment into militant activities. Because of data constraints, it is difficult to obtain reliable numbers on funding for refugee camps or the number of aid workers present. However, we can assess the GTD narratives to gauge the plausibility of this causal mechanism. To do so, we search for terrorism events that specifically mention “refugee” in the text through the GTD’s open search function, although narratives are only available for the post-1998 period. There are 258 events that specifically mention refugees and of these, a large share of the narratives point to attacks on aid workers and relief supplies. In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-0738894212456951">Table 6</xref>, we present a number of narratives, validating our claim that a large number of attacks are against aid workers and humanitarian supplies.</p>
<table-wrap id="table6-0738894212456951" position="float">
<label>Table 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Examples of Violence against Refugee Aid Resources.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-0738894212456951" xlink:href="10.1177_0738894212456951-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Date</th>
<th align="left">Country</th>
<th align="left">City</th>
<th align="left">Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>08/12/2008</td>
<td>Kenya</td>
<td>Dadaab</td>
<td>Armed assailants fired upon an ambulance carrying members of a German organization, Gesellschaft fur Technische Zusammenarbeit, at a refugee camp near Dadaab, Kenya.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>27/11/2008</td>
<td>Sri Lanka</td>
<td>Batticaloa</td>
<td>A Norwegian Refugee Council employee was shot dead by unidentified assailants in Batticaloa, Eastern Province, Sri Lanka.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>09/11/2008</td>
<td>Sudan</td>
<td>Zalinjay</td>
<td>In Zalingei, Gharb Darfur, Sudan, armed assailants dressed in civilian clothing fired upon a United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) vehicle, wounding a peacekeeper. The assailants then stole the vehicle.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>24/08/2008</td>
<td>Somalia</td>
<td>Mogadishu</td>
<td>Two journalists and their interpreter were abducted at gunpoint. The Somali journalists’ union said the journalists were being held in northeast Mogadishu by a militia group, although it was not clear if they were being held for political reasons or for ransom.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11/12/2007</td>
<td>Algeria</td>
<td>Algiers</td>
<td>A bomb went off outside the UN High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) and neighboring UN Development Program (UNDP) in Algiers, Algeria. Ten people belonging to the UN staff were killed. Al Qa‘ida is suspected of having carried out the attack.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>19/03/2007</td>
<td>Sudan</td>
<td>Torit County</td>
<td>Suspected Lord’s Resistance Army rebels raided a refugee camp in Sudan, killing 1 and displacing over 1,500 in eastern Equatoria (Sharq al Istiwa’iyah) Province.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>28/02/2007</td>
<td>Chad</td>
<td>Goz Amer</td>
<td>In Goz Amer, Chad, assailants armed with unspecified firearms attacked a refugee camp. Seventeen refugees were killed and the camp was damaged. The assailants also stole all of the camp’s livestock.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10/04/2006</td>
<td>Chad</td>
<td>Goz Beida</td>
<td>Chadian rebels entered a refugee camp in Goz Amer, Chad during a food distribution exercise. The rebels stole equipment from aid workers and forced 118 of them to spend the night at the camp before allowing them to leave the next morning.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18/01/2006</td>
<td>Ivory Coast</td>
<td>Guiglo</td>
<td>An angry crowd in Guiglo, Cote d’Ivoire, attacked and looted the office of the United Nations Refugee Agency. Many of the attackers claimed to be members of the Young Patriots movement.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>17/09/2000</td>
<td>Guinea</td>
<td>Conakry</td>
<td>A Togolese employee of the UN Refugee Agency was killed and a citizen of Ivory Coast was kidnapped in an attack by unknown perpetrators.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12/10/1999</td>
<td>Burundi</td>
<td>Unknown</td>
<td>Two senior United Nations officials and seven others were shot execution-style by rebels at the Mazye refugee camp. Rebels burnt three UN vehicles and stole some of the UN’s supplies.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Our main purpose here is illustrative. We note that the purpose of this exercise is not to rule out alternative causal mechanisms, or gauge the frequency of these types of attacks, which would be nearly impossible given that the GTD only offers narratives for recent years. We make no claim that attacks on aid workers are more or less important than other causal links between refugees and violence, including recruitment into militant groups or xenophobic attacks. In addition, there may be many more events in the GTD that involve refugee communities, but in which the term “refugee” is not used in the text (e.g. the words “migrant”, “foreigner”, or the specific nationality is used). Rather, our intention is to highlight—through a few illustrative events—the importance of this particular mechanism. Since there is relatively little attention to how aid workers and humanitarian supplies may provide incentives for terrorist attacks, we point to these cases as illustrative examples, thereby underscoring the plausibility of our claims. Future research into how humanitarian relief supplies and attacks on aid workers shape the security environment is encouraged.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0738894212456951" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>In this study, we extend the literature on refugee flows and the spread of violence. We are not the first to identify the potential security consequences of refugee flows, although we do present new findings regarding the impact of refugees on domestic and international terrorism. Although much of the literature focuses on attacks by migrants and rebel recruitment, we highlight an additional casual mechanism: the inflow of humanitarian resources. Aid supplies have often been subject to looting by militant actors. Moreover, foreign aid workers provide easy targets for terrorists who adopt anti-Western ideologies.</p>
<p>In future research, scholars should pay closer attention to interactions between refugees, humanitarian resources, and conflict. Improved data on the location of refugee camps, the nationality and source of aid supplies, and the location of attacks can test further hypotheses about which militant organizations are most likely to attack particular targets. A more fine-grained, disaggregated approach can also help improve policies and procedures for protecting refugees and aid workers.</p>
<p>From a policy perspective, our research underscores the importance of providing a safe, secure environment for refugees. While some may be tempted to block access to such migrants, we believe that this can be counter-productive in the long run. Aside from the ethical issues which arise from denying asylum to legitimate refugees, preventing entry may further exacerbate conflict in origin countries. Instead, we stress that improving conditions for refugees is a better alternative. International actors have often focused on material needs like food and shelter, but should first take care to ensure that refugee communities and aid workers are protected. Chaotic conditions surrounding war zones are clearly difficult areas to operate in. However, it is imperative to ensure that relief supplies do not fall into the wrong hands, that humanitarian workers operate in a safe environment, and that the refugees themselves get the care that they deserve.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<table-wrap id="table7-0738894212456951" position="float">
<label>Appendix 1.</label>
<caption><p>List of 154 Sample Countries.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table7-0738894212456951" xlink:href="10.1177_0738894212456951-table7.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Afghanistan</td>
<td>Costa Rica</td>
<td>Hungary</td>
<td>Mexico</td>
<td>Somalia</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Albania</td>
<td>Croatia</td>
<td>India</td>
<td>Moldova<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>South Africa</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Algeria</td>
<td>Cuba</td>
<td>Indonesia</td>
<td>Mongolia<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Spain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Angola</td>
<td>Cyprus</td>
<td>Iran</td>
<td>Morocco</td>
<td>Sri Lanka<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Argentina</td>
<td>Czech Rep</td>
<td>Iraq</td>
<td>Mozambique</td>
<td>Sudan</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Armenia</td>
<td>Dem. Rep. Congo</td>
<td>Ireland</td>
<td>Nepal</td>
<td>Swaziland</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Australia</td>
<td>Denmark</td>
<td>Israel</td>
<td>Netherlands</td>
<td>Sweden</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Austria</td>
<td>Djibouti</td>
<td>Italy</td>
<td>New Zealand</td>
<td>Switzerland</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Azerbaijan</td>
<td>Dominican Rep.</td>
<td>Ivory Coast</td>
<td>Nicaragua</td>
<td>Syria</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bahrain<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Ecuador</td>
<td>Jamaica<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Niger</td>
<td>Taiwan<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bangladesh</td>
<td>Egypt</td>
<td>Japan</td>
<td>Nigeria</td>
<td>Tajikistan</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Belarus</td>
<td>El Salvador</td>
<td>Jordan</td>
<td>Norway</td>
<td>Tanzania</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Belgium</td>
<td>Equatorial Guinea<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Kazakhstan</td>
<td>Oman</td>
<td>Thailand</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Benin</td>
<td>Eritrea</td>
<td>Kenya</td>
<td>Pakistan</td>
<td>Togo</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bhutan</td>
<td>Estonia<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Korea, South</td>
<td>Panama</td>
<td>Trinidad and Tobago<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bolivia</td>
<td>Ethiopia</td>
<td>Kuwait</td>
<td>Papua New Guinea</td>
<td>Tunisia</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bosnia</td>
<td>Fiji<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Kyrgyzstan</td>
<td>Paraguay</td>
<td>Turkey</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Botswana</td>
<td>Finland</td>
<td>Laos</td>
<td>Peru</td>
<td>Turkmenistan</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Brazil</td>
<td>France</td>
<td>Latvia<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Philippines</td>
<td>United Arab Emirates</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Burkina Faso</td>
<td>Gabon</td>
<td>Lebanon</td>
<td>Poland</td>
<td>Uganda</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Burundi</td>
<td>Gambia</td>
<td>Lesotho</td>
<td>Portugal</td>
<td>UK</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cambodia</td>
<td>Georgia</td>
<td>Liberia</td>
<td>Qatar<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Ukraine</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cameroon</td>
<td>Germany</td>
<td>Libya</td>
<td>Romania</td>
<td>Uruguay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Canada</td>
<td>Ghana</td>
<td>Lithuania<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Russia</td>
<td>USA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Central African Rep.</td>
<td>Greece</td>
<td>Macedonia</td>
<td>Rwanda</td>
<td>Uzbekistan</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Chad</td>
<td>Guatemala</td>
<td>Madagascar<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Saudi Arabia</td>
<td>Venezuela</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Chile</td>
<td>Guinea</td>
<td>Malawi</td>
<td>Senegal</td>
<td>Vietnam</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>China</td>
<td>Guinea Bissau</td>
<td>Malaysia</td>
<td>Sierra Leone</td>
<td>Yemen</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Colombia</td>
<td>Guyana<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Mali</td>
<td>Singapore</td>
<td>Zambia</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Comoros<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Haiti<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Mauritania</td>
<td>Slovakia</td>
<td>Zimbabwe</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Congo</td>
<td>Honduras</td>
<td>Mauritius<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0738894212456951">*</xref></td>
<td>Slovenia</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-0738894212456951">
<label>*</label>
<p>Countries that did not host any refugees.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table8-0738894212456951" position="float">
<label>Appendix 2.</label>
<caption><p>Muliticollinearity Diagnostics<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0738894212456951">1</xref></sup>.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table8-0738894212456951" xlink:href="10.1177_0738894212456951-table8.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">R<sup>2</sup></th>
<th align="left">Variance Inflation Factors</th>
<th align="left">Square Root of VIFs</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Refugee<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.19</td>
<td>1.23</td>
<td>1.11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Democracy<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.26</td>
<td>1.36</td>
<td>1.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>State Failure<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.15</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>1.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Econ Development<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.21</td>
<td>1.26</td>
<td>1.12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Population<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.21</td>
<td>1.26</td>
<td>1.12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Post-Cold War<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td>1.13</td>
<td>1.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Terrorism<sub><italic>t</italic>−1</sub></td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>1.13</td>
<td>1.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mean variance inflation factors</td>
<td/>
<td>1.22</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><italic>Eigenvalues</italic></td>
<td><italic>Condition Index</italic></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>4.33</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>1.13</td>
<td>1.96</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>1.05</td>
<td>2.03</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>2.62</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>0.46</td>
<td>3.05</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>0.37</td>
<td>3.40</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>14.80</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>27.29</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Condition number</td>
<td/>
<td>27.29</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Eigenvalues &amp; Condition Index computed from the scaled raw sscp with an intercept</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Det(correlation matrix)</td>
<td/>
<td>0.49</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-0738894212456951">
<label>1</label>
<p>A general rule of thumb: a serious multicollinearity problem is suspected if R<sup>2</sup> is greater than 0.80, if the mean of all the variance inflation factors is considerably larger than 10, or if condition number exceeds 1000.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</app-group>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank the editorial team at CMPS and the three anonymous reviewers for comments on earlier drafts.</p>
</ack>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0738894212456951">
<label>1.</label>
<p>One of the advantages of the GTD over other terrorism datasets such as the International Terrorism: Attributes of Terrorist Events (ITERATE) is that the former includes information about domestic terrorism, which accounts for the bulk of terrorist activity.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0738894212456951">
<label>2.</label>
<p>United Nations, Article 1 of the 1951 Convention Relating to the Status of Refugees.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0738894212456951">
<label>3.</label>
<p>The issue of states reinterpreting exclusionary clauses in the Refugee Convention led the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) to warn states against the practice of “employing exclusion as a test of admissibility” for asylum claims that are rejected on the basis of terrorism (quoted in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0738894212456951">Zard, 2002</xref>: 34).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0738894212456951">
<label>4.</label>
<p>For more detailed information on GTD, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.start.umd.edu/gtd/">http://www.start.umd.edu/gtd/</ext-link>. There are some problems with GTD; for example, the data for 1993 are missing due to an office move (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0738894212456951">LaFree and Dugan, 2007</xref>). Our empirical analysis follows the imputation technique proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0738894212456951">Enders et al. (2011)</xref>. With respect to the significance of the refugee variable, all estimation methods produce no substantially different results with or without the missing 1993 data on terrorism.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0738894212456951">
<label>5.</label>
<p>It should be noted that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0738894212456951">Enders et al. (2011)</xref> assert that the GTD data collection is inconsistent for some time periods. By using the ITERATE dataset as a benchmark, they show that the GTD seems to underreport transnational terrorism for the 1970–77 period. Because Enders et al. provide adjustment factors to “fix” this data issue, our empirical analysis employs their approach.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0738894212456951">
<label>6.</label>
<p>It should be noted that the <italic>World Refugee Survey</italic> is unable to report data for the years 1973, 1975, and 1979. For our data analysis to be completed, the missing data are interpolated based on the average between the previous and following years. With respect to the significance of the refugee variable, all estimation methods produce similar results with or without the missing data.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0738894212456951">
<label>7.</label>
<p>The discussion on the six control variables is presented in the context that they are likely to affect international as well as domestic terrorism for similar reasons. For example, Savun and Phillips (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0738894212456951">2009</xref>: 879) make a similar note that “if democracies are prone to transnational terrorism by design, as most existing theoretical arguments suggest, then democracies should be vulnerable to <italic>domestic terrorism</italic> as well”. Young and Findley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0738894212456951">2011</xref>: 421) also point out that “Li’s arguments [on the relationship between democracy and transnational terrorism] may be accurate when we apply his reasoning to domestic terrorism as opposed to the transnational form”.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0738894212456951">
<label>8.</label>
<p>The statistics literature also recommends that zero-inflated negative binomial regression be used for “cross-sectional” data with excessive zeros. This is because a standard negative binomial regression model loses some of its effectiveness since the prevalence of zero counts in the data can pose a statistical challenge if not estimated appropriately (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0738894212456951">Greene, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0738894212456951">Long and Freese, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0738894212456951">Hilbe, 2007</xref>). However, it is important to note that since zero-inflated negative binomial regression is designed for cross-sectional data only, it is not suitable for cross-sectional, time-series data in which the presence of excessive zeros is often related to individual observations with zero counts rather than to individual countries with no count events. In fact, the cross-sectional, time-series terrorism data collected for this study include only four countries that belong to the “Always-0” group: Mongolia, Oman, Turkmenistan, and North Vietnam. This implies that the excessive zeros have little relation with a country-specific characteristic and thus zero-inflated negative binomial regression is not the appropriate estimator for the cross-sectional, time-series data. Further, because determining which predictors should be included in the inflation equation is a daunting task and because estimated results greatly vary dependent on the choice of predictors, zero-inflated negative binomial regression is hard to implement.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0738894212456951">
<label>9.</label>
<p>In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table8-0738894212456951">Appendix 2</xref>, we run diagnostic tests for multicollinearity. We demonstrate that this is not a significant concern for our models.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-0738894212456951">
<label>10.</label>
<p>It is interesting to know whether the exclusion of a lagged dependent variable influences the results. When the lagged dependent variable is excluded in Model 1, the significance level of the refugee variable is dropped to 0.01, as the coefficient size becomes smaller and the standard error becomes bigger. Though negligible, this change is not consistent with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0738894212456951">Achen’s (2000)</xref> claim that the inclusion of a lagged dependent variable may “soak up” the explanatory power of theoretically interesting independent variables.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-0738894212456951">
<label>11.</label>
<p>As demonstrated in a study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0738894212456951">Sandler and Enders (2004)</xref>, terrorist activity often evolves in cycles, which requires researchers to account for a full set of year fixed-effects. The year fixed-effect model, however, failed to converge when it excluded the Cold War variable.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-0738894212456951">
<label>12.</label>
<p>It is worth noting that there are some shortcomings with GTD and ITERATE because their data sources come from newspaper accounts. This may introduce underreporting bias because autocratic regimes tend to suppress freedom of the press (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0738894212456951">Drakos and Gofas, 2006</xref>).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-0738894212456951">
<label>13.</label>
<p>The <italic>G<sub>i</sub>*</italic> statistic is calculated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0738894212456951">Braithwaite and Li (2007)</xref> who identify precisely which countries are located in terrorism hot-spots in given years by computing the statistic on the basis of three-year aggregates (as sliding windows) of the numbers of terrorist incidents in each country, producing <italic>G<sub>i</sub>*</italic> values for 143 countries for each year of the 23-year period from 1975 to 1997. Those states that return statistically significant <italic>G<sub>i</sub>*</italic> scores (<italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05) in each year are considered to be located in international terrorism hot-spots during that year.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-0738894212456951">
<label>14.</label>
<p>Interstate dispute is a dummy variable coded as 1 if a country is involved in an armed interstate dispute and 0 if it is not. Civil conflict is also a dummy that is coded 1 when a country is engaged in an intrastate conflict and 0 otherwise. Data for both these variables come from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0738894212456951">Gleditsch et al. (2002)</xref>.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-0738894212456951">
<label>15.</label>
<p>In an additional set of models, not shown, we found that humanitarian aid to a country significantly increases the number of terrorist incidents. This conforms to our expectation that some share of attacks is attributable to violence against aid workers and relief supplies. However, the data used for these models do distinguish between refugee aid and other aid. Because we are not confident in these data, we do not report these results.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<p>Seung-Whan Choi is Associate Professor of Political Science at the University of Illinois at Chicago. His research interests include democracy, terrorism, globalization, and methodology. His work has appeared in the <italic>American Journal of Political Science, British Journal of Political Science, International Studies Quarterly, Journal of Conflict Resolution, Journal of Peace Research</italic> and elsewhere. His book with Patrick James is <italic>Civil-Military Dynamics, Democracy, and International Conflict: A New Quest for International Peace</italic> (Palgrave, 2005).</p>
<p>Idean Salehyan is an Associate Professor of Political Science at the University of North Texas. He is the author of <italic>Rebels Without Borders: Transnational Insurgencies in World Politics</italic> (Cornell University Press, 2009).</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Achen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Why lagged dependent variables can suppress the explanatory power of other independent variables</article-title>. <comment>Working paper</comment>, <publisher-name>Society for Political Methodology</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>St Louis, WA</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adelman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Refugees and border security post-September 11</article-title>. <source>Refuge</source> <volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Andreas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Biersteker</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2003</year>) <source>The Rebordering of North America: Integration and Exclusion in a New Security Context</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bapat</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The internationalization of terrorist campaigns</article-title>. <source>Conflict Management and Peace Science</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Braithwaite</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Resisting infection: How state capacity conditions conflict contagion</article-title>. <source>Journal of Peace Research</source> <volume>47</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Braithwaite</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Transnational terrorism hot spots: Identification and impact evaluation</article-title>. <source>Conflict Management and Peace Science</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brouwer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Immigration, asylum, and terrorism: A changing dynamic. Legal and practical developments in the EU in response to the terrorist attacks of 11.09</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Migration and Law</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>424</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Buhaug</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gleditsch</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Contagion or confusion? Why conflicts cluster in space</article-title>. <source>International Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>52</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Signorino</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Back to the future: Modeling time dependence in binary data</article-title>. <source>Political Analysis</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>292</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S-W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Fighting terrorism through the rule of law?</article-title> <source>Journal of Conflict Resolution</source> <volume>54</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>940</fpage>–<lpage>966</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S-W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>military intervention reduce or increase terrorism?</article-title> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1900375">http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1900375</ext-link>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoeffler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Greed and grievance in civil war</article-title>. <source>Oxford Economic Papers</source> <volume>56</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>563</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Collyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Secret agents: Anarchists, Islamists and responses to politically active refugees in London</article-title>. <source>Ethnic and Racial Studies</source> <volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Terrorized economies</article-title>. <source>Public Choice</source> <volume>128</volume>(<issue>1/2</issue>): <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crisp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A state of insecurity: The political economy of violence in Kenya’s refugee camps</article-title>. <source>African Affairs</source> <volume>99</volume>(<issue>397</issue>): <fpage>601</fpage>–<lpage>632</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dowty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loescher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Refugee flows as grounds for international action</article-title>. <source>International Security</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Drakos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gofas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The devil you know but are afraid to face</article-title>. <source>Journal of Conflict Resolution</source> <volume>50</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>714</fpage>–<lpage>735</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dugan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The making of the Global Terrorism Database and what we have learned about the life cycles of terrorist organizations</article-title>. Unpublished paper.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Enders</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>The Political Economy of Terrorism</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Enders</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gaibulloev</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Domestic versus transnational terrorism: Data, decomposition, and dynamics</article-title>. <source>Journal of Peace Research</source> <volume>48</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eubank</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Does democracy encourage terrorism?</article-title> <source>Terrorism and Political Violence</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eubank</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Terrorism and democracy: Perpetrators and victims</article-title>. <source>Terrorism and Political Violence</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eyerman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Terrorism and democratic states: Soft targets or accessible systems</article-title>. <source>International Interactions</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fast</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Mind the gap: Documenting and explaining violence against aid workers</article-title>. <source>European Journal of International Relations</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laitin</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Ethnicity, insurgency, and civil war</article-title>. <source>American Political Science Review</source> <volume>97</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fekete</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The Terrorism Act 2000: An interview with Gareth Pierce</article-title>. <source>Race and Class</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Franzese</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Spatial econometric models of cross-sectional interdependence in political science panel and time-series–cross-section data</article-title>. <source>Political Analysis</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>140</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freilich</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Opesso</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Immigration, security, and civil liberties post 9/11: A comparison of American, Australian and Canadian legislative and policy changes</article-title>. In <source>Migration, Culture Conflict, Crime, and Terrorism</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Freilich</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guerette</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group> pp. <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Aldershot</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luechinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Measuring terrorism</article-title>. In <source>Law and the State: A Political Economy Approach</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Marciano</surname><given-names>Alain</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Josselin</surname><given-names>Jean-Michel</given-names></name></person-group> pp. <fpage>142</fpage>–<lpage>181</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Northampton, MA and Cheltenham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Edward Elgar</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luechinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stutzer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Calculating tragedy: Assessing the costs of terrorism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Economic Surveys</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gassebner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luechinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Lock, stock, and barrel: A comprehensive assessment of the determinants of terror</article-title>. <source>Public Choice</source> <volume>149</volume>(<issue>3–4</issue>): <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Givens</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2008</year>) <source>Immigration Policy and Security: U.S., European, and Commonwealth Perspectives</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gleditsch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Expanded trade and GDP data</article-title>. <source>Journal of Conflict Resolution</source> <volume>46</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>712</fpage>–<lpage>724</lpage> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://privatewww.essex.ac.uk/~ksg/exptradegdp.html">http://privatewww.essex.ac.uk/~ksg/exptradegdp.html</ext-link>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gleditsch</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wallensteen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sollenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Armed Conflict 1946–2001: A new dataset</article-title>. <source>Journal of Peace Research</source> <volume>39</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>615</fpage>–<lpage>637</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Dirty pool</article-title>. <source>International Organization</source> <volume>55</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Econometric Analysis</source>, <edition>5th edn.</edition> <publisher-loc>Upper Saddle River, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Greenhill</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Weapons of Mass Migration: Forced Displacement, Coercion and Foreign Policy</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guild</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>International terrorism and EU immigration, asylum and borders policy: The unexpected victims of 11 September 2001</article-title>. <source>European Foreign Affairs Review</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heston</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aten</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Penn World Table version 6.3</article-title>. <publisher-name>Center for International Comparisons of Production, Income and Prices at the University of Pennsylvania</publisher-name> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pwt.econ.upenn.edu/php_site/pwt_index.php">http://pwt.econ.upenn.edu/php_site/pwt_index.php</ext-link>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hilbe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Negative Binomial Regression</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>The Tragedy of Failure: Evaluating State Failure and Its Impact on the Spread of Refugees, Terrorism, and War</source>. <publisher-loc>Santa Barbara, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Praeger</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Who fights? The determinants of participation in civil war</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Political Science</source> <volume>52</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>436</fpage>–<lpage>455</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jessen-Petersen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>International migration and security: A pragmatic response</article-title>. In <source>Migration and the New Europe</source>, ed. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>Kimberly A.</given-names></name></person-group> pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Centre for Strategic and International Studies</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Explaining rare events in international relations</article-title>. <source>International Organization</source> <volume>55</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>715</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meierrieks</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>What causes terrorism?</article-title> <source>Public Choice</source> <volume>147</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>What Makes a Terrorist: Economics and the Roots of Terrorism</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>LaFree</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ackerman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The empirical study of terrorism: Social and legal research</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Law and Social Science</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>LaFree</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dugan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Introducing the Global Terrorism Database</article-title>. <source>Terrorism and Political Violence</source> <volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>LaFree</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dugan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fahey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Global terrorism and failed states</article-title>. In <source>Peace and Conflict</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>J. Joseph</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilkenfeld</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robert Gurr</surname><given-names>Ted</given-names></name></person-group> pp. <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Boulder, CO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Paradigm</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Does democracy promote or reduce transnational terrorist incidents?</article-title> <source>Journal of Conflict Resolution</source> <volume>49</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lischer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Dangerous Sanctuaries: Refugee Camps, Civil War, and the Dilemmas of Humanitarian Aid</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freese</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Regression Models for Categorical Dependent Variables Using Stata</source>, <edition>2nd edn.</edition> <publisher-loc>College Station, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stata</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lujala</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gleditsch</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gilmore</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A diamond curse? Civil war and a lootable resource</article-title>. <source>Journal of Conflict Resolution</source> <volume>49</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>538</fpage>–<lpage>562</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Forcibly displaced populations, 1964–2008. United States Committee for Refugees and Immigrants (USCRI)</article-title>, <source>World Refugee Survey</source> (Annual Series) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.systemicpeace.org/inscr/inscr.htm">http://www.systemicpeace.org/inscr/inscr.htm</ext-link>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jaggers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>POLITY IV Project: Political regime characteristics and transitions, 1800–2006, dataset users’ manual</article-title> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.systemicpeace.org/inscr/p4manualv2006.pdf">http://www.systemicpeace.org/inscr/p4manualv2006.pdf</ext-link>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kilner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Danish aid workers stay away from Muslim ceremony</article-title>. <source>Reuters</source>. <month>February</month> <fpage>9</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mickolus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murdock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Flemming</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>International Terrorism: Attributes of Terrorist Events, 1968–2008</source>. <publisher-loc>Dunn Loring, VA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Vinyard Software</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nezer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The material support problem: Where U.S. anti-terrorism laws, refugee protection, and foreign policy collide</article-title>. <source>Brown Journal of World Affairs</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Piazza</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Incubators of terror: Do failed states and failing states promote transnational terrorism?</article-title> <source>International Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>52</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>488</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Piazza</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Poverty, minority economic discrimination and domestic terrorism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Peace Research</source> <volume>48</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Plümper</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neumayer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Model specification in the analysis of spatial dependence</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Political Research</source> <volume>49</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>418</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Political Instability Task Force</collab> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Internal wars and failures of governance, 1955–2006</article-title> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://globalpolicy.gmu.edu/pitf/pitfpset.htm">http://globalpolicy.gmu.edu/pitf/pitfpset.htm</ext-link>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Prunier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Africa’s World War: Congo, the Rwandan Genocide, and the Making of a Continental Catastrophe</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Staying Alive: Safety and Security Guidelines for Volunteers in Conflict Areas</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Committee of the Red Cross</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosenblum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salehyan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Norms and interests in US asylum enforcement</article-title>. <source>Journal of Peace Research</source> <volume>41</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>677</fpage>–<lpage>697</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rotberg</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Failed states in a world of terror</article-title>. <source>Foreign Affairs</source> <volume>81</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salehyan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The externalities of civil strife: Refugees as a source of international conflict</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Political Science</source> <volume>52</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>787</fpage>–<lpage>801</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salehyan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Rebels Without Borders: Transnational Insurgencies in World Politics</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salehyan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gleditsch</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Refugees and the spread of civil war</article-title>. <source>International Organization</source> <volume>60</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>366</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Enders</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>An economic perspective on transnational terrorism</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Political Economy</source> <volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Savun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Democracy, foreign policy, and terrorism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Conflict Resolution</source> <volume>53</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>878</fpage>–<lpage>904</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Terrorism and democracy</article-title>. <source>Terrorism and Political Violence</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sidebotham</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Immigration policies and the war on terrorism</article-title>. <source>Denver Journal of International Law and Policy</source> <volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>581</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tomz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>RELOGIT: Rare Events Logistic Regression, version 1.1</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University</publisher-name> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gking.harvard.edu/">http://gking.harvard.edu/</ext-link>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>US Census Bureau, Population Division</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>International database (IDB)</article-title> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.census.gov/ipc/www/idb/summaries.html">http://www.census.gov/ipc/www/idb/summaries.html</ext-link>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Security, stability, and international migration</article-title>. <source>International Security</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Detention of asylum seekers in the UK and USA: Deciphering noisy and quiet constructions</article-title>. <source>Punishment and Society</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whitaker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Refugees: The security dimension</article-title>. <source>Citizenship Studies</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>434</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Findley</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Promises and pitfalls of terrorism research</article-title>. <source>International Studies Review</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>431</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-0738894212456951">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Exclusion, terrorism, and the refugee convention</article-title>. <source>Forced Migration Review</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>