<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CTJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spctj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Trials</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical Trials</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1740-7745</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1740-7753</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1740774512461978</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1740774512461978</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Data Management and Trial Conduct</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Academic investigator-initiated trials and the challenge of sponsor responsibility: the Cologne Sponsor Model</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Georgias</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1740774512461978">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Grunow</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1740774512461978">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Olderog</surname><given-names>Miriam</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1740774512461978">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>May</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1740774512461978">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Paulus</surname><given-names>Ursula</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1740774512461978">a</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1740774512461978"><label>a</label>Clinical Trials Center Cologne, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1740774512461978"><label>b</label>Legal Department, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1740774512461978">Christine Georgias, Clinical Trials Center Cologne, BMBF01KN1106, University of Cologne, Gleueler Str. 269, Cologne 50935, Germany. Email: <email>christine.georgias@uk-koeln.de</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<issue-title>University of Pennsylvania Conference on Statistical Issues in Clinical Trials: Emerging statistical issues in the conduct and monitoring of clinical trials</issue-title>
<fpage>781</fpage>
<lpage>787</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s), 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The Society for Clinical Trials</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-1740774512461978">
<title>Background</title>
<p>With the amendment to the German Drug Law in 2004, the conduct of clinical trials changed by at least two main aspects: (1) The principles of Good Clinical Practice (GCP) were implemented in the national legislation, and (2) for the first time, the function of the sponsor of a clinical trial and the clinical trial itself have become legally binding definitions. By that, legal differences between industrial and academic clinical trials no longer exist. Clinical trials initiated by investigators have to fulfil the same requirements while the entire sponsor responsibility has to be carried out by the Coordinating Investigator or his institution including implementation of a quality management system according to the GCP.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1740774512461978">
<title>Purpose</title>
<p>The Cologne Sponsor Model is an effective approach with settings, structures, basic features, action, and reporting lines, as well as funding for clinical trials initiated in an academic environment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1740774512461978">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The University of Cologne assumes the sponsor responsibility for clinical trials organised by the university researchers according to law. Sponsor’s duties are delegated to a central operational unit of the sponsor – the Clinical Trials Center Cologne – which further delegates duties to the Coordinating Investigator. Clinical Trials Center Cologne was established in 2002 to support the performance of clinical trials at the university by offering comprehensive advisory and practical services covering all aspects of study planning and conduct. Furthermore, a specialised division of its quality management department acts as an independent sponsor’s Quality Assurance Unit. The Clinical Trials Center Cologne has established a quality management system consisting of different components (1) to enable a reasoned decision to subsequent delegation, (2) for risk-based surveillance of trial conduct (audits, monitoring-checks, and reports), and (3) support and training of the Coordinating Investigator.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1740774512461978">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>Double functions of persons and departments in the university environment sometimes make it difficult to define roles in such a model. Therefore, it is necessary to establish clear reporting lines and moreover to monitor regularly and carefully the roles and responsibilities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1740774512461978">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>With the combination of central management and support, control and independence of the researchers, our model represents a ‘risk-based’ system that offers a sensible option that fulfils the requirements of legal regulations and GCP for trials organised within the university environment.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section6-1740774512461978" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The principles of the International Conference on Harmonization (ICH) Guideline on Good Clinical Practice (GCP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1740774512461978">1</xref>] for clinical investigations in European Union (EU) member states became binding with the issuing of EU Directive 2001/20/EG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1740774512461978">2</xref>]. In Germany, the directive was implemented in the national legislation in the 12th Amendment to the German Drug Law (AMG) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1740774512461978">3</xref>] and in the GCP Regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1740774512461978">4</xref>] that came into force in August 2004. Since then, for the first time, the concept and function of the sponsor of a clinical study have had legally binding definitions: ‘The sponsor is a natural or legal person who is responsible for initiating, organising and financing a clinical study in humans’. This definition is valid for all interventional clinical studies within the jurisdiction of the AMG. An equivalent definition of the sponsor in trials with medical devices was included in the Amendment to the German Medical Product Law that came into force in March 2010.</p>
<p>Because of these changes in legislation, the issues surrounding sponsor function are in urgent need of regulation with regard to non-commercial studies initiated as part of academic research (investigator-initiated trials (IITs)). Authorities and auditors no longer differentiate between the industrial and the academic environments. Especially important is the requirement that a sponsor carries the entire responsibility for a clinical trial and for setting up a quality management system in accordance with the GCP, thus posing a great challenge for Coordinating Investigators, who are the usual initiators of IITs.</p>
<p>Different ways of fulfilling the requirements of the sponsor in the academic environment have been discussed, especially with regard to questions of liability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1740774512461978">5</xref>]. These complex issues concern financial liabilities in case of injury to a study participant, but also responsibility for procedural or organisational obligations and, as these may be assured by punishment or fine, penal liability. All these matters will influence the design of an academic sponsor organisation.</p>
<p>Although legally permitted, it is not suitable for the Coordinating Investigators themselves to assume the role of the sponsor. In addition to the aspects of liability, it is practically impossible for a single person to assume the responsibilities and duties required by GCP, particularly for a multicentre trial. Moreover, the ICH-GCP guideline and the German Drug Law imply that the sponsor and the investigator should be independent of one another. In other words, there should be a clear separation between organisational and medical responsibilities.</p>
<p>One solution is to form a ‘Sponsor-GmbH’ (sponsor’s limited company), which is the option chosen by some study groups and scientific societies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1740774512461978">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1740774512461978">6</xref>]. The advantage of this solution is that the financial and procedural liabilities are limited to the company capital. The administration of a limited company, however, involves additional expense and effort.</p>
<p>The responsibilities of the sponsor increasingly are being assumed directly by universities or, in some cases, by university hospitals. This approach fulfils the legal requirement as well as the requirement of public financiers of IITs in Germany, who stipulate that the institution take on the role of the sponsor for IITs, even those outside the jurisdiction of the AMG or German Medical Device Act.</p>
<p>However, the organisational structures of universities and associated hospitals are not designed to assume the function of the sponsor. Although university hospitals are centres of outstanding clinical excellence and have a dense network of contacts with scientific partners for the conduct of clinical trials, the degree of expertise in organisation and quality management of clinical trials varies widely and is often not well established. Thus, the necessary structures have to be put in place, and processes have to be adapted to the new requirements before complete responsibility for a trial can be assumed by a university or medical centre.</p>
<p>The Cologne Sponsor Model provides an effective approach in which necessary settings, structures, and basic features are introduced and from which IITs can be conducted to conform to GCP requirements in a risk-controlled way while maintaining the independence of the researchers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1740774512461978" sec-type="results">
<title>Results: the Cologne Sponsor Model</title>
<p>Although the University of Cologne and University Hospital of Cologne are legally independent entities, they work very closely together. The university is legally bound to promote research efforts and therefore to promote clinical trials. The University Hospital of Cologne supports the Medical Faculty of the university in fulfilling its research and teaching commitments and also provides health-care services for patients, including high-performance medicine.</p>
<p>Because research efforts are within the competence of the university, the University of Cologne has declared, in accord with the 12th Amendment to the AMG, that it will assume the responsibility of a sponsor for all clinical research projects at the University of Cologne for which a sponsor is required. Fundamental to the decision of the university, besides the cooperation with the clinical hospital and its researchers, was the existence of the Clinical Trials Center Cologne (CTCC), which is an established central structure with the necessary expertise in the management of clinical trials. The Cologne Sponsor Model, with its delineation and delegation of roles and responsibilities, was developed jointly by the CTCC and the University Legal Department in order to map the legal liabilities and duties appropriately.</p>
<sec id="section8-1740774512461978">
<title>Structures for clinical trials at the University of Cologne</title>
<p>The CTCC was established in 2002 at the University of Cologne under a grant from the Federal Ministry for Education and Research (BMBF). The centre is a unit of the Medical Faculty of the University of Cologne whose charge is to support the conduct of clinical trials and the improvement of the quality of patient-oriented clinical research in the academic environment. The CTCC is divided into a Methodological Division and a Medical Division. The Methodological Division consists of several departments: project management, data management, monitoring, serious adverse event (SAE) management, training, information technology, and quality management. The quality management department is an independent central, comprehensive department that serves both divisions. For statistical and biometrical aspects, the Institute for Medical Statistics (IMSIE) of the university is the collaboration partner of the CTCC. The Medical Division is responsible for central site management, the development of clinical study centres at the University Hospital of Cologne, and further development of the modules of the Surgical and Paediatric Networks. The CTCC is headed by a board elected every 2 years by the Medical Faculty.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1740774512461978">
<title>Basic features of the Cologne Sponsor Model</title>
<p>The university assumes the sponsor function for a study that is initiated by a member of the university staff and for which no third party (e.g., a commercial company) is the sponsor. Furthermore, the financing of the study must be assured, and GCP principles must be adopted and implemented, so there may be no evident special financial or procedural liability risk for the university.</p>
<p>The university has formally assigned the Methodological Division of the CTCC to assume the duties of the executive organ of the sponsor, to delegate these to the Coordinating Investigator, and to monitor that all requirements are fulfilled (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1740774512461978">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1740774512461978" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The Cologne Sponsor Model.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1740774512461978-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>To fulfil these responsibilities without conflict with its role as a service provider, the Methodological Division of the CTCC has set up an independent Quality Assurance Unit (QAU) and has established a quality management system consisting of different components. This system should enable a reasoned decision as to whether the sponsor’s responsibilities should be assumed by the university and those responsibilities to be delegated to the Coordinating Investigator. Moreover, the system permits risk-based surveillance of study conduct. The qualification of the CTCC for its tasks is confirmed by regular external audits contracted by the university.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1740774512461978">
<title>Different components of the Quality Assurance System</title>
<sec id="section11-1740774512461978">
<title>Initial consulting and GCP assessment of a clinical trial</title>
<p>Before the University of Cologne assumes the sponsor function, the QAU assesses whether provisions for study management are able to fulfil the duties of sponsor and whether the study complies with ICH-GCP and can be performed in accordance with legal and regulatory requirements. The assessment is based on the essential documents of a clinical trial as part of a formal application: the trial protocol, patient information sheet, and the Summary of Product Characteristics or the Investigator’s Brochure. Information on resources, financial planning and funding, as well as the delegation of sponsor duties to third parties, qualifications of the third party, and any special aspects of the trial, are also required. Open questions are clarified in discussions among all parties. The assessment procedure and the results are summarised in a written report by the QAU.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1740774512461978">
<title>Delegation of sponsor duties and authorisation of the Coordinating Investigator as sponsor’s representative</title>
<p>Based on the QAU’s assessment report, the management of the Methodological Division decides to assume the sponsor function, on behalf of the University of Cologne, and to delegate the sponsor duties to the Coordinating Investigator. An agreement with a detailed list of the sponsor’s duties that are delegated (financing, pharmacovigilance, application to institutional review board and authorities, etc.) is signed by the Coordinating Investigator who then is authorised to act as a representative of the sponsor. The Coordinating Investigator assumes almost all sponsor duties; however, quality assurance audits and clinical monitoring cannot be assumed by the Coordinating Investigator.</p>
<p>The conduct of audits is an integral part of the quality assurance activities of the sponsor of clinical trials and therefore falls within the competence of the QAU. Monitoring as part of quality control has to be contracted to a qualified organisation that is not directly dependent on the Coordinating Investigator, that is, not a subordinate employee, to assure the separation of trial conduct and control. The Coordinating Investigator is free to choose the monitoring department of the CTCC or an external service provider. In the latter case, the QAU ensures that the monitoring is in conformance with GCP by assessing the qualifications, standard operating procedures (SOPs), and sample monitoring reports of the contracted service provider. Furthermore, in cases where GCP violations are detected, the QAU intervenes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1740774512461978">
<title>Audits</title>
<p>To conduct audits effectively, a clearly nominated QAU must perform audits independently of operative functions and report directly to the management. Within the university structure, this requirement is not easy to organise. For example, researchers at the university act as Coordinating Investigator and at the same time are part of the management of the CTCC.</p>
<p>The independence of the QAU is stated in the constitution of the CTCC. The QAU prepares an annual risk-based audit programme that determines the time points and focus of audits for individual trials and institutions that are involved in the trial conduct. Objective criteria with regard to the type and complexity of a trial (e.g., design, phase, number of centres, indication, and trial population) and the experience and qualifications of the sponsor’s representative and any service provider involved are taken into account when evaluating the risk potential. With regard to the audit reports and findings, a direct reporting line to the Research Dean, as a representative of the Faculty of Medicine and of the university, has been set up. The Dean is informed of major or critical GCP findings and could be consulted about the handling of any necessary consequences. This reporting path ensures the involvement of an individual who can act as a decision-maker and who can stop a trial, if judged necessary, or can refer this decision on to the Rector’s Office.</p>
<p>All these mechanisms are important to the effectiveness of the approach as well as for the acceptance of the audit function at the university hospital. As many Coordinating Investigators are not experienced with being audited, because in the past, IITs were often ‘uncontrolled’ in the sense of classical sponsor audits, initially, there was scepticism about the feasibility of the Cologne Sponsor Model. Therefore, the QAU often collaborates with external lead auditors. Finally, acceptance can be achieved by promoting the perception of the auditors as supporters and partners in a system of continuous quality improvement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1740774512461978">7</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1740774512461978">
<title>Reporting lines and escalation</title>
<p>The head of the Methodological Division and the QAU have primary responsibility for fulfilling the sponsor’s tasks on behalf of the university. Usually, the head of the Methodological Division decides on whether to assume responsibility for the sponsor function on the basis of the written assessment report and the recommendation of the QAU.</p>
<p>In cases where QAU personnel or the head of the Methodological Division identifies problems or special risks (e.g., liability risks, inadequate financing, first-in-human studies, large international studies, and studies outside the EU), the assessment process can be escalated to the board of the CTCC. Board involvement also occurs when the involved persons, that is, the QAU, head of the Methodological Division, and Coordinating Investigator, cannot agree on a solution. The board decides whether the decision has to be further escalated to the Dean’s Office or, for a final decision, to the University Rector’s Office.</p>
<p>The head of the Methodological Division and the QAU report annually to the University Rector’s Office on the status of sponsor function activities. Furthermore, the Rector’s Office is informed immediately about special circumstances that may have consequences for the university, such as a finding that patients’ rights are not being preserved or a critical finding in an authority’s inspection of the trial.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1740774512461978">
<title>Further quality assurance and support of IITs at the University of Cologne</title>
<p>In the Cologne Sponsor Model, the Coordinating Investigator acts as an official representative of the sponsor, and therefore, must have a thorough knowledge of the responsibilities of a sponsor and the regulatory basis. Therefore, the CTCC established a series of quality management measures. Indifferent ways, these measures provide Coordinating Investigators as sponsor’s representatives with information, tools, training, consultation, and service, thus ensuring that all phases of study conduct are carried out with the necessary attention to quality.</p>
<p>One main activity of the CTCC is the basic and advanced training of physicians and other study staff in the area of clinical research. Courses offered especially for Coordinating Investigators prepare them for the responsibility of being the sponsor’s representative and for the sponsor’s duties that are to be fulfilled. Furthermore, the CTCC departments offer consultation that covers all aspects of a clinical trial. Practical information on performing the sponsor’s duties in every day practice and references to suitable materials, links, and templates are summarised in an IIT Manual.</p>
<p>A further instrument to ensure GCP compliance is the quality management coaching to implement quality management in the Coordinating Investigator’s facility. The largest responsibility of the quality management coach is coordination and supervision of a working group in which SOP templates for key processes in central study management (ICH-GCP, 5) and processes at trial sites (ICH-GCP, 4) are being developed together with representatives of the facilities conducting studies at the university hospital. The adaptation of the SOP templates to individual facilities ensures that the most important aspects of a quality management system, reasonably adapted for the academic environment, are implemented. General sponsor processes increasingly are governed by SOPs within the university. Additionally, the quality management coach provides individual advice on quality management issues such as the postprocessing of audits and preparation for inspections or certifications.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1740774512461978">
<title>Sponsor function for multinational studies</title>
<p>Assuming the sponsor function for a multinational study poses special challenges for an academic institution, especially because the financial resources for IITs are often limited. The AMG and EU Directive 2001/20/EG require a single sponsor with overall responsibility for studies conducted in the EU. This requirement mandates an in-depth knowledge of the way in which the directive has been implemented in the different health and legal systems in the EU which the Coordinating Investigators do not necessarily have. For trials conducted with sites outside the EU, the challenges are even greater.</p>
<p>The Cologne concept for the conduct of international studies therefore relies on cooperation with national institutions that take over the central organisation for the country and are national ‘authorised institutions’. The national institution can be a structure similar to the CTCC, a hospital, a university, or a service provider, for example, a Clinical Research Organisation (CRO). At least for the studies initiated so far, Cologne has been able to benefit from existing cooperative ventures, especially from the existing study groups in Cologne.</p>
<p>A concept that holds much promise for the implementation of international IITs is the European Clinical Research Infrastructures Network (ECRIN) Programme. The aim of the ECRIN Programme is to set up a not-for-profit pan-European infrastructure incorporating national networks and institutions (clinical research centres and clinical trials units), so that coordination and service structures for the implementation and conduct of multinational clinical studies are in place.</p>
<p>If established cooperative ventures and structures described earlier for the study groups and ECRIN structures are not available, national sponsor’s authorised institutions are identified with the help of the co-operating partners of the Coordinating Investigator, that is, the medical co-operating partners, who typically have experience in conducting clinical trials and have contacts with appropriate units or organisations.</p>
<p>Before delegating responsibilities to institutions abroad, it is essential that the qualifications of the national sponsor’s authorised institution are thoroughly checked. This initial check is based on documents and certificates expected to demonstrate that the institution has the infrastructure, experience, and qualifications to fulfil the Sponsor’s duties in the respective country. In case the national institution is unwilling, unable, or insufficiently qualified to assume all the legal duties envisioned for a sponsor, the corresponding tasks remain the direct responsibility of the University of Cologne. Delegation of the sponsor’s duties is documented as a part of a contract between the University of Cologne as the sponsor and the national institution, with a planned audit of the national institution during the course of the study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1740774512461978">
<title>Experiences with the Cologne Sponsor Model</title>
<p>Before implementation of the Cologne Sponsor Model in 2006, the new legal situation, the responsibilities, and duties caused insecurity among many researchers. The result was that no or only a few trials were initiated. Introduction of the Cologne Sponsor Model opened the floodgates to a backlog of planned studies.</p>
<p>Since 2006, 52 applications have been submitted for the university to assume sponsor responsibility; 36 applications have been approved so far. The remainder either still are being processed or were turned down for different reasons, such as inadequate financing or organisational obstacles. More than half of approved trials (n = 22) are multicentre studies. Five studies are international with a total of eight different countries involved. For oncology studies, non-profit organisations similar to the CTCC often are authorised directly by the sponsor. For example, in Austria and Switzerland, similar organisations take on sponsor duties and complete the organisation of the study within the corresponding country. In other countries, for example, the Czech Republic, Denmark, and the Netherlands, the university or the university hospital is the authorised institution of the country and is represented by the national Coordinating Investigator who further delegates the sponsor tasks to commercial CROs or non-profit organisations similar to the CTCC.</p>
<p>Based on the risk assessments, the QAU generally performs four audits a year, some with external lead auditors. The results of the audits show that a considerable number of problems, sometimes serious, remain in study management and conduct. On the part of the Coordinating Investigator, for example, roles and responsibilities still are unclear, approval processes are missing, or the resolution and consequences of deficiencies identified during clinical monitoring are not established. On the part of study sites, auditors still find incorrect consent forms, delayed SAE reports, and violations of inclusion and exclusion criteria. These findings confirm that quality assurance procedures and monitoring are important to identify shortcomings. The first aim of the QAU and the CTCC is to support the Coordinating Investigator to resolve problems, that is, with the help from the quality management coach. Currently, a formal corrective and preventive action (CAPA) process is being established to guide this process and achieve effective improvement. In case of inadequate performance and insufficient quality, the QAU can escalate reporting to the Research Dean and up to the Rector’s Office; either of these individuals can close a trial site or the complete trial if necessary.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1740774512461978">
<title>Financing</title>
<p>The CTCC has one scientist position financed by the Faculty of Medicine of the University of Cologne. In addition, one position is being financed for the next 4 years by the (BMBF) as part of a grant for the improvement of ‘Clinical Study Centres’. The objective of the latter funding is further development and conception of the Cologne Sponsor Model. To achieve sustainability, it is planned that all quality assurance activities increasingly will be financed out of the study budgets. The costs for audits at investigational sites in multicentre trials or for audits of the national sponsor’s authorised institution for multinational trials already must be borne by the respective trial budget. These costs pose a challenge as IITs generally still have limited budgets. Meanwhile, public as well as private financiers increasingly pay the costs for quality assurance of a trial.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1740774512461978" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="section20-1740774512461978">
<title>CTCC as the central structure in the Cologne Sponsor Model</title>
<p>After enactment of the amendment to the AMG in 2004, the University of Cologne decided to assume the sponsor function for IITs conducted at the university or university hospital. Crucial for the decision of the university was the fact that the necessary expertise and support by an appropriate organisation, the CTCC, were in place. This qualified central unit that was integrated into the university research structure and the established independent QAU put the risks taken by the university as sponsor into a manageable perspective.</p>
<p>The CTCC is qualified to perform the tasks of the sponsor for a number of reasons. On one hand, the CTCC offers comprehensive advisory and practical services covering all aspects of study planning and conduct, and, in collaboration with the IMSIE, study evaluation. Especially, in areas that require high levels of expertise, such as SAE management, project management, and data management, resources can be concentrated to create properly qualified departments for the whole university hospital. On the other hand, based on its expertise, the CTCC is in a position to establish and perform the central quality assurance for the University of Cologne as sponsor. The university fulfils its responsibility to organise, control, and supervise by contracting external auditors to monitor the performance and qualifications of the CTCC.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-1740774512461978">
<title>What makes the Cologne Sponsor Model different?</title>
<p>In the academic environment, more and more universities and university hospitals are assuming the sponsor function for studies initiated by their researchers. However, it is rare that a central qualified unit such as the CTCC is responsible for all sponsor duties and for their delegation. In the Cologne Sponsor Model, very controlled conditions for university research have been created by incorporating the CTCC as a central unit of the sponsor directly into organisational and quality assurance activities. The Cologne Sponsor Model has been designed to give Coordinating Investigators as much autonomy as possible to design and conduct their trials. The quality management system developed and coordinated by CTCC provides, on the one hand, central quality assurance services and the possibility of involving the CTCC as an internal service provider concerning central services as SAE or data management. On the other hand, the CTCC offers a wide range of other quality management services that enable conduct of GCP-compliant trials by decentralised units. The mixture of central management and support for decentralised units represents a controlled-risk system that offers a sensible option to satisfy the requirements of GCP for the university environment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-1740774512461978">
<title>Assessment of the Cologne Sponsor Model and development perspectives</title>
<p>With the Cologne Sponsor Model, the University of Cologne has found a practicable means of implementing the requirements of the EU Directive 2001/20/EG and the 2004 amendment of the AMG in the academic environment, enabling the proper conduct of IITs. Challenges such as definition of roles and responsibilities, controlled delegation of duties, quality management according to GCP, knowledge and expertise regarding regulatory requirements and methodology and resources and risk management are accommodated within the model. The established structures and processes of the Cologne Sponsor Model contribute to data integrity and to patient security and protection within clinical trials.</p>
<p>Initially, there was scepticism with regard to the Cologne Sponsor Model on the part of Coordinating Investigators and researchers in Cologne. But the support of the CTCC in the service sector as well as within the quality management system with both centralised and decentralised components resulted in understanding and acceptance. Very positive responses to the Cologne Sponsor Model have been received from the authorities as well as from the industrial partners.</p>
<p>Now that the quality assurance function has been accepted and the general processes have been established, current discussions concern moving the QAU to the Research Dean’s office. The proposed relocation of the QAU should resolve potential conflicts of interest among the researchers and within the CTCC. Furthermore, the position of the QAU will be consolidated at the faculty and university level; as research activities are the Dean’s responsibility, the Cologne Sponsor Model will have more authority in terms of necessary actions and consequences in cases of quality shortcomings. The CTCC will keep its central role as executive institution and competent partner for clinical research at the university and as supporter of the sponsor.</p>
<p>The Cologne Sponsor Model is a practicable and effective ‘risk-based’ system that offers a sensible option for fulfilling the requirements of legal regulations and GCP for the university environment. However, the realisation of GCP requirements for IITs will remain challenging especially in the current environment of limited financial resources for research.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This study was supported by the BMBF (BMBF01K N1106).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interest</label>
<p>The authors have no conflict of interest to declare.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1740774512461978">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>ICH Topic E 6 (R1) Guideline for Good Clinical Practice</collab>. <article-title>International conference on harmonisation of technical requirements for registration of pharmaceuticals for human use (ICH) guideline E6: E6, note for guidance on good clinical practice, consolidated guideline (CPMP/ICH/135/95)</article-title>, <year>1997</year>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.emea.europa.eu/docs/en_GB/document_library/Scientific_guideline/2009/09/WC500002874.pdf">http://www.emea.europa.eu/docs/en_GB/document_library/Scientific_guideline/2009/09/WC500002874.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1740774512461978">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>Directive 2001/20/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 4 April 2001 on the approximation of the laws, regulations and administrative provisions of the Member States relating to the implementation of good clinical practice in the conduct of clinical trials on medicinal products for human use</collab>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1740774512461978">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>Arzneimittelgesetz (AMG) zuletzt geändert durch die 12. AMG-Novelle vom 30.Juli</collab> <year>2004</year> (BGBl. I S.2031), in Kraft getreten am 6. August 2004.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1740774512461978">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>Verordnung über die Anwendung der Guten Klinischen Praxis bei der Durchführung von klinischen Prüfungen mit Arzneimitteln zur Anwendung am Menschen (GCP-Verordnung - GCP-V) vom</collab> <day>9</day> <month>August</month> <year>2004</year> (BGBl. I <year>2004</year> S. 2081)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1740774512461978">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sträter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Kurzgutachten zur Übernahme der Sponsorverantwortung in klinischen Studien im Auftrag der TMF e.V</source>, <year>2005</year>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tmf-ev.de/Produkte/Uebersicht.aspx">http://www.tmf-ev.de/Produkte/Uebersicht.aspx</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1740774512461978">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Stellungnahme zu den Auswirkungen des neuen AMG auf die nichtindutrielle wissenschaftliche klinische Forschung</article-title>, <year>2005</year>. GMS Mitteilungen aus der AWMF; 2: Doc9.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1740774512461978">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="other">
<collab>Leitfaden für Qualitätsauditoren</collab>. <article-title>Planung und Durchführung von Audits nach ISO9001:2008</article-title>. Gerhard Gietl, Werner Lobinger. <year>2009</year> Carl Hanser Verlag München Wien.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>