<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EPM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spepm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Educational and Psychological Measurement</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0013-1644</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3888</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0013164411422250</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0013164411422250</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Establishing Effect Size Guidelines for Interpreting the Results of Differential Bundle Functioning Analyses Using SIBTEST</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>Cindy M.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0013164411422250">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0013164411422250">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>Kathleen</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0013164411422250">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Cappaert</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0013164411422250">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0013164411422250"><label>1</label>University of Wisconsin–Milwaukee, Milwaukee, WI, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0013164411422250"><label>2</label>University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0013164411422250">Cindy M. Walker, Department of Educational Psychology, University of Wisconsin–Milwaukee, PO Box 413, Milwaukee, WI 53201, USA Email: <email>cmwalker@uwm.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>72</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>415</fpage>
<lpage>434</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The purpose of this simulation study was to establish general effect size guidelines for interpreting the results of differential bundle functioning (DBF) analyses using simultaneous item bias test (SIBTEST). Three factors were manipulated: number of items in a bundle, test length, and magnitude of uniform differential item functioning (DIF) against the focal group in each item in a bundle. A secondary purpose was to validate the current effect size guidelines for interpreting the results of single-item DIF analyses using SIBTEST. The results of this study clearly demonstrate that ability estimation bias can only be attributed to DIF or DBF when a large number of items in a bundle are functioning differentially against focal examinees in a small way or a small number of items are functioning differentially against focal examinees in a large way. In either of these situations, the presence of DIF or DBF should be a cause for concern because it would lead one to erroneously believe that distinct groups differ in ability when in fact they do not.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>ability estimation</kwd>
<kwd>differential item functioning</kwd>
<kwd>effect size guidelines</kwd>
<kwd>SIBTEST achievement gap</kwd>
<kwd>racial group differences</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The issue of fairness in educational testing has been a concern for researchers, practitioners, and the public for some time now. An unfair test is one that disadvantages one group of examinees over another group of examinees, although both groups are equal in ability. One way in which researchers and practitioners have addressed the issue of fairness in educational testing is through differential item functioning (DIF) analyses. These analyses allow one to determine whether equal ability examinees from two distinct groups, referred to as the focal (i.e., female) and reference (i.e., male) groups, differ in their probability of answering a single test item correctly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0013164411422250">Angoff, 1993</xref>). DIF studies are often conducted in an exploratory fashion where each item is assessed in turn using the remaining test items as the matching subtest. Under this approach, substantive explanations as to why particular items function differentially for two distinct matched groups are postponed until after the items have been statistically flagged. An alternative approach is to conduct differential bundle functioning (DBF) analyses based on meaningful explanations for why certain bundles of items function differentially for distinct groups of examinees with equal ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0013164411422250">Douglas, Roussos, &amp; Stout, 1996</xref>). In this approach, substantive hypotheses are developed a priori to explain why bundles of items are functioning differentially and these hypotheses can then be tested using simultaneous item bias test (SIBTEST; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0013164411422250">Shealy &amp; Stout, 1993</xref>). This approach has great potential for helping psychometricians understand cultural and cognitive reasons for the occurrence of DIF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0013164411422250">K. Banks, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0013164411422250">Roussos &amp; Stout, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0013164411422250">Walker &amp; Beretvas, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0013164411422250">Walker, Zhang, &amp; Surber, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Specifically, the use of SIBTEST in DBF research has led to a greater understanding of DIF because of differences in accommodation status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0013164411422250">Finch, Barton, &amp; Meyer, 2009</xref>), culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0013164411422250">K. Banks, 2006</xref>), gender (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0013164411422250">Douglas et. al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0013164411422250">Gierl, Bisanz, Bisanz, &amp; Boughton, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0013164411422250">Gierl, Bisanz, Bisanz, Boughton, &amp; Khaliq, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0013164411422250">Mendes-Barnett &amp; Ercikan, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0013164411422250">K. E. Ryan &amp; Chiu, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0013164411422250">K. E. Ryan &amp; Fan, 1996</xref>), language spoken (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0013164411422250">Abbott, 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0013164411422250">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0013164411422250">Gierl &amp; Khaliq, 2001</xref>), reading ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0013164411422250">Walker et al., 2008</xref>), and writing ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0013164411422250">Walker &amp; Beretvas, 2001</xref>). SIBTEST has emerged as a quintessential method for conducting DBF research because of its (a) ability to detect DIF or DBF based on a researcher’s hypotheses, (b) ability to distinguish between genuine DIF/DBF and DIF/DBF due to impact (true mean ability differences between groups), and (c) use of a regression correction technique that deals with the problem of Type I error due to impact (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0013164411422250">Shealy &amp; Stout, 1993</xref>).</p>
<p>However, one issue that permeates the DIF research where SIBTEST is concerned is that, while there are guidelines for interpreting the size of DIF in individual items (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0013164411422250">Roussos &amp; Stout, 1996</xref>), there are presently no guidelines for interpreting the size of DIF in bundles of items. Researchers have been calling for the development of effect size guidelines in SIBTEST for some time now, and no one has taken up the challenge. Fifteen years ago, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0013164411422250">Douglas et. al. (1996)</xref> stated,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>a still further research question concerns how to judge the size of DIF displayed by a bundle. It is not clear how the typical criteria used in judging the level of item DIF could be extended to judging the level of bundle DIF or whether totally new criteria should be developed. (p. 466)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Four years ago, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0013164411422250">Abbott (2007)</xref> stated, “since researchers do not agree upon how to distinguish statistical from practical significance in DBF research, future research investigating and developing guidelines for interpreting bundle effect size measures is necessary” (p. 27).</p>
<p>It seems logical, given the impetus for DIF and DBF analyses, that any effect size guidelines for DIF detection procedures should take into consideration the impact of DIF and DBF on ability estimation bias which is independent of the power of the test statistic that is influenced by sample size. Today, test items are routinely examined to determine if they function differentially against certain groups of examinees prior to their use in any high-stakes large-scale testing endeavor. Items that are found to function differentially are typically revised or removed from the test altogether. However, despite attempts to ensure that tests are fair to all examinees, certain groups continue to lag behind others in their performance on high-stakes large-scale tests. Consider the National Assessment of Educational Progress (NAEP) as an example. English language learners (ELLs) lag behind non–English language learners (non-ELLs) on NAEP at Grades 4, 8, and 12 in reading, math, and science. In 2009, the largest difference in average scale score between ELLs and non-ELLs occurred at Grades 8 and 12. At Grade 8, the average scale score for ELLs was 50 points less than that for non-ELLs in science. At Grade 12, the average scale score for ELLs was 50 points less than that for non-ELLs in reading. Likewise, Blacks and Hispanics lag behind Whites on NAEP at Grades 4, 8, and 12 in reading, math, and science. However, the difference in average scale scores is more pronounced for Blacks. In 2009, the largest difference in average scale score between Blacks and Whites occurred at Grade 8 in science where the difference was 36 points.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0013164411422250">1</xref></sup> These findings inevitably beg the question of whether such disparities are caused by a series of items that are functioning differentially against the disadvantaged group, reflect true differences in achievement, or are the result of something else entirely.</p>
<p>Obviously, there is not one definitive reason why the achievement gap persists, but DIF analyses were first undertaken by the psychometric community in the 1960s in response to the public’s concern that achievement tests were unfair to minority examinees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0013164411422250">Angoff, 1993</xref>). The logic behind this effort was that if some test items focused on content that minority examinees were unfamiliar with then these examinees would be less likely to answer such items correctly even though they possessed the content knowledge measured by the test. The fact that the achievement gap continues despite meticulous test construction by test developers and item writers has resulted in a myriad explanations for the lingering achievement gap, other than the presence of DIF/DBF.</p>
<p>For example, when considering the achievement gap that persists for different racial groups it has been argued that “stereotype threat,” which exists when a person’s social identity is attached to a negative stereotype, may cause minority examinees to underperform in a manner consistent with the stereotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0013164411422250">Jordan &amp; Lovett, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0013164411422250">K. E. Ryan &amp; Ryan, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0013164411422250">Sackett, Hardison, &amp; Cullen, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0013164411422250">Steele, 1997</xref>). It has also been argued that the cultural mismatch between teachers, the majority of whom are middle-class White females, and students contributes to the achievement gap (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0013164411422250">Irvine, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0013164411422250">2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0013164411422250">Irvine &amp; Collison, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0013164411422250">Lee &amp; Majors, 2003</xref>). Also, teachers’ pedagogical practices can work to exacerbate or narrow the achievement gap (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0013164411422250">Cochran-Smith, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0013164411422250">Ladson-Billings, 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0013164411422250">2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0013164411422250">A. M. Ryan, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0013164411422250">Sleeter, 2001</xref>). Still another argument is that the very nature of the curriculum, which is believed to reflect the values, ideals, and perspectives of White middle-class Americans, has served to widen the achievement gap. Scholars who ascribe to this line of thinking posit that the achievement gap can be reduced through the adoption of a multicultural curriculum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0013164411422250">J. A. Banks, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0013164411422250">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0013164411422250">Gay, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>When considering the achievement gap that persists for ELL students, several studies have examined whether large-scale content area tests administered in English are valid measures of academic performance for ELL students (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0013164411422250">Mahoney, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0013164411422250">Martiniello, 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0013164411422250">2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0013164411422250">Ockey, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0013164411422250">Snetzler &amp; Qualls, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0013164411422250">Young et al., 2008</xref>). In each of these studies, although the mean score performance for ELL students was always significantly lower than that for non-ELL students, no systematic DIF against ELL students could be found. This suggests that the construct-irrelevant variance is external to the test. ELL students may face difficulty on large-scale tests because of their limited English vocabulary and inexperience with the English language. Research has shown that if a reader is to have any success at comprehension, he or she must know 95% of the printed words (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0013164411422250">Laufer, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0013164411422250">Liu &amp; Nation, 1985</xref>). This 95% includes 2,000 high-frequency items (87% of a given text) plus 800 terms from the University Word List (8% of a given text). Such a criterion is hard to attain for ELL students whose English vocabulary tends to be much smaller than that of native English speakers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0013164411422250">August, Carlo, Dressler, &amp; Snow, 2005</xref>). However, rather than urge test developers to simplify the language on large-scale tests, educators must find ways to increase the English vocabulary of ELL students. Educators must also work hard to teach ELL students how to navigate through the linguistic features they are likely to face on large-scale tests which include but are not limited to passive voice constructions, conditional clauses, long noun phrases, and relative clauses.</p>
<p>Given that there are a plethora of explanations for the lingering achievement gap, including the presence of DIF/DBF, coupled with the fact that the current effect size guidelines for interpreting the magnitude of DIF in single items when using SIBTEST is based on rules developed at ETS more than 20 years ago (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0013164411422250">Zwick &amp; Ercikan, 1989</xref>), it is imperative to establish more current effect size measures for SIBTEST that take into consideration the impact of DIF/DBF on ability estimation. Therefore, the primary purpose of this simulation study was to establish general effect size guidelines for interpreting the results of DBF analyses using SIBTEST. A secondary purpose was to validate the current effect size guidelines for interpreting the results of single-item DIF analyses using SIBTEST.</p>
<sec id="section1-0013164411422250">
<title>Overview of SIBTEST</title>
<p>SIBTEST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0013164411422250">Shealy &amp; Stout, 1993</xref>) uses a nonparametric statistical procedure to detect unidirectional DIF or DBF in dichotomous items. Unidirectional DIF occurs when the direction of DIF is constant across the ability scale. However, it should be noted that a version of SIBTEST known as Crossing-SIBTEST can be used if it is hypothesized that there is an interaction between ability and DIF such that an item functions differentially in favor of one group at lower levels of ability and functions differentially in favor of the other group at higher levels of ability.</p>
<p>DIF detection methods compensate for impact, or true mean ability differences between the two groups for which an item is thought to function differentially, by matching examinees on some conditioning variable and summarizing differences in item or bundle performance across the different levels of the conditioning variable. However, the presence of impact can still inflate the Type I error rates of DIF detection methods because the expected value of the reference group’s target ability will tend to differ from the corresponding expected value for the focal group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0013164411422250">Shealy &amp; Stout, 1993</xref>). SIBTEST uses a nonlinear regression correction to correct for this inflated Type-I error rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0013164411422250">Jiang &amp; Stout, 1998</xref>).</p>
<p>Specifically, SIBTEST is based on the assumption that DIF occurs when</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
<mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>|</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
<mml:mtext>F</mml:mtext>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>|</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0013164411422250" xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <italic>Y</italic> denotes the score on the studied item or bundle of items, <italic>T</italic> denotes the true score on the conditioning variable, and the subscript R or T refers to either the reference or the focal group, respectively. The conditioning variable used in SIBTEST is a matching subtest that consists of a set of items hypothesized to be unidimensional and therefore only measuring the primary construct of interest. The studied item is hypothesized to be multidimensional, measuring a secondary dimension on which the two matched groups are believed to differ, in addition to the primary construct of interest. The assumption outlined in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0013164411422250">Equation (1)</xref> implies that if <italic>E<sub>R</sub> [Y|T]</italic>−<italic>E<sub>F</sub> [Y|T]</italic> ≈ 0, then the studied item or set of items does not exhibit DIF or DBF. Denoting this difference by <italic>B</italic>(<italic>T</italic>), a global index of DIF can be obtained by</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="block" id="math2-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>uni</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mstyle displaystyle="true">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>∫</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0013164411422250" xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-eq2.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <italic>f</italic><sub>F</sub>(<italic>T</italic>) denotes the probability density function of <italic>T</italic> in the focal group. Therefore, the statistical procedure used by SIBTEST is H<sub>0</sub>: β = 0 versus H<sub>1</sub>: β ≠ 0. The global index of DIF is approximated by</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="block" id="math3-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mstyle displaystyle="true">
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-0013164411422250" xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-eq3.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <italic>n</italic> is defined to be the number of items in the matching subtest, <italic>p<sub>k</sub></italic> denotes the proportion of examinees who obtained a score of <italic>k</italic> on the matching subtest, and</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="block" id="math4-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
</mml:msubsup>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>¯</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
</mml:msubsup>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>¯</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>F</mml:mtext>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
</mml:msubsup>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula4-0013164411422250" xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-eq4.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <inline-formula id="inline-formula1-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math5-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>¯</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>G</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is defined to be the average performance on the studied item for examinees in group <italic>G</italic> (i.e., the reference or the focal group) who obtained a score of <italic>k</italic> on the matching subtest, corrected for bias. The matching subtest is corrected for bias by calculating an estimate of reliability, separately for both the reference and focal groups, and then using this estimate of reliability as the slope of a nonlinear regression of true scores on observed scores to estimate, <inline-formula id="inline-formula2-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math6-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>¯</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>G</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, the average performance on the studied item for group <italic>G</italic>. The average of the true scores for each of the two groups, <inline-formula id="inline-formula3-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math7-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>¯</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="inline-formula4-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math8-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>¯</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, is obtained using a first-order Taylor series approximation.</p>
<p>The test statistic corresponding to this global DIF index is defined by</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="block" id="math9-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula5-0013164411422250" xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-eq5.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula6-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="block" id="math10-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msqrt>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mstyle displaystyle="true">
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msubsup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>|</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>|</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>F</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>F</mml:mtext>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mstyle>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msqrt>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula6-0013164411422250" xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-eq6.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <inline-formula id="inline-formula5-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math11-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>|</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>G</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is the sample variance of the studied item for group <italic>G</italic> who obtained a score of <italic>k</italic> on the matching subtest. This test statistic, commonly referred to as beta-uni (β<sub>uni</sub>), is approximately normally distributed with a mean of 0 and a standard deviation of 1 and is easily generalized to test for DBF.</p>
<p>There has been extensive prior research investigating the influence of sample size on power and Type I error rates when using SIBTEST to detect DIF/DBF. However, it should be noted that this line of research is not particularly relevant to the current study because effect size measures should not be influenced by sample size. Whereas previous research, pertaining to the impact of sample size on power and Type I error rates, has focused on counting up the proportion of times the test statistic correctly (or incorrectly) rejected the null hypothesis, the present study focuses on how the presence of DIF/DBF affects the actual magnitude of <inline-formula id="inline-formula6-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math12-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, not how it affects the <italic>p</italic> value. Clearly, the <italic>p</italic> value may be affected by the magnitude of <inline-formula id="inline-formula7-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math13-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. However, it may also be affected by the standard error of <inline-formula id="inline-formula8-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math14-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and, when considering the impact of sample size on Type I error rates and power, it is likely that the standard error of <inline-formula id="inline-formula9-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math15-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is affected more than the magnitude of <inline-formula id="inline-formula10-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math16-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, because the computation of the standard error includes terms pertaining to the sample size of the reference and focal group (see <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula6-0013164411422250">Equation 6</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0013164411422250">Roussos and Stout (1996)</xref> found that even with as few as 250 examinees in the reference and focal groups, Type I and Type II errors were not inflated to a large degree, when impact was not present. With such small sample sizes, the Type I error rate was inflated slightly only in the presence of impact; however, this issue was only found with certain types of items (e.g., those with high discrimination and low difficulty). In terms of the effect of sample size on power, previous research has demonstrated that SIBTEST displays adequate power (slightly less than 0.8) when there are 500 examinees present in each group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0013164411422250">Gierl, Gotzmann, &amp; Boughton, 2004</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0013164411422250">Finch (2005)</xref> found that the greatest influence on power, when using SIBTEST to detect DIF, was the size of the focal group; smaller focal groups yielded lower power than focal groups with larger sample sizes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0013164411422250" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>Given the fact that the focus of this study was on creating effect size guidelines for DBF detection when using SIBTEST, as opposed to studying Type I error rates and power when doing DBF analyses, ideal conditions were simulated. Specifically, as previous research has demonstrated that impact may increase the Type I error rate, no impact was simulated. This ensured that the most ideal conditions were simulated and that the results would not be influenced by the well-known effect of impact on increasing the Type I error rate. No impact was simulated by randomly generating the true ability for both reference- and focal-group examinees from a standard normal distribution.</p>
<p>Similarly, sample size was also not considered in this study because prior research has shown that an increased sample size may increase the power of SIBTEST, whereas a decreased sample size may decrease the power of SIBTEST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0013164411422250">Furlow, Ross, &amp; Gagne, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0013164411422250">Gierl et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0013164411422250">Roussos &amp; Stout, 1996</xref>). Likewise, the ratio of focal-group examinees to reference-group examinees was not considered in this study because prior research has clearly indicated that having an unequal ratio of focal- and reference-group examinees is only an issue when the overall sample size is small, less than 250 in the reference and focal groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0013164411422250">Furlow et al., 2009</xref>). Therefore, this study only included ideal sample size conditions of 500 examinees in both the reference and focal groups. A sample size of 500 in each group is considered more than adequate for controlling the Type I error and power rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0013164411422250">Clauser &amp; Mazor, 1998</xref>).</p>
<p>Factors in this simulation study included the manipulation of (a) the number of items in a bundle (1, 3, or 5) that were simulated to function differentially, (b) test length (20 or 40 items), and (c) the magnitude of uniform DIF against the focal group in each item in a bundle. Of particular interest was the sum of the magnitude of DIF across items when testing for DBF. It was hypothesized that the magnitude of <inline-formula id="inline-formula11-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math17-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> would be larger for a bundle of items, when compared with a single item analysis, if the sum of the magnitude of DIF across items in a bundle was comparable with that of a single item, given the well-known attributes of amplification and cancellation that can occur when using SIBTEST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0013164411422250">Nandakumar, 1993</xref>). For example, it was expected that the results obtained from testing three items for DBF, in which the magnitude of DIF for all three items was 0.2, would be larger than the results obtained when testing one item for DIF, in which the magnitude of DIF for that one item was 0.6. Therefore, all possible combinations, ignoring item order, which resulted in the same sum of the magnitude of DIF were considered. The design of this study, which was replicated for a test that consisted of 20 items as well as one that consisted of 40 items, involved 116 conditions and is depicted in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0013164411422250">Table 1</xref>. Each condition was replicated 200 times.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0013164411422250" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Design of Simulation Study Conducted</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0013164411422250" xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">No. of DIF items</th>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Magnitude of DIF for five items studied</th>
<th align="center">Sum of DIF</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.3</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.5</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.7</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>1.8</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>2.4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>2.8</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>3.0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>1.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>1.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>1.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>1.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>1.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>1.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>1.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>2.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>1.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>2.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>2.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>2.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>2.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>2.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>2.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>2.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>3.0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0013164411422250">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. DIF = Differential item functioning.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Item parameters were randomly generated for each replication to ensure that the results were as generalizable as possible. Specifically, the discrimination parameter (<italic>a</italic>) was randomly generated from a log-normal distribution with a mean of 1.0 and a standard deviation of 0.5, the difficulty parameter (<italic>b</italic>) was randomly generated from a standard normal distribution, and the lower asymptote (<italic>c</italic>) was randomly generated from a beta distribution with a mean of approximately 0.16 and a standard deviation of approximately 0.004. When an item was simulated to function differentially, the item was always simulated to be more difficult for the focal group by adding the magnitude of the DIF to the difficulty parameter used for the reference group (e.g., <italic>b</italic><sub>foc</sub> = <italic>b</italic><sub>ref</sub> + magnitude of DIF).</p>
<p>SIBTEST was used to test for DIF/DBF. To prevent from biasing the results, the matching subtest was always created by using only those items that were not simulated to function differentially. In other words, the matching subtest was always DIF-free (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0013164411422250">Ackerman &amp; Evans, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0013164411422250">Gierl, 2005</xref>). One-tailed tests were conducted in all cases to examine whether the studied items were functioning differentially against the focal group, which is reflective of the direction for which DIF was simulated.</p>
<p>An additional step was included in this study. The additional step consisted of obtaining estimates of ability for the reference and focal groups in an effort to better understand the effect of DIF/DBF on ability estimation. This step was taken to determine how much DIF or DBF an item or bundle of items needed to contain before the ability estimates for the focal examinees became seriously biased. The ability estimates were obtained for the reference and focal group members simultaneously. This ensured that the estimates were on the same scale for each group. <italic>T</italic> tests were conducted to determine if the ability estimates were statistically significantly different because of the presence of DIF/DBF. The <italic>t</italic> tests were conducted on the average ability estimates obtained for the reference and focal groups for each of the various conditions examined. In addition, bias, defined as the average signed difference between true and estimated ability, was used to summarize the impact of DIF/DBF on ability estimation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0013164411422250" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section4-0013164411422250">
<title>One-Item DIF Analyses</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0013164411422250">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the results obtained from the simulations conducted to examine the behavior of <inline-formula id="inline-formula12-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math18-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> when conducing one-item DIF analyses. As the figure illustrates, there is almost a perfectly linear relationship between the magnitude of DIF and the average <inline-formula id="inline-formula13-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math19-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> obtained from SIBTEST. In addition, the results do not appear to depend on test length, as the lines are almost identical, regardless of test length. There are several exceptions to this finding, particularly when the magnitude of DIF exceeds 1.5, in which case the average <inline-formula id="inline-formula14-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math20-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is slightly larger when there are fewer test items. As theoretically expected, when no DIF occurs, the expected value of <inline-formula id="inline-formula15-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math21-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is zero. Interpreting these results with respect to the standard DIF effect size guidelines, in which large DIF is said to occur if <inline-formula id="inline-formula16-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math22-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>≥</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>088</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0013164411422250">Roussos &amp; Stout, 1996</xref>), large DIF would typically be found by SIBTEST if the magnitude of the DIF was 0.5. Moreover, as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0013164411422250">Figure 2</xref> illustrates, the power obtained from SIBTEST, approximately 0.85, is adequate when the magnitude of the DIF is 0.5, which is to be expected given the ideal conditions that were simulated and is consistent with the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0013164411422250">Roussos and Stout (1996)</xref>. Once again, as theoretically expected, when the magnitude of the DIF increases, so does the power. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0013164411422250">Figure 2</xref> also illustrates that the Type I error rate associated with SIBTEST is well within the nominal level of 0.05, as would be expected given the ideal conditions that were simulated.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0013164411422250" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Average <inline-formula id="inline-formula17-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math23-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> when using SIBTEST to test for DIF for all one-item conditions studied</p>
<p><italic>Note</italic>. SIBTEST = simultaneous item bias test; DIF = differential item functioning.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-0013164411422250" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Power when using SIBTEST to test for DIF for all one-item conditions studied</p>
<p><italic>Note</italic>. SIBTEST = simultaneous item bias test; DIF = differential item functioning.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0013164411422250">
<title>Multi-Item DBF Analyses</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0013164411422250">Figure 3</xref> illustrates the average <inline-formula id="inline-formula18-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math24-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> for all conditions studied, broken down by test length and sum of DIF across all items in a bundle. As the figure illustrates, the relationship between the sum of DIF and the average <inline-formula id="inline-formula19-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math25-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is almost perfectly linear, and there is little difference for the two test lengths considered, which is similar to what was observed when only looking at the results for one-item DIF analyses. However, the original hypothesis that the magnitude of the average <inline-formula id="inline-formula20-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math26-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> would be larger for a bundle of items than for a single-item analysis, if the sum of the magnitude of DIF was comparable, is only partially supported. On average, larger <inline-formula id="inline-formula21-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math27-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> are obtained when testing a bundle of items, as opposed to a single item, only as the sum of DIF increases. Specifically, in the current study, the effect of amplification is not observed until the sum of DIF/DBF reaches 2.0 for a test length of 20 and when it reaches 1.6 for a test length of 40.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0013164411422250" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption><p>Average beta-uni statistics obtained for all DIF/DBF sums studied, grouped by two different test lengths studied</p>
<p><italic>Note</italic>. DIF = differential item functioning; DBF, differential bundle functioning.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0013164411422250">
<title>Impact of DIF/DBF on Ability Estimation</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0013164411422250">Figure 4</xref> illustrates ability estimation bias as a function of the sum of DIF, under all conditions studied. As expected, test length has an effect on ability estimation bias, with more bias associated with shorter tests. However, what are more interesting are the different patterns of ability estimation bias obtained for the reference and focal groups. It was expected that as the presence of DIF or DBF increased there would be increased negative ability estimation bias for focal-group examinees. However, what <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0013164411422250">Figure 4</xref> illustrates is that as the sum of DIF increased there was increased negative ability estimation bias for focal-group examinees, as well as increased positive ability estimation bias for reference-group examinees. In other words, whereas the ability of the focal group was expectedly underestimated, the ability of the reference group was surprisingly overestimated. This effect is more pronounced for shorter length tests and for larger bundles of items that are functioning differentially.</p>
<fig id="fig4-0013164411422250" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption><p>Estimation bias obtained when using SIBTEST to test for DIF and DBF across all conditions studied</p>
<p><italic>Note</italic>. SIBTEST = simultaneous item bias test; DIF = differential item functioning; DBF = differential bundle functioning.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>So, does this estimation bias result in statistically significant differences in ability estimation for reference and focal groups? This question seems to get at the heart of establishing DIF or DBF effect size guidelines for SIBTEST because, after all, it is overall performance differences on achievement tests which initiated the development of DIF detection procedures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0013164411422250">Angoff, 1993</xref>) and, despite all our attempts to ensure that tests are fair to all examinees through DIF and DBF analyses, the achievement gap still persists today. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0013164411422250">Figure 5</xref> shows the rejection rates obtained when comparing the average estimated ability for the reference and focal groups under various DIF/DBF conditions studied using simple <italic>t</italic> tests. As the figure illustrates, the relationship between finding statistically significant differences in the average ability estimates for the reference and focal groups is highly dependent on two things: (a) the sum of DIF or DBF present in the items and (b) test length. In other words, it is the proportion of DIF or DBF, defined as the sum of DIF divided by the number of test items, that is indicative of whether mean ability estimates will statistically differ for reference- and focal-group examinees, not simply the presence of DIF or DBF. In addition, as the sum of DIF increases, having more items in a bundle will lead to finding statistically significant differences in average ability estimates for the reference and focal groups more often, as long as the proportion of DBF is high.</p>
<fig id="fig5-0013164411422250" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption><p><italic>T</italic> test rejection rates obtained when comparing the average estimated ability for the reference and focal groups under various DIF/DBF conditions studied</p>
<p><italic>Note</italic>. DIF = differential item functioning; DBF = differential bundle functioning.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>So how can these results be used to establish effect size guidelines for SIBTEST? In the conditions explored in this study, <inline-formula id="inline-formula22-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math28-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> was almost perfectly related to the sum of DIF or DBF (<italic>r</italic> = .97). In practice, although one would know <inline-formula id="inline-formula23-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math29-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, one would not know the sum of DIF or DBF. Therefore, a regression model was fit to predict the sum of DIF/DBF, given <inline-formula id="inline-formula24-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math30-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and the number of items in a bundle, and these results are depicted in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0013164411422250">Table 2</xref>. With a little algebraic manipulation, this model can be used in reverse, after running a SIBTEST analysis, to estimate the sum of DIF. Specifically, since</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula7-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="block" id="math31-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>011</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>155</mml:mn>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>Sum</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>DIF</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>015</mml:mn>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>Number</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>Items</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>in</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>Bundle</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula7-0013164411422250" xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-eq7.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>then</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula8-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="block" id="math32-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>Sum</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>DIF</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>011</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>015</mml:mn>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>Number</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>Items</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>in</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.5em"/>
<mml:mtext>Bundle</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>155</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula8-0013164411422250" xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-eq8.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0013164411422250" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Regression Model Obtained When Regressing Sum of DIF and Number of DIF Items on Beta-Uni Statistic From SIBTEST</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0013164411422250" xlink:href="10.1177_0013164411422250-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Unstandardized coefficients</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Standardized coefficients</th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic></th>
<th align="center">Significance</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>−.011</td>
<td>.005</td>
<td/>
<td>−2.065</td>
<td>.041</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sum of DIF</td>
<td>.155</td>
<td>.003</td>
<td>.902</td>
<td>53.666</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No. of DIF items</td>
<td>.015</td>
<td>.001</td>
<td>.187</td>
<td>11.140</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0013164411422250">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. DIF = differential item functioning; SIBTEST = simultaneous item bias test; <italic>SE</italic> = standard error. Dependent variable: Beta-uni statistic.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Dividing the Sum of DIF by the total number of items on the test will provide an estimate of the proportion of DIF which can be used as an estimate of how much the DIF or DBF will affect ability estimation. However, this estimate needs to be interpreted according to the number of items that are found to be functioning differentially, given that greater ability estimation bias is associated with having more items in a bundle (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0013164411422250">Figure 3</xref>). According to the results obtained from this study, when the proportion of DBF is 0.15 (i.e., 3/20, where 3 = the sum of DIF and 20 = the total number of items on the test, which is the highest proportion of DIF/DBF considered in this study) then statistically significant ability differences will be found between reference- and focal-group examinees about 60% of the time for a five-item bundle and about 40% of the time for a three-item bundle, which is likely cause for concern. Moreover, this trend seems to increase exponentially, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0013164411422250">Figure 5</xref>.</p>
<p>How do these results compare with the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0013164411422250">Roussos and Stout (1996)</xref> effect size guidelines for SIBTEST which state that <inline-formula id="inline-formula25-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math33-0013164411422250">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>≥</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>088</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> is indicative of large DIF? It is clear that using these guidelines will typically correspond to statistically significant DIF findings when using SIBTEST. However, assuming this occurs for a one-item bundle, this value corresponds to a sum of DIF of only about 0.54, that is, 0.088 + 0.011 − 0.014(1)/0.155 = 0.54. Taking this one step further and dividing 0.54 by 0.15, to determine the test length at which this would result in a statistically significant difference in average ability between reference- and focal-group examinees about 60% of the time, indicates that this would be of concern only if a test consisted of a mere 3.6 items.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0013164411422250">
<title>Real-Data Examples</title>
<p>To demonstrate how these results might be applied in a practical situation, the results of two previous studies that used a DBF analytic framework were considered. In the first study, published by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0013164411422250">Walker and Beretvas (2001)</xref>, Poly-SIBTEST was used to determine if open-ended items on a mathematics test that required examinees to explain their answers in writing functioned differentially in favor of examinees who were proficient in writing. In this study, the average <inline-formula id="inline-formula26-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math34-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, over 10 replications, was <inline-formula id="inline-formula27-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math35-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> = 1.18 for fourth-grade students and <inline-formula id="inline-formula28-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math36-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> = 2.31 for seventh-grade students. For both grades, there were 16 items included in the bundle. Therefore, for fourth-grade students the Sum of DIF = (1.1.8 + 0.011 − 0.015(16))/0.155 = 6.14, whereas for seventh-grade students the Sum of DIF = (2.31 + 0.011 − 0.015(16)/0.155 = 13.43. The fourth-grade test consisted of a total of 40 items, whereas the seventh-grade test consisted of a total of 46 items. Therefore, for the fourth-grade test, the proportion of DBF is 6.14/40 = 0.15, whereas for the seventh-grade test, the proportion of DBF is 13.43/46 = 0.29. Interpreting these results in terms of this study, 0.15 was the highest proportion of DBF considered in this study. Moreover, statistically significant differences in ability estimates were more likely to be found between the reference and focal groups when a greater number of items were included in a bundle. In fact, the highest number of items considered in a bundle was only 5 and when the proportion of DBF was 0.15 for a five-item bundle, statistically significant differences were found between reference- and focal-group examinees approximately 60% of the time. Therefore, both these findings should be a cause of concern from an effect size perspective.</p>
<p>In the second study, published by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0013164411422250">Walker et al. (2008)</xref>, SIBTEST was used to determine if mathematics items that required a higher reading load functioned differentially in favor of proficient readers. In this study, the highest <inline-formula id="inline-formula29-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math37-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> (0.695) was found when comparing fifth-grade students who were classified as basic readers with fifth-grade students who were classified as advanced readers. For this analysis, the bundle consisted of 15 items. Therefore, Sum of DIF = (0.695 + 0.011 − 0.015(15)/0.155 = 0.481. The total number of items on the fifth-grade test was 32. Therefore, the proportion of DBF for this analysis is only 0.481/32 = 0.015, which according to the results of the simulation study is likely not a cause for concern.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0013164411422250" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The primary purpose of this study was to determine effect size guidelines when using SIBTEST to conduct DBF analyses. This was accomplished by linking the original impetus for conducting DIF analyses—the fact that many believed that large-scale tests were unfair to minority students—to ability estimation since the achievement gap has lingered despite attempts by psychometricians to ensure that tests are fair to all by conducting DIF/DBF analyses. Obviously, there is not one definitive reason as to why the achievement gap persists, but the results of this study clearly demonstrate that only with very high levels of DIF or DBF, in terms of the proportion of DIF/DBF with respect to the total number of items on the test, can these disparities be caused by a series of items that are functioning differentially against the disadvantaged groups. This finding suggests that scholars must begin to look outside the statistical properties of the test in an effort to develop explanations for the lingering achievement gap. Ability estimation bias can only be attributed to DIF or DBF when a large number of items in a bundle are functioning differentially against focal examinees in a small way or a small number of items are functioning differentially against focal examinees in a large way. In either of these situations, the presence of DIF or DBF should be a cause for concern because it would lead one to erroneously believe that distinct groups differ in ability when in fact they do not. Given that large-scale test items are routinely examined for DIF, it is unlikely that this would occur in practice. It may be that the differential test performance between distinct groups is signaling a much broader and dire problem with the American educational system that extends far beyond the test.</p>
<p>It should be noted that the findings of this study are somewhat contingent on an adequate sample size and equal reference- and focal-group examinees. Future research is needed, in terms of investigating how overall sample size and the ratio of reference- and focal-group examinees affect the magnitude of <inline-formula id="inline-formula30-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math38-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. Previous research indicates that power would decrease, in terms of finding DIF or DBF with smaller sample sizes and unequal ratios. However, it is unclear if smaller sample sizes and unequal ratios would affect the magnitude of <inline-formula id="inline-formula31-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math39-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, which would in turn affect a practitioner’s estimate of the Sum of DIF/DBF, or if these conditions simply affect the standard error associated with <inline-formula id="inline-formula32-0013164411422250">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math40-0013164411422250">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>^</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>.</p>
<p>Finally, it is unclear why the well-known effects of amplification were only partially supported. The results of this study suggest that amplification only occurs with a large magnitude of DIF/DBF. Although this was unexpected, it was not the primary focus of this study. Therefore, future research is needed in this area to determine under what conditions amplification will occur in practice.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors would like to thank the reviewers for their helpful feedback and Mark Gierl for reading an earlier version of this article.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at">
<p>Earlier versions of this article were presented at the Seventh Conference of the International Test Commission, Hong Kong, and the 2011 Annual Conference of the National Council for Measurement in Education, New Orleans, LA.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0013164411422250">
<label>1.</label>
<p>The report was generated using the NAEP Data Explorer found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nces.ed.gov/nationsreportcard/naepdata/">http://nces.ed.gov/nationsreportcard/naepdata/</ext-link></p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>ESL reading strategies: Differences in Arabic and Mandarin speakers test performance</article-title>. <source>Language Learning</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>633</fpage>-<lpage>670</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>A confirmatory approach to differential item functioning on an ESL reading assessment</article-title>. <source>Language Testing</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ackerman</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>The influence of conditioning scores in performing DIF analyses</article-title>. <source>Applied Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>329</fpage>-<lpage>342</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Angoff</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Perspectives on differential item functioning methodology</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wainer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Differential item functioning</source> (pp. <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>August</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carlo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dressler</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The critical role of vocabulary development for English language learners</article-title>. <source>Learning Disabilities Research &amp; Practice</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>50</fpage>-<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The historical reconstruction of knowledge about race: Implications for transformative teaching</article-title>. <source>Educational Researcher</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Multicultural education: Characteristics and goals</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Multicultural education: Issues and perspectives</source> (<edition>6th ed.</edition>, pp. <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>A comprehensive framework for evaluating hypotheses about cultural bias in educational testing</article-title>. <source>Applied Measurement in Education</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>115</fpage>-<lpage>132</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clauser</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mazor</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Using statistical procedures to identify differentially functioning test items</article-title>. <source>Educational Measurement: Issues and Practice</source>, <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cochran-Smith</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Multicultural teacher education: Research, practice and policy</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of research in multicultural education</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>, pp. <fpage>931</fpage>-<lpage>975</lpage>). <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roussos</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Item-bundle DIF hypothesis testing: Identifying suspect bundles and assessing their differential functioning</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Measurement</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>465</fpage>-<lpage>484</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The MIMIC model as a method for detecting DIF: Comparison with Mantel-Haenszel, SIBTEST and the IRT likelihood ratio</article-title>. <source>Applied Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>278</fpage>-<lpage>295</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Differential item functioning analyses for accommodated versus non-accommodated students</article-title>. <source>Educational Assessment</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>38</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Furlow</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gagne</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The impact of multidimensionality on the detection of differential bundle functioning using simultaneous item bias test</article-title>. <source>Applied Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>441</fpage>-<lpage>464</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Curriculum theory and multicultural education</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of research in multicultural education</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>, pp. <fpage>30</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>). <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gierl</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Using dimensionality-based DIF analyses to identify and interpret constructs that elicit group differences</article-title>. <source>Educational Measurement: Issues and Practice</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gierl</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bisanz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bisanz</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boughton</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Identifying content and cognitive skills that produce gender differences in mathematics: A demonstration of the multidimensionality-based DIF analysis paradigm</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Measurement</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>281</fpage>-<lpage>307</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gierl</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bisanz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bisanz</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boughton</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khaliq</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Illustrating the utility of differential bundle functioning analyses to identify and interpret group differences on achievement tests</article-title>. <source>Educational Measurement: Issues and Practice</source>, <volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>26</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gierl</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gotzmann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boughton</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Performance of SIBTEST when the percentage of DIF items is large</article-title>. <source>Applied Measurement in Education</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>-<lpage>264</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gierl</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khaliq</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Identifying sources of differential item and bundle functioning on translated achievement tests: A confirmatory approach</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Measurement</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>164</fpage>-<lpage>187</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>In search of wholeness: African American teachers and their culturally specific classroom practices</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Educating teachers for diversity: Seeing with a cultural eye</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Teachers College Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collison</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Preparing teachers for urban classrooms</article-title>. <source>Black Issues in Higher Education</source>, <volume>16</volume>(<issue>20</issue>), <fpage>30</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lovett</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Stereotype threat and test performance: A primer for school psychologists</article-title>. <source>Journal of School Psychology</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Improved Type I error control and reduced estimation bias for DIF detection using SIBTEST</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational and Behavioral Statistics</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>291</fpage>-<lpage>322</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ladson-Billings</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>The dreamkeepers: Successful teachers of African American children</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ladson-Billings</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Fighting for our lives: Preparing teachers to teach African American students</article-title>. <source>Journal of Teacher Education</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>206</fpage>-<lpage>214</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laufer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>What percentage of text-lexis is essential for comprehension?</article-title> In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lauren</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nordman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Special language: From humans thinking to thinking machines</source> (pp. <fpage>316</fpage>-<lpage>323</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Clevedon, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Multilingual Matters</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Majors</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Heading up the street: Localized opportunities for shared constructions of knowledge</article-title>. <source>Pedagogy, Culture &amp; Society</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nation</surname><given-names>I. S. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Factors affecting guessing vocabulary in context</article-title>. <source>RELC Journal</source>, <volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>33</fpage>-<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Linguistic influences on differential item functioning for second language learners on the National Assessment of Educational Progress</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Testing</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>14</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martiniello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Language and the performance of English language learners on math word problems</article-title>. <source>Harvard Educational Review</source>, <volume>78</volume>, <fpage>333</fpage>-<lpage>368</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martiniello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Linguistic complexity, schematic representations, and differential item functioning for English language learners in math tests</article-title>. <source>Educational Assessment</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>160</fpage>-<lpage>179</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mendes-Barnett</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ercikan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Examining sources of gender DIF in mathematics using a confirmatory multidimensional model approach</article-title>. <source>Applied Measurement in Education</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>-<lpage>304</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nandakumar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Simultaneous DIF amplification and cancellation: Shealy-Stout’s measure test for DIF</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Measurement</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>293</fpage>-<lpage>311</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ockey</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Investigating the validity of math word problems for English language learners with DIF</article-title>. <source>Language Assessment Quarterly</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>149</fpage>-<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roussos</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Simulation studies of the effects of small sample size and studied item parameters on SIBTEST and Mantel-Haenszel Type I error performance</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Measurement</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>215</fpage>-<lpage>230</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The role of social foundations in preparing teachers for culturally relevant practice</article-title>. <source>Multicultural Education</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>10</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>An examination of item context effects, DIF, and gender DIF</article-title>. <source>Applied Measurement in Education</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>73</fpage>-<lpage>90</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Examining gender DIF on a multiple-choice test of mathematics: A confirmatory approach</article-title>. <source>Educational Measurement: Issues and Practice</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Psychological processes underlying stereotype threat and standardized math test performance</article-title>. <source>Educational Psychologist</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sackett</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hardison</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>On interpreting stereotype threat as accounting for African American-White differences on cognitive tests</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shealy</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>A model-based standardization approach that separates true bias/DIF from group ability differences and detects test bias/DTF as well as item bias/DIF</article-title>. <source>Psychometrika</source>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>159</fpage>-<lpage>194</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sleeter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Preparing teachers for culturally diverse schools: Research and the overwhelming presence of whiteness</article-title>. <source>Journal of Teacher Education</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>94</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Snetzler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qualls</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Examination of differential item functioning on a standardized achievement battery with limited English proficient students</article-title>. <source>Educational and Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>564</fpage>-<lpage>577</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>A threat in the air: How stereotypes shape intellectual identity and performance</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>613</fpage>-<lpage>629</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beretvas</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>An empirical investigation demonstrating the multidimensional DIF paradigm: A cognitive explanation for DIF</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Measurement</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>-<lpage>163</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Surber</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Using a multidimensional differential item functioning framework to determine if reading ability affects student performance in mathematics</article-title>. <source>Applied Measurement in Education</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>162</fpage>-<lpage>181</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cline</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Validity and fairness of state standards-based assessments for English language learners</article-title>. <source>Educational Assessment</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>170</fpage>-<lpage>192</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0013164411422250">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zwick</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ercikan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Analysis of differential item functioning in the NAEP history assessment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Measurement</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>