<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ALX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spalx</journal-id>
<journal-title>Adult Learning</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1045-1595</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1045159513477846</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1045159513477846</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Resources</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group><article-title>Book Review: <italic>The Professor’s Guide to Taming Technology, Leveraging Digital Media, Web 2.0, and More for Learning</italic> by K. P. King, and T. D. Cox</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Cunlif</surname><given-names>Ed</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1045159513477846">University of Central Oklahoma, Edmond, OK USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>87</fpage>
<lpage>87</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>2011</year>). <source>The Professor’s Guide to Taming Technology, Leveraging Digital Media, Web 2.0, and More for Learning</source>. <publisher-loc>Charlotte, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Information Age Publishing</publisher-name>. <page-count count="300"/> pp. ISBN <isbn>978-1-61735-333-8</isbn> (paperback).</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">American Association for Adult and Continuing Education</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The idea of taming technology has probably occurred to almost everyone in the field of education. This guide to the process of taming technology is written by faculty members who have managed to find ways to use various technologies to effectively support the learning process. The book is written in a style that is user-friendly and reflective of the faculty perspective. Regardless of the discipline, this guide introduces the reader to current teaching/learning technologies, explains the benefits, and provides relevant examples and references.</p>
<p>King and Cox, with the help of other faculty authors, have compiled 16 thoughtful chapters in a convenient guidebook. This is the type of guide that allows the reader to examine particular areas of interest without necessarily having to read other chapters. Each chapter can be approached as a stand-alone for the reader seeking specific information.</p>
<p>The book is divided into four parts and Part I, “Vision and Foundations,” provides a general perspective on the use of digital media. What doors are opened through digital media for faculty and students? How does using technology connect to the concepts or principles of adult learning? Those fundamental questions are addressed in the opening section along with an introductory table of various media and the learning outcomes that may be facilitated with their usage.</p>
<p>Part II, “Digital Media,” addresses the use of nine specific media, including podcasting, asynchronous audio, video, blogging, digital presentation, wikis, virtual office hours, Skype, and Facebook. Each chapter systematically defines, explains, and exemplifies the technology’s usage in higher education settings. If you have an interest in the use of blogging, for instance, the author (Teresa Carter) provides a clear picture of what it is and how a faculty member has used it. There are examples and resources for further exploration if you decide to experiment in this area. Each of the chapters realistically discusses some of the pros and cons that faculty should consider.</p>
<p>Part III, “Special Topics,” has two chapters speaking to the issues of students with disabilities and how the technologies can be of assistance. Adaptive technologies have implications for some of our veterans returning from actions in the Middle East as well as aging and other populations. The next two chapters provide very specific examples of digital media usages in the classroom. One chapter addresses 3D virtual labs as a cutting edge technology becoming more prevalent in the entertainment arena with tremendous advantages in education. The other chapter speaks of technology in the history classroom, an area that can become much more lively with digital media. In all of this section, the practical faculty usage of the technology is what speaks the loudest—it is not theory, but thoughtful and rational practice offered.</p>
<p>Part IV, “Thinking Ahead,” is best summarized, and is itself a summary and a vision, in the words of the authors themselves: “The driving vision of this books is for all educators to no longer be trapped by tradition or technology, but instead to allow dynamic new practices to emerge; specifically, learner-centered and reflective teaching” (King &amp; Cox, 2011, p. 268). The vision is shared by most in the field of education. How is it that we can use available tools to help students in the learning process? This book provides a significant response.</p>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<title>Author Biography</title>
<p>Ed Cunliff is a professor of adult and higher education at the University of Central Oklahoma. He has more than 35 years experience in innovative organizational development. He has worked in social services, health care, and higher education and has served in a consultative role with dozens of organizations.</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>