<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">APA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spapa</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Am Psychoanal Assoc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0003-0651</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1941-2460</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0003065112456292</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0003065112456292</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Contemporary Culture</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Money Talks: In Therapy, Society, and Life</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Eisold</surname><given-names>Kenneth</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0003065112456292">Kenneth Eisold 353 Central Park West New York, NY 10025 E-mail: <email>ken@keneisold.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>60</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>877</fpage>
<lpage>883</lpage>
<product><article-title>Money Talks: In Therapy, Society, and Life</article-title>. Edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>Brenda</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>Stephanie</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <year>2012</year>, <page-count count="xviii"/> + <page-count count="200"/> pp., <price>$34.95</price> paperback.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Psychoanalytic Association 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Psychoanalytic Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The financial crisis upended our world in 2008. As Brenda Berger, one of the editors of this new collection of papers, puts it: “suddenly, 21 years into my practice, money burst center stage into my office. It seemed to me it was on every patient’s mind, present in every session (or almost every session), and painfully it was very much on my mind.” She adds: “abruptly I was concerned about a diminished retirement account. And my patients were worried about their jobs, their savings, and whether they could afford their treatments with me” (p. 59).</p>
<p>That crisis, still profoundly affecting us all, was the occasion for this book. Money, usually a background issue in our work, forced itself to the forefront. Along with more practical and personal issues about supporting ourselves and preserving our savings, the crisis pushed us into the national debate on what has gone so horribly wrong with our society that allowed this to happen—the unbridled competition, deregulation and dangerous lack of oversight, and the vast upsurge of unequally distributed wealth.</p>
<p>This collection of papers touches on all these questions. It offers reflections by psychoanalysts on how we have changed in the past few decades as a result of the unstable prosperity that preceded the financial crisis. It provides accounts, as well, about how some have adjusted to dramatic changes in their financial status, both gaining and losing extraordinary wealth. It also offers our profession the opportunity to think about how we handle money, a charged topic too often avoided and neglected.</p>
<p>So the book is timely. Nonetheless, I think it might have been more sharply focused on the specific meaning that money and wealth have come to have today. There is a curious warp that runs throughout the papers here. On the one hand, many of them illustrate the impact of the hyperprosperity we have become used to in the past two decades, the backdrop to our recent crisis. On the other hand, many of the authors treat money as an age-old problem, perennially the same. Money may talk, but what it says is not always the same, and I think the more interesting and useful parts of this collection explore what differentiates our issues with money today from those of previous decades.</p>
<p>Let me give an example. The two editors of the book, Brenda Berger and Stephanie Newman, discuss in separate papers patients whose lives have been upended by dramatic changes of fortune. One patient suffered a financial reversal that forced a severe cutback in his standard of living. The effect was sobering but productive, as he was forced to confront certain realities previously kept at bay by his wealth. Another was thrown off kilter by huge financial success, losing his capacity to tolerate frustration as he came to believe that his money allowed him to evade his problems. One profited from failure; the other was profoundly compromised by success. Taken together, these two stories, with their intriguing symmetry, suggest how bewildering such experiences can be for those living through them. Their “successes” and “failures,” detached from social purpose and meaning, have purely personal and sometimes arbitrary consequences. It is as if they have won or lost at gambling.</p>
<p>Most wealth in our society has been built gradually, for the most part, in relation to products and services that have a social purpose. Often the process of accumulation was ruthless and destructive, but wealth was a by-product of creating railroads, factories, homes, domestic goods, cars, steamship lines, electric grids, retail chains, and the like. That is how our society grew. Today we still have comparable developments such as computers, cell phones, software, and search engines. But the great wealth that has driven our recent prosperity stems largely from the financial industry: the hedge funds, the banks, the mortgage products and other investment vehicles that have drawn in vast sums of money from around the world. My guess is that most of the case material discussed in this book involves money made in that industry, centered in New York, where most of the contributors to this volume and their patients live and work. That gives it unique qualities.</p>
<p>Money by its very nature is abstract, of course, the great solvent that allows the large-scale exchange of goods and services. But the financial industry has rendered it even more abstract and distant from tangible goods and services as it “securitizes” paper profits and losses, trades in contracts, calculates and manipulates risk, sells futures, and searches for ever more creative and lucrative ways of using money to make money. People in the industry are often brilliant, but their achievements often have little to do with things that obviously improve our lives.</p>
<p>I am not saying that the financial industry serves no real purpose. But the purposes it does serve have become disproportionate to need, bloated and disengaged from social values.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0003065112456292">1</xref></sup> My point is that much of the wealth described in the case material in this book, stemming from such financial enterprises, makes both the triumphs and the reversals of its players seem empty of meaning. Their sense of entitlement, with its accompanying arrogance, can often be more vicious because the competition they are engaged in is not tempered by a larger purpose. Work can easily seem like a sport or a card game, having no object but winning.</p>
<p>In addition, the industry is deeply shadowed by corruption, insider trading, and fraud, reflecting the enormous stakes and pressures for success it generates. And success is inevitably tainted with embarrassment and guilt, as the country increasingly divides into rich and poor. This development has been underscored by Occupy Wall Street and is now becoming part of our national political discourse. On a more personal level, it has profoundly infiltrated our identities and consciousness. Among themselves, bankers, traders, and others in the industry are often boisterous and arrogant, but they are also increasingly defensive and troubled by the reputation their industry has acquired. They have become reliant on lobbyists and public relations specialists to buffer themselves from public opinion. They still crave the wealth that is within their grasp and work desperately hard to get it, but increasingly it sets them apart from the vast majority of others—and the abstract nature of the money they earn fails to give meaning to their lives.</p>
<p>These problems are not unknown in any capitalist society, but they have become extreme and defining today, magnified by the growth of the financial industry. Often they can be discerned in the case material in the book, beyond the symmetrical cases offered by the editors. Occasionally they are approached more directly by the writers.</p>
<p>Janice Lieberman suggests in her paper that as a result of the upsurge of wealth, we have a “new superego.” That is, our values and ideals have been altered as new expectations and aspirations about wealth have been established. For the newly rich there are now extraordinary levels of entitlement and greed, as well as notable increases in jealousy, arrogance, and envy that are far less ego-dystonic than we have been used to.</p>
<p>This is often a problem not just for wealthy patients but also for their therapists, who must contend with countertransference issues exacerbated by their own diminished level of affluence, the devaluation and contempt of patients who feel superior and expect to get their way, and increasingly divergent values and norms. It encourages therapists to become dismissive of the problems experienced by wealthy patients, expressing the disapproval if not disdain that many of us harbor toward the new wealth around us.</p>
<p>Most of the authors here, however, treat money and wealth as an historical constant. Robert Glick offers a thoughtful essay on how the rich, as F. Scott Fitzgerald once said, are different from the rest of us. Wealth not only creates a wholly different set of expectations, but re-inforces tendencies to indifference and narcissism. He comments perceptively on differences between dynastic wealth, wealth acquired through marriage, and self-made wealth, as well as on the relationship between children and their wealthy parents; he notes how uneasy and suspicious the wealthy often are about the envy they typically expect to find in relationships with others less wealthy.</p>
<p>The reference to Fitzgerald also suggests a link to the last historical era in which finance exerted such an impact on our culture; it subtly suggests, without being explicit, that one of the ways in which the rich are different once again is that their money is different. The Jazz Age saw similar levels of speculation and excess, wealth that corrupted as it dazzled with ostentation.</p>
<p>The scope of the discussion enlarges considerably with the inclusion of Muriel Dimen’s paper, first published eighteen years ago, though it too skates around the historical issue of money’s meaning today. Trained as an anthropologist, she brings a broad theoretical perspective on money, employing Marx’s concept of alienation to remind us that the exchange of goods and services inevitably introduces an element of calculation and exploitation into all relationships. The relationship between therapist and patient is hardly exempt. Indeed, she deftly points out how money, always present, contaminates the subjectivity of relationships based on affection, identification, attraction, and common interests. To put it bluntly, the contradictory relationship between money and love inevitably infects all professional transactions.</p>
<p>Dimen brings a refreshing sophistication to the discussion and reminds us of how many significant thinkers are relevant to the discussion of money in our culture. To be sure, most analysts and other clinicians cannot be expected to be as proficient in economic history and social analysis. Citing one or two popular, nonscholarly books on the subject, as some of these writers do, suggests too great a willingness to settle for accounts that confirm prejudices and reinforce conventional ideas.</p>
<p>The book has a strong secondary theme more directly relevant to our field: the difficulty that analysts and other clinicians have in discussing money directly with patients and one another. In this, the book refers back to and frequently echoes a collection of essays published over twenty-five years ago, <italic>The Last Taboo</italic> (Krueger 1987), the last major attempt to address the topic of money in our field.</p>
<p>Indeed, <italic>Money Talks</italic> begins with a very strong article by Theodore Jacobs, perhaps the best in the collection, on precisely that topic. In it he notes, “It is as though there is something embarrassing about our interest in money. It is not a matter to be talked about.” In his characteristically direct way, Jacobs offers a number of examples that illustrate how little things have changed, how strong the taboo continues to be, and how much it infiltrates training.</p>
<p>Jacobs’s piece is followed by another strong one, by Irwin Hirsch, on the conflict of interest clinicians have in working with patients on termination. “It Was a Great Month: None of My Patients Left” explores with uncompromising honesty the tension we all feel, often unconsciously, between letting patients leave and losing income, a tension that inevitably distorts our judgment about what is best for the patient.</p>
<p>Other papers in the book abundantly illustrate how problematic and disabling the issue of money remains for many clinicians. A number of analysts write openly and with courage about their struggles to speak frankly with patients about unpaid fees, inadequate fees, or their need to raise fees over time.</p>
<p>Many authors cite Krueger’s book, a fact that suggests how little things have changed over the last quarter century. A number of them suggest that the issue goes back even further, quoting Freud’s comments about fees and his statement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0003065112456292">1913</xref>) that members of the medical profession are prone to act as if they were philanthropists, disinterestedly above the marketplace.</p>
<p>One has to wonder why this taboo, so frequently written about, persists as strongly as it does. Despite calls for change, there are few attempts to analyze the reasons for its persistence. The usual explanation is that money forces awareness of a fundamental contradiction between our desire to put the needs of patients first and our own need to be paid. Hirsch touches on this tension, as does Dimen in her comments on the pervasive social contradiction between love and money. Surely that is part of the explanation, as we are all attached, in varying degree, to our idealized professional self-image. Moreover, we are attached also to our own versions of what Freud called his “splendid isolation,” the sense that we are removed from the competition and greed that characterize the marketplace.</p>
<p>But the problem may be just the fact that we are not as removed from the market as we like to believe, not immune to competition with our peers, nor free from the general pressures and constraints of the economy. Many of us wish for successful and abundant lives, with nice places to live, country homes, vacation budgets. We want to send our children to private schools, to eat at good restaurants, wear attractive clothes. And why not? But that puts us squarely in competition with everyone else who wants those things.</p>
<p>So in this money-based society, driven by competition, our fees may be entirely legitimate and reasonable, but we actually are in conflict with other providers of goods and services, as well as with one another. That competition could be substantially mitigated if we had delegated our professional associations to recommend fees or establish guidelines so we could act in concert, as many professions do, but we have systematically resisted ceding that authority. Now it is being done for us by insurance companies, with less than happy results.</p>
<p>But that’s not all. We have attempted to stratify the profession by establishing training analysts, while becoming informally stratified as analysts from backgrounds in social work, psychology, medicine, and now, increasingly, graduate programs in mental health and counseling. These practices encourage competition over fees, in effect, but our competition with one another is largely unacknowledged. The field is rife with rumors about the extravagant fees some charge, but we are generally unwilling to share information about our own practices. At the same time, it is obvious that our ability to charge higher fees is a sign of status and value.</p>
<p>Our taboo, then, is essentially a collusion to keep this competition covert. That not only preserves our idealized identities, above the fray, but also preserves the economic advantages built into the status quo. Now, however, it is has become more urgent that we address these practices and contest that taboo, as increasingly the mental health industry is being regulated by governments, eager to expand access to services while bringing down costs, and by insurance companies, eager for a bigger slice of the pie.</p>
<p>The great virtue of <italic>Money Talks</italic> is that it brings our minds back to these issues. It gets us thinking about the larger world of which we are a part, and it encourages us to reflect on our own practices. Money is not a subject with which most of us are comfortable, or one on which we tend to be well informed. Indeed, we are at times prone to a spurious superiority, as if we lived in a parallel world, slightly elevated above the one inhabited by our patients. The book reflects all too well our own limitations, and it is not surprising that there are gaps and shortcomings in what it has to tell us. But it is a good step in the right direction, and it deserves our attention.</p>
<p>The editors are to be congratulated. We have serious business to conduct, as well as a profession to protect and maintain, and we are better able to address the issues with good ideas and without disabling illusions.</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0003065112456292">
<label>1</label>
<p>A good introduction to these issues can be found in James Galbraith’s <italic>Created Unequal</italic> (2000). A good account of the internal operations of the financial industry, written by an anthropologist, can be found in Gillian Tett’s <italic>Fool’s Gold</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0003065112456292">2009</xref>).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0003065112456292">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1913</year>). <article-title>On beginning the treatment</article-title>. <source>Standard Edition</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0003065112456292">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Galbraith</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Created Unequal: The Crisis in American Pay</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>, <year>2000</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0003065112456292">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ed. (<year>1986</year>). <source>The Last Taboo: Money as Symbol and Reality in Psychotherapy and Psychoanalysis</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brunner/Mazel</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0003065112456292">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tett</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Fool’s Gold: The Inside Story of How Wall Street Greed Corrupted Its Bold Dream and Created a Financial Catastrophe</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Simon &amp; Schuster</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>