<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EME</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">speme</journal-id>
<journal-title>Global Journal of Emerging Market Economies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0974-9101</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">0975-2730</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage India: New Delhi, India</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0974910113494536</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0974910113494536</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Editorial</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sood</surname><given-names>Anil</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>55</fpage>
<lpage>56</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 Emerging Markets Forum</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Emerging Markets Forum, Washington DC</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Dear Readers,</p>
<p>Welcome to the May 2013 issue of the <italic>Global Journal of Emerging Market Economies</italic>.</p>
<p>In the past two issues of the GJEME, we have taken the approach of publishing the best articles available to us on emerging market economies, regardless of theme or subject matter. We take the same approach in this issue, presenting the readers with three articles that address very relevant issues facing emerging market economies today: the resilience of emerging markets to external economic shocks, the effects of fluctuations in terms of trade on overall output growth, and the issues of fragility and conflict as they impact countries in Africa.</p>
<p>This issue’s first article is an update and extension of an index developed in 2010 in an effort to measure countries’ resilience to external economic shocks. This index was inspired by the aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis, particularly by the way in which different emerging market countries responded to the crisis. Some countries were well-positioned financially and had the fiscal room and the central bank credibility to guide themselves through the crisis. Other countries were badly positioned, with credit bubbles, assets of poor quality, and too much exposure abroad; these countries experienced a significant contraction in economic activity.</p>
<p>“The Centennial Resilience Index: Measuring Countries’ Resilience to Shock” by Boorman, Fajgenbaum, Ferhani, Bhaskaran, Arnold, and Kohli outlines a resilience index that attempts to quantify how exposed a country is to external economic crises and how able they are in responding to them. The index is broken down into ten sub-indices, so that one can see the areas in which countries are well-positioned and the areas in which countries need improvement. Boorman et al. find that over the past several years the resilience of emerging market countries has improved relative to that of high-income countries, and that many emerging market countries are now among the most resilient in the global economy.</p>
<p>The second article addresses the effects of terms of trade on economic growth, a very important and relevant issue facing many emerging market countries. Emerging market countries have grown very well relative to the rest of the world over the past 10 years. Yet in the case of commodity exporters, some of this growth can be attributed to an improvement in terms of trade. Commodity prices have increased, leading to more income for commodity exports, fueling growth within those countries. However, moving into the future, what would happen to these countries if commodity prices stabilized or declined?</p>
<p>“Commodity Terms of Trade in Emerging Markets: A Fragile Blessing” by Claudio Loser attempts to estimate the effect that terms of trade have had on growth, and the potential impact of a change in terms of trade moving into the future. Dr Loser finds that a reversal in terms of trade would have a major impact on the income of commodity exporting regions, particularly through expected multiplier effects of a decline in export income. Emerging market countries that rely on commodity exports should be aware of this risk and prepare themselves for managing it.</p>
<p>This issue’s final article, “Africa 2050: Jobs and Prosperity in a Multipolar Global Economy—Moving Out of Fragility and Conflict” by Serge Michailof, discusses the state of fragile African countries in depth. One of the greatest impediments to economic growth in several countries in Africa has been the “fragility trap”. In this trap, a country cannot grow because of ongoing conflict, but also experiences conflict due in part to the fact that it is not growing. Mr Michailof analyzes the sources of fragility in African countries with a view to identifying the conditions for the continent to move decisively out of conflict and fragility.</p>
<p>This article also presents a vision of an Africa in 2050 that has moved out of fragility and conflict. The vision is followed by a three-pillar agenda for realizing it: strengthen or, where necessary, rebuild from scratch fragile and conflict affected states; diversify fragile economies to meet the challenge of creating jobs for a fast growing youth population; and address the specific plight of resource-poor landlocked countries.</p>
<p>I wish our readers happy reading and encourage all to share their views with us on the important issues discussed in these articles.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>
Anil Sood<break/>
Managing Editor, <italic>GJEME</italic>
</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>