<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIF</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppif</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part F: Journal of Rail and Rapid Transit</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0954-4097</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-3017</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0954409712452239</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0954409712452239</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Effect of humidity, temperature and railhead contamination on the performance of friction modifiers: Pin-on-disk study</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>Stephen R</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0954409712452239">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0954409712452239"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>Roger</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0954409712452239">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Olofsson</surname><given-names>Ulf</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0954409712452239">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Eadie</surname><given-names>Don T</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0954409712452239">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0954409712452239">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Xin</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0954409712452239">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0954409712452239"><label>1</label>Department of Mechanical Engineering, The University of Sheffield, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0954409712452239"><label>2</label>Department of Machine Design, Royal Institute of Technolgy, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0954409712452239"><label>3</label>LB Foster Friction Management, Kelsan Technologies Corporation, Vancouver, Canada</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0954409712452239"><p>This paper originated from the 2011 IHHA Conference.</p></fn>
<corresp id="corresp1-0954409712452239">Stephen R Lewis, Department of Mechanical Engineering, The University of Sheffield, Mappin Street, Sheffield, S1 3JD, UK. Email: <email>stephen.lewis@sheffield.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>227</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>115</fpage>
<lpage>127</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Commercially available friction modifiers are used in many different countries that have widely different atmospheric conditions. These variations in atmospheric conditions lead to varying levels of railhead oxidation and debris build-up. Friction modifiers can be applied to the rail without any prior cleaning of the rail and this can lead to varying friction modifier/iron oxide ratios potentially affecting the performance of the friction modifier. This paper reports the results of an investigation that was performed to determine the effects of varying atmospheric and oxide conditions on the performance of friction modifiers. A pin-on-disk test rig with an attached environmental chamber was used for the study. Results show that relative humidity has a pronounced effect on the way in which the friction modifier affects friction levels, and also the amount of time it remains on the disk. This also depends on the concentration of oxide in the friction modifier. Glow discharge optical emission spectroscopy analysis was also carried out to assess the effect of the friction modifier and atmospheric conditions on the chemical composition of the surface of the disk. Results show that the depth of surface modification is vastly different depending on the conditions and level of railhead debris.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Friction modifier</kwd>
<kwd>coefficient of friction</kwd>
<kwd>relative humidity</kwd>
<kwd>temperature</kwd>
<kwd>iron oxide</kwd>
<kwd>pin-on-disc</kwd>
<kwd>wheel– rail contact</kwd>
<kwd>glow discharge optical emission spectroscopy analysis</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0954409712452239" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>The use of friction modifiers, (FMs), within the rail industry is growing as the benefits of using this relatively new technology are discovered by rail operators worldwide. However, the global use of FMs means there is a wide range of conditions in which they must work. For example, a friction modifier in Canada’s low-temperature winter conditions must perform the same job in the high humidity of Italy. The varying temperature and relative humidity (RH) lead to the creation of various iron oxides. It is thus important to understand the effect of varying levels of railhead contamination on the performance of friction modifiers. The particular friction modifier in question, KELTRACK®, is used in Canada, USA, Australia, Brazil and much of Europe. It is a water-based product which is designed to interact with the ‘third body’ on the rail surface.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954409712452239">1</xref></sup> Third body is a term that refers to the interfacial layer between the wheel and rail, excluding the bulk materials (wheel/rail steels) themselves. This layer mainly consists of oxidised wear debris in the form of Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (red oxide). Under certain circumstances Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> (black oxide) can also be produced, but in smaller quantities. Once applied to the track, this particular FM dries as a thin film and can control friction in the wheel–rail interface to be within the range 0.3–0.35, sufficient to reduce wear levels, but not impede braking.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954409712452239">1</xref></sup> A controlled friction level<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954409712452239">1</xref></sup> is not the only benefit of using FMs, also reduced noise levels,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0954409712452239">2</xref></sup> corrugations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954409712452239">3</xref></sup> and lateral forces<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0954409712452239">4</xref></sup> can be achieved.</p>
<p>The aim of the work described in this paper was to test the performance of this FM under various environmental conditions. Testing was performed using a pin-on-disk (POD) device to which an atmospheric chamber was attached. This allowed the testing of the FM at varying RH levels and temperatures. Part of the focus of this work was the study of the FM performance at typical underground tunnel conditions (typically 70% RH and 10 °C). Glow discharge optical emission spectroscopy (GDOES) analysis was also used to investigate any chemical changes in the surface of the disks post test.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0954409712452239"><title>Experimental set-up</title>
<sec id="sec3-0954409712452239"><title>POD rig</title>
<p>In this study FMs were tested under various environmental conditions and with varying levels of iron oxide concentration to simulate railhead rust. A POD rig with an attached environmental chamber, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954409712452239">Figure 1</xref>, was used to carry out the study. Use of the rig has been described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954409712452239">5</xref></sup>
<fig id="fig1-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>POD rig with environmental chamber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The rig simulates a sliding contact by loading a static pin against a rotating disk. The disc has a diameter of 90 mm and the pin end is curved with a radius of 5 mm, giving a point contact. The load is applied as a dead weight. An airtight surround encloses the rig and RH is increased from ambient by using steam from a water boiler. The steam is fed through a closed-loop network of ducting into the enclosed rig. The whole set-up is contained within a temperature-controlled room with external control interface.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0954409712452239"><title>Test parameters</title>
<p>The contact pressure used was 900 MPa with a sliding speed of 0.01 m/s. The FM was mixed with iron oxide by mass according to the concentrations shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0954409712452239">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0954409712452239">2</xref> and then painted onto the pin as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954409712452239">Figure 2</xref>. Although this method offered little control of the amount of FM in the contact, the obtained results were repeatable. The sliding speed was chosen to minimise the centripetal force that the FM/oxide mix would be subjected to and corresponds to the micro-slip condition within the actual simulated railhead–wheel tread contact.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954409712452239">6</xref></sup>
<fig id="fig2-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>FM mixed with red oxide initially painted on the pin which is then transferred to the disc.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Test parameters for series 1.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0954409712452239" xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Test number.</th>
<th>Temperature (°C)</th>
<th>RH (%)</th>
<th>Iron oxide</th>
<th>Mass concentration (%)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>Black</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>Black</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>Black</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.8</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>Black</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.10</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>Black</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.11</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.12</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>Black</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Test parameters for series 2.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0954409712452239" xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Test number</th>
<th>Temperature (°C)</th>
<th>RH (%)</th>
<th>Iron oxide</th>
<th>Mass concentration (%)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>2.1</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2.3</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2.4</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2.7</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2.8</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>Red</td>
<td>45</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0954409712452239"><title>Testing sequence</title>
<p>The test series were designed to ensure the maximum amount of variables could be tested in the least number of tests. This also ensured that each test could be repeated at least once. The tests were broken down into three series. Series 1 used a fixed temperature of 10 °C and an oxide concentration of 35%, while RH and type of iron oxide were varied, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0954409712452239">Table 1</xref>. Series 2, shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0954409712452239">Table 2</xref>, used a fixed RH of 40% while temperature and oxide concentration were varied. For these tests the type of oxide was kept constant and needed to be closely representative of what is seen in the field. Suzumura et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954409712452239">7</xref></sup> used a portable X-ray diffraction analysis technique to detect oxides on a section of rail which had been left to rust alongside the line in a mountain tunnel. Their measurements concluded that the majority of the oxides on the rail head were FeOOH (iron oxyhydroxide – red rust) with magnetite, Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, only appearing at the gauge corner of the rail. Zhu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0954409712452239">8</xref></sup> used X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy on rail sections from an active Stockholm railway line which showed that the majority of the iron oxide was present as Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> with small amounts of FeO also being observed. It was therefore decided to test only with red oxide, Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, in series 2. Tests 1.3 and 1.4 were run at typical tunnel conditions (10 °C and 70% RH).</p>
<p>The third series of tests was designed to explore transitions from the results seen in series 1 and 2. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0954409712452239">Tables 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0954409712452239">4</xref> show the test conditions for these transition investigations.
<table-wrap id="table3-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Test matrix to explore humidity transitions seen in initial tests.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0954409712452239" xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Test</th>
<th>Condition</th>
<th>Mass concentration (%)</th>
<th>Temperature (°C)</th>
<th>RH (%)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>55</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>55</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>65</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table4-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Tests to explore the oxide transition seen in the initial tests.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0954409712452239" xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-table4.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Test</th>
<th>Condition</th>
<th>Mass concentration (%)</th>
<th>Temperature (°C)</th>
<th>RH (%)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>Red oxide/FM</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Lu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954409712452239">1</xref></sup> compared FM application rates with levels of railhead oxidation. It was estimated that oxide would make up 90% of the FM/oxide mixture. Mixtures of this concentration were tried in the laboratory, but produced a very viscous ‘clay like’ compound which was not suitable for testing. However, the conditions at the real wheel/rail contact, i.e. rolling/sliding, may be able to successfully mix such high concentrations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0954409712452239"><title>Testing procedure</title>
<p>Before each test a fresh mixture of FM and iron oxide was prepared to prevent the mixture from drying out before the start of the test. Oxide and FM were both weighed in specific amounts according to the concentration in the mandate. This ensured that the mass of the mixture applied to the pin was of the best achievable consistency. The FM/oxide mix was applied directly to the pin. This was done to ensure the FM was in the simulated micro-slip region of the wheel/rail contact.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954409712452239">Figure 2</xref> shows how the mixture builds up around the edges of the wear track after contacting the disk. Tests were run for 30 min each to allow the FM mixture to dry and begin wear-out of the contact. It was hoped that this would be sufficient to see a transition in the friction curve. As well as recording the friction coefficient, surface chemical compositions were measured on discs which had been prepared separately to the main friction tests. This was done using GDOES analysis, which detects the composition of the disk surface layer by layer. The samples for the GDOES analysis had to be prepared separately from the friction tests. The FM and iron oxide was mixed as normal and applied to the pin. These tests, however, were much shorter than the friction tests only requiring the pin to be in contact with the disk for four complete revolutions. All the samples were prepared at 10 °C and the RH was varied between 40 and 70%. The FM was tested pure and also mixed with red and black oxide at a concentration of 35%.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0954409712452239" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title>
<p>Friction data from each test was gathered and is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954409712452239">Figures 3</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954409712452239">7</xref>. The test numbers refer to those in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0954409712452239">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0954409712452239">2</xref>.
<fig id="fig3-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Friction plots for tests 1.1, 1.3 and 1.5 with red oxide at a concentration of 35%, at 10 °C and varying RH.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig7-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Friction plots for tests 2.1, 2.3, 2.5, 2.7, 1.5 and 1.11 at a RH of 40% and temperature of 10 °C and varying oxide concentration.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig7.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<sec id="sec8-0954409712452239"><title>Test series 1</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954409712452239">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954409712452239">4</xref> show results from series 1 comparing red and black oxides. In both figures it can be seen that friction rises at low RH values but remains low for the higher RH levels. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954409712452239">Figure 4</xref> also shows that friction is generally higher for black oxide and the 40% RH rising at the fastest rate.
<fig id="fig4-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Friction plots for tests 1.2, 1.4 and 1.6 with black oxide at a concentration of 35% at 10 °C and varying RH.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig4.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0954409712452239"><title>Test series 2</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954409712452239">Figures 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954409712452239">6</xref> show results for series 2. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954409712452239">Figure 5</xref> shows the results of tests at 40% RH and 25% concentration with varying temperature. Note how friction rises for the lower temperature. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954409712452239">Figure 6</xref> shows tests performed at 40% RH and 45% concentration with varying temperature. Note how temperature does not seem to have much effect on the friction levels at the highest concentration tested.
<fig id="fig5-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Friction plots for tests 2.1, 2.2, 2.5 and 2.6 with red oxide at a concentration of 25% and RH of 40% and varying temperature.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig6-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Friction plots for tests 2.3, 2.4, 2.7 and 2.8 with red oxide at a concentration of 45% and RH of 40% and varying temperature.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig6.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954409712452239">Figure 7</xref> incorporates data from both series 1 and 2 with red oxide at 10 °C. This chart shows results for the three different concentrations used (25, 35 and 45%). Looking at this chart it can be seen how the rate of friction increase is inversely proportional to the concentration of oxide in the mixture. At a concentration of 45% there is no increase in friction levels for the duration of the test</p>
<p>It should also be noted here that the viscosity of the FM–oxide mixture could affect the friction and retentivity (defined as how long the FM can be effectively provide friction control) results of these samples. The samples with a lower oxide concentration are less viscous and more easily pushed away from the pin/disc contact zone. This could result in a lower retentivity of the tested film. In contrast, those with higher solid content could hold themselves within the contact zone and modify the pin/disc surface, providing a greater retentivity and helping to maintain a relatively low friction level for a longer time.</p>
<sec id="sec10-0954409712452239"><title>Exploration of temperature and RH transitions</title>
<sec id="sec11-0954409712452239"><title>Investigation of RH transition</title>
<p>A series of tests was also designed to explore the RH transition seen in series 1. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0954409712452239">Table 3</xref> shows these tests. The transition was seen to be somewhere between 40 and 70% RH. To explore this, three RH levels, which were evenly spaced in this range namely 45, 55 and 65%, were used. This was aimed at making a more accurate identification of the transition to a smaller range of RH levels.</p>
<p>Friction results are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954409712452239">Figure 8</xref> and it can be seen that friction stays low at all three RH levels. In conjunction with results from series 1 the transition point can now be said to lie within the more accurate range 40–45% RH. (i.e. in series 1 friction increased at 40% RH, but will stay low at RH levels above 45%).
<fig id="fig8-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Friction plots for test H1, H2 and H3 with red oxide at a concentration of 35%, 10 °C and varying humidity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig8.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0954409712452239"><title>Investigation of oxide transition</title>
<p>The data obtained in series 1 and series 2 were combined and revealed an oxide-dependent transition. A series of tests were designed to explore this further and more accurately locate the transition point. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0954409712452239">Table 4</xref> shows a matrix of the tests.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954409712452239">Figures 9</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954409712452239">10</xref> show the friction plots of the oxide investigation at 10 and 20 °C, respectively. The results from series 1 and series 2 show a transition in FM performance for oxide concentration levels between 35 and 45% at 10 °C with the friction level staying low at 45%. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954409712452239">Figure 9</xref> shows that the friction is also low at 40 and 43% concentrations, but begins to increase at 37%. The oxide transition at 10 °C can now be more accurately identified as occurring between 37 and 40% of red iron oxide concentration. However, no transition was observed at 20 °C during the initial tests, even though there was a large range of concentration levels (between 25 and 45%). It was decided to explore further within this range. The results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954409712452239">Figure 10</xref> reveal that the friction has a low value of approximately 0.25 over the entire range of concentrations tested at 20 °C. The test results obtained at 10 °C show that the friction level starts to rise at lower concentrations of iron oxide and thus it can be proposed that at 20 °C the friction level may start to rise at a concentration below 25%. However, further tests would be required to show this effect; if the conjecture were to hold true then it could be stated that the effect of increasing temperature would be to decrease the concentration at which the oxide transition occurs.
<fig id="fig9-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Friction plots for test O1, O2 and O3 with red oxide at a humidity of 40%, 10 °C and varying iron oxide concentration.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig9.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig10-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Friction plots for test O4, O5 and O6 with red oxide at a humidity of 40%, 20 °C and varying iron oxide concentration.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig10.tif"/>
</fig>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-0954409712452239"><title>GDOES results</title>
<p>Six samples were prepared for the GODES analysis by running the previously discussed short tests. These were run with pure, 100%, FM, FM with red oxide and FM with black oxide. Two samples of each were prepared, at both 40 and 70% RH and a temperature of 10 °C. Only disks of these samples could be analysed since GDOES works on flat surfaces with a focal patch of 4 mm diameter. To allow the analysis to obtain a greater image of the FM-affected disk, 10 individual tests were run over a 4 mm section each completing four full revolutions as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0954409712452239">Figure 11</xref>.
<fig id="fig11-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>Illustration of preparation of GDOES sample.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig11.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>When carrying out a GDOES analysis the sample is placed in an inert atmosphere, usually argon. A voltage is then applied between the anode and the disk surface (cathode). The argon becomes ionissed and in the process causes sputtering of the disc surface. This excites the atoms at the disk surface causing them to emit energy in the form of a photon.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0954409712452239">9</xref></sup> The wavelength and frequency of this emitted light can then be analysed using a spectrometer which allows the type and amount of an element at the surface to be identified. This test methodology has been previously used to evaluate environmentally adapted lubricants,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0954409712452239">10</xref></sup> biological layers on a rail<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0954409712452239">6</xref></sup> and roller bearing lubricants.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0954409712452239">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>The results of the GDOES analysis are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954409712452239">Figures 12</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig17-0954409712452239">17</xref>. The loci for manganese, carbon, silicon and chromium have been removed from the charts to aid clarity. These chemicals are constituents of the base steel and did not show any variation with the various test conditions.
<fig id="fig12-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 12.</label><caption><p>GDOES results for pure-FM test performed at 40% RH and 10 °C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig12.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig13-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 13.</label><caption><p>GDOES results for pure-FM test performed at 70% RH and 10 °C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig13.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig14-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 14.</label><caption><p>GDOES results for red oxide/FM test performed at 40% RH and 10 °C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig14.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig15-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 15.</label><caption><p>GDOES results for red oxide/FM test performed at 70% RH and 10 °C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig15.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig16-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 16.</label><caption><p>GDOES results for black oxide/FM test performed at 40% RH and 10 °C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig16.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig17-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 17.</label><caption><p>GDOES results for blackoxide/FM test performed at 70% RH and 10 °C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig17.tif"/></fig>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-0954409712452239" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>A large amount of data was generated in these tests and their analysis is discussed in the following sections. It should be noted that generally the friction coefficients seen in these POD tests are lower than those seen in the field.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0954409712452239">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0954409712452239">13</xref></sup> This has been seen in previous POD tests <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954409712452239">1</xref></sup> and was attributed to the lower speeds, pure sliding and lower roughness of surfaces used in the POD tests.</p>
<sec id="sec15-0954409712452239"><title>Friction data</title>
<p>The first series of tests were all carried out at 10 °C and with a 35% mass concentration of iron oxide mixed with the FM. The first thing that is noticeable from the series 1 charts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954409712452239">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954409712452239">4</xref>) is how RH has an obvious effect on the friction levels. At higher RH levels (70–90%) the friction level remains low over the entire test with a value of between 0.2 and 0.25 for red oxide and between 0.25 and 0.3 for black oxide. This compares with a value of 0.24 for the pure-FM which was obtained from the tests run for the GDOES analysis. Only at lower RH levels did friction start to rise at a sliding distance of 4 m in both cases. It was observed during testing that the FM dried out during the tests at 40% RH but remained wet at 70 and 90% RH. It is suggested that since the FM was still wet, it could seep back into the contact between the pin and disk hence keeping friction at a low level. Conversely, as the film dried no seepage could occur as the film was worn from the wear track leading eventually to metal-on-metal contact. This can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954409712452239">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954409712452239">4</xref> where high friction levels are obtained. This phenomenon can be explained with the aid of the chart in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig18-0954409712452239">Figure 18</xref>, plotted using data from a psychrometric chart. This shows how the humidity ratio changes with RH at 10 and 20 °C (RH is the mass (in grams) of water vapour in the air relative to 1 g of dry air). The chart clearly displays a doubling in the capacity of air to carry water vapour with an increase in its temperature from 10 to 20 °C. The water content of the FM is fixed and therefore the water content of the surrounding air will vary with temperature and humidity. This explains why a rise occurs in the friction levels in series 1 and series 2 (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954409712452239">Figure 5</xref>). At the lower temperature water can evaporate from the FM because the air around it contains a relatively small amount of water. Conversely, at the higher temperature; the effective doubling of the air’s water content means there is a slower evaporation rate (if any) and less water will evaporate from the FM mix.
<fig id="fig18-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 18.</label><caption><p>Change of humidity ratio with RH.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig18.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig19-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 19.</label><caption><p>Comparison of pure-FM friction (from tests run for GDOES analysis) with red and black oxide/FM data from friction tests under varying humidity and 10 °C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig19.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>This holds true if there is a concentration of iron oxide in the mixture of 35% or less. Results from the second test series (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954409712452239">Figure 6</xref>) indicate that at a concentration of 45%, the friction level stays low, regardless of changes in temperature. This suggests that iron oxide has the ability to retain water within the FM, slowing the evaporation/drying rate. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954409712452239">Figure 7</xref> shows how the rate of increase in friction drops off with an increase in oxide concentration. At a concentration of 45% there is no rise in friction over the duration of the test. This may indicate a turning point where any further increase in iron oxide concentration inhibits the effects of environmental factors on the drying time of the FM.</p>
<p>However, this does not mean that the longer the FM remains effective in these tests the better it will perform in the field. On a rail the FM is only a liquid in the first phase during which it is spread down the track by a train. Only once the FM has dried to form a thin film on the railhead will it become effective in controlling friction in the desired range i.e. between 0.3 and 0.35.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954409712452239">1</xref></sup> Thus, results where the friction stays low for the entire duration of the test may not be beneficial, but rather detrimental, to the performance of the FM. For example a high RH or oxide concentration will delay the drying of the film on the railhead meaning that it may be too thinly spread over too large an area. In any case it will take longer for the FM to become effective at these conditions.</p>
<p>The results also show that friction levels with black oxide in the mix are generally 0.05 to 0.1 friction coefficient points higher than those for red oxide at the corresponding RH level. The 40% line for the black oxide test also rises much faster than for the red oxide with the black oxide finishing up at a friction coefficient of 0.7, 0.1 point higher than for red oxide.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig19-0954409712452239">Figure 19</xref> shows a comparison between the friction results from series 1 and 2 and friction data obtained for pure-FM during the GDOES analysis tests. The first point to note is that the friction level is lower for higher RH values. This shows that friction is inversely proportional to RH, a phenomenon also shown by Olofsson and Sundvall.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954409712452239">5</xref></sup> Since all the tests for the GDOES analysis were relatively short in duration, friction data from the friction tests was averaged over a 30 s period at the start of the test to allow valid comparisons to be made. What is also noticeable from this chart is how friction is increased by the addition of oxide. At 40% RH a difference is noticeable. At 70% RH the differences are smaller and may actually be statistically insignificant.</p>
<p>As mentioned previously, part of this investigation was to look at the effects of tunnel conditions such as those for underground rail networks: typically 10 °C and 70% RH. These conditions were replicated in series 1 tests 1.3, 1.4, 1.9 and 1.10. The friction levels for these tests (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954409712452239">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954409712452239">4</xref>) were averaged to be 0.21 for red oxide and 0.28 for black oxide. These values are somewhat below the specified operating range of between 0.3 and 0.35,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954409712452239">1</xref></sup> but as mentioned earlier the friction values obtain from the POD tests are lower than those seen in the field.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec16-0954409712452239"><title>GDOES analysis</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0954409712452239">Figures 12</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig17-0954409712452239">17</xref> show all the data produced in the GDOES tests. The first aspect to be analysed was the depth of surface modification. The bulk material in this case was iron along with small concentrations of manganese, chromium and carbon. Six samples were analysed and the concentration of iron (bulk material) levelled out at approximately 97% in each of them. Therefore, the depth at which the concentration of iron became 97% of the elements detected was noted and is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig20-0954409712452239">Figure 20</xref>.
<fig id="fig20-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 20.</label><caption><p>Depth from surface at which iron content of disk reaches 97% by mass for 40 and 70% RH.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig20.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>At lower RH levels, pure-FM and FM mixed with black oxide give almost identical depths of surface modification with a value of just below 3 µm. At the same RH, however, FM mixed with red oxide gives a much shallower modification depth at just over 0.6 µm below the surface. This pattern is reversed for samples prepared at higher RH values with red oxide/FM now showing the greatest depth of modification at 4.9 µm and black oxide/FM showing the shallowest depth of surface modification at a value of 0.3 µm.</p>
<p>When the RH level increased, the thickness of the oxide layer on the disk’s surface also increased. This can be seen in the charts for pure-FM and red oxide/FM. It can be clearly observed in these charts that the concentration of oxygen falls off at a depth of 12 µm for pure-FM, and 3 µm for red oxide/FM for the samples prepared at 40% RH. However, the corresponding charts show how the concentration of oxygen levels out and reaches much deeper into disc at higher RH levels. The same observation has been made by Olofsson and Dizdar<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0954409712452239">11</xref></sup> for pure rail samples, i.e. increasing the RH level significantly increases the oxide thickness. However, this is reversed when there is black oxide mixed into the FM. Hydrogen also follows a similar pattern to oxygen, showing very shallow depths at low RH levels and being detected to much greater depths at higher RH values. This was the case for all six samples. The majority of the observed hydrogen and oxygen is a result of the water content of the FM. Oxygen is also present in the form of iron oxide and from the natural oxide layer which will have formed on the disk.</p>
<p>It is thus clear that these different conditions affect the depth of surface modification of the disk. Since the considered FM works by modifying the rail surface, the observed effective conditioning of the rail needs further investigation to see how it affects the friction properties of the rail when FMs are not in use. In other words, how does a rail that has been conditioned in this way behave differently when there is contamination (e.g. water, leaves, oil etc.) compared with a rail which has not been treated with a FM. Taking the case of red oxide/FM as being closest to what might be seen in the field it can be seen that the depth of surface modification is more than a factor of five higher at 70% RH than at lower RH values. Thus, it may be concluded that a rail in a tunnel treated with similar liquid FMs has a considerably different surface compared with a rail that is in the open air. Again investigations are needed to see how these different surface conditions may behave under various types of contamination.</p>
<sec id="sec17-0954409712452239"><title>Transition investigation</title>
<sec id="sec18-0954409712452239"><title>RH transition tests</title>
<p>The results of the RH transition tests are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954409712452239">Figure 8</xref>. These tests were carried out to explore the transition from low friction levels at 70% RH and high friction levels at 40% RH as identified in the initial tests and shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954409712452239">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954409712452239">4</xref>. This range dictated the RH used in these transition tests namely 45, 55 and 65% RH. These tests were performed to allow a more precise identification of the point of transition from high to low friction levels. As can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954409712452239">Figure 8</xref> the friction stayed in the low range (0.2–0.3) at all three humidity levels. It can be concluded from these results that the transition lies somewhere between 40 and 45% RH.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec19-0954409712452239"><title>Oxide transition</title>
<p>These tests were designed to explore the transition seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954409712452239">Figure 7</xref>. The chart clearly shows a trend of rising friction level with lower iron oxide/FM ratios. At a ratio of 45% the friction level remains in the low range for the duration of the test. However, at the 35% concentration the friction starts to rise during the test. Concentrations of 37, 40 and 43% at two temperatures of 10 and 20 °C were chosen to explore this transition. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954409712452239">Figure 9</xref> shows results at 10 °C and it can be seen that at a concentration of 37% the friction level increases during the test, however, at a slower rate than that seen in the initial tests. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954409712452239">Figure 7</xref> shows that the rate of increase in the friction level seems to be inversely proportional to the concentration. This confirms that a transition exists between 37 and 40% concentration at 10 °C. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0954409712452239">Figure 10</xref> shows the tests at 20 °C where friction remains low regardless of concentration. This was also seen in the initial tests for the same temperature, but at concentrations of 25 and 45%, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig21-0954409712452239">Figure 21</xref>. These results shows that temperature seems to have a stronger influence on the FM than concentration.
<fig id="fig21-0954409712452239" position="float"><label>Figure 21.</label><caption><p>Initial series 2 friction plots for tests 2, 4, 6 and 8 at 20 °C and 40% RH and varying oxide concentration.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954409712452239-fig21.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec20-0954409712452239" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>An investigation has been made into the effects of atmospheric conditions and iron oxide content on the performance of railhead FMs. This was done using a POD device with an attached atmospheric chamber. One of the objectives of this investigation was to focus on how the behaviour of the FM was affected when used in tunnels where high RH levels and low temperatures prevail. GDOES analysis was used to detect surface modifications of the test specimens as a result of the FM.</p>
<p>In the first series friction tests, at RH levels above 70% the friction level stayed artificially low for the duration of the test (18 m sliding distance). However, at 40% RH the friction started to rise back to dry levels with a 4 m sliding distance. This is a result of the higher amount of water in the air at higher RH values relative to the amount of water in the FM. This retards the evaporation rate of water from the FM meaning that a film can be formed between the pin and the disk for longer periods.</p>
<p>When Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> (black oxide) is mixed with the FM at 40% RH this leads to higher final friction levels and causes the friction to rise at a greater rate than with Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (red oxide). This may be due to the size of the Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> particles being larger than the Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> particles<sub>.</sub> When either type of oxide is mixed with the FM; this raises the friction over that observed for pure-FM.</p>
<p>The concentrations of iron oxide used in the tests were 25, 35 and 45%. Series 2 tests explored the effects of oxide content in the FM on its performance. It was shown that temperature has a decreasing effect on the friction level with increasing oxide content, i.e. when there was 25% oxide content in the FM the friction level rose to that observed for dry conditions at 10 °C, but remained low at 20 °C. However, at a 45% oxide content in the FM the friction remained low at both temperatures.</p>
<p>Further exploration of the transitions seen in series 1 and series 2 testing has allowed a more accurate isolation of the transition points. The RH transition originally witnessed in series 1 can now be said to lie in the region between 40 and 45% RH. Thus, at conditions of 10 °C and 35% oxide concentration, the FM film will dry, and hence the friction level will rise whereas, at RH levels below 40% and will remain wetted, friction remain steady, at RH levels above 45%.</p>
<p>The oxide transition seen in series 2 was also explored further and can now be narrowed down to a range between 37 and 40% red iron oxide concentration at 10 °C and 40% RH. Thus, the FM film will start to dry at concentrations below 37% and remain wet at concentrations above 40%. However, no such transition was seen at 20 °C.</p>
<p>The GDOES results (all performed at 10 °C) showed the level at which surface composition was modified i.e. the depth at which the bulk material readings returned to normal. Since Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (red oxide) is the major constituent of rust this case was closely investigated. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig20-0954409712452239">Figure 20</xref> indicates that the depth of surface modification is much greater at 70% RH (tunnel conditions) than at 40% RH (typical outdoor humidity). This indicates that the level of railhead conditioning in tunnels where FM is used is much more severe than situations where it is used in an open air site. It is clear that the effects of this surface modification on friction need further investigation.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec21-0954409712452239"><title>Funding</title>
<p>The authors would like to thank the University of Sheffield, UK, the Royal Institute of Technology, Sweden and the Royal Academy of Engineering, UK, for their financial support during the undertaking of this research.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0954409712452239"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eadie</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Laboratory study of the tribological properties of friction modifer thin films for friction control at the wheel/rail interface</article-title>. <source>Wear</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>259</volume>: <fpage>1262</fpage>–<lpage>1269</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0954409712452239"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eadie</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Local control of noise and vibration with KELTRACK™ friction modifier and Protector® trackside application: an integrated solution</article-title>. <source>J Sound Vib</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>267</volume>: <fpage>761</fpage>–<lpage>772</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0954409712452239"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eadie</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalousek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiddick</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of high positive friction (HPF) modifier in the control of short pitch corrugations and related phenomena</article-title>. <source>Wear</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>253</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0954409712452239"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Komine</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development of on-board friction control</article-title>. <source>Wear</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>258</volume>: <fpage>1109</fpage>–<lpage>1114</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0954409712452239"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olofsson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundvall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Inﬂuence of leaf, humidity and applied lubrication on friction in the wheel–rail contact: pin-on-disc experiments</article-title>. <source>Proc IMechE, Part F: J Rail Rapid Transit</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>218</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0954409712452239"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olofsson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A multi-layer model of low adhesion between railway wheel and rail</article-title>. <source>Proc IMechE, Part F: J. Rail Rapid Transit</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>221</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0954409712452239"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzumura</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishizak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>In situ X-ray analytical study on the alteration process of iron oxide layers at the railhead surface while under railway traffic</article-title>. <source>Wear</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>271</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0954409712452239"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Olofsson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A field test study of leaf contamination on railhead surfaces</article-title>. <conf-name>The first conference on railway technology: research, development and maintenance</conf-name>. <conf-loc>(ed J Pombo), Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, Spain, 16–20 April 2012. Stirlingshire, UK: Civil-Comp Press</conf-loc>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0954409712452239"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Application of glow discharge optical emission spectroscopy (GDOES) to the analysis of PVD- and CVD-layers</article-title>. <source>Fresenius' J Anal Chem</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>346</volume>(<issue>1–3</issue>): <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0954409712452239"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergseth</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Torbacke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Olofsson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Wear in environmentally adapted lubricants with AW/EP technology</article-title>. <source>J Synth Lub</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>158</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0954409712452239"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olofsson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Dizdar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Surface analysis of boundary lubricated spherical roller thrust bearings</article-title>. <source>Wear</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>215</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0954409712452239"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>McCanneya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recent developments in coefficient of friction measurements at the rail/wheel interface</article-title>. <source>Wear</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>253</volume>: <fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0954409712452239"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallardo-Hernandez</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Twin disc assessment of wheel/rail adhesion</article-title>. <source>Wear</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>265</volume>(<issue>9-10</issue>): <fpage>1309</fpage>–<lpage>1316</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>