<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HPY</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphpy</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hist Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title>History of Psychiatry</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0957-154X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1740-2360</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0957154X12469080</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0957154X12469080</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Classic Text No. 93</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>‘On the Diseases of the Head’ in the <italic>Scale of Medicine</italic> by Muhammad Akbar Arzānī [d. 1722]</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>Neil Krishan</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0957154X12469080">Columbia University, NY, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0957154X12469080">Neil Krishan Aggarwal, Columbia University, Creedmoor Psychiatric Center, Outpatient Division, 1051 Riverside Drive, Unit 11, New York, NY 10032, USA. Email: <email>aggarwa@nyspi.columbia.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>106</fpage>
<lpage>117</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This Classic Text examines the <italic>Mīzān-e Tibb</italic> (<italic>Scale of Medicine</italic>), an influential medical text by Muhammad Akbar Arzānī which circulated widely throughout South Asia. The success of Arzānī’s text rests in its simple prose and the translation of Graeco-Arabic medical knowledge into Persian, the language of educated discourse throughout South Asia. His chapter ‘Dar Amrāḍ-e Ras’ (On the Diseases of the Head) presents the classification and treatment of neuropsychiatric disorders within South Asian, Islamic medicine. The excerpt below is taken from a critically edited text published in 2001 in Iran.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Indo-Persian culture</kwd>
<kwd>Islamic medicine</kwd>
<kwd>Muhammad Akbar Arzānī</kwd>
<kwd>psychiatric nosology</kwd>
<kwd><italic>unānī tibb</italic></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0957154X12469080" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<sec id="section2-0957154X12469080">
<title>Scale of Medicine as a classic of South Asian Islamic medicine</title>
<p>This Classic Text introduces the first known English translation of Muhammad Akbar Arzānī’s ‘Dar Amrāḍ-e Ras’ (On the Diseases of the Head), a chapter from the <italic>Mīzān-e Tibb</italic> (<italic>Scale of Medicine</italic>). The South Asian Islamic medical tradition regards Arzānī as the first physician of the Mughal Empire (1526–1858 ce) to translate Arabic works into Persian, the language of South Asia’s literate class (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0957154X12469080">Qadeer, 2005</xref>). His books constituted the medical syllabus through the nineteenth century in contemporary India, Pakistan, Bangladesh and Iran (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0957154X12469080">Hadi, 1995</xref>). <italic>Mīzān-e Tibb</italic> became the most important textbook from the eighteenth century onwards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0957154X12469080">Hadi, 1995</xref>). In the nineteenth century Naval Kishore Press, the largest printing house in South Asia, began publishing Urdu translations of Arzānī’s works to create a market for specialty books in Islamic medicine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0957154X12469080">Stark, 2007</xref>). Arzānī’s textbooks are standard reading for students of Islamic medicine even today (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957154X12469080">Rahman, 2005</xref>). Given that there are over 35,000 Islamic medical practitioners in India alone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957154X12469080">Sheehan and Hussain, 2002</xref>) potentially exposed to his publications, Arzānī remains inestimably significant three centuries after his death.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0957154X12469080">
<title>A brief biography of Muhammad Akbar Arzānī</title>
<p>We know frustratingly little about Arzānī’s life despite his important contribution to South Asian medicine and his enormous impact on the history of medicine. A single article serves as the major source (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957154X12469080">Bari, 2002</xref>), and provides the following information: his date and place of birth are controversial, with some placing it in Iran or India; his father Mīr Hājjī Muhammad Muqīm Arzānī was an illustrious physician; Muhammad Akbar studied religion and belonged to the Qādirī sect of Sufism before turning to medicine; he served in the Royal Army of the Mughal Emperor Abūl Muzaffar Muhīuddīn Muhammad Aurangzeb (1658–1707) and returned to court in Delhi after the conquest of Golconda in 1687; he wrote several treatises among which are two Persian translations from Arabic and five original works on diagnosis and therapeutics; he had many disciples as evidenced by the frequent mention of his name in their works and the multiple manuscripts of his texts; he died in 1722 and is buried outside Delhi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957154X12469080">Bari, 2002</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0957154X12469080">
<title>South Asian Islamic medicine as a product of Indo-Persian culture</title>
<p>A clue to Arzānī’s success may lie in his keen perception of the shifting cultural and linguistic attitudes of his time. Arzānī may have helped to herald a sustained translation movement of Graeco-Arabic medical knowledge into Persian throughout South Asia. Earlier, Arabic acted as the <italic>lingua scientifica</italic> in Europe and West Asia. Virtually all non-literary and non-historical secular Greek texts from the Hellenistic, Roman and late Antiquity eras in the Eastern Byzantine Empire and Near East from the eighth to tenth centuries were translated from Greek into Arabic in a state programme sponsored by the Abbasid caliphate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0957154X12469080">Gutas, 1998</xref>). The translators were Muslims, Christians, Jews and Zorastrians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0957154X12469080">Browne, 2001</xref>) working in Greek, Syriac, Pahlavi (old Persian) and Sanskrit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0957154X12469080">Ullmann, 1997</xref>). The translated texts were culturally adapted so that the polytheistic references of Galen and Hippocrates, for example, were replaced by the monotheistic Allāh – literally ‘The God’ – in Arabic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0957154X12469080">Pormann and Savage-Smith, 2007</xref>). Original texts such as Abū Bakr Muhammad Ibn Zakarīya al-Rāzī’s <italic>Kitāb al-Hāwī fī al-Tibb</italic> (<italic>Liber Continens</italic>) and Abū Alī al-Husayn ibn ‘Abd Allāh ibn Sīna’s <italic>Kitāb al-Qānūn fī al-Tibb</italic> (<italic>The Canon of Medicine</italic>) spread widely throughout Europe and Asia, with the latter still held in high authority throughout South Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0957154X12469080">Subbarayappa, 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>With the spread of Islam into South Asia, Arabic and Persian became languages of educated discourse among a growing Muslim populace. Rulers from Central Asia brought their Persian-based language, culture and religion as they conquered contemporary Afghanistan, Pakistan and north India from the tenth through the twelfth centuries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957154X12469080">Alam, 2003</xref>). The sultans of Delhi took an active interest in medicine, tasking physicians with composing medical texts and treating the royal household (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0957154X12469080">Haidar, 2008</xref>). Physicians accompanied the military retinues of these rulers and began writing in Persian by the thirteenth century (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0957154X12469080">Verma, 1970</xref>). Arabic increasingly appeared to be reserved for the composition of religious texts, whereas Persian filled the pages of secular knowledge around history, literature and science, including medicine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957154X12469080">Qutbuddin, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>The Mughal Empire, founded by Zahiruddīn Bābur (1483–1531), greatly expanded the adoption of Persian as a secular language of the educated elite irrespective of religious affiliation. Mughal emperors invited Iranian nobles and intelligentsia to court, elevating Persian as the imperial language at all government levels through the commission of works in the natural sciences, humanities and civil administration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957154X12469080">Alam, 1998</xref>). In a gesture seen as politically liberal as well as astute, in 1574 Akbar entrusted a bureau [<italic>maktab khana</italic>] to translate Sanskrit and Arabic texts into Persian in order to promote a linguistic identity transcending ethnic or sectarian affiliations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957154X12469080">Alam, 1998</xref>). Translations and retellings of religious works from Indian religions led to the development of unique Indo-Persian literary styles and aesthetics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0957154X12469080">Truschke, 2011</xref>). Physicians from Persia – particularly Gīlān, Tabrīz, Isfahan and Shirāz – migrated to India during the Mughal Empire and established physician lineages through the nineteenth century (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0957154X12469080">Liebeskind, 1995</xref>). Indeed, Arzānī belonged to a line of Iranian physicians who found patronage among Mughal nobility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957154X12469080">Bari, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>The emergence of a secular Indo-Persian literary and cultural climate cultivated a medical tradition that distinctively synthesized Greek, Arabic and Indian influences. The Graeco-Arabic medical tradition<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0957154X12469080">1</xref></sup> flourished alongside the indigenous Ayurvedic tradition for centuries. While Ayurvedic medical treatises were certainly translated from Sanskrit into Persian (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0957154X12469080">Mishra, Bhatta, Bhat, Dwivedi, 1981</xref>), the vast majority of hundreds of texts was original, motivated by the practical concerns of adapting Avicennian medicine to an Indian environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957154X12469080">Speziale, 2011</xref>). In particular, Indo-Persian authors incorporated botanical and metal remedies from Ayurveda into Graeco-Arabic texts and attempted to find correspondences between both medical systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0957154X12469080">Speziale, 2009</xref>). While <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0957154X12469080">Qadeer (2005)</xref> praises Arzānī for initiating the Persian translation of Arabic medical texts, Persian translations originated during Nizāmshāhī rule (1490–1633) which slightly preceded the Mughal dynasty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957154X12469080">Speziale, 2011</xref>). Graeco-Arabic medicine did not acquire an Islamic character until the time of British colonial rule (1858–1947) when its defendants wanted to stress the shared Greek heritage of Islamic and Western medical systems against attacks that it was unscientific (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0957154X12469080">Metcalf, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0957154X12469080">Speziale, 2005</xref>). The nineteenth century witnessed another shift in medical culture: Arabic supplanted Persian as the language of the Muslim elite, and Urdu popularized medical concepts through popular printing presses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957154X12469080">Alavi, 2007</xref>). The <italic>Scale of Medicine</italic>’s Urdu translations may help to explain why Arzānī continues to find such a prominent place within the South Asian, Islamic medical tradition even today.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0957154X12469080">
<title>The layout and style of the Scale of Medicine</title>
<p>The <italic>Mīzān-e Tibb</italic> is divided into three sections: the first is on the temperaments or humors, the second is on simple and compound drugs, and the third is on symptoms and remedies divided according to organ system. Its clear prose was seen to help beginners struggling with complex medical terminology from Arabic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957154X12469080">Alavi, 2007</xref>). Its success can be measured through five Urdu translations, one in verse, and over 60 manuscripts in libraries throughout South Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957154X12469080">Bari, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>The section entitled ‘On the Diseases of the Head’ forms the first chapter of the third section. Each subchapter (<italic>fas.l</italic>) is devoted to a disease; immediately afterwards is a subchapter of that disease’s treatment (<italic>fāīda</italic>, literally ‘profit’ or ‘utility’ in Persian). This basic structure is used for all subchapters on organ systems.</p>
<p>The ‘Diseases of the Head’ offers a glimpse into a system of medicine that is genuinely different from contemporary allopathic biomedicine. Today’s physicians may notice that neurological and psychiatric disorders are classed together. Imbalances of the humors are considered to be the major sources of pathology. Treatment consists of manipulating the humors to restore balance, most commonly through purging or increasing the presence of one humor before attempting another intervention. Practices such as venesection, cupping and the warming of limbs represent more intense treatments. Arzānī assumes that his audience is intimately familiar with the various categories of purgatives, laxatives, anaesthetics and other drugs, so rather than explicitly mention names he usually lists the class of drug to be employed. Occasionally, he includes a recipe for a remedy, but translations of botanical names can only rise to the level of educated guesswork: we cannot be sure that terms in dictionaries have the same meanings as he intended. Arzānī draws upon a bewildering range of treatments, from coriander to breast milk.</p>
<p>More work is needed on Arzānī’s relationship with psychiatry, past and present. Since he did not list references, we are not sure if the <italic>Scale of Medicine</italic> is an original treatise, a synthesis of extant authorities, or a compendium of popular remedies at the time. A future task for historians of medicine and area specialists may be to attempt an intellectual genealogy of Arzānī’s ideas. Similarly, cultural psychiatrists and medical anthropologists could trace the extent to which his ideas influence current conceptions of illness presentation and treatment among South Asians. In this way, Arzānī’s work – and the work of reputed physicians in the past – can stimulate interdisciplinary research within the humanities, social sciences and cultural psychiatry.</p>
<p>The excerpt below is translated from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957154X12469080">Arzānī (2001</xref>: 39–50).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0957154X12469080">
<label>1</label>
<p>Graeco-Arabic medicine in South Asia is known variously as <italic>yunānī tibb, unānī tibb</italic>, or <italic>tibb. Yunānī</italic> and <italic>unānī</italic> mean ‘Greek’ in Urdu, Persian, and Arabic, and <italic>tibb</italic> is simply the Arabic word for ‘medicine’. The term ‘South Asian, Islamic medicine’ has been employed throughout this Introduction, consistent with use among contemporary practitioners.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The pursuit of Persian: language in Mughal politics</article-title>. <source>Modern Asian Studies</source> <volume>32</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The culture and politics of Persian in precolonial Hindustan</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Literary Cultures in History: Reconstructions from South Asia</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alavi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Medical culture in transition: Mughal gentleman physician and the native doctor in early colonial India</article-title>. <source>Modern Asian Studies</source> <volume>42</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>853</fpage>–<lpage>897</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arzānī</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Mīzān-e Tibb</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Nasri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>Qom</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Farhang-i Sama; in Persian</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Hakīm Muhammad Akbar Arzānī</article-title>. <source>Studies in History of Medicine and Science</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Islamic medicine</source>. <publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Goodword Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gutas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Greek Thought, Arabic Culture</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hadi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Dictionary of Indo-Persian Literature</source>. <publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Abhinav Publications</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haidar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Medical works of the medieval period from India and Central Asia</article-title>. <source>Diogenes</source> <volume>55</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liebeskind</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Unani medicine of the subcontinent</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Van Alphen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Oriental Medicine: An Illustrated Guide to the Asian Arts of Healing</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Serindia Publications</publisher-name>, <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Metcalf</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Nationalist Muslims in British India: the case of Hakim Ajmal Khan</article-title>. <source>Modern Asian Studies</source> <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhatta</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>PSN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Ideas of integration as a process of evolution of Indian system of medicine in the medieval period</article-title>. <source>Indian Journal of History of Science</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pormann</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Savage-Smith</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Medieval Islamic Medicine</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Georgetown University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Qadeer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>History of Medicine and Medical Ethics</source>. <publisher-loc>Delhi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rabbani Printers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Qutbuddin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Arabic in India: a survey and classification of its uses, compared with Persian</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Oriental Society</source> <volume>127</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Encyclopedia of Historiography</source>. <publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Anmol Publications</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sheehan</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Unani Tibb: history, theory, and contemporary practice in South Asia</article-title>. <source>Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science</source> <volume>583</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Speziale</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Indo-Muslim physicians and the yunani denominantion</article-title>. <source>International Institute for Asian Studies Newsletter</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Speziale</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The circulation of Ayurvedic knowledge in Indo-Persian medical literature</article-title>. <access-date>Retrieved (26 Nov. 2011)</access-date> from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://halshs.archivesouvertes.fr/docs/00/58/47/49/PDF/Speziale_Paper_2.pdf">http://halshs.archivesouvertes.fr/docs/00/58/47/49/PDF/Speziale_Paper_2.pdf</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Speziale</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Indo-Muslim physicians</article-title>. <access-date>Retrieved (26 Nov. 2011)</access-date> from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hal.archivesouvertes.fr/docs/00/58/47/47/PDF/India_xxxiii._IndoMuslim_Physicians.pdf">http://hal.archivesouvertes.fr/docs/00/58/47/47/PDF/India_xxxiii._IndoMuslim_Physicians.pdf</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>An Empire of Books: The Naval Kishore Press and the Diffusion of the Printed Word in Colonial India</source>. <publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Permanent Black</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steingass</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1892</year>) <source>A Comprehensive Persian-English Dictionary, Including the Arabic Words and Phrases to be Met with in Persian Literature</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge &amp; K. Paul</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Subbarayappa</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The roots of ancient medicine: an historical outline</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biosciences</source> <volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Truschke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The Mughal <italic>Book of War</italic>: a Persian translation of the Sanskrit <italic>Mahabharata</italic></article-title>. <source>Comparative Studies of South Asia, Africa and the Middle East</source> <volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>506</fpage>–<lpage>520</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ullmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Islamic Medicine</source>. <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0957154X12469080">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>) <article-title>The growth of Graeco-Arabian medicine in medieval India</article-title>. <source>Indian Journal of History of Science</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<sub-article article-type="other" id="sub1-0957154X12469080">
<front-stub>
<title-group>
<article-title>‘On the Diseases of the Head’ in the <italic>Scale of Medicine</italic> by Muhammad Akbar Arzānī [d. 1722]</article-title>
</title-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<sec id="section6-0957154X12469080">
<title>The First Chapter: On Diseases of the Head [<italic>dar amrāḍ-e rās</italic>], i.e. <italic>bīmārīhā-e sar</italic><sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0957154X12469080">2</xref></sup></title>
<p><bold>The first section: On headache [<italic>dar sudā’</italic>]</bold>, i.e. <italic>dard-e sar</italic>. This, if there is blood, corrupts the cephalic veins. And then they cup the head and feed the juice of a lemon. After the discharge of blood, if there is a seal of constipation, they open the seal with still, acidic water or a good laxative and restore the equilibrium of blood. And if it is from yellow bile, they balance yellow bile and having given a restorative elixir to it for its excretions, they cleanse it and make an infusion of white sandalwood with water and coriander seeds [<italic>sandal-e safīd be āb-e gishnīztar talā’ sāzand</italic>]. If it is due to phlegm, they balance it and they boil as much fennel as they need. Having mixed it with honey, they rub the oil of the costus plant on the head and after some time, they feed a purgative of phlegm. And root of castor and ginger levigated and infused in water is beneficial. If it is from black bile, they try to balance, maturate, and excrete it. And they infuse oil of chamomile and almond.</p>
<p><bold>Advantage</bold>: For headache of any type, a footbath is a physical act that is the most beneficial of things. In pain of the head, the head should not be rubbed in haste because even if it is suddenly advantageous, it will ultimately deliver harm. Instead, one should strike the feet and rub the palms which is beneficial. If they hold the head in their hands without rubbing and striking (the limbs], there is no need to worry. And after cleaning it slowly, rubbing also does not matter.</p>
<p><bold>Advantage</bold>: A headache that is due only to heat or coldness may present without a predominance of a humor. They call that “simple”. In this case, there is no need for cleaning; balancing is enough. If it is due to heat, they consume coldness and sniff it. If it is from coldness, they use heat. If at any time headache occurs with fever [<italic>tab</italic>], they pay attention to the treatment of fever. In this way, if it had arrived due to a cause of another illness, they try to manage that disease. And a type of headache that they call “<italic>shaqīqe</italic>” is in the middle of the head and long-lasting. The manner of its treatment is according to cause; it is the case that in total headache it remits and this ointment has benefit: gum Arabic [<italic>s.amgh-e ‘arabī</italic>], one diram;<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0957154X12469080">3</xref></sup> opium, half a diram; saffron, a quarter diram. Having made it fine with the whiteness of an egg of a bird or rosewater, it is collected on the head, and they clasp it at the base of the ear, having placed it on paper. There should be an especially large amount so that it is resilient [<italic>khū-e bozorgī ke besyār jahande bāshad</italic>]. And they treat this disease quickly since after tightening, suffering a headache is all-consuming.</p>
<p><bold>Advantage</bold>: People with a headache often make an ointment of anaesthetic-like opium or something like that, and there is no doubt that it gives immediate benefit. However, know [in the plural] that wise people prohibit it since its effect ends. And if they use this during pain, they make it better with saffron or chamomile that is a better treatment than opium. When they sprinkle rosewater on the head in headache, they should sprinkle a lot so that the head is moist, and if they do not do it like this, it is harmful. If at any time blood comes out of the nose of the person with the headache, they do not close it [the nose] since it is a good sign. But that which is not a headache due to blood [the humor], and lots of blood comes out, and there is a fear of weakness, then it should be closed. And the coming out of pus from the nose or from the ears in diseases of the head is commendable.</p>
<p><bold>The second section: On delirium [<italic>sar sām</italic>]</bold>, i.e. <italic>āmāsī</italic> [inflammation] which is located in the membranes or in the cavity of the brain. If it is due to blood, it is a disease of laughter. If it is due to yellow bile, [the patient] is bad-tempered and sour-faced. If it is due to phlegm [the patient] is confused and sluggish. If it due to black bile, he is wild. Delirium from black bile occurs less and, moreover, its signs are unique to each humor seen in it. And they call the blood type “<italic>qarānīt.s</italic>” and the yellow type “<italic>qarānīt.s-e khālis</italic>” and the phlegm type “<italic>līshraghs</italic>”.</p>
<p>It should be known that in the blood and yellow bile forms, there is fever, intense heat. In the phlegm and black bile forms, it [fever] is less and delirium [<italic>hazyān</italic>] and lack of consciousness is altogether obligatory. Its treatment is indicated from the cause of headache. And when there is heat, essential in this disease, they regard the management of fever at length. With the sign [of fever] there is cupping with two cups in blood. And without the condition, [the management is as] in types [of fever] other than blood. It is the most beneficial management, and the use of <italic>lakhlakha</italic><sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0957154X12469080">4</xref></sup> is the quickest in effect. And rubbing and closing the feet to absorb the vapour is beneficial to the end. In all cerebral diseases, washing the feet is the custom. Especially in delirium, bleeding should be completed quickly, so that if it is evening, they do not wait for the [next] day. In yellow bile forms they have also ordered bleeding. The reason for this is that the yellow form is delirium-producing – it is compounded with blood. Some investigators in the phlegm type and the black bile type have also permitted bleeding if it does not take away too much strength. It has also been useful in experience, though they take less blood.</p>
<p><bold>Advantage</bold>: Delirious ranting [<italic>hazyān</italic>] and speaking foolishly – and only those [signs] – are what are essential for delirium. Sometimes they also appear without inflammation of the brain. Such that in paroxysmal fevers, and only those, it is seen that at the time of the intensity of disease, an imbalance falls in the brain and at the time of relief there is nothing [no imbalance]. And some call this condition “delirium without basis” because inflammation of the brain is essential among the presenting signs until its conclusion. The treatment of this delirium with this presenting sign of disease is management of the disease and trying to strengthen the brain.</p>
<p><bold>The third section: On stiffness [<italic>jumūd</italic>]</bold>. This is a disease that happens all at once. Man becomes without sensation and action and stays like that. Having slept or sat or stood, in each form that it happened, his appearance is [as it was] at the time of the affliction. And the cause of this is the substance of black bile that brings about obstruction all at once in the back of the brain. <bold>Treatment</bold>: In the case of baldness, they make a warm collyrium or a clyster expelling the black bile. And oil of <italic>khīrī</italic><sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0957154X12469080">5</xref></sup> and oil of almond and ginger is mixed into this. They rub it [on him] and if they mix castoreum it gets better. In the case of hair, they give elixirs to mature and expel black bile. And they bring drinks and food [which are] warm and dry. Then they rub oil of wax on the head. In that situation where blood is also predominant, they strike a vein and they cup with two cups. If they strike a vein, a large vein should be struck. And they take out a little blood and stiffness. Swelling is also named <italic>shukhūs., ākhida</italic>, and <italic>madrika</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>The fourth section: On apoplexy</bold>. This is a disease that renders sensation and action futile and sickness befalls him and he seems dead. If breathing is not apparent, the cause is a complete blockage that has befallen all innards of the brain. <bold>Treatment</bold>: If there is a predominance of blood, they strike the cephalic vein out of necessity and they use only a clyster or collyrium so that the phlegm comes out. And they apply warm bandages to the head. The hair of the head [is] shaven, and they use medicines that are blown into the nostril and snuffed. If they can bring about vomiting, it gives a complete effect. Rubbing, scratching, and tying the hands and feet have benefit. If they make a graze at the crown of the head and rub mercury on it, or before it is used they made a fine cut and rub it on that, it is good. After convalescence, they try to balance, mature and purify the humor of phlegm. And in this illness, if at any time breathing is not perceptible, health is not possible. If breathing appears in him [the patient], he would also accept treatment less [willingly]. The difference between apoplexy and death is that in the condition of apoplexy, a reflection is seen in the silent eye. And in the dead person, it is not. They know that for the silent person, they do not bury [the patient] for up to seventy hours, which is three days and nights, more or less. There is still hope for health because the silent person is alive at this time. At times, it could be that through divine grace, he [the patient] starts to breathe again. But if the body is unwieldy and distended or turned livid, [the patient] is dead. Treatment should not be done as it is akin to punishment.</p>
<p><bold>The fifth section: On sleep</bold>. This is a [type of] sleep that is unnatural in the extent of [its] heaviness. The cause of that is a predominance of humidity in the brain, whether it is simple, whether it is from the substance of phlegm, or blood. <bold>Treatment</bold>: They balance and purify according to the cause and they force [the patient] to smell vinegar. And anything that is acrid, striking and an electuary of myrobalan is quick of effect. In that circumstance where the cause of sleep is gas of the stomach, the antecedence of indigestion and lightness in the state of hunger appears, and its management is the purification of the stomach. And myrobalan of coriander seed has complete benefit. And coriander seed beaten dry [and] sifted on top of food is beneficial.</p>
<p><bold>The sixth section: On insomnia</bold>, i.e. not sleeping. The cause of this is the predominance of dryness in the brain. It can be simple or substantial, and the substance causing insomnia is undoubtedly black bile and yellow bile. The phlegm is brackish also. <bold>Treatment</bold>: In simple insomnia, they manage [it] through moistening the brain by drinks, food, embrocation, snuffing, and all things that balance and moisten. In complex insomnia, they purify [it] according to the substance and not vinegar lest [the patient] smell it and insomnia increase. The medications of sleep are these: they place moist anise/dill [<italic>shibit</italic>]<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0957154X12469080">6</xref></sup> below the pillow. In the phlegm type they spread it also on the head. And they smell sweet basil sprinkled in rose water and use lots of <italic>lakhlakha</italic>. And having dissolved opium in oil of violet, they rub it on the crown of the head.</p>
<p><bold>Advantage</bold>: Any time that the cause of insomnia is fever or a warm gas, the best management is washing the feet, rubbing the sides, avoiding rubbing oils on the head, and trying to terminate its cause.</p>
<p><bold>The seventh section: On the sleep of insomnia [<italic>subāt-e sahrī</italic>]</bold>. This disease happens from the combination of the causes of sleep and insomnia. Some agree that it is a mental inflammation, a compound of yellow bile and phlegm. Altogether, the sign of this illness is that sometimes sleep is long and heavy and languid. And sometimes wakefulness is excessive. Because they [experts] say it is inflammation, they [also] expect delirious ravings [<italic>hazyān</italic>] and opening of the eyes at the time of wakefulness. In any consideration, if the aspect of sleep is predominant, they call it the “sleep of insomnia” and if the aspect of wakefulness is predominant, they name it the “insomnia of sleep”. And the equilibrium of each of the two aspects is found infrequently in which the aspect of sleep is equal to the aspect of non-sleep. If that is found, they say that either sleep or insomnia is preferred because the reason for its predominance is likely. <bold>Treatment</bold>: A combination of the treatments mentioned for sleep and for wakefulness: they use medicines compounded together. At the time of the predominance of phlegm, hot and light aromatics. And at the time of the predominance of yellow bile, they use cold aromatics and other similar management. In considering the occurrence of inflammation, they manage delirium of yellow bile or phlegm, and the justification of this is that inflammation is not necessary for this disease. But it can be [the case] that from inflammation, a compound [disease] also occurs.</p>
<p><bold>The eighth section: On nightmares</bold>. This is a disease in which man imagines in sleep that something serious has befallen him or someone has trodden over him. Then his breathing becomes tight and he emits a noise. <bold>Treatment</bold>: If blood is predominant, they recommend venesection of the cephalic vein, cupping and irrigation, and abstinence from food. And if phlegm or black bile is [predominant], one should purify them. In the management of this illness, they should not be careless that he dies quickly.</p>
<p><bold>The ninth section: On epilepsy</bold>. This is a disease in which a man falls without consciousness and [his] hand and mouth and feet become crooked and spasmodic. And it causes agitation and heaviness of the head. Greenness of the veins of the tongue is also necessary at the time that this happens. And that which comes very quickly is destructive. A quick death that befalls a child often happens when epilepsy happens seven or eight times in one day, then it discontinues and does not come again. <bold>Treatment</bold>: At the time of necessity –which they have called “fainting” [<italic>ghashy</italic>] – they act and put something round [<italic>karūhaha</italic>]<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0957154X12469080">7</xref></sup> in his mouth so that he does not bite his tongue. And they tie his sides so that he does not thrash. At the time of recovery, they purify the substance according to the humor. And they avoid moist fruits, meat of goat and tiger, and things like that. And they hang on the neck a three-cornered wooden [pendant] and they use a medicine that is put in the mouth.</p>
<p><bold>The tenth section: Epilepsy that befalls children</bold>, often they call it “the mother of children” or call it “the wind of children”. Its management is also according to the requisite substance. Excess of drying or chilling without justification should not be done. And they must also order abstinence from nursing, and they must order a prohibition on sex since sex is a corrupter of milk, and corruption of milk is a cause of calamities in children. Anytime the natural physiology of children is closed, opening it with a suppository is quick of benefit in thwarting this condition.</p>
<p><bold>The eleventh section: On melancholia</bold>. This is a disease that, in man, good thoughts and sound thinking are hindered. It is described that in posture and walking, he acts against wisdom in some things. And there are categories of this: foolishness, flippancy and licentious love. <bold>Treatment</bold>: According to the humor, they compose purifications and they call them “exhilarating drugs”. Elixir has complete benefit. And after purification, they try to balance [the humors] and they give light foods and compose purifications repeatedly. A harmful substance is given until the substance [needing balance] returns and strength is restored. In those [circumstances] in which the effect of purification and balancing is manifested late in diseases of melancholy/black bile, they [physicians] should not be dissuaded from management. And after investigating the cause, they should be familiar in management that is effective [in it] so that there will be benefit, if God the Highest wills it.</p>
<p>In love, the best management is unification with the beloved if possible. If not, it is necessary to pay attention to the type of maintained thoughts. There is a complete effect of sex in terminating the disease of love, especially if it is with the beloved.</p>
<p><bold>The twelfth section: On insanity</bold>, i.e. craziness. It is not a secret that insanity has classes. If it is with anger and distress, they call it “mania”. If it is with laughing, play and distress, [they call it] “the house of the dog”. If it is with moroseness and running away from people, [they call it] “wolfness”. To anyone with insanity, the degree of insanity is higher than the degree of melancholia. And they have counted some divisions of melancholia. However, in reality, it [insanity] is without that [melancholia] because in the causes of insanity, the unnatural burning of the humor is a requisite – any natural humor that burns produces melancholia, not insanity. For treatment of melancholia it has been said that they try to moisten [the patient] more. Expressing the milk of women on the head and sprinkling it in the nose, and rubbing oil of violet and almond on the head and body, and bathing and making an embrocation of warm water on the belly has benefit. A successful electuary often gives benefit after the disease has reached its peak.</p>
<p><bold>The thirteenth section: On dizziness and vertigo</bold>. Anytime a person stands or moves [and] the eyes become black, they call that “<italic>sadar</italic>”. And when it intensifies and surrounds the head, and all things in sight appear to be revolving, they name that “<italic>duwār</italic>”. <bold>Treatment</bold>: One should evacuate according to the humor. So if there is substance in the brain, one should know the necessary connection of the affliction in the brain. If the substance is in the stomach, one should be ready for fainting and other afflictions in the stomach. And likewise, for each organ that is the source of a substance, one should discover the affliction of that organ and one should know the purification that is required of the mentioned organ. And one should strengthen it with strengthening the brain. For vertigo that is from weakness, light foods and appropriate exhilarating drugs are the remover of that. And bdellium of mortar with liquid of lemon, and sandalwood with liquid of pomegranate, and things like that are helpful. If receiving the cold on the head is the cause of vertigo, they apply warm bandages and bind the head with warm things. They eat foods in which there are hot spices.</p>
<p><bold>The fourteenth section: On forgetfulness</bold>, i.e. <italic>farāmūshī</italic>. And this is mostly due the predominance of phlegm in the brain and due to black bile. It also appears on account of bad bile [that is] hot and simple. <bold>Treatment</bold>: In phlegmatic and black bile types, they purify after ripening [it], especially with the seeds of the <italic>qauqāyā</italic><sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0957154X12469080">8</xref></sup> and similar things which certainly purify the head. As mentioned by wise men, electuary, jam of galangale and jam of ginger and juniper gum with sugar is beneficial. It is necessary to avoid cold water. And moistening of fennel in the black bile type is necessary. In bad bile that is hot and simple, balancing with cold [objects] and moisteners is sufficient.</p>
<p><bold>The fifteenth section: On hemiplegia</bold>. This is a disease in which half of the body in its length is without sensation and action, and this befalls mostly from the moisture of phlegm. And sometimes it can be due to blood appearing on account of swelling, and its source is the nerves. <bold>Treatment</bold>: In the phlegmatic type, for four days they do not give strengthening medications and they refrain from food. If it is not possible, one can give a little gravy from meat with cumin and cinnamon. In place of water, one can present sufficient honey. After the fourth day, they give a maturation [agent] of phlegm and they give food of a decoction of peas with meat from the offspring of a pigeon, with cinnamon and black pepper. Then from the ninth day to the fourteenth day when the substance has matured, they give a laxative for it. After purification, they make an embrocation with oil of costus and things like that. And an electuary digestive, greater theriac, and mithridate are the most helpful medicines. And they cause medicine to be blown in the nostrils after purification, such as musk, <italic>kundus</italic> root, black pepper, and salt-ammoniac that works quickly. They do not let hot water reach the body since it is harmful to cold water. If blood is also predominant with hemiplegia, venesection is permitted. [In] that case where hemiplegia is accompanied with heat, one should not give hot medications and, first, one should end the hotness. After that, one should attempt treatment of hemiplegia. And [in] that case where the cause of hemiplegia is the occurrence of a swelling, they purify blood at the source of the nerves out of the substance of blood and they attend to the treatment of the swelling.</p>
<p><bold>Advantage</bold>: The lack of sensation and movement, if it befalls an organ without specifically befalling half the length [of the body], they call that “flaccidity” in technical language. Hemiplegia is a flaccidity specifically of half the body, according to people.</p>
<p><bold>The sixteenth section: On numbness</bold>. This is a disease in which the sensation of organs becomes void or deficient. <bold>Treatment</bold>: If it is from the predominance of blood, they do a venesection and declare a reduction of food. If it is from the predominance of phlegm, they purify phlegm. If it is due to dryness, they look for the signs and its treatment from dry contraction. If it is due to narrowness, it is from inflammation or the binding of the organ. And one should remove the cause.</p>
<p><bold>The seventeenth section: On facial paralysis</bold>, i.e. <italic>kaj shodan-e ruī</italic>. The cause of this affliction is either flaccidity or paralysis that falls on one side of the face. The signs of flaccidity are dimness of the senses, loss of taste, and the hanging down of the bottom eyelid and mouth. And the signs of paralysis are stretching of the skin of the forehead and paucity of the water of the mouth. <bold>Treatment</bold>: In flaccidity, they try the same treatment as for hemiplegia, and in paralysis, the treatment for paralysis.</p>
<p><bold>Advantage</bold>: For four days, but not beyond the seventh day, they do not do any treatment and they also restrain [the patient] from food and water, if it is possible. They sit [the patient] in a dark house and they hold a Chinese mirror before [his or her] view so that in distress, [the patient] can look at it continuously. And they put nutmeg in the mouth and they boil the bark of the weed of caper in honey water [for the patient to] gargle it. For that which is due to the predominance of blood, venesection is permitted. In management, they act quickly since paralysis does not go away for three months. Chinese mirror is a term for a mirror made from melted gold/silver, copper; when a face is seen within it during distress, the multiplicity of views in it [the mirror] conveys straightness of the paralysed [part].</p>
<p><bold>The eighteenth section: On paralysis</bold>, i.e. on the drawing together of the organs. They call this, if it is from phlegm, “paralysis of wetness and fullness”. Its sign is that it falls all at once and the signs of phlegm are found. If the cause of the event is dryness, they call it “paralysis of dryness” and the sign of it is that it falls in degrees. Excess vomiting or hot fevers or wakefulness can occur first. And excess sorrow can occur and organs become weak. <bold>Treatment</bold>: In fullness [type], they attempt a treatment of facial paralysis. In dryness [type], it is mentioned that [treatment is from] internal and external moistening from the cause of the corrupt dry humor, balancing elixirs, and wax oil. And they rub oil of violet and almond mixed together. And they order snuffing of women’s milk.</p>
<p><bold>Advantage</bold>: A paralysis that occurs from the sting of a spider or the wound of a sword on a nerve or is from worms of the bowels – they try to manage this by repelling the poison and repairing the wound and removing the worms and removing the distress of the nerve. A paralysis that occurs in epilepsy is its presenting sign; when the epilepsy ends, that also ends. If with the start of the epilepsy, the paralysis continues, they rub lukewarm flower oil or other oil according to the condition. And for some people at the time of yawning, their mouth stays open due to the cause of the shape of the mouth being paralysed – oiling is sufficient and, if it is not, one should undertake a complete treatment.</p>
<p><bold>The nineteenth section: On stretching</bold>, i.e. maintaining straightness of the limb. This is when the nerves are dragged from both sides.</p>
<p><bold>The twentieth section: On lockjaw</bold>, i.e. a paralysis that falls in the space of the neck and prevents inflection. <bold>Treatment</bold>: They look for treatment by investigating the paralysis according to cause. In treatment, they do not show haste since these [lockjaw] are more forceful than paralyses.</p>
<p><bold>The twenty-first section: On trembling</bold>, i.e. trembling of the limb. If it befalls from the substance of phlegm, forgetfulness and other marks of phlegm are found. <bold>Its treatment</bold>: is purification. If it is from the excess of copulation or from excess of drinking wine, they recommend foregoing the cause. In copulative trembling, consuming fresh milk, oiling the body, and eating half an egg that is very dry is beneficial.</p>
<p><bold>The twenty-second section: On throbbing</bold>, i.e. the throbbing of the limb. They have said that its persistence in the face portends facial paralysis; and in the stomach, a forerunner to epilepsy; and in the side, to an inflammation of the chest and side; and in the whole body, to apoplexy; and in the muscle of the stomach, to a forerunner of melancholia. <bold>Treatment</bold>: They heat salt and apply warm bandages to the body. If it does not end, they order a purification of phlegm. And [in] that circumstance where there is retention of menses and there is no production of blood from throbbing, it is immediately removed by venesection.</p>
<p><bold>The twenty-third section: On writhing [<italic>lawā</italic>] that they also call “<italic>fīhadaj</italic>”</bold>. This is a condition in which the limbs become heavy [and] the colour of the face and eyes becomes red. And yawning and gaping come often. And the person keeps stretching himself, as if at the beginning of the <italic>huma</italic> fever. Its requisite is that heat does not come, but after some [time] in that state, it rises and returns many times. <bold>Treatment</bold>: If that condition remains constant or returns, one must undertake a purification of the blood and yellow bile, and demonstrate a reduction of food. Drinking cold water for those hot of temperament and cleaning that [person] suddenly gives benefit. And the seed of coriander made into powder or dissolved with sugar is beneficial.</p>
<p><bold>The twenty-fourth section: On sense</bold>. This is a disease that makes the brain sore/itchy without pain. <bold>Treatment:</bold> They try to cool and moisten it, because the substance of this is steam from yellow bile. If balancing does not suffice, one must give a laxative of yellow bile. And in that case where blood has been predominant, they can venesect.</p>
<p><bold>The twenty-fifth section: On <italic>‘is.āba</italic></bold>. This is a pain that appears in the eyebrow. Its cause is a simple heat that falls on that location [upon] the immediate rising of the sun, and it predominates until the afternoon. Then with the departure of the sun, this [pain] also becomes less. And with the completion of the night, its effect is not there. It starts again in the morning. Its treatment is that camphor is dissolved in flower oil; they drop it in the nostrils and they try to open the outside of the nostril. If there is progression of steam from the body of the ill person, he is turned on his face and the forehead is extended. Its treatment is bringing [about] a haemorrhage by scratching inside the nostril with something rough. If haemorrhage does not work, they strike the cephalic vein and cause vinegar and camphor to be inhaled. And they rub the sides [of the body].</p>
<p><bold>The twenty-sixth section: On cold and rheum</bold>. Know that excretions of the brain, if they come outside the nostrils in the course of illness – they call that “<italic>zukām</italic>”. If it flows in the direction of the throat, they call it “<italic>nazla</italic>”. The sign of hotness is fineness and burning of the substance. And the sign of coldness is thickness or fineness without burning. <bold>Treatment</bold>: They try balancing the humors and they purify the substance accordingly. Altogether, in <italic>zukām</italic>, all excreted substance ceases before purification. One should not give [purification]. And one should treat it softly. The head is covered whether in hotness, coldness or deep sleep. And sleeping on the side, consuming acidic substances and dairy products and meats, lowering the head, and undertaking violent action must be forbidden. If it is coughing or <italic>zukām</italic>, they make a haemorrhage.</p>
<p><bold>Advantage</bold>: A bloody swelling and inflammation that falls on the face is treated through purification. At the end of the book, this will be mentioned in [the section on] occasional illness, if God the Highest permits.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<title>Translator’s Notes</title>
<p>(references are on pp. 109–10)</p>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0957154X12469080">
<label>2</label>
<p>Arzānī often glosses the Arabic medical expression with a Persian equivalent. This formula recurs throughout the text.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0957154X12469080">
<label>3</label>
<p><italic>Dirham</italic> is the Persian word for ‘drachma’ or coin. It is likely that this was used to weigh substances in proportion when making elixirs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0957154X12469080">Steingass, 1892</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0957154X12469080">
<label>4</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0957154X12469080">Steingass (1892)</xref> defines this term as an aromatic of aloe-wood, musk and camphor.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0957154X12469080">
<label>5</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0957154X12469080">Steingass (1892)</xref> mentions that this is the ‘name of a certain flower of which there are several species’, though he does not specify any in particular.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0957154X12469080">
<label>6</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0957154X12469080">Steingass (1892)</xref> mentions both terms.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0957154X12469080">
<label>7</label>
<p>I have been unable to locate a definition for <italic>karūhaha</italic> in standard Persian, Arabic or Urdu dictionaries. I can only guess that it has to do with something round, on the basis of the Arabic root <italic>k-r-r</italic>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0957154X12469080">
<label>8</label>
<p>I have been unable to find this plant term in Arabic, Persian or Urdu dictionaries.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
</back>
</sub-article>
</article>