<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IER</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spier</journal-id>
<journal-title>The Indian Economic and Social History Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0019-4646</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">0973-0893</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage India: New Delhi, India</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0019464612463808</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0019464612463808</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Albrecht Fuess and Jan-Peter Hartung, eds., <italic>Court Culture in the Muslim World: Seventh to Nineteenth Centuries</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Manan</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Anooshahr</surname><given-names>Ali</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0019464612463808">History Department, University of California, Davis</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>49</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Fractured Genres: The After-Lives of Medieval Indo-Persian Histories</issue-title>
<fpage>591</fpage>
<lpage>593</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fuess</surname><given-names>Albrecht</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hartung</surname><given-names>Jan-Peter</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, eds., <source>Court Culture in the Muslim World: Seventh to Nineteenth Centuries</source> (<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>), <year>2011</year>, pp. <page-count count="494"/>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>October–December 2012</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>

</front>
<body>
<p>The present volume came about as the result of a conference held in Gotha, Germany, in the summer of 2007. The organisers, and subsequent editors, Albrecht Fuess and Jan-Peter Hartung, had planned to analyse Islamic court culture along the lines of inquiry initially established by Norbert Elias. The resulting twenty-two contributions cover a vast chronology (seventh to the nineteenth century) and either deal with politics or patronage (read history and art history).</p>
<p>Michael Cook argues that Prophet Muhammad held rather informal and easily accessible gatherings. The memory of these gatherings survived in later periods and created a dilemma for subsequent generations of political thinkers. Stefan Heidemann shows how the coinage of the early Muslims represents the gradual emergence of an acceptable formula to represent a new universal Islamic empire. Hugh Kennedy finds evidence for the continuity of large-scale elite landownership from Late Antiquity to the early Islamic period. Nadia Maria El Cheikh analyses the vocabulary describing the early Abbasid court to conclude that there was no one single definition of court and courtier. Christina Müller traces the history of how the business of conducting justice in Islamic Iberia shifted from laymen or lords to men with legal training. Paul E. Walker studies the extensive courtly ceremonies of the Fatimid monarchs and the aristocracy and ends by stating that the fortunes of the Fatmid elite were closely connected to the ruler. Sunil Kumar draws on the rituals and construction projects of the Delhi Sultans to find, against the grain of modern scholarship, a fragile and insecure political tradition in search of stability and continuity. Albrecht Fuess demonstrates how Mamluk sultans of Egypt made themselves available to the public in <italic>mazalim</italic> sessions. This was a sharp contrast with the Ottoman rule starting in the sixteenth century. Hend Gilli-Elewy sketches the changing fortunes of Baghdad under the Mongols, from initial destruction to subsequent construction and eventual integration into the Ilkhanate. Andrew J. Newman makes the case for a more nuanced appreciation of later Safavid history in which the center successfully managed to address some of the major crises it faced. Eva Orthmann pushes back the formation of the <italic>din-i ilahi</italic> to Emperor Humayun’s early court rituals that drew on astrology and made claims of solar kingship. Christopher Werner describes the court of Karim Khan Zand in eighteenth-century Shiraz as overlapping spheres comprising the itinerant camp, palatial court, scholarly center, hospice for hostages and guests, and the city of pleasures. Felix Konrad finds in the function and ceremonies of the Khedival court of Egypt a hybrid Ottoman-European representation that was geared to Istanbul, Paris, or local Egyptians depending on the occasion or purpose of the particular event. Lucian Reinfandt treats the charitable endowments of Mamluk Sultan Inal as the extension of exclusive court rituals into the public, particularly during peacetimes. Henning Sievert presents examples of the rise of eighteenth-century Ottoman statesmen, one through favoritism the other without. The Ottoman case, he also suggests, does resemble its European contemporaries in a number of ways. Jan-Peter Hartung looks at patronage of scholars in diverse settings (Buyid, Safavid, Saljuq, Aqquyunlu, and Tipu Sultan’s courts) to classify the function of the ulama. Sonja Brentjes investigates the rich culture of patronage of physicians by the Ayyubid court. Stefan Leder calls for greater attention to be paid to the relationship between cuisine, ritual, and meaning at court. Syrinx von Hees examines a fourteenth-century Arabic mirror for princes written for a late Ayyubid prince and concludes by comparing and contrasting the image developed from the text with the definition of court derived by Norbert Elias. Lorenz Korn appraises the beautiful artistic and architectural legacy of the Artuqid court and provides some hypotheses for their patronage. Abbas Amanat studies the works of the Qajar court painter Sani‘ al-Mulk as the expression of a home-grown artistic modernity (mixing realism, irony, and caricature) that was however overshadowed by the increased diffusion of European graphic art. Hussein Keshani closes off the volume by describing how the monumental architecture at Lucknow in the eighteenth and the nineteenth centuries, and the ritualized activity there, were meant to prescribe the appropriate relationship among the Lucknow elite, the general populace, and the Nawab.</p>
<p>In short, <italic>Court Cultures in the Muslim World</italic> strings together a confounding range of academic fields dealing with several historical periods. Judging by the contributions of those authors with whose topic the present reviewer can claim more familiarity (Orthmann, Kumar, and Newman), the individual chapters significantly advance particular scholarly debates in which they are situated. However, since it is impossible for one person to adequately evaluate every single piece in this book, the remainder of this review will be devoted to assessing the overall goals of the volume. While drawing inspiration from Elias, the editors had decided that before scholars of Middle East history can participate in the larger field of court-culture studies, they should come together in order to ‘recognize the specificity of the Muslim context’ of royal courts. This decision is baffling. Elias’ analysis of Louis XIV’s court was part of a larger search into the genesis of self-censoring morality in modern Europe. A comparative analysis of, say, Ottoman, Mamluk, or Safavid courts with the Bourbons, Habsburgs, or the Stuarts might have helped clarify, problematise, nuance, or even discredit some of Elias’s theses. But what is the value of simply establishing the ‘Islamic’ feature of courts that are as far apart as Lucknow, Istanbul, or Cairo during a thousand-year period? This is a search for the essential, the ahistorical, and the constant. The editors seem aware of the problems of their approach when they state that there might not in fact be such a thing as distinct Muslim court culture at all. Strictly speaking however, the existence of such an ideal-type is historically impossible anyway, because it nullifies the point of time and place.</p>
<p>All in all, the most promising comparisons in the volume are diachronic ones. Albrecht Fuess’ own article on the shift in Cairo between Mamluk and Ottoman rule is a good example of this. The contrast between the open and public display of royal prerogative under the Mamluks and the secluded Ottoman government that followed it is so stark that it demands further investigation. Can this trajectory be understood by applying Lucian Reinfandt’s hypothesis regarding the increased need of public presence of Mamluk sultans during peace times to the Ottoman period as well? Further east, the intense use of astrological ordering of the court under the Mughal Emperor Humayun (as discussed by Orthmann) is so different than the accession ceremonies of the Delhi Sultans (as illustrated by Kumar) that one is left wishing to explore the matter much further through a detailed study of the socio-political context of late fifteenth and early sixteenth century north India. In other words, even if the new Mughal rituals reflect some sort of Timurid legacy, they still had to be translated into a meaningful message in the local political culture of Hindustan.</p>
<p>In sum, while the organising principle of <italic>Court Culture</italic> has made its editors wonder if they have reached a dead-end, the volume nonetheless contains excellent original research and opens up avenues for further work that will hopefully be undertaken in the future.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig><bold>Ali Anooshahr</bold><break/>
History Department,<break/>
University of California, Davis</sig></sig-block>
</body>
</article>