<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TRJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptrj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Textile Research Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0040-5175</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1746-7748</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0040517512471744</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0040517512471744</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A rapid measurement for cotton breeders of maturity and fineness from developing and mature fibers</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0040517512471744"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Delhom</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hinchliffe</surname><given-names>Doug</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Hee Jin</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Xiaoliang</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0040517512471744">Southern Regional Research Center, USDA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0040517512471744">James Rodgers, USDA-ARS-SRRC, 1100 Robert E. Lee Boulevard, New Orleans, LA 70124, USA. Email: <email>james.rodgers@ars.usda.gov</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>83</volume>
<issue>14</issue>
<fpage>1439</fpage>
<lpage>1451</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The Cottonscope simultaneously measures a cotton fiber’s maturity and fineness using a small amount of fiber sample. A program of testing was devised to establish the potential and capabilities of the Cottonscope to rapidly and accurately measure maturity and fineness of small quantities of near-isogenic cotton lines (NILs), and to examine the use of the Cottonscope maturity distributions for breeder applications. Cottonscope measurements were performed on mature and immature fibers of varying days post-anthesis (DPA) from two pairs of NILs (MD 52ne versus MD 90ne; TM-1 versus the low maturity <italic>im</italic>). The patterns of cotton maturity and fineness during cotton fiber development of each NIL measured by the Cottonscope were compared to those measured by more conventional methods (e.g. the Advanced Fiber Information System (AFIS), an older and currently more widely used method). The Cottonscope maturity and fineness results were much more responsive to increasing DPA than the AFIS results, and the patterns of Cottonscope maturity values were consistent with those of the Fibronaire micronaire. Comparisons of the Cottonscope maturity distributions among the NILs demonstrated that the maturity distribution for <italic>im</italic> was very different and exhibited much lower maturity values compared to the distributions of other lines. The results demonstrated that the Cottonscope is an efficient instrument for cotton breeders to monitor fiber maturity and fineness of developing and mature cotton fibers.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Cotton</kwd>
<kwd>breeder variety</kwd>
<kwd>maturity</kwd>
<kwd>fineness</kwd>
<kwd>image analysis</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Fiber maturity and fineness are important cotton quality and processing parameters.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0040517512471744">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0040517512471744"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0040517512471744"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0040517512471744"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0040517512471744">5</xref></sup> Cotton fiber maturity (often expressed as the maturity ratio (MR)) is often defined as the degree of thickening or secondary wall development of fibers. Cotton fiber fineness is expressed in several ways (e.g. linear density, cross-sectional area, diameter, or ribbon width), but linear density (in millitex) is most often used. Significant differences in maturity and fineness can impact ginning, textile processing, and fabric quality (such as fabric luster, dye uptake, and stiffness). There are several methods for measuring maturity and/or fineness, including the Uster Advanced Fiber Information System (AFIS), the Fineness Maturity Tester (FMT), polarized light microscopy of longitudinal fibers, cross-section image analysis microscopy (IAM), and spectroscopy (e.g. near infrared (NIR)).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0040517512471744">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0040517512471744"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0040517512471744">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0040517512471744">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0040517512471744"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0040517512471744">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Most fiber maturity and/or fineness methods entail the use of expensive instruments or equipment, extensive sample preparation, chemicals, and/or slow and laborious measurements. Micronaire is a combination of the fiber’s maturity and fineness, and it is often used to measure maturity and fineness indirectly. Common measurements of micronaire include the use of fast but expensive high-volume instruments (such as the Uster High-Volume Instrument (HVI) and Fibronaire). Micronaire is a key quality assessment parameter used by the Agricultural Marketing Service (AMS) of the USDA to classify cotton fiber, for which the HVI is used.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0040517512471744">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0040517512471744">9</xref></sup> For fiber maturity and fineness, the method most commonly utilized to serve as a reference for maturity and fineness results is the slow and laborious IAM method, and over 100 well-blended, well-defined cotton lint samples have often served as reference cotton samples.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0040517512471744">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0040517512471744">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>The need exists internationally for a technique that is easy to use and maintain, and that is a rapid, precise, and accurate simultaneous measurement of cotton fiber maturity and fineness. The Cottonscope has been recently introduced to meet these needs for maturity and fineness measurements, in which image analysis and polarized light microscopy are performed on weighted longitudinal fiber snippets (small cut fiber segments) in a water medium.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0040517512471744">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0040517512471744"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0040517512471744">14</xref></sup> Previous evaluations examined the Cottonscope and Siromat (maturity only) measurements on mature cotton lint fibers of typical commercial cottons.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0040517512471744">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0040517512471744"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0040517512471744"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0040517512471744">17</xref></sup> The potential and capabilities of the Cottonscope method for measuring cotton lint maturity and fineness were demonstrated. The maturity and fineness results yielded high agreement to the IAM method used as the reference, with over 90% of the samples meeting the method agreement criteria and with sample variability being the major source of measurement variability. The impact of bleach use and environmental conditions (location temperature and relative humidity) on the Cottonscope maturity and fineness results were minimal, with the exception of environmental conditions’ impacts on fineness.</p>
<p>The previous evaluations established the Cottonscope as a potent new rapid, accurate, and precise fiber quality assessment tool for cotton fiber maturity and fineness. But could the Cottonscope be used to assist breeders in evaluating new varieties? These new variety samples are often of small sample sizes/quantities, and their application to modern instrument testing instruments can be restricted. For example, often it is desired to run high-volume instruments (such as the Uster HVI) or Fibronaire for fiber micronaire and high-speed individual fiber measurements (such as AFIS) for fiber fineness and maturity. These measurements can require several grams of fiber (e.g. approximately 10 g for HVI and 3.24 g for Fibronaire), and that quantity of fiber may not be readily available for measurements in which the researcher wishes to measure key fiber properties as the fiber matures (e.g. with increasing days post-anthesis (DPA)). Thus, a need exists and interest has been expressed in new quality measurements and instrumentation that can rapidly and accurately measure key fiber properties for samples in which only small quantities of fiber are available. The Cottonscope, which utilizes only 50 mg/measurement of a sample for three measurements or replications, meets these needs for fiber maturity and fineness measurement. A program was implemented to (a) establish the potential and capabilities of the Cottonscope to rapidly and accurately measure maturity and fineness on small quantities of developing and mature fibers from cotton varieties, and (b) examine the use of the Cottonscope maturity distributions for breeder applications.</p>
<p>To test whether the Cottonscope is an appropriate instrument for cotton breeders to measure maturity and fineness, we have measured maturity and fineness from developing and mature fibers with two pairs of near-isogenic lines (NILs). The cotton NILs had been developed by cotton breeders and geneticists to study the cotton quantitative trait locus (QTL) because each set of NILs is genetically almost identical except for a few genetic loci. The first pair of NILs is MD 52ne and MD 90ne of cotton (<italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L.) derived by backcross breeding.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0040517512471744">18</xref></sup> The fiber length, fineness, and MR between the NILs were similar to each other, whereas the fiber-bundle strength of MD 52ne was 12% higher than that of MD 90ne.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0040517512471744">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0040517512471744">19</xref></sup> The second pair of NILs is Texas Marker-1 (TM-1) and <italic>im</italic> lines (<italic>G. hirsutum</italic> L.) backcrossed four times.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0040517512471744">20</xref></sup> The TM-1 is a wild type and a genetic standard for <italic>G. hirsutum</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0040517512471744">21</xref></sup> and <italic>im</italic> cotton is a mutant line showing lower maturity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0040517512471744">22</xref></sup></p>
<sec id="sec1-0040517512471744"><title>Experimental details</title>
<sec id="sec2-0040517512471744"><title>Plant materials and field experimental design</title>
<p>The cotton near-isogenic lines (NILs) MD 52ne and MD 90ne used in this study were developed in two separate backcross programs as described by Meredith.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0040517512471744">18</xref></sup> Additional information on these cotton NILs, including their pedigrees, is described in Hinchliffe et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0040517512471744">19</xref></sup> The fibers used in this study were harvested from the cotton NILs MD 52ne and MD 90ne grown during the 2009 season in a completely randomized design on a small experimental field plot located in New Orleans, LA. The soil type was aquents dredged over alluvium in an elevated location to provide adequate drainage. The plot size for each of the cotton NILs was four rows with equal sampling from each row. The row dimensions were 1 m × 18 m. Fibers from MD 52ne and MD 90ne were harvested at the following days post-anthesis (DPA) time-points: 20, 24, 28, 32, and 36 DPA, and at mature, open boll stage. Texas Marker-1 (TM-1) is a genetic standard for <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0040517512471744">20</xref></sup> The cotton NILs, TM-1, and <italic>im</italic> were developed in a backcross program as described by Kohel and McMichael.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0040517512471744">21</xref></sup> In addition to the mature fibers, the developing fibers from TM-1 and <italic>im</italic> were harvested at 24, 28, 33, and 37 DPA and mature in the 2011 season. The numbers of biological replications were three for each cotton NIL. For each time-point and cotton NIL, 20–30 first position bolls were harvested from individual plants and bulked for each biological replication. The developing cotton fibers were hand-ginned and allowed to dry at ambient room temperature. Mature fiber samples were also hand-ginned. For fiber property measurements, immature fibers were treated the same as mature fibers and equilibrated under the same humidity and temperature conditions required by ASTM D1776-08.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0040517512471744">23</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-0040517512471744"><title>AFIS and Fibronaire measurements</title>
<p>AFIS maturity and fineness measurements were performed on an Uster® AFIS-Pro for five replicates/5000 fibers per replicate (Uster Technologies, Knoxville, TN). Fibronaire micronaire measurements were performed for three loadings per sample, 3.24 g (50 grains) per loading (Motion Controls, Dallas, TX). The averages of the AFIS and Fibronaire measurements were used for this study. All measurements were performed at the Southern Regional Research Center of the Agricultural Research Service of the United States Department of Agriculture (USDA-ARS-SRRC). Measurements were performed on developing and mature cotton fibers from NILs.</p>
<p>For the comparison of five AFIS units, a set of 20 cotton lint samples was used, representing wide ranges of maturity and fineness. The 20 samples were selected for maximum property range from an original set of 104 well-defined, well-blended cottons that are often used as cotton standards for the IAM measurements.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0040517512471744">14</xref></sup> For the 20 samples, the maturity range was from 0.57–1.09 (0.52 maturity units) and the fineness range was from 146.8–199.0 mtex (42.2 mtex). All samples were measured at the 21℃ ± 2℃ temperature and 65% ± 2% relative humidity (RH). All samples were conditioned for a minimum of 24 h prior to measurements.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0040517512471744"><title>Cottonscope measurements</title>
<p>The details of the Cottonscope measurement have been described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0040517512471744">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0040517512471744"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0040517512471744">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0040517512471744">24</xref></sup> As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0040517512471744">Figure 1</xref>, the Cottonscope system consists of three components—the Cottonscope instrument, a knife-blade cutter, and a computer. The knife-blade cutter was used to prepare 50 ± 3 mg fiber samples for the Cottonscope measurements by placing a flattened portion of the cotton sample under the blade and making several “cuts” from different portions of the sample. The cut sample was placed into the Cottonscope water bowl, the water-fiber combination agitated in a counter-clockwise direction so as to separate the fiber snippets, and the measurement started. The moving fiber snippets passed under the camera/image analysis system, and the snippets were counted and measured. After a minimum of 20,000 counts the measurement stopped, and the maturity and fineness results were displayed. All sample measurements consisted of three 50-mg sub-sample/cuttings, with each sub-sample run in duplicate (<italic>n</italic> = 6 total measurements per sample). Cottonscope version 1.54 software was used. All Cottonscope measurements were made at the standard conditions of 21℃ ±2℃ temperature and 65%± 2% relative humidity (RH). All samples were conditioned for a minimum of 24 h prior to measurement.
<fig id="fig1-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Cottonscope system (computer, water-based Cottonscope instrument, and knife blade cutter).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0040517512471744"><title>Data analysis</title>
<p>The Cottonscope maturity and fineness results were evaluated for different breeder varieties and versus increasing DPA. These results were compared to, where available, the maturity and fineness results for the AFIS method and the Fibronaire micronaire results. Cottonscope maturity distributions were compared between varieties and for changes with increasing DPA.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0040517512471744" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title>
<sec id="sec7-0040517512471744"><title>MD 52ne and MD 90ne maturity and fineness</title>
<p>Experimental samples from a pair of NILs—MD 52ne and MD 90ne—were selected for preliminary Cottonscope evaluations and comparisons for maturity and fineness. The fiber samples were of a wide range of cotton fiber development (from 20 DPA to maturity). The primary genetic expression or characteristic modified for these sample sets was fiber strength, so similarities in maturity and fineness and their growth characteristics may be present. The Cottonscope maturity and fineness results were compared to AFIS maturity and fineness results and to Fibronaire micronaire results.</p>
<p>Distinct changes with increasing DPA were observed for the Cottonscope maturity and fineness measurements for MD 52ne and MD 90ne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0040517512471744">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517512471744">3</xref> for MD 90ne). The Cottonscope maturity and fineness results were much more responsive to increasing DPA (sharper and more distinct response and higher slope) than the AFIS results, especially for maturity. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0040517512471744">Figure 2</xref>, the maturity slopes are 0.124 for the Cottonscope versus 0.055 for the AFIS (an approximately 2.25 higher and sharper slope for the Cottonscope); in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517512471744">Figure 3</xref>, the fineness slopes are 32.39 for the Cottonscope versus 19.66 for the AFIS (an approximately 1.65 higher and sharper slope for the Cottonscope). In addition, similar sharp and more distinct curve responses and high slopes were observed for the Fibronaire micronaire and Cottonscope maturity results, indicating good trend agreement between the Cottonscope maturity and Fibronaire micronaire (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0040517512471744">Figure 4</xref>). The Fibronaire micronaire baseline for our instrument was 2.4, which leads to the “flat” Fibronaire micronaire results between 20–24 DPA. The Fibronaire micronaire-Cottonscope maturity measurement agreement from 24 DPA to mature was 0.938. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0040517512471744">Figures 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0040517512471744">6</xref>, very good agreement was observed between the MD 52ne and MD 90ne maturity and fineness results, as the increases in maturity and fineness with increasing DPA were very similar and tracked for both sample sets. The high response and increase for Cottonscope maturity and fineness with increasing DPA and very good agreement between the Cottonscope maturity and micronaire results demonstrate the high potential and capabilities of the Cottonscope to rapidly and accurately measure maturity and fineness on small quantities of new breeder varieties.
<fig id="fig2-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>MD 90ne, AFIS (solid line) versus Cottonscope (dashed line) maturity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>MD 90ne, AFIS (solid line) versus Cottonscope (dashed line) fineness (mtex).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>MD 90ne, AFIS (solid line), and Cottonscope (dashed line) maturity versus Fibronaire micronaire (dotted line).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig5-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Cottonscope maturity agreement of developing cotton fibers from MD 52ne (solid line) and MD 90ne (dashed line).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig6-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Cottonscope fineness agreement of developing cotton fibers from MD 52ne (solid line) and MD 90ne (dashed line).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig6.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0040517512471744"><title>AFIS comparisons</title>
<p>As noted above, the slope and response for the AFIS maturity measurements with increasing DPA were much lower than the slope and response for the Cottonscope method. Previous evaluations had shown that the AFIS slope for maturity was &lt;0.5 compared to the Cottonscope and the cross-section image analysis microscopy (IAM) methods.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0040517512471744">16</xref></sup> In order to ascertain if the low slope and response observed previously and in these evaluations was due to the AFIS unit used, fiber maturity and fineness measurements were made on a set of 20 wide-range cotton lint samples on five AFIS units at three locations (1-SRRC, New Orleans, LA, 1-Cotton Quality Research Station, Clemson, SC and 3-Cotton Incorporated, Cary, NC), and their results were compared to the Cottonscope and IAM maturity results (IAM reference). The SRRC AFIS results for these samples were suppressed compared to the Cottonscope and IAM maturity results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0040517512471744">Figure 7</xref>). In a comparison of the five AFIS units, very good maturity agreement was observed for maturity between the AFIS units, with high <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> and similar linear slopes (0.39–0.44) (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0040517512471744">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0040517512471744">2</xref>). The primary difference between the maturity results from the five AFIS units was a slight bias between the units (averages for all five units were within ±0.05 maturity units from the group average). The results demonstrated that the AFIS units yielded very similar results, and that these results and the overall AFIS response to the IAM and Cottonscope methods were low (&lt;50% gain). Thus, though precise and linear in response, the AFIS measurements for fiber maturity were suppressed and less responsive to maturity changes than those observed with the Cottonscope. Similar results were observed for the AFIS fineness measurements on the five units, but the slopes were not as suppressed for fineness as observed for maturity.
<fig id="fig7-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Comparison of Cottonscope and SRRC AFIS maturity versus IAM maturity (<italic>n</italic> = 20).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Maturity method agreements, Cottonscope and five AFIS units (IAM maturity as reference)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0040517512471744" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th colspan="2">Maturity ratio (MR)</th>
<th rowspan="2">Slope</th>
<th rowspan="2"><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></th>
</tr>
<tr><th>Method</th>
<th>Average</th>
<th>SD</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>IAM</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>0.16</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>NA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cottonscope<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0040517512471744">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.85</td>
<td>0.18</td>
<td>1.12</td>
<td>0.951</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SRRC<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0040517512471744">b</xref></sup> AFIS</td>
<td>0.87</td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>0.42</td>
<td>0.870</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CQRS<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0040517512471744">c</xref></sup> AFIS</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>0.40</td>
<td>0.937</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CI-1<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0040517512471744">d</xref></sup> AFIS</td>
<td>0.85</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>0.911</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CI-2<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0040517512471744">d</xref></sup> AFIS</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.36</td>
<td>0.893</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CI-3<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0040517512471744">d</xref></sup> AFIS</td>
<td>0.85</td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>0.44</td>
<td>0.939</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0040517512471744"><label>a</label>
<p>SRRC Cottonscope.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0040517512471744"><label>b</label>
<p>Southern Regional Research Center.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0040517512471744"><label>c</label>
<p>Cotton Quality Research Station.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0040517512471744"><label>d</label>
<p>Cotton Incorporated.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Maturity method agreements, five AFIS units (SRRC AFIS maturity as reference)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0040517512471744" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Method</th>
<th>Slope</th>
<th><italic>R</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0040517512471744">2</xref></sup></th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>CQRS<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0040517512471744">a</xref></sup> AFIS</td>
<td>0.90</td>
<td>0.961</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CI-1<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0040517512471744">b</xref></sup> AFIS</td>
<td>0.95</td>
<td>0.947</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CI-2<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0040517512471744">b</xref></sup> AFIS</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>0.919</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CI-3<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0040517512471744">b</xref></sup> AFIS</td>
<td>0.99</td>
<td>0.958</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-0040517512471744"><label>a</label>
<p>Cotton Quality Research Station.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0040517512471744"><label>b</label>
<p>Cotton Incorporated.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0040517512471744"><title>Agreement between circularity and Cottonscope maturity of cotton NILs</title>
<p>Although the Cottonscope maturity results for MD 52ne and MD 90ne indicate a high and improved response for the Cottonscope measurements compared to the AFIS maturity results, a question remained about the degree of the Cottonscope’s response to immature fibers in experimental breeder samples. MD 52ne and MD 90ne samples exhibited a wide maturity and fineness range with increasing DPA (especially for maturity), but the significant difference of cotton fiber properties between the two NILs was strength, not maturity. In order to validate the observed Cottonscope’s responsiveness to immature fibers in experimental breeder samples, Cottonscope measurements were performed on two NILs known to exhibit very different maturity responses—Texas Marker-1 (TM-1) and immature-1 (<italic>im</italic>). The phenotype differences between TM-1 and <italic>im</italic> fibers in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0040517512471744">Figure 8</xref> were caused by the different degree of fiber cell wall thickening or maturity. The three cotton locs for MD 52ne, MD 90ne, and TM-1 consist of fluffy fibers due the fiber’s high maturity, but the <italic>im</italic> loc is much smaller and less fluffy due to its low maturity. The circularity (degree of fiber cell wall thickening) of MD52ne, MD 90ne, TM-1, and <italic>im</italic> fiber was obtained from image analysis of cross-sectioned mature fibers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0040517512471744">Figure 9</xref>). Using the IAM method, the cotton fiber samples were embedded, thin-section cut, and imaged using the technique previously described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0040517512471744">22</xref></sup> From the images of the fiber cross-sections, the wall area (<italic>A</italic>) excluding lumen and perimeter (<italic>P</italic>) was measured. The circularity (<italic>θ</italic>) was calculated using the equation <italic>θ</italic> = 4π<italic>A</italic>/<italic>P</italic><sup>2</sup>. The circularity results readily discern that the MD 52ne (0.547), MD 90ne (0.560), and TM-1 fibers (0.500) are mature while the <italic>im</italic> fibers (0.370) were immature.
<fig id="fig8-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Representative mature locs of MD 52ne, MD 90ne, TM-1, and <italic>im</italic> from <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig8.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig9-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Circularity results for mature locs MD 52ne, MD 90ne, TM-1, and <italic>im</italic>. Interval bars represent 1 standard deviation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig9.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The agreement between fiber circularity and the Cottonscope MR was excellent, with <italic>R</italic><sup>2 </sup>&gt; 0.95 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0040517512471744">Figure 10</xref>). The Cottonscope measurements correctly exhibited higher maturity levels for TM-1 with increasing DPA compared to <italic>im</italic>, and the TM-1 maturity results were in the same general range as observed for the MD 52ne and MD 90ne samples. As shown in the circularity measurements, the TM-1 fibers are slightly less mature (lower MR) compared to the MD 52ne and MD 90ne fibers. Due to the differences in growth and sample preparation between the MD 52ne and MD 90ne and the TM-1 and <italic>im</italic> pair, exact/identical comparisons for maturity levels were not expected between the two sample sets. When the IAM circularity measurements were converted to maturity, the agreement between the calculated maturity and Cottonscope maturity yielded an <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> of 0.96. These results validated the Cottonscope’s capabilities and potential to rapidly and accurately measure cotton fiber maturity on experimental breeder samples as the fiber is developing.
<fig id="fig10-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Comparison of Cottonscope maturity with circularity of mature fibers among cotton NILs (MD 52ne, MD 90ne, TM-1, and <italic>im</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig10.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0040517512471744"><title>Cottonscope maturity of cotton NILs during fiber development</title>
<p>The Cottonscope maturity patterns of developing cotton fibers between MD 52ne and MD 90ne were almost identical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0040517512471744">Figure 5</xref>), and their degrees of fiber cell-wall thickening (circularities) were similar between the NILs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0040517512471744">Figure 9</xref>). In contrast, distinct changes with increasing DPA were observed for the measurements for TM-1 and <italic>im</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0040517512471744">Figure 11</xref>). The Cottonscope maturity pattern of developing <italic>im</italic> fibers was lower than that of developing TM-1 fibers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0040517512471744">Figure 11</xref>), and in accordance with the lower circularity of <italic>im</italic> fibers over its NIL, TM-1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0040517512471744">Figure 9</xref>). As fiber cell wall was thickening during fiber development (from 24 DPA to mature fiber), the maturity of each NIL was higher with increasing DPA.
<fig id="fig11-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>The patterns of Cottonscope maturity from developing cotton fibers. TM-1 (solid line), and <italic>im</italic> (dotted line).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig11.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0040517512471744"><title>Maturity distributions</title>
<p>In addition to maturity and fineness results, the Cottonscope provides the distribution of the maturity results for the 20,000 snippets measured. The maturity distributions for MD 52ne, MD 90ne, TM-1, and <italic>im</italic> with increasing DPA, and for the mature samples, were compared. For the mature samples, the peaks in the maturity distributions for the four samples were in line with the maturity results for the mature samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0040517512471744">Figure 12</xref>). As expected, the maturity distributions for the MD samples were very similar in shape and peak location. The maturity distribution of TM-1 was similar to the distributions for the MD samples. The orders from the highest to the lowest peak of the maturity distributions among four NILs were aligned in accordance to the circularity numbers in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0040517512471744">Figure 9</xref> (MD 90ne, MD 52ne, TM-1, and <italic>im</italic>). The maturity distribution for <italic>im</italic> is typical of distributions for immature samples, with a much lower MR peak compared to the other samples.
<fig id="fig12-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 12.</label><caption><p>Cottonscope maturity distributions for mature samples MD 52ne, MD 90ne, TM-1, and <italic>im</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig12.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The changes in maturity distributions with increasing DPA were compared for MD 52ne (similar to the MD 90ne distributions), TM-1, and <italic>im</italic> for 24 and 28 DPA, and the mature samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0040517512471744">Figures 13</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-0040517512471744"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-0040517512471744">15</xref>). It was readily observed from the distributions that the MD samples and TM-1 yielded higher or “faster” MR growth/development compared to <italic>im</italic> with increasing DPA. The MD 52ne and TM-1 distributions with increasing DPA were overall similar and in good agreement. Thus, these results demonstrated that the Cottonscope’s maturity distributions can provide valuable information on MR development and MR variability at selected DPA(s) for breeder varieties.
<fig id="fig13-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 13.</label><caption><p>MD 52ne Cottonscope maturity distributions with increasing DPA: 24 DPA, 28 DPA, and mature.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig13.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig14-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 14.</label><caption><p>TM-1 Cottonscope maturity distributions with increasing DPA: 24 DPA, 28 DPA, and mature.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig14.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig15-0040517512471744" position="float"><label>Figure 15.</label><caption><p>The <italic>im</italic> Cottonscope maturity distributions with increasing DPA: 24 DPA, 28 DPA, and mature.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512471744-fig15.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0040517512471744" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The Cottonscope is a new instrument for simultaneous measurement of fiber maturity and fineness. Interest has been expressed in using the Cottonscope to rapidly and accurately measure fiber maturity and fineness with small quantities of fibers from cotton varieties. A program was implemented to establish the potential and capabilities of the Cottonscope to rapidly and accurately measure maturity and fineness on small quantities of new breeder varieties and to examine the use of the Cottonscope maturity distributions for breeder applications. Cottonscope measurements were performed on four breeder variety samples from two pairs or sample sets with wide days post-anthesis (DPA) ranges. For the first pair, the primary difference between MD 52ne and MD 90ne samples was fiber strength. Distinct changes with increasing DPA were observed for the Cottonscope MD 52ne and MD 90ne maturity and fineness measurements, and the Cottonscope results were much more responsive to increasing DPA than the AFIS results, especially for maturity, and in agreement with the Fibronaire micronaire results. The AFIS method exhibited a low maturity range and slope compared to the Cottonscope and cross-section IAM methods, with a slope &lt;0.5 for maturity. A comparison of several AFIS units established that the observed low maturity slope was not limited to just the AFIS used in this evaluation; all fiber AFIS units exhibited very similar slopes and maturity responses.</p>
<p>In order to validate the Cottonscope response for maturity on the breeder samples, Cottonscope measurements were made on breeder samples from a second sample set with known maturity differences (TM-1 versus <italic>im</italic>). The <italic>im</italic> fiber was known to be more immature. Distinct patterns of Cottonscope maturity from developing cotton fibers between TM-1 and <italic>im</italic> with increasing DPA were observed, validating the Cottonscope’s ability to rapidly and accurately measure fiber maturity on experimental breeder samples during fiber development. The Cottonscope measurements correctly exhibited higher maturity levels for TM-1 with increasing DPA compared to <italic>im</italic>, and the TM-1 maturity results were in the same general range as observed for the MD 52ne and MD 90ne samples. Comparisons of the Cottonscope maturity distributions demonstrated that the <italic>im</italic> distributions were very different and exhibited much lower maturity values. The <italic>im</italic> maturity distributions were typical of distributions for immature fibers. The TM-1 and MD series maturity distributions were very similar. Thus, the results demonstrated that the Cottonscope can provide valuable information on MR development and MR variability at selected DPA(s) for breeder varieties by using both its average values and maturity distributions.</p>
<p>The patterns of cotton maturity and fineness during cotton fiber development of the NILs measured by Cottonscope were similar to those from developing and mature fibers measured by AFIS and Fibronaire. Based on the results, we concluded that the Cottonscope is an efficient instrument for cotton breeders to monitor fiber maturity and fineness for improving cotton properties.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>The authors wish to acknowledge the outstanding work by Ms Jeannine Moraitis and Ms Holly King in preparing and running all samples. The authors wish to thank Messrs Mark Brims and Hy Hwang of Cottonscope PTY LTD for their collaboration and assistance in this evaluation.</p></ack>
<sec id="sec14-0040517512471744"><title>Disclaimer</title>
<p>The use of a company or product name is solely for the purpose of providing specific information and does not imply approval or recommendation by the United States Department of Agriculture to the exclusion of others.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-0040517512471744"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research was partially funded by Cotton Incorporated (Cary, NC) under project number 58-6435-2-671.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0040517512471744"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wakelyn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertoniere</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Chapter 7</article-title>. <source><italic>In:</italic> Cotton Fiber Chemistry and Technology</source>, <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>, <year>2007</year>, pp. <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0040517512471744"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montalvo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Hoven</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Analysis of Cotton</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Workman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source>Near-Infrared Spectroscopy in Agriculture. Agronomy Monograph No. 44</source>, <publisher-loc>Madison, WI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Society of Agronomy</publisher-name>, <year>2004</year>, pp. <fpage>671</fpage>–<lpage>728</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0040517512471744"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>The Meaning and Assessment of Cotton Fiber Fineness</source>, <publisher-loc>Manchester, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Institute for Cotton</publisher-name>, <year>1982</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0040517512471744"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The fineness and maturity of cotton</article-title>. <source>J Text I</source> <year>1939</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>T173</fpage>–<lpage>T210</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0040517512471744"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Heap</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>The Origin and Assessment of Cotton Fiber Maturity</source>, <publisher-loc>Manchester, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Institute for Cotton</publisher-name>, <year>1988</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0040517512471744"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating quality components of natural fibers by near-infrared reflectance</article-title>. <source>Text Res J</source> <year>1982</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0040517512471744"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>NIR analysis of textiles</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciurczak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source>Handbook of Near-Infrared Analysis</source>, <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>, pp. <fpage>485</fpage>–<lpage>520</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0040517512471744"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Agricultural Marketing Service, Cotton Program. <italic>The Classification of Cotton</italic>. United States Department of Agriculture, April 2001</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0040517512471744"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Agricultural Marketing Service, Cotton Program. <italic>Cotton Classification. Understanding the Data</italic>. United States Department of Agriculture, April 2005</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0040517512471744"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boykin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thibodeaux</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A quick embedding method for light microscopy and image analysis of cotton fibers</article-title>. <source>Biotechnic Histochem</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0040517512471744"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hequet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyatt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Abidi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Creation of a set of reference material for cotton fiber maturity measurements</article-title>. <source>Text Res J</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>576</fpage>–<lpage>586</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0040517512471744"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Brims M and Hwang H. Introducing Cottonscope: A rapid and precise measurement of cotton fibre maturity based on Siromat. In: <italic>Proceedings of the 2010 Beltwide Cotton Conference</italic>, (Bill Robertson ed.). January 4–7. New Orleans, LA, 2010, pp. 1417–1423. National Cotton Council, Memphis, TN, USA</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0040517512471744"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Naylor G, Gordon S, Hwang H, et al. Cottonscope—Rapid, independent and simultaneous measurement of both cotton fiber linear density (fineness) and maturity. In: <italic>Proceedings of the 2011 Beltwide Cotton Conference</italic>, (Bill Robertson ed.). January 4–7, Atlanta, GA, 2011, pp. 1278–1281. National Cotton Council, Memphis, TN, USA</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0040517512471744"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Delhom</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rapid measurement of cotton fiber maturity and fineness by image analysis microscopy using the Cottonscope®</article-title>. <source>Text Res J</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0040517512471744"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Gordon S and Naylor G. Cottonscope: A new instrument for maturity and fineness measurements. (A) Instrument design. In: <italic>Proceedings of the 31st International Cotton Conference</italic>, (Friedrich Marquardt ed.). March 21–24, Bremen, Germany, 2012, pp. 133–142. Faserinstuit Bremen e.V., Bremen, Germany</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0040517512471744"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Rodgers J and Thibodeaux D. Cottonscope: A new instrument for maturity and fineness measurements. (B) Experimental results and experiences. In: <italic>Proceedings of the 31st International Cotton Conference</italic>, (Friedrich Marquardt ed.). March 21–24, 2012, Bremen, Germany, 2012, pp. 143–153. Faserinstuit Bremen e.V., Bremen, Germany</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0040517512471744"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bange</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Measuring the maturity of developing cotton fibers using an automated polarized light microscopy technique</article-title>. <source>Text Res J</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>471</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0040517512471744"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Registration of MD 52ne high fiber quality cotton germplasm and recurrent parent MD 90ne</article-title>. <source>Crop Sci</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>806</fpage>–<lpage>807</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0040517512471744"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hinchliffe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeater</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Near-isogenic cotton germplasm lines that differ in fiber-bundle strength have temporal differences in fiber gene expression patterns as revealed by comparative high-throughput profiling</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>1347</fpage>–<lpage>1366</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0040517512471744"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Texas Marker-1. Description of a genetic standard for <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L</article-title>. <source>Crop Sci</source> <year>1970</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>670</fpage>–<lpage>671</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0040517512471744"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McMichael</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immature fiber mutant of upland cotton</article-title>. <source>Crop Sci</source> <year>1990</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>419</fpage>–<lpage>421</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0040517512471744"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Kim HJ, Moon H, Delhom C, et al. Molecular markers associated with the immature fiber (<italic>im</italic>) gene affecting fiber cell wall thickening in cotton (<italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L.). <italic>Theor Appl Genet</italic> 2012. DOI 10.1007/s00122-012-1956-x</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0040517512471744"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>ASTM D1776-08 2008. Standard practice for conditioning and testing of textiles</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0040517512471744"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Hwang H and Brims M. Maturity ratio, fineness and ribbon width measurement using the water based Cottonscope. Technical Application Paper, 2010, Cottonscope PTY Ltd, Perth, Australia</comment>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>