<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JBA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjba</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Biomater Appl</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Biomaterials Applications</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0885-3282</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1530-8022</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0885328212446358</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0885328212446358</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Polyelectrolyte based molecular carriers: The role of self-assembled proteins in permeability properties</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Habibi</surname><given-names>Neda</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Pastorino</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0885328212446358"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
    <name><surname>Sandoval</surname><given-names>Oscar Herrera</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ruggiero</surname><given-names>Carmelina</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0885328212446358">Department of Communication, Computer and System Sciences, Nanobiotechnology and Medical Informatics Laboratory, University of Genova, Genova, Italy</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0885328212446358">Laura Pastorino, Department of Communication, Computer and System Sciences, Nanobiotechnology and Medical Informatics Laboratory, University of Genova, Via all’Opera Pia 13 16145, Genova, Italy. Email: <email>laura.pastorino@unige.it</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>262</fpage>
<lpage>269</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Polyelectrolyte capsules are seen as promising nanotechnology based drug delivery systems. In previous works, we have demonstrated the possibility to fabricate bio-activated surface layer containing capsules with improved features in terms of biocompatibility. In this study, we have characterized the permeability properties of such capsules towards low and high molecular weight molecules, including proteins. The results indicated that the presence of the surface layer strongly affects the permeability properties of the capsules in terms of loading capacity which was found to be higher compared to that of plain capsules. These properties make such systems interesting candidates as drug delivery platforms.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Layer-by-layer self assembly</kwd>
<kwd>self-assembled proteins</kwd>
<kwd>polyelectrolyte capsules</kwd>
<kwd>permeability</kwd>
<kwd>drug delivery</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0885328212446358" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>In the next few years, nanotechnology is promising to have a huge impact on pharmaceutical and biotechnology industries. Advancements in proteomics and genomics have led to the identification of biomarkers specifically associated with different diseases and thus leading to the discovery of a great number of pharmaceutically active new molecular entities (NMEs). In many cases, NMEs, even if exhibit potent biological activity, are considered undevelopable through conventional approaches due to limitations such as poor water solubility or severe side effects. However, drug nanoformulations show the potentiality to overcome the shortcomings associated to potential NMEs, allowing the development of new effective and optimally safe therapeutic modalities. The main foreseen advantages of using nanotechnology-based delivery systems are related to the possibility of prolonging drug half-life, improving solubility of hydrophobic drug molecules, targeting drug delivery to specific cells and/or tissues and reducing toxic side effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0885328212446358">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>Among nanotechnology drug delivery systems, polyelectrolye capsules assembled using the layer-by-layer technique (LbL)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0885328212446358">2</xref></sup> have been recently proposed as emerging drug carriers. The LbL technique provides a versatile and simple method to create multifunctional smart containers for the encapsulation and targeted release of molecules. Capsule properties such as composition, mechanical stability, morphology and permeability can be engineered at the nanometer scale depending on the specific application under investigation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0885328212446358">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0885328212446358">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>Functional properties can be tuned by incorporating different nanoscale building blocks, such as inorganic nanoparticles and proteins, in the shell wall.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0885328212446358">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0885328212446358">6</xref></sup> Specifically, the possibility to functionalize the outer surface of the shell with specific antibodies is of particular interest to target specific cells and tissues. Recently, the possibility to use crystalline bacterial cell surface layer (S-layer) proteins to coat the outer surface of the capsules has been explored in order to introduce reactive functions for covalent linking with antibody molecules.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0885328212446358">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>S-layers are the outer cell envelope of many prokaryotic organisms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0885328212446358">8</xref></sup> They are monomolecular structures which assemble into closed lattices during all stages of cell growth and cell division. Isolated S-layer subunits maintain the ability to self-assemble into monomolecular arrays at different interfaces.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0885328212446358">9</xref></sup> This provides a high density and regular arrangement of functional groups in the S-layer lattice, representing a powerful approach for the controlled ‘bottom-up’ assembly of functional supramolecular structures and devices.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0885328212446358">10</xref></sup> The possibility to reassemble S-layer subunits onto the outer surface of polyelectrolyte capsules has been demonstrated.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0885328212446358">11</xref></sup> S-layer coated capsules (S-capsules) are suitable candidates for targeted drug delivery.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0885328212446358">6</xref></sup> The architecture and chemical composition of the capsule shell define its permeability to low and high molecular weight molecules and nanoparticles.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0885328212446358">12</xref></sup> Therefore, coating capsules with S-layers would affect their permeability in terms of loading and releasing rate,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0885328212446358">11</xref></sup> and thus their practical utilization as drug delivery and releasing systems. Classical polyelectrolyte capsules, based on the alternate assembly of anionic poly (styrene sulfonate) (PSS) and cationic poly (allylamine hydrochloride) (PAH), have been demonstrated to be permeable for small molecules, such as dyes and ions, and under most conditions impermeable for high molecular weight molecules.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0885328212446358">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0885328212446358"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0885328212446358"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0885328212446358">16</xref></sup> Permeability to high molecular weight molecules can be triggered by changing the physicochemical properties of the multilayers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0885328212446358">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0885328212446358">17</xref></sup> This has been obtained by changing parameters such as pH and ionic strength of capsule dispersion. At acidic conditions, the permeability of PSS/PAH capsules has been found to increase drastically due to the formation of pores up to 100 nm in diameter. This conformational change has been demonstrated to be reversible. In S-capsules, a monolayer of S-layer proteins is crystallized onto the shell inducing a change in the multilayer charge density. This change is expected to impact on the permeability characteristics of the capsules.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0885328212446358">18</xref></sup> The focus of this study was to investigate the loading and release characteristics of S-capsules. To this aim, S-layer proteins were extracted from <italic>Bacillus thuringiensis</italic> and re-crystallized onto the modified by the crystallization of a monolayer of S-layer proteins onto the outer surface of PSS/PAH capsules. S-capsules were characterized according to Habibi et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0885328212446358">11</xref></sup> and by scanning electron microscopy (SEM). S-capsules were then loaded with fluorescently labelled dextran and bovine serum albumin (BSA) at acidic conditions and the loading and releasing processes were characterized by fluorescent microscopy and by Bradford assays. The obtained results were compared to that obtained for plain PAH/PSS capsules. The properties of PSS/PAH capsules were found to be strongly affected by coating them with S-layer proteins.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0885328212446358"><title>Experimental</title>
<sec id="sec3-0885328212446358" sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title>
<p>Anionic sodium PSS (<italic>Mw</italic> 70,000) and cationic PAH (<italic>Mw</italic> 70,000) from Sigma–Aldrich were used as polyelectrolytes for multilayer deposition. PSS and PAH solutions were prepared in 0.05 M NaCl at pH 7.4 at a concentration of 2 mg/mL. CaCO<sub>3</sub> with a diameter of 3 µm were purchased from PlasmaChem GmbH, Germany.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0885328212446358">19</xref></sup> In order to investigate permeability characteristics, trypan blue (<italic>Mw</italic> = 872), fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-dextran (<italic>Mw</italic> = 40,000 Da) and BSA from Sigma-Aldrich were used as cargo molecule. Bradford assay (Coomassie Brilliant Blue G-250) was from Sigma-Aldrich. All reagents were used without any further purification. The water used in all experiments was obtained from Milli-Q system with resistivity greater than 18 MΩ cm. All pH adjustments were done with 0.1 M HCl or 0.1 M NaOH.</p>
<p>Crystalline bacterial cell S-layers used in this study were isolated from <italic>B. thuringiensis</italic> (M-H_14, Nature Biotechnology Company). For S-layers isolation and purification nutrient broth, Tris<italic>–</italic>hydrochloride (Tris–HCl) buffer, guanidine hydrochloride, were from Sigma–Aldrich.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0885328212446358"><title>S-layer extraction and purification</title>
<p>S-layer proteins used in this study were isolated from <italic>B. thuringiensis</italic>. Overnight cell cultures of the lyophilized bacterium incubated in nutrient broth at 30℃ were centrifuged at 4000 g and subsequently washed three times with physiologic solution (0.9% NaCl). The pellets were exposed to guanidine hydrochloride for 5 min and 50 mM Tris–HCl (pH 7.2) and were incubated at 37℃ for 2 h. The obtained lysates were centrifuged at 4000 g for 20 min to recover S-layer which were then dialysed against distilled water (4℃). Finally, the protein aggregates were removed from the solution by centrifugation at 4000 g for 20 min (4℃). Prior to be used for the experimental work, S-layer proteins concentration was evaluated by means of the Bradford assay using BSA as standard protein to prepare solutions at known concentration. To this aim, purified S-layer proteins were mixed with Coomassie Brilliant Blue G-250 under acid conditions and after 30 min samples absorbance was read at 595 nm. The concentration of the protein solution was adjusted to 1 mg/mL and was used in further experiments.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0885328212446358">20</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0885328212446358"><title>Capsule preparation</title>
<p>The capsule shell was formed according to a well established procedure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0885328212446358">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0885328212446358">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0885328212446358">14</xref></sup> Namely, 0.1 g CaCO<sub>3</sub> microparticles, 3 µm in diameter, were dispersed in 10 mL of 0.05 M NaCl at pH 7.4. The multilayered structure (PSS/PAH)<sub>6</sub>/PSS was deposited onto the templates. After each adsorption step the particles were centrifuged at 3000 g, washed three times with 0.05 M NaCl at pH 7, resuspended in 20 mL of 0.05 M NaCl at pH 7.4 and exposed to the next polyelectrolyte solution. Core removal was carried out in 0.1 M HCl solution at a pH value between 1 and 1.5. Finally, the obtained hollow polyelectrolyte capsules were washed three times in 0.05 M NaCl at pH 7.4 and then stored at room temperature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0885328212446358">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0885328212446358">22</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0885328212446358"><title>S-layer recrystallization onto hollow capsules</title>
<p>The recrystallization of S-layer proteins was carried out onto hollow polyelectrolyte capsules using 0.1 mg/mL of protein in a buffer solution of 10 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> in 0.5 mM Tris–HCl. Namely, 400 µL of capsule dispersion (5 × 10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0885328212446358">6</xref></sup> capsules) were exposed to the protein solution and were incubated for 1 h at room temperature allowing the proteins to recrystallize on the polyelectrolyte shell. The obtained S-capsules were then centrifuged at 4000 g for 10 min to remove unbound proteins and were washed three times with 0.05 M NaCl at pH 7.4.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0885328212446358"><title>Permeability characterization</title>
<p>As a first step, permeability test were carried out using trypan blue as low molecular weight cargo molecule. Trypan blue was used at a concentration of 50 µg/mL in 0.05 M NaCl at pH 3. Loading of the dye inside the capsule volume was visualized by means of optical microscopy and assayed measuring the absorbance of the dispersion medium at 620 nm by means of a plate reader (Anthos Labtec Instruments GmbH).</p>
<p>The capsule permeability against trypan blue was investigated in 0.05 M NaCl within a range of pH from 3 to 9. pH 3 and 7.4 was further used as an indicator for open and closed state of capsules.</p>
<p>Then, FITC-labelled dextran was used as high molecular weight cargo molecule. FITC-labelled dextran was used at a concentration of 1 mg/mL in phosphate buffer saline 0.05 M NaCl at pH 3. Capsules were washed in pH 9 in order to close the shell pores avoiding any leakage due to the changes in the osmotic pressure of the solution in which the capsules were dispersed.</p>
<p>The capsules were then centrifuged and dispersed in 0.05 M NaCl at pH 7.4 and visualized by means of fluorescence microscope. Fluorescence measurements were performed by means of an Olympus IX 70 inverted epi-fluorescence microscope, equipped with HAMAMT 2U ORCA-ER II digital camera.The excitation and emission wavelengths were 488 and 580 nm, respectively. The images were analysed with Image pro-plus software.</p>
<p>Finally, BSA was used as model protein for permeability characterization respect to biomacromolecules. BSA was used at a concentration of 1 mg/mL at pH 3.</p>
<p>The amount of BSA loaded inside the microcapsules was estimated from the difference between the starting and the remaining one after loading process. The BSA content in the supernatant was determined by Bradford assay. The supernatant was diluted 1:40, 1 mL of the diluted protein solution was mixed with 1 mL of Bradford reagent. After 10 min the absorbance was read at 595 nm. Standard proteins were 1–30 µg/mL of BSA prepared in water pH 3.</p>
<p>The important loading parameters such as loading capacity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0885328212446358">15</xref></sup> (L) and capsule interior concentration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0885328212446358">16</xref></sup> [C<sub>in</sub>] were calculated using the following equations
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0885328212446358"><label>(1)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math1-0885328212446358"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Loading</mml:mtext><mml:mi> </mml:mi><mml:mtext>capacity</mml:mtext><mml:mi> </mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Mw</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0885328212446358" xlink:href="10.1177_0885328212446358-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>

<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0885328212446358"><label>(2)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math2-0885328212446358"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Capsule</mml:mtext><mml:mi> </mml:mi><mml:mtext>interior</mml:mtext><mml:mi> </mml:mi><mml:mtext>concentration</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>in</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>capsule</mml:mtext> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0885328212446358" xlink:href="10.1177_0885328212446358-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
where [<italic>c</italic>] is the concentration of loaded protein in mg/mL, <italic>Mw</italic> the molecular weight of the loaded protein in g/gmol, [<italic>N</italic>] the number of capsules per litre, <italic>N</italic><sub>A</sub> the Avogadro’s number,<inline-formula id="ilm1-0885328212446358"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math1-0885328212446358"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>capsule</mml:mtext> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>the volume of one microcapsule and [<italic>N</italic>*] the number of capsules/mL.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0885328212446358">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0885328212446358">16</xref></sup></p>
<p>In all cases, the loading process was performed by exposing 0.4 mL of empty capsules (10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0885328212446358">7</xref></sup> capsules/mL) to cargo molecules solutions at pH 3, when the capsules are in an open configuration, for 24 h with continuous shaking at 300 r/min. Afterwards, the loaded capsules were centrifuged at 3500 r/min for 8 min, the supernatant was removed and water solution (0.05 M NaCl) at pH 9 was added to wash the capsules and close the pores. The capsules were then dispersed in pH 7.4.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0885328212446358"><title>Scanning electron microscopy</title>
<p>To study the morphology of capsules a high-resolution SEM (HR-SEM) Philips XL30 FEG was used. The samples were deposited on 1 × 2 cm<sup>2</sup> flat silicon substrates and subsequently were dried. Silicones were housed directly inside the HR-SEM holder without any metallic coatings to avoid any artefact on the surface. HR-SEM images were obtained using 5.00 kV of electron beam energy and 3.0 nm of beam spot.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0885328212446358" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title>
<p>CaCO<sub>3</sub> templates were used in this study, as they can be completely removal during dissolution with acid or chelating agents.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0885328212446358">23</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0885328212446358"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0885328212446358">25</xref></sup> Uniform CaCO<sub>3</sub> templates with a size distribution of 3 ± 0.5 µm were used for polyelectrolyte deposition. PSS exhibits the ability to absorbs onto positive as well as negative charged surfaces and S-layers are known to absorb on negative layers;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0885328212446358">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0885328212446358">19</xref></sup> therefore, the first and last deposited monolayer was PSS. The architecture (PSS/PAH)<sub>6</sub>/PSS was deposited onto templates followed by the core removal in acidic pH. Thirteen monolayers were deposited to obtain a compact structure and thus to limit the permeability by diffusion through the loose structure of the interfacial layers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0885328212446358">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0885328212446358">26</xref></sup> The complete removal of the core and formation of hollow capsules were confirmed by means of optical microscopy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0885328212446358">Figure 1</xref>). As second step, S-layers were recrystallized onto the capsule shells. The effective recrystallization was verified by different techniques accordingly to Habibi et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0885328212446358">11</xref></sup> Moreover, the morphology of S-capsules was characterized by SEM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0885328212446358">Figure 2</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0885328212446358">Figure 2</xref>, reports the morphology of two S-capsule at pH 7. The shell of both capsules were found to be compact and defect free.
<fig id="fig1-0885328212446358" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Optical microscope image of (a) covered templates and (b) hollow capsules after acid treatment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885328212446358-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-0885328212446358" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>SEM images of two different dried S-capsules incubated at pH 7.4.</p>
<p>SEM: scanning electron microscope.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885328212446358-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>As a first step, permeability test were carried out using trypan blue as low molecular weight molecule. S-capsules were loaded with trypan blue at pH 3. The low molecular weight molecules were found to permeate rapidly the capsule volume. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0885328212446358">Figure 3</xref>, shows the optical micrograph of the dispersion of S-capsules in the solution containing trypan blue at pH 3. At pH values above 6, the loading process required more time, around 10 min. By increasing the ionic strength up to 0.1 M NaCl, the permeability was increased. The capsules were found to be closed at pH 7 and above. Due to this in further experiments pH 3 and 7.4 were used for open and closed state of capsules, respectively These observations are in agreement with data reported in the literature for plain PSS/PAH-based capsules.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0885328212446358">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0885328212446358">27</xref></sup> The loading capacity of S-capsules was compared to that of PSS/PAH capsules by determining the difference of the concentration of trypan between the solution before and after the loading process. Capsule interior concentration was calculated by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0885328212446358">equation (2)</xref> and was found to be 17.2 ± 1 and 23.5 mg/mL for PSS/PAH capsules and S-capsules, respectively. The loading efficiency calculated by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0885328212446358">equation (1)</xref> was found to increase from 30% to 44% for S-capsules. The results showed that the loading capability has been increased in the presence of S-layers in pH 3.
<fig id="fig3-0885328212446358" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Optical images of S-capsules in presence of trypan blue (a) pH 3.0 and (b) pH 7.4.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885328212446358-fig3.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Permeability respect to high molecular weight molecules was characterized using FITC-dextran. In previous works it has been shown that the polyelectrolyte multilayer shells can be switched between an open and a closed state by means of tuning the pH value.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0885328212446358">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0885328212446358">28</xref></sup> This is attributed to charging effects in the capsule wall creating local defects. As relates to S-capsules, in this study, the permeability characteristics towards high molecular weight molecules were also found to be pH dependent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0885328212446358">Figure 4</xref>). The results in this study also showed the open and closed state of both capsules and S-capsules promoted in 0.05 M NaCl at pH 3 and 7.4, respectively. The loading was carried out at 0.05 M NaCl at pH 3, then loaded S-capsules and PSS/PAH capsules were centrifuged and redispersed at pH 7.4 and their fluorescent profile was characterized and compared (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0885328212446358">Figure 5</xref>). It was found that the fluorescent profile for S-capsules was higher indicating an increased loading efficiency. The results showed a uniform and high distribution of the fluorescence dye inside the S-capsules prompted in pH 3, reaching the value of 4000 (a.u.) in the centre while a low density of the dye mostly on the walls was detected for plain PAH/PSS capsules. This result could be explained taking into account that the S-layer deposited onto the top of the shell is responsible for a change in the stoichiometry of the (PSS/PAH) multilayer leading to a change of its physicochemical properties which finally results in the formation of more defects. The morphology of S-capsules at pH 3 was characterized by SEM. Several holes having dimensions ranging from 100 to 400 nm were identified in the S-capsules wall (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0885328212446358">Figure 6</xref>). The surface of the capsules was found to be smooth and with pores in pH 3 while in pH 7.4 a rough and compact surface was observed.
<fig id="fig4-0885328212446358" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>S-capsules were loaded with FITC-dextran <italic>Mw</italic> 40,000 in pH 3 (open state) and visualized in pH 7.4 (closed state). Scale bar 3 µm.</p>
<p>FITC: fluorescein isothiocyanate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885328212446358-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig5-0885328212446358" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Capsules (A) and S-capsules (B) incubated with FITC-dextran at pH 3 and their fluorescence.</p>
<p>profile. Scale bar 3 µm.</p>
<p>FITC: fluorescein isothiocyanate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885328212446358-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig6-0885328212446358" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>SEM images of a S-capsule incubated in 0.05 NaCl at pH 3.</p>
<p>SEM: scanning electron microscope.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885328212446358-fig6.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Finally, the possibility of loading large macromolecules, such as proteins has been evaluated.</p>
<p>BSA was used as model protein in this study. The loading and release of BSA was investigated for S-capsules and obtained results compared with PSS/PAH capsules. The loading capacity of PSS/PAH capsules was found to be 9 × 10<sup>7</sup> molecules/capsule and increased to 1.2 × 10<sup>8</sup> for S-capsules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0885328212446358">Figure 7</xref>). The results confirmed the influence of electrostatic forces induced by S-layer on the multilayered shell wall which increased its permeability. The capsule interior concentration for S-capsules was found to be 83 mg/mL. The release of loaded BSA molecules from S-capsules was investigated in water solution at low pH.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0885328212446358">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0885328212446358">30</xref></sup> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0885328212446358">Figure 8</xref>, shows the cumulative release of BSA as a function of time. The release profile had two separate regions, initial burst release in the first 0.5 h followed by sustained release up to 3 h. A cumulative release of 53% in S-capsules was obtained at the end of 3 h. This can be explained taking into account that the release is controlled by the concentration gradient from inside to outside the capsule.
<fig id="fig7-0885328212446358" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Interior capsule concentration (mg/mL) and loading capacity (molecules/capsules) of S-capsules and PAH/PSS capsules for BSA at pH 3.</p>
<p>PAH: poly (allylamine hydrochloride); PSS: poly (styrene sulfonate); and BSA: bovine serum albumin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885328212446358-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig8-0885328212446358" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Release profile for BSA loaded S-capsules at pH 3.</p>
<p>BSA: bovine serum albumin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885328212446358-fig8.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0885328212446358" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>We demonstrated that the properties of polyelectrolyte capsules are largely tuned by coating them with S-layer proteins, thus representing the possibility of efficient loading and release of macromolecules such as proteins. The results showed that covering capsules with S-layer proteins increased the permeability of capsules at low pH. The process was reversible allowing to encapsulate macromolecules at higher pH. High distribution of FITC-dextran was detected in loaded S-capsules. The loading capacity and capsule interior concentration of capsules for BSA were found to be increased. The presence of several large pores on the shell surface at pH 3 was observed by SEM. In previous works, we have demonstrated that S-capsules represent a new class of functional and biocompatible capsules. In this study, we have demonstrated that such modified capsules can be easily loaded with low and high molecular weight molecules and that the release is promoted only at low pH while at physiological pH the shell is in a close conformation. Such new class of polyelectrolyte capsules are under investigation as effective drug delivery systems and their properties such as multifuntionality and versatility makes them promising candidate for the application as microreactors, in biosensing and cell transfection.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back><ack><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></ack>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0885328212446358"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pastorino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Erokhina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>CanevaSoumetz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Collagen containing microcapsules: smart containers for disease controlled therapy</article-title>. <source>J Colloid Interface Sci</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage> 56</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0885328212446358"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fuzzy nanoassemblies: toward layered polymeric multicomposites</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>277</volume>: <fpage> 1232</fpage>–<lpage>1237</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0885328212446358"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ariga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lvov</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Layer-by-layer self-assembled shells for drug delivery</article-title>. <source>Adv Drug Delivery Rev</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>63</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage> 762</fpage>–<lpage>771</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0885328212446358"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pastorino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Habibi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Caneva Soumetz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Polyelectrolyte multilayers for cell and tissue engineering</article-title>. <source>Eur Cell Mater</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage> 66</fpage>–<lpage> 66</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0885328212446358"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Mercato</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Pino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nanoparticle modified polyelectrolyte capsules</article-title>. <source>Nano Today</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage> 12</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0885328212446358"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mader</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kupcu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sleytr</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>S-layer-coated liposomes as a versatile system for entrapping and binding target molecules</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>1462</volume>: <fpage> 142</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0885328212446358"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toca-Herrera</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Krastev</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Recrystallization of bacterial S-layers on flat polyelectrolytes surfaces and hollow polyelectrolyte Capsules</article-title>. <source>Small</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage> 339</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0885328212446358"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Sleytr</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name><name><surname>Messner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <source>Crystalline bacterial cell surface proteins</source>, <edition>ch. 2</edition>. <publisher-loc>San Diego, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>, <year>1996</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0885328212446358"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sleytr</surname><given-names>UWB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anisotropic crystal growth of the S-layer of Bacillus sphaericus CCM 2177 at the air/water interface</article-title>. <source>Colloids Surf A</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>102</volume>: <fpage> 99</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0885328212446358"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>MAN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gliozzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Möhwald</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nanocapsules with functionalized surfaces and walls</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Nanobiosci</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage> 3</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0885328212446358"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habibi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pastorino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>CanevaSoumetz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nanoengineered polymeric S-layers based capsules with targeting activity</article-title>. <source>Colloids Surf B</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>88</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage> 366</fpage>–<lpage>372</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0885328212446358"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pastorino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Erokhina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianchini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Permeability variation study in collagen-based polymeric capsules</article-title>. <source>Bionanoscience</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage> 192</fpage>–<lpage>197</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0885328212446358"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antipov</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukhorukov</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Leporatti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Polyelectrolyte multilayer capsule permeability control</article-title>. <source>Colloids Surf A</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>198</volume>: <fpage> 535</fpage>–<lpage>541</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0885328212446358"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antipov</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukhorukov</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Polyelectrolyte multilayer capsules as vehicles with tunable permeability</article-title>. <source>Adv Colloid Interface Sci</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>111</volume>: <fpage> 49</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0885328212446358"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anandhakumer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagaraja</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Raichur</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reversible polyelectrolyte capsules as carriers for protein delivery</article-title>. <source>Colloids Surf B</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>78</volume>: <fpage> 266</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0885328212446358"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Khaled</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Exploiting the enhanced permeability and retention effect for tumor targeting</article-title>. <source>Drug Discovery Today F</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage> 812</fpage>–<lpage>818</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0885328212446358"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delcea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Möhwald</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Skirtach</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stimuli-responsive LbL capsules and nanoshells for drug delivery</article-title>. <source>Adv Drug Delivery</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>63</volume>: <fpage> 730</fpage>–<lpage>747</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0885328212446358"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ilk</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelseer</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferner-Ortner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Surface functionalized with self-assembling S-layer fusion proteins for nanobiotechnological applications</article-title>. <source>Colloids Surf A</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>321</volume>: <fpage> 163</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0885328212446358"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antipove</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shchukin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedutik</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Carbonate microparticles for hollow polyelectrolyte capsules fabrication</article-title>. <source>Colloids Surf A</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>224</volume>: <fpage> 175</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0885328212446358"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gufler</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>S-layer proteins as supporting scaffoldings for functional lipid membranes</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Nanobiosci</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage> 1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0885328212446358"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pastorino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Erokhina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Caneva</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Paclitaxal containing nano-engineered polymeric capsule towards cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>J Nanosci Nanotechnol</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>9</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage> 6753</fpage>–<lpage>6759</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0885328212446358"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delcea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yashchenok</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Videnova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multicompartmental micro- and nanocapsules: hierarchy and application in biosciences</article-title>. <source>Macromol Biosci</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage> 465</fpage>–<lpage>474</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0885328212446358"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Encyclopedia of surface and colloid science</source>, <edition>ch. 3</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Marcel Dekker</publisher-name>, <year>2002</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0885328212446358"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donath</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukhorukov</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Caruso</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Novel hollow polymer shells by colloid-templated assembly of polyelectrolytes</article-title>. <source>Angew Chem Int Ed</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage> 2202</fpage>–<lpage>2205</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0885328212446358"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balabushevich</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiourina</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Volodkin</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Loading the multilayer dextran sulfate/protamine microsized capsules with peroxidase</article-title>. <source>Biomacromolecules</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>4</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage> 1191</fpage>–<lpage>1197</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0885328212446358"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiourina</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Antipov</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukhorukov</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Entrapment of α-chymotrypsin into hollow polyelectrolyte microcapsules</article-title>. <source>Macromol Biosci</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage> 209</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0885328212446358"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Georgieva</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimova</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukhorukov</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of different salts on micro-sized polyelectrolyte hollow capsules</article-title>. <source>J Mater Chem</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage> 4301</fpage>–<lpage>4310</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0885328212446358"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaspro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Magrassi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nanocapsules: coating for living cells</article-title>. <source>IEEE Trans Nanobiosci</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage> 3</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0885328212446358"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esser-Kahn</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Odom</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sottos</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Triggered release from polymer capsules</article-title>. <source>Macromolecules</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage> 5539</fpage>–<lpage>5553</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0885328212446358"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavlukhina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukhishvili</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Polymer assemblies for controlled delivery of bioactive molecules from surfaces</article-title>. <source>Adv Drug Delivery Rev</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>63</volume>: <fpage> 822</fpage>–<lpage>836</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>