<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NEJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spnej</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nurs Ethics</journal-id>
<journal-title>Nursing Ethics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0969-7330</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0989</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0969733013484200</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0969733013484200</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Guest Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Ethical, cultural, and spiritual dimensions of healthcare practice</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>McHale</surname>
<given-names>Jean V</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0969733013484200"/>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0969733013484200"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0969733013484200">University of Birmingham, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name>
<surname>McHale</surname>
<given-names>Jean V</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0969733013484200">Jean V McHale, Professor of Health Care Law, Director of the Centre for Health Law, Science and Policy, Birmingham Law School, University of Birmingham, Edgbaston, Birmingham, B152TT, UK. Email: <email>j.v.mchale@bham.ac.uk</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>20</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<issue-title>Special issue: Ethical, cultural, and spiritual dimensions of healthcare practice</issue-title>
<fpage>365</fpage>
<lpage>365</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Enhanced migration, evolving communities, and changing attitudes across jurisdictions have led to new challenges for the delivery of healthcare. As populations become more culturally diverse, there is the prospect that the norms of individual health professionals and patients may diverge. Does this mean that we should embrace and recognize diversity? Or does this lead us to question the legitimacy of different norms and different perspectives? Are healthcare professionals simply “professionals” who should leave their own moral, ethical, religious beliefs at home? Or should we redefine the boundaries of professional responsibility in the light of such beliefs? In the past, these questions have arisen in Western jurisdictions in the context of conscientious objection in the area of reproductive medicine, but this is becoming an increasingly global question. We should also ask to what extent the delivery of healthcare services should be redefined to reflect a culturally diverse patient population. Is this is a necessity in a world in which healthcare practice is increasingly informed by respect for fundamental human rights and dignity as exemplified in international law through the Universal Declaration of Human Rights?</p>
<p>The articles in this issue of <italic>Nursing Ethics</italic> reflect some of the challenges arising from these questions and also from the diversity in practices and approaches across jurisdictions. In the context of the United Kingdom, Samanta illustrates the challenges of accommodating diversity in healthcare delivery in a jurisdiction where such care delivery will be increasingly impacted by the evolution of equality law in the form of the implementation of the Equality Act 2010. The considerable challenges in respecting cultural diversity are illustrated by Susilo et al.’s article examining these issues in relation to healthcare delivery in Indonesia. Defining the role of the nurse in terms of their own rights as well as responsibilities is increasingly recognized in some jurisdictions. In others, characterizing the nurses’ role in terms of their rights is a more recent development, and the implications of this are highlighted in the empirical study of Italian nurses by Kangasniemi et al. Raising awareness of questions of ethnicity, cultural, and spiritual practices should moreover not be simply a matter for determining on a case-by-case basis day by day but rather it requires reflection and, where necessary, regulation. It also requires education as highlighted by Choe et al. The need for bioethical education in nursing programs remains critically important as do clear ethical codes (see further the article by Kim et al. in this issue).</p>
<p>What is notable is that the whole area of the interface amongst ethics, culture, faith, belief, and spirituality is ripe for further consideration and evaluation by nurses, ethicists, lawyers, and regulators alike. As highlighted in several articles in this volume—by Almedia et al. in the context of spirituality in blood donation and by Ravari et al.—further research in these and related areas is needed in the future.</p>
</body>
</article>