<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">UEX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spuex</journal-id>
<journal-title>Urban Education</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0042-0859</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-8340</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0042085911429582</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0042085911429582</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>White and Black Teachers’ Job Satisfaction</article-title>
<subtitle>Does Relational Demography Matter?</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Fairchild</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0042085911429582">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0042085911429582">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Tobias</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0042085911429582">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Corcoran</surname><given-names>Sean</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0042085911429582">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Djukic</surname><given-names>Maja</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0042085911429582">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kovner</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0042085911429582">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Noguera</surname><given-names>Pedro</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0042085911429582">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0042085911429582"><label>1</label>New York University, New York, NY, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0042085911429582"><label>2</label>New Visions for Public Schools, New York, NY, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0042085911429582">Susan Fairchild, Director of Data and Applied Research, New Visions for Public Schools, 320 West 13th Street, New York, NY 10014, USA Email: <email>sfairchild@newvisions.org</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-0042085911429582">
<p>Susan Fairchild is the Director of Data and Applied Research at New Visions for Public Schools and a fellow at the Institute of Education and Social Policy at New York University.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio2-0042085911429582">
<p>Robert Tobias a clinical professor of Teaching and Learning at New York University’s Steinhardt School, Director of the Center for Research on Teaching and Learning, and the former Executive Director of Assessment and Accountability for the New York City Department of Education.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio3-0042085911429582">
<p>Sean Corcoran is an associate professor of educational economics at New York University’s Steinhardt School, an affiliated faculty of the Wagner Graduate School of Public Service, and a research fellow at the Institute of Education and Social Policy.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio4-0042085911429582">
<p>Maja Djukic is an assistant professor at the NYU College of Nursing, where she was a Mary Clark Rockefeller Doctoral Fellow.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio5-0042085911429582">
<p>Christine Kovner is a Professor at New York University’s College of Nursing and a Senior Fellow at the Hartford Institute for Geriatric Nursing also at the College of Nursing. She is a Nurse Attending at the NYU Langone Medical Center.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio6-0042085911429582">
<p>Pedro Noguera is the Peter L. Agnew Professor of Education at New York University. He holds faculty appointments in the departments of Teaching and Learning and Humanities and Social Sciences at the Steinhardt School of Culture, Education and Development, as well as in the Department of Sociology at New York University. Dr. Noguera is also the Executive Director of the Metropolitan Center for Urban Education and the co-Director of the Institute for the Study of Globalization and Education in Metropolitan Settings (IGEMS).</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>170</fpage>
<lpage>197</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Data on the impact of student, teacher, and principal racial and gender composition in urban schools on teacher work outcomes are limited. This study, a secondary data analysis of White and Black urban public school teachers using data taken from the restricted use 2003-04 Schools and Staffing Survey (SASS), examines the effects of relational demography on teacher job satisfaction adjusting for other known determinants of job satisfaction. Relational demography is conceptualized as a set of racial and gender congruency items between teachers and principals, teachers and teachers, and teachers and students. The results of the study show that some components of relational demography directly affect teacher job satisfaction, over and above the effects of work-related attitudes.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>diversity</kwd>
<kwd>principals</kwd>
<kwd>urban education</kwd>
<kwd>White teachers</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Data on professional teacher turnover show that between the 2003-04 and 2004-05 school years, 8.4% of the teacher workforce left the teaching profession and that this rate has been slowly rising for the past two decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0042085911429582">Luekens, Lyter, Fox, &amp; Chandler, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0042085911429582">Marvel, Lyter, Peltola, Strizek, &amp; Morton, 2007</xref>). Teacher turnover, particularly in urban schools where it is most pronounced, is of concern because of its negative effects on organizational functioning and quality of teachers (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0042085911429582">Hanson, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0042085911429582">Ingersoll, 2001a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0042085911429582">2001b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0042085911429582">Kirby, Berends, &amp; Naftel, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0042085911429582">Lankford, Loeb, &amp; Wyckoff, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0042085911429582">Loeb, Darling-Hammond, &amp; Luczak, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Organizational teacher turnover is also of concern and for related reasons. Between the 2003-2004 and 2004-2005 school years, 8% of the teacher workforce transferred to another school (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0042085911429582">Marvel et al., 2007</xref>), with a disproportionate number of these moving <italic>from</italic> high minority, urban school districts and not into them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0042085911429582">Ingersoll, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0042085911429582">Strizek, Pittsonberger, Riordan, Lyter, &amp; Orlofsky, 2006</xref>). Thus, of those teachers most likely to leave the profession or pursue employment in another district, the greater proportion will be taken from America’s most challenged, urban school districts; this will happen even as those districts are experiencing a surge in the number of students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0042085911429582">KewalRamani, Gilbertson, Fox, &amp; Provasnik, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>In addition to the perennial turnover of novice White teachers from urban school districts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0042085911429582">Clotfelter, Ladd, Vigdor, &amp; Wheeler, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0042085911429582">Kirby et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0042085911429582">Lankford et al., 2002</xref>), an experienced cohort of minority teachers is retiring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0042085911429582">Luekens et al., 2004</xref>). This matters for four reasons: (a) minority teachers are more likely to teach in high-poverty, urban schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0042085911429582">Kirby et al., 1999</xref>); (b) minority teachers are more likely to persist in classroom teaching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0042085911429582">Kirby et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0042085911429582">Murnane &amp; Olsen, 1989</xref>); (c) minority student enrollments are increasing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0042085911429582">KewalRamani et al., 2007</xref>); and (d) a growing body of evidence suggests minority teachers have a positive influence on minority learning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0042085911429582">Dee, 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0042085911429582">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0042085911429582">Ferguson, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0042085911429582">Hanushek, Kain, &amp; Rivkin, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0042085911429582">Hudson &amp; Holmes, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0042085911429582">Irvine, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0042085911429582">King, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0042085911429582">Quiocho &amp; Rios, 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Two important policy implications related to the shortfall of teachers in high-minority urban schools are (a) to increase the number of minority teachers within the teacher pipeline (increase supply) and (b) to identify factors that lead to turnover in the existing, predominately White, female teacher workforce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0042085911429582">Futrell, 1999</xref>). While the former approach—recruiting more minority teachers—may provide a longer term solution, immediate school staffing needs in high-minority urban schools necessitate an urgent reexamination of those factors thought to precipitate turnover, that is job satisfaction, within the urban teacher workforce.</p>
<p>Although there are many reasons that motivate teachers to leave a given school or to abandon the teaching profession, a primary factor in both instances is job dissatisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0042085911429582">Ingersoll, 2001a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0042085911429582">2001b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0042085911429582">Johnson, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0042085911429582">Marvel et al., 2007</xref>). Job satisfaction is a key mediating variable in all major models of voluntary turnover (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0042085911429582">Lee &amp; Mitchell, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0042085911429582">March &amp; Simon, 1958</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0042085911429582">Mobley, Griffeth, Hand, &amp; Meglino, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0042085911429582">Price, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0042085911429582">Steers &amp; Mowday, 1981</xref>). Research examining job satisfaction via models of voluntary turnover has primarily focused on the effect of economic factors (e.g., local and nonlocal job opportunities), work-related attitudes (e.g., autonomy, job stress, supervisor support), work attributes (e.g., pay, mandatory overtime), psychological factors (e.g., positive and negative affectivity), person demographics (e.g., age, gender), and workplace demographics (e.g., setting, size) on job satisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0042085911429582">Holtom, Mitchell, Lee, &amp; Eberly, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0042085911429582">Kovner, Brewer, Greene, &amp; Fairchild, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0042085911429582">Price, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0042085911429582">Steers &amp; Mowday, 1981</xref>).</p>
<p>To extend the knowledge of the factors that affect teacher job satisfaction, this study examined the direct effect of <italic>relational demography</italic>, the interaction between organization and person characteristics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0042085911429582">Pfeffer, 1983</xref>) on job satisfaction, adjusting for the effects of work attitudes, person demographics, and workplace demographics specified in a turnover model originally suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0042085911429582">Price (2001)</xref> and extended by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0042085911429582">Kovner et al. (2009)</xref>.</p>
<p>There are many racial and cultural interactions that manifest in diverse settings and are therefore frequently seen in urban, particularly high-minority, schools. These interactions (which potentially occur between teachers and principals, teachers and teachers, and teachers and students) are the inevitable result of bringing together individuals of diverse social, racial and economic backgrounds and are not to be regarded as negative phenomena per se. Nonetheless, such interactions may influence school environments and job satisfaction of educators. Based on the research in nonschool settings (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0042085911429582">Kanter, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0042085911429582">Kramer, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0042085911429582">Leonard &amp; Levine, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0042085911429582">Pelled, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0042085911429582">Riordan &amp; Shore, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0042085911429582">Sacco &amp; Schmitt, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0042085911429582">Sackett, DuBois, &amp; Noe, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0042085911429582">Zatzick, Elvira, &amp; Cohen, 2003</xref>), increasing diversity, ceteris paribus, inadvertently may decrease satisfaction with supervisor support because of demographic differences between teachers and principals, may increase job stress because of demographic differences between teachers and teachers, and may impair classroom communications and relationships because of demographic differences between teachers and students. The purpose of this study is to reexamine the effects of relational demography in school settings. Testing the direct effects of relational demography on job satisfaction allows further examination of the impact of diversity in urban schools that suffer from high teacher turnover.</p>
<sec id="section1-0042085911429582">
<title>Literature Review</title>
<p>Evidence is mixed regarding how person (teacher) demographics (e.g., age, gender, teaching experience) and workplace (school) demographics (e.g., percent minority enrollment, secondary or primary school) contribute to teacher job satisfaction. Gender is either not associated with job satisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0042085911429582">Klecker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042085911429582">Lee, Dedrick, &amp; Smith, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0042085911429582">Liu &amp; Ramsey, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0042085911429582">Mertler, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0042085911429582">Stockard &amp; Lehman, 2004</xref>) or women are found to be more satisfied with their jobs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0042085911429582">Bogler, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0042085911429582">Culver, Wolfe, &amp; Cross, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0042085911429582">Kearney, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0042085911429582">Ma &amp; MacMillan, 1999</xref>) or with teaching as a career (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0042085911429582">Renzulli, MacPherson, &amp; Beattie, 2007</xref>) than men. Younger teachers are more likely to be satisfied with their teaching jobs or teaching as a career than older teachers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0042085911429582">Culver et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0042085911429582">Mertler, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>) although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0042085911429582">Bogler (2001)</xref> found no significant association. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0042085911429582">Klecker (1997)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042085911429582">Lee et al. (1991)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0042085911429582">Bogler (2001)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0042085911429582">Culver et al. (1990)</xref> found that number of years teaching was not associated with job satisfaction, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0042085911429582">Renzulli et al. (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie and Baker (1997)</xref> found that it was negatively associated with job satisfaction and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0042085911429582">Liu and Ramsey (2008)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0042085911429582">Ma and MacMillan (1999)</xref> found that it was positively associated with job satisfaction. Teacher education was not associated with satisfaction with teaching as a career (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0042085911429582">Stockard &amp; Lehman, 2004</xref>) or facets of job satisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0042085911429582">Kearney, 2008</xref>). However, Culver et al. found that lower academic achievement was positively associated with job satisfaction and higher academic achievement was negatively associated with job satisfaction.</p>
<p>Teachers who teach in schools where students have higher socioeconomic backgrounds are found to be more satisfied than teachers who work in schools where students have lower socioeconomic backgrounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042085911429582">Lee et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0042085911429582">Stockard &amp; Lehman, 2004</xref>). Teachers who teach in schools with high-minority student enrollment were more likely to express lower levels of satisfaction with teaching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0042085911429582">Shann, 1998</xref>). Evidence generally supports the finding that teachers who work in elementary schools are more satisfied than teachers working in secondary or high school environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0042085911429582">Bogler, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0042085911429582">Kearney, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>). However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0042085911429582">Stockard and Lehman (2004)</xref> found that 1st-year teachers who taught in schools other than middle schools were more satisfied than those teaching in middle schools and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0042085911429582">Renzulli et al. (2007)</xref> found that high school teachers were more satisfied than either elementary or middle school teachers.</p>
<p>What is well established in the extant literature is a relationship between a number of work-related attitudes and teacher job satisfaction. Supervisor support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0042085911429582">Blase &amp; Blase, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0042085911429582">Bogler, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0042085911429582">Evans, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042085911429582">Lee et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0042085911429582">Ma &amp; MacMillan, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0042085911429582">Weiss, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0042085911429582">Youngs, 2007</xref>), procedural justice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0042085911429582">Imber, Neidt, &amp; Reyes, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0042085911429582">Rice &amp; Schneider, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0042085911429582">Rosenholtz, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0042085911429582">Shann, 1998</xref>), autonomy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0042085911429582">Hall, Pearson, &amp; Carroll, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0042085911429582">Ingersoll, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042085911429582">Lee et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0042085911429582">Renzulli et al., 2007</xref>), job stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0042085911429582">Hounshell &amp; Griffin, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0042085911429582">Ingersoll, 2001a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0042085911429582">2001b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0042085911429582">Johnson &amp; Birkeland, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042085911429582">Lee et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0042085911429582">Liu &amp; Ramsey, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0042085911429582">Pagano, Weiner, &amp; Rand, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>), and teacher–student relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0042085911429582">Brunetti, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0042085911429582">Hounshell &amp; Griffin, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0042085911429582">Ingersoll, 2001a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0042085911429582">2001b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042085911429582">Lee et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0042085911429582">Newberry &amp; Davis, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0042085911429582">Shann, 1998</xref>) are associated with teacher job satisfaction.</p>
<p>What is less well understood is how the intersection of organizational and individual demographics influences teacher job satisfaction. To the extent that various distributions within an organization of age, race, gender, tenure, and educational attainment shape ensuing social interactions (and inform group processes that then influence individual attitudes), “demographic distributions have a theoretical and empirical reality” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0042085911429582">Pfeffer, 1983</xref>, p. 303) that is more than the aggregation of individual demographics. When the demographic distribution of an organization intersects with individual characteristics, a pattern of effects emerges that may differentially influence attitudes and performance at the individual level.</p>
<p>Few studies have examined relational demography as it relates to teacher job satisfaction. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0042085911429582">Mueller, Finley, Iverson, and Price (1999)</xref> collected teacher and school-level data from 838 teachers working in a large, urban school system in the United States. As hypothesized, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0042085911429582">Mueller et al. (1999)</xref> found that racial congruence (at 40% and 50%) mattered for White teachers. White teachers in White teacher–student schools had higher job satisfaction and organizational commitment than White teachers in schools where the White teachers and/or the White students comprised the minority. The racial composition of teachers and students had no effect on Black teachers’ job satisfaction or commitment to school.</p>
<p>Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0042085911429582">Renzulli et al. (2007)</xref> found that the racial congruence between teachers and students mattered in terms of teacher job satisfaction. Examining 31,848 White, Black, and Hispanic teachers in 1,948 public and charter schools from the 1999-2000 publicly available Schools and Staffing Survey (SASS) data set, they found that racial composition variables, demographic characteristics of the teacher, demographic characteristics of the school, and work-related attitudes were significantly associated with teacher satisfaction. They also found that being a Hispanic teacher with a majority of Asian students and Black teacher with a majority of Asian students was associated with teacher dissatisfaction. Being a Black teacher with a majority of White students was weakly associated with teacher dissatisfaction. However, when satisfaction was regressed only on the teacher–student racial congruence items, the negative effects of racial mismatch on satisfaction were more pronounced. White teachers matched with White students were found to be more satisfied than White teachers who were not matched with White students. Black teachers matched with Black students were found to be less satisfied than White teachers who were matched with White students.</p>
<p>Because of their diverse demographic compositions, urban schools may be particularly susceptible to relational demography effects. Indeed, a growing body of literature addresses teacher–student racial congruence on student outcomes (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0042085911429582">Alexander, Entwisle, &amp; Thompson, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0042085911429582">Dee, 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0042085911429582">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0042085911429582">Ehrenberg, Goldhaber, &amp; Brewer, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0042085911429582">Pigott &amp; Cowen, 2000</xref>). However, relatively little literature exists regarding the demographic congruence between teachers and students, teachers and teachers, and teachers and principals on <italic>teacher outcomes</italic> such as a job satisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0042085911429582">Mueller et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0042085911429582">Renzulli et al., 2007</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0042085911429582">
<title>Purpose Statement and Hypotheses</title>
<p>The specific aim of this study is to examine the direct effects of relational demography on job satisfaction adjusting for the known determinants of job satisfaction, including work-related attitudes specified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0042085911429582">Price (2001)</xref> and workplace demographics and person demographic specified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0042085911429582">Kovner et al. (2009)</xref>. Determinants of job satisfaction are examined using two groups, namely, White and Black teachers.</p>
<sec id="section3-0042085911429582">
<title>Hypotheses</title>
<p>The main effects model with job satisfaction as the dependent variable assumes a direct effect of workplace demographics (principal age, principal race, principal gender, principal tenure, percentage of minority student enrollments, percentage of minority teachers in school, percentage of students on free lunch, school level), teacher demographics (age, race, gender, education, tenure at school, and teaching experience), teacher work-related attitudes (supervisor support, procedural justice, autonomy, job stress, and teacher–student relationships), and relational demography (teacher–principal racial congruence, teacher–principal gender congruence, teacher–student racial congruence, teacher–teacher racial congruence) on teacher job satisfaction.</p>
<list id="list1-0042085911429582" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1</italic>: Teacher job satisfaction is related to workplace demographics.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 2</italic>: Teacher job satisfaction is related to person (teacher) demographics.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 3</italic>: Teacher job satisfaction is related to teacher work-related attitudes.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 4</italic>: Teacher job satisfaction is related to relational demography.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0042085911429582" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>This study is a secondary data analysis of a subset of teachers drawn from the private restricted use SASS Public School Teacher Questionnaire administered by the National Center for Educational Statistics (NCES) in 2003-04 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0042085911429582">Strizek et al., 2006</xref>). The SASS uses a cross-sectional study design that collects extensive data on public and private elementary and secondary schools in the United States. Since its first administration in 1987, SASS has been conducted in 5 subsequent school years: 1990-91, 1993-94, 1999-2000, 2003-04, and 2007-08. SASS obtains data on the characteristics of teachers, principals, and other school conditions such as workplace climate, school safety and discipline, teacher hiring practices, computer usage and resources, and professional development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0042085911429582">Tourkin et al., 2007</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section5-0042085911429582">
<title>Sample</title>
<p>Teachers who responded to the SASS Public School Teacher Questionnaire administered by the NCES in 2003-04 were the unit of analysis for this study. The sample was restricted to full-time, public school teachers who identified as White, non-Hispanic or Black, non-Hispanic working in an urban setting. These 8,665 teachers represent 1,992 schools and each of the 1,992 schools contributed between 1 and 15 teachers to the sample. Approximately, 49% (<italic>n</italic> = 971) of the schools in this sample contributed up to 3 teachers to this sample.</p>
<p>In addition, items from the SASS 2003-04 Principal Questionnaire (principal race, principal gender, principal age, years principal worked at current school, total years teaching experience) and the SASS 2003-04 Public School Questionnaire (total number of students at school, total number of White students at school, total number of Black students at school, total number of teachers at school, total number of White teachers at school, and total number of Black teachers at school) were merged into the SASS Public School Teacher analytic database. Principal data were missing for 547 teachers in this sample. School data were missing for 596 teachers in this sample, and 242 cases were missing both school and principal data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0042085911429582">
<title>Instrumentation</title>
<p>The NCES’s SASS: Public Teacher Questionnaire from the 2003-04 school year is the primary data source for this study. The survey contained 83 questions and 420 items, and it was organized into 11 sections: (a) General Information, (b) Class Organization, (c) Educational Background, (d) Certification and Training, (e) Professional Development, (f) Resources and Assessments of Students, (g) Working Conditions, (h) Decision Making, (i) Teacher Attitudes and School Climate, (j) General Employment Information, and (k) Contact Information.</p>
<p>The SASS Public Teacher Questionnaire is composed of items as opposed to validated scales. Thirty-four items from the two sections of the SASS survey instrument (a) Decision Making and (b) Teacher Attitudes and School Climate were submitted to a principal axis factoring for the total sample (<italic>n</italic> = 8,665) to create the scales used in this study. Based on the scree plot, six factors (27 items) accounting for 52% of the variance were retained and rotated using varimax rotation to achieve simple structure. The six factors with eigenvalues greater than 1.0 were identified for this study and included five work-related attitudes (supervisor support, procedural justice, autonomy, job stress, teacher–student relationships), and the dependent variable (job satisfaction; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0042085911429582">Table 1</xref>). Factor loadings below 0.5 on a given factor were excluded from that factor. Scale reliability was determined using Cronbach’s alpha. Alpha coefficients ranged from .87 to .71 for this sample.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0042085911429582" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Work-Related Attitudes and Job Satisfaction Scales’ Items</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0042085911429582" xlink:href="10.1177_0042085911429582-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="center"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Scale</th>
<th align="center">Item</th>
<th align="center">Brief item description</th>
<th align="center">Item range</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Supervisor Support</td>
<td>T0330</td>
<td>The principal lets staff members know what is expected of them.</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0331</td>
<td>The school administration’s behavior toward the staff is supportive and encouraging.</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0337</td>
<td>My principal enforces school rules for student conduct and backs me up when I need it.</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0340</td>
<td>The principal knows what kind of school he or she wants and has communicated it to the staff.</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0342</td>
<td>In this school, staff members are recognized for a job well done.</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Procedural Justice</td>
<td>T0311</td>
<td>How much actual influence do you think teachers have over school policy at this school setting performance standards for students at this school?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0312</td>
<td>How much actual influence do you think teachers have over school policy at this school regarding establishing curriculum?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0313</td>
<td>How much actual influence do you think teachers have over school policy at this school determining the content of in-service professional development programs?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0314</td>
<td>How much actual influence do you think teachers have over school policy at this school regarding evaluating teachers?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0315</td>
<td>How much actual influence do you think teachers have over school policy at this school regarding hiring new full-time teachers?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0316</td>
<td>How much actual influence do you think teachers have over school policy at this school regarding setting discipline policy?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0317</td>
<td>How much actual influence do you think teachers have over school policy at this school regarding deciding how the school budget will be spent?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Autonomy</td>
<td>T0319</td>
<td>How much control do you think you have in your classroom at this school regarding selecting content, topics, and skills to be taught?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0320</td>
<td>How much control do you think you have in your classroom at this school regarding teaching techniques?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0321</td>
<td>How much control do you think you have in your classroom at this school regarding evaluating and grading students?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0323</td>
<td>How much control do you think you have in your classroom at this school regarding determining the amount of homework to be assigned?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Job Stress</td>
<td>T0364</td>
<td>To what extent is student tardiness a problem at this school?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0365</td>
<td>To what extent is student absenteeism a problem at this school?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0371</td>
<td>To what extent is lack of parental involvement a problem at this school?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0373</td>
<td>To what extent is students come to school unprepared to learn a problem at this school?</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Teacher–Student Relations</td>
<td>T0360</td>
<td>How often does student verbal abuse of teachers occur with students at this school?</td>
<td>1-5 (0-4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0361</td>
<td>How often does widespread disorder in classrooms occur with students at this school?</td>
<td>1-5 (0-4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0362</td>
<td>How often do student acts of disrespect for teachers occur with students at this school?</td>
<td>1-5 (0-4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Job Satisfaction</td>
<td>T0375</td>
<td>The stress and disappointments involved in teaching at this school aren’t really worth it.</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0376</td>
<td>The teachers at this school like being here; I would describe us as a very satisfied group. (reverse coded)</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0377</td>
<td>I like the way things are run at this school. (reverse coded)</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>T0379</td>
<td>I think about transferring to another school.</td>
<td>1-4 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0042085911429582">
<title>Workplace Demographics</title>
<p>Dummy variables from the SASS Public Principal Questionnaire and SASS Public School Questionnaire were created for principal race (1 = <italic>Black</italic>), for principal gender (1 = <italic>male</italic>), for middle schools (1 = <italic>middle school</italic>, 0 = <italic>all other</italic>), high schools (1 = <italic>high school</italic>, 0 = <italic>all other</italic>), and combined schools (1 = <italic>combined school</italic>, 0 = <italic>all other</italic>). Principal age is a continuous variable and represents the principal’s age in years. Amount of time working as a principal in the current school was dichotomized so that less than 5 years of experience working at the school was assigned a 1 and more than 5 years of experience working at the school was assigned a 0. The coding decision for tenure links the current study to a body of educational and occupational behavior literature. For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0042085911429582">Pfeffer (1983)</xref> used a 5-year cutoff when examining tenure as a measure of relational demography. Percentage of minority students enrolled at school, percentage of minority teachers at school, and percentage of students approved for the National School Lunch Program are continuous variables ranging from 0% to 100%.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0042085911429582">
<title>Teacher Demographics</title>
<p>Dummy variables from the SASS Public Teacher Questionnaire were created for teacher race (1 = <italic>Black</italic>), for teacher gender (1 = <italic>male</italic>), for new teacher (1 = <italic>new teacher</italic>), and for master’s degree (1 = <italic>obtained master’s</italic>). Amount of time working as a teacher in the current school (tenure) was dichotomized so that less than 5 years of experience working at the school was assigned a 1 and more than 5 years of experience working at the school was assigned a 0. The 5-year cutoff was used to be consistent with the coding for principal tenure. Age is a continuous variable and represents teacher’s age in years.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0042085911429582">
<title>Relational Demography</title>
<p>Relational demography is operationalized as racial and gender congruence between teachers and their principal, racial congruence between teachers and teachers, and racial congruence between teachers and students. A teacher and a principal are racially congruent if they share the same race. For instance, a White teacher and an Asian principal would not be racially congruent. A teacher and a principal are congruent with respect to gender if both share the same gender. Teacher–principal racial congruence was coded so that a 1 represented congruence and a 0 represented incongruence. Teacher–principal gender congruence was coded so that a 1 represented congruence and a 0 represented incongruence.</p>
<p>Teacher–teacher congruence was measured as the percentage of teachers within a school who shared the same race as the teacher. If the teacher was Black and the percentage of Black teachers teaching at that school was 20%, the measure for teacher–teacher congruence was 20%. Teacher–teacher congruence was then dichotomized into an indicator variable such that a 1 represents teacher–teacher congruence that is equal to or greater than 70% and a 0 represents congruence less than 70%. A 70% cutoff has theoretical underpinnings. When 70% of a group shares a single demographic characteristic (such as race), the group can then be categorized as “tilted” and individuals within the group who share this characteristic can be characterized as being part of a “majority” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0042085911429582">Kanter, 1977</xref>). Relational demography suggests that proportions differentially influence behaviors. Thus, members of a majority group are thought to have different attitudes than individuals who are not part of the majority.</p>
<p>Teacher–student congruence was measured as the percentage of students within a school who shared the same race as the teacher. If the teacher was Black and the percentage of Black students enrolled at the school was 20%, the measure for teacher–student congruence was 20%. Teacher–student congruence was then dichotomized into an indicator variable such that a 1 represented teacher–student congruence greater than 70% and a 0 represented congruence less than 70%.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0042085911429582">
<title>Analysis</title>
<p>Ordinary least squares (OLS) modeling techniques were used with teacher job satisfaction as the dependent variable. A sequential model was specified such that teacher job satisfaction was regressed on four functional sets of predictor variables. The first block of the regression model represents workplace demographics. The second block entered into the regression model was the set of variables representing teacher demographics. The third block of the regression model represents teacher work–related attitudes. The fourth block entered into the regression model was the set of variables representing relational demography.</p>
<list id="list2-0042085911429582" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Set A = Workplace Demographics</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Set B = Teacher Demographics</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Set C = Teacher Work-Related Attitudes</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Set D = Relational Demography</p></list-item></list>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0042085911429582" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section12-0042085911429582">
<title>Descriptive Statistics</title>
<sec id="section13-0042085911429582">
<title>Teacher demographics</title>
<p>In the urban teacher sample, 85% (<italic>n =</italic> 7,366) were White and 68% (<italic>n =</italic> 5,891) were female and, on average, were aged 43.4 years (<italic>SD</italic> = 11.26). Almost 99% (<italic>n =</italic> 8,539) of the sample had earned a bachelor’s degree, and of those who did, 49% (<italic>n =</italic> 4,251) earned a master’s degree. Approximately 84% (<italic>n =</italic> 7,235) of the total sample had 3 years or more teaching experience, and 56% (<italic>n =</italic> 4,849) had worked in their current school for 5 years or more. The main teaching assignment for 21.4% (<italic>n =</italic> 1,857) of the total sample was elementary. Almost 14% (<italic>n =</italic> 1,195) taught special education, 12.8% (<italic>n =</italic> 1,108) taught English/language arts, 9.5% (<italic>n =</italic> 824) taught math, 9.1% (<italic>n =</italic> 790) taught natural science, 8.6% (<italic>n =</italic> 743) taught social science, and 24.8% (<italic>n =</italic> 2,148) taught in some other field.</p>
<p>The percentage of female teachers in urban schools was higher for Black teachers (72.3%) than White teachers (67.2%). Also, a higher percentage of Black teachers had been working in the current school for less than 5 years (51.7%) and had been teaching for 3 years or less (22.6%) than White teachers (42.7%, 15.4%). There were no notable differences between White and Black teachers on age, education, or general field of main assignment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0042085911429582">
<title>Workplace demographics</title>
<p>Approximately 73% (<italic>n =</italic> 5,885) of the teachers in the sample worked in school in which the principal was White and 44.1% (<italic>n =</italic> 3,581) were female and, on average, were aged 50.7 years (<italic>SD</italic> = 7.42). Approximately 90% (<italic>n =</italic> 7,284) of the total teacher sample worked in schools in which the principal had 5 years or more teaching experience, and about 36% (<italic>n =</italic> 2,889) of the sample worked in a school where the principal had been employed in his or her current school for 5 years or more.</p>
<p>The average percentage of minority student enrollment at the schools where teachers in this sample worked was 53.1 (<italic>SD</italic> = 33.17). The average percentage of Black student enrollment was 27.6 (<italic>SD</italic> = 31.00), and the average percentage of White student enrollment was 50.3 (<italic>SD</italic> = 31.76). The average percentage of minority teachers employed at the schools where the teachers worked was 21.5 (<italic>SD</italic> = 25.00). The average percentage of Black teachers employed in the schools was 14.7 (<italic>SD</italic> = 23.49) and the average percentage of White teachers employed was 78.7 (<italic>SD</italic> = 25.88). The average percentage of enrolled students approved for the National School Lunch Program at schools where the teachers worked was 45.6 (<italic>SD</italic> = 27.57). A little more than 50% (<italic>n =</italic> 4,418) of the teachers in the sample taught in a high school, 28.4% (<italic>n =</italic> 2,465) in an elementary school, 13.9% (<italic>n =</italic> 1,205) in a middle school, and 6.7% (<italic>n =</italic> 577) in a combined school.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0042085911429582">
<title>Relational Demography</title>
<sec id="section16-0042085911429582">
<title>Teacher–principal racial and gender congruence</title>
<p>In this sample, White teachers were more racially congruent with their principals (79.2%, <italic>n</italic> = 5,500) than were the Black teachers (60.8%, <italic>n</italic> = 713). Gender congruence between teachers and principals for both White teachers and Black teachers was close to 50% (51.7%, <italic>n</italic> = 3,589; 54.6%, <italic>n</italic> = 640; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0042085911429582">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0042085911429582" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Relational Demography Congruence Items</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0042085911429582" xlink:href="10.1177_0042085911429582-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">White teachers (<italic>n</italic> = 7,366)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Black teachers (<italic>n</italic> = 1,299)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="center">%</th>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="center">%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Teacher–principal racial congruence<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0042085911429582">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Congruent</td>
<td>5,500</td>
<td>79.2</td>
<td>713</td>
<td>60.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Not congruent</td>
<td>1,446</td>
<td>20.8</td>
<td>787</td>
<td>39.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Teacher–principal gender congruence<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0042085911429582">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Congruent</td>
<td>3,589</td>
<td>51.7</td>
<td>640</td>
<td>54.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Not congruent</td>
<td>3,357</td>
<td>48.3</td>
<td>532</td>
<td>45.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Teacher–teacher racial congruence<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0042085911429582">b</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>M</italic></td>
<td>84.8</td>
<td/>
<td>50.9</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>SD</italic></td>
<td>19.58</td>
<td/>
<td>30.37</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Min</td>
<td>0</td>
<td/>
<td>0</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Max</td>
<td>100</td>
<td/>
<td>100</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Teacher–student racial congruence<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0042085911429582">b</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>M</italic></td>
<td>55.9</td>
<td/>
<td>67.8</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>SD</italic></td>
<td>29.47</td>
<td/>
<td>32.56</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Min</td>
<td>0</td>
<td/>
<td>0</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Max</td>
<td>100</td>
<td/>
<td>100</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0042085911429582">
<label>a</label>
<p>Data on principals were missing for 547 cases.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0042085911429582">
<label>b</label>
<p>Data on schools were missing for 596 cases.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0042085911429582">
<title>Teacher–teacher racial congruence</title>
<p>White teachers in the sample were more likely to be racially congruent with the teachers at their schools than Black teachers. The average percentage of White teachers employed at the school for the White teacher sample was 84.8% (<italic>SD</italic> = 19.58). The average percentage of Black teachers employed at the school for the Black teacher sample was 50.9% (<italic>SD</italic> = 30.37; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0042085911429582">Table 2</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0042085911429582">
<title>Teacher–student racial congruence</title>
<p>Black teachers in the sample were more likely to be racially congruent with the students at their schools than White teachers. The average percentage of Black students enrolled at the school for the Black teachers in this sample was 67.8% (<italic>SD</italic> = 32.56). The average percentage of White students enrolled at the school for the White teacher sample was 55.9% (<italic>SD</italic> = 29.47; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0042085911429582">Table 2</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0042085911429582">
<title>Correlations</title>
<p>Statistically significant correlations between the variables in this study were observed; however, because of the large sample size, effect sizes were used as the criterion for magnitude. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0042085911429582">Cohen (1988)</xref> operationally defines effect sizes for correlation coefficients as small, <italic>r</italic> = .10, medium, <italic>r</italic> = .30, and large, <italic>r</italic> = .50. The pairs of variables that had a large effect size include (a) percentage of minority teachers at the school and principal race (<italic>r</italic> = .54), (b) percentage of minority teachers at the school and percentage of minority student enrollment (<italic>r</italic> = .67), (c) percentage of minority student enrollment and percentage of students eligible for the National School Lunch Program (<italic>r</italic> = .59), (d) high schools and middle schools (<italic>r</italic> = −.55), (e) teacher race and percentage of minority teachers at the school (<italic>r</italic> = .54), (f) teacher job satisfaction and teacher perceptions of supervisor support (<italic>r</italic> = .60), and (g) teacher perceptions of job stress and teacher perceptions of teacher–student relationships (<italic>r</italic> = .59).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0042085911429582">
<title>Ordinary Least Squares Regression</title>
<p>Generalized estimating equations (GEE) were run to adjust for nonindependence of observations due to the clustered nature of the data—multiple teachers within schools. An exchangeable covariance structure was specified. The off-diagonal correlation was 0.063 which is a weak correlation and suggests that the school effect is nominal. Furthermore, when compared with results from the regression analysis, GEE estimates were essentially the same. Thus, results from the regression analysis are reported here.</p>
<p>Based on the <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> analysis, Model 4 explains that greatest amount of variance (47.4%) in job satisfaction (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0042085911429582">Table 3</xref>). The addition of the set of relational demography variables to the model explain a small (0.1%) but significant amount of variance adjusting for the effects of workplace demographics, teacher demographics, and teacher work–related attitudes. Unstandardized coefficients from Model 4 are reported here (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0042085911429582">Table 4</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0042085911429582" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Summary of Change in Explained Variance in Teacher Job Satisfaction Regression Models (<italic>N</italic> = 8,665)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0042085911429582" xlink:href="10.1177_0042085911429582-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Model</th>
<th align="center"><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></th>
<th align="center"><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> change</th>
<th align="center"><italic>F</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>F</italic> change</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1. Workplace demographics</td>
<td>.054</td>
<td>.053</td>
<td>38.256</td>
<td>38.256</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2. Workplace demographics</td>
<td>.066</td>
<td>.012</td>
<td>29.581</td>
<td>14.359</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Teacher demographics</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3. Workplace demographics</td>
<td>.473</td>
<td>.407</td>
<td>285.076</td>
<td>1029.769</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Teacher demographics</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Work-related attitudes</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4. Workplace demographics</td>
<td>.474</td>
<td>.001</td>
<td>240.731</td>
<td>4.648</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Teacher demographics</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Work-related attitudes</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Relational demography</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0042085911429582">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 (refers to <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> change).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table4-0042085911429582" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Summary of Sequential Regression Analysis for Variables Predicting Teacher Satisfaction (<italic>N</italic> = 8,665)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0042085911429582" xlink:href="10.1177_0042085911429582-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Model 1</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Model 2</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Model 3</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Model 4</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>9.482</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>8.634</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>7.855</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>7.717</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13">Step 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Principal age</td>
<td>−.004</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td/>
<td>−.005</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td/>
<td>.003</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td/>
<td>.003</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Principal race—non-Black ref group</td>
<td>−.318</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">**</xref></td>
<td>−.382</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>−.112</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td/>
<td>−.085</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Principal gender—female ref group</td>
<td>.163</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">*</xref></td>
<td>.151</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">*</xref></td>
<td>.187</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>.124</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Principal tenure—5+ years in school ref group</td>
<td>−.179</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">**</xref></td>
<td>−.183</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">**</xref></td>
<td>−.014</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td/>
<td>−.019</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Middle schools only</td>
<td>−.396</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>−.378</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>.042</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td/>
<td>.032</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> High schools only</td>
<td>−.418</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>−.399</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>.294</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>.294</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Combined schools only</td>
<td>.824</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">**</xref></td>
<td>.730</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">*</xref></td>
<td>.344</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td/>
<td>.332</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> % minority student enrollment</td>
<td>−.007</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>−.007</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>−.002</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td/>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> % minority teachers</td>
<td>−.007</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>−.011</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>−.006</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>−.007</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> % students for the National School Lunch Program</td>
<td>−.005</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>−.005</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>.001</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td/>
<td>.001</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13">Step 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Teacher age</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.021</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>.010</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>.010</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Teacher race—White ref group</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.548</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>−.055</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td/>
<td>−.093</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Teacher gender—female ref group</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.129</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td/>
<td>−.172</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">**</xref></td>
<td>−.140</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Teacher education—non-MA ref group</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.056</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td/>
<td>−.041</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td/>
<td>−.038</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> New teacher—3+ years teaching ref group</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.003</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td/>
<td>−.011</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td/>
<td>−.012</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Teacher tenure—5+ years in school ref group</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.197</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">**</xref></td>
<td>−.087</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td/>
<td>−.079</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13">Step 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Supervisor support</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.352</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>.353</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Job stress</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.102</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>−.101</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Procedural justice</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.056</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>.055</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Autonomy</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.072</td>
<td>.012</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>.072</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Teacher–student relationships</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.132</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
<td>−.132</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13">Step 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> T–P racial congruence</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.072</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> T–P gender congruence</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.148</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> T–T racial congruence</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.046</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> T–S racial congruence</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.140</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0042085911429582">*</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0042085911429582">
<p>Note: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = .054 for Step 1 (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001); Δ<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = .012 (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) for Step 2; Δ<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = .407 (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) for Step 3; Δ<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = .001 (<italic>p</italic> = .001) for Step 4.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0042085911429582">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section21-0042085911429582">
<title>Hypothesis 1a: Teacher job satisfaction is related to workplace demographics</title>
<p>Adjusting for all other variables in the model, working for a male principal was associated with a .124-unit increase in teacher job satisfaction (<italic>t</italic> = 2.424, <italic>p</italic> = .015) and working in a high school was associated with a .294-unit increase in teacher job satisfaction (<italic>t</italic> = 4.504, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). A 10% increase in minority teachers employed at the school was associated with a .07-unit decrease in teacher job satisfaction (<italic>t</italic> = −4.256, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) after adjusting the other variables in the model (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0042085911429582">Table 4</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0042085911429582">
<title>Hypothesis 1b: Teacher job satisfaction is related to teacher demographics</title>
<p>Teacher age was associated with a .010-unit increase (<italic>t</italic> = 4.431, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) in teacher job satisfaction and being male was associated with a .140-unit decrease (<italic>t</italic> = −2.713, <italic>p</italic> = .007) in teacher job satisfaction after accounting for all other variables in the model (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0042085911429582">Table 4</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0042085911429582">
<title>Hypothesis 1c: Teacher job satisfaction is related to teacher work–related attitudes</title>
<p>Supervisor support was associated with a .353-unit increase in teacher job satisfaction (<italic>t</italic> = 45.373, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001); job stress was associated with a .101-unit decrease (<italic>t</italic> = −9.833, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) in teacher job satisfaction; procedural justice was associated with a .055-unit increase (<italic>t</italic> = 9.277, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) in teacher job satisfaction; autonomy was associated with a .072-unit increase (<italic>t</italic> = 6.151, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) in teacher job satisfaction; and poor teacher–student relationships was associated with a .132-unit decrease (<italic>t</italic> = −15.787, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) in teacher job satisfaction after adjusting for all other variables in the model (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0042085911429582">Table 4</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0042085911429582">
<title>Hypothesis 1d: Teacher job satisfaction is related to relational demography</title>
<p>The congruence between teacher–principal gender and teacher–student race had a direct effect on teacher job satisfaction. Teacher–principal gender congruence was associated with a .148-unit decrease (<italic>t</italic> = −2.990, <italic>p</italic> = .003) in teacher job satisfaction and teacher–student racial congruence was associated with a .140-unit increase (<italic>t</italic> = 2.253, <italic>p</italic> = .024) in teacher job satisfaction after adjusting for all variables in the model (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0042085911429582">Table 4</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-0042085911429582" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Findings from this study are similar to those of other studies that found that teachers’ work-related attitudes explain a greater amount of the variance related to job satisfaction than demographics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042085911429582">Lee et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0042085911429582">Stockard &amp; Lehman, 2004</xref>). The results also support previous findings that supervisor support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042085911429582">Lee et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0042085911429582">Liu &amp; Ramsey, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0042085911429582">Stockard &amp; Lehman, 2004</xref>), autonomy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042085911429582">Lee et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0042085911429582">Renzulli et al., 2007</xref>), and procedural justice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0042085911429582">Imber et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0042085911429582">Rice &amp; Schneider, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0042085911429582">Rosenholtz, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0042085911429582">Shann, 1998</xref>) are positively associated with job satisfaction. Experiences in the classroom are also linked to teacher job satisfaction. High job stress and poor teacher–student relationships were both associated with teacher dissatisfaction. These findings are similar to other studies that identify student discipline problems and lack of student motivation as a source of dissatisfaction for teachers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0042085911429582">Ingersoll, 2001a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0042085911429582">2001b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0042085911429582">Johnson &amp; Birkeland, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042085911429582">Lee et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0042085911429582">Liu &amp; Ramsey, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>).</p>
<p>Findings from this study are consistent with other findings that demonstrate male teachers are more dissatisfied than female teachers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0042085911429582">Bogler, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0042085911429582">Culver et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0042085911429582">Kearney, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0042085911429582">Ma &amp; MacMillan, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085911429582">Perie &amp; Baker, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0042085911429582">Renzulli et al., 2007</xref>). Teachers in this sample are more satisfied working in high schools—a finding supported by the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0042085911429582">Renzulli et al. (2007)</xref>.</p>
<p>Although the set of relational demography variables accounted for a small amount of the overall variance in the regression model after adjusting for teacher demographics, workplace demographics, and work-related attitudes, its direct effect on job satisfaction was significant. Teacher–student racial congruence and teacher–principal gender congruence influence teacher job satisfaction. Teacher–student racial congruence findings from this study are mixed in terms of their consistency with those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0042085911429582">Mueller et al. (1999)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0042085911429582">Renzulli et al. (2007)</xref>. Different cutoffs were implemented in each of the three studies on relational demography and teacher job satisfaction. For example, Muller et al. categorized a school as “racially matched” when at least 40% of the teachers and students were of the same race. They found similar findings at 50% but no significant findings at 60%. Renzulli et al. defined a school as “racially homogeneous” at 60%. This study defined a school as “racially homogeneous” at 70% and used <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0042085911429582">Kanter’s (1977)</xref> work with women as the theoretical rational for selecting the cutoff.</p>
<p>Teacher–student racial congruence is positively associated with job satisfaction. When the racial composition of students is equal to or exceeds 70% of the entire student population (what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0042085911429582">Kanter, 1977</xref>, refers to as a <italic>majority</italic>), and the teacher shares the same race with the majority of students at the school, this racial congruency was positively associated with job satisfaction. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0042085911429582">Mueller et al. (1999)</xref> found this same pattern at 40% and 50%, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0042085911429582">Renzulli et al. (2007)</xref> found this pattern at 60%.</p>
<p>Findings from this study suggest that the gender congruence between teachers and principals should be further examined. Gender <italic>incongruence</italic> (female teacher/male principal; male teacher/female principal) has a positive effect on job satisfaction for teachers compared with gender congruence (female teacher/female principal; male teacher/male principal)—and the negative effect of teacher–principal gender congruence is more pronounced for female teachers and female principals. Deeper understanding of the female teacher/female principal relationship is particularly germane, not only because the principalship is becoming a more feminized profession (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0042085911429582">Mertz &amp; McNeely, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0042085911429582">U.S. Department of Education, National Center for Education Statistics, 2007</xref>) but also because of the well-established relationship between supervisor support and job satisfaction. The effects of relational demography, if not addressed, may negatively interact with supervisor support. The principal, often at the center of successful school initiatives, can create opportunities within the school for professional development and can help facilitate a collaborative environment for teachers. To the extent that principals are more aware of the potential negative effects of relational demography, they can better navigate staff through conflict thereby reaching the known benefits of diversity.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the negative relationship between teacher–principal gender congruence on job satisfaction may support the argument that female principals are held to different standards than male principals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0042085911429582">Mertz &amp; McNeely, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0042085911429582">Pollard, 1997</xref>). Though, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0042085911429582">Addi-Raccah (2006)</xref> suggests, female principals who work in schools where they have diminished social power may have fewer resources at their disposal to extend to teachers.</p>
<sec id="section26-0042085911429582">
<title>Implications</title>
<p>Relational demography highlights the unique demographic makeup inherent to all organizations and has implications for increasing the effectiveness of programs and interventions. Understanding the effects of relational demography has the potential to improve teacher job satisfaction by helping to locate conflict. That is, relational demography helps to identify sources of conflict and tension within and between groups and brings into focus misunderstandings that are rooted in social or cultural differences.</p>
<p>Thus, mapping the demographic terrain of organizations has important implications for the manner in which interventions are implemented at schools. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0042085911429582">Glasgow, Lichtenstein, and Marcus (2003)</xref> discuss the differences between efficacy and effectiveness trials and note the gap between research and practice. They suggest that generalization is compromised in efficacy studies because they are designed around a “homogeneous, highly motivated sample” and exclude those with complicating factors (p. 1262). Thus, the effectiveness of programs should be reexamined across schools with varying demographic makeup.</p>
<p>The findings from this study also point to the continued and urgent need to rethink teacher education programs. Programs such as the Urban Teacher Residency (UTR) movement are emerging as unique, innovative teacher education programs designed to bridge the gap between academic preparation and on-the-ground realities of teaching in urban schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0042085911429582">Berry, Montgomery, &amp; Snyder, 2008</xref>). UTRs differ from other alternative pathways to certification; in many respects, the relational demography findings surfaced in this study are inherently addressed in UTR programs. UTRs fuse education theory and classroom practice over the course of 14 months. Residents learn alongside an experienced mentor-teacher and receive ongoing support for multiple years once they become teachers of record. Candidates are prepared in cohorts to facilitate learning communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0042085911429582">Berry et al., 2008</xref>). Communities of practice and deep mentor–resident relationships provide different levels of support for new teachers and help root them more firmly in urban schools. Negative effects of relational demography may have less relevance for those teachers who are well trained in urban schools to begin with and who have access to a network of supportive colleagues.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-0042085911429582">
<title>Study Limitations</title>
<p>This study has certain limitations. First, the data examined in this study were cross-sectional. Cross-sectional data are measured at one point in time and offer a partial representation of the phenomenon under consideration. A cross-sectional design does not capture the phenomenon as it unfolds. The advantage of a longitudinal or panel design, on the other hand, affords greater perspective—illustrating how the effects of relational demography expand or diminish as the work environment changes. It may also be the case that the effects of relational demography are less relevant at different points in a teacher’s career. Furthermore, teachers whose job satisfaction may have been strongly and negatively influenced by relational demography may have left the school or the field of teaching prior to the administration of the study. Teachers who fall within this category may potentially be underrepresented in a cross-sectional study design.</p>
<p>Second, only the structural determinants, the workplace demographic variables in this study, of job satisfaction model suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0042085911429582">Price (2001)</xref> were tested. It is possible that relational demography will affect the psychological and economic components of the model that were not tested here. Inclusion of these determinants may influence the association between relational demography and job satisfaction.</p>
<p>Finally, demography, itself, is a blunt instrument used to make comparisons within and across groups based on visible and identifiable characteristics. Although relational demography is a slightly more subtle tool, it too lacks precision. In this study, the construction of a set of congruency items represents relational demography. Racial congruence among teachers and teachers, teachers and students, and teachers and principals and gender congruence between teachers and principals each have different social and cultural weight. Relational demography does not assign different weight to gender or race—though, arguably, different contexts would afford greater importance to one over the other. Rather, relational demography serves as a marker that locates and flags potential conflict. In this respect, relational demography is a unique tool that may help guide the implementation of educational interventions and programs. Future studies should continue to examine the relationship between female teachers and female principals and how the context of the school may influence female principals’ responsiveness to teachers. Future studies should also examine relational demography with more precise measures of relational demography.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>The authors would like to acknowledge Sharon Weinberg and Patrick Shrout for their thoughtful review and comments on earlier drafts of this article.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Addi-Raccah</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Assessing internal leadership positions at school: Testing the similarity-attraction approach regarding gender in three educational systems in Israel</article-title>. <source>Educational Administration Quarterly</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>291</fpage>-<lpage>323</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Entwisle</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>School performance, status relations, and the structure of sentiment: Bringing the teacher back</article-title> in. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>665</fpage>-<lpage>682</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blase</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blase</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>Empowering teachers: What successful principals do</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Corwin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bogler</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The influence of leadership style on teacher job satisfaction</article-title>. <source>Educational Administration Quarterly</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>662</fpage>-<lpage>683</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brunetti</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Resilience under fire: Perspectives on the work of experienced, inner city high school teachers in the United States</article-title>. <source>Teaching and Teacher Education</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>812</fpage>-<lpage>825</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Urban teacher residency models and institutes of higher education: Implications for teacher preparation</source>. <publisher-loc>Chapel Hill, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Center for Teaching Quality</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.teachingquality.org/legacy/UTR_IHE.pdf">http://www.teachingquality.org/legacy/UTR_IHE.pdf</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clotfelter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ladd</surname><given-names>H. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vigdor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>High poverty schools and the distribution of teachers and principals</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Terry Sanford Institute of Public Policy, Duke University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Culver</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Testing a model of teacher satisfaction for Blacks and Whites</article-title>. <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>323</fpage>-<lpage>349</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dee</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Teachers, race, and student achievement in a randomized experiment</article-title>. <source>Review of Economics and Statistics</source>, <volume>86</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>195</fpage>-<lpage>210</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dee</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A teacher like me: Does race, ethnicity, or gender matter?</article-title> <source>American Economic Review</source>, <volume>95</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>158</fpage>-<lpage>165</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ehrenberg</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldhaber</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Do teachers’ race, gender and ethnicity matter? Evidence from the national educational longitudinal study of 1988</article-title>. <source>Industrial and Labor Relations Review</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>547</fpage>-<lpage>561</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Understanding teacher morale &amp; job satisfaction</article-title>. <source>Teaching and Teacher Education</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>831</fpage>-<lpage>845</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Teachers’ perceptions and expectations and the Black–White test score gap</article-title>. <source>Urban Education</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>460</fpage>-<lpage>507</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Futrell</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Recruiting minority teachers</article-title>. <source>Educational Leadership</source>, <volume>56</volume>(<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>30</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glasgow</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lichtenstein</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Why don’t we see more translation of health promotion research to practice? Rethinking the efficacy-to-effectiveness transition</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source>, <volume>93</volume>, <fpage>1261</fpage>-<lpage>1267</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Teachers’ long-range teaching plans: A discriminant analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Research</source>, <volume>85</volume>, <fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>225</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Institutional theory and educational change</article-title>. <source>Educational Administration Quarterly</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>637</fpage>-<lpage>661</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hanushek</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kain</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rivkin</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Why public schools lose teachers</article-title>. <source>Journal of Human Resources</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>326</fpage>-<lpage>354</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holtom</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eberly</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Turnover and retention research: A glance at the past, a closer review of the present, and a venture into the future</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Annals</source>, <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>274</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hounshell</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Science teachers who left—A survey report</article-title>. <source>Science Education</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>433</fpage>-<lpage>443</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Missing teachers, impaired communities: The unanticipated consequences of <italic>Brown v. Board of Education</italic> on the African American teaching force at the precollegiate level</article-title>. <source>Journal of Negro Education</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>388</fpage>-<lpage>393</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Imber</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neidt</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Factors contributing to teacher satisfaction with participative decision making</article-title>. <source>Journal of Research &amp; Development in Education</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>216</fpage>-<lpage>224</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ingersoll</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001a</year>). <source>Teacher turnover, teacher shortages, and the organization of schools</source>. <publisher-loc>Seattle, WA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Center for the Study of Teaching and Policy</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ingersoll</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001b</year>). <article-title>Teacher turnover and teacher shortages: An organizational analysis</article-title>. <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>499</fpage>-<lpage>534</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ingersoll</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Is there really a teacher shortage?</source> <publisher-loc>Seattle, WA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Center for the Study of Teaching and Policy and The Consortium for Policy Research in Education</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Beyond role models—An examination of cultural influences on the pedagogical perspectives of Black teachers</article-title>. <source>Peabody Journal of Education</source>, <volume>66</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>The workplace matters: Teacher quality, retention, and effectiveness</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Education Association Research Department</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birkeland</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Pursuing a “sense of success”: New teachers explain their career decisions</article-title>. <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>581</fpage>-<lpage>617</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kanter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <article-title>Some effects of proportions on group life: Skewed sex ratios and response to token women</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>82</volume>, <fpage>965</fpage>-<lpage>990</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Factors affecting satisfaction and retention of African American and European American teachers in an urban school district: Implications for building and maintaining teachers employed in school districts across the nation</article-title>. <source>Education and Urban Society</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>613</fpage>-<lpage>627</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>KewalRamani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gilbertson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Provasnik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Status and trends in the education of racial and ethnic minorities</source> (<comment>NCES 2007-039</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Center for Education Statistics, Institute of Education Sciences, U.S. Department of Education</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>The limited presence of African-American teachers</article-title>. <source>Review of Educational Research</source>, <volume>63</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>115</fpage>-<lpage>149</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berends</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naftel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Supply and demand of minority teachers in Texas: Problems and prospects</article-title>. <source>Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis</source>, <volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klecker</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>, <month>November</month> <day>12</day>). <source>Male elementary school teachers’ ratings of job satisfaction by years of teaching experience</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the annual meeting of the Mid-South Educational Research Association</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Memphis, TN</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kovner</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fairchild</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Understanding new registered nurses’ intent to stay at their jobs</article-title>. <source>Nursing Economics</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>81</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Intergroup relations and organizational dilemmas: The role of categorization processes</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Staw</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Research in organizational behavior</source> (<volume>Vol. 13</volume>, pp. <fpage>191</fpage>-<lpage>228</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Greenwich, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>JAI Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lankford</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wyckoff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Teacher sorting and the plight of urban schools: A descriptive analysis</article-title>. <source>Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>An alternative approach: The unfolding model of voluntary employee turnover</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>V. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dedrick</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>The effect of the social organization of schools on teachers’ efficacy and satisfaction</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Education</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>190</fpage>-<lpage>208</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>D. I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The effect of diversity on turnover: A large case study</article-title>. <source>Industrial &amp; Labor Relations Review</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>547</fpage>-<lpage>572</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramsey</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Teachers’ job satisfaction: Analysis of the teacher follow-up survey in the United States for 2000-2001</article-title>. <source>Teaching and Teacher Education</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1173</fpage>-<lpage>1184</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Darling-Hammond</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luczak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>How teaching conditions predict teacher turnover in California schools</article-title>. <source>Peabody Journal of Education</source>, <volume>80</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>44</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luekens</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lyter</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>, <month>August</month>). <source>Teacher attrition and mobility: Results from the teacher follow-up survey, 2000-01</source> (<comment>Education Statistics Services Institute</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Center for Education Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacMillan</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Influences of workplace conditions on teachers’ job satisfaction</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Research</source>, <volume>93</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>March</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1958</year>). <source>Organizations</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>David Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marvel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lyter</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peltola</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strizek</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Teacher attrition and mobility: Results from the 2004-05 teacher follow-up survey</source> (<comment>National Center for Education Statistics</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Institutes for Research</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mertler</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Job satisfaction and perceptions of motivation among middle and high school teachers</article-title>. <source>American Secondary Education</source>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mertz</surname><given-names>N. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNeely</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>How are we doing? Women in urban school administration</article-title>. <source>Urban Education</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>361</fpage>-<lpage>372</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mobley</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Griffeth</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hand</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meglino</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Review and conceptual analysis of the employee turnover process</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>493</fpage>-<lpage>522</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Finley</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iverson</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The effects of group racial composition on job satisfaction, organizational commitment, and career commitment: The case of teachers</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>219</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Murnane</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>The effects of salaries and opportunity costs on duration in teaching: Evidence from Michigan</article-title>. <source>Review of Economics and Statistics</source>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>347</fpage>-<lpage>352</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Newberry</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The role of elementary teachers’ conceptions of closeness to students on their differential behavior in the classroom</article-title>. <source>Teaching and Teacher Education</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1965</fpage>-<lpage>1985</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pagano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>, <month>March</month> <day>24-28</day>). <source>How teaching in the urban setting affects career motivations of beginning teachers: A longitudinal study</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Chicago, IL</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pelled</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Demographic diversity, conflict and work group outcomes: An intervening process theory</article-title>. <source>Organization Science</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>615</fpage>-<lpage>631</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Perie</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Job satisfaction among America’s teachers: Effects of workplace conditions, background characteristics, and teacher compensation</source> (<comment>Statistical Analysis Report No. NCES-97-471</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Center for Education Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pfeffer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Organizational demography</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Staw</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Research in organizational behavior</source> (<volume>Vol. 5</volume>, pp. <fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>357</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Greenwich, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>JAI Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pigott</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cowen</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Teacher race, child race, racial congruence and teacher ratings of children’s school adjustment</article-title>. <source>Journal of School Psychology</source>, <volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>177</fpage>-<lpage>196</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Race, gender, and educational leadership: Perspectives from African American principals</article-title>. <source>Educational Policy</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>353</fpage>-<lpage>374</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Reflection on the determinants of voluntary turnover</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Manpower</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>600</fpage>-<lpage>624</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Quiocho</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The power of their presence: Minority group teachers and schooling</article-title>. <source>Review of Educational Research</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>485</fpage>-<lpage>528</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Renzulli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacPherson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beattie</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Are charter schools satisfying? The effects of racial composition and school type of teacher satisfaction</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the annual meeting of the American Sociological Association</conf-name>, <conf-loc>New York, NY</conf-loc>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.allacademic.com/meta/p182879_index.html">http://www.allacademic.com/meta/p182879_index.html</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>G. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>A decade of teacher empowerment: An empirical analysis of teacher involvement in decision-making 1980-1981</article-title>. <source>Journal of Education Administration</source>, <volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Riordan</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shore</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Demographic diversity and employee attitudes: An empirical examination of relational demography within work units</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>, <volume>82</volume>, <fpage>342</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosenholtz</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Effective schools: Interpreting the evidence</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Education</source>, <volume>93</volume>, <fpage>352</fpage>-<lpage>387</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A dynamic multilevel model of demographic diversity and misfit effects</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>, <volume>90</volume>, <fpage>203</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sackett</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DuBois</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Noe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Tokenism in performance evaluation: The effects of work representation on male–female and Black–White differences in performance ratings</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>263</fpage>-<lpage>267</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shann</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Professional commitment and satisfaction among teachers in urban middle schools</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Research</source>, <volume>92</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>73</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steers</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mowday</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>Employee turnover and postdecision accommodation processes</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Staw</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Research in organizational behavior</source> (<volume>Vol. 3</volume>, <fpage>235</fpage>-<lpage>281</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Greenwich, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>JAI Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stockard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Influences of the satisfaction and retention of 1st year teachers: The importance of effective school management</article-title>. <source>Educational Administration Quarterly</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>742</fpage>-<lpage>771</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strizek</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pittsonberger</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riordan</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lyter</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orlofsky</surname><given-names>G. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Characteristics of schools, districts, teachers, principals, and school libraries in the United States: 2003-04 schools and staffing survey</source> (<comment>NCES 2006-313 revised</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Education, National Center for Education Statistics, U.S. Government Printing Office</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nces.ed.gov/pubsearch/pubsinfo.asp?pubid=2006313">http://nces.ed.gov/pubsearch/pubsinfo.asp?pubid=2006313</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tourkin</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parmer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zukerberg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Soderborg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Documentation for the 2003-04 schools and staffing survey</source> (<comment>NCES 2007-337</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Education, National Center for Education Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>U.S. Department of Education, National Center for Education Statistics</collab>. (<year>2007</year>). <source>The condition of education 2007</source> (<comment>NCES 2007-064</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Government Printing Office</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Perceived workplace conditions and first-year teachers’ morale, career choice commitment, and planned retention: A secondary analysis</article-title>. <source>Teaching and Teacher Education</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>861</fpage>-<lpage>879</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Youngs</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>How elementary principals’ beliefs and actions influence new teachers’ experiences</article-title>. <source>Educational Administration Quarterly</source>, <volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>137</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-0042085911429582">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zatzick</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elvira</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>When is more better? The effects of racial composition on voluntary turnover</article-title>. <source>Organization Science</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>483</fpage>-<lpage>496</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>