<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CJR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcjr</journal-id>
<journal-title>Criminal Justice Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0734-0168</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1556-3839</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0734016812451854</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0734016812451854</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Enforcing the Convict Code: Violence and Prison Culture</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stoddart</surname>
<given-names>Dahlia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0734016812451854"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0734016812451854"><italic>Prairie View A&amp;M University, Prairie View, TX, USA</italic></aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>38</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>140</fpage>
<lpage>141</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Trammell</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <source>Enforcing the Convict Code: Violence and Prison Culture</source> <publisher-loc>Boulder, CO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lynne Rienner Publishers, Inc</publisher-name>., <year>2012</year>. <page-count count="157"/> pp. <price>$49.95</price>. <isbn>ISBN 978-1-58826-808-2</isbn></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 Georgia State University</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Georgia State University, College of Health and Human Sciences</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In the book <italic>Enforcing the Convict Code: Violence and Prison Culture,</italic> the author, Rebecca Trammell, gave an in-depth quantitative account of exactly how and why violence occurs in prison, and the impact of inmates’ culture of violence. This book unfolds in seven chapters. It is primarily written for administrators in the criminal justice system and affiliate organizations, parents, teachers, and students.</p>
<p>In Chapter I, Trammell described the nature of <italic>violence behind bars </italic>and she described the research approach as a qualitative study. She interviewed former inmates to understand how they perceived violence while incarcerated. Trammell’s goal was to understand how violence is linked to cultural norms in prison.</p>
<p>In Chapter II, Trammell focused on <italic>prison culture</italic> and explored it through the lens of ex-inmates who explained that they maintained an informal culture by: mentoring incoming inmates to adhere to the informal prison culture; forming race-based gangs to achieve more informal power; and using alternative measures to outwit the formal justice system toward stability behind bars. Even though relationships between correctional officers and inmates were prohibited, at some point, both worked cohesively toward peace. Prison lockdowns and uncontrolled eruptions of violence affect underground drugs sale and other illegal activities; so, contrary to what outsiders might assume, inmates did not like these events.</p>
<p>In Chapter III, Trammell analyzed <italic>race and relations </italic>and offered an in-depth description of the nature of segregation as it is embedded in the informal norms of the prison culture. A comparison was made between the states of Texas and California and between male and female inmates. In California, male inmates are separated by race and gang affiliations. While in Texas, inmates are desegregated and are randomly placed in confinements. At present, Texas’ prison population is one of the most integrated in the United States. Even though inmates in the California prisons do not want to be integrated racially, they come together for social activities. Female inmates, on the other hand, also have problems with racial segregation, but to a lesser extent when compared to their male counterparts.</p>
<p>In Chapter IV, Trammell examined <italic>gender, sex,</italic> and <italic>rape</italic> as they relate to male and female inmates and posits that previous studies had a male bias. There has also been an absence of inmate’s sexual versatility. The author discussed “protective pairing”—where sexual gratification is given in return for protection, and “gay for the stay” where some inmates chose to be homosexual only while they are incarcerated. These issues can be problematic and may result in serious violence and/or even rape. Inmates have largely redefined rape as part of the contextual norm of prison and as a result, it is seldom reported.</p>
<p>Chapter V assessed <italic>interpersonal conflicts</italic>. Trammel allowed ex-inmates to describe how some problems escalated into violence and the extent to which conflict resolution measures may have an impact. The ex-inmates explained that disrespect, drugs, theft, and rape were often behind violence. Avoiding problematic inmates was the most common refuge from violent victimization. Women became prison-smart by mastering the art of staying out of trouble, and of reporting problems to prison staff. While women would distance themselves from violence and avoid harmful stigmatizations, men on the other hand bragged, about how they were able to dominate other inmates.</p>
<p>Chapter VI outlined the formal and informal mechanisms of social control. The California Code of Regulation, Title 15, handbook, describes formal rules for inmates. Trammell concluded that the formal social control measures would be most effective if they impact activities that the inmates value such as avoiding lockdown (among the men), friendship and avoiding trouble (among the women). For male inmates, most conflicts could be solved with an apology. In contrast, women used gossip and rumor as a method of informal social control, but they also face formal sanctions as necessary.</p>
<p>In Chapter VII, Trammell gave an overview of the previous chapters by highlighting the main concepts. She provides worthy policy suggestions in regard to the effectiveness of mass incarceration and its intended purposes. Trammell also offers suggestions on how prison officials could make prisons more functional by: changing the informal culture and byfacilitating better relationships between staff and inmates. The author believes that more research is needed on violence and social control.</p>
<p>This book is both interesting and informative. The author used a cultural theoretical framework that connects violence in situations with someone’s identity when threatened. She explained prison culture and violence from the viewpoint of ex-inmates, representing the views of both men and women. The narratives given by the ex-inmates were enlightening and real. Even though the author glaringly omitted discussing sexually transmitted diseases as they relate to rape and sex, the book remains worth reading.</p>
</body>
</article>