<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PSP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppsp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pers Soc Psychol Bull</journal-id>
<journal-title>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0146-1672</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7433</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0146167211432762</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0146167211432762</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Social Roles, Basic Need Satisfaction, and Psychological Health</article-title>
<subtitle>The Central Role of Competence</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Talley</surname><given-names>Amelia E.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0146167211432762">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kocum</surname><given-names>Lucie</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0146167211432762">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Schlegel</surname><given-names>Rebecca J.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0146167211432762">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Molix</surname><given-names>Lisa</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0146167211432762">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Bettencourt</surname><given-names>B. Ann</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0146167211432762">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0146167211432762"><label>1</label>University of Missouri, Columbia, MO, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0146167211432762"><label>2</label>Saint Mary’s University, Halifax, Canada</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0146167211432762"><label>3</label>Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, Texas, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0146167211432762"><label>4</label>Tulane University, New Orleans, Louisiana, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0146167211432762">B. Ann Bettencourt, 104A McAlester Hall, Department of Psychological Sciences, University of Missouri, Columbia, MO 65211, USA Email: <email>bettencourta@missouri.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>38</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>155</fpage>
<lpage>173</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>14</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>12</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 Society for Personality and Social Psychology, Inc.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Society for Personality and Social Psychology, Inc.</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The authors propose that competence need fulfillment within valued role domains (i.e., spouse, parent, worker) will account, in part, for associations between autonomy and relatedness need fulfillment and psychological health. Testing these assertions in cross-sectional and longitudinal surveys of women in two independent community samples, the findings are the first to formally examine whether the satisfaction of competence needs within social roles accounts for associations between other types of need satisfaction and affective outcomes as well as depressive symptomology. Evidence supporting the hypothesis was stronger when examining individuals’ affective health as compared to their depressive symptoms. Implications of the findings are discussed with regard to need fulfillment within social roles.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>roles</kwd>
<kwd>competence (self-efficacy)</kwd>
<kwd>need satisfaction</kwd>
<kwd>self-determination theory</kwd>
<kwd>affect</kwd>
<kwd>depression</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In human life, social roles are ubiquitous. Historically, social and personality psychologists sought to understand the relation between social roles and psychological functioning (see, e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0146167211432762">Barnett &amp; Baruch, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0146167211432762">Verbrugge, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-0146167211432762">Warr &amp; Parry, 1982</xref>). Contemporary social and personality psychologists, however, have focused much less attention on understanding the ways in which social roles influence psychological adjustment. Nevertheless, current research on aging and illness provides consonant evidence that social roles play a crucial function in psychological and physical health (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0146167211432762">Adelmann, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0146167211432762">Kikuzawa, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0146167211432762">Plach, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-0146167211432762">Vandewater &amp; Stewart, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr89-0146167211432762">Wickrama, Conger, Lorenz, &amp; Matthews, 1995</xref>). Our research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0146167211432762">Bettencourt, Molix, Talley, &amp; Sheldon, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211432762">Bettencourt &amp; Sheldon, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0146167211432762">Talley, Molix, Schlegel, &amp; Bettencourt, 2010</xref>) argues that social roles are important mechanisms through which basic psychological needs can be satisfied, and as such, fulfilling social roles has the capacity to enhance psychological health.</p>
<p>Our assertions reflect the theorizing of Deci and Ryan (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0146167211432762">Deci &amp; Ryan, 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0146167211432762">2002</xref>), who have identified autonomy, relatedness, and competence as the three basic psychological needs. One of the central tenets of self-determination theory (SDT) is that the satisfaction of these needs is “essential for ongoing psychological growth, integrity, and well-being” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0146167211432762">Deci &amp; Ryan, 2000</xref>, p. 229) and research has supported this notion (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0146167211432762">Hahn &amp; Oishi, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick, Knee, Canevello, &amp; Lonsbary, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0146167211432762">Reis, Sheldon, Gable, Roscoe, &amp; Ryan, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0146167211432762">Sheldon &amp; Niemiec, 2006</xref>). Autonomy concerns people’s feelings of volition and the desire for behavior to be “concordant with one’s integrated sense of self” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0146167211432762">Deci &amp; Ryan, 2000</xref>, p. 231). Relatedness involves feeling connected with others and the desire “to love and care, and to be loved and cared for” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0146167211432762">Deci &amp; Ryan, 2000</xref>, p. 231; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0146167211432762">Ryan, 1993</xref>). Finally, competence is related to people’s feelings of efficacy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0146167211432762">Deci, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr88-0146167211432762">White, 1959</xref>).</p>
<p>Critically, SDT suggests that these three needs are equivalent with regard to their importance for psychosocial functioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0146167211432762">Ryan &amp; Deci, 2000</xref>). Past research reflects this mutual emphasis such that studies typically combine reports of two or three of these needs into a single index of need satisfaction (NS; e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0146167211432762">Deci, Ryan, Gagné, et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0146167211432762">La Guardia, Ryan, Couchman, &amp; Deci, 2000</xref>, Studies 1 and 2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0146167211432762">Standage, Duda, &amp; Ntoumanis, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0146167211432762">Talley et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-0146167211432762">Vansteenkiste et al., 2007</xref>). As useful as this research has been for understanding the overall effect of basic psychological NS, investigators have not fully considered potential dynamic interrelations among these needs (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211432762">Bettencourt &amp; Sheldon, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick et al., 2007</xref>). Addressing this latter point, we sought to test whether the association between the satisfaction of autonomy and relatedness needs within particular social roles and psychological health is achieved, at least in part, through the satisfaction of competence needs.</p>
<p>Although few hypotheses have been offered within the SDT literature regarding the ways basic psychological needs may influence one another, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0146167211432762">Bandura (1989)</xref> theorizes that competence (i.e., self-efficacy) functions as the primary “cognitive mediator” in determining motivation and subsequent psychological health. Supporting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0146167211432762">Bandura’s (1989)</xref> theorizing, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick et al. (2007)</xref> found that, of SDT’s three psychological needs, competence NS within the relationship domain was the most consistent predictor of romantic partners’ well-being (i.e., self-esteem, positive affect, vitality). Our belief that competence need fulfillment is a primary mediator within social role domains is consistent with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0146167211432762">Bandura’s (1989)</xref> social cognitive theory. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0146167211432762">Bandura (1997)</xref>, feelings of personal competence are related to self-perceptions of efficacy regarding one’s ability to deal effectively with distinct social domains and are seen as proximal and direct predictors of psychological motivation, affect, and behaviors. Thus, we believe that individuals’ feelings of autonomy and relatedness within a given social role may be used as information in determining perceptions of one’s competence within that role.</p>
<p>The current work draws on the aforementioned theories to advance a hypothesis regarding a specific mediating relation among basic psychological needs within social role domains. Although we recognize distinctions between the two theories (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0146167211432762">Deci &amp; Ryan, 2000</xref>, for a discussion), our primary interest in SDT is its assumption that fulfillment of the three basic psychological needs has the capacity to enhance psychological health. Our primary interest in social cognitive theory is the contention that perceptions of competence within specific domains should function as a proximal mediator of psychological health outcomes.</p>
<sec id="section1-0146167211432762">
<title>Role-Related Competence NS as a Mediator</title>
<p>A person’s ability to perform a role competently should be a function of how authentic he or she feels in that role. Early research showed that participants assigned to roles that were congruent with self-characteristics were more satisfied with their role performances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0146167211432762">Benoit-Smullyan, 1944</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0146167211432762">Bunker, 1967</xref>) as well as more likely to succeed in problem-solving tasks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0146167211432762">Borgatta, 1961</xref>). Thus, social roles that are congruent with one’s authentic self are more likely to foster feelings of competence.</p>
<p>People may also derive feelings of competence from social role fulfillments that engender feelings of relatedness. Social roles that produce feelings of closeness should evoke a greater sense of responsibility in role players and motivate stronger efforts that may translate into more successful role performance. In addition, individuals should receive information from others about their effectiveness in social roles (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0146167211432762">McCall &amp; Simmons, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0146167211432762">Stryker, 1987</xref>). Sociological theories suggest that feelings of competence can arise as a consequence of reflected appraisals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0146167211432762">Harter, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0146167211432762">Sarbin &amp; Allen, 1969</xref>) and support from others associated with the social role who contribute to feelings of relatedness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0146167211432762">McCall &amp; Simmons, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0146167211432762">Scott &amp; Stumpf, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0146167211432762">Stryker, 1987</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0146167211432762">1</xref></sup> That is, positive social feedback is thought to contribute to perceived competence within social roles (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0146167211432762">Allen &amp; Howe, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0146167211432762">Amorose &amp; Horn, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0146167211432762">Amorose &amp; Smith, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0146167211432762">Hein &amp; Koka, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>A few studies (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0146167211432762">Abraido-Lanza, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211432762">Bettencourt &amp; Sheldon, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick et al., 2007</xref><bold>)</bold> also provide initial suggestive evidence that perceptions of competence within roles function as a mediator. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0146167211432762">Abraido-Lanza (1997)</xref> conducted a cross-sectional study, based on the tenets of identity theorists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0146167211432762">Pearlin, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0146167211432762">Tajfel, 1981</xref>), and found that feelings of self-efficacy partially accounted for the association between role identification (i.e., collapsing across social roles: mother, grandmother, wife, worker, homemaker, friend) and affective outcomes. As another example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211432762">Bettencourt and Sheldon (2001)</xref> found evidence that feelings of autonomy and relatedness were associated with feelings of competence across a number of roles that were self-selected by undergraduate students. Findings also showed that these feelings of competence were related to subsequent improved subjective well-being.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0146167211432762">
<title>The Current Studies and Hypothesis</title>
<p>We conducted two studies within the domain of social roles that examined the likelihood that competence NS serves as a mediator in the relation between autonomy and relatedness NS and psychological health. In doing so, we adopted a number of methodological strategies that allowed us to advance this area of inquiry. First, unlike previous findings based on samples of undergraduate students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211432762">Bettencourt &amp; Sheldon, 2001</xref>), both studies in the present article include samples of adult women. Second, given that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0146167211432762">Krause (2007)</xref> questioned the importance of roles that were assessed in prior studies, we focus on three roles that are likely to be central and valued in the lives of adult women. Third, although Study 1 involves a cross-sectional survey, Study 2 includes a five-wave longitudinal survey assessment, providing a powerful means by which to test our hypotheses within each of the three social roles. Finally, whereas a variety of studies examining need fulfillment have used multiple measures of positive psychosocial functioning, such as psychological well-being, relationship functioning, and positive affect (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0146167211432762">Hahn &amp; Oishi, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0146167211432762">Sheldon &amp; Niemiec, 2006</xref>), ours considers ratings of depressive symptoms as well as positive affective balance. The inclusion of depressive symptoms allowed us to examine the contribution of basic NS not only to psychological thriving but also to psychological vulnerability.</p>
<p>In Study 1, we examine our hypotheses in a nonclinical community sample of adult women who reported on feelings of NS within three central social roles (i.e., spouse, parent, worker). We expected that feelings of competence across social roles would account for shared variance between reports of autonomy and relatedness NS within these roles and psychological health outcomes (i.e., positive affective balance, depressive symptoms).</p>
<p>In Study 2, we examined our hypotheses within a longitudinal framework using a sample of women who had been diagnosed with breast cancer. We sought to understand whether interrelations among psychological needs were distinct within each of three central social roles and with regard to psychological health. We expected that when considering the satisfaction of all three basic needs in tandem, feelings of competence within roles would function as the most proximal contributor to patients’ reports of psychological health. We used structural equation modeling and multilevel modeling to provide evidence for our hypothesis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0146167211432762">
<title>Study 1</title>
<sec id="section4-0146167211432762">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section5-0146167211432762">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>One hundred seventeen adult rural women (<italic>M</italic> age = 53.02, <italic>SD</italic> = 10.23) completed a paper-and-pencil survey. Participants who did not report being engaged in at least one central social role were excluded from analyses (final <italic>n</italic> = 107). The larger purpose of this study was to better understand rural women’s physical and psychological health as well as health care needs. The majority of participants were White European American (96%). Most participants (77%) reported a household income below $50,000. Most participants (87.2%) reported being a parent to at least one child, and most were in a marital relationship or living with their significant other (73%; single = 9%, divorced = 12%, widowed = 7%).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0146167211432762">
<title>Measures</title>
<sec id="section7-0146167211432762">
<title>Role-related autonomy/relatedness NS</title>
<p>To measure the extent to which participants felt their relatedness and autonomy needs were being met through the fulfillment of their spouse, parent, and worker roles,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0146167211432762">2</xref></sup> we included a known measure of role-related NS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211432762">Bettencourt &amp; Sheldon, 2001</xref>). Participants’ fulfillment of relatedness and autonomy needs was assessed with two items each, respectively, within each social role. Examples of the spousal-role items are as follows: “When I carry out the role of spouse/partner, I feel free to be myself” and “When I carry out my spouse/partner role, I feel close to my partner” (1 = <italic>strongly disagree</italic>, 6 = <italic>strongly agree</italic>). Correlations between role-related feelings of autonomy and relatedness NS for the spousal, parental and worker roles were .61, .69, and .68, respectively (all <italic>p</italic>s &lt; .001). As has been done in other studies (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0146167211432762">Niemiec et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0146167211432762">Sheldon &amp; Elliot, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0146167211432762">Sheldon &amp; Niemiec, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0146167211432762">Talley et al., 2010</xref>) and to limit the undue influence of multicollinearity, autonomy and relatedness NS items were combined (spousal A/R α = .80, parental A/R α = .84, worker A/R α = .84) and averaged across roles into a single index (overall A/R α = .77).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0146167211432762">3</xref></sup> We refer to this measure as <italic>role-related autonomy/relatedness NS</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0146167211432762">
<title>Role-related competence NS</title>
<p>Using the same measure of role-related NS, an index of competence NS within social roles was created by averaging two items within each role (spousal α = .69, parental α = .68, worker α = .64). Feelings of competence NS were then averaged across the three social roles (α = .66). An example of a spousal-role item is “When I carry out the spouse/partner role, I feel competent (skilled)” (1 = <italic>strongly disagree</italic>, 6 = <italic>strongly agree</italic>). We refer to this measure as <italic>role-related competence NS</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0146167211432762">
<title>Positive affective balance</title>
<p>The 20-item Positive and Negative Affect Schedule (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-0146167211432762">Watson, Clark, &amp; Tellegen, 1988</xref>) was used to measure the extent to which participants felt each type of affect “on average” (1 = <italic>not at all</italic>, 4 = <italic>somewhat</italic>, 7 = <italic>very much</italic>). An index of positive affective balance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0146167211432762">Bradburn, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0146167211432762">McDowell, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0146167211432762">Sheldon, Elliot, Kim, &amp; Kasser, 2001</xref>) was created by subtracting the standardized sum of the negative affect index (α = .88) from the standardized sum of the positive affect index (α = .92).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0146167211432762">
<title>Depressive symptoms</title>
<p>Fifteen items from the Center for Epidemiologic Studies–Depression Scale (CES-D; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0146167211432762">Radloff, 1977</xref>) were averaged to assess depressive symptomology (α = .91).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0146167211432762">4</xref></sup> Participants rated the intensity and frequency of depressive symptoms they had experienced in the previous week (0 = <italic>rarely or none of the time</italic>, 3 = <italic>most or all of the time</italic>). Example items included “I felt sad” and “I had crying spells.”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0146167211432762">
<title>Covariates</title>
<p>Twelve items from a health measure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0146167211432762">Sintonen, 2001</xref>) were used to assess participants’ levels of physical functioning (α = .82), ranging from experiences with mobility to physical pain. On each item, participants chose from five options (1 = <italic>relatively high functioning</italic> to 5 = <italic>poor functioning</italic>). Global self-esteem was assessed with 4 items from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0146167211432762">Rosenberg’s (1965)</xref> 10-item scale (α = .74). An example item included “On the whole, I am satisfied with myself” (1 = <italic>strongly disagree</italic>, 7 = <italic>strongly agree</italic>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0146167211432762">
<title>Results and Discussion</title>
<sec id="section13-0146167211432762">
<title>Descriptive analyses</title>
<p>Eighty-eight participants reported being engaged in the parental role, 91 in the spousal role, and 89 in the worker role. Bivariate associations among the primary variables are reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0146167211432762">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0146167211432762" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Study 1 Descriptive Statistics and Total Score Correlations for Primary Study Measures</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0146167211432762" xlink:href="10.1177_0146167211432762-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Measure</th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center">α</th>
<th align="center">1</th>
<th align="center">2</th>
<th align="center">3</th>
<th align="center">4</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1. Role-related autonomy/relatedness NS</td>
<td>5.54</td>
<td>1.07</td>
<td>.77</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2. Role-related competence NS</td>
<td>5.86</td>
<td>0.97</td>
<td>.66</td>
<td>.79</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3. Positive affective balance</td>
<td>1.78</td>
<td>2.14</td>
<td>.92/.88<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0146167211432762">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>.66</td>
<td>.69</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4. Depressive symptoms</td>
<td>1.76</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>.91</td>
<td>−.61</td>
<td>−.61</td>
<td>−.83</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0146167211432762">
<p>NS = need satisfaction. Regression analyses controlled for global self-esteem and self-reported physical functioning. All correlations significant at <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0146167211432762">
<label>a</label>
<p>Reliability for positive affect subscale/negative affect subscale.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0146167211432762">
<title>Cross-sectional mediation models</title>
<p>A cross-sectional analysis with maximum likelihood estimation was conducted using MPlus 5.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0146167211432762">Muthén &amp; Muthén, 2007</xref>). After controlling for covariates, the direct associations between role-related autonomy/relatedness NS and both positive affective balance and depressive symptoms were significant (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0146167211432762">Figure 1</xref>). Supporting mediation, when role-related competence NS was added to the models, these direct associations were reduced in magnitude.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0146167211432762" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Study 1 primary mediation model</p>
<p>NS = need satisfaction. Standardized coefficients are provided. Numbers in parentheses are direct path coefficients (without role-related competence NS included in the model). In these models, self-reported physical (dys)function was negatively related to role-related autonomy/relatedness NS (β = –.22*), competence NS (β = –.12, <italic>ns</italic>), and positive affective balance (β = –.43***) and positively related to depressive symptoms (β = .44*). Self-esteem was positively related to role-related autonomy/relatedness NS (β = .56***), competence NS (β = .28***), and positive affective balance (β = .25***) and negatively related to depressive symptoms (β = –.29***).</p>
<p>*<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0146167211432762-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>PRODCLIN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0146167211432762">MacKinnon, Fritz, Williams, &amp; Lockwood, 2007</xref>) was employed to provide bias-corrected estimates of the confidence intervals around the indirect effects. These analyses revealed that the indirect influence of role-related autonomy/relatedness NS on positive affective balance via role-related competence NS was significant, αβ <italic>= .</italic>71, <italic>SE = .</italic>18, 95% CI [.36, 1.07]. These findings suggest that feelings of competence NS within social roles, which are related to autonomy and relatedness NS, may be most proximally associated with individuals’ positive affective balance. Similarly, the indirect effect was found to be significant for depressive symptoms, αβ = –.16, <italic>SE = .</italic>06, 95% CI [–.27, –.05]. An inspection of standardized paths contained in the lower panel of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0146167211432762">Figure 1</xref> suggests that feelings of autonomy/relatedness NS and competence NS within social roles may independently and equivalently contribute to overall feelings of depression (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick et al., 2007</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0146167211432762">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>These results provide evidence consistent with the assertion that feelings of competence NS within social roles may mediate, in part, associations between role-related autonomy/relatedness NS and psychological health. Although the findings of Study 1 provide additional evidence regarding the ways in which feelings of basic NS within valued social roles contribute to psychological health, they were limited by the cross-sectional study design and multicollinearity among ratings of NS.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0146167211432762">
<title>Study 2</title>
<p>Women tend to experience poor psychological health during breast cancer treatment and survivorship (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0146167211432762">Bardwell et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0146167211432762">Hagedoorn, Sanderman, Bolks, Tuinstra, &amp; Coyne, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0146167211432762">Hoskins et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0146167211432762">Primo et al., 2000</xref>; Schlegel, Talley, Molix, &amp; Bettencourt, in press). Many breast cancer survivors report changes to their social-role functioning and role-related responsibilities during this same period (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0146167211432762">Bloom et al., 1991</xref>). It is reasonable to suspect that the disruption of social-role functioning may diminish NS, which would otherwise be derived through social-role fulfillment. It has been theorized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0146167211432762">Pearlin, 1983</xref>) that decreased feelings of competence could explain why disruption in social-role functioning contributes to diminished psychological health.</p>
<sec id="section16-0146167211432762">
<title>Between- Versus Within-Person Variation in Need Fulfillment</title>
<p>In Study 2 analyses, we expect to replicate the results of Study 1 and find that individual differences in levels of competence NS will mediate associations between average levels of autonomy/relatedness NS and overall psychological health. We use structural equation modeling to examine between-person relations between need fulfillment within social roles and psychological outcomes across a 2-year period, allowing us to better observe traitlike relations that may not be as evident or powerful with cross-sectional models.</p>
<p>Admittedly, relations among aggregate levels of need fulfillment and psychological health are unable to fully address the within-person, process associations implied in our hypotheses: Individuals’ satisfaction of autonomy and relatedness needs will inform feelings regarding their satisfaction of competence needs in social roles, which in turn will contribute to reports of psychological health. Methodologists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0146167211432762">Robinson, 1950</xref>) have warned that findings obtained at the between-person level of analysis may not necessarily be replicated in within-person analyses. We expect that within-person variability in competence need fulfillment within a given social role will account for associations between within-person variability in autonomy/relatedness NS in that same role and psychological health. We use multilevel modeling to examine whether within-person processes are similar to or different from aggregate, between-person associations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0146167211432762">
<title>Differential Associations Based on Social Role</title>
<p>Research has examined the fulfillment of psychological needs within specific role domains, such as close relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0146167211432762">Deci, La Guardia, Moller, Scheiner, &amp; Ryan, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0146167211432762">La Guardia et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0146167211432762">Milyavskaya et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0146167211432762">Ryan, La Guardia, Solky-Butzel, Chirkov, &amp; Kim, 2005</xref>) and work and school relationships (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0146167211432762">Ilardi, Leone, Kasser, &amp; Ryan, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0146167211432762">Milyavskaya et al., 2009</xref>). Most previous research has focused on only one role domain (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0146167211432762">Ilardi et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0146167211432762">Talley et al., 2010</xref>) or, as in the current Study 1, averaged across multiple roles (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211432762">Bettencourt &amp; Sheldon, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0146167211432762">La Guardia et al., 2000</xref>, Study 1). One limitation of this approach is that researchers are unable to consider whether feelings of NS, in particular social roles, differentially influence outcomes. Given that some social roles may be more inherently meaningful,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0146167211432762">6</xref></sup> NS within particular role domains may be differentially related to psychosocial outcomes (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0146167211432762">La Guardia et al., 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Some studies have found evidence for differential associations between need fulfillment and psychological outcomes within specific role domains. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick et al. (2007)</xref> found that within romantic relationships, competence need fulfillment was most consistently and independently associated with personal well-being outcomes (i.e., self-esteem, positive affect, vitality, low negative affect), but all types of need fulfillment were positively and equivalently associated with relationship outcomes (e.g., satisfaction, responses to conflict). In Study 2, we use a longitudinal design to test our hypotheses separately within each social role, allowing for a more optimal understanding of dynamic psychological processes that may occur between and within persons during survivorship.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0146167211432762">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section19-0146167211432762">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>Participants were 211 female breast cancer patients (<italic>M</italic> age = 59, <italic>SD</italic> = 12) who were part of a larger study (<italic>N</italic> = 244); participants from the sample who did not report being engaged in at least one central social role (<italic>n</italic> = 33) were excluded from analyses. Participants’ average income was between $45,000 and $55,000 (range = less than $15,000 to $115,000 or more). At baseline, 175 participants fulfilled the partner or spousal role, 170 the parental role, and 167 the worker role. Eighteen percent of participants were diagnosed with Stage 0 cancer, 45% Stage I, 21% Stage II, 15% Stage III, and 1% Stage IV (<italic>n</italic> = 4 missing).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0146167211432762">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>Participants were part of a larger study examining psychosocial outcomes of breast cancer survivorship. A nurse provided the baseline survey (Wave 1) to a convenience sample of eligible patients during their 1st week of radiation therapy. Of those patients who received a packet from a nurse, approximately 59% returned the survey. For patients who refused to participate, no data on reasons for refusal or demographics were available. Subsequent surveys were mailed by the research staff 12, 24, 56, and 104 weeks, respectively, after the start of radiation treatment. Participants were paid $25 for each survey. Over five waves, 211 patients responded to the Wave 1 survey, 195 (93%) to Wave 2, 190 (91%) to Wave 3, 176 (83%) to Wave 4, and 128 (73%) to Wave 5.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0146167211432762">7</xref></sup> Comparisons between participants who completed all waves and those who were missing at least one revealed that they did not differ on any disease or illness variables (stage of cancer, physical symptoms), demographics (age, number of cohabitating children, income), or psychological functioning indicators (depression, positive affective balance) at baseline. Surveys included other measures not discussed in this current report.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0146167211432762">
<title>Measures</title>
<sec id="section22-0146167211432762">
<title>Role-related autonomy NS</title>
<p>We included the measure of NS used in Study 1. Autonomy items for each respective role were combined into a single index (average spouse α = .84, parent α = .84, worker α = .85, respectively).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0146167211432762">
<title>Role-related relatedness NS</title>
<p>Items assessing relatedness NS within each respective role type were combined into a single index (average spouse α = .77, parent α = .64, worker α = .63, respectively).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0146167211432762">
<title>Role-related competence NS</title>
<p>Patients’ competence NS within each role was measured with four items, which were found to be internally reliable (average spouse α = .82, parent α = .83, worker α = .82, respectively).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-0146167211432762">
<title>Positive affective balance</title>
<p>The Profile of Mood States (POMS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0146167211432762">McNair, Lorr, &amp; Droppelman, 1981</xref>) was used to create a measure of affective balance. The POMS is commonly used as a measure of affect in cancer patient samples (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0146167211432762">Baker, Denniston, Zabora, Polland, &amp; Dudley, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0146167211432762">Stanton et al., 2002</xref>). It includes five subscales (i.e., Vigor, Depression, Tension, Fatigue, Anger). Participants rated the degree to which they were feeling each mood since their diagnosis or the previous wave of data collection, depending on the assessment (0 = <italic>not at all</italic>, 4 = <italic>extremely</italic>). A measure of affective balance was calculated by subtracting the mean of the four negative subscales from the mean of the Vigor subscale (average α = .85).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-0146167211432762">
<title>Depressive symptoms</title>
<p>The 20-item CES-D (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0146167211432762">Radloff, 1977</xref>) was used; participants rated depressive symptoms they had experienced during the previous week (average α = .91).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-0146167211432762">
<title>Covariate</title>
<p>Although no assessment of self-esteem was included in any Study 2 survey, physical symptoms were assessed at each wave with 18 items derived from several reports based on their appropriateness for the sample (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0146167211432762">Andersen &amp; Tewfik, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0146167211432762">Ganz, Dau, Ware, Redman, &amp; Fisher, 1995</xref>). Symptoms included nausea, breast pain, hair loss, weight gain, hot flashes, itchiness or discomfort of the skin, decreased arm mobility, and swelling of the arm (average α = .81). A 7-point response scale was used (1 = <italic>not at all</italic>, 7 = <italic>severe</italic>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section28-0146167211432762">
<title>Results and Discussion</title>
<sec id="section29-0146167211432762">
<title>Descriptive statistics</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0146167211432762">Table 2</xref> presents correlations among autonomy NS, relatedness NS, and competence NS within each social role at each wave, as well as bivariate associations among positive affective balance and depressive symptoms.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0146167211432762" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Study 2 Descriptive Statistics and Total Score Correlations for Primary Study Measures</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0146167211432762" xlink:href="10.1177_0146167211432762-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Wave 1</th>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Wave 2</th>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Wave 3</th>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Wave 4</th>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Wave 5</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Aut</th>
<th align="center">Rel</th>
<th align="center">Com</th>
<th align="center">Aff</th>
<th align="center">Dep</th>
<th align="center">Aut</th>
<th align="center">Rel</th>
<th align="center">Com</th>
<th align="center">Aff</th>
<th align="center">Dep</th>
<th align="center">Aut</th>
<th align="center">Rel</th>
<th align="center">Com</th>
<th align="center">Aff</th>
<th align="center">Dep</th>
<th align="center">Aut</th>
<th align="center">Rel</th>
<th align="center">Com</th>
<th align="center">Aff</th>
<th align="center">Dep</th>
<th align="center">Aut</th>
<th align="center">Rel</th>
<th align="center">Com</th>
<th align="center">Aff</th>
<th align="center">Dep</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="26">Spousal role</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rel</td>
<td>.68</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.74</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.73</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.72</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.76</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Com</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.65</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.66</td>
<td>.72</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.68</td>
<td>.69</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.72</td>
<td>.66</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.71</td>
<td>.75</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Aff</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td>.39</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td>.47</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.55</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td>.50</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>.62</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td>.47</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Dep</td>
<td>−.40</td>
<td>−.45</td>
<td>−.43</td>
<td>−.67</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.41</td>
<td>−.49</td>
<td>−.50</td>
<td>−.72</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.49</td>
<td>−.51</td>
<td>−.56</td>
<td>−.81</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.52</td>
<td>−.46</td>
<td>−.57</td>
<td>−.81</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.49</td>
<td>−.49</td>
<td>−.48</td>
<td>−.76</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>M</italic></td>
<td>5.44</td>
<td>5.53</td>
<td>5.25</td>
<td>0.37</td>
<td>1.60</td>
<td>5.41</td>
<td>5.52</td>
<td>5.44</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>1.53</td>
<td>5.43</td>
<td>5.57</td>
<td>5.49</td>
<td>1.20</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>5.43</td>
<td>5.45</td>
<td>5.40</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>1.53</td>
<td>5.37</td>
<td>5.34</td>
<td>5.49</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>1.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>SD</italic></td>
<td>1.39</td>
<td>1.44</td>
<td>1.34</td>
<td>1.38</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>1.44</td>
<td>1.56</td>
<td>1.32</td>
<td>1.41</td>
<td>0.51</td>
<td>1.53</td>
<td>1.43</td>
<td>1.33</td>
<td>1.49</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>1.47</td>
<td>1.49</td>
<td>1.39</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>1.51</td>
<td>1.70</td>
<td>1.27</td>
<td>1.43</td>
<td>0.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>n</italic></td>
<td>175</td>
<td>175</td>
<td>175</td>
<td>209</td>
<td>211</td>
<td>162</td>
<td>162</td>
<td>162</td>
<td>192</td>
<td>192</td>
<td>160</td>
<td>160</td>
<td>160</td>
<td>188</td>
<td>191</td>
<td>149</td>
<td>149</td>
<td>149</td>
<td>182</td>
<td>182</td>
<td>132</td>
<td>132</td>
<td>133</td>
<td>148</td>
<td>149</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="26">Parental role</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rel</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.72</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.70</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.74</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.47</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Com</td>
<td>.51</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.75</td>
<td>.71</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.75</td>
<td>.66</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.72</td>
<td>.76</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.58</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Aff</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.51</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td>.53</td>
<td>.50</td>
<td>.53</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td>.36</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td>.37</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Dep</td>
<td>−.42</td>
<td>−.43</td>
<td>−.46</td>
<td>−.67</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.56</td>
<td>−.54</td>
<td>−.60</td>
<td>−.72</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.59</td>
<td>−.56</td>
<td>−.57</td>
<td>−.81</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.36</td>
<td>−.47</td>
<td>−.55</td>
<td>−.81</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.41</td>
<td>−.37</td>
<td>−.45</td>
<td>−.76</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>M</italic></td>
<td>5.73</td>
<td>6.10</td>
<td>5.83</td>
<td>0.37</td>
<td>1.60</td>
<td>5.79</td>
<td>6.12</td>
<td>5.85</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>1.53</td>
<td>5.84</td>
<td>6.14</td>
<td>5.95</td>
<td>1.20</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>5.82</td>
<td>6.18</td>
<td>5.96</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>1.53</td>
<td>5.81</td>
<td>6.12</td>
<td>5.97</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>1.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>SD</italic></td>
<td>1.23</td>
<td>1.11</td>
<td>1.14</td>
<td>1.38</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>1.22</td>
<td>1.14</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>1.41</td>
<td>0.51</td>
<td>1.26</td>
<td>1.13</td>
<td>1.15</td>
<td>1.49</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>1.12</td>
<td>0.96</td>
<td>1.07</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>1.06</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.03</td>
<td>1.43</td>
<td>0.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>n</italic></td>
<td>170</td>
<td>169</td>
<td>170</td>
<td>209</td>
<td>211</td>
<td>148</td>
<td>148</td>
<td>149</td>
<td>192</td>
<td>192</td>
<td>143</td>
<td>143</td>
<td>142</td>
<td>188</td>
<td>191</td>
<td>133</td>
<td>133</td>
<td>133</td>
<td>182</td>
<td>182</td>
<td>126</td>
<td>126</td>
<td>128</td>
<td>148</td>
<td>149</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="26">Worker role</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rel</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.65</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.75</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.73</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.72</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Com</td>
<td>.50</td>
<td>.69</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.67</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.65</td>
<td>.61</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.75</td>
<td>.60</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.58</td>
<td>.50</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Aff</td>
<td>.31</td>
<td>.41</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.47</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td>.54</td>
<td>.47</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td>.53</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>.51</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td>.23</td>
<td>.23</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Dep</td>
<td>−.42</td>
<td>−.50</td>
<td>−.53</td>
<td>−.67</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.53</td>
<td>−.56</td>
<td>−.58</td>
<td>−.72</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.50</td>
<td>−.48</td>
<td>−.48</td>
<td>−.81</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.52</td>
<td>−.49</td>
<td>−.51</td>
<td>−.81</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.39</td>
<td>−.32</td>
<td>−.42</td>
<td>−.76</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>M</italic></td>
<td>5.51</td>
<td>5.59</td>
<td>5.70</td>
<td>0.37</td>
<td>1.60</td>
<td>5.61</td>
<td>5.58</td>
<td>6.00</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>1.53</td>
<td>5.49</td>
<td>5.52</td>
<td>5.92</td>
<td>1.20</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>5.59</td>
<td>5.68</td>
<td>6.00</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>1.53</td>
<td>5.66</td>
<td>5.71</td>
<td>6.16</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>1.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>SD</italic></td>
<td>1.27</td>
<td>1.35</td>
<td>1.23</td>
<td>1.38</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>1.32</td>
<td>1.40</td>
<td>1.02</td>
<td>1.41</td>
<td>0.51</td>
<td>1.33</td>
<td>1.41</td>
<td>1.09</td>
<td>1.49</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>1.26</td>
<td>1.22</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>1.30</td>
<td>1.22</td>
<td>0.96</td>
<td>1.43</td>
<td>0.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>n</italic></td>
<td>166</td>
<td>166</td>
<td>167</td>
<td>209</td>
<td>211</td>
<td>140</td>
<td>140</td>
<td>140</td>
<td>192</td>
<td>192</td>
<td>144</td>
<td>144</td>
<td>144</td>
<td>188</td>
<td>191</td>
<td>143</td>
<td>143</td>
<td>143</td>
<td>182</td>
<td>182</td>
<td>129</td>
<td>129</td>
<td>129</td>
<td>148</td>
<td>149</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0146167211432762">
<p>Aut = autonomy need satisfaction (NS); Rel = relatedness NS; Com = competence NS; Aff = positive affective balance; Dep = depressive symptoms. All correlations are significant at <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section30-0146167211432762">
<title>Structural Equation Models</title>
<sec id="section31-0146167211432762">
<title>Model description</title>
<p>The proposed, between-person mediation models were tested using MPlus 5.2. Missing data were handled through full-information maximum likelihood estimation (FIML; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0146167211432762">Collins, Schafer, &amp; Kam, 2001</xref>). We used state-trait models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0146167211432762">Eid, Notz, Steyer, &amp; Schwenkmezger, 1994</xref>) to test the magnitude of aggregate longitudinal effects within each of the three central roles. These models were used to test associations between individual differences in need fulfillment and aggregate psychological health outcomes during cancer survivorship. We expected that, considering all three psychological needs, average levels of role-related competence NS would most strongly relate to increased positive affective balance and decreased depressive symptoms, respectively.</p>
<p>State-trait models specified five latent variables for each social role: trait of feelings of autonomy, relatedness, and competence NS; the tendency to experience positive affect relative to negative affect; and the tendency to experience depressive symptoms. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0146167211432762">Figures 2</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0146167211432762">4</xref>, model fit was good to adequate across all models.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0146167211432762">8</xref></sup> Wave 1 assessments, corresponding to patients’ period of active radiation treatment, exhibited consistently lower factor loadings.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0146167211432762" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Study 2 state-trait mediation models for need satisfaction within the spousal role</p>
<p>NS = need satisfaction; W = wave; CFI = comparative fit index; TLI = Tucker–Lewis index; SRMR = standardized root mean square residual. Standardized coefficients are provided. Not depicted are within-time correlations between all manifest variables assessed at the same time point. Self-reported physical symptoms were negatively related to role-related autonomy NS (β = –.28**), relatedness NS (β = –.31**), and competence NS (β = –.25**) in models predicting positive affective balance (β = –.28*). Self-reported physical symptoms were negatively related to role-related autonomy NS (β = –.27**), relatedness NS (β = –.29**), and competence NS (β = –.26**) in models predicting depressive symptoms (β = .37***).</p>
<p>†<italic>p</italic> &lt; .10. *<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0146167211432762-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-0146167211432762" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Study 2 state-trait mediation models for need satisfaction within the parental role</p>
<p>NS = need satisfaction; W = wave; CFI = comparative fit index; TLI = Tucker–Lewis index; SRMR = standardized root mean square residual. Standardized coefficients are provided. Not depicted are within-time correlations between all manifest variables assessed at the same time point. Self-reported physical symptoms were negatively related to role-related autonomy NS (β = –.23*), relatedness NS (β = –.35***), and competence NS (β = –.14*) in models predicting positive affective balance (β = –.28***). Self-reported physical symptoms were negatively related to role-related autonomy NS (β = –.21*), relatedness NS (β = –.35***), and competence NS (β = –.14*) in models predicting depressive symptoms (β = .32***).</p>
<p>*<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0146167211432762-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-0146167211432762" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Study 2 state-trait mediation models for need satisfaction within the worker role</p>
<p>NS = need satisfaction; W = wave; CFI = comparative fit index; TLI = Tucker–Lewis index; SRMR = standardized root mean square residual. Standardized coefficients are provided. Not depicted are within-time correlations between all manifest variables assessed at the same time point. Self-reported physical symptoms were negatively related to role-related autonomy NS (β = –.24), relatedness NS (β = –.40**), and competence NS (β = –.21*) in models predicting positive affective balance (β = –.29*). Self-reported physical symptoms were negatively related to role-related autonomy NS (β = –.20), relatedness NS (β = –.37***), and competence NS (β = –.21**) in models predicting depressive symptoms (β = .31***).</p>
<p>*<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0146167211432762-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section32-0146167211432762">
<title>Model outcomes</title>
<p>Similar to Study 1, aggregate reports of relatedness and autonomy NS were highly correlated within all role domains. Nevertheless, we modeled them as separate latent factors to understand the contribution of each type of NS. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0146167211432762">Figure 2</xref> shows the path coefficients for the primary mediation model within the spousal role. As expected, patients who reported higher average levels of relatedness NS within the spousal role were also likely to report higher average levels of competence NS. Patients who endorsed higher feelings of autonomy within the spousal role also reported marginally higher average levels of competence NS. As shown in the upper panel of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0146167211432762">Figure 2</xref>, patients’ trait-level feelings of competence NS within the spousal role were, in turn, related to higher levels of positive affective balance throughout survivorship. By contrast, as shown in the lower panel of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0146167211432762">Figure 2</xref>, patients who generally reported higher levels of autonomy NS in the spousal role were those who endorsed lower levels of depressive symptoms on average, whereas average levels of competence NS and relatedness NS were unrelated to reports of depressive symptoms.</p>
<p>PRODCLIN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0146167211432762">MacKinnon, Fritz, et al., 2007</xref>) was used to provide estimates of the confidence intervals around indirect effects. Estimates of indirect effects provided evidence that the relation between aggregate levels of relatedness NS and positive affective balance was explained via average levels of competence NS in the spousal role, αβ = .18, <italic>SE = .</italic>09, 95% CI [.04, .38], <italic>p &lt; .</italic>05. Notably, when simultaneously considering aggregate levels of relatedness NS and competence NS in the spousal role, neither the direct association between autonomy NS and positive affective balance nor the indirect effect via competence NS, was significant, αβ = .10, <italic>SE = .</italic>07, 95% CI [–.02, .26], <italic>ns.</italic> Unexpectedly, average levels of competence NS in the spousal role did not appear to mediate the relation between trait-level satisfaction of other basic needs and tendencies for depression.</p>
<p>A test of alternative models in which average levels of relatedness NS and autonomy NS were considered, respectively, as the primary mediator would fit the data equally well (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-0146167211432762">Tomarken &amp; Waller, 2003</xref>). Indeed, direct effects in the alternative models would be the same as those depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0146167211432762">Figures 2</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0146167211432762">4</xref>. Estimations of indirect effects for alternative models are contained in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0146167211432762">Table 3</xref>. For the spousal role, findings suggested that trait-level competence NS could best account for the shared association between mean-level feelings of relatedness NS and tendencies toward affective balance. By contrast, results showed that trait-level perceptions of autonomy NS in the spousal role, as opposed to competence NS, seemed most important in terms of accounting for the shared association between individual differences in feelings of relatedness NS and lessened depression, on average, during survivorship.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0146167211432762" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Study 2 Indirect Effects From Primary and Alternative State-Trait Mediation Models for Positive Affective Balance and Depressive Symptoms</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0146167211432762" xlink:href="10.1177_0146167211432762-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="6">Positive affective balance</th>
<th align="center" colspan="6">Depressive symptoms</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Via competence NS<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0146167211432762">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Via autonomy NS</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Via relatedness NS</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Via competence NS</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Via autonomy NS</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Via relatedness NS</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">αβ</th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">αβ</th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">αβ</th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">αβ</th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">αβ</th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">αβ</th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="13">Spousal role</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Competence NS</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>−.00</td>
<td>.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Autonomy NS</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>−.02</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Relatedness NS</td>
<td><bold>.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0146167211432762">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>.09</bold></td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td><bold>–.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0146167211432762">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>.05</bold></td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13">Parental role</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Competence NS</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td><bold>–.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0146167211432762">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>.06</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Autonomy NS</td>
<td><bold>.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0146167211432762">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>.19</bold></td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.15</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td><bold>–.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0146167211432762">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>.06</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Relatedness NS</td>
<td><bold>.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0146167211432762">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>.18</bold></td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13">Worker role</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Competence NS</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>.17</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Autonomy NS</td>
<td><bold>.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0146167211432762">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>.20</bold></td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td><bold>–.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0146167211432762">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>.07</bold></td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Relatedness NS</td>
<td><bold>.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0146167211432762">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>.10</bold></td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td><bold>–.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0146167211432762">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>.04</bold></td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0146167211432762">
<p>NS = need satisfaction. Unstandardized indirect coefficients (αβ) are presented. Bolded values are statistically significant, using PRODCLIN to determine which estimates were contained in asymmetric confidence intervals not including 0.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0146167211432762">
<label>a</label>
<p>“Via” indicates the need satisfaction variable that was considered as the mediator in the corresponding column analyses.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0146167211432762">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>As predicted and shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0146167211432762">Figure 3</xref>, patients who reported higher average levels of autonomy NS and relatedness NS within the parental role were more likely to report higher average levels of role-related competence NS. Shown in the upper panel, patients who felt higher levels of competence NS, on average, within the parental role were likely to report higher overall levels of positive affective balance. By contrast and as depicted in the lower panel, patients who reported elevated trait-level feelings of relatedness NS within the parental role were those who reported lower levels of depression throughout the first 2 years of cancer survivorship, whereas patients’ trait levels of competence and autonomy NS in this role were unrelated to overall levels of depression during this time.</p>
<p>Indirect effects provided evidence that the relation between trait-level feelings of relatedness NS and positive affective balance, αβ = .35, <italic>SE = .</italic>18, 95% CI [.06, .75], <italic>p &lt; .</italic>05, as well as autonomy NS and positive affective balance, αβ = .39, <italic>SE = .</italic>19, 95% CI [.07, .82], <italic>p &lt; .</italic>05, could both be explained through average levels of competence NS in the parental role. By contrast, individual differences in perceptions of relatedness NS in the parental role seemed most important in terms of accounting for associations between average feelings of autonomy and competence NS and the tendency to report lessened depression.</p>
<p>For the parental role, a comparison of alternative models suggested that the hypothesized model was preferred when considering affective balance. By contrast, average reports of relatedness NS in the parental role seemed to most proximally relate to a lower likelihood for depressive symptoms during survivorship.</p>
<p>As predicted and shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0146167211432762">Figure 4</xref>, patients who endorsed higher average levels of autonomy NS and relatedness NS within the worker role were more likely to report higher average levels of competence NS. Patients who endorsed higher levels of competence NS, on average, within the worker role were likely to report higher trait-like levels of positive affective balance and lower trait-like levels of depression during survivorship.</p>
<p>An examination of indirect effects provided evidence that the mean-level associations between autonomy NS and positive affective balance, αβ = .35, <italic>SE = .</italic>20, 95% CI [.004, .78], <italic>p &lt; .</italic>05, as well as depression, αβ = –.15, <italic>SE = .</italic>07, 95% CI [–.30, –.02], <italic>p &lt; .</italic>05, could be explained through their relation to individual differences in feelings of competence NS in the worker role, respectively. Similarly, the average relations between relatedness NS and positive affective balance, αβ = .15, <italic>SE = .</italic>10, 95% CI [.003, .38], <italic>p &lt; .</italic>05, as well as depression, αβ = –.06, <italic>SE = .</italic>04, 95% CI [–.15, –.01], <italic>p &lt; .</italic>05, could be explained via associations with trait-like feelings of competence NS in this role. A comparison of alternative models suggested that among the three psychological needs, competence NS within the worker role was the most consistent, proximal associate of higher tendencies for psychological health during survivorship.</p>
<p>The results of state-trait models revealed individual difference associations that were consistent with hypotheses, largely with regard to average levels of positive affective balance. Comparing standardized effects across social roles, findings showed that patients who reported higher trait-like feelings of relatedness NS during survivorship were those who were likely to feel higher competence NS with regard to their spousal role, and this was likely to relate to higher average levels of positive affect relative to negative affect. Patients who reported higher trait-like feelings of relatedness NS and autonomy NS in the parental role during survivorship were more likely to feel more competent in this role, on average. These individual differences in feelings of competence NS were likely to contribute to greater feelings of positive affect relative to negative affect throughout survivorship. Finally, average levels of autonomy and relatedness NS within the worker role were uniquely related to higher average levels of competence NS that were, in turn, related to higher trait-like levels of positive affective balance and lower trait-like levels of depression.</p>
<p>Similar to Study 1, evidence for our hypotheses was stronger when examining positive affective balance, suggesting that trait-like feelings of competence within social roles may be most proximally related to individuals’ levels of affective health (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick et al., 2007</xref>). With regard to the tendency to report depression, model findings were less consistent with expectations. Indeed, only trait-like levels of competence NS within the worker role were found to explain aggregate relations between the other psychological needs and depressive symptoms.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section33-0146167211432762">
<title>Multilevel Analyses</title>
<sec id="section34-0146167211432762">
<title>Model description</title>
<p>We conducted a series of hierarchical linear models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0146167211432762">Raudenbush &amp; Bryk, 2002</xref>) to examine within-person associations of interest. Multilevel modeling is a suitable technique for testing our process-oriented hypothesis because it has the capacity to model each participant’s own regression line, which may or may not differ from the average regression line.</p>
<p>Two-level models were constructed using HLM2 version 6.04 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0146167211432762">Raudenbush, Bryk, Cheong, Congdon, &amp; du Toit, 2004</xref>), with five waves (Level 1) nested within 208 individuals (3 patients in the full sample were missing Level 2 covariates and were eliminated from analyses). Three models examined whether role-related autonomy NS and relatedness NS were independently associated with role-related competence NS within each social role. Six models tested whether role-related autonomy NS and relatedness NS were independently associated with positive affective balance and depressive symptoms within each social role. Finally, six models examined whether the inclusion of role-related competence NS altered these associations. As before, FIML was used to obtain estimates.</p>
<p>All models followed the same structure. Predictors of positive affective balance and depressive symptoms were represented through separate two-level models in which within-person, time-varying variables (role-related autonomy NS, relatedness NS, and competence NS) were entered at Level 1. Between-person covariates were entered at Level 2 and included the average level of self-reported physical symptoms across all measurement occasions and the mean-level counterpart of the time-varying predictors<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0146167211432762">9</xref></sup> (i.e., average level of role-related autonomy, relatedness, and competence NS within social roles across time). The main effects of positive affective balance and depressive symptoms were modeled as random variables. Level 1 variables were person-mean centered. Level 2 variables were grand-mean centered.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section35-0146167211432762">
<title>Model outcomes</title>
<p>All HLM model results are provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0146167211432762">Table 4</xref>. As expected, findings showed that a patient’s ratings of autonomy NS and relatedness NS were positively related to her own reports of competence NS in the spousal role. Within-person results showed that a patient in a spousal role who reported greater levels of autonomy NS than were typical for her would also be likely to report levels of positive affective balance that were elevated above her average. This outcome was only marginally likely for a patient who might report greater levels of relatedness NS than were typical for her. By contrast, a patient who reported greater levels of relatedness NS than were typical for her in the spousal role would be likely to report lower levels of depressive symptoms. Her perceptions of autonomy NS within the spousal role were marginally related her own lowered endorsement of depressive symptoms.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0146167211432762" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Study 2 Multilevel Model Coefficients</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0146167211432762" xlink:href="10.1177_0146167211432762-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Role-related competence NS</th>
<th align="center" colspan="6">Positive affective balance</th>
<th align="center" colspan="6">Depressive symptoms</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center">(<italic>SE</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic> value</th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center">(<italic>SE</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic> value</th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center">(<italic>SE</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic> value</th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center">(<italic>SE</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic> value</th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center">(<italic>SE</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic> value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="16">Spousal role</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Autonomy NS</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>(.03)</td>
<td>11.44<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">***</xref></td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>(.03)</td>
<td>4.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">***</xref></td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>(.05)</td>
<td>1.90</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>(.01)</td>
<td>−1.67</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>(.01)</td>
<td>0.36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Relatedness NS</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>(.03)</td>
<td>8.99<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">***</xref></td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>(.05)</td>
<td>1.92</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>(.05)</td>
<td>0.15</td>
<td>−.10</td>
<td>(.01)</td>
<td>−4.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">***</xref></td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>(.01)</td>
<td>−2.62<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Competence NS</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>.15</td>
<td>(.05)</td>
<td>5.44<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>(.02)</td>
<td>−5.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="16">Parental role</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Autonomy NS</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td>(.03)</td>
<td>9.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">***</xref></td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>(.06)</td>
<td>2.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">*</xref></td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>(.06)</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>(.02)</td>
<td>−3.71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">***</xref></td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>(.02)</td>
<td>−2.81<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Relatedness NS</td>
<td>.26</td>
<td>(.03)</td>
<td>7.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">***</xref></td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>(.06)</td>
<td>3.69<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">***</xref></td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>(.06)</td>
<td>2.81<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">**</xref></td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>(.02)</td>
<td>−2.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">*</xref></td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>(.02)</td>
<td>−1.42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Competence NS</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>(.07)</td>
<td>2.82<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">**</xref></td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>(.02)</td>
<td>−2.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="16">Worker role</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Autonomy NS</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>(.04)</td>
<td>5.71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">***</xref></td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>(.05)</td>
<td>2.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">*</xref></td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>(.05)</td>
<td>1.04</td>
<td>−.08</td>
<td>(.02)</td>
<td>−2.77<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">**</xref></td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>(.02)</td>
<td>−1.93</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Relatedness NS</td>
<td>.31</td>
<td>(.04)</td>
<td>7.92<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">***</xref></td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>(.06)</td>
<td>3.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">**</xref></td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>(.06)</td>
<td>1.68</td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>(.02)</td>
<td>−2.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">*</xref></td>
<td>−.02</td>
<td>(.02)</td>
<td>−0.88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Competence NS</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>(.06)</td>
<td>4.58<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>−.08</td>
<td>(.02)</td>
<td>−3.71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0146167211432762">**</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn7-0146167211432762">
<p>NS = need satisfaction. Estimated coefficients are standardized. Coefficients for covariates in analyses predicting positive affective balance (physical symptoms: average β <italic>=</italic> –.35, <italic>SE = .</italic>11, <italic>p &lt; .</italic>001; aggregate NS: average β <italic>= .</italic>39, <italic>SE</italic> = .08, <italic>p &lt; .</italic>001) and depressive symptoms (physical symptoms: average β <italic>= .</italic>31, <italic>SE</italic> = .03, <italic>p &lt; .</italic>001; aggregate NS: average β <italic>= –</italic>.51, <italic>SE</italic> = .02, <italic>p &lt; .</italic>001) were similar across all three roles.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn8-0146167211432762">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Results supported hypotheses that feelings of competence NS in the spousal role could partially account for within-person associations between autonomy NS and relatedness NS and psychological outcomes. The mediation model in which feelings of autonomy NS, relatedness NS, and competence NS in the spousal role were simultaneously considered revealed that a patient who reported feelings of competence NS that were elevated above her average on any given measurement occasion was more likely to report a higher level of affective balance and a lower level of depressive symptoms than was typical for her. At the same time, associations between her feelings of autonomy NS and relatedness NS and her reports of affective balance, on any given occasion, were found to become unreliable. By contrast, the association between her feelings of relatedness NS and her reports of depressive symptoms only became relatively less reliable when competence NS was considered.</p>
<p>Despite the result that within-person analyses found that feelings of competence NS and relatedness NS both maintained independent associations with lowered levels of depression, competence NS in the spousal role was, in fact, the psychological need most strongly associated with heightened positive affective balance and lowered depression during cancer survivorship. These results were consistent with our hypotheses. Between-person findings were consistent with these within-person results, except with regard to depressive symptoms. In between-person analyses, patients who reported higher trait levels of autonomy NS within the spousal role were likely to report lower average levels of depression, whereas in within-person analyses, a patient’s feelings of autonomy NS at a given assessment were unrelated to her own reports of depressive symptoms.</p>
<p>With regard to the parental role, findings again showed that a patient’s ratings of autonomy NS and relatedness NS were positively related to her own reports of competence NS. A patient who reported greater levels of autonomy NS and relatedness NS in the parental role than were typical for her would also be likely to report levels of positive affective balance that were elevated. Also in line with hypotheses, a patient who endorsed greater levels of autonomy NS and relatedness NS in the parental role than were typical for her would report lower levels of depressive symptoms.</p>
<p>The model in which autonomy NS, relatedness NS, and competence NS were simultaneously considered revealed that a patient who reported perceptions of competence NS within the parental role that were elevated above her average would also be likely to endorse elevated levels of positive affective balance and lowered levels of depressive symptoms. Consistent with mediation, associations between her feelings of autonomy NS and relatedness NS and reports of positive affective balance were found to be less reliable when accounting for competence NS. These findings also suggested that feelings of competence NS and relatedness NS within the parental role were both uniquely important in contributing to her reports of positive affective balance during survivorship. Although associations between a patient’s feelings of autonomy NS and relatedness NS and her own reports of depressive symptoms became relatively less reliable when competence NS within the parental role was considered, endorsements of autonomy NS that were above her own average remained a unique predictor of her experiencing lower levels of depressive symptoms.</p>
<p>Within-person analyses showed that a patient’s feelings of competence NS and relatedness NS in the parental role were both independently associated with her own heightened levels of positive affective balance at any given assessment. By contrast, between-person analyses more strongly supported our hypothesis that patients’ feelings of competence NS in this role would be most proximally related to tendencies for heightened affective balance. With regard to depression, within-person analyses showed that a patient’s feelings of autonomy NS and competence NS in the parental role were independently and inversely associated with her own reports of depressive symptoms at any given assessment. Between-person analyses showed, however, that patients who reported higher trait levels of relatedness NS within the parental role would be those who would tend to report lowered levels of depression.</p>
<p>Within the worker role, a patient’s feelings of autonomy NS and relatedness NS that were higher than her average were positively related to contemporaneous reports of competence NS. As expected, a patient who reported greater levels of autonomy NS and relatedness NS in the worker role than were typical for her was also likely to endorse higher levels of positive mood relative to negative mood. Similarly, a patient’s reports of autonomy NS and relatedness NS in the worker role were inversely associated with her endorsements of depressive symptoms during survivorship.</p>
<p>The model in which autonomy NS, relatedness NS, and competence NS in the worker role were simultaneously considered revealed that a patient’s feelings of competence NS that were higher than her average were reliably associated with her own increased levels of affective balance and decreased levels of depressive symptoms. At the same time, associations between her reports of autonomy NS and relatedness NS within the worker role and endorsements of affective balance became unreliable. Similarly, when accounting for her feelings of competence NS within the worker role, the inverse associations between a patient’s reports of autonomy NS and relatedness NS and her experiences with depressive symptoms became unreliable. Thus, results were consistent with hypotheses.</p>
<p>With regard to the worker role, both between- and within-person analyses supported our mediation hypothesis that among the three basic psychological needs, trait-level and assessment-specific feelings of competence NS in this role would consistently be the most proximal contributor to greater endorsements of positive affective balance and fewer endorsements of depressive symptoms during cancer survivorship.</p>
<p>Analyses examining within-person fixed, indirect effects (not shown) conducted in PRODCLIN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0146167211432762">MacKinnon, Fritz, et al., 2007</xref>) confirmed that endorsements of competence NS accounted for significant within-person variation between reports of autonomy NS and relatedness NS and psychological health outcomes in examined social roles. This evidence was supported by 95% asymmetric confidence intervals that did not include zero although, consistent with between-person results, support for our assertion that competence NS in the parental role would be the most proximal contributor to contemporaneous reports of depressive symptoms was tenuous.</p>
<p>Within-person analyses confirmed that at any given assessment, a person’s perceptions of autonomy and relatedness NS within each of the three social roles were equally likely to inform her feelings of competence NS. These analyses also showed that patients’ feelings of competence NS within each of three social roles was consistently found to be either the strongest or an independent shared associate of psychological health in all within-person models. That is, results supported that a person’s own feelings of competence NS within a given role could serve to mediate, at least in part, significant relations between her feelings of autonomy and relatedness NS within roles and contemporaneous reports of psychological health. Notably and consistent with our between-person analyses, the mediation hypothesis was most often supported in models examining positive affective balance. These findings suggest that competence NS within social roles may be most proximally related to positive individual psychological outcomes, as opposed to negative individual psychological outcomes (e.g., depression).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section36-0146167211432762">
<title>General Discussion</title>
<p>Guiding human functioning and interactions, social roles are important for our daily lives (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0146167211432762">Kikuzawa, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-0146167211432762">Vandewater &amp; Stewart, 2006</xref>). Research (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211432762">Bettencourt &amp; Sheldon, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0146167211432762">La Guardia et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0146167211432762">Talley et al., 2010</xref>) has supported the assertion that social roles are functional mechanisms for meeting basic psychological needs, and as such, fulfilling social roles has the capacity to enhance psychological health. Although the three basic psychological needs identified by SDT have been viewed as equally important with regard to psychosocial functioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0146167211432762">Ryan &amp; Deci, 2000</xref>), work within social role domains has found evidence that certain need fulfillments may contribute differentially to functioning (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick et al., 2007</xref>). Borrowing from the tenets of social cognitive theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0146167211432762">Bandura, 1989</xref>), we proposed that when considering NS within role domains, competence NS would be the most proximal contributor to individual psychological health and would mediate, in part, associations between autonomy and relatedness NS and these same outcomes.</p>
<p>The current research is the first to provide formal tests of our hypotheses, showing that the satisfaction of competence needs within social roles may partially explain associations between the satisfaction of needs for autonomy and relatedness in these roles and psychological health. Study 1 provided initial support for our hypothesis across three social roles with a sample of healthy rural women. With five waves of data, Study 2 further supported our hypothesis with state-trait analyses that investigated between-person associations as well as multilevel analyses that examined within-person associations among breast cancer survivors. Extending the literature on psychological need fulfillment, we compared results for two separate indicators of psychological health, namely, affective balance and depression. Importantly, our mediation hypothesis was more strongly supported for affective balance than for depressive symptoms. This outcome seems congruent with Patrick et al.’s (2007) findings that show that of the three needs, competence was the most consistent predictor of positive well-being (i.e., positive affect, vitality) but not of negative affective outcomes.</p>
<p>The analytic approach in Study 2 allowed us to examine each of the three roles separately for the distinct contributions of autonomy and relatedness NS to competence NS. Between-person findings suggested that over time, feeling connected with one’s spouse during survivorship is more strongly associated with overall feelings of competency within the spousal role. By contrast, feelings of autonomy are likely to contribute to greater feelings of competency in the worker role during survivorship. Within-person analyses that examined interrelations among types of need fulfillment showed that at any given assessment, a person’s perceptions of autonomy and relatedness NS influenced feelings of competence NS within each of the three social roles.</p>
<p>Study 2 offered the unique opportunity to compare results across three valued social roles at the aggregate level and within person. For affective balance, findings were more similar than different across the three social roles in both between- and within-person analyses. Average levels of competence need fulfillment were largely found to account for relations between aggregate levels of autonomy and relatedness need fulfillment and affective balance within all three roles. Within-person findings showed that with regard to both spousal and worker roles, reports of competence need fulfillment that were elevated above one’s average on a given assessment occasion were found to explain associations between elevated feelings of autonomy and relatedness need fulfillment and levels of affective balance that were higher than expected.</p>
<p>With the exception of robust findings within the worker role, evidence for our hypothesis was often more tenuous when depressive symptoms were the outcome. It is possible that the formal, public appraisal of performance in the worker role, as well as the risk of losing the role and related benefits in instances where social role functioning is found to be substantially lacking, may explain the more consistent link between perceptions of competency NS in this role and overall depression. Individual differences in feelings of relatedness in the parental role seemed most important for alleviating depression during survivorship, whereas individual differences in feelings of autonomy appeared most important in the spousal role. Although within-person analyses suggested that a respondent’s satisfaction of autonomy and competence needs within the parental role were equally likely to influence depressive symptoms at any given time, satisfaction of relatedness and competence needs within the spousal role were equally important for this same outcome. It may be that depression is more independently and equally determined by relatedness, autonomy, and competence need fulfillment (i.e., as they are currently measured) within the parental and spousal roles, and thus, support for a consistent mediator was not found. In line with the latter argument, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick et al. (2007)</xref> found that all three needs were equivalently related to reports of negative affect in close relationships.</p>
<sec id="section37-0146167211432762">
<title>Theoretical Implications</title>
<p>The current studies are the first to formally test whether respondents’ feelings of competence within social roles mediate, in part, associations between feelings of autonomy and relatedness in these roles and psychological health. Importantly, the findings provided evidence for our hypothesis as well as for <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0146167211432762">Bandura’s (1989)</xref> theorizing that competence (i.e., self-efficacy) is a “cognitive mediator” of human motivation. The findings support our assertion that the satisfaction of needs for competence explain why the fulfillment of autonomy and relatedness needs in social roles contributes to psychological health, even in times of great duress. Also, it appears that feelings of autonomy and relatedness, acquired through the fulfillment of social roles, serve as important sources of information for feelings of competency.</p>
<p>Consistent with other SDT research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-0146167211432762">Véronneau, Koestner, &amp; Abela, 2005</xref>), we found evidence for conflation among the basic needs within each domain. Existing sources of methodological overlap in these constructs clearly present a problem for assertions that each is conceptually unique and meaningfully related to important psychological outcomes. Multicollinearity may reflect the inability of persons to disambiguate the sources of NS differentiated by the SDT framework. Indeed, the consistent need for clarification of the meaning of these constructs among academics (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0146167211432762">Carver &amp; Scheier, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0146167211432762">Deci &amp; Ryan, 2000</xref>) raises the larger question of whether most laypersons have access to distinctions between these aspects of need fulfillment. As such, methodological innovations may be required to better distinguish the three basic needs from each other. In addition to improving issues with multicollinearity among constructs, refining measurement of SDT constructs would also advance our understanding of the ways in which distinct sources of need fulfillment influence, in unique or similar ways, both positive and negative indicators of psychological health. Critically, participants’ inability to distinguish between sources of need fulfillment may have contributed to our equivocal pattern of findings with regard to depressive symptoms. Although some alternative models did not support that competence NS was a consistent, proximal determinant of depression, we expect that improved measures of NS would provide robust support for our theoretical assertions that competency within social role domains is a primary “cognitive mediator” of psychological health. Additional research is necessary to shed light on whether methodological innovations or theoretical refinements or both are necessary to advance SDT.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section38-0146167211432762">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>There are several imitations of these studies that should be considered. First, all participants were adult women fulfilling valued social roles (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0146167211432762">Abraido-Lanza, 1997</xref>). Although an advance over exclusively college-aged samples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211432762">Bettencourt &amp; Sheldon, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0146167211432762">La Guardia et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick et al., 2007</xref>), it is unclear whether our findings are generalizable to adult men or individuals fulfilling less valued social roles. A few studies of the psychological benefits of role fulfillment have found differential associations, depending on gender (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0146167211432762">Marcussen &amp; Piatt, 2005</xref>) and social role domains (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0146167211432762">La Guardia et al., 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Next, although the findings revealed that competence NS seems to, at least in part, explain meaningful variation between psychological health and autonomy and relatedness NS, we have yet to explore a broader range of potential explanatory mechanisms and outcomes. For example, feelings of autonomy and relatedness provided by social-role fulfillment may also be related to persons’ perceptions of meaning in life (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0146167211432762">Steger, Kawabata, Shimai, &amp; Otake, 2008</xref>). Future research may seek to examine additional explanatory mechanisms of relations between need fulfillment and psychological health.</p>
<p>As discussed previously, that ratings of NS within each social role were often highly correlated is another limitation. Consistent with our findings, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0146167211432762">Patrick et al. (2007)</xref> assessed basic psychological needs in romantic relationship domains and found correlations above .80 between ratings of autonomy and relatedness as well as between ratings of relatedness and competence across multiple samples (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-0146167211432762">Véronneau et al., 2005</xref>). It is plausible that these correlations are a result of semantic overlap within the items or assessing the constructs within the same time point. Items assessing NS all began with the phrase “When I carry out my role as . . .” This common method variance mostly likely contributed to inflation between scores. Additional research is necessary to determine how best to address this issue to allow for appropriate advancements in SDT.</p>
<p>The current work sought to examine the relation between role-related autonomy and relatedness NS as <italic>predictors</italic> of competence NS in social roles and, in turn, competence NS as a more proximal <italic>predictor</italic> of psychological health. Although the explicit modeling of directed effects of role-related psychological NS on psychological health that used multiple measurements to estimate between- and within-person relations between these constructs results is a better test of mediational hypotheses than cross-sectional data, because these data are correlational, conclusions must be based on strong theoretical ground (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0146167211432762">Cheong et al., 2003</xref>). It must be noted that the causal structure assumed by the proposed models may be fit equivalently by an infinite number of alternative models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0146167211432762">MacKinnon, Fairchild, &amp; Fritz, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-0146167211432762">Tomarken &amp; Waller, 2003</xref>). Despite these interpretational limitations, findings are bolstered by examinations of alternative models and arguments drawn from the literature documenting that feelings of competence should, theoretically, function as a mediator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0146167211432762">Bandura, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0146167211432762">Bunker, 1967</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0146167211432762">McCall &amp; Simmons, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0146167211432762">Stryker, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0146167211432762">Scott &amp; Stumpf, 1984</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section39-0146167211432762">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Social roles allow individuals to feel that they are acting on personal values and goals and, at the same time, are sharing unique aspects of themselves with others. As a result of these feelings, individuals seem to endorse that they are more effective in their roles and subsequently may experience improved affect and motivation. Individuals who do not experience feelings of need fulfillment within their held social roles are likely to be those most vulnerable to the experience of poor psychological health. The current findings suggest that interventions and therapies (e.g., cognitive-behavioral therapy; A. T. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0146167211432762">Beck, 1979</xref>; J. S. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211432762">Beck, 1995</xref>) that appreciate the importance of social roles as well as successfully bolster feelings of efficacy through role enactment may provide the most direct and powerful means of improving psychological health, especially when stressful life experiences disrupt social-role functioning.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We gratefully acknowledge the assistance of the staff at the Radiation Oncology Clinics, especially Linda Robb, as well as Laura King, Ken Sheldon, and Andrew K. Littlefield for their comments on earlier drafts of this manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article:</p>
<p>Data collection and manuscript preparation were supported by a grant from the National Cancer Institute (CA97916-01) and the National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (T32 AA13526).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0146167211432762">
<label>1.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0146167211432762">Scott and Stumpf (1984)</xref> posit that a sense of competence develops as a consequence of positive self-evaluated role performances, particularly in roles a person considers central to the self-concept. Empirical support for this assertion is provided by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0146167211432762">Elliot et al. (2000)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0146167211432762">
<label>2.</label>
<p>We anticipated that some of the older women in our sample might not have a formal worker/employee social role, but would otherwise be engaged in volunteer/service activity that would be analogous in some regard. For women with no formal worker role we determined, through open-ended responses, whether they were engaged in a volunteer role. If the volunteer role seemed analogous to worker roles (e.g., church volunteer, hospital volunteer), these were included in analyses. The number of women who had a formal worker role in Study 1 was 71, and the number of women who had a volunteer role that met the criteria was 18. The number of women who had a formal worker role in Study 2 was 127, and the number of women who had a volunteer role that met the criteria was 40.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0146167211432762">
<label>3.</label>
<p>This index is similar to approaches in the empirical literature that have combined reports of autonomy, relatedness, and competence into an overall assessment of “need satisfaction” (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0146167211432762">La Guardia, Ryan, Couchman, &amp; Deci, 2000</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0146167211432762">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Because of an unintentional error with the design of the survey, the last five items from the Center for Epidemiologic Studies–Depression Scale were not assessed.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0146167211432762">
<label>5.</label>
<p>Alternative models were run that considered role-related autonomy/relatedness as the mediator of the relation between role-related competence NS and psychological health. The unstandardized indirect effect was significant for positive affective balance, αβ = .55, <italic>SE = .</italic> 20, 95% CI [.17, .94], <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05, though the magnitude of the effect appeared smaller than that of the hypothesized model. By contrast, the magnitude of the indirect effect for the depressive symptoms outcome was equivalent in the alternative, αβ = –.18, <italic>SE = .</italic>06, 95% CI [–.30, –.05], <italic>p &lt; .</italic>05, and hypothesized models, suggesting all role-related need satisfaction variables were equivalent in their contributions to the experience of depressive symptoms.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0146167211432762">
<label>6.</label>
<p>An assessment of the importance of social roles was only included at Wave 3 in Study 2, approximately 3 months after patients’ initial radiation treatment. Female participants rated their worker role (<italic>M =</italic> 2.96, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.02) as being less important than either their parent (<italic>M</italic> = 3.84, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.54) or spouse (<italic>M</italic> = 3.72, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.72) roles, <italic>F</italic>(1, 76) = 52.10, <italic>p &lt; .</italic>001.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0146167211432762">
<label>7.</label>
<p>Notably, the original design of the study included only four assessments (Waves 1 to 4). An opportunity for additional data collection was acquired toward the end of the study. Ninety-four percent of participants who completed a Wave 4 survey agreed to receive more information about future studies. Of those who agreed and were sent a Wave 5 survey, 73% responded to the final survey (<italic>n</italic> = 128).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0146167211432762">
<label>8.</label>
<p>As per <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0146167211432762">Hu and Bentler’s (1999)</xref> recommendation, two goodness-of-fit indexes were used in assessing model fit: the comparative fit index (CFI; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0146167211432762">Bentler, 1988</xref>) and the standardized root mean square residual (SRMR; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0146167211432762">Bentler, 1995</xref>). Adequate fit is indicated by a CFI near .95 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0146167211432762">Hu &amp; Bentler, 1999</xref>). A reasonable SRMR is indicated by a value close to.08 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0146167211432762">Hu &amp; Bentler, 1999</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0146167211432762">
<label>9.</label>
<p>Including a mean-level, aggregate version of time-varying variables has been strongly recommended (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0146167211432762">Raudenbush &amp; Bryk, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0146167211432762">Snijders &amp; Bosker, 1999</xref>) because these effects often differ quite substantially from their time-varying, within-person counterparts. Unless these between-person differences are taken into account, mean-level differences between individuals on aggregate values of time-varying predictors might bias the estimation of Level 1 coefficients.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abraido-Lanza</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Latinas with arthritis: Effects of illness, role identity, and competence on psychological well-being</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Community Psychology</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>601</fpage>-<lpage>627</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adelmann</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Multiple roles and psychological well-being in a national sample of older adults</article-title>. <source>Journal of Gerontology</source>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>S277</fpage>-<lpage>S285</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Player ability, coach feedback, and female adolescent athletes’ perceived competence and satisfaction</article-title>. <source>Journal of Sport and Exercise Psychology</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>280</fpage>-<lpage>299</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Amorose</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Intrinsic motivation: Relationships with collegiate athletes’ gender, scholarship status, and perceptions of their coaches’ behavior</article-title>. <source>Journal of Sport &amp; Exercise Psychology</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Amorose</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P. J. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Feedback as a source of physical competence information: Effects of age, experience, and type of feedback</article-title>. <source>Journal of Sport &amp; Exercise Psychology</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>341</fpage>-<lpage>359</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tewfik</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Psychological reactions to radiation therapy: A reconsideration of the adaptive aspects of anxiety</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>1024</fpage>-<lpage>1032</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Denniston</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zabora</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Polland</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>W. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>A POMS short form for cancer patients: Psychometric and structural evaluation</article-title>. <source>Psycho-Oncology</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>273</fpage>-<lpage>281</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Human agency in social cognitive theory</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>1175</fpage>-<lpage>1184</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Self-efficacy: The exercise of control</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Freeman</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bardwell</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weingart</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dimsdale</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Fatigue varies by social class in African Americans but not Caucasian Americans</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Behavioral Medicine</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>252</fpage>-<lpage>258</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baruch</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Women’s involvement in multiple roles and psychological distress</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>135</fpage>-<lpage>145</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <source>Cognitive therapy and the emotional disorders</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>Cognitive therapy: Basics and beyond</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benoit-Smullyan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1944</year>). <article-title>Status, status types, and status interrelations</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bentler</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Comparative fit indexes in structural models</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>107</volume>, <fpage>238</fpage>-<lpage>246</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bentler</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>EQS structural equations program manual</source>. <publisher-loc>Encino, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Multivariate Software</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bettencourt</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Molix</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Talley</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Psychological need satisfaction through social roles</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Postmes</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jetten</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Individuality and the group: Advances in social identity</source> (pp. <fpage>196</fpage>-<lpage>214</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bettencourt</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Social roles as mechanism for psychological need satisfaction within social groups</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>1131</fpage>-<lpage>1143</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fobair</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spiegel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Varghese</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoppe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Social supports and the social well being of cancer survivors</article-title>. <source>Advances in Medical Sociology</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>114</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Borgatta</surname><given-names>E. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1961</year>). <article-title>The Make a Sentence Test (MAST): A replication study</article-title>. <source>Journal of General Psychology</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>292</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bradburn</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969</year>). <source>The structure of psychological well-being</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aldine</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bunker</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>). <source>Self-role congruence and status congruence as interacting variables in dyadic behavior</source> (<comment>Doctoral dissertation</comment>). <publisher-name>University of California</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Berkley</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carver</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scheier</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Autonomy and self-regulation</article-title>. <source>Psychological Inquiry</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>284</fpage>-<lpage>291</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cheong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacKinnon</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khoo</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Investigation of mediational processes using parallel process latent growth modeling</article-title>. <source>Structural Equation Modeling</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>238</fpage>-<lpage>262</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kam</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>A comparison of inclusive and restrictive strategies in modern missing data</article-title>. <source>Psychological Methods</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>330</fpage>-<lpage>351</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <source>Intrinsic motivation</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Plenum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>La Guardia</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moller</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scheiner</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>On the benefits of giving as well as receiving autonomy support: Mutuality in close friendships</article-title>. <source>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>313</fpage>-<lpage>327</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>A motivational approach to self: Integration in personality</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dienstbier</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Nebraska Symposium on Motivation, 1990: Perspectives on motivation</source> (pp. <fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>288</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Lincoln</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Nebraska Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The “what” and “why” of goal pursuits: Human needs and the self-determination of behavior</article-title>. <source>Psychological Inquiry</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>227</fpage>-<lpage>268</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Handbook of self-determination research</source>. <publisher-loc>Rochester, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Rochester Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gagné</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leone</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Usunov</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kornazheva</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Need satisfaction, motivation, and well-being in the work organizations of a former Eastern Bloc country: A cross-cultural study of self-determination</article-title>. <source>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>930</fpage>-<lpage>942</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Notz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steyer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwenkmezger</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Validating scales for the assessment of mood level and variability by latent state-trait analyses</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Faler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>W. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sedikides</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harackiewicz</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Competence valuation as a strategic intrinsic motivation process</article-title>. <source>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>780</fpage>-<lpage>794</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ganz</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dau</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Redman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Base-line quality-of-life assessment in National Surgical Breast and Bowel Project</article-title>. <source>Journal of the National Cancer Institute</source>, <volume>87</volume>, <fpage>1372</fpage>-<lpage>1382</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hagedoorn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanderman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bolks</surname><given-names>H. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tuinstra</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Distress in couples coping with cancer: A meta-analysis and critical review of role and gender effects</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>134</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oishi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Psychological needs and emotional well-being in older and younger Koreans and Americans</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>689</fpage>-<lpage>698</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Effectance motivation reconsidered</article-title>. <source>Human Development</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>34</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koka</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Perceived feedback and motivation in physical education and physical activity</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hagger</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chatzisarantis</surname><given-names>N. L. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Intrinsic motivation and self-determination in exercise and sport</source> (pp. <fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Champaign, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Human Kinetics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoskins</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bohlander</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bookbinder</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Budin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Maislin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Social support and patterns of adjustment to breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Research and Theory for Nursing Practice</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bentler</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Cutoff Criteria for Fit Indexes in Covariance Structure Analysis: Conventional Criteria Versus New Alternatives</article-title>. <source>Structural Equation Modeling</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ilardi</surname><given-names>B. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leone</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kasser</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Employee and supervisor ratings of motivation: Main effects and discrepancies associated with job satisfaction and adjustment in a factory setting</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Social Psychology</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1789</fpage>-<lpage>1805</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kikuzawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Multiple roles and mental health in cross-cultural perspective: The elderly in the United States and Japan</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health and Social Behavior</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>62</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Longitudinal study of social support and meaning in life</article-title>. <source>Psychology and Aging</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>456</fpage>-<lpage>469</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>La Guardia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Couchman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Within-person variation in security of attachment: A self-determination theory perspective on attachment, need fulfillment, and well-being</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>367</fpage>-<lpage>384</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>MacKinnon</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fairchild</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Mediation analysis</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Psychology</source>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>593</fpage>-<lpage>614</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>MacKinnon</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lockwood</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Distribution of the product confidence limits for the indirect effect: Program PRODCLIN</article-title>. <source>Behavior Research Methods</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>384</fpage>-<lpage>389</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marcussen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Piatt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Race differences in the relationship between role experiences and well-being</article-title>. <source>Health: An Interdisciplinary Journal for the Social Study of Health, Illness and Medicine</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>379</fpage>-<lpage>402</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <source>Identities and interactions: An examination of human associations in everyday life</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Measuring health: A guide to rating scales and questionnaires</source> (<edition>3rd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McNair</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lorr</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Droppelman</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <source>EDITS manual for the Profile of Mood States</source>. <publisher-loc>San Diego, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Educational and Industrial Service</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Milyavskaya</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gringas</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mageau</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koesnter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boiché</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Balance across contexts: Importance of balanced need satisfaction across various life domains</article-title>. <source>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>1031</fpage>-<lpage>1045</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muthén</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muthén</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Mplus</article-title> (<comment>version 5. 2</comment>). <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Statmodel</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Niemiec</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vansteenkiste</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The antecedents and consequences of autonomous self-regulation for college: A self-determination theory perspective on socialization</article-title>. <source>Journal of Adolescence</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>761</fpage>-<lpage>775</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Knee</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Canevello</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lonsbary</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The role of need fulfillment in relationship functioning and well-being: A self-determination theory perspective</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>92</volume>, <fpage>434</fpage>-<lpage>457</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pearlin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Role strains and personal stress</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Psychosocial stress: Trends in theory and research</source> (pp. <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Plach</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Psychological well-being in women with heart failure: Can social roles make a difference?</article-title> <source>Health Care for Women International</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>54</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Primo</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Compas</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oppedisano</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Epping-Jordan</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krag</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Intrusive thoughts and avoidance in breast cancer: Individual differences and associations with psychological distress</article-title>. <source>Psychology &amp; Health</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>1141</fpage>-<lpage>1153</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Radloff</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <article-title>The CES-D Scale: A self-report depression scale for research in the general population</article-title>. <source>Applied Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>385</fpage>-<lpage>401</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Raudenbush</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bryk</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Hierarchical linear models</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Raudenbush</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bryk</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheong</surname><given-names>Y. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Congdon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>du Toit</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>HLM6: Hierarchical linear and nonlinear modeling</source>. <publisher-loc>Lincolnwood, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scientific Software International</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>H. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>K. M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gable</surname><given-names>S. L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roscoe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Daily well-being: The role of autonomy, competence, and relatedness</article-title>. <source>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>419</fpage>-<lpage>435</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1950</year>). <article-title>Ecological correlations and the behavior of individuals</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1965</year>). <source>Society and the adolescent self-image</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Agency and organization: Intrinsic motivation, autonomy, and the self in psychological development</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Nebraska Symposium on Motivation: Developmental perspectives on motivation</source> (<volume>Vol. 40</volume>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Lincoln</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Nebraska Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Self-determination theory and the facilitation of intrinsic motivation, social development, and well-being</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>68</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>La Guardia</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Solky-Butzel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chirkov</surname><given-names>V. I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>On the interpersonal regulation of emotions: Emotional reliance across gender, relationships, and culture</article-title>. <source>Personal Relationships</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>146</fpage>-<lpage>163</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sarbin</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>V. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969</year>). <article-title>Role theory</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lindzey</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aronson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of social psychology</source> (<volume>Vol. 1</volume>, pp. <fpage>488</fpage>-<lpage>567</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Reading, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Addison-Wesley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schlegel</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Talley</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Molix</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bettencourt</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Rural breast cancer patients, coping and depression: A prospective comparison study</article-title>. <source>Psychology and Health</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>933</fpage>-<lpage>948</lpage>. DOI: 10.1080/08870440802254613<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08870440802254613</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stumpf</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Personal satisfaction and role performance: Subjective and social aspects of adaptation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>812</fpage>-<lpage>827</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Goal striving, need satisfaction and longitudinal well-being: The self-concordance model</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>482</fpage>-<lpage>497</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kasser</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>What is satisfying about satisfying events? Testing 10 candidate psychological needs</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>325</fpage>-<lpage>339</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niemiec</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>It’s not just the amount that counts: Balanced need satisfaction also affects well-being</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>331</fpage>-<lpage>341</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sintonen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The 15D instrument of health-related quality of life: Properties and applications</article-title>. <source>Annals of Medicine</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>328</fpage>-<lpage>336</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Snijders</surname><given-names>T. A. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bosker</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Multilevel analysis: An introduction to basic and advanced multilevel modeling</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Standage</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duda</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ntoumanis</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A test of self-determination theory in school physical education</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>411</fpage>-<lpage>433</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stanton</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danoff-Burg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sworowski</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Branstetter</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodriguez-Hanley</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Austenfeld</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Randomized, controlled trial of written emotional expression and benefit finding in breast cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Oncology</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>4160</fpage>-<lpage>4168</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steger</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kawabata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shimai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Otake</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The meaningful life in Japan and the United States: Levels and correlates of meaning in life</article-title>. <source>Journal of Research in Personality</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>660</fpage>-<lpage>678</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stryker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Identity theory: Developments and extensions</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Yardley</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Honess</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Self and identity: Psychosocial perspectives</source> (pp. <fpage>89</fpage>-<lpage>103</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tajfel</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <source>Human groups and social categories: Studies in social psychology</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Talley</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Molix</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schlegel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bettencourt</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The influence of breast cancer survivors’ perceived partner social support and need satisfaction on depressive symptoms: A longitudinal analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychology and Health</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>433</fpage>-<lpage>449</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tomarken</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>N. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Potential problems with “well-fitting” models</article-title>. <source>Journal of Abnormal Psychology</source>, <volume>112</volume>, <fpage>578</fpage>-<lpage>598</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vandewater</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Paths to late midlife well-being for women and men: The importance of identity development and social role quality</article-title>. <source>Journal of Adult Development</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>76</fpage>-<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vansteenkiste</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nyerinck</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niemiec</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soenens</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Witte</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van den Broeck</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>On the relations among work value orientations, psychological need satisfaction and job outcomes: A self-determination theory approach</article-title>. <source>Journal of Occupational and Organizational Psychology</source>, <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>251</fpage>-<lpage>277</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr84-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Verbrugge</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Multiple roles and physical health of women and men</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health and Social Behavior</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>16</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr85-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Véronneau</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koestner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abela</surname><given-names>J. R. Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Intrinsic need satisfaction and well-being in children and adolescents: An application of the self-determination theory</article-title>. <source>Journal of Social and Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>280</fpage>-<lpage>292</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr86-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Warr</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Paid employment and women’s psychological well-being</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>498</fpage>-<lpage>516</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr87-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tellegen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Development and validation of brief measures of positive and negative affect: The PANAS scales</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>1063</fpage>-<lpage>1070</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr88-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1959</year>). <article-title>Motivation reconsidered: The concept of competence</article-title>. <source>Psychological Review</source>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>297</fpage>-<lpage>333</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr89-0146167211432762">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wickrama</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conger</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>F. O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Role identity, role satisfaction, and perceived physical health</article-title>. <source>Social Psychology Quarterly</source>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>270</fpage>-<lpage>283</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>