<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DMS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdms</journal-id>
<journal-title>The Journal of Defense Modeling and Simulation: Applications, Methodology, Technology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1548-5129</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1557-380X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1548512911422240</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1548512911422240</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Evaluation of visual cues of three-dimensional virtual environments for helicopter simulators</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name><surname>Isler</surname><given-names>Veysi</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name><surname>Vural</surname><given-names>Fatos Yarman</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Çetin</surname><given-names>Yasemin</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yılmaz</surname><given-names>Erdal</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Çetin</surname><given-names>Yasemin Yardımcı</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1548512911422240">Middle East Technical University, Ankara, Turkey</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1548512911422240">Yasemin Çetin, METU, Informatics Institute, Information Systems Department, 06531, Cankaya, Ankara, Turkey. Email: <email>ycetin@ii.metu.edu.tr</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: USMOS Conference: Recent Research on Defence M&amp;S in Turkey</issue-title>
<fpage>347</fpage>
<lpage>360</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2011 The Society for Modeling and Simulation International</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">The Society for Modeling and Simulation International</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Visual cues are an essential part of helicopter flight simulators. The required cues for hover are particularly large, due to closeness to the ground and small movements. However, the research on low-altitude helicopter flight is limited. In this research, the density and height of the three-dimensional (3D) objects in the scene are analysed to find their effect on hovering and low-altitude helicopter flight. An experiment is conducted using a personal computer-based flight simulator on 10 professional military pilots. The results revealed that 3D object density and 3D object height affect both horizontal and vertical hovering performance. In hover and low-altitude flight, altitude control is positively affected by smaller object height. Paradoxically, the pilots preferred the scenes composed of tall and mixture objects. Pilot distance estimation was significantly affected by the knowledge of both object density and object height, but these factors do not individually improve distance estimation.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>flight simulator</kwd>
<kwd>helicopter</kwd>
<kwd>hover</kwd>
<kwd>low-altitude flight</kwd>
<kwd>three-dimensional object</kwd>
<kwd>visual cue</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1548512911422240" sec-type="intro">
<title>1. Introduction</title>
<p>Helicopter flight simulators are used in military, commercial and civil aviation for training, research and development. Simulators offer advantages to the users in terms of safety, availability, versatility and cost saving. They can also provide the opportunity for training in unlikely and emergency situations. Personal computer-based flight simulators (PC-FSs) are an alternative to enhanced flight simulators with their low cost and portability.</p>
<p>With the improvement in PC and Internet technologies, simulators have improved rapidly and are more widespread. Wider use also brings up new questions about simulators in terms of their reliability, validity and risks. Studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1548512911422240">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1548512911422240"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1548512911422240">3</xref></sup> show that PC-based simulators affect some stages of aircraft flight training positively. Examples of these stages are procedural training, recurrent training, instrument training and new tasks. However, lack of fidelity gives rise to longer training time and relearning of some manoeuvres.</p>
<p>D’Alessandro<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1548512911422240">1</xref></sup> conducted a literature survey about the effectiveness of PC-based simulators. He stated that previous studies indicate positive training transfer from PC-based simulators to real aircraft.</p>
<p>The negative transfer of training from the simulator to a real flight environment is a serious problem. Effective flight simulators provide pilots with cues that are equivalent to those of the real world. Therefore, the necessary visual and peripheral cues should be clarified in order to determine the effectiveness of PC-based flight simulators. Identification of the Out the Window Scene (OTWS) cues, adequate for performance and bringing minimum system load, is a concern for designing an optimized simulator balancing effectiveness and cost.</p>
<p>A significant amount of research has been done to investigate the required OTWS cues for low-altitude flight. Required OTWS constituents for low-altitude flight have been investigated by many researchers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1548512911422240">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1548512911422240"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1548512911422240"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1548512911422240"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1548512911422240"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1548512911422240"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1548512911422240"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1548512911422240"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1548512911422240"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1548512911422240"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1548512911422240"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1548512911422240">15</xref></sup> These studies mainly concentrate on essential visual cues for low-altitude, high-speed flight. However, the helicopter flight task differs from other aircraft in terms of altitude and speed. Hover, one of the most important helicopter flight tasks, is completely different from jet aircraft flight in terms of speed and altitude values. However, research on low-altitude helicopter flight is limited.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1548512911422240">1</xref></sup> The visual cues needed for hover are fairly high and detailed, because of the small movements closer to the surface. Karaahmetoğlu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1548512911422240">4</xref></sup> conducted an experiment by using a PC-based helicopter simulator used for hover. They claimed that terrain shape has a significant effect on drift performance, but that it does not affect the vertical hovering performance. Drift performance was improved with hilly terrain. In order to find the effect of visual level of detail (LOD) on altitude repositioning, Johnson et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1548512911422240">5</xref></sup> conducted an experiment by using AH-64 Apache helicopter simulation. They compared the LOD constancy (low, medium and high) and found that use of constant LOD improved the altitude estimation performance of pilots. Johnson and Stewart II<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1548512911422240">6</xref></sup> conducted a utility evaluation of a PC-based aviation training device for a helicopter flight simulator. After using the simulator for a specific task, the participants considered that simulators were not suitable for hovering in terms of peripheral visual cues, field of view (FOV) and visual cues to depth. Proctor et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1548512911422240">7</xref></sup> with 45 pilots, conducted an experiment to compare the motion, no motion and desktop platform for helicopter flight. The pilots complained about the detail of the terrain display. They needed more detailed terrain for more accurate speed and distance judgment in all three configurations.</p>
<p>This study investigates the effects of three-dimensional (3D) objects on helicopter flight performance of pilots for hover and low-altitude flight on a PC-based flight simulator. Density and height parameters of 3D objects are varied and the distance travelled (DT), altitude travelled (AT), distance estimation and speed estimation performance of the pilot are measured.</p>
<p>The results of this study can be used for determining the quality of the OTWS details required for hover and low-altitude helicopter flight. This information can in turn be used to design effective and cost-efficient simulators. They can also be used for the evaluation of pilot performance and training.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1548512911422240">
<title>2. Background</title>
<p>Previous studies on the effectiveness of OTWS constituents for low-altitude flight generally focused on crucial visual cues for low-altitude, high-speed flight. Only two of them<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1548512911422240">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1548512911422240">14</xref></sup> were conducted for helicopters and others were conducted for airplanes cruising at low altitudes. However, helicopter flight tasks differ from aircraft in terms of altitude and speed.</p>
<p>The seminal research in this domain is belongs to Kleiss.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1548512911422240">8</xref></sup> Using a multidimensional scaling analysis, he found that pilot performance at low-altitude flight is affected by three OTWS constituents. These are terrain shape, surface texture and 3D objects in the scene. He stated that object size, density and their spacing in the scene are the most prominent OTWS cues that pilots use during low-altitude flight. Therefore, we concentrated on the effect of 3D objects for helicopter flight tasks in this study. The related work on 3D objects can be grouped under four categories: object density, distribution of objects, object height and object type.</p>
<sec id="section3-1548512911422240">
<title>2.1 Object density</title>
<p>In order to determine the required object density for aircraft and helicopter flight, several experiments were conducted.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1548512911422240">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1548512911422240">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1548512911422240">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1548512911422240">15</xref></sup> This is included in the present study as well.</p>
<p>For the aircraft flight, with 10 experienced pilots at 600 knots and 150 feet above ground level (AGL), De Maio et al. (as cited by Chung<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1548512911422240">15</xref></sup>) found that 3D objects are useful for altitude estimation. They stated that 12–15 objects per mi<sup>2</sup> (= 4.63–5.79 objects per km<sup>2</sup>) are sufficient for maintaining altitude.</p>
<p>Kleiss,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1548512911422240">10</xref></sup> in his investigation with 12 professional pilots, tried the effects of 4, 17 and 67 objects per km<sup>2</sup> object densities on the pilots’ detection of altitude change. The percentage of correct response and reaction time improved when vertical 3D object density increased. The results of this study are similar to De Maio’s results. Participants in Kleiss’s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1548512911422240">10</xref></sup> study did not actively use the simulator, rather they responded to the altitude change via a joystick. Pongracic et al. [11] conducted a research in which participants used a three-channel simulator. The task was to keep an altitude of 100 metres (328.084 feet) AGL for three minutes. In a visual environment at a speed of 400 knots with 12 pilots, the duration of the deviation from 100 m altitude with ±20 m tolerance was measured. They found that more than four objects per km<sup>2</sup> was sufficient for altitude control. In addition, altitude control performance did not significantly increase with higher object density. This result was consistent with results of Kleiss and De Maio, in the sense that minimum required object density.</p>
<p>The above three studies were conducted for airplanes. The required altitude and speed are different for helicopter flight; therefore, the effect of object density could differ. Peitso<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1548512911422240">14</xref></sup> conducted an experiment with a PC-based helicopter simulator to determine the required object density for hovering. He found that 3D object density is effective on positional stability and perceived drift. He compared 1%, 0.25%, 0% density of 3D vegetation on pilots’ drift performance, where 1% refers to one object on average per 100 m<sup>2</sup>. He found that the required density for positional stability is around 1%.The altitude stabilization was not tested due to an implementation limitation of the flight simulator used in the experiment.</p>
<p>Except for Peitso’s work,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1548512911422240">14</xref></sup> these studies were carried out at high speeds that are not suitable for hovering. Furthermore, they only analyse the minimum essential object density. However, there can be a breaking point at which further increasing the 3D objects on the scene causes a decrease in the hovering performance. In addition, no study was found in the literature investigating the effect of object density on vertical hovering. Therefore, minimum and maximum object densities essential for lateral and longitudinal hovering should also be investigated. Similarly, these scene properties should be specified for low-altitude helicopter flights.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1548512911422240">
<title>2.2 Distribution of objects</title>
<p>Distribution of objects is another cue that affects flight performance. A study was conducted by Kleiss and Hubbard<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1548512911422240">9</xref></sup> to investigate the effect of object grouping on altitude perception at 450 knots and 150 feet initial altitude. Object grouping had three levels: no objects, evenly spaced objects and grouped objects. The results show that perception of altitude change was positively affected by object grouping. They also examined the effect of terrain shape and its interaction with object grouping. They found that the stand-alone terrain shape has no effect on altitude perception, whereas detection of altitude change was positively affected by the interaction of terrain shape and object grouping.</p>
<p>Another dimension of object distribution that is not studied is the type of spacing. Spacing can be random or even. It is conceivable that the vertical and horizontal positional offset can be detected more readily in evenly spaced scenes than randomly spaced scenes. The effect of random and uniform distribution of objects should be investigated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1548512911422240">
<title>2.3 Object height</title>
<p>Another visual cue that could be used during hover and low-altitude flight is object height. Pongracic et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1548512911422240">11</xref></sup> claimed that altitude control would improve if the height of the object increased. However, they did not carry out any experiment to prove this claim. Furthermore, we could not find a study that investigates the effect of 3D objects’ height in terms of uniformity, that is, scenes composed of equal height versus different height objects. Therefore, the effect of the height of objects should be investigated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1548512911422240">
<title>2.4 Object type</title>
<p>Object type was analysed by Kleiss<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1548512911422240">10</xref></sup> to clarify its effect on altitude perception at low-altitude flight. With a 150 feet initial altitude and 450 knot constant speed, he found that improving level of objects’ detail, that is, a tetrahedron (low-level detail) and a pine tree (high-level detail), did not affect the detection of altitude change performance of pilots. The altitude and speed values of this experiment were typical for jet aircraft, but are not suitable for hover. It is conceivable that object details can contribute to pilot performance for hover. The effect of details on the 3D objects on altitude perception at low-altitude flight and hovering performance should be compared.</p>
<p>Other OTWS constituents that affect pilot performance in conjunction with the object are surface texture and texture resolution. Kleiss<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1548512911422240">10</xref></sup> conducted an experiment that investigated if complex texture reduces the need for vertical object density to detect altitude change. He found that texture had a positive effect on determining altitude change, but it could not eliminate the vertical object requirement. Moreover, subjects detected altitude change more quickly and correctly when a vertical object was present.</p>
<p>Karaahmetoğlu et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1548512911422240">4</xref></sup> with 10 military pilots, conducted a PC-based helicopter simulation experiment with no 3D objects. They found that image spatial resolution did not affect the horizontal and vertical hovering when there were no identifiable two-dimensional (2D) objects on the scene surface. In addition, they found that terrain shape has a significant effect on drift performance, but it does not affect the vertical hovering performance. Drift performance was improved with hilly terrain.</p>
<p>We investigate the effects of 3D objects on the helicopter flight performance of pilots for hover and low-altitude flight on a PC-based flight simulator in this study. Density and height parameters of 3D objects are varied and the DT, AT, distance estimation and speed estimation performance of the pilot are measured. The actual performances of the subjects in a given scene are compared with their evaluations of the scene’s suitability for the given task.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1548512911422240" sec-type="methods">
<title>3. Method</title>
<sec id="section8-1548512911422240">
<title>3.1 Participants</title>
<p>Ten male professional helicopter pilots participated in the experiment. All participants had normal or corrected-to-the-normal vision. The mean age of participants was 28.9 (SD = 1.3, range = 27–33) and mean total flight hours was 1072 (SD = 293.4, range = 580–1850). Average elapsed time from last flight was 4.2 days (SD = 2.3, range = 1–7 days).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1548512911422240">
<title>3.2 Equipment</title>
<p>A PC-based flight simulator was constructed for our experiment by using commercially available hardware. The system was composed of one PC, three liquid crystal display (LCD) monitors, one graphics card for dividing the scene into three displays and flight controls, including a stick, a collective and a cyclic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1548512911422240">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1548512911422240">2</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>System overview.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Flight controls.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>X-Plane version 9.0 was used in this study. X-Plane is a flight simulator for PCs produced by Laminar Research. It is preferred<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1548512911422240">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1548512911422240">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1548512911422240">16</xref></sup> due to its flexible and realistic structure. Scenes of X-Plane are editable by the user. Once the new scenery is created, the locations of the 3D objects are specified by using the scenery editor. 3D mesh objects on the scene are edited by Google Sketch Up and added to the scene.</p>
<p>In the experiment, the instrument panel of the helicopter was not shown to the participants. In order to eliminate the effect of informational cues provided via flight instruments, such as the altimeter and barometer, the without HUD (Head up Display) view was chosen. The screen resolution was set to the 3840×1024. The helicopter type used in the experiment was an S-61 Sea King. The data of the flight, including time, speed, altitude and location, was recorded at one second intervals via the Data Input &amp; Output tool of X-Plane.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1548512911422240">
<title>3.3 Experimental design</title>
<p>The main factors of this experiment were 3D object height and density. As 3D objects, trees with identical shapes but different heights were used. 3D trees were placed on the scene with different orientations to eliminate the impression of the viewing the scene from the same point. The scenes vary according to the height and density of the trees used.</p>
<list id="list1-1548512911422240" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p><bold>Density:</bold> this experiment has four object density levels: 36 (=6<sup>2</sup>), 144 (=12<sup>2</sup>), 576 (=24<sup>2</sup>) and 1296 (=36<sup>2</sup>) objects per km<sup>2</sup>. The object density level ‘36 (=6*6) objects per km<sup>2</sup>’ can be interpreted as approximately six trees in each row and six rows for each 1 km<sup>2</sup> area. However, the trees were randomly distributed in the scene with samples from the uniform distribution.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Height:</bold> in this experiment the height of 3D objects has three levels: 2, 5 and 10 m.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Uniformity:</bold> this experiment has two uniformity levels for object height: uniform and non-uniform (mixture). At the uniform level, all trees have the same height. On the non-uniform level, a mixture of all three trees (2, 5 and 10 m) with the same probability is used in the same scene.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1548512911422240">
<title>3.4 Procedure</title>
<p>The experiments were scheduled as a single session according to the pilot’s schedule. The participants were informed about the purpose of the experiment. The windows of the room were closed with blinds and the room was illuminated with a lamp. The participants sat approximately at a distance of 80 cm from the centre monitor.</p>
<p>The experiment had four phases: pre-brief, familiarization, data collection and de-brief.</p>
<p>The pre-brief stage had two steps. In the first step, the subjects signed the consent form. This form includes the purpose and short information about the procedure of the experiment. In the second step, subjects filled the pre-questionnaire, which specifies gender, age, total flight hours, last flight time, most frequently used helicopter type, simulator experience and their opinion about fidelity and possible usage areas of flight simulators.</p>
<p>The familiarization stage consisted of approximately 10 minutes flight time on the simulator prior to data collection. The pilots started the experiment when they felt ready. Minimum familiarization time was 5 minutes and maximum was 19 minutes.</p>
<p>The experiment consisted of 16 treatments each for hover and low-altitude flight cases. In order to eliminate learning effect, the order of treatments for each subject was determined randomly and each subject participated in all treatments.</p>
<p>Each run had two parts: hovering followed by low-altitude flight. Before each run, the helicopter position was reset to the starting point.</p>
<p>In the hovering part, data recording was initiated after the subject took off for hover. DT and AT data were recorded for a duration of 2 minutes. The experimenter used a stopwatch and stopped the process after 2 minutes. The subject ranked the scenery from 1 to 5 (best to worst) according to its suitability for hover.</p>
<p>For the low-altitude flight part, the data recording was initiated after the subject took off for low-altitude flight. DT, AT, the speed and orientation of the helicopter were recorded. The recording stopped when the subjects said that the displacement from origin was 2 km. The subject evaluated the scenes from 1 to 5 (best to worst) according to its suitability for low-altitude flight and estimated the speed of the flight. These two parts were repeated for all 16 combinations: 12 (4 density * 3 height * 1 uniformity (uniform level)) and 4 (4 density * 1 uniformity (non-uniform level)).</p>
<p>The de-brief stage consisted of completing the post-questionnaire and the de-brief information form. The post-questionnaire form asked the opinion of the participants about the PC-based simulator used in the experiment and the performance in terms of ability to control the helicopter. The de-brief information form included the goal of the study and contact information for further information if needed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1548512911422240">
<title>3.5 Model</title>
<p>The independent variables of the experiment were object density (four levels), object height (three levels) and uniformity (two levels).</p>
<p>Two analyses were done for all performance measures. Firstly, four object density levels and three object height levels were analysed. Finally, the effect of the object height uniformity on the pilot performance was analysed. The significance level, ‘α’ value, was chosen as 0.05 for all analyses.</p>
<p>Before the pilot performance results were analysed, model adequacy was examined. Montgomery<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1548512911422240">17</xref></sup> rectified a method and gave a table for selecting the proper variance stabilizing transformation so that an analysis of variance (ANOVA) could be used. We used the above method while selecting the form of the transformation for each performance. Logarithm transformation was suitable for the DT, AT (hover) and AT (low-altitude flight) data. Square root transformation was suitable for the distance estimation error (DEE) data to stabilize residual variance to satisfy ANOVA’s assumption.</p>
<p>To verify that the randomization successfully eliminated the learning effect on hovering and low-altitude flight, an ANOVA was run on the transformed dependent variables (LOGDT and LOGAT for hover, and SQRTDEE and LOGAT for low-altitude flight). There was no influence of run order of the treatment on DT hovering performance, <italic>F</italic> (15, 135) = 1.22, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05, AT performance, <italic>F</italic> (15, 135) =1.56, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05, speed estimation error (SEE), <italic>F</italic> (15, 135) = 1.07, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05 or DEE, <italic>F</italic> (15, 135) = 1.73, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05. The order effect <italic>p</italic>-value of 0.006 indicates there was influence of order of the treatment on AT low-altitude performance, <italic>F</italic> (15, 135) = 2.30, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05. It is conceivable that if the pilots needed more time for familiarization on low-altitude flight, then they opted out.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1548512911422240" sec-type="results">
<title>4. Experiment results</title>
<p>Pilot performance was measured according to the flight type: hover and low-altitude flight.</p>
<sec id="section14-1548512911422240">
<title>4.1 Hovering</title>
<p>In each treatment, the vertical and the horizontal position of the helicopter was recorded every second for 2 minutes. Positions at 5-second intervals were calculated by averaging the data points. Two measures, DT and AT, were calculated for hover. Distances between averaged points were summed as DT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1548512911422240">Figure 3</xref>). AT data was calculated by summing absolute values of the distance between averaged points (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1548512911422240">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig3-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption><p>Calculation of distance travelled (DT) for hover.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption><p>Calculation of altitude travelled (AT) for hover.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Apart from the 5-second interval, DT and AT were calculated for 1-second and 10-second intervals and vertical and horizontal hovering performance were analysed. The results were examined to detect whether any difference caused by changing the duration of calculation would occur. No difference was observed in terms of significance effects of the factors on the performance. Results of the 5-second interval data are reported in this paper.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1548512911422240">
<title>4.2 Low-altitude flight</title>
<p>In each treatment, the vertical position, the horizontal position and the speed of flight were recorded at every second until the participant stated that the displacement was 2 km. DEE, AT and SEE were calculated as the performance measures of low-altitude flight.</p>
<p>The distance between the start and the end point was used to calculate how far the participant flew. The deviation from 2000 m is recorded as DEE. AT was calculated for the altitude data that were above the ½*Maximum Altitude for each run. The mean of the altitudes of the subject above the ½*Maximum Altitude was subtracted from the altitude and absolute values were summed as AT. Absolute values of the difference between the speed estimated by the participants and the one calculated by X-Plane data output was calculated as the SEE.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1548512911422240">
<title>4.3 Hover</title>
<sec id="section17-1548512911422240">
<title>4.3.1 Horizontal hovering performance</title>
<p>To investigate the effect of object density and object height on horizontal hovering performance, DT data was analysed.</p>
<p>An analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) was conducted with the covariance run order and the factors Object Density (four levels) and Object Height (four levels) on LOGDT. The covariate run order was not significantly related to the horizontal hovering performance, <italic>F</italic> (1,107) = 0.01, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05 There was a significant effect of height and density on horizontal hovering after controlling for the effect of run order, <italic>F</italic> (2, 107) = 3.52, <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.05 and <italic>F</italic> (3, 107) = 3.22, <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.05.</p>
<p>When a statistically significant main effect was found, Sidak corrected post hoc analysis was conducted for all the flight performances.</p>
<p>The post hoc test revealed that the horizontal hovering performance was significantly better with 576 objects per km<sup>2</sup>than with 144 objects per km<sup>2</sup>(<italic>t</italic> (29) = 2.70, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and with 2 m objects than with 10 m objects (<italic>t</italic> (39) = 2.60, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). It is shown in the main effects plot in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1548512911422240">Figure 5</xref> that, when the object height increased, the DT performance of the participant decreased. The best object height for horizontal hover performance was 2 m, the second was 5 m and the last was 10 m. The best object density for DT performance was 576 objects per km<sup>2</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1548512911422240">Figure 5</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig5-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption><p>Main effects plot for LOGDT versus Object Density (four levels) and Object Height (three levels).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Although object density and object height had significant effects on the DT performance of participants, their interaction was not significant, <italic>F</italic> (6, 107) = 0.29, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05.</p>
<p>Standard deviation scores for density and height levels of LOGDT and LOGAT for hover and SQRTDEE, LOGAT and SEE for low-altitude flight are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1548512911422240">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1548512911422240">2</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Standard deviation scores for density levels.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1548512911422240" xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">LOGDT</th>
<th align="left">LOGAT</th>
<th align="left">SQRTDEE</th>
<th align="left">LOGAT</th>
<th align="left">SEE</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><bold>36</bold></td>
<td>0.19</td>
<td>0.23</td>
<td>16.65</td>
<td>0.38</td>
<td>19.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>144</bold></td>
<td>0.22</td>
<td>0.37</td>
<td>14.46</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>18.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>576</bold></td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>0.42</td>
<td>15.44</td>
<td>0.34</td>
<td>14.47</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>1296</bold></td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td>0.43</td>
<td>16.81</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>19.69</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Standard deviation scores for height levels.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1548512911422240" xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Height</th>
<th align="left">LOGDT</th>
<th align="left">LOGAT</th>
<th align="left">SQRTDEE</th>
<th align="left">LOGAT</th>
<th align="left">SEE</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><bold>2</bold></td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>0.38</td>
<td>17.20</td>
<td>0.35</td>
<td>18.41</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>5</bold></td>
<td>0.22</td>
<td>0.43</td>
<td>13.93</td>
<td>0.32</td>
<td>17.42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>10</bold></td>
<td>0.23</td>
<td>0.26</td>
<td>16.03</td>
<td>0.27</td>
<td>18.21</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>In order to analyse the effect of uniformity on DT score, a <italic>t</italic>-test was conducted. There was no significant difference in the DT score for uniform (M = 3.054, SD = 0.22) and non-uniform (M = 3.042, SD = 0.24) conditions; <italic>t</italic> (158) = 0.284, <italic>p</italic> = 0.777. The mixture level (M = 3.042) was almost equal to 5 m object height level (M = 3.043). The object used in the mixture level was a combination of 2, 5 and 10 m objects and their mean height was 5.66 m. Therefore, it is not surprising that the mixture level performance was similar to that of the 5 m level.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1548512911422240">
<title>4.3.2 Vertical hovering performance</title>
<p>An ANCOVA was conducted with the covariance run order and the factors Object Density (four levels) and Object Height (three levels) on LOGAT. The covariate run order was not significantly related to the horizontal hovering performance, <italic>F</italic> (1,107) = 3.48, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05 There was a significant effect of height and density on horizontal hovering after controlling for the effect of run order, <italic>F</italic> (2, 107) = 9.91, <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.001 and <italic>F</italic> (3, 107) = 2.87, <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.05.</p>
<p>Although object density and object height had significant effects on the AT performance of participants, their interaction was not significant, <italic>F</italic> (6, 107) = 1.59, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05.</p>
<p>A post hoc test revealed that the vertical hovering performance was significantly better with 576 objects per km<sup>2</sup>than with 144 objects per km<sup>2</sup>(<italic>t</italic> (29) = 2.90, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05), with 2 m objects than with 10 m objects (<italic>t</italic> (39) = 4.27, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and with 5 m objects than with 10 m objects (<italic>t</italic> (39) = 3.29, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). It was shown in the main effects plot in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1548512911422240">Figure 6</xref> that when the object height increased, the vertical hovering performance of the participant decreased. The best object height was 2 m, the second was 5 m and the last was 10 m. The best object density for AT performance was 576 objects per km<sup>2</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1548512911422240">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig6-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption><p>Hover: main effects plot for mark versus Object Density and Object Height.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig7-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption><p>Main effects plot for LOGAT versus Object Density (four levels) and Object Height (three levels).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Specific altitude requirements of hover could also explain the superiority of smaller objects. As it is performed at 3–15 feet (~1–5 m), the objects that are smaller than the required height, such as 2 m, are seen from the top. The pilot would not need to avoid the objects during hover for 2 m trees. In addition, 5 m objects were almost equal to the hover altitude.</p>
<p>In order to analyse the effect of uniformity on AT score, a <italic>t</italic>-test was conducted. There was no significant difference in the AT score for uniform (M = 1.600, SD = 0.38) and non-uniform (M = 1.552, SD = 0.48) conditions; <italic>t</italic> (158) = 0.63, <italic>p</italic> = 0.53.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1548512911422240">
<title>4.3.3 Pilot evaluation of hover</title>
<p>After each hover flight run was complete, participants were asked the following question in written format: ‘How suitable is the scenery for “hovering”?’ The rating scale ranged from 1 = ‘Best for hovering’ to 5 = ‘Worst for hovering’.</p>
<p>An ANCOVA was conducted with the covariance run order and the factors Object Density (four levels) and Object Height (three levels) on pilot mark. The covariate run order was not significantly related to the vertical low-altitude flight performance, <italic>F</italic> (1,107) = 0.03, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05. There was also significant effect of height on pilot mark after controlling for the effect of run order, <italic>F</italic> (2, 107) = 5.66, <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.05. However, the effect of object density and object height and density interaction on pilot mark was not significant after controlling for the effect of run order, <italic>F</italic> (3, 107) = 2.11, <italic>p</italic> ≥ 0.05 and <italic>F</italic> (6,107) = 1.28, <italic>p</italic> ≥ 0.05.</p>
<p>A post hoc test revealed that pilot mark was significantly better with 10 m objects than with 2 m objects (<italic>t</italic> (39) = 3.353, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1548512911422240">Figure 7</xref> illustrates the main effects of pilot mark. It is seen that when the object height increased, pilot mark also improved. However, the actual pilot DT data revealed that the pilots’ performance was worst at 10 m. Pilots perform better at hovering (both in vertical and horizontal dimension) with small objects, whereas they ranked the scenes that contain small objects as the worst scenes.</p>
<p>Pilots thought that the scene with the higher object density was more suitable for hovering than that with the lower object density. However, this increase has a peak point after which increasing the object density decreases their remarks about the suitability of the scene for hovering. These results are in accordance with pilot performance.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-1548512911422240">
<title>4.4 Low-altitude flight</title>
<sec id="section21-1548512911422240">
<title>4.4.1 Horizontal low-altitude flight performance</title>
<p>In order to clarify the effect of object density and object height on horizontal low-altitude flight performance, DEE data was analysed.</p>
<p>An ANCOVA was conducted with the covariance run order and the factors Object Density (four levels) and Object Height (four levels) on LOGDT. The covariate run order was not significantly related to the horizontal hovering performance, <italic>F</italic> (1,107) = 3.23, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05. There was no significant effect of height and density on horizontal hovering after controlling for the effect of run order, <italic>F</italic> (2, 107) = 1.63, <italic>p</italic> = &gt; 0.05 and <italic>F</italic> (3, 107) = 0.99, <italic>p</italic> = &gt; 0.05.</p>
<p>The best object height for horizontal low-altitude flight was 2 m, the second was 5 m and last was 10 m. In terms of object density, 144 objects per km<sup>2</sup> was the best object density level for the DEE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1548512911422240">Figure 8</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig8-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Figure 8.</label>
<caption><p>Main effects plot for SQRTDEE versus Object Density (four levels) and Object Height (three levels).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-fig8.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Although object density and object height have no effect on the distance estimation, their interaction has a significant effect on the distance estimation, <italic>F</italic> (6, 99) = 2.64, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05. This indicates that object height had different effects on the distance estimation of the pilots, depending on the density of the objects in the scene. To explore the differences, paired sample <italic>t</italic>-test analyses were conducted. Bonferronni correction was applied and an alpha value of 0.0042 was used to control for Type I error. Between 2 and 10 m object height, paired sample <italic>t</italic>-tests revealed a statistically significant difference for distance estimation performance for the scene that composed of 576 objects per km<sup>2</sup>, <italic>t</italic> (9) = –4.6, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0042. Other paired sample <italic>t</italic>-tests revealed no significant difference. As the subjects do not have any access to information on their altitude, it is conceivable that they cannot effectively estimate their displacement from the origin unless they can deduce the density of the objects in the scene.</p>
<p>In order to analyse the effect of uniformity on DEE score, a <italic>t</italic>-test was conducted. There was no significant difference in the DEE score for uniform (M = 29.209, SD = 15.73) and non-uniform (M = 29.241, SD = 19.88) conditions; <italic>t</italic> (158) = 0.011, <italic>p</italic> = 0.992.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-1548512911422240">
<title>4.4.2 Vertical low-altitude flight performance</title>
<p>During the learning effect analysis, it was found that run order significantly affects the AT performance of low-altitude flight. In order to eliminate the effect of the run order on the performance score, an ANCOVA was conducted with the covariance run order and the factors Object Density (four levels) and Object Height (three levels) on LOGAT. The covariate run order was significantly related to the vertical low-altitude flight performance, <italic>F</italic> (1,107) = 5.07, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 There was also significant effect of height on AT performance of low-altitude flight after controlling for the effect of run order, <italic>F</italic> (2, 107) = 8.89, <italic>p</italic> = &lt; 0.001. However, the effect of object density on AT performance of low-altitude flight was not significant after controlling for the effect of run order, <italic>F</italic> (3, 107) = 1.23, <italic>p</italic> = &gt; 0.05.</p>
<p>A post hoc test revealed that the vertical low-altitude flight performance was significantly better with 2 m objects than with 10 m one (<italic>t</italic> (39) = 4.57, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and with 5 m objects than with 10m objects (<italic>t</italic> (39) = 3.96, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). It is shown in main effects plot in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-1548512911422240">Figure 9</xref> that, when the object height increased, AT performance of the participant decreased. The best object height was 2 m, the second was 5 m and last was 10 m. In addition, the interaction of the object density and object height was not significant, <italic>F</italic> (6, 99) = 0.57, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05.</p>
<fig id="fig9-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Figure 9.</label>
<caption><p>Main effects plot for LOGAT versus Object Density (four levels) and Object Height (three levels).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-fig9.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In order to analyse the effect of uniformity on the AT score, a <italic>t</italic>-test was conducted. There was a significant difference in the AT score for uniform (M = 2.708, SD = 0.33) and non-uniform (M = 2.845, SD = 0.36) conditions; <italic>t</italic> (158) = 2.27, <italic>p</italic> = 0.025. These results suggest that uniformity affects the vertical low-altitude flight performance. Mixture level (M = 2.708 was between the 5 m (M = 2.644) and 10 m (M = 2.880) levels in terms of AT performance. Even though mean height is 5.66 m for the mixture, its mean effect is closer to that of 10 m. This could be due to the prominence of higher objects during low-altitude flight.</p>
<p>Pongracic et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1548512911422240">11</xref></sup> claimed that altitude perception would improve with higher vertical object height. The result of the current study contradicts her claim. The participants performed better with small objects than with tall objects.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-1548512911422240">
<title>4.4.3 Speed estimation performance</title>
<p>An ANCOVA was conducted with the covariance run order and the factors Object Density (four levels) and Object Height (three levels) on LOGDT. The covariate run order was not significantly related to the horizontal hovering performance, <italic>F</italic> (1,107) = 3.30, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05. Neither object density and object height nor their interaction have a significant effect on low-altitude flight SEE performance after controlling for the effect of run order, <italic>F</italic> (2, 107) = 0.67, <italic>p</italic> = &gt; 0.05, <italic>F</italic> (3, 107) = 1.52, <italic>p</italic> = &gt; 0.05 and <italic>F</italic> (6, 107) = 0.94, <italic>p</italic> = &gt; 0.05 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-1548512911422240">Figure 10</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig10-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Figure 10.</label>
<caption><p>Main effects plot for SEE versus Object Density (four levels) and Object Height (three levels).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-fig10.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In order to analyse the effect of uniformity on the SEE score, a <italic>t</italic>-test was conducted. There was no significant difference in the SEE score for uniform (M = 28.381, SD = 17.91) and non-uniform (M = 29.644, SD = 17.63) conditions; <italic>t</italic> (158) = 0.39, <italic>p</italic> = 0.699.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-1548512911422240">
<title>4.4.4 Pilot evaluation of low-altitude flight</title>
<p>After each low-altitude flight run was complete, participants were asked the following question in written format: ‘How suitable is the scenery for “low-altitude flight”?’ The rating scale ranged from 1 = ‘Best for low-altitude flight’ to 5 = ‘Worst for low-altitude flight’.</p>
<p>An ANCOVA was conducted with the covariance run order and the factors Object Density (four levels) and Object Height (three levels) on pilot mark. The covariate run order was not significantly related to the vertical low-altitude flight performance, <italic>F</italic> (1,107) = 0.02, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05. There was also significant effect of object height and density on pilot mark after controlling for the effect of run order, <italic>F</italic> (2, 107) = 10.80, <italic>p</italic> = &lt; 0.001 and <italic>F</italic> (3,107) = 6.77, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001. However, the effect of object height and density interaction on pilot mark was not significant after controlling for the effect of run order, <italic>F</italic> (6,107) = 0.30, <italic>p</italic> = &gt; 0.05.</p>
<p>A post hoc test revealed that pilot mark was significantly better with 576 objects per km<sup>2</sup> than with 36 objects per km<sup>2</sup> (<italic>t</italic> (29) = 4.08, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05), with 144 objects per km<sup>2</sup> than with 36 objects per km<sub>2</sub> (<italic>t</italic> (29) = 3.628, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05), with 10 m objects than with 2 m objects (<italic>t</italic> (39) = 4.465, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and with 10 m objects than with 5 m one (t (39) = 3.351, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-1548512911422240">Figure 11</xref>, the pilots rated the scenes of 2 m height objects as the most difficult for low-altitude flight. This was the opposite of their performance. AT and DEE performances were better with 2 m objects than with 10 m ones.</p>
<fig id="fig11-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Figure 11.</label>
<caption><p>Low-altitude flight: main effects plot for mark versus Object Density and Object Height.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-fig11.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The pilots thought that the scene containing the higher object density was more suitable for low-altitude flight than that with lower object density, with maximum suitability of 576 objects per km<sup>2</sup>. These results are consistent with their performance. The DEE has a peak point at 144 objects per km<sup>2</sup>, whereas the AT performance has a peak point at 576 objects per km<sup>2</sup>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-1548512911422240">
<title>4.5 Discussion</title>
<p>The result of the experiment are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1548512911422240">Table 3</xref>, in which the significant factors for the performance were marked with √ at object density <italic>D</italic> and object height <italic>H</italic>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1548512911422240" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Summary of the performances for hover and low-altitude flights.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1548512911422240" xlink:href="10.1177_1548512911422240-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="6">Hover<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="9">Low-altitude flight<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Distance travelled</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Altitude travelled</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Distance estimation error</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Altitude travelled</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Speed estimation error</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>D</td>
<td>H</td>
<td>D*H</td>
<td>D</td>
<td>H</td>
<td>D*H</td>
<td>D</td>
<td>H</td>
<td>D*H</td>
<td>D</td>
<td>H</td>
<td>D*H</td>
<td>D</td>
<td>H</td>
<td>D*H</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>√</td>
<td>√</td>
<td/>
<td>√</td>
<td>√</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>√</td>
<td/>
<td>√</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The results revealed that horizontal and vertical hovering performance was significantly affected by object density and object height, but not by their interaction.</p>
<p>The pilots hovered better in denser scenes. This result was consistent with pilot marks. They indeed preferred dense scenes for hovering. In addition, both pilot marks of the scenes and their performance revealed that there is a peak point at 576 objects per km<sup>2</sup> object density. Up to this density, performance of the pilots increased. The result of this experiment is consistent with the result of Peitso,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1548512911422240">14</xref></sup> in the sense that horizontal hovering improves with increased object density. However, he claimed this increase is continuous, whereas we observed that increasing the object density beyond 576 objects per km<sup>2</sup>might decrease performance. It should be noted that the objects they used were smaller (about 60 cm) than our objects, which were 2–10 m. As for the vertical hovering performance, no previous study was found in the literature.</p>
<p>Regarding the object height, the pilots hovered better with small objects: their best performance was with 2 m height objects. The advantage of the small object can be the result of the flight type in terms of the required altitude. Hover is performed between 1 and 5 m and 2 m height objects could provide strong cues about their altitude. Objects shorter than 5 m will not impede the movements of the helicopter with a hover task. The pilots can freely get closer to small objects in the scene and control the position of the helicopter more accurately. This can contribute to the advantage of the small and relatively dense scenes.</p>
<p>The pilots’ mark for the scene suitability for hover and their actual performance were contradictory. While the pilots performed better with small objects, they preferred tall objects.</p>
<p>During the low-altitude flight, vertical stabilization performance of the pilots was significantly affected by object height but not by their density. When the object height was increased, altitude stabilization performance decreased. Pilot mark for low-altitude flight indicated that tall objects are more suitable, but they performed better with small objects.</p>
<p>The result of the low-altitude flight experiment is consistent with the previous studies conducted by Kleiss<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1548512911422240">10</xref></sup> and Pongracic et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1548512911422240">11</xref></sup> regarding the importance of object density on altitude perception. They conducted experiments at 100–150 feet altitude and 400–600 knot speeds. They stated that object density has a positive effect on altitude perception and approximately four objects per km<sup>2</sup> was sufficient for altitude perception. Increasing the object density does not improve the performance significantly. Although the object density effect we found was not significant at the α = 0.05 level statistically, the altitude perception was consistently improved with increased object density.</p>
<p>The pilots’ distance estimation was significantly affected by the interaction of the object density and height. This is expected, because they cannot estimate distance by only observing the density of the objects unless they know the size (or their altitude) and can estimate the distance between them. They estimated the distance more accurately with 2 m height objects. Furthermore, object density, object height and their interaction did not affect the speed estimation significantly.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-1548512911422240" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>5. Conclusions and future work</title>
<p>This study was conducted to determine essential OTWS visual cues for hovering and low-altitude flight. The density and height of 3D objects in the scene were investigated. Ten professional pilots participated to the experiment. A PC-based flight simulator was used with the wide FOV and with a flight control set composed of a stick, a collective and a cyclic. Horizontal and vertical stabilization performances of the pilots were evaluated for hover. In low-altitude flight, in addition to horizontal and vertical stabilization, distance and speed estimation performances were evaluated. In addition, pilots marked each scene according to their suitability for hover and low-altitude flight.</p>
<p>Results revealed that object density and object height are effective on both horizontal and vertical hovering performance. In low-altitude flight, altitude control is positively affected by smaller object height. However, pilots prefer the scenes composed of the high objects while hovering and flying at low altitudes. Distance estimation is affected by the interaction of the object density and height.</p>
<p>The findings of our study can guide developers in the design and development phases of helicopter flight simulators. They can design simulators that will provide the needed detail with the lowest complexity. In this way, the cost of the simulator for a given flight task can be optimized. A balance between effectiveness and time/cost efficiency will be achieved.</p>
<p>Training designers, on the other hand, will profit from these results when preparing an aviation training program. They can arrange the OTWS for a task using the results of this experiment. For example, at the initial phases of the training, simpler scenes with small objects can be constructed. After pilots feel comfortable with the small objects, more challenging scenes with the taller objects can be utilized.</p>
<p>This study analysed the static objects only in terms of density, height and uniformity. The effects of stationary objects on hovering and low-altitude flight should be analysed according to their distribution on the scenery: random or uniform. In addition, discrimination can be an important cue. For example, a scene containing a different coloured tree can be compared with a scene composed of same coloured trees. Similarly, height mixture was tried for only equal height priors; different variations can have different effects. The effect of moving objects on hover and low-altitude flight should be investigated.</p>
<p>In this study wide FOV was used. Narrow FOV can be compared with wide FOV. In addition, three 19” LCD monitors was used in the experiment. Other display type, that is, Head Mounted Displays (HMDs), can be used and their effect should be investigated.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>Yasemin Çetin is on leave from Gaziosmanpaşa University, Tokat, Turkey.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Yasemin Çetin</bold> is a research assistant at the Information Systems Department of the Informatics Institute, Middle East Technical University (METU). She is currently a PhD candidate in Information Systems at the METU. Her research interests include human–computer interaction, evaluation of e-service systems and information technology adoption.</p>
<p><bold>Erdal Yılmaz</bold> is a retired engineer major. His main research areas are geographical information systems (GISs), 3D virtual environments, crowd simulation and video games. Currently he is the research and development (R&amp;D) manager of Sobee Game Studios. He is also teaching part-time at the METU, Informatics Institute, Game Technologies Department, Ankara, Turkey.</p>
<p><bold>Yasemin Yardımcı Çetin</bold> is a full professor and the department chair at the Information Systems Department of the Informatics Institute, METU. Before joining the Information Systems Department she worked as a faculty member at the Modeling and Simulation Program of the same institute. Her research interests vary from man–machine interfaces to image processing for food safety and remote sensing.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1548512911422240">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>D’Alessandro</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. ‘<article-title>Transference of PC-based Simulation to Aviation Training: Issues in Learning</article-title>’, <comment>indianaviationnews. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://net/allimages/AlessandroPaper.pdf">net/allimages/AlessandroPaper.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<year>2007</year>, <access-date>accessed 27 August, 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1548512911422240">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Macchiarella</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Innovations in ab initio pilot training: an application of high fidelity flight training devices</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of the Flight Simulation Group Committee of the Royal Aeronautical Society: Cutting Costs in Flight Simulation: Balancing Quality and Capability</conf-name>, <conf-loc>London</conf-loc>, <conf-date>2006</conf-date></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1548512911422240">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Macchiarella</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arban</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Transfer of training from flight training devices to flight for ab-initio pilots</article-title>. <source>FAA Int J Appl Aviat Stud</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>314</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1548512911422240">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Karaahmetoğlu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yardimci Cetin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Köksal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Out-the-window scene properties in pc-based helicopter simulators</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of SPIE: Enhanced and Synthetic Vision</source>, <publisher-name>Orlando (Kissimmee), FL</publisher-name>, <year>2006</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1548512911422240">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Center</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Visual-motion cueing in the control of altitude</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of the Systems, Man and Cybernetics. ‘Intelligent Systems for the 21st Century’, IEEE International Conference</conf-name>, <conf-date>1995</conf-date>, pp.<fpage>2676</fpage>–<lpage>2681</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1548512911422240">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>II</suffix></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Utility of a personal computer-based aviation training device for helicopter flight training</article-title>. <source>Int J Appl Aviat Stud</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>305</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1548512911422240">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lucario</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Helicopter flight training through serious aviation gaming</article-title>. <source>J Defense Model Simulat</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1548512911422240">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kleiss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Terrain visual cue analysis for simulating low-level flight: a multidimensional scaling approach</source>. <publisher-loc>Dayton, OH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Dayton Research Institute</publisher-name>, <year>1990</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1548512911422240">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kleiss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Effect of terrain shape and object grouping on perception of change in altitude in a flight simulator</source>. <publisher-loc>Dayton, OH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Dayton Research Institute</publisher-name>, <year>1995</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1548512911422240">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kleiss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Tradeoffs among types of scene detail for simulating low-altitude flight</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of the Systems, Man and Cybernetics, 1992, IEEE International Conference on Systems, Man and Cybernetics</conf-name>, <conf-date>1992</conf-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1548512911422240">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pongracic</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grabovac</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yildiz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An initial investigation into visual cues for altitude perception in terrain following flight</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of SimTecT 2003</source>, <publisher-loc>Adelaide, South Australia</publisher-loc>, <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage> <month>May</month>, <year>2003</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1548512911422240">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schnell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katherine Lemos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Terrain sampling density and texture requirements for synthetic vision systems</source>. <publisher-loc>Iowa City, IA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Center for Computer Aided Design, Operator Performance Laboratory (OPL), The University of Iowa</publisher-name>, <year>2002</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1548512911422240">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schnell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lemos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glaab</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parrish</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pilot performance as a function of display resolution and field of view in a simulated terrain following flight task using a synthetic vision system</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of the Digital Avionics Systems Conference DASC’03</conf-name>, <conf-date>2003</conf-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1548512911422240">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peitso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Visual field requirements for precision nap-of-the-earth helicopter flight</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Naval Monterey, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Postgraduate School</publisher-name>, <year>2002</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1548512911422240">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. ‘<article-title>A Review of Approaches to Determine the Effectiveness of Ground-Based Flight Simulations</article-title>’, <comment>American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AIAA), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aviationsystemsdivision.arc.nasa.gov/publications/hitl/technical/human_computer_interfaces.pdf">http://www.aviationsystemsdivision.arc.nasa.gov/publications/hitl/technical/human_computer_interfaces.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<year>2000</year>, <access-date>accessed 20 January 2008</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1548512911422240">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. ‘<article-title>X-Plane. Laminar Research</article-title>’, <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.x-plane.com/pg_Meet_X-Plane.html">http://www.x-plane.com/pg_Meet_X-Plane.html</ext-link></comment> (<year>2010</year>, <access-date>accessed 20 July 2010</access-date>)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1548512911422240">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Design and analysis of experiments</source>. <edition>5th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons</publisher-name>, <year>2001</year>, pp. <fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>