<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcrj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Criminology &amp; Criminal Justice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1748-8958</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1748-8966</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1748895811431850</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1748895811431850</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Public safety regimes: Negotiated orders and political analysis in criminology</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>Alistair</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>McAra</surname><given-names>Lesley</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>Gordon</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1748895811431850">Cardiff University, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1748895811431850">Adam Edwards, Cardiff University, School of Social Sciences, Glamorgan Building, King Edward VII Avenue, Cardiff University, CF10 3WT, UK Email: <email>EdwardsA2@cf.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Negotiated Orders</issue-title>
<fpage>433</fpage>
<lpage>458</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Implicit in the concept of negotiated orders is an understanding of the social productivity of political power; the <italic>power to</italic> accomplish governing programmes for citizens as much as the <italic>power over</italic> citizens for the purposes of social control. This distinction is especially pertinent for the role of political analysis in critical criminological thought, where criticism of the authoritarian state has vied with studies of governmentality and governance to explain the exercise of political power beyond the State and with the distinction between politics and administration found in liberal criminology. Outside of criminology, political economists interested in the ‘power to’ govern suggest its analysis in terms of ‘regimes’ of advocacy coalitions that struggle for the capacity to govern complex problems and populations in specific social contexts. Regime formation or failure can differ in character, and in outcomes, as much within nation states as between them and in relation to different kinds of governing problems. The article considers the applicability of regime theory to the negotiation of ‘public safety’, a governing problem which is a particular focus for political analysis within criminology.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>critical criminology</kwd>
<kwd>negotiated orders</kwd>
<kwd>political analysis</kwd>
<kwd>public safety</kwd>
<kwd>regime theory</kwd>
<kwd>socially productive power</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1748895811431850" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>It may seem perverse to emphasize the negotiation of social order in a contemporary context characterized by so much coercion. Various wars on crime, drugs and terror suggest little interest in, or capacity for, bargaining. Yet, a focus on the negotiation of social orders is warranted as combatants have had cause to reflect on the limits to authoritarian interventions, whether military campaigns, punitive responses to the illegal drugs trade, financial limits to the expansion of penal estates or the effectiveness of criminal law enforcement for volume crime reduction. Indeed the limits to sovereign power, to government by command, have been a significant focus of criminological thought over the past two decades, provoking debate over the adaptation of liberal democratic orders to the normality of crime and the responsibilization of liberal subjects for their own safety, even while state actors indulge in ‘punitive display’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1748895811431850">Garland, 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1748895811431850">2001</xref>). Conversely, it is argued that far from any recognizable limitations to sovereign power, authoritarian state interventions have expanded exponentially in the last two decades representing a ‘punitive turn’ in liberal democracies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1748895811431850">Pratt et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1748895811431850">Wacquant, 2009</xref>). In this body of work it is argued the capacity for projecting state power is now so enhanced that liberal democratic principles of separating the powers of legislatures, executives and the judiciary are being subordinated to a process of ‘securitization’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1748895811431850">Buzan et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1748895811431850">Hallsworth and Lea, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>In summary there is a divergence in political analyses of criminological issues between those retaining a focus on authoritarian state power (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1748895811431850">Coleman et al., 2009</xref>) and those emphasizing the diffusion of political power through networks and programmes of governance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1748895811431850">Crawford, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1748895811431850">Johnston and Shearing, 2003</xref>). Counterpoised to this fragmentation of political analysis within critical criminology is a liberal criminological tradition of work that reproduces the separation of powers principle in its own research programmes, focusing political analysis on the arena of legislatures, their election, their law making and policy formulations and the pressure group activity this provokes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1748895811431850">Downes and Morgan, 1994</xref>). The arena approach deflects analysis away from the relations of power that permeate the whole policy process, from the definition of problems to the formulation, implementation and evaluation of responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1748895811431850">Leftwich, 1984</xref>). In turn this enables those working within the liberal tradition to bracket political analysis off from the science of explaining crime and ‘what works, what doesn’t and what’s promising’ for prevention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1748895811431850">Sherman et al., 1997</xref>). It is in this sense that such criminology can be depicted as ‘administrative’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-1748895811431850">Young, 1994</xref>).</p>
<p>Policies on public safety or, in the Anglophone world, ‘community safety’, are a particular empirical focus for arguments about the scope of political analysis in criminology and of the coerced or negotiated character of social order. These policies formally acknowledge the inability of the core police and criminal justice agencies of the State to comprehend and prevent problems of crime and disorder ‘alone’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1748895811431850">Home Office, 1984</xref>). They consequently emphasize the need for these agencies to work in ‘partnership’ with other statutory, commercial and voluntary actors and to ‘engage’ the wider citizenry in responses to these problems. Interpretation of these policies among criminologists is divergent, representing the main traditions of political analysis in criminological research: liberal criminology, structural-functionalist Marxism, governmental criminology and studies of governance (see later). For example, some believe these policies demonstrate real limits to state power and the diffusion of political power into nodes of governance that generate genuine opportunities for empowering subordinate groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1748895811431850">Johnston and Shearing, 2003</xref>). Others regard them as a ‘new liberal speak’ that mystifies state coercion, obscuring the bigger picture of the mass criminalization and subsequent penal warehousing of poor populations ejected from the labour process of ‘neo-liberal’ capitalism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1748895811431850">Coleman et al., 2009</xref>). As such public safety has become an important empirical focus for political analysis in criminology.</p>
<p>Our intention here is to contribute to these arguments and their broader implications for understanding the negotiation of social order, drawing upon insights from our own research into public safety policies and from a theoretical perspective that has, as yet, been notably limited in its impact on criminological research. It is suggested that regime analysis, initially developed within studies of urban political economy in the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1748895811431850">Mossberger and Stoker, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1748895811431850">Stone, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1748895811431850">2005</xref>), offers a conceptual and methodological framework that is useful for testing and building criminological accounts of the role of political power in negotiating social order. To distinguish this contribution and as a prelude to discussing the core elements of this framework, it is helpful to locate the concerns of regime analysis in relation to the predominant traditions of political analysis in criminology.</p>
<p>The article is organized as follows. In the first section we begin by noting that the negotiation of social orders as a topic for criminology implies an understanding of the role of politics and political analysis in criminology. In turn we suggest that insight into the negotiation of social orders implies a socially productive concept of the ‘power to’ govern not simply the ‘power over’ subject populations and that regime analysis provides a framework for both the conceptual and empirical investigation of the power to govern. This argument is clarified through a comparison and contrast with more established traditions of political analysis in criminology. It is contended that the distinctive contribution of regime analysis revealed through this comparison is its analytical focus on ‘governing capacity’ and its empirical focus on the formation, reproduction and failure of ‘governing arrangements’ in specific local political-economies which reveal the possibilities for different types of regime. Building on this discussion, the analytical and empirical applications of regime analysis in criminology are then illustrated in the second section of the article through reference to arguments about public safety (noting that the latter has attracted interest from the breadth of traditions of political analysis in criminology given its explicit attempt to take government beyond the State and into partnerships of state and non-state actors).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1748895811431850">
<title>Negotiation, Political Analysis and Criminology</title>
<p>Implicit in the concept of negotiated orders is an understanding of the social productivity of political power; the <italic>power to</italic> accomplish governing programmes for citizens as much as the <italic>power over</italic> citizens for the purposes of social control. The distinction between ‘power to’ and ‘power over’ has been used by advocates of regime analysis to distinguish their political-economic approach from that of more established intellectual traditions of political analysis, such as pluralism, elitism and structural-functionalism, including some variants of Marxist state theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1748895811431850">Mouleart et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1748895811431850">Stone, 2006</xref>). It is argued that these other traditions, notwithstanding their significant differences, share an analysis of political power in terms of a contest of wills around fixed preferences (be these related to class, status or party), whereas the socially productive concept of power acknowledges that, ‘Preferences not only precede action, they can also be shaped by experience’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1748895811431850">Stone, 2006</xref>: 24). As such the analytical focus on regimes reflects an interest in, ‘how actors come to embrace <italic>and stay with</italic> some courses of action rather than others’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1748895811431850">Stone, 2006</xref>: 24, emphasis in original) and what the empirical investigation of the different courses of action taken by governing regimes can tell us about the possibilities for the reform, if not the transformation, of political settlements. The concept of regimes emphasizes the provisional qualities of political power as an ongoing struggle rather than an accomplished state formation or a condition that can be otherwise imputed from constitutional-legal mandates or membership of elite groups. In doing so, regime analysis privileges a focus on the arrangements that equip regimes with the capacity to govern; with the political agency of forming coalitions around distinctive policy agendas and securing the governing resources to deliver on these agendas. It is concerned with the ‘schemes of co-operation’ used to interest, enrol, mobilize and sustain governing coalitions. Given this focus, regime analysts acknowledge that schemes of co-operation can fail or cease to be sufficiently interesting and that regime failure is a likely scenario, particularly for more ambitious policy agendas that seek to transform not just maintain or develop established governing arrangements. Of course regimes are not neutral mechanisms, they do exercise ‘power over’ others, and the resources needed to form and sustain governing coalitions are unequally distributed. Yet it is this sense, akin to Marx’s <italic>18th Brumaire</italic>, of the possibility of actors making their own history albeit not in conditions of their own choosing, of therefore having to negotiate not simply command order, which is re-centred in the analysis of regimes as contrasted with analyses of sovereign, state or elite power.</p>
<p>The provenance of regime analysis in urban political studies and its prospective contribution to criminological thought can be further elaborated and distinguished from more established traditions of political analysis in criminology.</p>
<sec id="section3-1748895811431850">
<title>Regime analysis</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1748895811431850">Mossberger (2009</xref>: 50) has observed that urban regime analysis emerged as an empirical theory which sought to explain the formal and informal relationships that seek to overcome the fragmentation of authority between states and markets, public authorities and private interests, in capitalist democracies, and more specifically the fundamental tensions, if not contradictions, these create for democratic governance and the ‘well-being’ of cities. In essence, this mode of analysis, ‘touches the fundamental questions of politics, such as the nature of power and the potential for democratic governance’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1748895811431850">Mossberger, 2009</xref>: 40). Specifically, as the power to govern cannot be imputed from constitutional-legal mandates alone, the analysis of power must entail some consideration of the capacity to govern. Such capacity is accomplished (or lost) through attempts to reconcile the will of the electorates that legitimize regimes with the interests of the economic (particularly corporate) actors on whom regimes are dependent for the resources to deliver their policy agendas.</p>
<p>A concern with the strategic dilemmas between politics and economics in liberal democracies is hardly novel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1748895811431850">Habermas, 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1748895811431850">Jessop, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1748895811431850">Offe, 1984</xref>) but, through its socially productive concept of power, regime analysis argues that the working out of these dilemmas is not a foregone conclusion; the inter-dependencies of state and market create opportunities for alternative policy agendas. These can ‘maintain’ an existing political-economic settlement, ‘develop’ it (e.g. by leveraging greater corporate investment through the promise of tax-breaks), take it in a ‘progressive’ direction (e.g. by negotiating a higher corporate tax-take for investment in social policies with the promise of government contracts for business) or seek to transform it (e.g. through the pursuit of social justice policy agendas entailing significant redistribution of income) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1748895811431850">Stoker and Mossberger, 1994</xref>). Understanding how such courses of action are pursued in relation to particular governing problems in specific localities and with what consequences is the generic aim and distinctive contribution of regime analysis to political-economic studies. This aim prioritizes a concern with identifying the discretion open to political actors and how this is acknowledged and exercised; how political actors ‘re-make’ local governance albeit in conditions not (entirely) of their own choosing. The concern with political action implies a concern with the instrumental and expressive motivations of actors seeking to form and sustain regimes; whether, for example, there are opportunities for the pursuit of such ‘large purposes’ as ‘social justice’ or whether these are inhibited by the ‘bounded rationality’ of actors preoccupied with their personal advancement and/or fearful of radical departures from established policy agendas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1748895811431850">Stone, 2006</xref>). Consequently, core questions for the research programme of regime analysis concern the schemes of co-operation that can realize reformist, even transformative, policy agendas and the social conditions that render these schemes possible.</p>
<p>The type of political-economy advocated by regime analysts is therefore one which avoids the imputation of social change from purported social formations such as ‘neo-liberalism’ (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1748895811431850">Cavadino and Dignan, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1748895811431850">Reiner, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1748895811431850">Wacquant, 2009</xref>). In these terms, regime analysis could be regarded as a species of the ‘new institutionalism’, which rejects, ‘the “market-determinism” of neo-liberal approaches and the account of linear progress and convergent modernisation where all institutional regimes will be ultimately assimilated’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1748895811431850">Karstedt, 2010</xref>: 354). It thus represents a political-economic perspective where the significance of the dialectical relationship between economic constraints and political action is fore-grounded as both a theoretical and empirical problem to be explored in research. Indeed the possibility of variation in local regimes – the particular condensation and realization of structural forces in local contexts – distinguishes it from most other political-economic approaches, including <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1748895811431850">Molotch’s (1976)</xref> ‘growth machine’ concept (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1748895811431850">Mossberger, 2009</xref>: 42–43) and those associated with structural-functionalist Marxism (see later).</p>
<p>The research programme associated with regime analysis was originally rooted in the decentralized and fragmented policy environment of urban government in the United States. In turn, urban regime research has tended to emphasize the key role of business and economic development in urban policy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1748895811431850">Mossberger, 2009</xref>: 40), as epitomized in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1748895811431850">Stone’s (1989)</xref> case study of regime politics in the southern US city of Atlanta 1946–1988. However, more recent work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1748895811431850">Mossberger, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1748895811431850">Stone, 2005</xref>) has highlighted how urban regimes in the USA (and beyond) can also form around other social issues beyond that of economic development in urban conurbations. In broadening the analytical scope of their approach beyond the ‘urban’, to other kinds of locality, and to other problems of government, such as education and public safety, regime analysts have facilitated the application of their political-economic approach in other social science disciplines, such as criminology. For example, in a recent re-appraisal of regime analysis, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1748895811431850">Stone (2005</xref>: 329) defines the ‘core elements of a model of local governance’ which can organize empirical research into the formation, sustainability or failure of regimes around a breadth of governing problems. A regime has:</p>
<list id="list1-1748895811431850" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>an agenda to address a distinct set of problems;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>a governing coalition formed around the agenda, typically including both governmental and non-governmental members;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>resources for the pursuit of the agenda, brought to bear by members of the governing coalition; and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>given the absence of a system of command, a scheme of co-operation through which the members of the governing coalition align their contribution to the task of governing.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Whether or not a regime is successfully realized and subsequently sustained is open to empirical investigation as are the possible reasons for regime failure. Central to the analysis of regimes is investigation into the schemes of co-operation – the inducements, incentives and threats – that would-be governors employ to enrol coalition members into their governing programme. Regimes are thus possible where the interests of coalition members may not be the same but are sufficiently contiguous. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1748895811431850">Stone (1989)</xref> illustrates this through reference to the governing coalition formed in Atlanta between White mayors, corporate business leaders and Black middle class representatives of the civil rights movement during the first 40 years of the post-war period in which the electoral power of the African-American population increased in this city. This regime was formed through incentives to corporate business to continue to invest in the city, principally the provision of public sector contracts for downtown real estate construction, and to pay business taxes levied at a sufficient rate to support various community development projects, job training programmes and support for minority businesses. It was subsequently acknowledged that the interests of Black working class communities in the city were neglected by the regime and they struggled to exert much influence on its policy agenda (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1748895811431850">Stone and Pierannunzi, 2000</xref>). Even so, the experience of Atlanta, as an ultimately ‘developmental’, rather than progressive or social justice-oriented, regime, in leveraging continued economic investment into the City, is contrasted with the economic decline and intensification of ethnic segregation in other comparable cities in the southern states of the USA. As such, the Atlanta experience demonstrates the political options open to municipal governing coalitions and the opportunity costs of not taking them, as well as the structural limitations to regimes seeking to reconcile business interests with ‘non-contiguous’ agendas for social justice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1748895811431850">Stone, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>Analytically, the importance of the Atlanta case study for regime analysis has been to build an understanding of whether and how interdependencies between state and market are interpreted and acted upon and what the specific difficulties of realizing social justice agendas are even in political conditions that appear favourable, such as the predominance of socially excluded populations in the electorate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1748895811431850">Stone, 2006</xref>). The criminological applications of regime analysis for concrete research into how local social orders are negotiated are discussed further and in relation to the particular problem of ‘public safety’ in the next section. Here it suffices to say that regime analysis provides the kind of middle-range concepts for grounding theory about the power to govern and its limits in particular local experiences. Prior to this, it is helpful to clarify the prospective contribution of regime analysis to criminological thought through a contrast with more established approaches to political analysis in this research field. For this purpose it is possible to distinguish regime theory from other traditions of political analysis in terms of their concept of power, analytical and empirical focus and exemplary criminological applications, see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1748895811431850">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1748895811431850" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Traditions of political analysis in criminology</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1748895811431850" xlink:href="10.1177_1748895811431850-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Tradition</th>
<th align="left">Concept of power</th>
<th align="left">Analytical focus</th>
<th align="left">Empirical focus</th>
<th align="left">Criminological applications</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Regime analysis</td>
<td>Socially productive ‘power to’ govern</td>
<td>Governing capacity</td>
<td>Governing arrangements, formation, sustainability or failure of regimes coalescing round specific policy agendas</td>
<td>Public safety regimes coalescing around policy agendas for criminal justice, risk management, restorative justice, social justice, other …</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Liberal criminology</td>
<td>Separation of powers between legislature, executive and judiciary; distinction between politics and administration</td>
<td>Decision-making arenas</td>
<td>Election of legislatures, legislative programmes, pressure groups</td>
<td>Electoral competition over ‘law and order’ issues, influence of criminal justice pressure groups and mass media reportage of crime issues on the legislative process</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Structural-functionalist Marxism</td>
<td>Repressive ‘power over’ subjects</td>
<td>State functions in reproducing historically specific social structures</td>
<td>State formations in capitalist societies, their function in reproducing circuits of capital accumulation</td>
<td>Authoritarian state repression of opposition to capital accumulation, criminalization and warehousing of populations surplus to the labour process; under-criminalization of corporate crime</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Governmental criminology</td>
<td>Production of problems and populations for government</td>
<td>Political rationalities that render problems and populations thinkable for the purposes of government</td>
<td>Neo-liberal rationalities defining populations of free-willed, rationally calculating individuals posing certain risks in need of management; actuarial technologies for defining, calculating and targeting such risk</td>
<td>Diagnosis of how political rationalities have defined the ‘rationally calculating offender’, the responsibilities of private citizens for their own security, the rise of actuarial justice, the targeting of policing around risky individuals, ‘at risk’ groups and ‘communities’</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Governance studies</td>
<td>Power-dependence between state and non-state actors given the fragmentation of political authority</td>
<td>Pursuit of collective interests through bargaining, the particular exchange relationships involved in bargaining, alternatively, the proliferation of competing centres of power</td>
<td>Interest intermediation in the process of public policy formulation, implementation and evaluation; governing through public–private partnerships and networks; governing through regulation; nodes of governance</td>
<td>The crime control policy process; local security networks or ‘partnerships’; the relationship of public to private security; the formation of private governments</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1748895811431850">
<title>Liberal criminology</title>
<p>The analytical focus on the ‘power to’ govern in regime analysis arises out of a concern with the tendency of much liberal political science to limit political analysis to the institutions of government (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1748895811431850">Leftwich, 1984</xref>). This arena approach concentrates on the election of legislative assemblies and the key decision-making processes informing the legislative process. An exemplary instance of this in criminology is Downes and Morgan’s essays on the politics of law and order in Britain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1748895811431850">1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1748895811431850">1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1748895811431850">2002</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1748895811431850">2007</xref>). Underpinning this approach is a concept of political power as the mandated ‘power over’ populations granted through the electoral process of liberal democracies. A basic proposition of regime analysis is that such constitutional-legal authority is, in itself, inadequate to deliver governing programmes given the ‘interdependence between the policy-making capacity of democratic institutions and the wealth-generating resources of the market economy’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1748895811431850">Mossberger, 2009</xref>: 41). As such the power to govern cannot be imputed from the mandated power over electorates. The interdependence of political authority and economic power is central to understanding the actual performance of elected authorities and consequently shifts the analytical focus from their decision making to the ‘formal and informal modes of collaboration between business and government’ that are located outside of legislative arenas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1748895811431850">Mossberger, 2009</xref>: 41).</p>
<p>A further consequence of the focus on the power to govern is a rejection of the liberal argument that politics can be distinguished from ‘administration’. In this regard, regime analysis is aligned to and builds on studies of governance that document how political power permeates the entire policy process from legislative action and policy formulation through implementation to the evaluation of policy outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1748895811431850">Marsh and Rhodes, 1992</xref>). While this insight might be well established in the research programmes of political science, in liberal criminology the distinction between politics and administration remains paramount, both as a normative principle and as an empirical representation of how crime control policies are implemented and evaluated. The pejorative description of such criminology as ‘administrative’ identifies the evacuation of political analysis from the doing of control and from accounts of ‘what works, what doesn’t and what’s promising’ offered by evaluative criminology, whether of an experimental or ‘scientific realist’ variety (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1748895811431850">Sherman, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1748895811431850">Tilley, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1748895811431850">2009</xref>). Extending political analysis throughout the policy process provokes argument about the possibility of demarcating science from politics and criminologists from political action (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1748895811431850">Edwards and Sheptycki, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1748895811431850">Goldson and Hughes, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1748895811431850">Loader and Sparks, 2010</xref>). In these terms regime analysis acknowledges the political context and uses of science and other forms of governmental knowledge in struggles over the reformulation, implementation and evaluation of policy in subsequent policy cycles, while provoking further debate over the uses of social science to represent and constitute the power to govern.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1748895811431850">
<title>Structural-functionalist Marxism</title>
<p>Structural-functionalist Marxism has been a particularly influential tradition of political analysis in criminology, especially in terms of asking ‘whose law and what order is being protected’ in the class-based socio-economic and political structures in which the labels of ‘criminal’ and ‘legal’ are both constructed and upheld (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1748895811431850">McLaughlin, 2010</xref>: 154). Underpinning much contemporary Marxist analysis of the politics of crime and control is <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1748895811431850">Poulantzas’ (1978</xref>) structural-functionalist account of an authoritarian state formation arising out of the collapse of the post-war settlement (the meta-negotiation between capital and labour). According to this account, the legitimization crises encountered by Keynesian welfare states both fuelled labour protest and undermined the possibilities for its incorporation. This left state authorities with little option but the use of coercion to restore the conditions for liberal democratic capitalism. In ‘the great moving right show’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1748895811431850">Hall, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1748895811431850">Hall et al., 1978</xref>) the authoritarian state disciplines populations marginalized in the flexible accumulation regimes of neo-liberalism through penal warehousing, aggressive street policing and systematic criminalization of dissent.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1748895811431850">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>It is argued that the ‘authoritarian state’ concept has become axiomatic in a certain ‘orthodox critical criminology’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1748895811431850">McLaughlin, 2010</xref>). This orthodoxy identifies, as priorities for political analysis, the processes of criminalization emanating from this state formation and their functions for managing the structural contradictions of capital accumulation. In an important reflection on the current state of this orthodoxy, however, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1748895811431850">McLaughlin (2010</xref>: 170) notes that:
<disp-quote>
<p>Reification of the 1970s concept of the ‘authoritarian state’ – as a credo – rather than as twenty-first century sensitising concept, limits the possibilities for engaging in the rigorous examination of the contradictory evidence that is so vital for renewal [of critical criminology]. There is evidence that a self-referential orthodox Critical Criminology is deteriorating theoretically to the point where it is incapable of engaging with the complex of risks and uncertainties that define a rapidly changing sociological and political landscape.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>McLaughlin notes further that this orthodoxy has increasing difficulty in accessing institutional sites of criminal justice and security in order to generate primary research data and methodological innovation. It is selective about the injustices it seeks to intervene against, prioritizing the crimes of the powerful but distancing itself from the conventional crime issues that dominate popular debate. In sum it has a ‘tendency to slip into sweeping generalisations that push aside tensions and contradictions’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1748895811431850">McLaughlin, 2010</xref>: 170–171).</p>
<p>In a recent interview Stuart Hall (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1748895811431850">Hall and Taylor, 2011</xref>) acknowledges countervailing political forces and the presence of social justice agendas in liberal democracies. Using a musical metaphor, he argues that, nonetheless, the authoritarian ‘refrain’ of politics has remained louder within contemporary governing programmes. Even so, we suggest a conceptual framework is needed to inform research into <italic>how</italic> this refrain has managed to drown out competing agendas, if it has. Our argument is that the kind of structural-functionalist account advocated by Poulantzas, Hall and their followers within critical criminology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1748895811431850">Coleman et al., 2009</xref>) does not of itself provide these concepts. Countervailing tendencies towards agendas for restorative and social justice are obviated in theories of the authoritarian state that focus analysis and research almost exclusively on evidence that exemplifies authoritarian interventions. As such they become self-referential. Whether or not these countervailing refrains are, in practice, so quiet as to be imperceptible in the noise of the punitive turn is a moot point, but one that requires empirical investigation rather than a priori assertions. What is needed is some sense of how dominant the tendencies identified by theories of the authoritarian state have to be in particular social contexts for them to be regarded as ‘hegemonic’ and this implies some recognition of countervailing tendencies and why they ought to be regarded as marginal. In relation to this research problem, regime analysis eschews the imputation of state formations found in structural-functionalist accounts in favour of a focus on the scope for political action and the lessons that can be drawn from the formation, reproduction and failure of governing coalitions in certain political-economic contexts for action elsewhere.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1748895811431850">
<title>Governmental criminology</title>
<p>This emphasis on political agency and struggle in regime analysis also contrasts with the analysis of power developed in the ‘governmental criminology’ that has emerged out of the work of Foucault and his followers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1748895811431850">O’Malley, 2010</xref>). Following Foucault’s concept of power as productive, not just repressive, studies of governmentality focus analysis on political rationalities that define problems and populations of government in order that they can then be governed. Power is productive in defining objects of government in certain ways rather than others, for example defining illicit drug use as primarily a problem of criminal justice rather than of public health. A major contribution of governmental criminology is to diagnose the play of power in the very translation of social problems, in the linguistic representation of these problems in ways that privilege certain policy aims (e.g. incarceration) over others (e.g. drug rehabilitation and treatment).</p>
<p>Political rationalities are the focus of analysis in governmental criminology because they define how problems of government are translated in accordance with certain values and interests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1748895811431850">Smandych, 1999</xref>). Given the preoccupation of much governmental criminology with histories of the present, its empirical research programme has concentrated on ‘neo-liberal’ rationalities of rule and how they constitute populations of free-willed, rationally calculating, individuals posing certain risks of offending behaviour or vulnerability to victimization which need to be managed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1748895811431850">O’Malley, 1992</xref>). More recent arguments in this tradition have contended that entire liberal democracies, such as the USA, can be ‘governed through crime’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1748895811431850">Simon, 2007</xref>) and even supra-national blocs of liberal democracies, such as the European Union, can be ‘governed through security’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1748895811431850">Buzan et al., 1998</xref>). In these ways, the political rationality of neo-liberalism aligns the tasks of governing with fears over crime, terrorism, migration and so forth while obviating other rationalities concerned with social inclusion, equality and justice.</p>
<p>Work in this tradition has also begun to emphasize the hybridity of political rationalities, the ways in which, for example, social democratic and neo-conservative rationalities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1748895811431850">Stenson and Edwards, 2003</xref>) can be assembled together in the kind of messy, inchoate, compromises and unpredictable outcomes that often characterize the struggle to govern.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1748895811431850">2</xref></sup> Less clear is how far governmental criminology can accommodate the concerns of sociological realist approaches, such as that proposed in regime analysis, to understand the rise of certain policy agendas about crime and public safety in particular places and moments and with what consequences (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1748895811431850">Rose and Miller, 1992</xref>). Attempts to blend the insights of governmentality studies with sociological accounts of the policy process, for example in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1748895811431850">Stenson’s (2005)</xref> ‘realist governmentality’ thesis nonetheless suggest this is feasible.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1748895811431850">
<title>Studies of governance</title>
<p>Studies of governance have become an important feature of political analysis in criminological research as some have found the over-homogenized concept of ‘the State’ inadequate for the task of capturing the fragmentation of authority in liberal democratic states and the variegated corporatist, plural and, at certain points, authoritarian crime control agendas this enables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1748895811431850">Crawford, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1748895811431850">Garland, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1748895811431850">Hughes, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1748895811431850">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1748895811431850">Johnston and Shearing, 2003</xref>). It is also argued that studies of governance provide concepts for comparative research into different political cultures of control, which recognize the role of policy networks in filtering, resisting and adapting the transfer of crime control policies within and across nation states (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1748895811431850">Muncie, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1748895811431850">Newburn and Sparks, 2004</xref>). This is particularly germane to arguments over the purported projection of neo-liberal crime control policies within the USA as well as from the USA to other liberal democracies in Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1748895811431850">Edwards and Hughes, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1748895811431850">Jones and Newburn, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Regime analysis has an affinity with the broader literature on ‘governance’ insofar as both traditions share a concern with the fragmentation of authority between, and the <italic>interdependence</italic> of, states and markets in capitalist democracies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1748895811431850">Mossberger, 2009</xref>). In terms of this focus on inter-dependence, both traditions regard the exercise of political power as emerging out of the bargaining that political authorities have to engage in with actors organized at different tiers above and below the nation state and in different (statutory, commercial and voluntary) sectors of the polity in order to acquire governing capacity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1748895811431850">Jones, 2007</xref>). These negotiations are structured, in turn, by exchange relationships regarding constitutional-legal authority, finance, organizational capacity, information and political acumen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1748895811431850">Rhodes, 1997</xref>). These relationships are asymmetrical as clearly some actors, particularly European nation states with a tradition of strong, interventionist, government from the centre, have more resources to draw upon than others. Nonetheless, it is no accident that it is at the municipal scale of government that actual governing capacity for most domestic affairs is concentrated and most fiercely contested, particularly in those areas, of health, education and social services, which assume the greatest proportion of public expenditure in liberal democracies. This generates both competing mandates to govern and a degree of autonomy for municipal actors to develop their own distinctive policy agendas. Although the autonomy of local authorities from European nation states may not be as pronounced as the discretion available to municipal authorities in the United States,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1748895811431850">3</xref></sup> its existence leads advocates of regime analysis to argue that this approach can be adapted from its origins in the study of urban political-economy in the USA to the particular conditions of governance in European localities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1748895811431850">Mossberger and Stoker, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1748895811431850">Stoker and Mossberger, 1994</xref>).</p>
<p>It is argued, however, that contrasted with the relatively abstract concept of interdependence found in studies of governance, regime analysis offers more concrete concepts and testable propositions about the formation, sustainability and failure of governing arrangements arising out of relations of power-dependence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1748895811431850">Mossberger, 2009</xref>: 51). In turn, this is related to the more specific focus of regime analysis on the dilemmas encountered by <italic>public</italic> authorities who have constitutional-legal mandates to govern but are dependent on private, particularly corporate, resources for the actual capacity to govern. By contrast, studies of governance can be much broader in focus, recognizing that relations of power-dependence can also limit the writ of public authority in ways that generate competing centres of power. It is in these terms that some studies of governance identify ‘nodes’ or ‘bubbles’ of governance that exist in parallel to public authorities, as in the mass private spaces of retail malls, aeroplanes and ocean liners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1748895811431850">Johnston and Shearing, 2003</xref>) or that actively challenge public authority, as in the private ‘fiefdoms’ of paramilitary and criminal organizations and other forms of ‘governance from below’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1748895811431850">Stenson, 2005</xref>). Proponents of the concept of governance argue that one of its strengths is its relatively abstract and capacious character, which in turn enables a research programme of cumulative case studies comparing and contrasting governing arrangements as diverse as UN peace-keeping missions, state-sponsored crime prevention partnerships and the type of private government exercised by drug cartels in Mexico or war lords in Somalia (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1748895811431850">Peters and Pierre, 2006</xref>). By contrast, the more concrete analytical focus of regime analysis on the legitimacy and governing capacities of <italic>public</italic> authorities embedded in particular political-economies reflects a concern with the normative and empirical distinctiveness of public authority as an object of inquiry. Here, the analytical goal is to understand the implications of inter-dependencies between state, market and civil society <italic>for the governing capacity of public authorities, including their capacity to express and realize a collective will</italic>. This contrasts with studies of governance that have challenged the normative as well as empirical primacy (let alone the exclusivity) of the State in political analysis, in which the fragmentation of public authority is celebrated for liberating populations, such as the ‘denizens’ of South African townships, from state oppression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1748895811431850">Johnston and Shearing, 2003</xref>). Conversely, the normative as well as empirical concerns of regime analysis accord with those who are critical of this anarchistic-libertarian tendency within studies of governance, both for obscuring the moral significance of public authority (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1748895811431850">Loader and Walker, 2004</xref>) and for ignoring the importance of state power for socially excluded populations who have been abandoned by the market and are subject to the arbitrary and predatory rule of private governments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1748895811431850">Lea, 2002</xref>: 185–189).</p>
<p>In summary, the socially productive concept of the power to govern, when cognisant of the social bases of such power in specific political economies, provides regime analysis with a distinctive approach to political analysis in criminology. This foregrounds sensitizing, middle-range, concepts about the formation, reproduction and failure of governing coalitions of state and non-state actors around competing policy agendas. As such it clarifies <italic>how</italic>, for example, social justice agendas have proven so challenging to realize while nonetheless identifying the scope for enlightened policy change and learning. In the remainder of the article, we illustrate the contribution this kind of political analysis can make to criminological thought through reference to research on competing public safety agendas.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1748895811431850">
<title>Negotiation, Public Safety and Regime Analysis</title>
<p>Public safety is an especially apposite policy focus for the type of criminological research that investigates theoretical claims about the negotiation of social orders rather than their constitution through sovereign command. Indeed it is in this policy area that liberal democratic states have explicitly acknowledged the limits to their own governing capacity and the necessity of enrolling, ‘Every individual citizen and all those agencies whose policies and practices can influence the extent of crime’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1748895811431850">Home Office, 1984</xref>: 1). As such there is explicit recognition that to achieve impact, social reform initiatives depend on how governmental and non-governmental actions are aligned and, within this, how they need to be sustained through contributions from non-elites, the broader citizenry, as well as strategic support from elites with the relevant governing resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1748895811431850">Stone, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Multi-agency partnerships for the prevention of crime and disorder have become a loud refrain in public policy, certainly in Western European democracies, over the past three decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1748895811431850">Crawford, 2009</xref>). Whether such policy talk represents a genuine alignment of elite and non-elite actors in the politics of public safety or merely a ‘new liberal speak’ mystifying a more efficient and penetrating form of authoritarian state power, is the subject of lively, ongoing debate among traditions of political analysis in criminology. It is also an area of criminological research that has produced studies exemplifying each of the main traditions considered earlier and thus presents a useful focus for distinguishing the potential contribution of regime analysis. For example, the liberal tradition of demarcating politics from administration is evident in the representation of crime prevention as an enlightened, evidence-driven, exercise in ‘problem solving’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1748895811431850">Ekblom, 1988</xref>). An even more strident demarcation of the politics and administration of crime prevention is presented in the work of ‘crime science’ and its analytical techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1748895811431850">Tilley, 2002</xref>). In turn this demarcation has attracted criticism from governmental criminology for obscuring the alignment of crime prevention and community policing techniques with neo-liberal programmes of government that delimit both the problems of crime and their solution to situational opportunities and rational choices, while excluding as irrelevant the treatment of crime as an issue of social justice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1748895811431850">O’Malley, 1992</xref>). Studies of governance have further documented how the demarcation of administration from politics obscures the relations of power that contest the implementation and evaluation of crime prevention policies as well as the problematization of crime and disorder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1748895811431850">Crawford, 1997</xref>). In turn they have highlighted how the opening-out of the policy process to partnerships of state and non-state actors creates opportunities for the advancement of more diverse policy agendas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1748895811431850">Edwards and Hughes, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1748895811431850">2009</xref>). A more sceptical account of partnerships documents how they enhance authoritarian state projects, enrolling state and non-state actors in elitist programmes aimed at the repression of marginalized street populations rather than crimes of the powerful (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1748895811431850">Coleman et al., 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1748895811431850">2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1748895811431850">Croall, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The specific contribution of regime analysis to this debate is to switch the analytical focus onto issues of governing capacity, to question what policy agendas exist for public safety and how the variegated governing arrangements indicated by partnerships of state and non-state actors in varying local political economies enable or frustrate these agendas. This implies an ambitious programme of both conceptual analysis and empirical research comparing the formation of governing coalitions at the municipal level at which public safety partnerships are organized, the resources and schemes of co-operation they employ and what this tells us about the possibilities for different kinds of political action. This ‘analytic of local governance’ provokes certain research questions about the ‘particulars of local governance’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1748895811431850">Stone, 2005</xref>: 330):</p>
<list id="list2-1748895811431850" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>What specific concerns generate policy agendas?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What motivates actors to participate in governing coalitions seeking to deliver these agendas?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What resources are relevant for the governing capacity of coalitions?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>How are the schemes of co-operation constituted through blends of shared purpose, selective incentives and established inter-personal and inter-organizational networks?</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>In what follows we examine how these four research questions may open up analytical spaces as yet undeveloped in the criminological study of the politics of public safety.</p>
<sec id="section9-1748895811431850">
<title>Policy agendas for public safety</title>
<p>The ways in which problems of governing can be framed are, themselves, an important aspect of the power to govern. In these terms, the nomenclature of ‘public safety’ is not merely semantic but conveys certain political assumptions.</p>
<p>The preference for ‘community safety’ in the Anglophone world, to signify a ‘preventive turn’ in policy responses to crime, is indicative of the purchase that communitarian thinking has had on the broader spectrum of public policy in these countries and particularly on issues of ‘law and order’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1748895811431850">Hughes, 1996</xref>). This is in contrast to the preference for notions of ‘public security’ found in European countries retaining an <italic>Etatiste</italic> tradition of conservative corporatist and social democratic state intervention in defence of national-popular notions of the public sphere. Following comparisons of policy trends in penal policy across different liberal democracies, it is tempting to contrast policy trends in the ‘preventive turn’ using such ideological categories (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1748895811431850">Crawford, 2009</xref>: 9–16). In comparisons of penal policy it is argued there is a strong correspondence between high imprisonment rates and punitive cultures in ‘neo-liberal’ polities that are also marked by extreme levels of social inequality; significantly lower imprisonment rates in more solidaristic, corporatist conservative polities, with relatively less social inequality; and dramatically lower rates in the more egalitarian, social democratic, polities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1748895811431850">Cavadino and Dignan, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>However, these categories appear too abstract and too neat when transposed onto the ‘triangulated’ politics of public safety (see note 2). They elide the <italic>realpolitik</italic> of governing, particularly the compromises that have to be struck between ideological vision and the mundane economies of governing. Ideological categories may capture elements of the larger moral purposes motivating some participants in governing arrangements, but they can obscure the effects of the instrumental, self-interested, motivations of bureaucratic politics, professional enmities, special interest-group pressures and occupational sub-cultures on the power to govern. In the politics of public safety, a preoccupation with ideological standpoints and allied ‘political rationalities’ obscures the instrumental interests of police and criminal justice institutions in securing their role in policy responses to crime, and of other state and non-state institutions that seek to expand their role in this policy area and reframe crime problems in ways that privilege their role and claim on governing resources. Such ‘bureau-shaping’ politics, while glossed-over by the high politics of ideological purpose, are none the less central to the mundane governance of crime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1748895811431850">Hughes, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1748895811431850">Hughes and Edwards, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>To capture this admixture of ideological and instrumental motivations, we suggest that public safety can be defined in terms of policy agendas arranged round the concerns of justice (differentiated further between those of ‘criminal’, ‘restorative’ and ‘social’ justice) and of ‘risk management’. While these are not without their own limitations as sensitizing concepts, they resonate more with the narratives used by the participants in public safety partnerships to describe their own concerns. They also have greater purchase in the criminological research that can inform these policy agendas than the overtly ideological and somewhat monolithic notions described above. These categories also have greater international recognition and are therefore important for framing cross-cultural comparative research, while recognizing that care needs to be taken to clarify the practices signified by their usage in any particular cultural context. Used as sensitizing devices to guide empirical research into different public safety regimes, these distinctions help begin<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1748895811431850">4</xref></sup> to distinguish different agendas and are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1748895811431850">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1748895811431850" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Policy agendas for public safety</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1748895811431850" xlink:href="10.1177_1748895811431850-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Agenda</th>
<th align="left">Concerns</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Criminal justice</td>
<td><italic>Public safety policies augment criminal law enforcement and public order policing</italic> through such measures as: ‘community intelligence’ about ‘prolific and priority’ offenders (PPOs); enhanced surveillance of suspects of serious crimes and in support of counter-terrorism; monitoring of serious offenders on release from conviction; prosecution of suspects of ‘anti-social behaviour’</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Risk management</td>
<td><italic>Public safety policies anticipate risks</italic> through such measures as: reducing the situational opportunities for crime; early interventions with groups ‘at risk’ of embarking on offending careers or of becoming victimized; prudential advice and inducements enabling citizens to take responsibility for their own safety</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Restorative justice</td>
<td><italic>Public safety policies facilitate the reintegration of offenders and non-state conflict resolution</italic> through such measures as: diversion from custody; referral to youth offending panels; negotiation of reparations between victims and offenders</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Social justice</td>
<td><italic>Public safety policies augment policies for the social and political inclusion of all citizens</italic> through such measures as: extending the entitlements of citizens to improved education, training, employment, housing, health, leisure and family support; improving adult health and safety at work; targeting corporate and environmental crimes as well as street crime; facilitating citizen engagement with government and active citizenship</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>To reiterate, these are sensitizing devices aimed at diagnosing the principal orientation and focus of a public safety regime as, and if, it is stabilized around particular policy goals. In practice, public safety regimes may incorporate inchoate, potentially contradictory,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1748895811431850">5</xref></sup> admixtures of a number of these policy concerns. Inchoate agendas may, in turn, reflect the ongoing political struggles (of ideological and instrumental motivation) to steer a regime away from one policy direction to another and the consequent failure to negotiate an agreed agenda around which a governing coalition can coalesce and which a regime can be stabilized. An outcome of such struggle can be policy drift and regime failure, so there is no presumption that regimes are accomplished. This is a moot point for empirical research, off the back of which this preliminary characterization of public safety regimes can be further refined.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1748895811431850">
<title>The motivations of governing coalitions for public safety</title>
<p>The distinction between ideological and instrumental motivations for participation in public safety politics draws on an understanding, in regime theory, of political actors as ‘meaning seeking’ as well as self-interested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1748895811431850">Stone, 2005</xref>). It helps to clarify the different motivations that prospective participants might have and the range of inducements that are needed for enrolling them into governing coalitions and for maintaining their continued participation, given the particular structural contexts of governing arrangements.</p>
<p>To take the example of public safety politics in England and Wales, certain state institutions (constabularies, police authorities, local government, health authorities, fire services and probation services) are statutorily obliged to form partnerships for the reduction of crime and disorder, and to undertake annual ‘strategic assessments’ of community safety. Prior to the election of the UK Coalition Government in May 2010, they were also required to meet certain performance targets defined in ‘public service agreements’ with central government in exchange for grant aid. Nonetheless, even under the auspices of this former, more <italic>dirigiste</italic>, government, local discretion existed in the agendas of particular partnerships and the uptake of particular powers, such as CCTV surveillance, anti-social behaviour orders, problem-oriented policing initiatives, youth crime prevention and substance misuse programmes, burglary reduction schemes, restorative justice panels and so on (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1748895811431850">Hughes, 2007</xref>: 54–138). For example, case study research suggests a diversity of public safety regimes, with Merseyside depicted as pursuing an agenda primarily oriented around criminal justice and risk management (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1748895811431850">Coleman et al., 2002</xref>), while the Thames Valley region prioritized innovations in restorative justice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1748895811431850">Burney, 2005</xref>). In turn, other case studies identify the lack of any coherent agenda and partnership drift or, in the terms advanced here, of regime failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1748895811431850">Hallsworth, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>Whether such diversity reflects the particular theoretical reconstructions of these partnerships or a genuine diversity of practices remains a moot point and one we would argue is better clarified through comparative case study research employing the concepts of regime analysis. What is needed is a programme of empirical research into the particular participants in these partnerships and their motivations. For, while the English experience suggests the domination of state institutions, notwithstanding the considerable clash of bureaucratic interests and occupational subcultures among these (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1748895811431850">Crawford, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1748895811431850">Hughes, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1748895811431850">2007</xref>), there is evidence of greater commercial participation in relation to problems of particular interest to the business sector, for example in reducing alcohol-related violence in the night-time economy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1748895811431850">Hobbs et al., 2005</xref>). As a policy agenda, restorative justice has also attracted significant interest from voluntary or ‘third sector’ organizations, particularly from faith organizations given the roots of restorative justice in religious notions of repentance and recompense (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1748895811431850">Braithwaite, 1989</xref>). Evidence for the pursuit of ‘larger purposes’, infused with moral and ideological meaning, can also be found in the devolved Welsh Government’s social justice agenda for community safety (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1748895811431850">Drakeford, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1748895811431850">Edwards and Hughes, 2009</xref>). Again, whether the Welsh Government’s agenda is translated into practice across different Welsh municipalities is a moot point for case study research into governing capacity and competing policy agendas (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1748895811431850">Muncie, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Of particular interest is whether and how the admixture of instrumental and ‘meaning-seeking’ motivations are sufficiently aligned to stabilize public safety regimes around the focal concerns of criminal, restorative and social justice and of risk management. Analyses of governing capacity are consequently concerned with whether and how any contradictions between these policy concerns can be reconciled and what lessons can be drawn from comparative research into how public safety agendas can be otherwise negotiated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1748895811431850">
<title>Relevant resources for governing public safety</title>
<p>The concern with instrumental and expressive motivations deliberately steers political analysis towards a Weberian, humanistic, focus on the possibilities for agency, but this is combined in regime analysis with an acknowledgement of how political interaction is structured by the relevant resources for governing capacity. To re-emphasize, regime analysis is a form of political economy precisely because it acknowledges the dependence of liberal democratic states on private sector resources for delivering policy agendas, particularly at the municipal level which is, across modern states, the fulcrum of legitimate governing capacity. By return, however, business interests are dependent on state institutions to provide the conditions for capital accumulation, as exemplified in bargaining over the inward investment, employment opportunities and local revenues generated by night-time economies and responsibility for policing the health and safety consequences of alcohol-based leisure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1748895811431850">Hobbs et al, 2005</xref>). It is precisely as a consequence of these power-dependent relationships that political choices and opportunities for regime change exist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1748895811431850">Edwards and Hughes, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Again, the structuring of political interactions in specific social contexts and in relation to particular governing problems is a question for empirical investigation. It is possible, however, to distinguish the kinds of <italic>constitutional-legal, financial, organizational, informational</italic> and <italic>political</italic> resources that structure these interactions in the policy field of public safety.</p>
<p>To continue with examples from the UK, it was noted earlier how the statutory duty placed on ‘responsible authorities’ for community safety has ensured the pre-dominance of state institutions in governing arrangements and how, pre-Coalition Government, agendas were structured by the dependence of municipal partnerships on central government grant aid and allied performance management targets. Although, at the time of writing, Coalition Government reforms of community safety are still in formulation, the emphasis, in the Police Reform and Social Responsibility Act 2011, on both reducing central government grant aid, abolishing performance management and devolving greater discretion to partnerships overseen by elected Police and Crime Commissioners (PCCs), suggests there will be greater diversity of regimes forming and failing around a broad range of agendas. The other major structural change within the UK constitution is the impact of devolution on public safety. Scotland, along with Northern Ireland, has independent institutions of public safety and provides an important focal point for comparative policy research within the UK (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1748895811431850">Henry, 2009</xref>). While England and Wales are invariably treated as a single political entity for the purposes of criminal justice research and while policing and criminal justice are not, as yet, competencies that have been devolved to the Welsh Government, responsibility for other public safety-relevant competencies has been, notably education, health and social services. The Welsh Government has used these competencies to define a social justice agenda for youth crime prevention and action on substance misuse, including the major policy concern with alcohol-related violence against the person (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1748895811431850">Drakeford, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1748895811431850">Edwards and Hughes, 2009</xref>). In these terms, the constitutional-legal restructuring of the UK polity has created a major resource for setting diverse policy agendas.</p>
<p>Another structural change is in relation to <italic>financial</italic> resources, specifically the major retrenchment in public expenditure across the liberal democracies post-financial crisis of 2008 and the related intensification of sovereign debts. How public safety regimes will form and fail in the ‘age of austerity’ is a key subject for political-economic analyses. There is scepticism about notions of the ‘big society’ and of self-regulation, as surrogate forms of governance for state intervention, particularly in localities whose political-economic histories have left them relatively dependent on the public sector. From the perspective of regime analysis, though, the context of austere public finances places an even greater onus on leveraging inward corporate investment to localities with a concomitant increase in the structural power of business to set local policy agendas. This emerging structural context promises to make regime analysis, hitherto criticized as an ethnocentrically US form of political analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1748895811431850">Davies, 2002</xref>), even more commensurate with the conditions of European liberal democracies. An obvious proposition is that such structural conditions will further reduce the scope for social justice agendas, and possibly for the resource-intensive agendas of criminal justice,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1748895811431850">6</xref></sup> while prioritizing risk management agendas that claim to minimize the opportunities for crime and the costs of their reduction for indebted local states. Another plausible scenario is the abandonment of non-profitable populations and localities by both the State and market; a hollowing-out of governing capacity, providing opportunities for predatory forms of governance from below, including forms of ‘authoritarian gangsterism’.</p>
<p>Even so, local state institutions still retain the major <italic>organizational</italic> and <italic>informational</italic> resources relevant for governing capacity, particularly in relation to ‘public’, ‘collectively consumed’ goods that cannot be delivered through market mechanisms and are of limited self-interest to business. Many of the issues that are central to public safety agendas, local electorates and their mass media interlocutors (see later), are of negligible self-interest to the commercial sector. Short of a major infusion of ‘large moral purpose’ in the corporate sector it seems unlikely that much governing capacity will be left for addressing concerns about the ‘anti-social behaviour’ of youthful street populations and the gross concentration of criminal victimization, for both personal and property offences, on residential populations characterized by other indices of multiple disadvantage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1748895811431850">Hope, 2001</xref>). It is suggested there is even less self-interest among the corporate sector for providing resources to address corporate crimes and issues of health and safety in the workplace (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1748895811431850">Croall, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Yet, the impact of overtly <italic>political</italic> resources – scandals, media coverage, perceptions of governing incompetence and gluttonous, exploitative, commerce – on the structure of political interactions cannot be underestimated. At the time of writing the UK is immersed in one of the greatest corruption scandals in living memory, involving allegations of payments to the police by tabloid editors and their employment of private detectives to ‘hack’ personal information from the mobile phones of private citizens (most notoriously of all, the phone of the murdered teenager Milly Dowler). Off the back of the scandal of fraudulent expenses claims by Members of Parliament and of the grotesquely inflated bonuses and redundancy settlements received by financiers widely regarded as responsible for the financial crash of 2008, the elimination of social justice concerns from the public policy agenda cannot be assumed. This structural context elicits significant public outrage at the behaviour of major state and commercial institutions and not inconsiderable pressures for a re-moralization of public life.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1748895811431850">
<title>Schemes of co-operation constituting public safety regimes</title>
<p>Whether and how the resources afforded by the structural contexts of political interaction are apprehended and used by coalition members in pursuit of particular agendas cannot be imputed from these structural contexts. Rather, they need to be understood in relation to devices for inducing, rewarding, threatening and otherwise recruiting supporters of a particular policy agenda while discrediting and disorganizing opponents. Again, instrumental and expressive motivations play a major role. Whether it is possible to buy support through various ‘selective incentives’ (e.g. performance management, grant aid, awards of lucrative contracts, channelling of public sector investment in schools, police patrols, youth services and so on, into particular municipalities, parliamentary constituencies and electoral wards) or through exerting moral pressures for the pursuit of ‘large purposes’ such as social justice or by threatening reputational damage for the non-compliant, all constitute the ‘blood and guts’ of political interaction. It is this full blooded concept of political interaction, rather than the relatively anaemic image of ‘rational choice’, that regime analysis seeks to capture and explain through its notion of ‘schemes of co-operation’.</p>
<p>These schemes are the stratagems through which governing capacity is actually realized and through which it can be lost. In public safety, advocacy of criminal justice invariably plays on, or feels obliged to respond to, public outrage at ‘signal events’ of criminal victimization and wrongdoing, especially in relation to the vulnerable, and this invariably outflanks the cold-hearted rationality of appeals to the social science of ‘what works, what doesn’t and what’s promising’ about crime prevention. By contrast these narratives and the vernacular of ‘business analytics’ predominate in risk management agendas; sentiment has little purchase on the bottom line. As criminal justice operates with a moral code of retribution, so restorative agendas employ the litany of repentance and forgiveness augmented with claims about the cost-effectiveness of re-integrative shaming relative to the stigmata and recidivism of the penal process. Meanwhile, social justice agendas appeal to a larger purpose, displacing categories of crime and risk into those of problems of social inequality, integration and regulation.</p>
<p>The distinction between selective incentives and larger purposes alerts us to the ‘bounded rationality’ and ‘inherent conservatism’ of the political process and how these impact on schemes of co-operation. Regime analysts presume that a major inhibition to social justice agendas, limiting their recruitment of supporters, is the bounded rationality of most citizens, particularly their preoccupation with the familiar and the immediate. This is, of course, a dominant refrain among advocates of criminal justice as the immediate wrongs of an offence and the harms experienced by particular victims are more intelligible for most citizens than the relatively nebulous concepts of social and political exclusion and their putative relationship to individual offending behaviour or the distribution of victimization. Translating this relationship for popular consumption and mobilization bedevils advocates of social justice agendas. In contrast, advocates of risk management self-consciously bracket-off the ‘distal’, remote (in their terms), causes of crime from the ‘proximate’, situational, opportunities for crime and reduction. Again, advocates of social justice agendas struggle to translate the antecedent conditions of these opportunities and of the particular crime events circumscribed by crime scientists for the purposes of measuring ‘hot-spots’ and targeting preventive efforts. However, advocates of restorative justice can convey their concerns through the relatively comprehensible ideas of bringing offenders and victims face-to-face for the purposes of apology, reparation and forgiveness. Advocates of social justice, again, struggle to counter this methodological individualism with accounts of the cultural contexts in which apology, reparation and reintegration are likely to work or at least to avoid exacerbating social conflicts.</p>
<p>Even so, there is evidence of attempts to cultivate shared purposes around notions of safer cities, quality of life and local economic regeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1748895811431850">Hughes, 2007</xref>: 165–191). A sceptic might argue these are less to do with social justice than ‘civic boosterism’ in a structural context compelling localities to compete with each other for inward investment. The concepts of regime analysis suggest, however, that framing issues of public safety explicitly in the terms of local political economy create opportunities for better articulating the relevance of social inclusion. The current preponderance of ‘strategic thinking’, evident in the English experiment with ‘local strategic partnerships’ and, in Wales, with ‘local service boards’, about how entire cities and localities ought to be governed, explicitly identify interrelationships between crime, health, education, employment, housing, provision for young people or, in the argot of crime prevention, issues of ‘primary prevention’ that are geared towards the entire population, not just known offenders and victims nor even ‘at risk’ groups.</p>
<p>For regime analysis schemes of co-operation do often work with the grain of established preferences, for example responding to popular perceptions of crime and just law and order, and maintaining the predominant role of those state institutions popularly associated with crime control. Experience suggests, however, that such ‘maintenance regimes’ experience recurrent crises of legitimacy as their inability to govern public safety results in popular and media pressures for change given the perceived inadequacies of policing and criminal justice solutions to problems of crime and disorder (most recently evidenced in the aftermath of the civil unrest in English cities in August 2011).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1748895811431850">7</xref></sup> This was, after all, the origin of the experiment in multi-agency crime prevention partnerships over the past three decades in the UK.</p>
<p>Such crises generate opportunities for regime change and, again, regime analysis suggests three ideal-typical solutions for empirical investigation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1748895811431850">Stone, 2005</xref>). First, ‘developmental regimes’ work with established inter-personal and inter-organizational networks but seek to augment these. In public safety terms, it is evident how risk management agendas have been aligned with criminal justice agendas to develop the capacity for crime reduction. We might hypothesize that this admixture characterizes the dominant form of public safety regime in England and Wales over the past three decades. Second, restorative agendas have an affinity with the ideal type of the ‘progressive regime’ identified by some regime analysts to reflect the political clout of the liberal middle-class and, particularly, of faith-based organizations in local governance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1748895811431850">Stone, 2005</xref>). Such regimes have proven particularly attractive in relatively prosperous localities with sufficient pockets of crime to warrant some policy response but without the critical mass of public safety problems that can qualify local partnerships for substantial grant aid. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1748895811431850">Stenson (2002)</xref> identifies these motivations as central to understanding how the Thames Valley community safety partnership in ‘middle England’ acquired such a reputation for its innovations with restorative justice. Third, as noted in the broader research programme of regime analysis, ‘social justice regimes’ promising radical egalitarian agendas are rare, both because they entail a break with (rather than a progressive addition to) established local political networks and interests and because they require major leaps of imagination among prospective supporters as to what such a regime might look like in practice and how the governing capacity for it might be realized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1748895811431850">Stoker and Mossberger, 1994</xref>). Even so, major political-economic shocks, such as the scandals, public disorders and perceived injustices of austere public services discussed above, do create the structural context for regime change. Whether there is the political acumen to build a shared purpose around a social justice agenda for public safety remains an issue for empirical investigation and a challenge for a critical social science that uses its skills to support policy and practice developments towards this agenda, and not simply to document or decry them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1748895811431850">Goldson and Hughes, 2010</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1748895811431850" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>There are two modest ambitions underpinning this article. First it has sought to make a contribution to both the revitalization of conceptually and empirically innovative research into the politics of local crime control and public safety in critical criminology. Second, it has argued for the rebalancing of critical interventions in criminology by engaging with both the regressive and progressive policies and practices on the ‘crime question’. More specifically, we have argued that one fruitful means of working through the limitations of much existing political analysis in criminology is by means of the promotion of the middle range political-economic analysis associated with regime theory. In particular, the article has sought to highlight how power ‘constructs’ as well as ‘constrains’ to acknowledge the negotiation not just command of social orders; an analytical position widely associated with Foucault’s work. However, unlike Foucault and in line with critical realist thinkers like <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1748895811431850">Sayer (2011</xref>: 242), we contend the crucial next step in discussing the nature of power is to distinguish between ‘the benign and malign forms of such power’ and to study their effects on human suffering and flourishing. Finally, the conceptual tools offered up by regime analysis provide critical social scientists with the possibility of deploying their skills to provoke policy change.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1748895811431850">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Commentators acknowledge a similar process of warehousing in other liberal democracies, especially those characterized by extreme social inequalities and lacking the protection provided by social democratic welfare states (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1748895811431850">Cavadino and Dignan, 2006</xref>). Underpinning this analysis of a ‘punitive turn’ is a belief in the functionality of imprisonment for incapacitating populations that are now surplus to the requirements of formal labour markets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1748895811431850">Pratt et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1748895811431850">
<label>2.</label>
<p>The New Labour administrations in Britain, following Clinton’s administration in the USA, were, for example, renowned for their promotion of ‘triangulation’ as a political strategy for partially incorporating policy goals and initiatives from across the ideological spectrum as a means of outflanking political opponents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1748895811431850">Campbell and Rockman, 2002</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1748895811431850">
<label>3.</label>
<p>That noted, the ‘localism’ agenda currently being pursued by the Coalition Government in Westminster and Whitehall promises to take local governance in England further away from the ideals of the European model of interventionist nation states and towards a US model of greater local autonomy over policy agendas but with less national financial support for realizing these agendas.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1748895811431850">
<label>4.</label>
<p>In advance of an empirical programme of research designed specifically for the purposes of regime analysis, these concepts are necessarily simple and heuristic. It is expected that cumulative evidence from case studies and comparative analyses of public safety regimes will result in their revision and refinement to better understand the concrete experiences of regime formation, reproduction and failure.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1748895811431850">
<label>5.</label>
<p>For example the objectives of diversion and reintegration for offenders found in restorative policy goals and the use of anti-social behaviour orders against the same offenders to evict them from their residential addresses, prohibit their presence in particular geographical areas and at certain times and otherwise frustrate their re-integration.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1748895811431850">
<label>6.</label>
<p>However the dramatic reversal of the Coalition Government’s sentencing policy proposals for serious sexual offences in 2011 is a stark reminder of the substantial power that overtly political resources hold.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1748895811431850">
<label>7.</label>
<p>Major incidents of civil unrest escalated first across London, following a public protest against a fatal police shooting of a young African-Caribbean male in Tottenham, and subsequently in provincial English cities including Birmingham, Wolverhampton, Manchester and Liverpool over the first weekend in August 2011. Popular accounts of these incidents included a focus on the ‘sheer criminality’ and opportunism of those involved in widespread arson and looting, the role of criminal gangs in organizing this unrest, including the novel use of smart phone technologies and ‘flash mobbing’ (in which rapid assembly of looters and arsonists at particular places and moments is co-ordinated through mobile phone messaging services) and on a broader moral malaise in which young urban populations were thought to have followed the example of feckless finance capitalists and corrupt politicians in helping themselves to desired goods that could not be secured legally. More sober reflection from the social scientific community awaits the outcome of ongoing empirical investigation into the actual sentiments and motivations behind these events, including their significance for clarifying the formation, sustainability and failure of particular public safety regimes. It remains, for example, a moot point whether the policy agendas of criminal justice and risk management will suffice as a response to the emerging social problems associated with urban populations that are being ejected from the formal labour process precisely at the same time that draconian public expenditure cuts (in the region of 20–30 per cent) are being made to the police and other public authorities. In these terms, the riots and their aftermath provide an acid test of whether it is possible to so degrade the governing capacity of public authorities, particularly in a context of economic stagnation and increasing unemployment, while simultaneously seeking to re-moralize civil society and re-legitimize public authority.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Adam Edwards</bold> is Senior Lecturer in Criminology at Cardiff School of Social Sciences, Cardiff University.</p>
<p><bold>Gordon Hughes</bold> is Professor of Criminology at Cardiff School of Social Sciences, Cardiff University.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Braithwaite</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>Crime, Shame and Reintegration</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burney</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Making People Behave: Anti-Social Behaviour, Politics and Policy</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Buzan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Wilde</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Security: A New Framework for Analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Boulder, CO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lynne Rienner</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rockman</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Third Way leadership, old way government: Blair, Clinton and the power to govern</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Politics and International Relations</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cavadino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dignan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Penal policy and political economy</article-title>. <source>Criminology and Criminal Justice</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whyte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Power, politics and partnerships: The state of crime prevention on Merseyside</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Crime Control and Community: The New Politics of Public Safety</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tombs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whyte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Introduction: State, power, crime</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Colman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tombs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whyte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>State, Power, Crime</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>The Local Governance of Crime</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Situating crime prevention policies in comparative perspective: Policy travels, transfer and translation</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Crime Prevention Policies in Comparative Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Croall</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Community safety and economic crime</article-title>. <source>Criminology and Criminal Justice</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Urban regime theory: A normative-empirical critique</article-title>. <source>Journal of Urban Affairs</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Downes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>‘Hostages to fortune’? The politics of law and order in post-war Britain</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Oxford Handbook of Criminology</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Downes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Dumping the ‘hostages to fortune’? The politics of law and order in post-war Britain</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Oxford Handbook of Criminology</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Downes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The skeletons in the cupboard: The politics of law and order at the turn of the millennium</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Oxford Handbook of Criminology</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Downes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>No turning back: The politics of law and order into the millennium</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Oxford Handbook of Criminology</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Drakeford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Devolution and youth justice in Wales</article-title>. <source>Criminology and Criminal Justice</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Introduction: The community governance of crime control</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Crime Control and Community: The New Politics of Public Safety</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Comparing the governance of safety in Europe: A geo-historical approach</article-title>. <source>Theoretical Criminology</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>345</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The preventive turn and the promotion of safer communities in England and Wales: Political inventiveness and governmental instabilities</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Crime Prevention Policies in Comparative Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sheptycki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Third Wave criminology: Guns, crime and social order</article-title>. <source>Criminology and Criminal Justice Studies</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ekblom</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <source>Getting the Best Out of Crime Analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Crime Prevention Unit, Paper 10. London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Home Office</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Garland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The limits of the sovereign state: Strategies of crime control in contemporary society</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Criminology</source> <volume>36</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>471</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Garland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>The Culture of Control</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Sociological criminology and youth justice: Comparative policy analysis and academic intervention</article-title>. <source>Criminology and Criminal Justice</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Habermas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <source>Legitimation Crisis</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Heineman</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>The great moving right show</article-title>. <source>Marxism Today</source> <month>January</month>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Interview with Stuart Hall, Thinking Allowed, BBC Radio 4</article-title>, <day>21</day> <month>March</month>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00zfkfn">http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00zfkfn</ext-link>.</comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Critcher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <source>Policing the Crisis: Mugging, the State and Law and Order</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hallsworth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Representations and realities in local crime prevention: Some lessons from London and lessons for criminology</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Crime Control and Community: The New Politics of Public Safety</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hallsworth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lea</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Reconstructing Leviathan: Emerging contours of the security state</article-title>. <source>Theoretical Criminology</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The development of community safety in Scotland: A different path?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Crime Prevention Policies in Comparative Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hobbs</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winlow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hadfield</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Violent hypocrisy: Governance and the night-time economy</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Criminology</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Home Office</collab> (<year>1984</year>) <source>Crime Prevention</source>. <publisher-loc>Circular 8/84. London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Home Office</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hope</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Crime victimisation and inequality in risk society</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Crime Prevention, Disorder and Community Safety</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Communitarianism and law and order</article-title>. <source>Critical Social Policy</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Understanding Crime Prevention: Social Control, Risk and Late Modernity</source>. <publisher-loc>Buckingham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open University Press/McGraw</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>The Politics of Crime and Community</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Crime Control and Community: The New Politics of Public Safety</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jessop</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>State Theory: Putting Capitalist States in Their Place</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shearing</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>The Governance of Security: Explorations in Policing and Justice</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The governance of security: Pluralization, privatization, and polarization in crime control</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Oxford Handbook of Criminology</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newburn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Policy Transfer and Criminal Justice: Exploring US Influence over British Crime Control Policy</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw Hill</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Karstedt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The new institutionalism in criminology: Approaches, theories and themes</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newburn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The SAGE Handbook of Criminological Theory</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lea</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Crime and Modernity</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leftwich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>On the politics of politics</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Leftwich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>What Is Politics?</source> <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basil Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Loader</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Public Criminology? Criminological Politics in the Twenty-First Century</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Loader</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>State of denial? Rethinking governance and security</article-title>. <source>Punishment and Society</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>RAW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>1992</year>) <source>Policy Networks in British Government</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Clarendon Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Critical criminology</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newburn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The SAGE Handbook of Criminological Theory</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Molotch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>The city as a growth machine</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source> <volume>82</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mossberger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Urban regime analysis</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Imbroscio</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Theories of Urban Politics</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mossberger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stoker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The evolution of urban regime theory: The challenge of conceptualization</article-title>. <source>Urban Affairs Review</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mouleart</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swyngedouw</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Introduction: Social innovation and governance in European cities: Urban development between path dependency and radial innovation</article-title>. <source>European Urban and Regional Studies</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muncie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Illusions of difference: Comparative youth justice in the devolved United Kingdom</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Criminology</source> <volume>51</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Newburn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2004</year>) <source>Criminal Justice and Political Culture: National and International Dimensions of Crime Control</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Offe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <source>Contradictions of the Welfare State</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hutchinson</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Malley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Risk, power and crime prevention</article-title>. <source>Economy and Society</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>252</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Malley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Governmental criminology</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newburn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The SAGE Handbook of Criminological Theory</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pierre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Governance, government and the state</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The State: Theories and Issues</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Poulantzas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <source>State, Power, Socialism</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New Left Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hallsworth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2005</year>) <source>The New Punitiveness: Trends, Theories, Perspectives</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Law and Order: An Honest Citizen’s Guide to Crime and Control</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>RAW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Understanding Governance</source>. <publisher-loc>Buckingham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Political power beyond the state: Problematics of government</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Sociology</source> <volume>43</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sayer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Why Things Matter to People: Social Science, Values and Ethical Life</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Evidence and liberty: The promise of experimental criminology</article-title>. <source>Criminology and Criminal Justice</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gottfredson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bushway</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Preventing Crime: What Works, What Doesn’t, What’s Promising</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Institute of Justice</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Governing through Crime: How the War on Crime Transformed American Democracy and Created a Culture of Fear</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Smandych</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) (<year>1999</year>) <source>Governable Places: Readings on Governmentality and Crime Control</source>. <publisher-loc>Aldershot</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stenson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Community safety in Middle England: The local politics of crime control</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Crime Control and Community: The New Politics of Public Safety</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stenson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Sovereignty, biopolitics and the local government of crime in Britain</article-title>. <source>Theoretical Criminology</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stenson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Crime control and local governance: The struggle for sovereignty in advanced liberal polities</article-title>. <source>Contemporary Politics</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>217</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stoker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mossberger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Urban regime theory in comparative perspective</article-title>. <source>Environment and Planning C: Government and Policy</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>Regime Politics: Governing Atlanta 1946– 1988</source>. <publisher-loc>Lawrence, KS</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University Press of Kansas</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Looking back to look forward: Reflections on urban regime analysis</article-title>. <source>Urban Affairs Review</source> <volume>40</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Power, reform and urban regime analysis</article-title>. <source>City and Community</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pierannunzi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Atlanta’s biracial coalition in transition</article-title>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the annual meeting of the American Political Science Association</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Washington, DC</conf-loc>, <conf-date>31 August–3 September</conf-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tilley</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The rediscovery of learning: Crime prevention and scientific realism</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Crime Control and Community: The New Politics of Public Safety</source>. <publisher-loc>Cullompton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Willan Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tilley</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Sherman vs Sherman: Realism versus rhetoric</article-title>. <source>Criminology and Criminal Justice</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wacquant</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Punishing the Poor: The Neoliberal Government of Social Insecurity</source>. <publisher-loc>Michigan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-1748895811431850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Incessant chatter: Recent paradigms in criminology</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Oxford Handbook of Criminology</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>