<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EDQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spedq</journal-id>
<journal-title>Economic Development Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0891-2424</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3543</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0891242412457484</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0891242412457484</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Reconnecting Markets: Innovative Global Practices in Connecting Small-Scale Producers With Dynamic Food Markets</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Metcalf</surname><given-names>Sara</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0891242412457484">State University of New York, Buffalo, NY, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>26</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>373</fpage>
<lpage>374</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Biénabe</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berdegué</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peppelenbos</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Belt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>2011</year>). <source>Reconnecting Markets: Innovative Global Practices in Connecting Small-Scale Producers With Dynamic Food Markets</source>. <publisher-loc>Farnham, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Gower</publisher-name>. ISBN <isbn>978-1-4094-3027-8</isbn></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The editors have combined their expertise in agricultural economics, rural development, and sustainable trade to produce an informative book about the challenges and opportunities for small-scale farmers in globalizing markets. Through the use of examples, this book provides a glimpse of the possibility of space for innovative inclusion of small-scale producers in global food chains. After introducing a conceptual framework of inclusion in terms of vertical and horizontal supply chain integration, a series of 10 cases is then presented. Each case report is structured around a set of guiding questions that call attention to the nature of the innovation, the supply chain context, evidence of inclusion, and the prospects for diffusion of the innovation to other settings. Contributing authors represent academic institutions, governments, nongovernmental organizations, and businesses from the diverse geographies of China, the Philippines, India, Sri Lanka, Bulgaria, Togo, South Africa, Guatemala, and Mexico.</p>
<p>These cases are pragmatic examples of best practices for including small-scale food producers in local, regional, national, and international supply chains. By way of these examples, the book can help scholars and practitioners navigate emerging economic spaces in the agrifood chain that have been enabled by international development. Equipped with an index and chapter-specific bibliographies, the book serves as a useful reference for those interested in the role that smallholders can play in global agrifood chains. The cases in this volume are a subset of 39 selected cases (out of 131 submissions) during two rounds of global competitions for the Regoverning Markets program in 2005 and 2006. The book’s conclusion summarizes insights from the entire set of 39 cases, along with direct links to full reports for each of the cases online. Several themes appear in comparing these examples of smallholder inclusion. The extent to which these forms of smallholder inclusion in dynamic markets are replicable is considered along institutional, organizational, financial, and attitudinal dimensions of sustainability. In closing, the editors advocate anticipatory policy that addresses the economic and social needs that accompany restructuring.</p>
<p>While opportunities for cooperation within a globally competitive value chain are highlighted, the book also emphasizes that inclusion of small-scale farmers in supply chain governance is less common than participation. One path to inclusion is through the development of farmer’s organizations, which provide a certain strength in numbers to influence the structure and decisions of the supply chain. Such organizations streamline the exchange costs incurred by the value chain and can provide downstream benefits, as food processors, distributors, and retailers often prefer (and are willing to pay a premium) to deal with organizations rather than individual farmers.</p>
<p>The addition of an intermediary can improve farmers’ access to high-value markets such as regional supermarkets and export markets. Some intermediaries add value to the chain by facilitating produce quality assessment and certification, as with the emergence of producer organizations to evaluate avocado crops in Mexico (Chapter 10). Intermediaries may also provide advice on crop selection and market potential based on closer knowledge of current trends. As relationships develop across the supply chain, practices of transparency build trust between stakeholders and enable the entire system to become more efficient. For example, MA’S Tropical Food Company in Sri Lanka practices transparency in openly sharing cost details so as to better inform the whole supply chain (Chapter 3).</p>
<p>Supermarkets and large corporate members of the food chain often have rigid quality requirements that are difficult for small-scale producers to meet without support from the public and private sectors. In the case of spice production in Sri Lanka (Chapter 3), a lack of quality consciousness among producers was cited as a major barrier to entering a market that places quality at a premium. Although organic practices are preferred for the highest quality food, customer’s negative associations with the organic label and indigenous production in the Philippines (Chapter 6) compelled Upland Marketing Foundation Incorporated to cautiously label its organic rice instead as “Healthy Rice.”</p>
<p>One risk of integrating the supply chain with intermediaries to connect small-scale farmers with dynamic markets is that new members might exploit their position in the value chain by underpaying farmers and overcharging customers. For this reason, the elimination of costly intermediaries can streamline the food chain relative to conventional channels (e.g., Chapter 9). The risk of exploitation by intermediaries can be minimized with farmers’ organizations, knowledge sharing, and cultivation of trust among stakeholders.</p>
<p>The coexistence of informal economies alongside export-oriented agriculture, and the persistence of subsistence farming, suggests that 100% inclusion of small farmers in formal markets is unlikely. The costs of participating in high-value, often volatile formal markets make participation daunting for traditional farmers. Downstream members of the food chain such as Carrefour in China (Chapter 1) and Soya Nyo in Togo (Chapter 7), while promoting inclusion of smallholders, manage to avoid dealing with farmers who subsist at the smallest scale due to concerns over crop consistency and commitment. Others, such as HOPCOMs in India (Chapter 9), are designed to be nonexclusionary, benefitting marginal as well as small farmers.</p>
<p>Contributors to this volume recognize economic forces as shaping a dynamic environment of shifting opportunities in which small-scale farmers must surmount significant hurdles to gain financial security. External support from both the private and public sectors is needed to build the capacity of small-scale farmers to adapt to the restructuring of agrifood systems. In countries such as Bulgaria (Chapter 4) that have experienced liberalizing of state-controlled economies, small-scale farmers stand to benefit particularly from alignment of public policy with private sector priorities that enhance the entrepreneurial capacity of their farms.</p>
<p><italic>Reconnecting Markets</italic> is the second of two volumes to emerge from the Regoverning Markets program. The first volume, <italic>Regoverning Markets: A Place for Small-Scale Producers in Modern Agrifood Chains?</italic>, was published in 2007 and edited by Bill Vorley, Andrew Fearne, and Derek Ray. Andrew Fearne is also the editor of the Gower Sustainable Food Chains series, which is composed of these volumes as the first two in the series. Both volumes consist of selections from the larger set of cases included in the Regoverning Markets program. One of the strengths of this project is that materials about each case in the program are available online at the Regoverning Markets website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.RegoverningMarkets.org">www.RegoverningMarkets.org</ext-link>). <italic>Reconnecting Markets</italic> therefore represents the latest portal to a wealth of online information about perspectives championed by the Regoverning Markets program.</p>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<title>Bio</title>
<p><bold>Sara Metcalf</bold> conducts research utilizing dynamic modeling to address problems in urban geography. Her research is focused on the potential for urban agriculture in local food systems and the social dimensions of healthy aging in urban environments. She has a PhD in geography from the University of Illinois, an MBA and MS in chemical engineering from MIT, and BS degrees in chemical engineering and biochemistry from Texas A&amp;M University.</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>