<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="abstract">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JRI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjri</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Research in International Education</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1475-2409</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-2943</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1475240912468735</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1475240912468735</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Thesis abstracts</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Perspectives on the EdD from academics at English universities</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>Jeff</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1475240912468735">Doctor of Education 2012 University of Bath Email: <email>brianqpoole@gmail.com</email></aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<issue-title>Tenth anniversary special issue</issue-title>
<fpage>283</fpage>
<lpage>284</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">IBO, Sage Ltd.</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Since first appearing in British universities during the early 1990s, the Doctor of Education (EdD) degree has spread rapidly through the UK higher education sector. However, despite the existence of a single set of Quality Assurance Agency (QAA) descriptors for doctoral-level achievement, some in academia have always been willing to describe the EdD, either openly or in private, as inferior to the PhD. This thesis endeavours (through a wide-ranging questionnaire completed anonymously by 27 academics from a total of 16 English universities, and follow-up interviews with seven individuals selected from the original sample) to discover how a sample of those who teach on such programmes (EdD academics) view the EdD, in general terms. For instance, it seeks to ascertain how widespread among EdD academics is the notion that the EdD does not reach the ‘gold standard’ represented by the PhD in Education.</p>
<p>As data collection proceeds from the questionnaire to the interviews, the focus narrows to three key topics: specific characteristics of the EdD as compared with the PhD in Education (in terms, for example, of learning experience, programme aims, and modes of assessment); strengths, weaknesses and purposes of the EdD <italic>viva voce</italic> examination; and the concept of ‘originality’ as operationalized by EdD academics/examiners in deciding whether or not an EdD candidate/thesis displays ‘doctorateness’. A range of informed and sometimes forthright views from EdD academics on these matters is recorded. On the basis of data analysis and interpretation, the thesis concludes with proposals for further, more extensive research, and a call for one of two courses of action: either the abolition of the EdD, or the appointment of a committee to review EdD practices nationally, and to recommend ways of strengthening EdD rigour and reputation.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1475240912468735">
<title>An analysis of the relationship between K–5 elementary school teachers’ perceptions of principal instructional leadership and their science teaching efficacy</title>
<p><bold>Ian Clark</bold></p>
<p>Doctor of Education 2009</p>
<p>University of Minnesota</p>
<p>Email: <email>ian@isd.sn</email></p>
<p>The purpose of this study is to analyze the relationship between K–5 elementary school teachers’ perceptions of principal instructional leadership and their science teaching efficacy. The influence of background variables on both leadership and efficacy is also analyzed. A sequential mixed methods approach was used in this study. The survey sample was comprised of teachers in the elementary divisions of schools from the nine international school regional associations. Teacher participation was obtained through an email containing an online survey link. Following the analysis of survey responses (<italic>N</italic> = 356), in-depth interviews (<italic>N</italic> = 17) were conducted. Reliability for the instructional leadership scale was found to be 0.94 (coefficient alpha) and 0.69 for the personal science teaching efficacy (PSTE) scale. The results show a significant correlation between elementary school teachers’ perceptions of principal instructional leadership and their PSTE levels, with the most significant correlation that between the study of a science-related major or minor at college and higher PSTE scores. Strong correlations were also found between PSTE levels and having principals who discussed goals at faculty meetings, participated in science curricular review, supported recognition of student progress, encouraged new skills and concepts, discussed student progress with faculty, and used assessments to see science progress towards easily understood goals. PSTE levels were also higher in schools where principals had grade or school level science coordinators in place and where they supported the use of science kits.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1475240912468735">
<title>An exploration of Virginia law on recognition, university officials, and perceptions of the International Baccalaureate Diploma Programme</title>
<p><bold>Kimberley Daly</bold></p>
<p>Doctor of Philosophy 2012</p>
<p>George Mason University, Virginia</p>
<p>Email: <email>kdaly1@masonlive.gmu.edu</email></p>
<p>This study investigated how university officials at five public universities in the Commonwealth of Virginia responded in the aftermath of a law concerning credit policies for International Baccalaureate (IB) and Advanced Placement (AP) examinations. Mandated by the Code of Virginia section 23-9.2:3.8, this policy is unique in the area of AP and IB recognition in the USA and required public colleges and universities to complete four steps by 31 May 2011. These included setting comparable credit recognition policies for both AP and IB examinations, providing credit for both IB standard and higher level examinations, identifying the requirements students met by successfully completing the IB Diploma, and reporting policies to the State Council for Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV) and publishing those policies on university websites. Interviews, artifact analysis, and website reviews were used to produce policy case studies of five Virginia universities’ compliance with the law. In addition to documenting policy compliance, additional goals of the study included understanding university officials’ attitudes concerning the law, IB student readiness for college-level course work, and general perceptions of the IB Diploma Programme and IB students.</p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>