<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PSC</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppsc</journal-id><journal-title>Philosophy &amp; Social Criticism</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0191-4537</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1461-734X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0191453712473081</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0191453712473081</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Reconstructing republican freedom</article-title><subtitle>A critique of the neo-republican concept of freedom as non-domination</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0191453712473081"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0191453712473081"/></contrib><aff id="aff1-0191453712473081">William Paterson University, Wayne, NJ, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-0191453712473081">Michael J. Thompson, Department of Political Science, Raubinger Hall, William Paterson University, 300 Pompton Road, Wayne, NJ 07470, USA. Email: <email>thompsonmi@wpunj.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>3</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>39</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder></permissions><abstract><p>This article presents a critique of Philip Pettit’s concept of ‘freedom as non-domination’ and provides an alternative theory of both domination and republican political freedom. I argue that Pettit’s neo-republican concept of domination is insufficient to confront modern forms of domination and that this hampers his concept of republican freedom and its political relevance under the conditions of modernity. Whereas the neo-republican account of domination is defined by ‘arbitrary interference’, modern forms of domination, I argue, are characterized by routinization and systemic forms of control and subordination. In the end, the neo-republican account of domination is more appropriate for 17th- and 18th-century social institutions rather than those that persist under modernity. In its place, I propose a more dynamic concept of domination and rework the concept of freedom in order to place the republican tradition within the context of modernity itself. I argue that the core insight of republicanism is its emphasis on the arrangement and reformation of social institutions to enhance social freedom. From this, I argue that republicanism can take its place as a more attractive alternative to liberal theory.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Authority</kwd><kwd>domination</kwd><kwd>freedom</kwd><kwd>liberalism</kwd><kwd>modernity</kwd><kwd>republicanism</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="section1-0191453712473081"><title>I Introduction</title><p>The emergence of republicanism as a coherent alternative to liberalism and communitarianism as well as socialism has been seen as an important shift in contemporary political theory. This theoretical turn has sought to revisit the republican tradition in order to enhance the character of modern democracy. Arguing that liberal theory’s conceptualization of freedom as ‘non-interference’ is limited, these theorists have been interested in the more robust notion of political freedom put forth by the republican tradition. Perhaps one of the most important theorists of this neo-republican turn has been Philip Pettit whose concept of republicanism has centered around the normative ideal of ‘freedom as non-domination’, something he and others see as the core ethical-political commitment of the republican tradition. My intention in this article is not to oppose the ongoing project of reconstructing republican theory, but to go beyond what I see to be the limitations of the neo-Roman variant of this theory. I want to revive what I see to be a deeper, more compelling insight implicit within the republican tradition: that the ways social institutions are arranged affect seriously the shaping of the nature of individual agents and, as a result, the nature of freedom.</p><p>Republicans placed emphasis on the ways in which the relations between individuals were rooted in the ways power was organized within society as a whole. Rather than being the central concern of the republican tradition, I argue that domination should be seen as the <italic>expression</italic> of oligarchic (and even tyrannical) concentrations of power within society as a whole, as pathological results of a badly arranged society. This is because, as I see it, the republican tradition is rooted in a socialized conception of the political subject which means that social structures and systems shape individual consciousness by providing certain background conditions for their orientations in the world. Power, domination, authority, are all woven into the socialization process of modern consciousness, something Max Weber termed ‘legitimate authority’. The key to a republican conception of freedom therefore needs to be seen as intrinsic within the architecture, or the arrangement of social institutions. To be free in the republican sense is not only to be free from the domination of others, although it is a central concern of republican thought. Rather, the emphasis should be placed on the ways in which the freedom of individual agents is rooted in the structure of social power as a whole: in ensuring that society is arranged in such a way as to orient social power not only negatively, but positively as well. From a modern perspective, domination is therefore a matter of the ways modern social systems are able to secure hierarchical power relations by making them legitimate in the minds of their members. I believe this insight violates the conditions Pettit and other neo-Republicans lay out in their analytic conceptualization of ‘freedom as non-domination’.</p><p>In an era when rational choice, methodological individualism and ethical subjectivism have become hegemonic in political theory and the social sciences, I see it as crucial to resuscitate the way that republican political theory places emphasis on the civic nature of citizens and seeks to shape individuals toward organized forms of self-government. The essence of republican freedom is found in this insight: in the relational nature of human beings and the centrality of politics and civic life to the security of their public and private liberties. I want to suggest that, within the context of modernity, republican theory sees domination not as arbitrary interference (the basic concept that lies at the heart of the neo-republican conception of freedom as non-domination) but rather as routinized into the systemic logics of social systems that are oriented toward forming a culture of legitimate authority around oligarchic or elite imperatives and interests. Republicans should see domination as the expression of perversions or corruptions of common power, where the concept of the common, public good is the regulative ideal to know when domination is actually occurring. In this sense, republicanism puts forth the basic idea that power, domination, the common good, etc., are all expressions of the architecture of social institutions. What is most significant in the republican tradition is the thesis that this architecture of society has the capacity to shape social relations and, therefore, individual agents themselves. Pettit’s emphasis on inter-agent forms of domination misses this core insight of republican political theory. Furthermore, his conception of domination is unable adequately to account for the nature of domination within the context of modernity.</p><p>I also take issue with the concept of domination initially put forth in the work of Pettit and other neo-republican thinkers who follow this approach and the way that they construct a theory of ‘republican freedom’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0191453712473081">1</xref></sup> The emphasis placed on freedom as non-domination is misplaced and misses the deeper commitment of the republican tradition: to arrange society in ways which can mitigate concentrations of power which, they believed, distort the autonomy of public life. Such distortions were seen as ‘corruption’: the ways that republican government and culture can be reorganized so as to serve the interests of the few rather than those of the whole. Because of this, argue that Pettit’s conception of domination theorizes far too small a domain of social power in modern societies and as such does not offer us a robust critical conceptual apparatus distinct from that offered by liberal theory. What I do claim is that the basic concept of domination and freedom is tied together in the republican tradition, but in a more complex way than neo-republicans have developed it: within the context of modernity, the state of domination is not simply the agent’s arbitrary interference in another agent’s choices or will, but the reflection of the functional imperatives of oligarchic forms of social power. Put more simply, domination is not simply the constraint of one’s will by another agent, it is, under conditions of modernity, the shaping of the wills of others in such a way that any kind of unequal society is legitimated. Domination exists in multiple forms, but I would like to suggest that in modern societies, it takes a form that neo-republican thinkers do not capture. In this sense, domination needs to be seen as a broader reality than theorized by Pettit and other neo-republicans in that domination. Relations of domination cannot be theorized apart from the institutional architecture in which they are embedded. Freedom therefore shifts its emphasis from domination alone to the more comprehensive concern of the arrangement of social institutions and their ability to provide for common, public ends. It is not only about defending against domination, it is also, and perhaps more importantly, about providing the context for the development of the members of the political community.</p><p>This domination is usually not perceived or known by those involved, but it nevertheless has corrupting force on the nature of public life, of republican politics, on the ability of individuals and groups to possess political control over the institutions which govern their lives. The result of this corruption is that individuals can be so constituted by the institutions and culture to accept, tolerate, see as legitimate and even value a condition of domination. Domination is therefore a question not simply of interference, but of the <italic>constitution of individuals</italic>. In this sense, domination in the modern world consists more in routinized, rational form than in arbitrary form – it is a feature of certain modern institutions, as I will show. It is essential to push beyond the ‘thin’ interpretation of domination Pettit lays out which places more emphasis on a concept of rational agency, and the ‘thick’ interpretation that I will lay out absorbing insights from Weber and the Marxian tradition which see the essence of the problem of domination as the expression of institutional arrangements. In the end, I reconstruct the republican notion of freedom as a concept where one’s acts, deeds, choices and so on are not oriented toward the unequal benefit of others, but toward mutual, or reciprocal, benefit. In my view, republican theory is strongest not when talking about master–slave relationships (as important as that may be from an historical vantage point) but rather in its emphasis on the ways that concentrations of minority interests and social power have corrupting influence on the political fabric of any society. Domination is the expression of these imbalances of social and political power, not the cause of them. I want to draw attention back to this insight in republican political theory and move beyond the neo-republican emphasis on interpersonal relations of domination toward a more comprehensive republicanism: one that brings us to the core of republican thought, the mitigation of organized concentrations of social power.</p><p>Although Pettit has made an important contribution to the development of the republican concept of freedom, the concept of domination that he develops – and the notion of freedom which follows from it – is insufficient and misses a larger, more developed concept of both domination and freedom which the republican tradition can potentially bring forth. It is inadequate because it is constructed far too narrowly and misses the more complex ways in which domination operates through modern social institutions and its effects upon individuals. Pettit’s concern seems to me to be too closely linked to the liberal concern of negative liberty and the need to constrain arbitrary power, a concept of domination which seems most useful when seen in relation to monarchical and feudal forms of political power and does not take us very far when confronting modern forms of social power and domination. In the end, I think that Pettit’s theory of domination is concerned with the same issue that liberals have always been concerned with, especially modern liberals: with the problem of constraining the arbitrary exercise of power, of the dependency of one person’s will on that of another. As a result, I do not see the basic structure of Pettit’s theory as going far enough to place republicanism as an alternative to liberal theory nor as an appropriate anchor for a new concept of political freedom.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0191453712473081">2</xref></sup> Instead, Pettit’s idea of domination is drawn from the historical expressions of the republican tradition – and the concerns of those writers are different, in many respects, than those of modern societies.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0191453712473081">3</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="section2-0191453712473081"><title>II Pettit’s account of domination and its limitations</title><p>Pettit puts forth the thesis that the republican tradition privileges a conception of freedom as ‘non-domination’. Central to this idea is the notion that non-domination is a more superior type of freedom than the liberal notion of freedom as non-interference. Interference exists when an agent is ‘prevented from obtaining a goal by human beings’;<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0191453712473081">4</xref></sup> it is the purposeful blocking of one’s life-choices and any possible options an agent might have open for acting. Interference is an actual activity, an intervention of one agent into the course of actions or the choices of another. Pettit sees this as a limited way of thinking about political freedom. To be free from an agent actively interfering with you is not enough to obtain freedom since that same individual may in fact possess the <italic>capacity</italic> to interfere at any time; even when actual interference is not present, the mere possibility of that interference is itself inimical to human freedom. In this sense, the possibility of interference is itself an element in the diminution of human freedom. The master who decides to rule his slaves with benevolence still has the power to interfere at any moment, at his discretion, in the lives of his subjects. It is therefore on the master’s will, his <italic>arbitrium</italic>, that power rests. This Pettit sees as the crucial insight of the republican tradition: to guard against such forms of arbitrary interference. From this he derives his understanding of domination: the ability of an agent to interfere with another at his will, on an arbitrary basis, without taking any kind of consideration as to the effects of that interference. The constraint of that power is what Pettit refers to as ‘freedom as non-domination’.</p><p>For Pettit, domination occurs when an agent can interfere with another on an arbitrary basis, or ‘can interfere, in particular, on the basis of an interest or an opinion that need not be shared by the person affected’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0191453712473081">5</xref></sup> In this sense, a relationship is dominating when one agent possesses the power to interfere on an arbitrary basis with another’s choices. The emphasis on the arbitrary nature of interference is important for Pettit since interference on its own is not inherently a moral or political wrong. Instead, the nature of arbitrariness is where the dominating agent does not have any concern for the interests of the agent being dominated: ‘I think that someone has an arbitrary power of interference in the affairs of another so far as they have a power of interference that is not forced to track the avowed or readily avowable interests of the other: they can interfere according to their own <italic>arbitrium</italic> or decision.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0191453712473081">6</xref></sup></p><p>To formalize this concept, Pettit lays out three basic conditions for a dominating relationship. An agent has domination over another when that agent:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>has the capacity to interfere</p></list-item><list-item><p>on an arbitrary basis</p></list-item><list-item><p>in certain choices that the other is in a position to make.</p></list-item></list><p>Several further points are made to systematize this notion of domination. First, Pettit is clear that it must be an agent – an individual or a corporate group – which performs this dominating role, it cannot be a process or a system which is dominating.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0191453712473081">7</xref></sup> Second, he also explains that any act of domination purposely tries to lessen the realm of choices of the dominated agent – it consciously reduces the realm of freedom of the dominated agent.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0191453712473081">8</xref></sup> At the conceptual core of this theory of domination is the category of ‘arbitrariness’: the notion that for one to be dominated, it must be at the will of another and that this other, alien power is something that can be exercised at any time. Even more, Pettit is clear that this concept of domination needs to be seen as a capacity to interfere – even if a dominating agent never acts upon the power to interfere in the welfare or choices of another, that other is still under domination living in the shadow of the dominating agent’s power: ‘What constitutes domination is the fact that in some respect the power-bearer has the capacity to interfere arbitrarily, even if they are never going to do so.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0191453712473081">9</xref></sup></p><p>To what extent does this account of ‘non-domination’ really provide us with a more robust alternative to the liberal tradition of freedom? I am not convinced that it does. First, Pettit’s concept of domination relies on a notion of political and social power which is more akin to those forms of social and political power characteristic of the 17th and 18th centuries and the concerns which republicans (and liberals, too) had at that time with respect to the nature of political authority.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-0191453712473081">10</xref></sup> By this I mean that the form of domination which Pettit theorizes is ‘pre-modern’ in the sense that it relies on forms of social relations which were still caught in monarchical, personal, patriarchal – in short, feudal – forms of social domination and power. These forms of domination characterized the broad sense of unfreedom during the 17th and 18th centuries, and they were the focus of much of the republican struggle against monarchy and other forms of arbitrary power.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-0191453712473081">11</xref></sup> This form of social power was characterized by dependency and subordination linked to individuals, to status and to social rank.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-0191453712473081">12</xref></sup></p><p>This is not to say that such relations do not also persist in modernity, rather that they cannot be an <italic>exhaustive</italic> account of domination in the modern world. Derived from theoretical writings from a pre-modern context, freedom as non-domination relies on an understanding of social relations and political consciousness which has significantly eroded in modern times. In this sense, the category of domination Pettit lays out is defined more by certain historical concerns which have been largely addressed by the liberal discourse.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-0191453712473081">13</xref></sup> His emphasis is on a type of domination which is pre-liberal in nature, in other words, a kind of servitude which is akin to direct forms of subjugation or ‘defenseless susceptibility to interference, rather than actual interference’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-0191453712473081">14</xref></sup> It is true that modern society still suffers from social relations of arbitrary power, of the kind of domination that Pettit discusses, but it is ultimately wrong to assume that this is the prevailing way that domination manifests itself in modernity where we are confronted with corporatist forms of power, with the corruption of public institutions, and the basic problem of the legitimacy of those institutions. With his emphasis on the notion of the arbitrary exercise of power over other individuals, Pettit places an emphasis on pre-liberal forms of social relations, as did many of the republicans from whom he garners his theory of non-domination. Although there was clearly a distinction between the ways that liberal and republicans saw the issue of political society, they were united by their opposition to the problem of constraining the arbitrary exercise of power, particularly by a monarch. The real issue for 18th-century political theorists was the problem of monarchy and moving toward a society of free institutions which were governed by legal-rational institutions and formed by the rational consent of the governed rather than forms of political power which were at the whim of an individual with no checks or accountability to that power.</p><p>This brings me to the next issue with Pettit’s theory of domination: he is explicit that domination has to be the act of one agent upon another. ‘While a dominating party will always be an agent – it cannot just be a system or network or whatever – it may be a personal or corporate or collective agent: this, as in the tyranny of the majority, where the domination is never the function of a single individual’s power.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-0191453712473081">15</xref></sup> This is a gross misunderstanding not only of the way that social domination actually operates in modern societies (as I will show in the next section), but it also misses the point of what makes the republican tradition unique and, to be sure, superior to that of liberalism: namely that it is able to see individuals as ‘embedded’ in certain social processes, habits, or other forms of routinized activities and institutions which transcend the wills of individual agents. In Pettit’s account, domination has to be a product of an agent’s will, it has to be arbitrary, i.e. it is a function of the express will of one agent to worsen the condition of another agent. But this need not always be the case. Consider the office worker who obeys the dictates of a bureaucratic mandate which in turn has negative effects on others; or consider a woman who is forced to sell herself into prostitution by economic reasons to place herself at the will of others. These forms of domination and control are not well captured by Pettit’s theory of domination because they miss the larger, systemic dimensions of domination which frame the actions and relations of particular agents. Pettit claims that all participants are aware when they are being dominated; but this seems false once we consider the routinized ways that control and subordination are active in modern institutions.</p><p>Pettit seems to see all domination of a piece; he believes that domination can be defined generally, through the concept of arbitrariness. But in so doing, much of what constitutes modern forms of domination is left out of his analysis. Even more, the real issue which lurks behind these concerns is that many republican theorists (such as Cicero, Machiavelli, Sydney and Rousseau, among others) saw that the agency of individuals was in fact shaped or at least very strongly influenced by the social institutions within which they were individuated. Unequal wealth not only makes the poor or less well-off more vulnerable to the power of their masters, it also begins to change the very culture of a republic. Human agency was therefore <italic>contextualized</italic> and could not be seen as the <italic>locus</italic> for the problems of creating and expanding freedom. Instead, there was a need to construct institutions which would not only restrain the powerful, but those which would also shape citizens who possessed the capacities needed for a free, political life. Read in this way, domination is not simply a matter of arbitrary interference, it is a matter of the ways individuals are constituted by the social arrangements around them. From this insight, we must seek to construct a more general understanding of domination that embraces the different ways it manifests itself and how this can lead us to a more nuanced understanding of domination than offered by liberal theory.</p></sec><sec id="section3-0191453712473081"><title>III Toward a general theory of domination</title><p>If Pettit’s conception of domination is insufficient for the actual way social power manifests itself in modernity, then we need to re-evaluate the concept of domination within this context. Pettit’s account of domination rests on certain flawed assumptions about the range or extent of what it means to be subjected to a dominating power and what constitutes a relationship of domination. It becomes clear that Pettit’s real intention in summoning the concept of non-domination as central to the republican tradition is that (1) he sees it as being closer to the moral impulse of the republican tradition as a whole; and (2) he wants to preserve interference alone (i.e. by the state) as a concept useful for republican ends. If interference itself were inherently negative in a moral sense, then it would be morally impermissible for the state to interfere with the choices of individuals in order to promote public ends. Pettit is able to preserve an interfering role for the republican state as opposed to the liberal state which, in its classical formulation at least, forbids any kind of interference as a net loss of the individual’s freedom. Hence, Pettit is able to extract a positive power by differentiating plain interference from a dominating, arbitrary interference.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-0191453712473081">16</xref></sup></p><p>But domination operates in a much more expanded way within the context of modernity. To this extent, a modern view of the phenomenon of domination needs to take into account a very different set of actions between agents than specified by Pettit. It needs to take into account the ways in which domination is not simply based on the notion of arbitrary power, but on the routinization of power relations in everyday life. It must also move away from the notion that domination is ‘arbitrary interference’ in the choices of other agents. More to the point, modern forms of domination operate differently from the historical, feudal forms of domination that inspired much of the republican thought of the 17th and 18th centuries. This is because modern forms of domination become embedded in the systemic operation of social institutions in a very specific way. Individual agents therefore do not become the primary unit of analysis, but the logics of social systems. Pettit is clear that domination cannot be performed by a network or system, but by the arbitrary interference of one agent by another. But interference in what, exactly? Those that adopt the neo-Roman argument believe that it is the ability ‘to change what the latter would otherwise prefer to do’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-0191453712473081">17</xref></sup> But this obfuscates the nuanced way that domination occurs, namely because it is not always clear that one might make choices that deliberately put one in a position of inequality or reduced power with respect to others. This is a severely limiting condition since much of what can be considered dominating under modernity is not at all arbitrary, but thoroughly routinized and structured. Furthermore, domination acts in a more nuanced way under conditions of modernity: most importantly in the ways it can shape the values of individuals to legitimate subordination and control. In this sense, Pettit’s 18th-century formulation of domination cannot bear the weight which he places upon it, or at least which I think ought to be placed on it: the kind of domination which occurs from the shaping of consciousness and action from the arrangement of modern social institutions. In this respect, I want to propose a richer, more dynamic conception of domination which covers the different ways in which individuals and groups can be subject to domination in modern society.</p><sec id="section4-0191453712473081"><title>1 Authority and domination</title><p>As a first move toward broadening the concept of social domination, I want to look into the way that domination can be seen as a relationship of ‘authority’. As a concept, authority is distinct from the forms of domination that Pettit specifies. Whereas Pettit sees that domination is the imposing of the will of one agent on the interests of another and that this will be known by both agents, modern forms of authority and domination cannot be characterized this way.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-0191453712473081">18</xref></sup> Although it is true that the real mark of domination is that the dominated agent’s welfare is being reduced, it is not necessary that this be known by either of the two agents. Authority is a relationship which encompasses the dominating and dominated agent; it is not simply enacted by the will of the dominator, but is part of the overall logic or process of the society, institution, or association, to which the dominator and dominated belong. In this sense, domination is a process that requires legitimation – both individuals feel that the authority relationship is itself a legitimate one. On this view, what Pettit misses in his account of domination is that it need not be arbitrary at all. In his sociological treatment of domination, Weber makes a crucial distinction between ‘power’ [<italic>Macht</italic>], and ‘domination’ or ‘authority’ [<italic>Herrschaft</italic>].<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-0191453712473081">19</xref></sup> Weber defines ‘power’ as one agent in a social relationship being ‘in a position to carry out his own will despite resistance, regardless of the basis on which this probability rests’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20-0191453712473081">20</xref></sup> When this power is exercised over another on threat of punishment or rests on some other kind of compulsion, this kind of power is ‘coercion’.</p><p>But Weber contrasts this form of power to that of ‘domination’ or ‘authority’ which is ‘the probability that a command with a given specific content will be obeyed by a given group of persons’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21-0191453712473081">21</xref></sup> It requires that there be a set of habits which allow for a disciplined acceptance of commands and the loss of one’s autonomy to the extent that a dominating agent possesses the capacity to control another. The key element in this conception of domination is therefore one of the ‘disciplining’ of the accepting agent. Domination is therefore not concerned with the problem of arbitrariness – something that is contained within the concept of ‘power’ – but rather with the routinized acceptance and legitimation of unequal power relations. Modernity displays new, distinct forms of power relations – and in this way, Weber was able to capture a crucial aspect of domination: its non-arbitrary character. Even more, it means that there is some degree of obedient acceptance of domination that becomes a routinized, habitual character of modern society. In this respect, there can be no doubt that there is a discrete difference between forms of domination which dominate pre-modern society and those which pervade modern institutions. Domination works itself out through routinized systems based upon the rational legitimation of social agents – in other words, agents give authority relations legitimacy on a voluntary basis. This is the key aspect of domination that Pettit misses, and this has, I believe, deep consequences for his theoretical reconstruction of republican theory.</p><p>This second dimension of domination, that of legitimacy and the acquiescence or obedience to relations of authority, needs to be explored more fully. In this respect, domination requires not an arbitrary exercise of power as Pettit suggests, but, rather, the opposite: a defined set of behaviors which are ingrained within the agent through a process of ‘routinization’ [<italic>Veralltäglichung</italic>] wherein the subjective orientations of individuals make up a constitutive part of the presence of domination.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22-0191453712473081">22</xref></sup> The resulting concept of domination is therefore seen as a relation bound not to the personal will of one individual over the other, but by the recognition of both individuals of a process of power integrating them through the process of ‘obedience’ [<italic>Gehorsam</italic>].<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23-0191453712473081">23</xref></sup> This results in an ‘authority relationship’ [<italic>Herrschaftsverhältnis</italic>] which is defined by two crucial features:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>that the subject of domination enters, to some degree, into the relationof domination in a voluntary way;</p></list-item><list-item><p>submission of the will (of thought and of reason) to that of an other.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24-0191453712473081">24</xref></sup></p></list-item></list><p>These two reformulations of social power under conditions of modernity point to a broad sphere of domination not covered by Pettit, namely that of ‘authority’. Weber’s theory of authority is defined as ‘legitimate domination’: where one individual obeys the orders, norms, legal strictures and so on of another agent and believes these orders, norms and legal strictures to be valid. Several crucial features of authority need to be pointed out. First, it is based on the fact that the dominated party sees obedience as valid or correct from a normative point of view. It is not necessarily seen as domination, as a reduction of freedom. This comes from the dual problem of routinization and discipline. On the one hand, discipline is necessary because of the nature of modern domination: an agent is not compelled to act because of an external threat, but has rather internalized a set of norms which lead to self-imposed subordination to the authority relation. The dominated party sees it as legitimate, and accepts it as a part of its world-view. This is made necessary because, for Weber, modern forms of domination (legal-rational forms) are not related to the will of the individual, but rather to the rules of the institutions to which individuals belong. It is through the process of rationalization of an institution that these older forms of coercion can become forms of domination. Read in a deeper way, it means that certain forms of coercion and control in one period of time may become, through the process of routinization, accepted forms of <italic>legitimate domination</italic>. This process of rationalization is crucial since without it, a form of domination cannot serve its true sociological function: to hold the social order together according to some legitimating logic.</p><p>We can say that Weber provides a theory of domination as authority which works under different principles. From mere coercion since dominating authority requires legitimation, it requires that those logics of domination operate within institutions as well as within the internal, subjective orientations of individuals toward that authority. Weber’s key insight, in this regard, is that there is a differentiation between two kinds of domination: between substantive and formal or between personal and impersonal forms.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25-0191453712473081">25</xref></sup> We are therefore presented with a very different question than the one posed by Pettit: to what extent do modern social institutions embed individuals within different contexts of domination? More importantly, can we argue, in the face of Weber, that domination can only be between agents? This is in contrast to the emphasis placed on domination being the source of one’s dependency upon another’s will since, in Weber’s analysis, rational forms of domination – those which characterize modern society – are not reducible to the will of another. Instead, rational forms of domination are embedded in social processes and institutions, ingraining themselves within the lives, habits and even structures of consciousness of agents. Rational modern forms of domination (legal-rational authority) transcend the dependency of one agent’s will on that of another and become the systemic logic of social institutions.</p><p>It therefore becomes a crucial expansion of the concept of domination within the context of modernity to move beyond the acts of mere agents and to move into the ways that social institutions and their functional logics manifest relations of domination and control. What the modern conception of domination highlights is the fact that social processes, institutions and their logics, shape relations of domination and even act as dominating systems. Whereas Pettit emphasizes an inter-agent conception of domination – one that would have been the focus of 17th- and 18th-century republican political thinkers – this is inadequate to confront the modern forms of domination and control which are characteristic of modernity. Of course, as is well known, Weber also theorizes other bases for legitimate domination such as ‘traditional’ or ‘charismatic’: in either case, we are still dealing with an ‘authority relation’ since both agents in the relation see the relation as legitimate, although based on very different rationales. By contrast, Pettit reduces the concept of domination to the Weberian category of ‘coercion’, since the individual affected by its concept of domination is at the will of another agent, not a system of rules or any kind of institutional logic. Weber recognizes a wider typology of social power which corresponds to different historical and social situations. But this does not take us far enough, in my view, since we need to have a more concrete understanding of domination which can serve as a new focus for republican theory.</p></sec><sec id="section5-0191453712473081"><title>2 Extractive power and domination</title><p>‘Extractive power’ is the ability for one individual or an institution to subject another individual or group to relations of inequality and control for the purpose of securing them as a source of surplus benefit for another.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26-0191453712473081">26</xref></sup> Even more, this surplus benefit is then used to maintain control and domination of those individuals who provide surplus. In this sense, the power one wields over the other is within a relationship of transferring labor, money, or other social goods or personal abilities in order to accrue surplus. Individuals are subordinated to the power of others or another for the systemic purpose of producing surplus. This can be at the level of individual relations (such as one person owning a slave) or systemic logic, as in the institution of wage labor. Extractive domination is therefore in play when there is a concrete transfer of some value from the dominated agent to the surplus of the dominating one. In this sense, the power of extraction need not be reducible to the authority relation. Take, for example, the case of a manager and a factory worker: the worker is dominated by the manager in terms of authority – the worker will obey commands from the manager, follow the work schedule that the manager fixed, and so on. But this does not mean that the manager is the beneficiary of the work produced by the laborer. The owner(s) of the factory – who employs both the manager and the laborer – possesses extractive power over both these individuals. In this sense, extractive domination can be either coerced, as in a master–slave relation, where one is forced into the process of production for the sake of another or another group; or it can be rationalized to produce a relationship where an individual willfully submits to the authority of another or to another organization, but the purpose of that submission is extractive. One can see this in the institution of wage labor under capitalism where individuals sell their labor power, via contract, to another in order to survive or for some other set of goods. What makes it domination is that it manifests a relation of subordination or control and that this relation confers a disproportionate benefit to the dominating agent over the dominated. Extraction implies that one ‘takes out’ of another some value, some benefit, which is unevenly consumed or benefited from by the dominating agent.</p><p>The relation between structure and agency is crucial here, just as it was in the Weberian concept of ‘rational domination’, because it also leads us to the thesis, put forward initially by Marx, that certain social institutions – in his case, specifically ‘capital’ – are social processes and a distinct ‘social power’ [<italic>gesellschaftliche Macht</italic>] unto themselves. This means that social processes and structures have the ability to constrain and even shape the agency of individuals – the core of domination therefore lies outside of the individual and is a property of the social institutions themselves. Read in this way, domination cannot be reduced solely to the will of an agent, but must be seen as generated <italic>by the logic of social structures</italic>, as with Weber’s account of rational domination or authority. From the Marxian tradition, we see that power relations are the result of certain processes of extracting gain from another individual or group of individuals. But this process of extraction need not be isolated to the system of modern capitalism: slave societies are extractive; personal relations can even be extractive, as when one individual extracts personal surplus benefit from another (a wife, a child and so on); or they can be institutionalized, as in the system of wage labor. The domain of extractive domination is distinct from Weber’s concept of authority in the sense that it is a specific kind of dominating relationship, and one present in all societies to a greater or lesser extent. Its relevance for the republican theory of freedom, however, is central since it deals with a specific kind of social relation, one that limits the capacities, development and freedom of the subject.</p><p>Consider, in this sense, a factory which will close down due to economic pressures of globalization. The workers within the factory would be, in Pettit’s view, subject to the arbitrary will of the factory owner for their livelihood. They are dependent upon the owner for their work, wages, and so on. But is this really the case? It is perhaps more likely that we should read this situation as a result of the functional logic of the institution of a capitalist economy. It could be argued that the owner of the factory could choose to accept less profits rather than relocate; but it is more likely that, regardless of the predisposition of the owner as a moral agent, the functional logic of the economy would dictate such a move: the need for more extractive power (lower wages, less-organized labor force, and so on). In this sense, the workers would be subject to the inequality of social power given to them as actors within a system which distributes benefits based on the ownership of capital. They are dependent less on the individual capitalist than on the structure of extractive power. We would hardly be able to characterize this kind of domination as ‘arbitrary’ in the sense that Pettit theorizes it, and we would also be unable to characterize it as between two agents in the sense that there exists a systemic context within which these agents operate, constraining their choices and options.</p></sec><sec id="section6-0191453712473081"><title>3 Three domains of power: a dynamic analysis of domination</title><p>This discussion therefore leads us to question the extent to which Pettit’s conception of domination is an exhaustive one under modern conditions. As I have argued above, I do not think that it is and believe that a more dynamic, more general conceptualization is needed. By dynamic, I mean that these three basic ‘domains’ of domination are in fact interactive. From Weber’s notion of authority relations we see that individuals follow forms of authority for different reasons – because they are traditionally obeyed, because of charismatic zeal, or because of the rationalization of the process of obedience to certain instrumental ends. In either case, authority is a specific kind of domination. From the Marxian tradition, we see that domination has a more cohesive structure: to have power over others means to have the capacity to ‘extract’ profit or some other kind of benefit from them or their labor. Social power is therefore a function of, and is shaped by, the need to increase extractive domination. This constitutes a dominating relationship in the sense that one is subordinate to another for the concrete purpose of extracting benefits from one agent to that of another. Pettit’s concept of domination fits more squarely into the notion of coercion, or the ability to reduce an individual’s abilities, range of choices, and so on, but from the point of view of the arbitrary power of an other. It is, as I have argued above, a concept of domination which fails because it is in fact stamped by the social and political concerns of the 17th and 18th centuries.</p><p>To broaden this view, I will lay out these three distinct types of domination which can be either co-present or exclusive of one another within certain social and political contexts. In this way, we can see a more dynamic, more cohesive way of approaching the problem of domination under the processes of modernity. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0191453712473081">Figure 1</xref> lays out the three types of domination I have been discussing and also the ways that each of these ‘power domains’ interact to create different situations of domination. Each of these domains is ‘pure’ in the sense that they could theoretically exist on their own, but more realistically manifest themselves in conjunction with another. <italic>Coercion</italic> can be defined in the way that Pettit sees his comprehensive theory of domination: as the capacity of one agent to be able to act at its own will to worsen the welfare of another. What counts in this domain is that the dominating agent has arbitrary power over the dominated agent. <italic>Authority</italic> is the kind of domination explicated by Weber where domination is a mutually constituted relation – both the dominating and dominated agents participate in the authority relation because they see some overwhelming legitimacy to that relation or to the ends that relation are supposed to achieve. This could be based on rational, traditional, or charismatic forms of legitimacy. <italic>Extractive</italic> domination is when one agent’s power over another is used to extract benefit from that other. Each of these three domains interacts with the others in various ways and can give us a richer, more complex understanding of domination. Whereas the theory of domination as arbitrary power is certainly repugnant, it does not exhaust the concept of domination. Forms of power, especially in modern societies, are not simply based on arbitrary power, but derive from the logics of social processes and institutions and in turn also shape the subjective orientations of individuals. The implication is that republican theory needs to take into account the institutional and systemic nature of domination in modern society for it to be a rival theory of political freedom to that of liberalism.</p><fig id="fig1-0191453712473081" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Three domains of power.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0191453712473081-fig1.tif"/></fig><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0191453712473081">Figure 1</xref>, we can see the ways that these three different ‘power domains’ can interact and blend to express different forms of domination. Any relationship manifesting domination can be theorized through this dynamic form of categorization. There can exist exclusively coercive forms of domination – where one is enslaved to another, or when one mugs another at gunpoint. If one is in a coercive relation but in order to produce for another, or to perform favors for another, and the dominating agent benefits from this, then we have a relationship of ‘coercive extraction’ (<bold>A</bold>). Similarly, there can exist a relation of ‘rational-extractive domination’ (<bold>C</bold>) where one submits to another willingly through a system of laws and instrumental interests, as in wage labor where profit is made. This can also be based on traditional authority, as when individuals submit to the will of others based on some kind of caste system or some other form of ascriptive category, and are exploited. There can also be forms of ‘coercive authority’ (<bold>B</bold>) as when one is forced into recognizing certain legal limits to activity, or when one is forced into certain contractual relations against one’s will, but either by necessity or some kind of threat to one’s well-being. In the end, we can also see that all three domains can culminate in coercive forms of authority in place for the purpose of extraction (<bold>D</bold>) as when individuals are faced with coercive ‘choices’ in the labor market, or in other forms of economic life. These forms of domination are shaped and framed mostly by the arrangements of society and the structural-functional logics of modern institutions. There are instances of arbitrary coercion, to be sure, but the predominant character of modern domination stems, I think, from the systemic nature of domination rooted in social arrangements and institutional logics.</p></sec></sec><sec id="section7-0191453712473081"><title>IV Freedom and the republican tradition: reworking the theory</title><p>The discussion of domination leads us back to the central issue that I have proposed against Pettit’s concept of domination: namely that he places an exclusive emphasis on the actions of agents rather than considering the complex interplay between structure and agency in the discussion of political freedom. This kind of de-contextualization of domination is crucial: since domination is something which can become <italic>institutionalized</italic>, something which is in fact <italic>systemic</italic>, it is insufficient to theorize domination as an interfering capacity grounded in the will of another. What needs to be seen is that domination works itself (1) into certain structures, certain logics of institutions; and (2) into the consciousness of agents themselves. By this I emphasize a political reality which sees the structure of society as a central issue of concern rather than the ways individuals are treated by others as an exclusive concern of republican theory. What this means is that the concept of domination in modernity needs to be changed so as to make the republican discourse in modern democratic theory a more relevant and, indeed, more attractive alternative to liberal political theory. What republicanism ought to be able to offer us is not only the normative ideal of the public good as having a central place in political life, but also the empirical claim that domination is embedded in social institutions and processes and permeates the consciousness of political subjects. Republicanism is a theory of the architecture of social relations; it is a theory which sees that individuals are products of these relations, and that social contexts within which individuals are formed play a crucial role in forming individuals and conditioning their freedom. For freedom to hold in the republican sense, the institutional design of society needs to be arranged in such a way that we focus not on domination as the central goal, but on the more crucial aim of maximizing the common good. This is not a vague, communitarian perspective, rather it places domination in a much more robust context since domination can be understood not only as interpersonal terms (as in coercion) but also in the ways that society can be arranged for the unequal benefit of some rather than the majority (extractive power) as well as the ways that these relations can be legitimated so that agents lose their awareness of their own subordination and the devolution of the public realm (authority). This is because the republican sees institutions and the arrangement of society more broadly as having a dramatic developmental impact on individuals. Domination can become necessary for the very functioning of many social institutions, and they can therefore be seen as necessary where individuals submit their wills to the logics of those institutions. Republican freedom must include, but also go beyond, the concern with restraining arbitrary power and seek to transform and reorder the social institutions which deprive individuals of capacities for individual and social freedom by orienting them toward private rather than public benefits and goods.</p><p>Pettit’s interpretation of republicanism adopts the liberal, 18th-century conception of the political subject as an independent agent who is assumed to be capable of making individual choice. Domination consists in the arbitrary interference with the individual’s choices rather than the ways in which that individual is constituted. This leads to Pettit’s emphasis on the ‘neo-Roman’ interpretation of the republican tradition, one that sees that the individual can be free only, as Quentin Skinner has argued, ‘within a free state’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27-0191453712473081">27</xref></sup> According to this interpretation, individuals are free to the extent that they live within a context of free laws, laws which eliminate the capacity of agents to interfere arbitrarily in the affairs of others. Republican forms of freedom also give people freedom over their capacities to intervene in the power relations within which they find themselves, or what he calls ‘discursive control’: ‘An agent will be a free person so far as they have the ability to discourse and they have access to discourse that is provided in such relationships.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28-0191453712473081">28</xref></sup> In this sense, individuals must be free from the ability of others to dominate them, and this is a problem solved by institutions which prevent or negate the power of dominating agents. Republican institutions fulfill the role of providing ‘anti-power’ to vulnerable agents in that they protect them from the dominating influence of others.</p><p>I believe that the republican concept of freedom is a much more robust one than that of liberalism even though others have previously argued that there is no real, or substantive, difference between the two or that the difference between them is essentially confused by republicans.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29-0191453712473081">29</xref></sup> My interpretation of what makes the republican tradition unique lies not in the emphasis on domination per se but, rather, in the recognition that social processes can either impede or promote free political life. Whereas the liberal tradition has placed emphasis on the freedom of the individual, on the importance of negative liberty, and the absence of the arbitrary exercise of power, the distinctiveness of the republican tradition lies in its ability to embed the concern of individual freedom within the structure of social relations. We therefore come to see the individual as a property of social relations and social institutions, and that the extent of freedom or non-freedom of the individual is in some way predicated on the ways that social institutions and arrangements can foster free agents by arranging the powers of society toward the common good, not simply negating the power of dominating agents. One of the core issues we find organizing the republican tradition, for example, is the emphasis on the ways property was tied to political power and the corruption of ‘civic virtue’ or orientations of citizens toward the common good. Whereas liberals saw property as a natural right and tied to individual labor, republicans generally saw unequal divisions of property as capable of distorting the structure of a free political life since individuals would be tied to forms of servitude and domination having effects within the sphere of civic life.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30-0191453712473081">30</xref></sup> They would be exposed to forms of servitude and robbed of their ability to develop and live as free and equal citizens.</p><p>Unequal divisions of property were seen as detrimental to the maintenance of a free polity because property and social-political power were linked. As a result, early republicans and those inspired by republican themes tended to advocate the redistribution of property by the state and they were generally critics of economic inequality. This brand of republicanism – we can call it ‘radical republicanism’ – sought to constrain unequal power relations (e.g. relations of domination) by preventing the unequal accumulation of property by institutional design which would provide certain individuals or groups with the capacity to exercise domination over others.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31-0191453712473081">31</xref></sup> But this need not be limited to forms of economic power, other unequal power structures and systems could be critiqued, those based on race, gender, or any number of categories. The republican sees that the individual’s freedom as a political agent, as a social being, is in the first instance dependent upon the restraint of the powerful from acting upon you arbitrarily, but also, and more deeply, that social systems which restrain your own abilities, capacities and functionings need to be broken and reshaped to promote freedom as self-determination. It is not enough, in this sense, simply not to interfere arbitrarily with others, the republican also sees that institutions need to be constructed positively: to enhance the participation and balance the power of individuals to prevent oligarchy and tyranny – in short, the subordination of the public to the interests of the few. The republican also sees that this freedom as self-determination is itself socially constituted: that the power, abilities, functionings, etc., are provided for through the structure of social arrangements.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32-0191453712473081">32</xref></sup> This is the distinctiveness of the republican viewpoint. The central role of politics in this reading is therefore to root out the institutions and social processes which prevent that kind of freedom from being realized. Indeed, the kind of domination that hinders the realization of this kind of freedom need not be <italic>arbitrary</italic>, in Pettit’s sense. It can transform the logic of political institutions, rework the imperatives of the law, of education, of the very structure of society, but in so doing, it is not arbitrary, but rather admits a functionalist relationship between agency and structure. To be more precise, domination becomes a <italic>logic</italic> rather than the mere arbitrary exercise of authority, and it is a logic that persists because of the systemic nature of a kind of economic life which is rooted in patterns of property ownership and social power that are highly concentrated or organized toward private ends rather than public ends. This is the more direct problem with which republican theory ought to be concerned, one it can deal with more satisfactorily than liberalism.</p><p>This form of republicanism is in contrast to another strand of republican thought which is where thinkers like Pettit take their cue for reworking republican theory in the modern context. This ‘neo-Roman’ theory of republicanism emphasizes an equality and non-arbitrariness in legal terms. The law and the rights of individuals are to be protected from the power of other individuals; master–servant relations are to be expunged, achieved by making rules which limit the capacity of individuals to ‘interfere’ with others on a non-arbitrary basis: ‘the world must be a non-interference world of that kind, not by accident, but by virtue of your being secured against the powerful.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33-0191453712473081">33</xref></sup> I am not convinced that the way Pettit theorizes domination allows such a maxim to be realized politically. Even more than this, the concept of ‘freedom as non-domination’ that Pettit and other neo-republican thinkers put forth does not confront the ways in which social processes impact and shape consciousness and, as a result, the capacities for free political choice. Individuals begin to conform to social institutions which thereby dominate, have some kind of control over, their choices and their world-views. This can deprive individuals of certain capacities for agency by, as Weber shows in his theory of authority, molding their consciousness through obedience and routinization. Similarly, extractive forms of domination can violate republican freedom not only in inter-personal terms, but also by giving one class or group of people a larger degree of influence over social resources and institutions further shaping individual character and choice. One need only think of the ways public education can be adapted to serve the interests of the business community in modern times, this would be a prime example of public corruption and a violation of republican freedom.</p><p>The significance of this goes to the heart of Pettit’s concept of republicanism since it relies heavily on the notion of agency. For Pettit, and those that have followed his conception of republicanism, the key issue of domination is that it occurs between two agents where the dominating agent does not consider, or ‘track’, the interests of the dominated agent: ‘The key to determining what is arbitrary centers on whether or not the interfering agent consulted and tracked the opinions or interests of the agent subjected to the interference.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34-0191453712473081">34</xref></sup> Pettit himself sees this as a crucial feature of his theory of domination and freedom, namely that individuals must be seen as capable of choosing between certain options and that the arbitrary interference by another agent in that individual’s choice constitutes a relation of domination. This he terms ‘alien control’ where ‘the first party will control what the second does, at least to some degree, and control it in an alien way that takes from the personal choice of that agent’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35-0191453712473081">35</xref></sup> The problem with this, as I have argued above, is that this does not provide a distinctive theory of freedom nor of domination that is sufficiently distinct from liberal theory. There are two reasons for this: first, Pettit sees domination relations through an exclusively agent-centered perspective; and second, he sees that domination is the result of arbitrary interference in the choices of another agent. In this sense, Pettit invests too much power in inter-personal, agent-centered forms of domination and control and remains, in my view, within the domain of liberal theory.</p><p>Now, having said this, it is important to return to what I argued above was the more salient theme of the republican tradition: the effect of social systems and processes upon social and individual freedom. The concept of domination that I put forth above, derived from a blending of themes from Weber and the Marxian tradition, sees that emphasis needs to be placed on the structure of social relationships and institutions within society as a whole. If the republican thesis about political freedom is correct, then it relies on seeing that the individual is not the Archimedean point for liberty but the relations which produce the individual, which shape that individual’s powers for moral reflection and political agency. Republican institutions seek to maximize social institutions which allow for the free development of individuality, not simply to prevent arbitrary interference. Republicanism therefore sees this as best realized by maximizing the extent to which institutions serve common rather than particular ends. In this sense, republican freedom is not simply concerned with securing individuals against domination, it is more concerned with providing and protecting an arrangement of social institutions which serve public ends and this includes producing an environment which will allow for the self-development of its members. Hence, even in instances when Pettit’s conception of domination is not in effect, we can see that republicans would be concerned with the logics of many modern institutions based on this criterion. This is because, as the discussion above about authority indicates, individuals can be oriented toward relations of domination by institutions which instill obedience to those institutions. In this sense, we can see that republican theory has a distinct vantage point to direct the empirical investigation of as well as the normative vision of politics. The core concern is not simply the protection of the vulnerable from domination; even more, it means that the maintenance of republican freedom depends on a social order which disables concentrations of power and interests from guiding, ‘corrupting’, the institutions of society as a whole and that they instead serve public ends. This is the prior condition to the existence of domination itself.</p></sec><sec id="section8-0191453712473081"><title>V Conclusion</title><p>In this article, I have sought to demonstrate three separate but inter-related theses. First, is that the concept of ‘domination’ as put forth by Philip Pettit and other neo-republican thinkers is insufficient to critique sufficiently the forms of domination in modern societies. Second, I put forth what I see to be a more comprehensive theory of domination which more adequately captures its complexity in modern societies. Finally, I put forward the thesis that the republican tradition provides us with a theory of freedom linked not to the individual alone, but to the ways that social structures shape individuality and that free individuals are the product not simply of relations of non-interference but, more importantly, of a society bereft of institutions which shape individuals based on subordination, control and inequality. As a result, I argued that republican freedom encompasses a broader set of concerns and institutions than do classical forms of liberalism.</p><p>I think the ‘neo-Roman’ theory advanced by thinkers such as Pettit holds far too closely to liberal theory to count as sufficiently distinct in this regard because of (1) its focus on agents rather than on the relational structure within which agents are embedded; and (2) its narrow definition of freedom as the absence of an agent’s arbitrary interference in the affairs of others. Republicanism – or at least the interpretation of republicanism that I privilege – sees the individual as shaped by relations of social power and it sees those social relations as structured by institutional patterns of political, economic, social and cultural life. This means that the common (liberal) assumption made about the rational, conscious, political, or moral agent cannot be seen as a starting point for constructing a political theory. Rather, what republicanism can contribute to political theory is the idea that individuals are produced by social systems which shape as well as constrain their subjectivity and agency. In this sense, republican institutions must be organized not simply to immunize individuals from the domination of others, they must be so arranged, so structured and designed as to give individuals certain capacities and social goods necessary for self-government. Republican freedom is sensitive to the ways that equal social relations can be distorted and perverted toward the interests of the few. Domination is not simply the crude subordination of one’s will by that of an another, it is the shaping of social relations and institutions toward certain portions of the community rather than the common good. To have power over others is not simply to have constraint over their wills, it is also the capacity to shape their wills, to legitimate the unequal relations of social life that benefit the few rather than the totality of the community. Domination needs to be seen, as Weber rightly saw, as much more deeply rooted in the ways modern institutions work and the ways they affect the constitution or development of individuals. They cannot be conceived as atomistic moral-political agents, but as agents constituted by certain restraints imposed by forces of coercion, relations of various types of authority, or systems of property or unequal economic relations. As such, republican theory sees an embedded form of individuality and agency and places importance on the ways that social institutions operate, the ways that social structures are arranged within any given polity.</p><p>If this interpretation of republicanism has merit, it lies in an emphasis on the insight of the social embeddedness of individuals, in the fact that their subjective consciousness, their ability to discourse, to reflect ethically and politically, to act, and so on are constituted by the social institutions within which they find themselves. It connects this insight of the systemic nature of domination with the normative concern expressed by Algernon Sydney that ‘liberty consists only in being subject to no man’s will, and nothing denotes a slave but a dependence on the will of another’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36-0191453712473081">36</xref></sup> Domination rightly should be one of the central categories on which the concept of republican freedom is based, but it must take into consideration the broader typology of domination that I have laid out here and must attempt to confront the obstacles to freedom which manifest themselves <italic>socially</italic>, rather than only <italic>inter-personally</italic>. From this ‘empirical’ argument stems a moral one: that social institutions, the very structure of social relations, can either enhance or erode an individual’s capacity to choose moral ends which are in tune with public ends, that the freedom of the individual is deeply connected with the structure of social arrangements and their respective logics. Institutions do not only have the role of preventing arbitrary interference, they also must find ways of enhancing public life itself. Modern forms of domination can lead to just such an erosion of the capacity for moral autonomy on the part of the subject which means that the older emphasis on uninterfered choice becomes almost meaningless since domination becomes ingrained, rationalized, routinized and internalized. Given the predominance of these kinds of institutions, freedom needs to be theorized from within the context I have laid out here if republican theory can have any meaningful import to the problems of contemporary politics.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other" id="fn37-0191453712473081"><label>Authors Note</label><p>I would like to thank Robert Fitch, Dick Howard and Nichole Shippen for their comments on earlier drafts of this article.</p></fn></fn-group><notes><title>Notes</title><fn-group><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0191453712473081"><label>1.</label><p>Pettit’s concept of domination and ‘freedom as non-domination’ has also been taken up by others. See Quentin Skinner, ‘Freedom as the Absence of Arbitrary Power’, in C. Laborde and J. Maynor (eds) <italic>Republicanism and Political Theory</italic> (Oxford: Blackwell, 2008), pp. 83–101; John Maynor, <italic>Republicanism in the Modern World</italic> (Cambridge: Polity, 2003), pp.108–40; and Frank Lovett, ‘Domination: a Preliminary Analysis’, <italic>The Monist </italic>84 (2001): 98–112. These writers are in contrast to the ‘civic republican’ thinkers who emphasize more communitarian concepts of politics such as Michael Sandel and Frank Michelman.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0191453712473081"><label>2.</label><p>For another argument of the similarity between the republican and liberal concepts of liberty, see Alan Patten, ‘The Republican Critique of Liberalism’, <italic>British Journal of Political Science</italic> 26(1) (1996): 25–44.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0191453712473081"><label>3.</label><p>For previous understandings of republican liberty, see Quentin Skinner, ‘The Republican Ideal of Political Liberty’, in Gisela Bock et al. (eds) <italic>Machiavelli and Republicanism</italic> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1988), pp. 293–309.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0191453712473081"><label>4.</label><p>Isaiah Berlin, ‘Two Concepts of Liberty’, in <italic>The Proper Study of Mankind</italic> (New York: Farrar, Straus, &amp; Giroux, 1997), pp. 191–242 (p. 194).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0191453712473081"><label>5.</label><p>Philip Pettit, <italic>Republicanism: A Theory of Freedom and Government</italic> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1997), p. 22.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0191453712473081"><label>6.</label><p>Philip Pettit, ‘Keeping Republican Freedom Simple: On a Difference with Quentin Skinner’, <italic>Political Theory</italic> 30(3) (2002): 339–56 (341–2).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0191453712473081"><label>7.</label><p>Pettit, <italic>Republicanism</italic>, p. 52.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0191453712473081"><label>8.</label><p>ibid., p. 53.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0191453712473081"><label>9.</label><p>ibid., p. 63.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-0191453712473081"><label>10.</label><p>See Stephen Eric Bronner, <italic>Reclaiming the Enlightenment: Toward a Politics of Radical Engagement</italic> (New York: Columbia University Press, 2004), pp. 41–60.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-0191453712473081"><label>11.</label><p>See Gordon Wood, <italic>The Radicalism of the American Revolution</italic> (New York: Vintage, 1991), pp. 95–228.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-0191453712473081"><label>12.</label><p>This understanding of unfreedom is also shared by Quentin Skinner in his discussion of ‘dependency’. See his <italic>Liberty before Liberalism</italic> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998), pp. 68–99.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-0191453712473081"><label>13.</label><p>I think Charles Larmore is correct on this point. See his ‘A Critique of Philip Pettit’s <italic>Republicanism</italic>’, <italic>Noûs</italic> 35(1) (2001): 229–43. For a more historical understanding of this process, see Karen Orren, <italic>Belated Feudalism: Labor, the Law and Liberal Development in the United States</italic> (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1991).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-0191453712473081"><label>14.</label><p>Philip Pettit, ‘Freedom as Antipower’, <italic>Ethics</italic> 106(3) (1996): 576–604 (577).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-0191453712473081"><label>15.</label><p>Pettit, <italic>Republicanism</italic>, p. 52.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-0191453712473081"><label>16.</label><p>‘What is required for non-arbitrary state power … is that the power be exercised in a way that tracks not the power-holder’s personal welfare or world-view, but rather the welfare and world-view of the public’ (ibid., p. 56).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn17-0191453712473081"><label>17.</label><p>Frank Lovett, ‘Domination and Distributive Justice’, <italic>The</italic> <italic>Journal of Politics</italic> 71(3) (2009): 817–30.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn18-0191453712473081"><label>18.</label><p>Pettit claims that any act of domination ‘will be a matter of common knowledge among the people involved, and among any other who are party to their relationship – any other in the society who are aware of what is going on – that the three base conditions are fulfilled in the relevant degree’ (<italic>Republicanism</italic>, p. 59). It seems to me that this mistakes the mechanisms of modern forms of authority and domination, in particular as Weber lays them out. On Weber’s account, forms of domination become absorbed by individual agents making domination a part of a kind of ‘second nature’.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn19-0191453712473081"><label>19.</label><p>The translation into English of Weber’s use of the term <italic>Herrschaft</italic> has been seen by some to be problematic. Some have seen different implications to the rendering of <italic>Herrschaft</italic> either as ‘domination’ or as ‘authority’. See David Easton, ‘The Perception of Authority and Political Change’, in Carl Friedrich (ed.) <italic>Authority</italic>, Nomos I (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1958), pp. 170–96; as well as Dennis Wrong, <italic>Power: Its Forms, Bases, and Uses</italic> (New Brunswick, NJ: Transaction, 2002), pp. 35–41; and Reinhard Bendix, <italic>Max Weber: An Intellectual Portrait</italic> (New York: Anchor Books, 1962). However, I see this as largely unproblematic since Weber suggests that the terms ‘authority’ and ‘domination’ are interchangeable. Weber’s text reads: ‘<italic>Herrschaft (“Autorität”) in diesem Sinn kann im Einzelfall auf den verschiedensten Motiven der Fugsamkeit: von dumpfer Gewöhnung angefangen bis zu rein zweckrationalen Erwängungen, beruhen</italic>’, in <italic>Wirtschaft und Gesellschaft</italic> (Tübingen: J. C. B. Mohr [Paul Siebeck], 1972), p. 122.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn20-0191453712473081"><label>20.</label><p>ibid., p. 28.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn21-0191453712473081"><label>21.</label><p>ibid.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn22-0191453712473081"><label>22.</label><p>‘We therefore find that the concept of domination … is therefore identical with authoritarian power of command [<italic>autoritärer Befehlsgewalt</italic>]’ (ibid., p. 544).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn23-0191453712473081"><label>23.</label><p>ibid.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn24-0191453712473081"><label>24.</label><p>Herbert Marcuse, ‘A Study on Authority’, in <italic>Studies in Critical Philosophy</italic> (Boston, MA: Beacon Press, 1972), pp. 51–5. Also see the more detailed discussion by Weber, <italic>Wirtschaft und Gesellschaft</italic>, pp. 122–4.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn25-0191453712473081"><label>25.</label><p>For an important discussion, see Wolfgang Schluchter, <italic>The Rise of Western Rationalism: Max Weber’s Developmental History</italic> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1981), pp. 106–38.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn26-0191453712473081"><label>26.</label><p>I take this concept of ‘extractive domination’ from C. B. MacPherson’s concept of ‘extractive power’. He defines this simply: ‘political power, being power over others, is used in any unequal society to extract benefit from the ruled for the rulers. … The amount of power may therefore be measured by the amount of benefit extracted.’ See his <italic>Democratic Theory: Essays in Retrieval</italic> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1973), pp. 47–8.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn27-0191453712473081"><label>27.</label><p>Skinner, <italic>Liberty before Liberalism</italic>, pp. 17–57; and Quentin Skinner, <italic>Hobbes and Republican Liberty</italic> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2008), pp. 149–210.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn28-0191453712473081"><label>28.</label><p>Philip Pettit, <italic>A Theory of Freedom: From the Psychology to the Politics of Agency</italic> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2001), p. 70.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn29-0191453712473081"><label>29.</label><p>See Charles Larmore, ‘Liberal and Republican Conceptions of Freedom’, <italic>Critical Review of International Social and Political Philosophy</italic> 6(1) (2003): 96–119 as well as Melvin L. Rogers, ‘Republican Confusion and Liberal Clarification’, <italic>Philosophy &amp; Social Criticism</italic> 34(7) (2008): 799–824.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn30-0191453712473081"><label>30.</label><p>See Michael J. Thompson, <italic>The Politics of Inequality: A Political History of the Idea of Economic Inequality in America</italic> (New York: Columbia University Press, 2007), pp. 57–98.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn31-0191453712473081"><label>31.</label><p>For a fuller discussion of the way republicanism was employed in the context of early industrial capitalism in America, see Michael J. Thompson, ‘The Critique of Economic Inequality in Early American Political Thought’, <italic>New Political Science</italic> 30(4) (2008): 307–24.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn32-0191453712473081"><label>32.</label><p>Pettit claims that institutions are important to help constitute the state of non-interference of citizens: ‘To be immune to arbitrary interference, to enjoy non-domination, is to have inhibitors present in your society – maybe these, maybe those – which prevent arbitrary interference in your life and affairs. And the presence of suitable inhibitors – suitable institutions and arrangements – represents a way of realizing your non-domination; it is not something that leads by a causal path to that non-domination’ (<italic>Republicanism</italic>, p. 108).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn33-0191453712473081"><label>33.</label><p>ibid., p. 24.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn34-0191453712473081"><label>34.</label><p>Maynor, <italic>Republicanism in the Modern World</italic>, p. 38.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn35-0191453712473081"><label>35.</label><p>Philip Pettit, ‘Republican Freedom: Three Axioms, Four Theorems’, in C. Laborde and J. Maynor (eds) <italic>Republicanism and Political Theory</italic> (Oxford: Blackwell, 2008), pp. 102–30 (p. 106).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn36-0191453712473081"><label>36.</label><p>Algernon Sydney, <italic>Discourses Concerning Government</italic> (Indianapolis, IN: Liberty Fund, 1990), pp. 402–3.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></back></article>