<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IBE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spibe</journal-id>
<journal-title>Indoor and Built Environment</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1420-326X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1423-0070</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1420326X11425964</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1420326X11425964</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Energy Consumption Behaviour of an Urban Residential Sector in the Northern Province of Madhya Pradesh (India)</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>Anita</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1420326X11425964">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Jaiswal</surname><given-names>Y. K.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1420326X11425964">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>Khurshreed Ahmad</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1420326X11425964">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1420326X11425964"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1420326X11425964"><label>a</label>IGAEERE, Jiwaji University, Gwalior, Madhya Pradesh, India</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1420326X11425964"><label>b</label>School of Studies in Biochemistry, Jiwaji University, Gwalior, Madhya Pradesh, India</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1420326X11425964">Khursheed Ahmad Wani, Indira Gandhi Academy of Environmental Education Research and Ecoplanning, Jiwaji University, Gwalior, Madhya Pradesh, India Mob. +918109487624, Fax +917512442621, E-Mail: <email>kuursheedeva@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>703</fpage>
<lpage>709</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s), 2011. Reprints and permissions: http://www.sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">International Society of the Built Environment</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Energy crises represent a bottleneck in the progress of the Indian economy. In the present scenario, high energy consumption is more noticeable with the development of the economy of the country, due to changes in the lifestyle of the consumers in the residential sector. The current challenge is to seek sustainable development, maintaining activities, transformation and progress levels while adopting more efficient use of existing resources and achieving energy conservation. An assessment of the energy consumption of the residential sector of the Gwalior city, Madhya Pradesh (India) has been carried out in the present investigation. Structured questionnaires were distributed among the 500 households during the present investigation. The survey has indicated that the majority of households are using modern high energy appliances leading to overuse of the valuable energy resources. The present investigation demonstrates that most of the buildings were not climate responsive, and were consuming high levels of energy to achieve thermal comfort for residents. The western region of the country is the largest consumer of the total energy. There is a dire need to go for an energy-efficient operation with public participation that may greatly reduce the energy consumption and ultimately reduce burden on fossil fuels.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Energy crisis</kwd>
<kwd>assessment households</kwd>
<kwd>Gwalior</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1420326X11425964"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Energy is a key element in the overall efforts to achieve sustainable development. The increased population and economic development have raised the energy consumption in the past few decades. The earthen society has completely transformed into throwaway society by adopting highly intensive and unsustainable lifestyle. Some studies have shown a positive relationship between economic growth and energy consumption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1420326X11425964">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1420326X11425964"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1420326X11425964">3</xref>]. Since, urban living is highly intensive, it is important to understand energy interactions at different levels, so that information on this possible decoupling can be obtained [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1420326X11425964">4</xref>]. Chen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1420326X11425964">5</xref>] has pointed out that, in order to achieve a good balance among the economy, development, energy consumption and environmental quality, it is important to look into the actuality of residential energy consumption and its influence factors, so as to put forward reasonable countermeasures to impel energy conservation. Energy use in the residential sector, which account for about 15% of the world delivered energy consumption in 2006, is defined as the energy consumed by households, excluding transportation uses. The type and amount of energy use by households vary from country to country, depending on income levels, natural resources, climate and available energy infrastructure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1420326X11425964">6</xref>]. The per capita energy consumption by developed countries like USA, Canada, etc. is much higher than India. Even the consumption pattern varies significantly within the country.</p>
<p>In this study, the relationship between energy consumption and household activities are determined by comparing a snapshot of energy consumption with household size, possession and utilisation of domestic energy consuming appliances and consumption behaviour. In addition to this, the present study attempts to throw some light on the influence of seasonal variations on the energy consumption pattern. Weather is known to be an important factor affecting energy consumption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1420326X11425964">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1420326X11425964"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1420326X11425964">9</xref>]. It has now been accepted that global warming is taking place, which will increase the winter mean temperature, resulting in lower demand for heating energy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1420326X11425964">10</xref>]. On the other hand, there is an evidence of an increase in the number of hot spells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1420326X11425964">11</xref>]. So, it is obvious that, there will be a significant rise in cooling degree days and significant reduction in heating degree days. Therefore, seasonal variation is an important factor in determining residential energy consumption, particularly for heating and cooling of space [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1420326X11425964">12</xref>]. India is a country with diverse climatic conditions, which may be the major cause for the building sector to consume a high level of energy to achieve thermal comfort for the built environments.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1420326X11425964"><title>Material and Methods</title>
<p>The survey instrument was a questionnaire containing 21 items addressing household size, resource availability, energy consumption, possession and utilisation of electrical appliances and behavioural pattern to obtain relevant information.</p>
<p>A simple random sampling was performed in urban households of Gwalior city situated in the Northern Province of Madhya Pradesh (India). The total number of samples selected was 500 urban households, of which 421 complete responses were received. To account for seasonal variations in fuel consumption, the survey was conducted in two phases representing typical summer, i.e. in the month of June and in winter during December.</p>
<p>The study subjects were categorised on the basis of end users – cooking, artificial lighting, cooling, heating, entertainment, washing clothes. In each case, quantities reported by the households were accepted. The approximate electricity consumption was calculated by multiplying the wattage and usage time. The energy demand consumed in these appliances was assumed to remain constant during the entire operating period. The calculated energy consumption could only provide an indication of the likely end use, and not the actual consumption as was pointed out by Yan and Tso [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1420326X11425964">13</xref>]. In case of Liquid Petroleum Gas (LPG) and electricity the energy values were derived by using standard conversion factors for facilitating comparisons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1420326X11425964">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1420326X11425964">15</xref>]. Statistical results were obtained through the application of mean, standard deviation and Pearson correlation coefficient.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1420326X11425964"><title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec4-1420326X11425964"><title>Basic Information of the Study Area</title>
<p>The present study was conducted in Gwalior city, situated in the northern province of Madhya Pradesh (India) at Latitude 26° 22′ N and Longitude 78°18′ E, having total area of 5214 km<sup>2</sup>. It has an average elevation of 197 m (646 ft). The climate of Gwalior region may be described as composite with hot and dry summers, hot and humid rainy season and short autumns and winters. Mean maximum temperature in summers is 33°C, with the highest maximum of 48°C and mean minimum temperature in winters is 18.5°C with the minimum range of 1–3°C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1420326X11425964">16</xref>]. Thus, the scorching summers and chilly winters provide environmental scenarios for heating and cooling of space for the investigation of energy consumption behaviour.</p>
<p>The city region is within a rain shadow zone, and the rainfall in the area is 700 mm/annum, which is half the average rainfall during the monsoon months in the state. The site is characterised by large pockets of fallow and barren land [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1420326X11425964">16</xref>]. These situations are not suitable for the development of vegetation, which provides high biomass value. So, people are rarely using biomass fuel for their energy requirements.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1420326X11425964"><title>Energy Availability and Utility Indices</title>
<p>The changes in lifestyles have induced households shift to technologies that are user friendly and provide greater comfort, for example, firewood kerosene LPG electricity. Affordability and accessibility to these fuels has played a significant role in fuel choice by households. Decisions are made by households depending upon their needs and priorities. In the present study, the overall energy needs of the households are fulfilled by two dominant energy resources: LPG and Electricity. However, a negligible amount of the sample population (0.023%) uses twigs and leaves for cooking and heating purposes during winter season. The domestic energy consumption varies according to living standards of the consumers. The majority of households are using modern high energy consuming appliances. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1420326X11425964">Figure 1</xref> shows the possession of electric appliances by households. Refrigerators, ceiling fans and television top the list, followed by compressed fluorescent light (CFL) and desert coolers, while an electric heater is least possessed, i.e. about 13.95% of households. However, the state is facing the problem of energy scarcity, a provision of 5-h power blackout is introduced by Madhya Pradesh Electricity Board in peak hours, i.e. 3 h in the morning (6:00 am to 9:00 am) and 2 h in the evening (3:00 pm to 5:00 pm) in the city.
<fig id="fig1-1420326X11425964" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Possession of electrical appliances by the households.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11425964-fig1.tif"/></fig>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1420326X11425964"><title>Energy Consumption Pattern</title>
<p>The total energy consumption per household is dominated by electricity, which accounts for 65.4% while remaining 34.4% use LPG. The consumption pattern is significantly influenced by seasonal variations. In summer, the electricity consumption (62%) is higher than gas (38%). However, in winter both sources, electricity (51%) and gas (49%), are used almost equally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1420326X11425964">Figure 2</xref>).
<fig id="fig2-1420326X11425964" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>(a) Overall, (b) summer, (c) winter months’ energy consumption pattern on the basis of fuel used.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11425964-fig2.tif"/></fig>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-1420326X11425964"><title>Gas Consumption</title>
<p>The average per household gas consumption was calculated as 6.34 MJ. According to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1420326X11425964">Figure 3</xref>(a), LPG is mainly used for cooking (54.46%) and water heating (45.54%). In summer, cooking sector consumes 73.20% and water heating takes about 26.19% of the total share (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1420326X11425964">Figure 3</xref>(b)). While during winter, the situation is almost reverse, cooking consumes 35.72% of the total energy and water heating 64.28% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1420326X11425964">Figure 3</xref>(c)). People’s usage behavioural pattern also has a significant impact on consumption, as 21% of the sample population cook with high flame.
<fig id="fig3-1420326X11425964" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>(a) Overall, (b) summer, (c) winter months’ gas consumption pattern on the basis of end use.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11425964-fig3.tif"/></fig>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1420326X11425964"><title>Electrical Energy Consumption</title>
<p>The annual electricity consumption per average household was found to be 8.09 MJ by the survey. The electrical energy consumption can be classified according to its ultimate use such as cooking, artificial lighting, cooling, heating, entertainment and washing. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1420326X11425964">Figure 4</xref> highlights the individual contribution of electronic appliances in electricity consumption.
<fig id="fig4-1420326X11425964" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Energy consumption by electric appliances possessed by households.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11425964-fig4.tif"/></fig>
</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1420326X11425964">Figure 5</xref> shows the overall and seasonal sectorial electrical energy consumption where 38% of energy consumption was attributed to cooling followed by heating (15%) and artificial lighting (12%). Thus, it is clear from the figures that the heating and cooling contributes to more than half (53%) of the total consumption. Electrical energy consumption is also influenced significantly by seasonal variations. In summers, cooling alone takes a grand share of 45% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1420326X11425964">Figure 5</xref>(a)), which is dominated by the use of desert coolers, ceiling fans and air conditioners. Whereas in winters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1420326X11425964">Figure 5</xref>(b)), heating (24%), artificial lighting (20%) and entertainment (25%) contribute almost equally.
<fig id="fig5-1420326X11425964" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>(a) Overall, (b) summer and (c) winter’s sectorial electricity consumption pattern.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11425964-fig5.tif"/></fig>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1420326X11425964"><title>Factors Influencing Energy Consumption Levels</title>
<p>To understand the relationship between energy consumption in urban households and variables affecting the consumption, a correlation matrix was constructed using 8 variables. There is a significant correlation between energy consumption and ownership of appliances (<italic>r</italic> = 0.311, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05). One of the most important variable, i.e. family size has an unexpected negative correlation (<italic>r</italic> = −0.132) with the energy consumption, but this is not statistically significant. Whereas, family size (4.8 ± 2.22) shows a positive relationship with ownership of appliances (<italic>r</italic> = 0.24, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05), number of rooms (<italic>r</italic> = 0.338, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05), number of windows (<italic>r</italic> = 0.173, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01) and number of doors (<italic>r</italic> = 0.48, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1420326X11425964">Table 1</xref>). These variables are not sufficient to draw a significant conclusion, so there is a need to further investigate the influencing factors.
<table-wrap id="table1-1420326X11425964" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Correlation matrix of the relationship between household energy consumption and independent variables</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1420326X11425964" xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11425964-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th>Variables</th>
<th>1</th>
<th>2</th>
<th>3</th>
<th>4</th>
<th>5</th>
<th>6</th>
<th>7</th>
<th>8</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Energy consumption (per capita)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Family size</td>
<td>−0.132</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Time spend indoors</td>
<td>−0.064</td>
<td>−0.153</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Ownership of appliances</td>
<td>0.311<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.240<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.151</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>No. of rooms</td>
<td>0.077</td>
<td>0.338<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.295<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.366<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>No. of windows</td>
<td>−0.005</td>
<td>0.173<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.036</td>
<td>0.371<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.445<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>No. of doors</td>
<td>−0.141</td>
<td>0.480<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.246<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.263<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.796<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.393<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>1</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Courtyard</td>
<td>0.155</td>
<td>0.075</td>
<td>0.317<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.325<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.271<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.205<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.288<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1420326X11425964">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>1</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1420326X11425964"><label>a</label><p>p&lt;0.01; <sup>b</sup>p&lt;0.05.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-1420326X11425964"><title>Country-wise and Region-wise Energy Consumption</title>
<p>The per capita consumption of electrical power in India in 2005–2006 as calculated by Central Electricity Authority was about 631.41 kWh (2273 MJ), which is very low as compared to the world average. The per capita consumption in countries like Canada (17179 kWh), USA (13338 kWh), Australia (11126) is more than the double of India [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1420326X11425964">17</xref>].</p>
<p>On the other hand, per capita consumption also varies significantly within the country due to highly variable climatic conditions. The western region (which includes Madhya Pradesh) takes a significant share of energy as compared to the rest of the country. It consumes about 287.87 kWh more energy per year than the country average [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1420326X11425964">17</xref>]. In the present study, per year per average household electricity consumption was 2952.85 MJ and 2314.1 MJ, gas. According to Madhya Pradesh Human Development Report 2007, per year per person electricity consumption in Northern region of the state (including Gwalior) was 780 kWh, which is equivalent to 2808 MJ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1420326X11425964">18</xref>].</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-1420326X11425964"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>In India, the household sector is one of the largest users of energy, accounting for about 37% of final energy consumption reflecting the importance of that sector in total national energy scenario [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1420326X11425964">19</xref>]. Residential energy use in an urban area was analysed and reported in this paper based on a two-phase survey.</p>
<p>Lifestyle changes are taking place rapidly partially fuelled by higher disposable incomes, and changing work, leisure and behavioural patterns. The people’s choice for fuel is changing; they are switching over to the cleaner and more convenient options. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1420326X11425964">Figure 1</xref> illustrates that the majority of households possess modern high energy consuming appliances. A positive correlation between appliances and consumption further strengthen the fact (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1420326X11425964">Table 1</xref>). Reddy and Srinivas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1420326X11425964">19</xref>] have pointed out that during the period of 1980 to 2005, the biofuels’ share showed a declining trend, from 98% to 65%. In 1950s fuel choice was limited to biofuels and charcoal while with time fuels like kerosene, LPG and electricity continued to replace the former. The domestic energy consuming appliances are more and more prevalent these days and these often result in higher residential energy usage.</p>
<p>The family size has a positive relationship with the ownership of appliances, number of rooms, number of windows and number of doors. This may be due to the increasing needs, running time of appliances and high heat gain and losses through the openings by frequent movements of households. Considering the growth rate of population and living standards of the Indian community, it is expected that more energy will be consumed in the near future.</p>
<p>The results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1420326X11425964">Figures 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1420326X11425964">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1420326X11425964">5</xref>, have illustrated the apparent seasonal effect in energy consumption in India. The survey shows that the space cooling equipments is a dominating factor in the energy consumption. Desert cooler, ceiling fan and air conditioners accounts for more than 50% of total energy consumption. This is due to the high outdoor temperature and prolonged summers.</p>
<p>The chilly winters and outdoor temperature approaching sub-zero, would require space heating for most dwellings. Although the heating sector consumes less electrical energy than cooling, the LPG takes the major share of energy use. Only 13.95% of the sample population uses an electric heater. For water heating 30.95% of population solely use LPG, whereas, the rest of the population is dependent on electricity. This may be due to power blackouts in peak hours (6:00 am to 9:00 am), when students and employees require warm water for their daily needs. In addition to this, about 21% of the population would cook with high flames, which significantly has an impact on energy consumption. It has also become evident from the present study that people are using energy sources leading to overuse.</p>
<p>India is the sixth greatest electricity generating countries and accounts for about 4% of the world's total annual electricity generation. India is also currently ranked sixth in annual electricity consumption, accounting for about 3.5% of the world's total annual electricity consumption. Overall, India's need for power is growing at a prodigious rate; annual electricity generation and consumption in India have increased by about 64% in the past decade, and its projected rate of increase of electricity consumption is one of the highest in the world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1420326X11425964">20</xref>].</p>
<p>The per capita consumption by western region is much higher than the rest of the country. This may be due to the long and scorching summers, which would increase cooling load requirements for most homes. In turn, the demand of energy for running heating, ventilating and air conditioning devices would therefore, increase the energy consumption. The building sector has an important impact on energy consumption especially in such climatic conditions. According to Khitoliya et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1420326X11425964">21</xref>], in India, building sector being a large consumer can contribute to a large extent to address this issue concerning energy use for cooling.</p>
<p>In the present scenario, India suffers from a severe shortage of electric capacity. The blackouts are a common occurrence throughout the country’s main cities. Energy conservation is important in ensuring a sustainable future for households especially in developing countries. In fact, the energy efficiency and conservation are an important issue in many countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1420326X11425964">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1420326X11425964"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1420326X11425964"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1420326X11425964"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1420326X11425964"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1420326X11425964"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1420326X11425964">27</xref>]. The need of the hour is to amalgamate sustainable features in the process of development consciously and in an orderly manner. Climate responsive/green buildings should be designed, to reduce overall impact on the environment and natural resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1420326X11425964">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1420326X11425964">28</xref>], instead of transforming the valuable fuels to the basket of greenhouse gases. On the basis of the findings, the present study has revealed that proper energy planning, improved physical settlement; sustainable people behaviour and public participation can help in mitigating energy crises; conserve valuable resources and achieving sustainable development, not only in the study area but all over the world. The incorporation of rural features in these areas (urban areas) is the need of the hour which will serve as an effective tool to make our environment greener and safer.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1-1420326X11425964"><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1420326X11425964">Figures 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1420326X11425964">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1420326X11425964">5</xref> appear in colour online</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<ack><title>Acknowledgement</title>
<p>The authors are thankful to the owners of households for their kind cooperation. They also thank late Prof. R. R. Das for his technical, administrative and moral support. They are greatful to Prof. Rekha Bhadauria, Director, IGAEERE, Jiwaji University, Gwalior, for providing all necessary facilities to carry out the present study.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1420326X11425964"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dincer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dost</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Energy and GDP</article-title>: <source>Energy Resources</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1420326X11425964"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadoshin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>The trend in current and near future energy consumption from a statistical perspective</article-title>: <source>Applied Energy</source> <year>2000</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1420326X11425964"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egerlioglu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohhamad</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Guven</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Economic variables and electricity consumption in Northern Cyprus</article-title>: <source>Energy</source> <year>2001</year>;<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1420326X11425964"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahu</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nisanka</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Domestic fuel energy consumption in an Indian urban ecosystem</article-title>: <source>Biomass and Bioenergy</source> <year>1995</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>486</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1420326X11425964"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Statistical analyses on summer energy consumption characteristics of residential buildings in some cities of China</article-title>: <source>Energy and Buildings</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>42</volume>:<fpage> 136</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1420326X11425964"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Anonymous</collab>: <article-title>International Energy outlook</article-title>. <year>2009</year>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eia.doe.gov/oiaf/ieo/world.html/">http://www.eia.doe.gov/oiaf/ieo/world.html/</ext-link> (accessed May 2009)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1420326X11425964"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wrench</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Effects of climate change on commercial building energy demand</article-title>: <source>Energy Sources</source> <year>1994</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage> 332</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1420326X11425964"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Balmor</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Climate related evaluations of summer peak hours’ electric load in Israel</article-title>: <source>Appl Meteorol</source> <year>1992</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1492</fpage>–<lpage>1508</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1420326X11425964"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salior</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Relating residential and commercial sector electricity loads to climate evaluating state level sensitivities and vulnerabilities</article-title>: <source>Energy</source> <year>2001</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>645</fpage>–<lpage> 657</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1420326X11425964"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>What are the energy and power consumption patterns of different types of built environment?</article-title>: <source>Energy Policy</source> <year>2008</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>4622</fpage>–<lpage>4629</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1420326X11425964"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Climate and residential electricity consumption in Hong Kong</article-title>: <source>Energy</source> <year>1998</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1420326X11425964"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>An analysis of residential sector energy use in Hong Kong</article-title>: <source>Energy</source> <year>1996</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1420326X11425964"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tso</surname><given-names>G K F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>KKW</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>A study of domestic energy usage patterns in Hong Kong</article-title>: <source>Energy</source> <year>2003</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>1671</fpage>–<lpage>1682</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1420326X11425964"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chadwick</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Air pollution</article-title>: in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pasztor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristoferson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group> (eds): <source>Bioenergy and the Environment</source>, <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Westview Press</publisher-name>, <year>1990</year>, pp. <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>286</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1420326X11425964"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandola</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>A pilot survey of fuel consumption in rural areas</article-title>: <source>Indian Forester</source> <year>1976</year>;<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>692</fpage>–<lpage>699</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1420326X11425964"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Anonymous</collab>: <article-title>Gwalior weather</article-title>: <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mustseeindia.com/Gwalior-weather">http://www.mustseeindia.com/Gwalior-weather</ext-link> (accessed November 2009).</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1420326X11425964"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Anonymous</collab>: <article-title>Per capita power consumption in India</article-title>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.inrnews.com/realestateproperty/india/infrastructure/per_capita_power_consumption_i.html">http://www.inrnews.com/realestateproperty/india/infrastructure/per_capita_power_consumption_i.html</ext-link>. (accessed June 2009).</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1420326X11425964"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Anonymous</collab>: <article-title>Madhya Pradesh Human Development Report</article-title>: <year>2007</year>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mp.gov.in/difmp/mphdr/Chap3_E_2007.pdf">http://www.mp.gov.in/difmp/mphdr/Chap3_E_2007.pdf</ext-link>. (accessed November 2009).</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1420326X11425964"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Energy use in Indian sector – An actor oriented approach</article-title>: <source>Energy</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>992</fpage>–<lpage>1002</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1420326X11425964"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Trends and patterns of energy consumption in India</article-title>: <comment>MPRA. 2009. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mpra.ub.uni-muenchen.de/16774/2008">http://mpra.ub.uni-muenchen.de/16774/2008</ext-link>. (accessed October 2009).</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1420326X11425964"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khitoliya</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddharth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Green buildings: An energy conservation in India: Need and opportunities</article-title>: <source>Indian Green Building Congress</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>Vol.XIII</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1420326X11425964"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZX.</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Energy conservation in China</article-title>: <source>An international perspective: Energy Policy</source> <year>1995</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1420326X11425964"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Energy efficient end use electrical technologies and mitigation of greenhouse gas emissions in selected African Countries</article-title>: <source>Energy Resources</source> <year>1996</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1420326X11425964"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaoban</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Baseline energy and electricity consumption in Lebanon and opportunities for conservation</article-title>: <source>Energy Policy</source> <year>1998</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>487</fpage>–<lpage>493</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1420326X11425964"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eiswerth</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Abensoth</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cilianio</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouerghi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozog</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Residential electricity use and the potential impact of energy efficiency option in Pakistan</article-title>: <source>Energy Policy</source> <year>1998</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>306</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1420326X11425964"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fartahbaksh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ugursal</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>A residential end use energy consumption model for Canada</article-title>: <source>Energy Resources</source> <year>1998</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1420326X11425964"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>The analysis of energy consumption of a commercial building in Tianjin, China</article-title>: <source>Energy Policy</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>2092</fpage>–<lpage>2097</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1420326X11425964"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doijode</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Green architecture - Sustainability and conservation</article-title>: <source>Indian Green Building Congress</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>Vol. XIII</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>