<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HEJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphej</journal-id>
<journal-title>Health Education Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0017-8969</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1748-8176</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0017896911398812</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0017896911398812</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The effect of an education program utilising PRECEDE model on the Quality of Life in patients with type 2 diabetes</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Taghdisi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0017896911398812">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Borhani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0017896911398812">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0017896911398812">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Solhi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0017896911398812">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Afkari</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0017896911398812">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0017896911398812">c</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0017896911398812"><label>a</label>Department of Hygiene Education and Hygienic Services, Medicine Sciences University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0017896911398812"><label>b</label>Hygiene Center of Minoodasht, Minoodasht, Iran</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0017896911398812"><label>c</label>Department of Statistics and Hygienic Services, Medicine Sciences University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0017896911398812">M Borhani, Master of Health Education Medicine Sciences, University of Golestan, Hygiene Center of Minoodasht, Minoodasht, Iran Email: <email>borhani@goums.ac.ir</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>71</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>229</fpage>
<lpage>238</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Health Education Journal 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Health Education Journal</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><bold>Background and objective</bold>: The problems caused by diabetes have direct and indirect impacts on the quality of life of diabetic patients. An increase of these problems means a decrease in a patient’s quality of life. This study was conducted to assess the effect of the educational programme based on the precede model in promoting quality of life of patients with type 2 diabetes.</p>
<p><bold>Design and methods</bold>: This pre- and post-intervention quasi-experimental study was conducted on 78 patients with type 2 diabetes who were referred to a diabetes clinic in Minoodasht, Iran. The educational programme was based on the precede model and patients’ educational needs were included in the design. The data were collected using two questionnaires, including The World Health Organization Quality of Life (WHOQOL) questionnaire and the precede model-based educational questionnaire. The subjects were followed for one month after intervention to identify the role of educational intervention them. The data were analyzed by paired sample <italic>t</italic>-test, variance of analysis test and bivariate correlation test using SPSS version 15.</p>
<p><bold>Results</bold>: After the intervention, the mean score of quality of life increased from 80.39 ± 11.35 to 81.35 ± 8.31. No significant difference existed in the total score of quality of life after intervention, but there were significant differences in physical health (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05), self-evaluation of quality of life by patients (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), and self-assessment of health by patients after educational intervention. In addition, no significant differences were observed between demographic parameters and quality of life, except in the number of children.</p>
<p><bold>Conclusion</bold>: The educational programme based on the precede model was effective in improving the quality of life of patients with regard to physical health and self-assessment of their health status.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>precede model</kwd>
<kwd>quality of life</kwd>
<kwd>type 2 diabetes</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0017896911398812" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Diabetes is one of the most important health problems, and one of the most prevailing metabolic chronic diseases which demands constant care.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0017896911398812">1</xref></sup> This need for constant care is one of the main causes of its mortality rate and sickness.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0017896911398812">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0017896911398812">3</xref></sup> According to a report of the World Health Organization (WHO), in the next 25 years the number of individuals afflicted with diabetes will double, from 171 million people in 2000 to 366 million in 2030.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0017896911398812">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>There is a mutual relationship between disease and quality of life. The physical disorders and the existence of physical symptoms have a direct effect on all aspects of life quality. According to The American Diabetes Association, one of the chronic diseases which causes the emergence of physical and mental problems in individuals is Diabetes Mellitus. Today, diabetes is one of the most prevailing metabolic disorders – in particular in old people – which leaves disabling and dangerous impacts on vital organs of the body, such as blindness, the need for amputation, kidney failure, and cardiovascular disease.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0017896911398812">5</xref></sup> So, through education, the patient must try to manage the disease, to make an effort to improve the quality of their life.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0017896911398812">6</xref></sup></p>
<p>Different methods of health education are appropriate instruments to create motivation and correct improper performances, because health education is nothing but the science of drawing people’s attention towards the learning process, in order to create an ideal behaviour to achieve health.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0017896911398812">7</xref></sup> The selection of the model of health education is the first step in the process of designing an educational plan. An educational model starts the plan on a proper path and continues the orientation of the plan up to the stage of evaluation. The precede model starts from the final results (causes) and moves ahead through seven consequent and constant stages in design, implementation and evaluation. This model shows how social identification, epidemiology and behaviour lead to a clear understanding of needs, problems and individuals’ desires for society. It will investigate the causes of those groups of behavioural factors who have a close relation with health. Three potential factors which affect the sanitary behaviour (awareness, attitude, etc.), are determined in preparing factors, reinforcing factors (others’ impacts, family, peer groups, etc.) and empowering factors (accessibility of sources, skills, etc.).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0017896911398812">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0017896911398812">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>The precede model is unique because, by active involvement of the target community, it starts to determine the concerned final result and then it moves back to see which factors led to these results.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0017896911398812">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0017896911398812">11</xref></sup> Unfortunately, education of the patient is given less attention compared with other clinical practices, and the educational interventions for patients in most cases have been accidental and without planning.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0017896911398812">12</xref></sup> Preparing an educational plan in harmony with needs, experiences and interests of patients is still identified as a big challenge for the staff of health and treatment centres.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0017896911398812">13</xref></sup> It should be taken into consideration that using the theory will increase the effect of educational plans and will help with the identification of the features of individuals and his/her surrounding environments which have impacts on behaviours in one way or another. The theories play an effective role in designing comprehensive plans and their evaluations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0017896911398812">14</xref></sup> In this research, the precede model was used in order to plan for the promotion of the quality of the patients’ life. This model has been introduced by Green et al as a diagnostic framework for planning health education and for the promotion of health.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0017896911398812">15</xref></sup></p>
<p>Quality of life of diabetic patients is under the influence of various sources, so any kind of action to increase it should be in accordance with the individual, and in accordance with environmental and social factors. As the framework of the precede model investigates the individual and the environmental factors affecting a problem, the framework of this comprehensive model was used for the promotion of the quality of the life of diabetic patients. The effective application of this model in various health subjects has been proved. For instance, Jalili showed that an educational plan based on the precede model has had a greater impact on the behavioural nutrition correction of mothers and blood indexes of their children, compared with the classic education and prescription of iron supplements.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0017896911398812">16</xref></sup></p>
<p>In other research, Zygheymat showed that education based on the framework of the precede–proceed model is effective in the increase of awareness, attitude, reinforcing factors and also positive reacting behaviours in epileptic patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0017896911398812">17</xref></sup> Bastani could also reduce the rate of stress in pregnant women and results of pregnancy with an educational planning based on the precede model through his health belief model and self-efficiency theory.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0017896911398812">18</xref></sup> A study in 1995 on rural adult women in North Carolina, USA, on the rate of breast screening based on precede model showed that, by implementing designed educational plans based on the precede model, the rate of screening of rural women increased by 20 per cent during three years.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0017896911398812">19</xref></sup> Also the framework of precede was used in diagnosing obstacles of screening uterocervical cancer by women and taking action to remove cases through proper educational planning.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0017896911398812">20</xref></sup></p>
<p>This research has been conducted due to the increase of the rates of diabetes in our country (Iran) and the lack of an educational written plan based on educational and behavioural models and theories. It aimed at planning based on the precede model and its impact in the promotion of the quality of life of diabetics patients with type 2 diabetes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0017896911398812" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method of investigation</title>
<p>This research is a pre- and post- semi-empirical study which has been designed to determine and compare the impact of designed educational plans based on the precede model on the quality of life and its (physical, mental, social and environmental) domains on diabetic patients with type 2 diabetes within the following stages:</p>
<list id="list1-0017896911398812" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>At the stage of social diagnosis, the quality of a patient’s life was determined based on the standard questionnaire of the WHO. In accordance with the collected data from the questionnaire of quality of life and previous researches in this area, primary feasibility studies and the direction of intervention was conducted based on the identification of patients, and the social problems, which have a negative impact on the quality of the life of diabetic patients, were determined.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>At the epidemiological diagnosis stage, the health problem of patients was determined with regard to the review of texts and findings extracted from interviews with patients, and also preliminary studies on patients (lack of self-care skill). At this stage, the general goals and exclusive goals of the educational plan were compiled.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>With regard to the review of texts and findings collected from the interviews with patients, the lack of self-care skills included lack of control of blood sugar, fats, blood pressure and body weight through improper diet and lack of physical activities, sports, also consumption of alcohol and smoking cigarettes. So these cases were selected as the most important health problems which affect the quality of life of diabetic patients. Also the variables of age, gender, income, rate of education, job, body mass index and duration of affliction with disease were considered as non-health factors affecting the quality of the life of diabetic patients. At the stage of behavioural diagnosis, the behaviours classification was performed in accordance with their importance.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Finally, behaviours such as consumption of prescribed medicine in accordance with the instruction of their physician, blood sugar control, fats, blood pressure and observing food diet, exercising, formation of file in diabetes clinic and on-time attendance in educational classes were determined as behavioural factors affecting health problems. Also, age, gender, genetic potential and lack of facilities for doing exercise and observing diet, and lack of free-of-charge facilities to measure blood sugar, fat and blood pressure were determined as effective non-behavioural factors.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>At the stage of educational diagnosis, preparing, enabling and reinforcing factors were reviewed. With regard to the studies and preliminary studies by the researchers, awareness, attitudes, beliefs and values were selected as preparing factors for performing self-care factors. Furthermore, the enabling factors for self-care behaviours included sufficient skill to control disease (blood sugar, blood pressure, weight) and having access to sources, educational classes and family support. The reinforcing factors were the positive experiences of patients, families’ encouragement and involving staff in the research.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>With regard to these stages, standard and self-made questionnaires were prepared. After preparing the respective questionnaires, 78 patients who were referred to a diabetes clinic in Minoodasht city were included in the study. The sample volume, with regard to the researches performed in the quality of the life of diabetic patients, and with the 95 per cent assurance and 80 per cent testing power, and with a forecast of 10 per cent fall, the sample was estimated to be at least 78 people.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0017896911398812">21</xref></sup></p>
<p>The standards for inclusion in this research were, first, affliction with type 2 diabetes, and second, having had the illness for at least six months. The patients should have agreed their participation in the plan and should be under the health coverage of the health centre of Minoodasht city. The standards for leaving the plan were: the cases of the patients who were afflicted with other types of diabetes, dissatisfaction of patients with the continuation of research, affliction with another disease or incurable diseases, and death. Lack of a standard group is one of the limits of this study, the reason for which being due to the low number of active samples under the coverage of the clinic.</p>
<p>Note that the individuals’ agreement to join the research was obtained. The method of sampling was easy and it was made at the time period when the researchers were present in the clinic. In this research, the instruments of data collection included a questionnaire, which was adjusted in four sections. The first part of the questionnaire was related to the quality of life, which was measured through WHOQOL. This questionnaire assesses four domains of physical health, mental health, social relations and environmental health through 24 questions (each of the domains had seven, six, three and eight questions respectively). The first two questions do not belong to any domains and they assess the condition of health and quality of life in general form. So, this questionnaire has 26 questions in total. This questionnaire has been translated and accredited in Iran by Sahar Naznejat et al. The quantities of Cronbach’s alpha coefficient in all domains was over 7 percent.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0017896911398812">22</xref></sup></p>
<p>The second part of the questions related to demographic factors which included age, gender, job, level of education, marital status, number of children, rate of monthly income, duration of affliction with diabetes, body mass index and family history of affliction with this diabetes, and genetics.</p>
<p>The third part was a checklist for the behavioural factors affecting diseases. This checklist comprised seven questions. The fourth part of the questionnaire included the preparing factors (awareness, attitudes, beliefs and values), enabling factors and reinforcing factors. The awareness questions were designed within the format of eight closed questions, attitude with 14 questions at Likert scale, enabling questions within nine questions and reinforcing factors within the framework of three questions.</p>
<p>All questions were scored. The questions with a correct response were given one score and the negative responses were given no scores. For the purpose of scientific credit of the self-made questionnaire, the content creditability method was used. The questionnaire was given to 10 professors related to this subject and their corrective views were implemented.</p>
<p>For the calculation of the reliability of these questions, the method of calculation of re-test was used with a time span of two weeks for 15 patients. The obtained coordinative coefficient from the re-test for the self-made questionnaire was <italic>r</italic> = 0.8. Meanwhile, questionnaires were completed in the form of an interview by the researcher. After completing the questionnaires, the data were analyzed and the educational contents were adjusted in three cognitive, attitudinal and behavioural domains and the educational materials were selected.</p>
<p>The educational intervention was adjusted after five weeks and, each week, one session was held. The duration of each session was different with regard to the patients and their conditions, ranging between 20 to 30 minutes. The educational CD, educational pamphlet and tracts were prepared on each late outcome of diabetes, nutrition, sport and false beliefs and were given to patients. Additionally, the methods of lectures, question and answer, group discussion and showing educational films were used to educate patients.</p>
<p>In the sessions when patients were referred to the clinic, they were given special diet advice by the nutrition experts, and they began practicing this and the method of performing useful sport exercise for diabetic patients in practice and group forms. In the educational sessions, it was decided to have the presence of family members, and an educational pamphlet was also prepared to increase family support and assistance for the patient in controlling diabetes. In order to increase the support extended to diabetic patients by personnel, an educational session was held for the personnel. Note that the positive experiences of patients were also considered a reinforcing source.</p>
<p>Finally, four weeks after the end of intervention, the effects of the educational plan on the quality of the patient’s life was measured. The collected data were analyzed using SPSS statistical software. In order to determine the existence of any meaningful difference among the scores – the different dimensions of the quality of life, preparing factors of behaviour, and enabling and reinforcing factors at the previous stage, and four weeks after the end of educational intervention in the patients – the statistical matched-pair t<bold>-</bold>test was used.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0017896911398812">
<title>Findings</title>
<p>The average age of the individuals was 49 years. Of the patients, 79.5% per cent were female and 20.5 per cent were male; 87.2 per cent were married and 12.8 per cent had a deceased partner. The greatest percentage of those under consideration (76.9 per cent) were housewives, and 1.3 per cent were unemployed. Of those researched, 19.2 per cent were illiterate, 43.6 per cent had primary level education, and 5.1 per cent had an academic background at the level of guidance school. Seven point seven per cent of them were suffering fatness at level 1 and almost 65 per cent had a family record of affliction with diabetes. About 64 per cent of the individuals had been afflicted with their diseases for more than five years. The results showed that there was no meaningful difference between the quality of life of diabetic patients before education with demographic factors.</p>
<p>As for the link between the quality of life with demographic variables, a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) showed that there was no meaningful difference between demographic variances of age, gender, marital status, level of education and quality of life before education, with the exception in the number of children. The findings showed that patients with less than two children had a better life qualitatively compared with those with more than three children.</p>
<p>The statistical paired <italic>t</italic>-test showed that, from the viewpoint of scores of awareness, attitude, behaviour, enabling factors, and reinforcing factors before education and after education, there is not a meaningful difference (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0017896911398812">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0017896911398812" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>A comparison between the average and standard deviation of scores of awareness, attitude, and behaviour, enabling factors and reinforcing factors before and after intervention in the research units who referred to the Clinic of Diabetes at the Health Center of Minoodasht city, 2009</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0017896911398812" xlink:href="10.1177_0017896911398812-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable under consideration</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Pre-intervention</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Post-intervention</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Paired <italic>t</italic>-test</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Average</th>
<th align="left">Standard deviation</th>
<th align="left">Average</th>
<th align="left">Standard deviation</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic> value</th>
<th align="left"><italic>t</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Awareness</td>
<td>12.66</td>
<td>4.04</td>
<td>15.32</td>
<td>2.41</td>
<td><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001</td>
<td>−8.93</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Attitude</td>
<td>54.01</td>
<td>5.42</td>
<td>56.15</td>
<td>5.15</td>
<td><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001</td>
<td>−8.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Behaviour</td>
<td>3.99</td>
<td>1.02</td>
<td>4.83</td>
<td>0.87</td>
<td><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001</td>
<td>−7.94</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Enabling factors</td>
<td>4.64</td>
<td>1.09</td>
<td>5.29</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001</td>
<td>−6.16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reinforcing factors</td>
<td>1.88</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>2.41</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001</td>
<td>−6.65</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The average of the score of awareness, attitude, and behaviour, reinforcing factors and enabling factors increased after educational intervention. The paired <italic>t</italic>-test showed a meaningful difference in pre- and post-intervention in all stages of the model (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.1001).</p>
<p>The paired <italic>t</italic>-test showed that there is a meaningful statistical relationship between the average of physical health in pre- and post-education period, but no meaningful statistical relationship was seen between mental, social and environmental health before and after education.</p>
<p>The results of this research showed that there is a statistical meaningful relation between assessment of one’s life-quality and health situation in diabetic patients before and after education. However, in general, the paired <italic>t</italic>-test showed that there is no statistical meaningful relation between the average score of life-quality in the diabetic patients before and after education (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0017896911398812">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0017896911398812" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>The score of life quality of diabetic patients before and after educational intervention in research units in respect of clients of diabetic clinic at health centre of Minoodasht city, 2009</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0017896911398812" xlink:href="10.1177_0017896911398812-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Dimensions of life quality</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Before intervention</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">After intervention</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Paired <italic>t</italic>-test</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Average</th>
<th align="left">Standard deviation</th>
<th align="left">Average</th>
<th align="left">Standard deviation</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic> value</th>
<th align="left"><italic>t</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Physical health</td>
<td>21.09</td>
<td>3.20</td>
<td>21.47</td>
<td>2.54</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>−2.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mental health</td>
<td>18.29</td>
<td>3.76</td>
<td>18.61</td>
<td>3.30</td>
<td>0.09</td>
<td>−1.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Social health</td>
<td>9.92</td>
<td>2.66</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>0.34</td>
<td>−0.96</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Environmental health</td>
<td>24.10</td>
<td>4.45</td>
<td>24.2</td>
<td>3.16</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>−0.21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Assessment of one’s life quality</td>
<td>3.38</td>
<td>0.61</td>
<td>3.52</td>
<td>0.57</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>−3.56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Assessment of one’s health condition</td>
<td>2.8</td>
<td>0.70</td>
<td>2.97</td>
<td>0.62</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>−3.61</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Life quality</td>
<td>80.39</td>
<td>11.35</td>
<td>81.35</td>
<td>8.31</td>
<td>0.19</td>
<td>−1.32</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0017896911398812" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Quality of life is considered as a sign of the quality of healthcare and a result, in part, of programmes to control the patient. Studying this feature in our diabetic patients will help us to get an effective short term result, and thereby help us to assess the quality of services and care, and any other interfering and preventive measures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0017896911398812">23</xref></sup> The results of the study showed that there can be a significant difference in awareness rate, attitude, enabling factors, reinforcing factors and performance of effective self-care behaviours in patients after and before intervention by designing and performing of educational plans which are in accordance with the precede model. The findings of this research are compatible with other studies in which the precede framework model has been used for educational planning. As an example, Shakoori, in research under the title of ‘The Impact of Health Education Plan Based on precede Model on the Control of Anaemia and Iron Deficiency Among the Female Students of High School Level at Talesh City’ showed that the intervention of educational plan based on precede model and its main components (preparing, enabling and reinforcing factors) had a positive impact on the increase of preventive behaviors of insomnia and iron deficiency in the community under investigation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0017896911398812">24</xref></sup> Yates et al made an educational intervention in order to improve the management of ache in cancer patients in accordance with the precede model. The patients of the test group had a meaningful difference in awareness and attitude towards pain and realized control of pain compared with the standard group after educational intervention.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0017896911398812">25</xref></sup> In research by Johnson et al, the quality of life in diabetic patients and non-diabetic patients were compared with each other in 1997; 1,518 samples were studied in different parts of UK and the quality of the life of diabetic patients was less than non-diabetic people considerably. The rate of depression and anxiety was greater in diabetic patients and the greatest difference between the diabetic people and others was seen in their mental health.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0017896911398812">26</xref></sup></p>
<p>Another study was done in order to determine the impact of educational plans based on the PRECEDE model regarding prevention of depression in patients of bypass coronary surgery operations. The findings confirm the efficiency of the impact of educational plan based on the precede model to prevent and reduce the rate of depression in patients with the mentioned surgery operation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0017896911398812">27</xref></sup></p>
<p>In this research, the quality of life and its dimensions are observed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0017896911398812">Table 2</xref>. The average of the total score of life quality before educational intervention was 11/35 ± 80/93 which, after this intervention, increased to 81/35 ± 8/31. However, the paired <italic>t</italic>-tests did not show a meaningful statistical difference between average of the score of life quality in diabetic patients before and after education.</p>
<p>The results of the research of Litaker et al also showed that the impact of group care in diabetic patients had improved after glycemic control, but the quality of the life of patients had not changed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0017896911398812">28</xref></sup></p>
<p>The findings of this research in different domains of life quality showed that there is a meaningful statistical difference between the average of the score of physical health before and after education, but there was no meaningful statistical difference between mental, social and environmental health before and after education. Perhaps the reason for this is that, in addition to individual factors, other factors such as economic, social and cultural factors such as poverty, lack of facilities etc. in the society under research have influenced the results of this study.</p>
<p>The results of similar research showed that, after intervention, a considerable improvement took place in physical and mental dimensions of the life quality of patients but no meaningful changes were observed in social and environmental dimensions of life quality. The results are similar to some other studies (e.g. Tankova, 2000 and Rosemary and Bruci, 1995) and are also incomparable with some other studies (Nathan, 1999). A study which was performed by Aghamolyii et al is compatible with the results of this study. In this research, there was a meaningful increase in the average of awareness, physical health, mental health and a meaningful reduction in the average of A1c hemoglobin and also a meaningful increase from the viewpoint of personal control of blood sugar, weight control, sport and observing diet. However, no meaningful difference was observed between social and environmental dimensions of life quality.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0017896911398812">29</xref></sup></p>
<p>In this research, findings showed that there is a meaningful statistical difference between assessment of one’s life quality and one’s health condition in diabetic patients before and after education. In a research made by Rakhshandehro in the Iranian Association of Diabetes, the quality of life had a considerable increase three months after education.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0017896911398812">30</xref></sup> In other research by Dehdari et al, life quality of by-pass patients post-surgery was assessed before and after education intervention based on the Precede-Proceed model and it was shown that this model made an increase in the quality of life of patient after the coronary bypass surgery.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0017896911398812">31</xref></sup> These other studies show that quality of life is a complex concept, and determining the changes depends on the definition of the concept and the instruments being used.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0017896911398812" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Since education is considered to be one of the main organs of health and treatment care, and part of a patient’s rights, a greater significance should be attached to educational design and planning based on educational models and theories and also social and behavioural sciences for different diseases and heath subjects. The PROCEDE model is a comprehensive model in planning health education and promotion of health and can be used in different health issues.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>This article is the result of a Research Project with Code No: P/745 which was approved in the Office of Vice-President for Research at Iran University of Medical Science. The authors of the article wish to extend their sincere thanks to the staff of the Unit to Fight with Diseases at the Office of Vice-President for Health of Golestan University of Medical Science and all staff of Diabetes Clinic and Unit to Fight with Diseases at Minoodasht city who helped us with the implementation of the project.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0017896911398812">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tazakori</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zarei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mirzarahimi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of nutrition education on the level of blood sugar and Large nutrients received nutritional in diabetic insulin-dependent patients</article-title>. <source>Journal of Scientific Researches of Ardebil University of Medical Science</source>, <year>2002</year>: <volume>2</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>, <comment>Persian</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0017896911398812">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bate</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jerums</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Preventing complications of diabetes</article-title>. <source>Medical Journal of Australia</source>, <year>2003</year>: <volume>179</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>498</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0017896911398812">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Molassiotios</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The relationship between diabetes knowledge and compliance among Chinese with non-insulin dependent diabetes mellitus in Hong Kong</article-title>. <source>J of Adv Nurs</source>, <year>1999</year>: <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>438</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0017896911398812">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>A Rising Global Burden</collab>. <article-title>Action Now Booklet</article-title>. <comment>Online. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/diabetes/BOOKLET-HTML/en/">www.who.int/diabetes/BOOKLET-HTML/en/</ext-link></comment>,<comment>Diabetes</comment> (<access-date>accessed 14 August 2006</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0017896911398812">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zimmet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The burden of type 2 diabetes: Are we doing enough?</article-title> <source>Diabetes Metabolism</source>, <year>2003</year>: <volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0017896911398812">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stromberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Educating nurses and patients to manage heart failure</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cardiovasc Nurs</source>, <year>2002</year>: <volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0017896911398812">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hosseiny</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Survey knowledge, attitude and practice girl’s students about iron deficiency anemia</article-title>. <source>J of Medical Science University Gorgan</source>, <year>2006</year>: <volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0017896911398812">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kreuter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Health Promotion Planning: An Educational and Environmental Approach</source>. <publisher-loc>Mountain View, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mayfield Publishing Co.</publisher-name>, <year>1991</year> (pp. <fpage>26</fpage>, <fpage>30</fpage>, <fpage>153</fpage>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0017896911398812">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hiderbrank</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diniz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nutritional profile of non-pregnant women from the slums of Dinjapur, Bangladesh</article-title>. <source>Trop Doct</source>, <year>1999</year>: <volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0017896911398812">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Principles of Health Education and Health Promotion</source> (<edition>3rd edition</edition>). <publisher-loc>Belmont</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wadsworth</publisher-name>, <year>2001</year> (pp. <fpage>250</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0017896911398812">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glanz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rimer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jossey-Bass</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Health behavior and health Education: Theory, research, and practice</article-title>. <source>Education for Health</source>, <year>2004</year>: <volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0017896911398812">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deyirmenjian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salameh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Preoperative patient education for open-heart patients: A source of anxiety?</article-title> <source>Patient Educ Couns</source>, <year>2006</year>, <volume>62</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0017896911398812">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Redman</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Patient education at 25 years: Where we have been and where we are going</article-title>. <source>J Adv Nurs</source>, <year>1993</year>: <volume>18</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>725</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0017896911398812">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Behavioral science theory and principles for practice in health education</article-title>. <source>Health Education Research</source>, <year>1997</year>: <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0017896911398812">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hersey</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iverson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Health behavior models compared</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>, <year>1987</year>: <volume>24</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>973</fpage>–<lpage>981</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0017896911398812">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="thesis">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jalili</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Control of anaemia in once fives with using precede model in Kerman city</article-title>. <comment>PhD Dissertation</comment>, <publisher-name>Tarbiat Modares University</publisher-name>, <year>2000</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0017896911398812">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zygheymat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naderi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ebadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kajuoei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mehdizadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of education based on precede–proceed model on knowledge, attitude and behavior of epileptic patients</article-title>. <source>Behavioral Science Issue</source>, <year>2009</year>: <volume>3</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage> <comment>Persian</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0017896911398812">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="thesis">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bastani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of relaxation training based on synthesis of precede–proceed model with health belief model in reducing anxiety and pregnancy outcomes in pregnant women</article-title>. <comment>PhD Dissertation</comment>, <publisher-name>Tarbiat Modares University</publisher-name>, <year>2004</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0017896911398812">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alpeter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mayne</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Viadro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Omalley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The North Carolina breast cancer screening program: Foundations and design of a model for reaching older, minority, rural women</article-title>. <source>Breast Cancer Research &amp; Treatment</source>, <year>1995</year>: <volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0017896911398812">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hislop</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deschamps</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>tu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuniyuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Facilitators and barriers to cervical cancer screening among Chinese Canadian women</article-title>. <source>J Public Health</source>, <year>2003</year>: <volume>94</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0017896911398812">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Monjamed</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ali Asgharpoor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mehran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peymani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Quality of life of patients with diabetic complications</article-title>. <source>Journal of Nursing and Midwifery University of Medical Sciences Tehran</source>, <year>2006</year>: <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>, <comment>Persian</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0017896911398812">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nejat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Montazeri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Halakouei-Naeini</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohamad</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Majdzade</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Psychological assessment of Iranian strain (WHOQOL-BREF), standardization of quality of life of WHO questionnaire</article-title>. <source>Scientific Journal of School of Public Health and Institute of Public Health Research</source>, <year>2006</year>: <volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>, <comment>Persian</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0017896911398812">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Diabetic foot care: Assessing the impact of care on the whole patient</article-title>. <source>Practical Diabetes International</source>, <year>2000</year>: <volume>17</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0017896911398812">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shakoori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharifi-Rad</surname><given-names>Gh</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Golshiri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hasanzadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shafe Shakoori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of health educational programs based on precede model on control of iron deficiency anemia in high school girls in Talesh province</article-title>. <source>Seasonal Issue of Arak University of Medical Science</source>, <year>1388</year>: <volume>3</volume>(<issue>48</issue>): <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>, <comment>Persian</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0017896911398812">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aranda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Purdie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Najman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A randomized controlled trial of a nurse-administered educational intervention for improving cancer pain management in ambulatory settings</article-title>. <source>Patient Education and Counseling</source>, <year>2004</year>: <volume>53</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0017896911398812">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pickard</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conner</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Longitudinal changes in health related quality of life with diabetes compared to those without chronic conditions</article-title>. <conf-name>17th plenary meeting of THEEUROQOL Group Report</conf-name>, <conf-date>Summer 1999</conf-date> (pp. <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0017896911398812">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hazavei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sabzmakan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hasanzadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rabei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of an educational program based on precede on depression in patient after coronary artery bypass surgery</article-title>. <source>Journal of Ghazvin Medical Science</source>, <year>1387</year>: <volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>, <comment>Persian</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0017896911398812">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Litaker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mion</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Planavsky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kippes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frolkis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Physician–nurse practitioner teams in chronic disease management: The impact on costs, clinical effectiveness, and patients’ perception of care</article-title>. <source>J Interpr of Care</source>, <year>2003</year>: <volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0017896911398812">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aghamolyii</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eftekhar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kazem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sobhani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shojaei-zadeh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nakhjavani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of educational intervention using interactive approach to behavioral changes, Hemoglobin A1C and health-related quality of life in diabetic patients</article-title>. <source>Scientific Journal of School of Public Health and Institute of Public Health Research</source>, <year>1384</year>: <volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>, <comment>Persian</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0017896911398812">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rakhshandero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heydarnia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rajab</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of health education impact on quality of life in diabetic patients</article-title>. <source>Two-Monthly Scientific Research Issue of Shahed of University</source>, <year>1383</year>: <volume>13</volume>(<issue>63</issue>): <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>, <comment>Persian</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0017896911398812">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dehdari</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heydarnia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramezankhani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sadeghiyan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghofranipoor</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>planning and evaluation of an educational intervention based on precede–proceed model on improving the quality of life of patients after coronary artery bypass surgery</article-title>. <source>Journal of Birjand Medical Science</source>, <year>1387</year>: <volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>, <comment>Persian</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>