<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ISC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spisc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Intervention in School and Clinic</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1053-4512</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1538-4810</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1053451212443150</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1053451212443150</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Features</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Fostering Self-Determination Through Building Productive Relationships in the Classroom</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Bassett</surname><given-names>Diane S.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>Cari</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>Sharon L.</given-names></name>
<degrees>EdD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1053451212443150">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>Abigail S.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MEd</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1053451212443150">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1053451212443150"><label>1</label>Wayne State University, Detroit, MI, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1053451212443150"><label>2</label>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1053451212443150">Sharon L. Field, Wayne State University, 441 EDUC, College of Education, Detroit, MI 48202, USA Email: <email>sharon.field@wayne.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>48</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Transition and Students with Learning Disabilities and Emotional–Behavioral Disorders</issue-title>
<fpage>6</fpage>
<lpage>14</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Hammill Institute on Disabilities 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Hammill Institute on Disabilities</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Self-determination is essential to promoting successful transitions for students with and without disabilities. Numerous studies have found that positive relationships are central to the ability to be self-determined, thus making relationship building a key area to address to promote successful transitions. This article provides information on strategies, classroom modifications, and curricula that can be used to help students improve their ability to build an increased sense of belonging through positive relationships with others. Strategies are discussed within the context of self-determination to demonstrate how students can increase their ability to establish and maintain positive relationships and their self-determination concurrently.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>adolescence</kwd>
<kwd>self-determination</kwd>
<kwd>transition</kwd>
<kwd>interpersonal skills</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1053451212443150-img1.tif"/>
<p>People who are self-determined have “a combination of skills, knowledge and beliefs” that helps them
<disp-quote>
<p>engage in goal-directed, self-regulated, autonomous behavior. An understanding of one’s strengths and limitations together with a belief in oneself as capable and effective are essential in self-determination. When acting on the basis of these skills and attitudes, individuals have greater ability to take control of their lives and assume the role of successful adults in our society. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1053451212443150">Field, Martin, Miller, Ward, &amp; Wehmeyer, 1998</xref>, p. 2)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Self-determination is essential to successful transitions. Research beginning in the 1990s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1053451212443150">Wehmeyer &amp; Schwartz, 1997</xref>) found that students who had higher self-determination scores in their final year of high school were more likely to have expressed a preference to live outside the family home, have a savings or checking account, and be employed for pay 1 year following high school. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1053451212443150">Sowers and Powers (1995)</xref> found that self-determination instruction increased the participation and independence of students with severe disabilities in performing community activities.</p>
<p>Self-determination also supports academic success. Students who help choose school activities show enhanced motivation to perform those tasks and are more likely to achieve their goals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1053451212443150">Benz, Lindstrom, &amp; Yovanoff, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1053451212443150">Schunk &amp; Zimmerman, 1998</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1053451212443150">Houchins (1998)</xref> found that students who scored higher on a self-determination assessment also had higher academic achievement scores, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1053451212443150">Sarver (2000)</xref> found a positive relationship between self-determination and grade-point average.</p>
<p>There is evidence to suggest that increased self-determination is linked to better mental health, which is also a contributing factor to both successful transitions and academic achievement. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1053451212443150">Bruno (2000)</xref> found a decrease in depressive features of students at risk for depression after they participated in a self-determination curriculum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1053451212443150">Field &amp; Hoffman, 1996</xref>). In addition, he found that the number of children at risk for depression in the treatment group significantly decreased from pretest to posttest, whereas the number of children at risk for depression in the control group increased.</p>
<sec id="section1-1053451212443150">
<title>Importance of Relationships to Increased Self-determination</title>
<p>In an explanation of self-determination theory, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1053451212443150">Ryan and Deci (2000)</xref> stated that <italic>relatedness</italic> is one of three basic human psychological needs (i.e., along with autonomy and competence) that, when met, results in a greater sense of self-determination. According to Ryan and Deci, contexts that encourage relatedness also foster greater internal motivation than settings that thwart the satisfaction of this need. Ryan and Deci’s claim is supported by research conducted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1053451212443150">Field, Hoffman, Sawilowsky, and St. Peter (1996)</xref> that found that positive relationships were viewed by the majority of persons they interviewed as the most important support for self-determination, and difficult relationships were noted as the most significant barrier to self-determination.</p>
<p>Because of the preponderance of evidence supporting the importance of positive relationships to promoting self-determination, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1053451212443150">Hoffman and Field (2006)</xref> revised their initial self-determination model to provide a stronger emphasis on the importance of relationships as a component element of self-determination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1053451212443150">Figure 1</xref>). In the revised model, the importance of relationships to self-determination is specifically noted under Value Yourself (i.e., “develop and nurture positive relationships”) and Act (i.e., “access resources and support,” “communicate,” “negotiate,” and “deal with conflict and criticism”).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1053451212443150" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Model of self-determination</p>
<p>Revised (2003) from Field and Hoffman (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1053451212443150">1994</xref>, p. 165). Copyright 1994 by the Hammill Institute on Disabilities. Reprinted with permission.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1053451212443150-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Helping students learn to form and maintain positive relationships is a key area of instruction that needs to be addressed to help students be more self-determined. Within a context of self-determination, relationships can be considered positive if they are (a) built on and support a foundation of relatedness, competence, and autonomy and (b) supportive of an individual’s ability to engage in the steps of self-determination in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1053451212443150">Figure 1</xref> (i.e., Know Yourself and Your Environment, Value Yourself, Plan, Act, Experience Outcomes, and Learn).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1053451212443150">
<title>Strategies for Building Relationship Skills</title>
<p>Teachers have a powerful impact on the growth of students’ ability to develop and maintain positive social relationships by what they model, what they teach, the types of relationships they have with students, and the way they manage classrooms. For example, the extent to which teachers arrange and organize features of the classroom environment to meet students’ social needs has an impact on social interactions and relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1053451212443150">Hamre &amp; Pianta, 2010</xref>) as well as students’ perceptions of their social relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1053451212443150">Hamm, Farmer, Dadisman, Gravelle, &amp; Murray, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1053451212443150">Skinner &amp; Belmont, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1053451212443150">Wentzel, 2010</xref>). Classroom relationships include, but are not limited to, teacher–student relationships and student–peer relationships. Social relationships within the classroom potentially support or exacerbate students’ social adjustment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1053451212443150">Hamre &amp; Pianta, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1053451212443150">Ladd, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1053451212443150">Ladd &amp; Burgess, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1053451212443150">Meehan, Hughes, &amp; Cavell, 2003</xref>). Teachers who are attuned to children’s social experiences may be more responsive to students’ social needs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1053451212443150">Hamm et al., 2011</xref>) and also are more able to simultaneously recognize and exploit the supportive and minimize the nonsupportive qualities of naturally occurring peer group memberships in the classroom social dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1053451212443150">Farmer, 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Teachers can help students develop the ability to form and maintain positive relationships by (a) supporting students to increase their self-awareness, (b) implementing social skills training, (c) being a positive role model, (d) providing opportunities for positive teacher–student interactions, and (e) increasing teacher awareness of and attention to classroom peer ecology (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1053451212443150">Farmer, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1053451212443150">Field &amp; Hoffman, 2002a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1053451212443150">2002b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1053451212443150">Hamm et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1053451212443150">Wehmeyer &amp; Field, 2007</xref>). These strategies that help students develop the ability to have positive relationships can all be connected to component elements of self-determination instruction, as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1053451212443150">Figure 1</xref>. For example, increased self-awareness is essential to the first self-determination model component (i.e., know yourself and your environment). Social skills training is an important part of the Act component, especially the communication subcomponents. Providing appropriate role models and opportunities for experiential learning are consistent with the cornerstones for self-determination instruction identified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1053451212443150">Hoffman and Field (2006)</xref> in the introduction to the <italic>Steps to Self-Determination</italic> curriculum. Finally, increasing teacher awareness of and attention to classroom peer ecology addresses the environment component of the self-determination model as well as incorporating the self-determination instruction cornerstone of experiential learning. Each of these vehicles to promote students’ abilities to form positive relationships is further discussed below, and practical examples of each method are provided.</p>
<sec id="section3-1053451212443150">
<title>Supporting Students’ Self-Awareness</title>
<p>To have relationships that balance autonomy, competence, and relatedness, it is essential that students develop a strong internal foundation (i.e., Know Yourself and Value Yourself components in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1053451212443150">Figure 1</xref>) from which they can connect with others. It is important that individuals have awareness of their strengths, weaknesses, needs, and preferences, as delineated under the Know Yourself component in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1053451212443150">Figure 1</xref>, to maintain a sense of autonomy and competence within the context of a relationship. It is also essential that an individual values and has positive regard for himself or herself. Sample activities to promote student self-awareness are provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1053451212443150">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1053451212443150" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Sample Activities to Promote Self-Awareness</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1053451212443150" xlink:href="10.1177_1053451212443150-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Have students develop a resume. Work with them to use the resume writing experience to develop their knowledge of their strengths, weaknesses, needs, and preferences.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pass a bag of small bite-sized snacks around the room. For every snack a student takes, the person must tell the others one thing about herself or himself.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tape a piece of construction paper on each student’s back. Using washable markers, ask each student to write one positive thing about each of the other students on their construction paper.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Provide an opportunity for students to make a word or picture collage of things they do or do not like.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1053451212443150">
<title>Building Relationship Skills</title>
<p>Social skills training helps students develop the skills to communicate effectively and positively with others. It includes such skills as active listening, assertive communication, negotiation, and conflict resolution skills as identified under the Act component of the self-determination model in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1053451212443150">Figure 1</xref>. Social skills and problem-solving training is a component of instruction that is fundamental to positive relationships and contributes to increased self-determination.</p>
<p>A variety of social skills and problem-solving curricula are available. An important caveat that must be remembered when using social skills and problem solving methods to promote stronger relationships and increased self-determination is that these skills must be taught in conjunction with activities that help students further develop and honor awareness of their own strengths, weaknesses, needs, and preferences. According to self-determination theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1053451212443150">Ryan &amp; Deci, 2000</xref>), relatedness, autonomy, and competence are three balanced psychological needs that, when met, lead to greater self-determination. If relatedness is encouraged at the expense of autonomy and competence, self-determination will be thwarted. Some examples of social skills–related training that could contribute to the development of positive relationships and self-determination follow.</p>
<p>A curriculum to help students develop social and interpersonal skills was offered by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1053451212443150">Bauminger (2002)</xref>. Bauminger taught students about social concepts, such as starting a conversation, and then presented them with a vignette about a student who had difficulty using the skill. Students were taught a problem solving process to address the problem in the vignette. The steps included (a) define the problem, (b) discuss emotions associated with the problem, (c) define alternative social actions, (d) consider consequences of each alternative, (e) make a decision about the best alternative, (f) role-play solution with their teacher, (g) receive homework to practice the social skill covered in the lesson at home, and (h) receive feedback from the teacher on the homework. Research has found that students generated more appropriate solutions to problems faced in social situations and initiated more social interactions with their peers after 7 months of instruction in this procedure.</p>
<p>Problem solving in social situations is an example of a skill that is important to the ability to form and maintain relationships. A computer program to teach social problem–solving skills was developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1053451212443150">Bernard-Opitz, Sriram, and Nakhoda-Sapuan (2001)</xref>. The program provided pictures or videos of people experiencing social conflicts. The students then completed an animated problem solving process in which they developed alternative solutions to solve the problem. After students developed an alternate solution using the program, a video clip of the actors resolving the problem was provided. As students had more experience with the program, they developed more alternative solutions to the scenarios. Helping students learn how to increase the number of solutions generated is important. If students are able to generate more solutions to a problem, they will often develop a better resolution of the problem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1053451212443150">D’Zurilla &amp; Nezu, 1980</xref>).</p>
<p>Within the <italic>Steps to Self-Determination</italic> curriculum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1053451212443150">Hoffman &amp; Field, 2006</xref>), a variety of strategies are provided to teach social skills within the context of self-determination. This curriculum was designed to meet the needs of students with high-incidence disabilities, such as learning disabilities and behavioral disorders, with little to no modification in inclusive or special education settings. The curriculum is also appropriate for students with more severe disabilities when adaptations are made to meet specific individual needs. Examples of social skills strategies provided in the curriculum include the following:</p>
<list id="list1-1053451212443150" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Teach students the component steps of assertive communication (i.e., make eye contact, use appropriate body language and gestures, use facial expressions that match your words, use appropriate tone and volume of voice, select appropriate time to communicate, use “I” statements).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Model passive, assertive, and aggressive communication and have students differentiate between the three types of communication and help students identify the positive and negative aspects of each type of communication.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Provide opportunities for students to role-play passive, active, and aggressive communication in situations that are relevant to them (e.g., your parents ask you to clean your room, a friend breaks a promise to call you, a boss asks you to work late).</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1053451212443150">
<title>Providing Positive Role Models</title>
<p>Research has demonstrated that modeling is a highly effective instructional strategy. The models of behavior that students see often have a more powerful effect on their acquisition of new behaviors than what is explicitly taught (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1053451212443150">Bandura, 1986</xref>). With this research in mind, it is important for teachers to be aware of the types of relationship skills that they are modeling for students, both with other adults whom students have the opportunity to observe and in the relationships they have with students. Teachers need to consider what they are trying to teach students about relationships and self-determination (e.g., beginning relationships from a foundation of self-awareness, using appropriate social skills such as assertive communication and win–win negotiations) and reflect on whether or not that is what they are modeling.</p>
<p>One way to promote the development of positive relationship skills through role modeling is by connecting students with mentors who can serve as positive role models. The <italic>Journal Journey Program</italic> is an innovative mentoring model, incorporating the use of alumni volunteers, that was created to help students develop their writing, geography, and history skills concurrently with increasing their self-awareness and their relationships with mentors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1053451212443150">Feldman, 2011</xref>). The alumni foundation purchased composition books for all students who would be participating in the program. They asked the students to write a page about themselves. The book was then mailed to an alumnus, who wrote a page about where he or she currently lives and a memory of the school. Alumni were also asked to send a picture postcard of where they live to the students whom they were mentoring. This project has given students an opportunity to practice relationship skills by being in positive relationships with the alumni (see <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1053451212443150">Note 1</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1053451212443150">
<title>Building Relationship Skills Through Student–Teacher Interaction</title>
<p>The importance of students’ perceptions of their relationships with teachers in the classroom has been emphasized in the research literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1053451212443150">Chang, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1053451212443150">Wentzel, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1053451212443150">2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1053451212443150">2010</xref>). Classrooms in which students perceive teachers as showing warmth, mutual respect, and autonomy are more likely to motivate and engage students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1053451212443150">Wentzel, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1053451212443150">2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1053451212443150">2010</xref>). That is, a key aspect of teachers’ influence is conceptualized in terms of the extent to which teachers create contexts for students to feel cared about, respected, autonomous, and competent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1053451212443150">Chang, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1053451212443150">Pianta &amp; Allen, 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1053451212443150">Pianta and Allen (2008)</xref> suggested that motivation-producing interactions are created through the following:</p>
<list id="list2-1053451212443150" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Teachers’ intentional interest in and expression of warmth and caring for youth</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Teachers’ instructional and social interactions with students that draw on and support adolescents’ drive for autonomy and competence</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Teachers’ instructional interactions that bring relevance to classroom learning.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>These features of teacher–student interactions and relationships serve as resources for youth as they learn to form and maintain relationships.</p>
<p>To have the ability to form the types of positive relationships with students described previously, teachers need to have an awareness of their own strengths, weaknesses, needs, and preferences. Just as helping students develop positive relationships begins with helping them to form a foundation of self-awareness, teachers need to be aware of their needs and preferences to have the ability to form positive relationships with students. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1053451212443150">Richardson and Shupe (2003)</xref>, “[I]ncreased self-awareness involves a more accurate understanding of how students affect our own emotional processes and behaviors and how we affect students, as well” (p. 8). Richardson and Shupe provided five key questions teachers can use to increase their self-awareness:</p>
<list id="list3-1053451212443150" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Am I taking proactive steps to identify and defuse my own “emotional triggers”?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Am I paying attention to what I need to pay attention to?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Am I using effective strategies to reduce burnout and nurture my own mental health?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Am I using an appropriate sense of humor to build relationships, diffuse conflict, engage learners, and manage my own stress?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Do I regularly acknowledge significant ways I (and others) make a difference in the lives of students?</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Building on a foundation of self-awareness, one process that has been found to promote positive relationships is coaching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1053451212443150">Parker, Field Hoffman, Sawilowksy, &amp; Rolands, 2011</xref>). Many definitions of <italic>coaching</italic> have been provided in the literature. One of the definitions that best describes coaching as an intervention to promote self-determination follows:
<disp-quote>
<p>In a co-active coaching relationship the agenda comes from the client, not the coach. . . . The relationship is entirely focused on getting the results clients want. They set the agenda. The coach’s job is to make sure the agenda doesn’t get lost. . . . This is different from consulting, for example, where the consultant brings specialized expertise and very often sets the agenda for the relationships. Co-active coaching is not about the coach’s content, or the coach’s expertise, or giving solutions. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1053451212443150">Whitworth, Kimsey-House, &amp; Sandahl, 1998</xref>, pp. 4–5)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1053451212443150">Byron and Parker (2002)</xref>, a number of beliefs are implicit throughout the array of coaching definitions and frameworks. These include (a) using questioning as a primary communication tool, (b) working from a belief base that clients or students usually possess the capacity to develop their own solutions, (c) explicitly deciding on communication and logistical components of the coaching relationship that are mutually agreed on by the coach and the client, and (d) emphasizing the importance of breaking goals into small steps and working to achieve those goals one step at a time.</p>
<p>Coaching is a new model that originated within the corporate leadership and supervision literature and is emerging as a support service for students in high school and college settings. The concept of coaching is highly consistent with the basic tenets of self-determination and deserves careful consideration and research as a potentially positive strategy for promoting student self-determination in students with and without disabilities. Although classroom teachers typically are not in a position to provide direct coaching to students, the use of coaching-inspired techniques can often help teachers communicate with students in a manner that helps build relationships. One strategy that is often used in coaching is the use of questioning techniques, particularly the use of broad, open-ended questions that encourage students to think more expansively about possible answers. For example, a question that begins with “what” often elicits more information than one that begins with “why” or one that can be answered by a simple “yes” or “no.” By using questions that elicit broader responses, we are often able to increase understanding and build stronger relationships. Examples of questions that can elicit broader thinking that leads to both positive relationships and increased self-determination are provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1053451212443150">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1053451212443150" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Questioning Strategy Examples</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1053451212443150" xlink:href="10.1177_1053451212443150-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Narrow questions</th>
<th align="center">Broad questions</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Did you have trouble completing the assignment?</td>
<td>What steps did you use to complete the assignment?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Why were you late?</td>
<td>What helps you to be on time?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Do you understand the material in this chapter?</td>
<td>What did you learn from this chapter?</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>For more information on coaching resources, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1053451212443150">Whitworth et al. (1998)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1053451212443150">Parker, Field, and Hoffman (in press)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1053451212443150">Quinn, Ratey, and Maitland (2000)</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1053451212443150">
<title>Building Relationship Skills Through Positive Classroom Peer Ecology</title>
<p>As noted in the self-determination model in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1053451212443150">Figure 1</xref>, students’ environments play an important role in either supporting or hindering student self-determination. Students’ peer groups are the contexts in which they are afforded the opportunity to establish connections to others. Peer group connection is a pathway for students to meet a fundamental human need for connection throughout the life course (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1053451212443150">Baumeister &amp; Leary, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053451212443150">Cairns &amp; Cairns, 1994</xref>). Although students self-select into naturally occurring peer groups, they still depend on teachers to navigate classroom social dynamics successfully and to benefit fully from positive social relationships. In fact, a central aspect of a teacher’s responsibility is to organize the classroom environment in ways that best attend to children’s developmental needs, including their need to feel connected to others in the classroom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1053451212443150">Doll, Song, &amp; Siemers, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1053451212443150">Hamre &amp; Pianta, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1053451212443150">Skinner &amp; Belmont, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1053451212443150">Wentzel, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>A substantial body of research demonstrates that children’s adjustment is supported when teachers create classrooms that address the basic social need to feel accepted by and related to others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1053451212443150">Furrer &amp; Skinner, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1053451212443150">Osterman, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1053451212443150">Wentzel, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1053451212443150">2010</xref>). For teachers to create supportive classroom environments, they must first be aware of key aspects of classroom social dynamics, such as students’ preferences in relationships. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053451212443150">Cairns and Cairns (1994)</xref> suggested that teachers’ accurate assessment of peer group affiliation patterns is a key feature of the teacher’s influence in students’ social adjustment and is referred to as <italic>teacher attunement</italic>. Teacher attunement to students’ peer group preferences enables teachers to more effectively use naturally occurring peer group memberships to foster social adjustment in the classroom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1053451212443150">Hamm et al., 2011</xref>). Accordingly, a heightened attunement to peer group memberships helps teachers organize classrooms to facilitate and sustain accepting, caring, and supportive social interactions.</p>
<p>Elementary and middle school experiences provide the foundation for building the types of positive relationships that will lead to successful transitions from school to postsecondary experiences. Recent research demonstrates that middle school teachers with higher attunement more effectively manage classroom social dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1053451212443150">Hamm et al., 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053451212443150">Cairns and Cairns (1994)</xref> characterized this process as an aspect of a teacher’s “invisible hand,” to conceptualize the everyday and often intentional ways that teachers (as well as other adults) shape social processes that support or constrain students’ adjustment in the classroom. The teacher’s invisible hand metaphor includes attunement to peer group memberships and classroom social dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053451212443150">Cairns &amp; Cairns, 1994</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1053451212443150">Farmer, Lines, and Hamm (2011)</xref> suggested that the teachers’ invisible hand “promotes students’ self-directed, autonomous, and developmentally productive peer experiences” (p. 249). According to this characterization, teachers act as social engineers in the classroom and arrange the context to support positive and productive relationship for students and their peers.</p>
<p>Teachers who have an understanding of peer group memberships may be better able to design interventions that address factors in peer group memberships that support or inhibit problematic behaviors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1053451212443150">Farmer, 2000</xref>). When teachers are attuned to peer group memberships, they may be better able to accurately identify potentially healthy connections between and among students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1053451212443150">Farmer, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1053451212443150">Rodkin &amp; Hodges, 2003</xref>) and intentionally organize classroom activities to be fun, supportive, and inclusive. Through students’ classroom interactions, relationships among classmates emerge (i.e., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053451212443150">Cairns &amp; Cairns, 1994</xref>). Classrooms in which students have the opportunity to interact with many different classmates support student likeability and sociability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1053451212443150">Van den Oord &amp; Rossem, 2002</xref>). By taking students’ peer group memberships into account, teachers may more likely coordinate social opportunities among classmates that are successful (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1053451212443150">Farmer, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1053451212443150">Rodkin &amp; Hodges, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>Cooperative learning is an example of an instructional strategy that capitalizes on knowledge of peer ecology and role modeling to help students build relationship skills while they are learning in a content area. Cooperative learning (a) increases the availability of peer role modeling experiences and (b) helps students learn and practice communication and collaboration skills. The effectiveness of cooperative learning is well established in the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1053451212443150">Johnson, Johnson, &amp; Holubec, 2008</xref>). Examples of strategies that use cooperative learning to encourage positive relationships are provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1053451212443150">Table 3</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1053451212443150" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Using Peers and Cooperative Learning to Encourage Productive Relationships</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1053451212443150" xlink:href="10.1177_1053451212443150-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Provide instruction in multiple academic competencies relevant for successful group tasks (e.g., creativity, visual ability, reasoning).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Publicly recognize students’ academic competencies as they relate to group work with specific and favorable feedback.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Assign authentic leadership roles to students.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Carefully pair students who have relatively low status with high-status peers who will actively support their social competencies.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1053451212443150">
<title>Summary</title>
<p>Teachers can create an environment in which developmentally competent and productive relationships are established when they (a) provide opportunities for students to increase their self-awareness, (b) directly teach social competencies, (c) provide opportunities for youth to experience positive role models, (d) consciously nurture warm and supportive teacher–student relationships, and (e) increase their attention to and knowledge of the classroom peer ecology.</p>
<p>As shown in the model of self-determination in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1053451212443150">Figure 1</xref>, positive relationships are fundamental to self-determination. In addition, many of the skills that lead to more positive relationships are embedded within the component skills depicted in the self-determination model (e.g., know your strengths, weaknesses, needs, and preferences; accept and value yourself; communicate; deal with conflict and criticism). Self-awareness provides students with the foundation to make decisions about the types of relationships they want to have. Instruction in competencies that lead to more positive relationships (e.g., assertive communication and negotiation skills) provides students with tools they can use to create and maintain positive and nurturing relationships. Positive role models provide another avenue for students to learn the skills that lead to more effective relationships using one of the most time-efficient and powerful instructional strategies available. Warm and supportive relationships between students and teachers provide both modeling and experiential learning for students about positive relationships. These positive relationships that result in students experiencing more positive emotion can also help students be more receptive to all instruction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1053451212443150">Kok, Catalino, &amp; Fredrickson, 2008</xref>). Finally, attention to creating a positive classroom peer ecology provides a context in which students can learn about and demonstrate positive relationship skills.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1053451212443150">
<label>1.</label>
<p>More information about the alumni mentoring model can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pasteuralumni.org">www.pasteuralumni.org</ext-link>.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <source>Social foundations of thought and action: A social cognitive theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leary</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The need to belong: Desire for interpersonal attachments as a fundamental human motivation</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>117</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>529</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bauminger</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The facilitation of social-emotional understanding and social interaction in high-functioning children with autism: Intervention outcomes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>32</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yovanoff</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Improving graduation and employment outcomes of students with disabilities: Predictive factors and student perspectives</article-title>. <source>Exceptional Children</source>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>529</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bernard-Opitz</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sriram</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nakhoda-Sapuan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Enhancing social problem solving in children with autism and normal children through computer-assisted instruction</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>The effects of a self-determination intervention on youth explanatory style and depressive features</source> <comment>(Unpublished doctoral dissertation). Wayne State University, Detroit, MI</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Byron</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>College students with ADHD: New challenges and directions</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Brinckerhoff</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Postsecondary education and transition for students with learning disabilities</source> (pp. <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>367</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Austin, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PRO-ED</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>Lifelines and risks: Pathways of youth in our time</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Variable effects of children’s aggression, social withdrawal, and prosocial leadership as functions of teacher beliefs and behaviors</article-title>. <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>74</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>548</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Doll</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siemers</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Classroom ecologies that support or discourage bullying</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Espelage</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swearer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Bullying in American schools: A social-ecological perspective on prevention and intervention</source> (pp. <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>D’Zurilla</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nezu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>A study of the generation-of-alternatives process in social problem solving</article-title>. <source>Cognitive Therapy and Research</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The social dynamics of aggressive and disruptive behavior in school: Implications for behavior consultation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational and Psychological Consultation</source>, <volume>11</volume>(<issue>3&amp;4</issue>), <fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lines</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamm</surname><given-names>J. V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Revealing the invisible hand: The role of teachers in children’s peer experiences</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>. doi:10.1016/j.appdev.2011.04.006<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.appdev.2011.04.006</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Pasteur elementary school alumni foundation</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pasteuralumni.org">www.pasteuralumni.org</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Development of a model for self-determination</article-title>. <source>Career Development for Exceptional Individuals</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Steps to self-determination</source>. <publisher-loc>Austin, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PRO-ED</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002a</year>). <article-title>Lessons learned from implementing the</article-title> <source>Steps to Self-Determination</source> curriculum. <source>Remedial and Special Education</source>, <volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002b</year>). <article-title>Preparing youth to exercise self-determination: Quality indicators of school environments that promote the acquisition of knowledge, skills and beliefs related to self-determination</article-title>. <source>Journal of Disability Policy Studies</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>St. Sawilowsky</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Research in self-determination</source>. <publisher-loc>Detroit, MI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wayne State University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wehmeyer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>A practical guide to teaching self-determination</source>. <publisher-loc>Reston, VA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Council for Exceptional Children</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Furrer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Sense of relatedness as a factor in children’s academic engagement and performance</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>95</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamm</surname><given-names>J. V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dadisman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gravelle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Teachers’ attunement to students’ peer group affiliations as a source of improved student experiences of the school social-affective context following the middle school transition</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>. doi:10.1016/j.appdev.2010.06.003<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.appdev.2010.06.003</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamre</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pianta</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Early teacher-child relationships and the trajectory of children’s school outcomes through eighth grade</article-title>. <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>638</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamre</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pianta</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Classroom environments and developmental processes: Conceptualization and measurement</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Meece</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of research on schools, schooling, and human development</source> (pp. <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Steps to self-determination</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Austin, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PRO-ED</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Houchins</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>The self-determination of youth with and without disabilities who have been adjudicated</source> <comment>(Unpublished doctoral dissertation). University of Florida, Gainesville</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holubec</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Cooperation in the classroom</source>. <publisher-loc>Edina, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Interaction</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kok</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Catalino</surname><given-names>L. I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fredrickson</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The broadening, building, buffering effects of positive emotions</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Positive psychology: Exploring the best of people: Vol. 3: Capitalizing on emotional experiences</source> (pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ladd</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Having friends, keeping friends, making friends, and being liked by peers in the classroom: Predictors of children’s early school adjustment?</article-title> <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>1081</fpage>–<lpage>1100</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ladd</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>K. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Do relational risks and protective factors moderate the linkages between childhood aggression and early psychological and school adjustment?</article-title> <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>72</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>1579</fpage>–<lpage>1601</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Meehan</surname><given-names>B. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cavell</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Teacher–student relationships as compensatory resources for aggressive children</article-title>. <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>74</volume>, <fpage>1145</fpage>–<lpage>1157</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Osterman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Students’ need for belonging in the school community</article-title>. <source>Review of Educational Research</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>367</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>in press</year>). <source>Supporting self-determination in high school and college students: Learning from case studies</source>. <publisher-loc>Austin, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PRO-ED</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Field Hoffman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sawilowksy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rolands</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>An examination of the effects of ADHD coaching on university students’ executive functioning</article-title>. <source>Journal of Postsecondary Education and Disability</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pianta</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Building capacity for positive youth development in secondary school classrooms: Changing teachers’ interactions with students</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Shinn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Toward positive youth development: Transforming schools and community programs</source> (pp. <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>P. O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ratey</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maitland</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Coaching college students with ADHD: Issues and answers</source>. <publisher-loc>Silver Spring, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Advantage Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shupe</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The importance of teacher self-awareness in working with students with emotional and behavioral disorders</article-title>. <source>Teaching Exceptional Children</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rodkin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>E. V. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Bullies and victims in the peer ecology: Four questions for psychological and school professionals</article-title>. <source>School Psychology Review</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>384</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Self-determination theory and the facilitation of intrinsic motivation, social development, and well-being</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>55</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sarver</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>A study of the relationship between personal and environmental factors bearing on self-determination and the academic success of university students with learning disabilities</source> <comment>(Unpublished doctoral dissertation). University of Florida, Gainesville</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schunk</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Self-regulated learning: From teaching to self-reflective practice</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Belmont</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Motivation in the classroom: Reciprocal effects of teacher behavior and student engagement across the school year</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>85</volume>, <fpage>571</fpage>–<lpage>581</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sowers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Enhancing the participation and independence of students with severe physical and multiple disabilities in performing community activities</article-title>. <source>Mental Retardation</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Van den Oord</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rossem</surname><given-names>R. V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Differences in first graders’ school adjustment: The role of classroom characteristics and social structure of the group</article-title>. <source>Journal of School Psychology</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wehmeyer</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Instructional and assessment strategies to promote the self-determination of students with disabilities</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Corwin Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wehmeyer</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Self-determination and positive adult outcomes: A follow-up study of youth with mental retardation or learning disabilities</article-title>. <source>Exceptional Children</source>, <volume>63</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wentzel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Are effective teachers like good parents? Teaching styles and student adjustment in early adolescence?</article-title> <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wentzel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Motivating students to behavior in socially competent ways</article-title>. <source>Theory Into Practice</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wentzel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Students’ relationships with teachers</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Meece</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of research on schools, schooling, and human development</source> (pp. <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1053451212443150">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whitworth</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kimsey-House</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sandahl</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Co-active coaching: New skills for coaching people toward success in work and life</source>. <publisher-loc>Palo Alto, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Davies-Black</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>