<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HEA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphea</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Health (London)</journal-id>
<journal-title>Health:</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1363-4593</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7196</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1363459311407801</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1363459311407801</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: J. Mesman, <italic>Uncertainty in Medical Innovation: Experienced Pioneers in Neonatal Care</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Manns</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1363459311407801">Centre for Child and Adolescent Health, University of the West of England, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>16</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>107</fpage>
<lpage>109</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mesman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <source>Uncertainty in Medical Innovation: Experienced Pioneers in Neonatal Care</source>, <publisher-loc>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>; <page-count count="282"/> pp.: <issn>0230216722</issn> (hbk)</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The author won the 2009 Sociology of Health and Illness Book prize with this contribution to the literature in which she theorizes around the care provided, the processes and the role of reflexivity in the neonatal unit. Drawing on the notion of exnovation, Mesman endeavours to explore the shifting moral decision making and issues raised by the technological developments that play out in the neonatal unit. Through exnovation, she seeks to make explicit what can pass as unchallenged, implicit or hidden aspects of behaviour and by doing so, highlight the skill and capabilities of those who work in the unit. Through a good use of scene setting the reader is drawn into both the world of the unit that parents have to inhabit and by extensive quotations we can listen in to the actors in the accounts we read.</p>
<p>One of the strengths of the book is that by drawing on two systems of health care, the USA and the Netherlands, we hear different discourses around viability and how the need to provide a type of care is met. The practice of health care in the USA can perhaps be regarded as a practice that is hedged by or operated within the potential threats of lawsuits; this hedging can lead to the practice of defensive medicine which can separate care for the vulnerable population in a neonatal unit from a potential best interest for the baby. A sense of eavesdropping through the quotations can lead to real qualms when hearing of the imperatives or drivers that underpin the offer of care when they are perhaps not what the lay public or media might suppose them to be. Mesman leads us to the edge of uncomfortable reading and places us in the position of confronting reality with the world of one interventionist who regards their work on 23 week old babies as providing experience for 24 week old babies. The reader feels that while this might not be an experiment in care, the fact of reading this off the page can certainly feel like it might be.</p>
<p>Mesman moves us through aspects of life in a unit, and explores the expectations of roles, the languages of the unit, the role of numbers and how decision making can be ‘made’ in life and death. Each reader who has spent time in a unit will perhaps search for their own interest in the areas she tackles and I found that differing views of temporal relations perhaps the most compelling. Her discussions are helpful in considering how to understand the unit and its performance in the terms of the different rhythms of the unit: clock time; task-oriented time; process-oriented time. By viewing the unit in this fashion, we are shown there might be clashes between these time-related activities and the struggles that might arise in providing best care to the baby, to the family, but also to the activities such as providing medications that are time critical.</p>
<p>Perhaps unconsciously, Mesman has adopted a practice which can occur in units and when we hear of the family, they are being talked with as opposed to listened to.</p>
<p>When talking of the specific constructed identity of the baby, the parents are not included in this construction. It is all too easy to become blinded by the medical and nursing noise when both sound and sight can be lost of parents and babies getting to know each other.</p>
<p>The style of writing reflects the practice of <italic>processes</italic> in units since it ‘proceeds’ in chunked data, tasked to deliver a message and this might be a stylistic choice. As a result, there can be judders in the terminology adopted and this can interfere with the reading of the text; by example, although this is the world of neonatology, throughout the book the word ‘child’ is used in a situation where ‘baby’ is more usually adopted. This convention can act as a barrier between the reader and the message.</p>
<p>There are hints throughout about the baby and technology being regarded as one. This cyborg interface is not addressed and it would have been an interesting chapter to have explored this aspect through the prism of exnovation. By saying this, I mean that I could read more from the author on this topic. This is a book that requires our attention and time. Mesman succeeds in asking us to look afresh at the ‘how’ differing units with a differing delivery of care and perhaps most importantly a different thinking underlying the care might support these families.</p>
</body>
</article>