<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">APA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spapa</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Am Psychoanal Assoc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0003-0651</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1941-2460</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0003065112455361</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0003065112455361</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Panel Papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Analytic Listening and the Five Senses</article-title>
<subtitle>Introduction</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Chodorow</surname><given-names>Nancy J.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0003065112455361">61 Roseland Street Somerville, MA 02143 E-mail: <email>nancy_chodorow@hms.harvard.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>60</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>747</fpage>
<lpage>758</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Psychoanalytic Association 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Psychoanalytic Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This introductory essay, the three papers that follow—by Jonathan Palmer, Forrest Hamer, and Peter Goldberg—and the commentary by Susan Yamaguchi are products of the panel “Analytic Listening and the Five Senses,” presented at the American Psychoanalytic Association meeting in San Francisco, June 11, 2011.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>During the spring of 2011, just a month before the panel “Analytic Listening and the Five Senses,” I attended a symposium at the Boston Psychoanalytic Institute—three distinguished poets brought together to discuss Freud’s “Creative Writers and Day-Dreaming” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0003065112455361">1908</xref>). Each poet spoke about writing and the artistic process, and each read one of their poems. During the first reading, by Gail Mazur, a listener could detect, along with the poet’s voice, a loud rustle of turning pages from the audience, as Mazur moved to the second part of her poem. I myself was not reading but listening intently to Mazur’s voice and picturing the images from the poem in my mind. One of our panelists-to-be, Jonathan Palmer, seated next to me, was sketching—it seemed automatically and as if without noticing his own activity—whoever was speaking.</p>
<p>Reading, listening, drawing: this was serendipity. Members of the audience seemed to filter differently both the poem being read and the reader. As the discussion continued, my observations turned to the poets themselves. Louise Glück noted that for her, a poem belongs on the page: poems have shape, and their lines have size and chosen fonts. Pages contain the poem, and you lose that containment when you don’t <italic>see</italic> it. Robert Pinsky took another point of view. For him, the medium of poetry is not visual but vocal. The <italic>sounds</italic> compose the words, phrases, and lines. In fact, he added, he wishes he could have been a musician, since music is the most immediate of all the arts and the most collaborative.</p>
<p>In both cases, as it can be with each of us, the personal view was taken to be universal. Poems are poems only when they are seen on the page; poems are poems only when they are listened to as they are read aloud. In neither case is poetry simply a matter of words, sounds, and their combinative construction: poetry is something you <italic>see</italic>, or poetry is something you <italic>perform</italic> and <italic>hear</italic>. Mazur did not weigh in on this particular discussion. The poem she chose to read is a meditation written in the period when the death of her husband—the painter Michael Mazur—was imminent. “Figures in a Landscape” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0003065112455361">2011</xref>) describes visual experience and expresses affect, thus putting into perspective, literally, through a portrayal of figures in a landscape, her immediate emotional situation at the time of writing.</p>
<p>“Analytic Listening and the Five Senses” asks whether and how we find similar variation among analysts and how such specificity of sensory predilection infuses clinical work. Freud bequeathed us the talking cure, and we all use words. Yet, just as a few poets can tell us how, or imply that, they experience words through different sensory modalities, we can also wonder how differential sensory prisms might be experienced by each analyst. We explore the place of the senses in analytic work—how individual analysts filter their listening, their noticing, their analytic presence through differently developed, or inborn, sensory modalities and predilections.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0003065112455361">1</xref></sup> We ask how these modalities, so basic to psychoanalytic theory, affect our work—how they may be employed by different analysts and how we respond to these modalities as they are brought out in patients. We wonder how these features of the analyst’s individuality—if she is visual, musical, tactile, or sensitive to the sounds, rhythms, and meanings of words and the spaces between and among words—affect her listening. We explore how sensory modalities shape our clinical identity outside the consulting room and then reenter it, creating what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0003065112455361">McLaughlin (1993)</xref> has called “transference sanctuaries” (p. 378)—for him, specifically, working in his woodshed and garden, and painting eggs. As the “creative writers and day-dreaming” morning progressed, Jonathan Palmer continued to sketch. I found myself in a familiar mode of my own, thinking about this panel and writing ethnographic notes.</p>
<p>Contributors to our literature give us a rich sense of how the analyst’s person (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0003065112455361">Bonaminio 2008</xref>), character (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0003065112455361">Baudry 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0003065112455361">Kantrowitz 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0003065112455361">Kite 2008</xref>), mind (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0003065112455361">Jacobs 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0003065112455361">1997</xref>), personal history and vulnerabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0003065112455361">McLaughlin 2005</xref>), mortality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0003065112455361">Pinsky 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0003065112455361">2012</xref>), and personal idiom and personal internal setting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0003065112455361">Parsons 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0003065112455361">Coltart 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0003065112455361">Balint 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0003065112455361">Milner 1950</xref>) are constitutive features of each individual analyst’s presence and activity. According to these writers, we cannot <italic>not</italic> bring our character, person, mind, vulnerabilities, personal internal setting, or mortality to our work.</p>
<p>In a similar vein, this panel considers how such particularity inheres not only in qualities of mind and character but also in different modalities of sensory filtering. We wonder what developed and undeveloped senses we bring to our work. We hear and see, but we also smell, taste, and touch. In everyday parlance we say we have “blind spots,” are “mis-attuned” to the patient, that a patient is “difficult to reach.” We may feel that we are left with a “bad taste” in our mouths after a session, or that we are “touched” by something a patient says or does. Most American analysts do not touch their patients directly, but many Europeans shake hands before or after sessions. We all touch and feel our chairs, pens, notepads, and appointment books; we change the napkins on the couch cushion, and we straighten the magazines that patients have thumbed through in our waiting rooms. We make minor adjustments after particular patients—after some (a smoker, a perfume wearer, someone who sweats or doesn’t wash) we may open the windows or use air freshener, and in this context we can note that some clinicians, just as some patients, notice personal and other odors more than others do.</p>
<p>As we endeavor to investigate analytic listening and the five senses, we remember that we do not begin from a level sensory playing field (or empty canvas). We picture Freud’s consulting room, filled with small sculptures from antiquity. We know that Freud wrote on da Vinci and on the Moses of Michelangelo and that in other works he often drew on poetry and literature. Our folkloric wisdom contrasts Freud’s passion for these arts with his disavowal of interest in music. He writes, confirming our expectation, that he is “almost incapable of obtaining any pleasure” from those arts, like music, whose effects on himself he cannot explain:
<disp-quote>
<p>Nevertheless, works of art do exercise a powerful effect on me, especially those of literature and sculpture, less often of painting. This has occasioned me, when I have been contemplating such things, to spend a long time before them trying to apprehend them in my own way, i.e. to explain to myself what their effect is due to. Wherever I cannot do this, as for instance with music, I am almost incapable of obtaining any pleasure. Some rationalistic, or perhaps analytic, turn of mind in me rebels against being moved by a thing without knowing why I am thus affected and what it is that affects me [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0003065112455361">1914</xref>, p. 211].</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Sterba, discussing Freud’s claim, challenges our assumption. Freud, he remarks, loved Mozart’s operas and knew them well. He notes further that Freud occasionally used musical metaphors in his writing: Adler and Jung, Freud asserts, “have picked out a few cultural overtones from the symphony of life, and have once more failed to hear the mighty and primordial melody of the instincts” (quoted in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0003065112455361">Sterba 1965</xref>, p. 97).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0003065112455361">2</xref></sup> Following Sterba’s lead, I found an early letter from Freud to Martha Bernays, in which he reports to his “sweet little Princess” about having seen Beaumarchais’s <italic>The Marriage of Figaro</italic>. He loved the production, finding it brilliant and witty, but, he says, “Now and again I missed the wonderful music” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0003065112455361">Freud 1886</xref>, p. 192). Freud mentions particular passages of Mozart’s music that he missed, and he knows just where opera and play do not coincide.</p>
<p>Sterba points out that Freud favored artistic forms that involve the visual or the verbal (i.e., manifest representations of reality). These he could interpret in the fashion of dream interpretation, working toward finding latent unconscious meanings and unpacking condensations, displacements, and transformations. Music, Sterba points out, simply is what it is, not a traceable transformation of anything.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0003065112455361">3</xref></sup> The problem when it comes to music, Sterba claims, is that “the intellectual, interpretively searching approach to works of art—which was Freud’s approach—has to fail. . . . In general, works of the other arts are copies of reality. . . . psychoanalysis attempts to draw conclusions as to the latent, i.e., unconscious, content of the work of art. This method cannot be applied in the realm of music, where the work of art is not a copy of reality” (p. 97). With dreams, we might notice, Freud insisted on their final form as visual and pictorially representational, <italic>as</italic> “copy.”</p>
<p>Analysts may themselves participate in artistic creativity, and thereby in an interchange between their creative and their analytic work. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0003065112455361">Marion Milner’s classic <italic>On Not Being Able to Paint</italic> (1950)</xref>, perhaps inspiring Winnicott’s squiggle game, must certainly have been written by an analyst for whom the visual, or acts and represented acts of drawing, played a greater role than the musical in her listening. As we have this in her writings, Milner’s internal analytic setting and image of free association and its blocks are metaphorically linked to free-drawing on the page. Consciousness, the unconscious, and their expression are found through drawing, which may also use the whole body and body activity, representing, in what is then found, mind <italic>and</italic> body.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0003065112455361">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>As I mentioned earlier, I have observed Jonathan Palmer at meetings. He does not listen without sketching, or perhaps he listens <italic>through</italic> sketching. We may wonder how he is using his mind here: Is his sketching representational, as it can seem to the observer, perhaps like our attempts to capture process, or the points of presentations, in verbal notes? Is he attending to his countertransference, as others notice through their body, their mind’s wanderings, or the images or music that come to mind? Does sketching foster evenly hovering attention? (Jonathan points out that my own, less sense-driven process of listening is cerebral: I take notes and have organizing ideas, notice turns of phrase and things said and not said.)</p>
<p>We find a contrast to Milner and Palmer in Gilbert Rose and Julie Jaffe Nagel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0003065112455361">Nagel 2010</xref>). In <italic>Between Couch and Piano</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0003065112455361">Rose (2004)</xref> tells us that his couch shares office space with the same baby grand that gave him comfort when he was a child. He claims that nonrepresentational, nonverbal arts, and especially music, “generate feelings and help to process them” (p. xxvii). For Rose, the tempo, the time, the implicit motion of repetitions and changes, all these call particularly upon and evoke layerings of affect that accompany words. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0003065112455361">Nagel (2010)</xref> reports that specific music came to mind during her analysis and that she would often wish she could communicate the rush of thoughts in her head in music, rather than being limited to one word at a time (p. 650). In contrast to words, Nagel implies, music enables one to hear or produce many notes at the same time: it is synchronic as well as diachronic.</p>
<p>My own curiosity about sensory modes began in the mundane. I had puzzled over discussions with colleagues about phone analysis, which became a regular feature of my own work, as student and young professional patients relocated, and after I made a cross-country move. As I discussed this work with colleagues, I found some who could not imagine phone work but who were completely at ease doing clinical work through Skype, which I, by complement, found unimaginable. Others could imagine neither. The ear, the eye, and the body: analysts vary in their comfort with Skype and phone work, and one differentiating feature seems to be how much the visual, the tactile-visceral-bodily, or the tonal, rhythmic, and auditory, guides their listening presence.</p>
<p>My observations led me to think further about my own sense predilections and how these affect my work. I do not have a strong innate visual sense, have no artistic capabilities, am (germane to the Skype-phone discussion) more than electronically challenged, and something of a cyberphobe. Consciously, I had noticed in myself a visceral reaction to our field’s relative neglect of music, in contrast to the other arts, until quite recently. I love music and, though in no way an accomplished musician, have, generally, musicality and a good ear. Whether with patients in the office or on the phone, I am attuned to rhythm, voice, and timbre. I notice a tonal index, as my patients’ voices get slower or more speedy or go up and down octaves, depending on what is being felt, thought, or said. I pick up on and remember patients’ musical memories, hearing and entering imaginatively into their musical associations. Is a patient associating to a particular aria in an opera or to <italic>Long Black Veil</italic> as it evokes for her the 1960s? Is another hearing music in the clinical moment as he reports hearing, over the weekend, moving renditions of <italic>Shenandoah</italic> and “that song from Casablanca,” as I am hearing both music and words (“Oh Shenandoah, I long to hear you . . .” and “You must remember this, a kiss is just a kiss”)? As we are talking about his deep sadness, despair, and hopelessness, and a patient says, “I think, somehow, if I could understand music. . . . If someone would sing to me as I was dying,” I am moved, and I think immediately of the lullaby the patient remembers from his early childhood. I name, internally, another patient’s dream as his “Tamino dream.”</p>
<p>I remember and respond to patients’ associations to art and the visual surround, but I do not, I think, myself as immediately imagine or associate to these: they do not resonate internally in the same way (indeed, I do not myself find a visual word in the way that “resonate” comes naturally to mind). They seem more—well, visual. They are not as <italic>felt</italic> in my mind, affective state, inner ear, and body. And though I attend carefully and can place myself imaginatively into visual scenes described by patients who are more visual, I do not have as easy a time as with music in imagining, being moved by, or sometimes even knowing particular artists or works of art. As we learn from our panel, other clinicians experience differently.</p>
<p>In my mind for some time, consciously or preconsciously, was another observation. While working in the Bay Area, I was involved in a peer group with our panelist Forrest Hamer and another colleague. As we moved, under Forrest’s guidance, from discussing clinical cases to reading and discussing poetry, I found that the effect on my clinical work—on my listening, hearing, noticing, feeling, and sensing—was equally profound and useful, and in no way lessened. Somehow, the rhythm, sounds, and tones, along with the meaning of words, when read and thought about with colleagues, provided clinical deepening, in terms of both meaning and affect.</p>
<p>All of these sensory modalities take us directly to the body, and we find differences among analysts, as we listen to our colleagues and read the literature, in how much their clinical listening involves observations of body in their patients or of direct bodily experiences in themselves. The body itself—its size, shape, posture, movement, smell, how it is noticed—seems to figure more immediately and in the present for some analysts and patients than for others, and this must itself emerge from some specific aspect of the analyst’s own being-in-the-world. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0003065112455361">Balsam (2012)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0003065112455361">Chasseguet-Smirgel (2005)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0003065112455361">Dimen (2003)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0003065112455361">McDougall (1989)</xref>, among others, notice bodily sexuality in the consulting room, as well as bodily presence more generally—their patients’ bodies (and their own) as maternal, fecund, anorexic, drawn, over- or underexcited. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0003065112455361">Jacobs (1991)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0003065112455361">McLaughlin (2005)</xref> make us aware of the continual workings of the autonomic nervous system, the relaxation or tension of heart and chest, the clenching of the stomach, and other bodily distractions, as they observe these in patients and experience them in themselves. These practitioners all attend carefully to and query their patients about bodily experiences and sensations. Similarly, all our panelists, each immersed in particular modalities of expression and experience, notice the body. Peter Goldberg, especially, has focused extensively on the psychophysical body and bodily experience. He explores compulsive exercise, bodily being or not-being, and bodies experienced as alive and not alive. He describes bodily pseudovitality, fabricated bodies, and the somatic false self, as patients bring such (non)experiencing into the consulting room and affect themselves, the analyst, and the analytic field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0003065112455361">Goldberg 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0003065112455361">2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Individual analysts, then, may be more attuned to the visual, the musical, the tactile, the bodily-visceral. Meanwhile, we no longer think of words themselves as exclusively or primarily cognitive, and some, more than others, will be sensitive to the sounds, the rhythms, and the meanings of words, and to the spaces between and among words. We note the presence in our community of enough analyst-poets that there is a poetry section in each issue of <italic>The American Psychoanalyst</italic> and poetry workshops and symposia at several institutes. Several colleagues, focused on rhythm and tone as well as on meaning, conceptualize free association as a melding of the words and sounds of poetry into music. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0003065112455361">Ogden (1999)</xref> writes of “‘the music of what happens’ in poetry and psychoanalysis,” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0003065112455361">Seiden (2004)</xref>, in “On the Music of Thought,’” about metaphor in poetry and psychoanalysis, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0003065112455361">Jones (1997)</xref> of the missing “orchestration” (p. 694) of words, tone, timbre, and emphasis in many case reports. Jones, like Hamer a poet and psychoanalyst, claims that “as analysts, we attune ourselves to the overlap of meaning and music in words. . . . We not only use tone and melody, but choose words with particular rhythms” (p. 694). She points out that both analysis and poetry approach the unsayable, giving voice to experience and fantasy that has not yet been recognized: “experience that is in its intensity or its oldness beyond words” (p. 684; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0003065112455361">Parsons 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>My citations are sparse and selective, and they can be drawn on only heuristically, yet they also must capture sensuous reality in some way. Developmentally, sounds and rhythms (the music of what happens), experienced as they are in utero, precede vision, yet this does not mean that, universally, seeing is an advance. For some, the visual is a sensory filter, whereas for others, it is the ear, words, the tactile, or the visceral (literally, in the viscera). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0003065112455361">Schachtel (1947)</xref> characterizes seeing and hearing, as compared to taste, touch, and smell, as distal senses, but seeing is <italic>not</italic> distal for those, like painters and potters, who live with their eyes and creative hands and for whom touch and smell, the most proximal senses, also enter the studio. Nor is hearing distal for those who hear “melodies in the mind” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0003065112455361">Nagel 2010</xref>). For one patient, <italic>saying</italic> what comes to mind enables an avoidance of what have been, since childhood, her deepest terrors, which are always experienced in visual form—immediately, viscerally, and in detail. Further, when we parse things in our ordinary language of the senses, we bypass the cross-modal sensory perception that we learn about from infant developmentalists like <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0003065112455361">Stern (1985)</xref>: loud sounds and bright colors have common experiential presence and intensity.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0003065112455361">5</xref></sup> Loewald brings such observations to the clinical consulting room, noticing that language, the ostensible primary medium of communication in analysis, always partakes of the undifferentiated, global, affective, visceral, tonal, bodily, and relational resonances initially developed with the mother, from whom language is first learned. He describes these as the “undifferentiated ingredients of the total situation. . . . the sounds, tone of voice, and rhythm of speech . . . fused within the apprehended global event” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0003065112455361">1978</xref>, pp. 185, 187). Loewald also tells us that in a good analytic hour, patient and analyst “become both artist and medium for each other,” and he specifically does not differentiate between modalities, as he says, “the progression in such an hour is quite similar to the progression of a work of art, a poem, a musical composition, a painting. . . . propelled by . . . directional tension” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0003065112455361">1975</xref>, p. 369).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0003065112455361">6</xref></sup></p>
<p>Beginning from Loewald, Schachtel, and infant developmentalists, we retain our sense of cross-modality and individual specificity, asking further, What if the global apprehended linguistic-psychoanalytic event involves patient or analyst with particular sensory listings? We wonder how we can expand our understanding of the ways sensory predilections consciously and unconsciously infuse each clinician’s presence in the consulting room, what difference it makes if the medium is by predilection more verbal, visual, tonal, rhythmic, or rooted more in global or specific bodily being. These are questions our panel hopes to illuminate. The participants each consider how their own particularized sensory modality or modalities enter the consulting room and make a difference in their work, just as other aspects of the analyst’s personhood make a difference.</p>
<p>We know structure, Freud told us, by observing how the crystal shatters. So also, we can understand facets of everyone’s sensory experience by listening to those who are aware of and accomplished in one sensory mode or another. Each of the panelists has dual or multiple identities, backgrounds, or interests—creative vocations or avocations that draw on different sensory modalities and sensitivities—and each has also written or taught about bodily presence and bodily states in patient and analyst. Their contributions draw on these dual identities. Jonathan Palmer is a painter who writes that painting is “particularly well-suited to revealing feelings” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0003065112455361">2008</xref>, p. 481). Forrest Hamer is a poet who has also written about psychically and bodily experienced race and racism in the consulting room (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0003065112455361">2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0003065112455361">2006</xref>). In “Listening with Both Ears,” he describes how his two careers complement and reinforce one another: “the poems I author are written by a psychoanalyst, and the psychoanalysis I practice is conducted by a poet” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0003065112455361">2008</xref>, p. 86). Peter Goldberg observes and writes about bodily states with particular acuity and focus; he also plays rhythm and blues piano and is a serious gardener whose palette is his backyard. Susan Yamaguchi is a potter who has written about the relations between her states of mind when throwing pots and when doing clinical work.</p>
<p>Such a range was designed to provide audience members, and now readers, with evocative ways of thinking about themselves in their own clinical work. We have wanted to help ourselves and others to notice what predilections of sense, sound, voice, seeing, word, body, may shape our clinical work. The panelists write about their own sensuous-creative modality in relation to the clinical encounter and their clinical stance, about what they notice themselves noticing, observing, or feeling, and each presents illustrative clinical material. Susan Yamaguchi comments on the panel and conveys something of the alive and engaged tone of the meeting panel itself.</p>
<p>“Analytic Listening and the Five Senses” works toward understanding the role of sensory and somatic modalities in analytic work. We consult colleagues with specifically developed identities and practices in different creative arenas, or with particularly notable grounding in somatic experience and representation. Our goal is to provide an associ-ative basis through which readers, like those who attended the panel, can locate themselves and think about themselves in their own clinical work.</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>Training and Supervising Analyst, Boston Psychoanalytic Institute and Society; faculty, San Francisco Psychoanalytic Center; Lecturer in Psychiatry, Harvard Medical School; Professor of Sociology Emerita and Clinical Faculty Emerita, University of California, Berkeley.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0003065112455361">
<label>1</label>
<p>Our considerations are already sensuously shaped, since listening is by definition aural.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0003065112455361">
<label>2</label>
<p>Sterba quotes the Brill translation, but I have used Strachey.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0003065112455361">
<label>3</label>
<p>Excepting, perhaps, that we attribute, in some cases and especially with some composers, mood (for a psychoanalytic example of such attribution, see, e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0003065112455361">Feder 2004</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0003065112455361">
<label>4</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0003065112455361">Parsons (2001)</xref> reports that Milner taught supervisees that in order “to understand as fully as possible what was happening in their patients, they must be attuned to what they found happening in their own bodies as they listened” (p. 609).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0003065112455361">
<label>5</label>
<p>During the San Francisco meetings at which this panel was presented, nearby museums had exhibitions of the collections of the Stein family and an exhibit on Gertrude Stein herself. At the latter, Stein was quoted on cross-modality: “A writer should write with his eyes and a painter paint with his ears.”</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0003065112455361">
<label>6</label>
<p>Loewald also describes childhood experience in cross-modal terms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0003065112455361">Chodorow 2003</xref>).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Balint</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>Before I was I: Psychoanalysis and the Imagination</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Association Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Balsam</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <source>Women’s Bodies in Psychoanalysis</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baudry</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>The relevance of the analyst’s character and attitudes to his work</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>917</fpage>–<lpage>938</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bonaminio</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The person of the analyst: Interpreting, not interpreting, and countertransference</article-title>. <source>Psychoanalytic Quarterly</source> <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>1105</fpage>–<lpage>1146</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chasseguet-Smirgel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>The Body as Mirror of the World</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Association Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chodorow</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The psychoanalytic vision of Hans Loewald</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Psychoanalysis</source> <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>897</fpage>–<lpage>913</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coltart</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <source>Slouching towards Bethlehem</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dimen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Sexuality, Intimacy, Power</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feder</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Gustav Mahler: A Life in Crisis</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1886</year>). <article-title>Letter to Martha Bernays, January 17</article-title>. In <source>Selected Letters of Sigmund Freud</source>, ed. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>, <year>1960</year>, pp.<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1908</year>). <article-title>Creative writers and day-dreaming</article-title>. <source>Standard Edition</source> <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1914</year>). <article-title>The Moses of Michelangelo</article-title>. <source>Standard Edition</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>“Successful” dissociation, pseudovitality, and inauthentic use of the senses</article-title>. <source>Psychoanalytic Dialogues</source> <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>510</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Fabricated bodies: A model for the somatic false self</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Psychoanalysis</source> <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>823</fpage>–<lpage>840</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Guards at the gate: Race, resistance, and psychic reality</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association</source> <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>1219</fpage>–<lpage>1237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Racism as a transference state: Episodes of racial hostility in the psychoanalytic context</article-title>. <source>Psychoanalytic Quarterly</source> <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Listening with both ears</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Applied Psychoanalytic Studies</source> <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>The Use of the Self</source>. <publisher-loc>Madison, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Universities Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>In search of the mind of the analyst: A progress report</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association</source> <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1035</fpage>–<lpage>1059</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Experiencing language: Some thoughts on poetry and psychoanalysis</article-title>. <source>Psychoanalytic Quarterly</source> <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>683</fpage>–<lpage>700</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kantrowitz</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>The uniqueness of the patient-analyst pair: Approaches for elucidation</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Psychoanalysis</source> <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>873</fpage>–<lpage>904</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kite</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Ideas of influence: The impact of the analyst’s character on the analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychoanalytic Quarterly</source> <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>1075</fpage>–<lpage>1104</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Loewald</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <article-title>Psychoanalysis as an art and the fantasy character of the psychoanalytic situation</article-title>. In <source>Papers on Psychoanalysis</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>, <year>1980</year>, pp. <fpage>352</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Loewald</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Primary process, secondary process, and language</article-title>. In <source>Papers on Psychoanalysis</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>, <year>1980</year>, pp. <fpage>178</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Figures in a landscape</article-title>. In <source>Figures in a Landscape</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McDougall</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <source>Theaters of the Body: A Psychoanalytic Approach to Psychosomatic Illness</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Norton</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Work with patients: The impulse for self-analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychoanalytic Inquiry</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>The Healer’s Bent: Solitude and Dialogue in the Clinical Encounter</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Analytic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1950</year>). <source>On Not Being Able to Paint</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Universities Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Melodies in the mind: The polyphony of mental life</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association</source> <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>649</fpage>–<lpage>662</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>‘The music of what happens’ in poetry and psychoanalysis</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Psychoanalysis</source> <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>979</fpage>–<lpage>994</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Forging an analytic identity through clinical writing</article-title>. <source>Psychoanalytic Inquiry</source> <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>477</fpage>–<lpage>492</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Marion Milner 1900–1998</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Psychoanalysis</source> <volume>82</volume>:<fpage>609</fpage>–<lpage>611</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Raiding the inarticulate: The internal analytic setting and listening beyond countertransference</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Psychoanalysis</source> <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>1441</fpage>–<lpage>1456</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pinsky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Mortal gifts: A two-part essay on the therapist’s mortality: Part 1. Untimely loss</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Academy of Psychoanalysis &amp; Psychodynamic Psychiatry</source> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pinsky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Physic himself must fade: A view of the therapeutic offering through the lens of mortality</article-title>. <source>American Imago</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Between Couch and Piano: Psychoanalysis, Music, Art and Neuroscience</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brunner-Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schachtel</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1947</year>). <article-title>On memory and childhood amnesia</article-title>. In <source>Metamorphosis: On the Development of Affect, Perception, Attention, and Memory</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>, <year>1959</year>, pp. <fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seiden</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>On the “music of thought”: The use of metaphor in poetry and in psychoanalysis</article-title>. <source>Psychoanalytic Psychology</source> <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>638</fpage>–<lpage>644</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sterba</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1965</year>). <article-title>Psychoanalysis and music</article-title>. <source>American Imago</source> <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0003065112455361">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <source>The Interpersonal World of the Infant: A View from Psychoanalysis and Developmental Psychology</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>