<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">VCU</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spvcu</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Visual Culture</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1470-4129</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-2994</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1470412912444230</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1470412912444230</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Events</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Editorial</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name><surname>Guins</surname><given-names>Raiford</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>Juliette</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="editor">
<name><surname>Pui San Lok</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Pui San Lok</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1470412912444230">Middlesex University [email: <email>s.lok@mdx.ac.uk</email>]</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: The Ways of Seeing 40th Anniversary Issue</issue-title>
<fpage>205</fpage>
<lpage>206</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s), 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Five photo essays make up this issue’s Events. <italic>Ways of Selling</italic> is an image sequence compiled in the spirit of Berger and Dibb’s montage of advertising billboard images; Julian Stallabrass takes up the subject of the fourth and last programme of the television series (the seventh and final chapter of the book), to continue the circuitous critique of looking, desiring, and selling, into the realm of subvertising, alighting on minor, incidental moments of sabotage by ‘us as we are now’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1470412912444230">1</xref></sup> Sonia Boyce’s <italic>Performing Being Looked At</italic> directly cites Vertov, as cited in Berger, and indirectly cites Mulvey, in the relay and duplication of eyes and lenses. Here, the mechanical eye rotates around and with its at least doubled subjects, who in turn rotate, watchful and mindful, of contact (sheets) and contracts – the sometime apparently dualistic (black and white?) terms of exchange undercut by playful pops of colour, and castings of and against type (gender, ethnic, and graphic).</p>
<p>The intermingled dreams of advertising and movie industries converge in Ming Wong’s billboards for his video installation, <italic>Life of Imitation</italic> (2010), transposed from slick digital photo-finishes to hand-painted signs, from 1950s Hollywood to 1950s Singapore, and so-called West to East. Shifting centres and perspectives to re-play a pivotal scene in Douglas Sirk’s melodrama, <italic>Imitation of Life</italic> (1959), three male actors from the dominant ethnic groups in Singapore (Chinese, Malay and Indian) alternate the roles of ‘black’ mother and ‘white’ daughter from shot to shot. The discourse of the copy, between multiple renditions of fictive characters and their players, is nuanced by the knowing impersonation and approximation of each subject, engaged in a performative (gender and) racial drag – ‘passing’ for women, ‘passing’ for white, ‘passing’ for black. The mirror as a recurrent motif in melodrama, and its substitute screens, are doubled across all these essays, multiplying and amplifying the artifices and fictions at play.</p>
<p>If notions of essential culture(s) continue to be both refuted and revived, the same might be said of ‘nature’; John Timberlake’s essay alludes to the politics and disavowal of climate change, to pose anew ‘the problem of painting sky and distance’ (p. 105). <italic>The sky has no surface and is intangible …</italic> turns on the productive tensions and contradictions of the text–image/image–text relation, a romantic relation of sense and sensibility, of aspiration and nostalgia. The intangible sky is made tangible, quantified by absences, made quantifiable by the lapses of time that produce a palimpsest of nothings – ‘no surfaces’ – layers of waiting materialized in the grain. If the seemingly nondescript expanse offers another kind of mirror to our interior lives and dreams, the trace of a flight, of jet-propelled eyes in the sky, the yellow corner of sign (a warning? a destination?) together hint at pollutant incursions upon an urban picturesque.</p>
<p>Finally, dislocated from any specific sky or terrain, the blindfolded figures of Broomberg and Chanarin’s <italic>Afterlife</italic> series appear at first to float free of historical and cultural context. Now standing, now prostrate, cut out and pinned against a stark white ground, details of clothing, shades and guns begin to fill in the blanks – somewhere in the Middle East, sometime in the late 1970s – an execution. Then and now, facing violence and death, what are the politics of looking, of watching, or turning the page/changing channels/turning away? ‘The relation between what we see and what we know is never settled’ (p. 7). What do we see now – how are we blinded – and what do we know?</p>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1470412912444230">
<label>1.</label>
<p>All citations (except the first, which references the television script) from: Berger, J. with S. Bloomberg, C. Fox, M. Dibb and R. Hollis (2008[1972]) <italic>Ways of Seeing</italic>. London: BBC/Penguin Books.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
</back>
</article>