<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PMJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppmj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Palliat Med</journal-id>
<journal-title>Palliative Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0269-2163</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-030X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0269216313479843</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0269216313479843</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Prescribing in palliative care A quest for appropriateness</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Toscani</surname><given-names>Franco</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0269216313479843">Lino Maestroni Foundation – Istituto di Ricerca in Medicina Palliativa, Cremona, Italy</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0269216313479843">Lino Maestroni Foundation – Istituto di Ricerca in Medicina Palliativa 1, via Palestro, Cremona 26100, Italy Email: <email>f.toscani@alice.it</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>293</fpage>
<lpage>294</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A drug prescription is usually the conclusion of a complex mental process that requires knowledge, experience and insight. It also involves a degree of risk: doctors and other prescribers can never be absolutely sure that their prescriptions are the most appropriate in each situation, and accept variability and uncertainty as part of the practice of medicine. However, patients expect doctors to prescribe the correct and appropriate medication, and if the drug choice proves incorrect, they expect doctors to justify their prescribing choices and be liable for the consequences of such choices.</p>
<p>The wise doctor probably follows two guides in determining whether a prescription is appropriate: empirical knowledge and the law. When a drug is chosen that research indicates as effective with reasonably mild adverse effects for a given population of patients for a given disease and the procedures required by the law are followed, doctors can reassure themselves that they have done well for their patients and for themselves. It means they have used a registered medication for its specific indication, as written in the approved labelling insert.</p>
<p>In clinical practice, off-label prescriptions (i.e. drugs prescribed at an unlicensed dose or for an unlicensed indication, or administered by an unlicensed route) are quite common but can be rarely reported in the clinical records. They are given in this way in the belief that they will benefit patients who cannot be better helped with alternative on-label drugs. These prescriptions are supposed to be grounded on established clinical knowledge and/or well-known pharmacological principles but often lack supporting evidence, or have only limited evidence of benefit, and may expose patients to unwarranted risk, being associated with more frequent and/or unrecognised adverse reactions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0269216313479843">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>Nevertheless, doctors may lawfully prescribe a drug off-label. In this case, they need to consider the evidence of the effectiveness of that drug for the unlicensed indication and what risks are involved, and patients should be fully informed about this type of medication.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0269216313479843">2</xref></sup> Some off-label prescriptions are supported by research or, at least, biological and pharmacological plausibility, but there are few instructions on how to distinguish those prescriptions supported by evidence and those which are not. Thus, even when they are likely to be safe, caution is essential. In all cases, the ultimate responsibility lies with the prescriber.</p>
<p>In palliative care off-label prescribing can be seen as an issue for four reasons:</p>
<list id="list1-0269216313479843" list-type="simple"><list-item><p>First, the frequency of use: In palliative care, nearly one prescription out of four is off-label, affecting two-thirds of inpatients in palliative care units.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0269216313479843">3</xref></sup> Some drugs are prescribed to take advantage of known side effects, for example, amitriptyline for drooling. Other drugs may be off-label because of the chosen route of administration. For example, subcutaneous administration is helpful in patients at the end of life who may be unable to take oral medication. This is particularly the case for drugs used in syringe drivers, widely used in palliative care in the United Kingdom and Europe, and frequently, in spite of the lack of information on pharmacokinetics, stability and compatibility that often concern drugs officially licensed only for the intravenous (IV) or intramuscular (IM) routes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0269216313479843">4</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Second, lack of research: At present palliation does not seem an appealing market for the pharmaceutical industry, and except for analgesics, research is not oriented to developing, and companies to marketing, new drugs specifically designed for controlling symptoms at the end of life. Even when the official approvals could be updated, the procedure is so expensive and time consuming, or the expiration of a previous registration makes the commercial value of the drug so poor, that pharmaceutical companies have no gain – and hence little interest – in doing it. It is therefore likely that off-label prescriptions will continue to play a part in prescribing in palliative care.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Third, the prescribers’ understanding: Doctors have a poor understanding of the regulations regarding off-label prescribing and the status of the drugs they routinely use.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0269216313479843">5</xref></sup> Palliative care prescribers are no exception: in 2001, poor documentation of reasons for off-label use was found that may suggest an embarrassingly low rate of specific knowledge regarding the level of evidence available and of the possibility of better alternatives.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0269216313479843">2</xref></sup> In any case, being unaware of the nature of the drug used means not being in good standing with both professional and legal duties.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Fourth: informed consent. There is a supposed impracticability of always obtaining informed consent to give a drug ‘off-label’ from someone who is unwell, and can also have reduced cognitive capacity. Doctors working in palliative care may believe that requesting written consent and the giving of information about the drug, and the patient’s condition that necessarily accompanies this, may create additional patient anxiety and suffering. There is also tension between a dislike of bureaucratic formalities that can be seen as distant from the spirit and methods of palliative care, and using this as an alibi for resistance to following legal requirements.</p></list-item></list>
<p>This edition of <italic>Palliative Medicine</italic> reports on two surveys,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0269216313479843">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0269216313479843">7</xref></sup> which add to our knowledge by exploring issues relating to off-label prescribing. These articles are among the few that deal with this topic in palliative care, and explore two different but crucial aspects: prescribers’ knowledge and adherence to current regulatory guidance of independent prescribers.</p>
<p>To et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0269216313479843">6</xref></sup> evaluate the difficulty that palliative care clinicians have in distinguishing between on-label and off-label prescriptions, and examine the clinical, moral and legal implications of such prescribing, outlining the possible approach clinicians, regulatory bodies and policy-makers should adopt to reduce the barriers to approving more suitable indications for the registered drugs. Culshaw et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0269216313479843">7</xref></sup> confirm the prescribers’ resistance to informing patients about the off-label medication they are prescribing, even in a country where the rules on this problem are more pragmatic and flexible than those of other European countries. In particular, they consider the emerging issues engendered by the enabling of a wider range of health professionals (in particular, nurses and pharmacists) to act as supplementary prescribers, and therefore, investing them with the same responsibility and obligations of doctors when dealing with off-label drugs. These studies show that the situation is not substantially changed and should be taken as a model for further research in other countries, in particular in those of the European Community.</p>
<p>Off-label prescribing entails, in reality, only problems of <italic>clinical</italic> appropriateness, and is only one aspect of broader prescribing issues those working in palliative care must address. Equally difficult issues are raised by the ethical, anthropological and epistemological implications of the appropriateness of most on-label medications near the end of life. There are many clinical circumstances when uncertainty of prognosis, and the changing balance between a care/cure dichotomy, makes the choice of whether to commence, continue or discontinue medication<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0269216313479843">8</xref></sup> a complex ethical and ontological issue. This is a crucial problem, as palliative care philosophy and methods are expected to spread into, and to enrich, other medical disciplines.</p>
<p>The appropriateness of off-label prescriptions in palliative care must become clear, simple and safe, as much as any other prescription at the end of life. This is a problem that cannot only be left to national professional organisations, but should be considered at international level: agreed and up-to-date guidelines should be issued asking national regulatory bodies to set formal procedures that are both effective and feasible. Reflection and discussion on this problem must continue, and needs all palliative care professionals to contribute to theory, research and policy in this area.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0269216313479843">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neubert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dormann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of unlicensed and off-label drug use on adverse drug reactions in paediatric patients</article-title>. <source>Drug Saf</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1059</fpage>–<lpage>1067</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0269216313479843">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pavis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prescribing of drugs for use outside their licence in palliative care: survey of specialists in the United Kingdom</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>323</volume>: <fpage>484</fpage>–<lpage>485</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0269216313479843">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirkham</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Unlicensed uses for medication in a palliative care unit</article-title>. <source>Palliat Med</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0269216313479843">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Toscani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Di Giulio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>.; <collab>End of Life Observatory Research Group</collab>. <article-title>Off-label prescriptions in Italian hospices: a national survey</article-title>. <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0269216313479843">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wynia</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moloney</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>U.S. physician knowledge of the FDA-approved indications and evidence base for commonly prescribed drugs: results of a national survey</article-title>. <source>Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1094</fpage>–<lpage>10100</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0269216313479843">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Culshaw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kendall</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Off-label prescribing in palliative care: A survey of independent prescribers</article-title>. <source>Palliat Med</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0269216313479843">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>To</surname><given-names>THM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Agar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shelby-James</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Off-label prescribing in palliative care - a cross-sectional national survey of Palliative Medicine doctors</article-title>. <source>Palliat Med</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>320</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0269216313479843">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayley</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Reconsidering medication appropriateness for patients late in life</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>166</volume>: <fpage>605</fpage>–<lpage>609</lpage>.</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>