<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MDM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmdm</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Med Decis Making</journal-id>
<journal-title>Medical Decision Making</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0272-989X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-681X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0272989X12452342</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0272989X12452342</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Patient Decision Aids and Risk Perception</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Effect of Narrative Reports about Vaccine Adverse Events and Bias-Awareness Disclaimers on Vaccine Decisions</article-title>
<subtitle>A Simulation of an Online Patient Social Network</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Betsch</surname><given-names>Cornelia</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Renkewitz</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Haase</surname><given-names>Niels</given-names></name>
<degrees>Dipl-Psych, MA</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0272989X12452342">Center for Empirical Research in Economics and Behavioral Science, University of Erfurt, Erfurt, Germany</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0272989X12452342">Cornelia Betsch, PhD, Center for Empirical Research in Economics and Behavioral Sciences (CEREB), University of Erfurt, Nordhaeuser Strasse 63, D-99089 Erfurt, Germany; e-mail: <email>cornelia.betsch@uni-erfurt.de</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>33</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Decision Aids and Risk Perception</issue-title>
<fpage>14</fpage>
<lpage>25</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>16</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>31</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<abstract>
<p><bold>Background</bold>. As the number of individuals who search for health information in interactive online environments is increasing, patient networks deserve more scientific attention. <bold>Objective</bold>. To quantitatively examine if and how reading statistical and/or narrative information as typically displayed in patient networks (e.g., <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://patientslikeme.com">patientslikeme.com</ext-link>) affects decisions for pharmaceuticals. Previous work suggests that narrative information (e.g., about vaccine adverse events, VAE) affects risk perceptions and intentions. The authors compare the effect of narrative and statistical information about VAE on vaccination decisions and examine if a disclaimer reduces the narrative bias as well as if low numeracy leads to increased use of the narratives. <bold>Method and Design</bold>. In an online experiment, 458 participants were randomly assigned to a 3 (relative frequency of vaccine adverse events in 1, 7, or 17 of 20 cases) × 3 (type of information: narratives, summary statistics, or both) × 2 (bias awareness v. control disclaimer) between-subjects design. <bold>Measurements</bold>. Perceived risk, vaccination intention, and subjective numeracy. <bold>Results</bold>. A higher relative frequency of cases reporting VAE decreased the intention to get vaccinated. This relation was mediated by increased risk perception. The type of information moderated the contents’ impact: Summary statistics had the smallest impact, whereas narrative information was more influential, and the presence of both types of information had the greatest impact on risk perception. Individuals who received the bias-awareness disclaimer were less influenced by the patient network. Highly numerate individuals were generally more sensitive to the provided information independent of its format. <bold>Conclusions</bold>. Patient networks can influence vaccination decisions by delivering risk-related information. Disclaimers may help to reduce the influence if desired.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Internet</kwd>
<kwd>online social networking</kwd>
<kwd>preventive health behavior</kwd>
<kwd>decision making</kwd>
<kwd>vaccination</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A growing number of people use the Internet to obtain health information,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0272989X12452342">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0272989X12452342"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0272989X12452342">3</xref></sup> such as about pharmaceuticals and their potential side effects (e.g., following vaccinations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0272989X12452342">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0272989X12452342">5</xref></sup>). Websites that allow and promote interaction among users represent a source of health information that is increasing in popularity. Users of such so-called Web 2.0 applications (e.g., social media), although still in the minority, represent a growing proportion of online communicators. Social patient networks (e.g., <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.patientslikeme.com">www.patientslikeme.com</ext-link> [PLM]) provide individuals the opportunity to locate patients with the same ailment, in order “to share their experience using patient-reported outcomes, find other patients like them matched on demographic and clinical characteristics, and learn from the aggregated data reports of others to improve their outcomes.”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0272989X12452342">6</xref></sup> Furthermore, for individuals interested in desired and undesired effects of pharmaceuticals (e.g., off-label prescription, adverse events<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0272989X12452342">7</xref></sup>), these networks may provide easily accessible sources of personal experiences.</p>
<p>In such networks, patients can report, rate, and describe their experiences (e.g., vaccine adverse events [VAEs]) following the seasonal immunization against influenza. Patients who access the website (e.g., search for experiences with a certain vaccine) receive aggregated summary statistics of the ratings provided by other users, which are displayed in a pie chart. The graph indicates the relative frequency of VAEs reported within the network as well as their severity. In addition to viewing the summary statistics, users can also access “individual patient evaluations,” which display lists of individual narrative descriptions of the rated conditions. In the current study, we adopted the design of PLM (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0272989X12452342">Figure 1</xref>, which illustrates the materials used in this study, designed in the PLM style). On PLM, for example, of the 20 individuals who reported about the occurrence or nonoccurrence of adverse events after receiving the seasonal influenza vaccination, 6 individuals reported adverse events, resulting in the presence of VAEs in 30% of cases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.patienslikeme.com">www.patienslikeme.com</ext-link>, accessed 15 February 2012; search term: influenza vaccine). This sample, of course, is not representative but rather highly self-selected and biased. Thus, it is potentially skewed toward individuals with negative experiences with the vaccine or those with chronic conditions, which might have increased the a priori probabilities of the occurrence of adverse events.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0272989X12452342" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sample material designed to be similar to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://patientslikeme.com">patientslikeme.com</ext-link>. (a) Summary statistics and (b) narrative reports (original materials were in German).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0272989X12452342-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In general, scientific evaluations of online patient networks have been quite positive and stress the benefits of such networks. Patients who use PLM more often also report deriving greater benefits. Specifically, self-reports about “how helpful” PLM was revealed that the site helped patients in starting or stopping medication or changing treatment dosages as well as understanding treatment side effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0272989X12452342">6</xref></sup> A qualitative study shows that people interact based on the information provided, give advice to each other, and build networks.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0272989X12452342">8</xref></sup> However, to the best of our knowledge, no study has quantitatively examined if and how information from online patient networks systematically affects decisions regarding pharmaceuticals.</p>
<p>The decision to protect oneself against a health threat can be predicted using a number of theories.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0272989X12452342">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0272989X12452342">10</xref></sup> Most models typically use the perception of the health risk (i.e., of the illness a vaccine protects against) to predict the uptake of protective behavior (vaccination). Perceptions about the risk <italic>given</italic> the preventive action are seldom reported.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0272989X12452342">11</xref></sup> Vaccinations are a special case of preventive health behavior, as they involve the administration of pharmaceutical substances to a healthy organism. The substance may have undesired side effects, as do all medical treatments. Following the same logic of avoiding risks, higher perceived vaccination risk should lead to lower vaccination intentions. Thus, we focus on the perception of vaccination risk as well as whether reading statistical and/or narrative information as typically displayed in an online patient network affects vaccination risk perception and intention to vaccinate.</p>
<p>With this work, we relate directly to recent studies assessing the effect of narrative information on vaccination decisions, in which the existence of narratives about VAEs on websites increased the perceived risk of adverse events.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0272989X12452342">4</xref></sup> Subsequent lab experiments showed that the more narratives that people read, the higher their perception of risk was, regardless of the information contained in simultaneously presented statistical information on the base rate of VAEs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0272989X12452342">5</xref></sup> The perceived risk of VAEs further mediated the relation between the narratives and declining vaccination intentions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0272989X12452342">5</xref></sup> This so-called narrative bias has also been demonstrated in other areas.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0272989X12452342">12</xref></sup> As the underlying mechanisms are still unclear,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0272989X12452342">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0272989X12452342">14</xref></sup> researchers are reluctant to recommend the inclusion of narratives that indirectly mention either the risks or benefits of medical options in health communications (such as decision aids). Given that online patient networks can be considered self-organized, social media–like decision aids, it is especially important to assess their potential impact.</p>
<sec id="section1-0272989X12452342">
<title>Objectives and Hypotheses</title>
<p>The goal of the current study was to explore how the information environment that is typically available in online patient networks—namely, a self-selected sample of patients whose experiences with pharmaceuticals are summarized in a pie chart and described in a narrative way—may influence people’s decisions regarding pharmaceuticals. As a domain, we used reports about VAEs. On the basis of the strong influence of narrative information and the specific set of information provided by PLM, we pose the following hypotheses.</p>
<list id="list1-0272989X12452342" list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Hypothesis 1: We expect that a higher relative frequency of cases reporting VAEs will increase perceived risk of vaccinating.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Hypothesis 2: We expect that the manner in which side effect data are displayed will moderate the effect of the relative frequency of cases reporting VAEs: Perceived risk should be more strongly related to variations in the relative frequency of VAEs when users also read narrative information as compared with users who have access only to statistical summary information (<italic>narrative bias</italic>).</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Hypothesis 3: We assess if a higher relative frequency of cases reporting VAEs decreases the intention to get vaccinated. If so, this effect should be mediated by increased risk perception, as has been shown previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0272989X12452342">5</xref></sup></p>
</list-item>
</list>
<p>When individuals receive information about a source’s lack of reliability and trustworthiness, the impact of the source’s information is reduced immediately by this discounting cue.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0272989X12452342">15</xref></sup> Thus, awareness that the sample of individuals delivering the information is potentially biased should decrease trust in the online patient network as a source of reliable health information. Consequently, we test the following:</p>
<list id="list2-0272989X12452342" list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Hypothesis 4a: When users are made aware of potential sampling biases before encoding information, reports of VAEs should be discounted; in turn, variations in the relative frequency of cases reporting VAEs should have a lesser or even no effect on risk perceptions and vaccination intentions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0272989X12452342">16</xref></sup></p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Hypothesis 4b: As a second discounting cue, we included one condition in which nearly all narratives report the occurrence of VAEs (i.e., 85%). This unreasonably high proportion might also make individuals aware of the highly skewed sample, thus undermining the trustworthiness of the source. We expect that this will reduce the effect of the narratives on risk perceptions and vaccination intentions.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<p>We also explored the role of numeracy, that is, the ability to use and understand numbers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0272989X12452342">17</xref></sup> Previous research has shown that people with low numeracy make suboptimal health decisions and are affected more by biased narrative information than individuals with high numeracy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0272989X12452342">18</xref></sup> We therefore expect the following:</p>
<list id="list3-0272989X12452342" list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Hypothesis 5: Individuals with low numeracy will rely more strongly on narrative as compared with statistical information.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0272989X12452342">
<title>Overview</title>
<p>Participants received detailed information about a fictitious disease: <italic>Dysomerie</italic> was described as highly infectious, transmittable via droplets, and associated with severe symptoms (fever, emesis, meningitis) and long-term risks (palsy). The participants learned that the German Standing Committee on Vaccination (STIKO) recommends vaccination against the illness. An icon array<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0272989X12452342">19</xref></sup> illustrated the base rate of VAEs (20%). Thereafter, participants received information about a fictitious online patient network with a disclaimer either indicating the presence of sampling bias or stressing the importance and value of the single contributions (see below). Participants then read the information presented in the social network. Depending on the condition, the social network presented either narrative reports about postvaccination experiences (with varying percentages of cases reporting VAEs), summary statistics of the same information, or both, in which case the statistical summary preceded the corresponding narratives. After encoding the information, the dependent variables (risk perception, vaccination intention), manipulation checks, descriptive variables, and numeracy were collected.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0272989X12452342" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section4-0272989X12452342">
<title>Design</title>
<p>Participants were recruited via mailing lists and the Internet (Twitter, Facebook, websites related to childhood topics). As an incentive, we raffled off five 25€ (~US $34.50) gift certificates for a large Internet store. In total, 1543 individuals clicked on the link to the study. Of the 953 participants who proceeded to the first page of the survey, 605 completed the study; 147 indicated that they had previously participated in a similar study and were therefore excluded from the sample. Participants were randomly assigned to a 3 (relative frequency of adverse events in 1, 7, or 17 of 20 cases; equaling 5%, 35%, and 85%, respectively) × 3 (type of information: narratives, summary statistics, or both) × 2 (bias awareness v. control disclaimer) between-subjects design.</p>
<p>The information was provided within a simulated social network similar in style to the website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.patientslikeme.com">www.patientslikeme.com</ext-link> (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0272989X12452342">Figure 1</xref>). As in the disclaimer of PLM, the simulated site included the statement that the network provides “access to side effect surveys and treatment evaluations to report your experiences with medications and other treatments you use, including your experiences with adverse events.”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0272989X12452342">20</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0272989X12452342">
<title>Disclaimer</title>
<p>Disclaimers were used to manipulate bias awareness. The bias-awareness disclaimer informed participants that the information provided by the social network may be biased and nonrepresentative due to patient self-selection: “In contrast to results from clinical studies, the patient reports published here are not representative of the experiences of all people who have received the respective medical product. The authors independently registered at the Patientenportal.de and voluntarily reported their experiences without being asked to do so. Therefore, it is possible that a self-selection is present. The published reports represent only the authors’ individual perceptions.” The control disclaimer was copied from PLM and stressed the importance of individual contributions to the network<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0272989X12452342">20</xref></sup>: “While there is much information learned from clinical trials, they do not fully reflect the way a medical product is used in real life. By completing these reports, you can help improve the outcomes and safety of patients by contributing real world safety data to drug manufacturers and regulators.” In both conditions, participants also read that the network does not provide medical advice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0272989X12452342">
<title>Relative frequency of VAE</title>
<p>To assess the impact of the information provided in the social network, we systematically varied the relative frequency of patients in the social network who had experienced VAEs such that it decreased and increased the initially stated base rate (i.e., 20%) by 15% (i.e., 5% and 35%, respectively) and exceeded it remarkably (85%). Thus, depending on condition, 5%, 35%, or 85% of patients reported mild VAEs (e.g., insomnia, fever, rash, emesis; the VAEs used were pretested and ranged between 1.97 and 2.77 on a 1–7 severity scale; unpublished data<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0272989X12452342">*</xref>), whereas the remaining patients reported unproblematic vaccination experiences.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0272989X12452342">
<title>Type of information</title>
<p>In the narratives condition, the vaccination experiences of the patients within the social network were displayed as single narratives, with 4 narratives on 1 of 5 pages; the 5 pages were displayed in random order. Two sets of 5 pages each were created to allow for counterbalancing the sex of patients reporting VAEs. The narratives, both those describing VAEs and those reporting an absence of VAEs, were of equal length (VAE, mean = 18 words; no VAE, mean = 18.5 words). In the narratives condition, 1, 7, or 17 narratives reported VAEs (resulting in relative frequencies of 5%, 35%, and 85%, respectively). In the summary statistics condition, experiences were displayed in a pie chart with 5%, 35%, or 85% colored in orange, indicating the occurrence of mild VAEs; the cases without VAEs were displayed in green. In the third condition, participants first viewed the summary pie chart with 5%, 35%, or 85% VAEs before reading the narratives, which reflected the distribution displayed in the pie chart. This sequence was not counterbalanced, as we aimed to approximate the design and sequence of information provided by PLM.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0272989X12452342">
<title>Dependent variables</title>
<p>Risk was assessed by means of a scroll bar (“How risky do you judge the vaccination against Dysomerie to be?” ranging from 0 = <italic>not at all risky</italic> to 100 = <italic>very risky;</italic> numeric anchors were not visible to participants). Perceived probability was assessed by asking for the numeric percentage of VAEs following vaccinations against Dysomerie. The severity of potential VAEs was rated on a 7-point scale (1 = <italic>not severe;</italic> 7 = <italic>very severe</italic>). Participants’ intentions to get vaccinated against Dysomerie if they had the chance to do so in the upcoming week were rated on a 7-point scale (1 = <italic>definitely not vaccinate;</italic> 7 = <italic>definitely vaccinate</italic>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0272989X12452342">
<title>Manipulation checks and descriptive variables</title>
<p>To assess whether the information contained in the disclaimer increased participants’ awareness of the skewed sample of contributions within the social network, we asked participants which source they trusted more when reading about pharmaceuticals’ risks (1 = <italic>clinical trials;</italic> 7 = <italic>personal reports such as those in the social network</italic>). Participants also judged how representative they considered the reports published in the social network to be (1 = <italic>not at all representative, they provide a biased picture;</italic> 7 = <italic>representative, they correspond to reality</italic>). As additional manipulation checks, we asked participants to recall the initially stated base rate of VAEs as well as the information provided in the social network (narrative, statistical, or both, depending on condition).</p>
<p>Personal e-health routines were assessed with importance ratings (1 = <italic>unimportant;</italic> 5 = <italic>important</italic>) of several sources (health professionals, reference books; books; Internet; courses and lectures; family, friends, and colleagues; pharmacies; newspapers and magazines; and TV/radio<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0272989X12452342">3</xref></sup>); in addition, we asked participants how often they use the Internet to search for health information. We also assessed membership at online patient networks as well as participants’ general attitudes toward vaccination (1 = <italic>totally against vaccination;</italic> 7 = <italic>totally in favor of vaccination</italic>).</p>
<p>
<italic>Numeracy</italic> was assessed via the 8-item subjective numeracy scale, which uses self-report items (e.g., “How good are you at working with percentages?” “How good are you at figuring out how much a shirt will cost if it is 25% off?” with 1 expressing the low numeracy response and 6 expressing the high numeracy response) to assess an individual’s ability to understand and use numbers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0272989X12452342">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0272989X12452342">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0272989X12452342">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0272989X12452342">22</xref></sup> Cronbach’s α was 0.82.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0272989X12452342" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section11-0272989X12452342">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>The sample comprises 458 participants (85.6% female; mean [SD] age 31.71 [8.91], 70% with German Abitur or higher education). Of the participants, 4.5% (<italic>n</italic> = 20) indicated that they were members of an online patient network; 43%, 38%, and 19% use the Internet to search for health information up to once a year, once a month, or on a weekly or daily basis, respectively. The Internet was rated as the fourth most important source overall (mean [SD] 3.62 [1.02]; 95% confidence interval [CI], 3.52–3.72), less important than medical personnel (4.33 [0.88]; 4.25–4.41), medical books or brochures (3.93 [1.01]; 3.83–4.02), and pharmacies (3.78 [1.05]; 3.68–3.87). All other sources were rated as less important than the Internet (e.g., family and friends, etc.). The mean (SD) time required to complete the study was 9.94 (3.49) minutes. Participants had a mean (SD) numeracy of 4.18 (0.95) and were generally more in favor of vaccination than against it (5.57 [1.51]).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0272989X12452342">
<title>Manipulation checks</title>
<p>Following the dependent measures, we assessed the recalled base rate of VAEs that was initially presented to the participants (before the social network information was provided). The majority of participants correctly recalled the base rate (mode = 20; <italic>n</italic> = 349). However, the manipulations within the social network also affected the recalled base rate: The higher the probability of VAEs implied by the reports in the social network, the higher the recalled base rate was (mean [SD] 17.65 [5.81] for the 5% condition, 19.4 [6.9] for 35%, and 25.1 [11.36] for 85%), <italic>F</italic>(2, 455) = 20.34, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p>
<p>When asked for the information provided within the social network setting, participants indicated that they remembered a mean (SD) number of 1.43 (1.8) narratives reporting adverse events (correct answer = 1) in the 5% condition, 7.88 (7.49; correct = 7) in the 35% condition, and 17.04 (10.29; correct = 17) in the 85% condition, <italic>F</italic>(2, 311) = 115.5, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001. Likewise, the recalled statistical information provided by the patient network differed as an effect of the displayed probability, with a mean (SD) of 8.91 (7.79), 25.43 (13.59), and 49.50 (28.92) in the 5%, 35%, and 85% conditions, respectively, <italic>F</italic>(2, 291) = 112.67, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001. Especially in the 85% condition, participants appeared to have difficulties remembering the correct summary statistics. A comparison of the absolute differences between the stated and recalled number of narratives and summary statistics (in the group that received both) shows that deviations were indeed much larger in the summary statistics group, as suggested by the previous findings, <italic>F</italic>(1, 147) = 138.43, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p>
<p>It is possible that the disclaimer requires a high educational level, as it includes concepts such as clinical studies and self-selection. We therefore controlled for education level (Abitur and higher, <italic>n</italic> = 317 v. below Abitur, <italic>n</italic> = 141) in the following analyses: Participants who received the bias-awareness disclaimer perceived patient self-reports as less trustworthy (mean [SD] 2.66 [1.49] v. 3.32 [1.72]; <italic>F</italic>(1, 454) = 14.81, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and judged the information provided in the social network to be less representative (2.89 [1.41] v. 3.32 [1.56]; <italic>F</italic>(1, 454) = 8.11, <italic>P</italic> = 0.01) than participants who received the control disclaimer. Education had a main effect on both variables: Highly educated participants perceived patient self-reports as generally less trustworthy, <italic>F</italic>(1, 454) = 17.47, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, and judged the information provided in the social network to be less representative, <italic>F</italic>(1, 454) = 36.23, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001. Education did not interact with the effect of the bias-awareness disclaimer (<italic>F</italic>s &lt; 1.07).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0272989X12452342">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>In the following, we use regression analyses to test the hypotheses. To assess the effect of information type, we created 2 dummy variables with the summary statistics as the reference group. In the following, we will refer to the 2 variables as “narrative information” (= 1, rest = 0) and “summary statistics plus narratives” (= 1, rest = 0). For all regression analyses, we centered predictors and created interaction terms by multiplying the respective predictors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0272989X12452342">23</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0272989X12452342">
<title>Risk perception</title>
<p>In a regression analysis, the following variables predicted the perceived risk of VAEs: relative frequency of cases reporting VAEs, information types used to communicate these frequencies, bias-awareness disclaimer, interactions between the relative frequency of the cases and information types, and the interaction between relative frequency and the disclaimer (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0272989X12452342">Table 1</xref>; <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.19). The higher the relative frequency of cases that reported VAEs, the higher the perceived risk of VAEs was (hypothesis 1); this relation was weakest when cases were displayed as a summary statistic (<italic>r</italic> between risk and relative frequency = 0.27, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), stronger when vaccination experiences were communicated by narratives (<italic>r</italic> = 0.44, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), and strongest when both types of information were provided (<italic>r</italic> = 0.48, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). This pattern of results confirms hypothesis 2 and is mirrored by the interaction terms of the types of information and relative frequency (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0272989X12452342">Figure 2</xref>). Participants who received the bias-awareness disclaimer were less sensitive to variations in the relative frequency of cases that reported VAEs, as indicated by the disclaimer × relative frequency interaction (hypothesis 4a): In the presence of a bias-awareness disclaimer, perceived risk correlated with relative frequency at <italic>r</italic> = 0.34, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; in the presence of a control disclaimer, the correlation was <italic>r</italic> = 0.46, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 (Fisher’s <italic>z</italic> = −1.52, <italic>P</italic> = 0.06).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0272989X12452342" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Regression Analysis</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0272989X12452342" xlink:href="10.1177_0272989X12452342-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Perceived Risk, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.19<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Probability Change, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.14<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Intention, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.083<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Predictors</th>
<th align="center">B</th>
<th align="center">SE</th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center">B</th>
<th align="center">SE</th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center">B</th>
<th align="center">SE</th>
<th align="center">β</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>37.277</td>
<td>1.071</td>
<td/>
<td>6.061</td>
<td>0.848</td>
<td/>
<td>3.891</td>
<td>0.086</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Relative frequency of cases reporting VAE (5%, 35%, 85%)</td>
<td>10.008</td>
<td>1.073</td>
<td>0.398<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0272989X12452342">*</xref></td>
<td>6.406</td>
<td>0.849</td>
<td>0.331<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0272989X12452342">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.476</td>
<td>0.086</td>
<td>−0.252<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0272989X12452342">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Narrative information</td>
<td>−2.058</td>
<td>1.258</td>
<td>−0.082</td>
<td>0.964</td>
<td>0.996</td>
<td>0.050</td>
<td>0.055</td>
<td>0.101</td>
<td>0.029</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Summary statistics plus narratives</td>
<td>−2.458</td>
<td>1.260</td>
<td>−0.098<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0272989X12452342">**</xref></td>
<td>0.785</td>
<td>0.998</td>
<td>0.041</td>
<td>0.079</td>
<td>0.101</td>
<td>0.042</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Disclaimer (1 = bias awareness; 2 = control)</td>
<td>1.361</td>
<td>1.073</td>
<td>0.054</td>
<td>2.153</td>
<td>0.849</td>
<td>0.111<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0272989X12452342">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.059</td>
<td>0.086</td>
<td>−0.031</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Interaction of relative frequency of cases × narratives</td>
<td>2.414</td>
<td>1.251</td>
<td>0.096<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0272989X12452342">**</xref></td>
<td>1.137</td>
<td>0.990</td>
<td>0.059</td>
<td>−0.084</td>
<td>0.100</td>
<td>−0.044</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Interaction of relative frequency of cases × summary statistics and narratives</td>
<td>2.504</td>
<td>1.260</td>
<td>0.098<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0272989X12452342">*</xref></td>
<td>0.749</td>
<td>0.997</td>
<td>0.038</td>
<td>−0.200</td>
<td>0.101</td>
<td>−0.104<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0272989X12452342">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Interaction of relative frequency of cases × disclaimer</td>
<td>1.932</td>
<td>1.074</td>
<td>0.077<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0272989X12452342">**</xref></td>
<td>1.808</td>
<td>0.850</td>
<td>0.093<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0272989X12452342">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.164</td>
<td>0.086</td>
<td>−0.086<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0272989X12452342">**</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0272989X12452342">
<p>VAE, vaccine adverse event.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0272989X12452342">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05. **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.07.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig2-0272989X12452342" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Perceived risk as a function of the relative frequency of cases reporting vaccine adverse events (VAEs) and type of information displaing the relative frequency.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0272989X12452342-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0272989X12452342">
<title>Numeracy</title>
<p>To assess whether the ability to understand and use numbers affected risk judgments, we included numeracy in the regression analyses reported above in addition to the following interactions: the interaction with the relative frequency of cases reporting VAEs to assess whether highly numerate participants’ risk judgments reflected the variations in relative frequency differently than those of less-numerate participants, as well as 3-way interactions with the different types of information to assess whether highly numerate participants’ risk judgments were affected more strongly by the summary statistics than those of less-numerate participants.</p>
<p>The pattern reported above remained stable. The effect of the relative frequency of cases reporting VAEs on perceived risk was greater for participants with high numeracy (interaction β = 0.09, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <italic>r</italic> = 0.48, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 for high numeracy and <italic>r</italic> = 0.30, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 for low numeracy; Fisher’s <italic>z</italic> = −2.26, <italic>P</italic> = 0.01), irrespective of information type (no significant 3-way interactions, which yields no support for hypothesis 5; <italic>P</italic>s &gt; 0.25). The results remained the same when controlling for level of education, which can be seen as a proxy for general literacy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0272989X12452342">
<title>Probability change</title>
<p>We assessed both the perceived probability and the recalled initial base rate of VAEs. The difference between the 2 variables represents the estimated effect of the patient network information on perceived risk. We subjected this difference score to the same regression model reported above (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0272989X12452342">Table 1</xref>). The relative frequency of cases reporting VAEs was related to changes in the perceived probability; more cases led to higher probability judgments. Participants who received the bias-awareness disclaimer showed a smaller effect of the patient network information—their perception of probability was influenced less by the relative frequency of cases reporting VAEs (correlation between probability change and relative frequency for participants with bias disclaimer: <italic>r</italic> = 0.27, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; control disclaimer: <italic>r</italic> = 0.39, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). All other predictors did not influence changes in the recalled probability of VAEs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0272989X12452342">
<title>Intention to get vaccinated</title>
<p>The mean intention varied around the scale’s midpoint (mean [SD] 3.9 [1.89]; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0272989X12452342">Figure 3</xref>) and followed the same pattern as risk perception (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.083). This provides support for hypothesis 3 (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0272989X12452342">Table 1</xref>). The higher the relative frequency of cases that reported VAEs, the lower the intention to get vaccinated was. This relation was weakest when cases were displayed as a summary statistic (<italic>r</italic> between intention and relative frequency = −0.14, <italic>ns</italic>), stronger when vaccination experiences were communicated in narratives (<italic>r</italic> = −0.254, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), and strongest when both types of information were provided (<italic>r</italic> = −0.351, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). In addition, in the presence of a bias-awareness disclaimer, vaccination intentions correlated with relative frequency at <italic>r</italic> = −0.17 (<italic>ns</italic>); in the presence of a control disclaimer, the correlation was <italic>r</italic> = −0.33, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0272989X12452342">Figure 3</xref>). Thus, vaccination intentions were influenced to a lesser extent by the risk information provided in the patient network when a bias-awareness disclaimer was present.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0272989X12452342" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Intention to vaccinate as a function of the relative frequency of cases reporting vaccine adverse events (VAEs) and disclaimer type.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0272989X12452342-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0272989X12452342">
<title>Mediation analysis</title>
<p>In a mediation analysis, we assessed whether the effect of patient information on the occurrence of VAEs on vaccination intentions was mediated by risk perception (hypothesis 3<sup>5</sup>). We calculated 2 models (displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0272989X12452342">Figure 4</xref>). In model 1, the perceived risk fully mediated the relation between information about VAEs and intention (Sobel test <italic>z</italic> = 4.764, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). In model 2, we explored the effects of risk information on 2 constituents of risk: the perceived probability and expected severity of VAEs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0272989X12452342">24</xref></sup> A great number of cases reporting VAEs resulted in an especially large increase in the recalled probability of VAEs as well as the expected severity of adverse events. Perceived risk was strongly predicted by the perceived severity of adverse events.</p>
<fig id="fig4-0272989X12452342" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mediation models testing hypothesis 2. VAE, vaccine adverse event. M indicates a significant mediation effect. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0272989X12452342-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0272989X12452342" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The goal of this contribution was to explore the effect of anecdotal information regarding adverse events. Such information is readily available through patient social networks. We assessed whether patient experiences summarized in narratives and statistics have the potential to influence vaccine decisions by influencing risk perceptions. The data confirmed our first hypothesis that a higher relative frequency of cases reporting VAEs increases perceived vaccination risk. The type of information moderated the contents’ impact: Summary statistics had the smallest impact, whereas narrative information was more influential, and the presence of both types of information had the greatest impact on risk perception (hypothesis 2). The relative number of cases reporting VAEs also decreased intentions to get vaccinated. As expected, this relation was mediated by increased risk perception (hypothesis 3).</p>
<p>Although all participants received the same initial information about the base rate of adverse events, perceived risk varied according to the personal reports provided by other people in the patient network. The results show that summary statistics influence risk judgments. However, narrative information was more influential than statistical information and most influential when combined with summary statistics. It is possible that receiving both the narratives and summary statistics leads to enhanced encoding and easier recall of the relative number of VAEs. However, the data suggest that this was not the case, as participants in the condition with both summary statistics and narratives did not recall the number of narratives more accurately than those who viewed only the narratives without the statistical summary (<italic>F</italic> &lt; 1). Furthermore, the time elapsed between encoding the initial statistics and the assessment of the dependent variables was greatest in the combined condition, which could impede the correct recall of the initial base rate information (20% VAE). However, participants in this condition did not show poorer recall of the initial statistics, <italic>F</italic> &lt; 1. Thus, it appears that, overall, the narrative information was encoded better than the statistical information, as is already apparent in the manipulation check data.</p>
<p>The reported results add to the growing body of evidence on the <italic>narrative bias</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0272989X12452342">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0272989X12452342">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0272989X12452342">14</xref></sup> (i.e., that narrative information can bias risk judgments even when base rate information is also presented). To illustrate the impact of narrative information, we calculated the relative frequency of adverse events necessary to shift the intention from “rather vaccinate” (&gt;4) to “rather not vaccinate” (&lt;4). When the relative frequency was communicated in the form of statistical information, 35.7% of the reported sample must have experienced adverse events for participants to shift their intentions from vaccinating to not vaccinating. When communicated in the form of narratives, the relative frequency need only be 25.5% for participants to change their intentions (i.e., roughly 10% fewer cases than when using statistical information). Previous research suggests that narratives that are formulated in a more emotional way (than the ones used in this study) are likely to be even more influential.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0272989X12452342">5</xref></sup> Thus, the effect size estimates of the relative frequency of narratives may be considered rather conservative. Furthermore, the mediation analysis indicated that perceived severity influences risk perceptions to an even greater extent than the perceived probability of adverse events. Therefore, narratives presenting cases with high severity are likely to be more influential than the narratives reporting mild VAEs used in the current study.</p>
<p>The relative frequency of cases reporting VAEs was varied systematically such that it decreased and increased the stated initial probability (i.e., 20%) by 15% (i.e., 5% and 35%) and exceeded it remarkably (85%). The effect of narratives was not symmetric: In the 5% condition, the mean (SD) deviation of the probability judgment from the recalled initial probability was −1.42 (11.64), whereas it was 4.43 (12.67) in the 35% condition. Thus, even though the narratives deviated equally from the initial probability in terms of relative frequency, perceived risk did not decrease in the 5% condition as much as it increased in the 35% condition. This is in line with findings that suggest that individuals trust information stating the presence of risk more than they trust information stating an absence of risk.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0272989X12452342">25</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0272989X12452342"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0272989X12452342">27</xref></sup> On the basis of this finding, future studies should assess whether patient networks are more likely to increase rather than decrease risk perceptions.</p>
<p>We included the 85% condition to assess whether participants perceive exceptionally high deviations from the initial base rate statistics to be invalid and discount them as a result (hypothesis 4b). The reported results show that perceived risk increased from the 35% to the 85% condition, thus contradicting the idea that the exceptionally frequent reports were discounted. In line with this finding, there was also no relation between trusting narratives v. clinical trials and the relative frequency of cases reporting adverse events (<italic>r</italic> = 0.06, <italic>P</italic> = 0.21). Thus, even though the 85% condition strongly exceeded the initial probability of VAEs, participants took the information seriously and integrated it into their judgments.</p>
<p>Contrary to hypothesis 5 and previous findings,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0272989X12452342">18</xref></sup> risk perceptions of individuals with low numeracy were not affected more strongly by the narrative information than were those of highly numerate individuals. Rather, in this study, highly numerate individuals were generally more sensitive to the provided information independent of its format. As the results remained the same when we controlled for education level (as a proxy for general literacy), we assume that the effect is not the result of highly numerate individuals’ higher general literacy. Even though recent findings indicate that highly numerate individuals can make better use of provided health information,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0272989X12452342">17</xref></sup> the results of the present study raise the question whether higher numeracy is always advantageous. The provided patient network information (5%, 35%, 85%) deviated from the initially stated 20% VAE and, therefore, biased the judgments of highly numerate individuals more strongly than of those of less-numerate individuals. One potential speculative explanation might be that highly numerate individuals processed the information without assessing its validity, perhaps because they felt more ease in processing the information than individuals with low numeracy. Future research should test the hypothesis whether the ease (or fluency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0272989X12452342">28</xref></sup>) with which information is processed (due to high or low numeracy) has an influence on the degree to which individuals trust the information. A feeling of disfluency (due to low numeracy) may induce a more critical mind-set,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0272989X12452342">29</xref></sup> thus resulting in a lesser influence of unreliable information.</p>
<p>Half of the participants received a bias-awareness disclaimer informing them about potential biases in the sample delivering the information. We expected that such a disclaimer would reduce or eliminate the effect of the information provided in the patient network (hypothesis 4a). Analyses showed that individuals who received the bias-awareness disclaimer were less sensitive to variations in the relative frequency of cases reporting VAEs and that their vaccination intentions were influenced less by the risk information provided in the patient network. However, the effect was rather weak, despite the fact that individuals who read the bias-awareness disclaimer had less trust in the patient reports and considered the information to be less representative than participants who read the control disclaimer. It seems that participants did not completely discount the information provided by the network but instead attributed it less weight in their judgments. Future research should assess whether— despite the partial discounting of the information at the time of the judgment—the encoded information gains more weight over time, as suggested by research on the sleeper effect.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0272989X12452342">15</xref></sup> This will help assess the potential (long-term) benefits of disclaimers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0272989X12452342">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>A number of possible limitations to the results should be noted. First, we employed a hypothetical scenario and collected self-report data with regard to vaccination intentions. Thus, responses were without consequences for the participants and might therefore have limited external validity. Furthermore, individual perceptions of the illness were not assessed (such as perceived severity or personal susceptibility). According to several theories of protective health behavior,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0272989X12452342">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0272989X12452342">10</xref></sup> these constructs also affect the intention for protective behavior. As a consequence, the results regarding the vaccination intention should be viewed cautiously. Future research should strive to move to the realm of real-life decisions, assess the full set of variables relevant to predict behavior, and follow up on actual behavior. If this is unfeasible due to financial or ethical constraints, settings could be created in such a way that biased answers are somehow costly for participants (e.g., by reducing the chances of monetary rewards in proportion to the reported bias), thereby creating a more robust test of the observed effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0272989X12452342">30</xref></sup></p>
<p>Second, 2 apparent core properties of social networks were missing from the simulated patient network in our study’s design: actual membership and interactivity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0272989X12452342">31</xref></sup> Known and trusted sources of information are more likely to affect attitudes and behavior,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0272989X12452342">32</xref></sup> and membership appears to be a prerequisite for developing knowledge of and trust in other members of a network. This limitation suggests that the effect sizes in this study might be conservative due to lacking membership and subsequently low trust. However, much of the information on PLM is also available for nonmembers and certainly has the advantage of being authored by “people like me” as opposed to an official source. “People like me” may be seen as credible, trustworthy, and lacking an additional agenda.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0272989X12452342">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0272989X12452342">34</xref></sup> Although active participation is essential for developing virtual relationships and experiencing social support,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0272989X12452342">35</xref></sup> simply reading others’ reports led to an equally high reception of information in online patient support groups.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0272989X12452342">36</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0272989X12452342">
<title>Implications</title>
<p>One positive aspect of patient networks that has not yet been discussed may be that narratives reporting the <italic>absence</italic> of adverse events are published online, which, to date, occurs only occasionally.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0272989X12452342">37</xref></sup> Narratives about the absence of adverse events will allow users who search for narrative information (e.g., parents who already perceive high vaccination risks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0272989X12452342">38</xref></sup>) to receive a more balanced picture of what might occur following vaccination.</p>
<p>As the number of individuals who search for health information in interactive online environments is increasing, patient networks represent an important environment that deserves more scientific attention. The present research suggests that patient networks may be influential in terms of medication decisions, as they deliver narrative and statistical information about risk. Future research should assess whether changes in perceptions of risk due to patient network information may be the driver for reported changes in dosage, medications, or doctors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0272989X12452342">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0272989X12452342"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0272989X12452342">8</xref></sup> Furthermore, disclaimers referring to potential biases in the samples underlying the shared data seem useful in real patient networks, especially because humans are not naturally sensitive to sampling biases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0272989X12452342">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0272989X12452342">40</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>This research was financed by a grant to the first author from the German Science Foundation (DFG, grant number BE 3970/4-1). The authors are grateful to Philipp Schmid and Elisa Herbert for their support in setting up the study material and programming the questionnaire and to Heather Fuchs for comments on a previous version of the manuscript. They also gratefully acknowledge <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sparba">http://www.sparba</ext-link> by.de, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.urbia.de">http://www.urbia.de</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.netdoktor.de">http://www.netdoktor.de</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.onmeda">http://www.onmeda</ext-link>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.medizinfo.de">http://www.medizinfo.de</ext-link> for posting a link to the study on their websites, blogs, discussion boards, or via Twitter.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0272989X12452342">
<label>*</label>
<p>Pretest: 31 participants rated 66 medical conditions on a 7-point rating scale with the verbal anchors <italic>not severe</italic> and <italic>very severe</italic>. The conditions we selected were rash, fever, emesis, dizziness, restlessness, and insomnia. Their mean scores did not differ significantly from values of either 2 or 3.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0272989X12452342">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Harris Interactive</collab>. <article-title>The Growing Influence and Use of Health Care Information Obtained Online</article-title>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harris Interactive</publisher-name>; September 2011 [<access-date>cited 28 November 2011</access-date>]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.harrisinteractive.com/vault/HI-Harris-Poll-Cyberchondriacs-2011-09-15.pdf">http://www.harrisinteractive.com/vault/HI-Harris-Poll-Cyberchondriacs-2011-09-15.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0272989X12452342">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. The Engaged e-Patient Population. Washington, DC: Pew Internet &amp; American Life Project; <month>August</month> <year>2008</year> [cited <day>28</day> <month>November</month> <year>2011</year>]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pewinternet.org/Reports/2008/The-Engaged-Epatient-Population.aspx">http://www.pewinternet.org/Reports/2008/The-Engaged-Epatient-Population.aspx</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0272989X12452342">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kummervold</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chronaki</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lausen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>eHealth trends in Europe 2005–2007: a population-based survey</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e42</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0272989X12452342">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Betsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Renkewitz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Betsch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ulshöfer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The influence of vaccine-critical websites on perceiving vaccination risks</article-title>. <source>J Health Psychol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>446</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0272989X12452342">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Betsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ulshöfer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Renkewitz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Betsch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The influence of narrative vs. statistical information on perceiving vaccination risks</article-title>. <source>Med Decis Making</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>742</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0272989X12452342">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wicks</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Massagli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Sharing health data for better outcomes on PatientsLikeMe</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e19</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0272989X12452342">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Okun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heywood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wicks</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Patient-reported outcomes as a source of evidence in off-label prescribing: analysis of data from PatientsLikeMe</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e6</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0272989X12452342">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Massagli</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Social uses of personal health information within PatientsLikeMe, an online patient community: what can happen when patients have access to one another’s data</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e15</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0272989X12452342">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Van der Pligt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Risk perception and self- protective behavior</article-title>. <source>Eur Psychol</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0272989X12452342">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Testing four competing theories of health-protective behavior</article-title>. <source>Health Psychol</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>324</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0272989X12452342">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gerrard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCaul</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analysis of the relationship between risk perception and health behavior: the example of vaccination</article-title>. <source>Health Psychol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0272989X12452342">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fagerlin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ubel</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reducing the influence of anecdotal reasoning on people’s health care decisions: is a picture worth a thousand statistics?</article-title> <source>Med Decis Making</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>398</fpage>–<lpage>405</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0272989X12452342">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Winterbottom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bekker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Does narrative information bias individual’s decision making? A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>2079</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0272989X12452342">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hinyard</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kreuter</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Using narrative communication as a tool for health behavior change: a conceptual, theoretical, and empirical overview</article-title>. <source>Health Health Educ Behav</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>777</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0272989X12452342">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kumkale</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albarracín</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The sleeper effect in persuasion: a meta-analytic review</article-title>. <source>Psychol Bull</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>130</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0272989X12452342">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pratkanis</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenwald</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leippe</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baumgardner</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>In search of reliable persuasion effects, III: the sleeper effect is dead: long live the sleeper effect</article-title>. <source>J Pers Soc Psychol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0272989X12452342">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reyna</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dieckmann</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>How numeracy influences risk comprehension and medical decision making</article-title>. <source>Psychol Bull</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>943</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0272989X12452342">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dieckmann</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slovic</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The use of narrative evidence and explicit likelihood by decision makers varying in numeracy</article-title>. <source>Risk Anal</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1473</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0272989X12452342">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>Pictograph Generator</collab>. Available from: at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cbssm.org/research_tools/pictographs">http://cbssm.org/research_tools/pictographs</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0272989X12452342">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>PatientsLikeMe</collab>. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.patientslikeme.com">http://www.patientslikeme.com</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0272989X12452342">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fagerlin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zikmund-Fisher</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ubel</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jankovic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Derry</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Measuring numeracy without a math test: development of the Subjective Numeracy Scale (SNS)</article-title>. <article-title>Med Decis Making</article-title>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>672</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0272989X12452342">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siegrist</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of risk communication formats on risk perception depending on numeracy</article-title>. <source>Med Decis Making</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0272989X12452342">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aiken</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>West</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Multiple Regression: Testing and Interpreting Interactions</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage;</publisher-name> <year>1991</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0272989X12452342">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The risk construct</article-title>. <publisher-loc>In</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yates JF, ed. RiskTaking Behavior. Oxford, UK</publisher-name>: John Wiley; <year>1991</year>. p <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0272989X12452342">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Siegrist</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cvetkovich</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Better negative than positive? Evidence of a bias for negative information about possible health dangers</article-title>. <source>Risk Anal</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0272989X12452342">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pahl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buehner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Trust in risky messages: the role of prior attitudes</article-title>. <source>Risk Anal</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0272989X12452342">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Betsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sachse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Debunking vaccination myths: strong risk negations can increase perceived vaccination risks</article-title>. <source>Health Psychol</source>. <year>2012</year> Mar 12. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0272989X12452342">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oppenheimer</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The secret life of fluency</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn Sci</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0272989X12452342">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alter</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oppenheimer</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Uniting the tribes of fluency to form a metacognitive nation</article-title>. <source>Pers Soc Psychol Rev</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0272989X12452342">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hertwig</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ortmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Experimental practices in economics: a methodological challenge for psychologists?</article-title> <source>Behav Brain Sci</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0272989X12452342">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sevdalis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Lay vaccination narratives on the web: are they worth worrying about?</article-title> <source>Med Decis Making</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>707</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0272989X12452342">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abroms</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Obama’s Wired Campaign: lessons for public health communication</article-title>. <source>J Health Commun</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0272989X12452342">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McAteer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Michie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Beliefs underlying UK parents’ views towards MMR promotion interventions: a qualitative study</article-title>. <source>Psychol Health Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0272989X12452342">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haase</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Betsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Parents Trust Other Parents: Lay Vaccination Narratives on the Web May Create Doubt About Vaccination Safety</article-title>. In press. Medical Decision Making.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0272989X12452342">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leimeister</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schweizer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leimeister</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krcmar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Do virtual communities matter for the social support of patients? Antecedents and effects of virtual relationships in online communities</article-title>. <source>Inform Tech People</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>350</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0272989X12452342">
<label>36.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van Uden-Kraan</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drossaert</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seydel</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van de Laar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Self-reported differences in empowerment between lurkers and posters in online patient support groups</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e18</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0272989X12452342">
<label>37.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Betsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brocard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Opportunities and Challenges of Web 2.0 for Vaccination Decisions</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>25</issue>):<fpage>3727</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0272989X12452342">
<label>38.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Betsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Renkewitz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Langfristige Auswirkungen einer Informationssuche auf impfkritischen Internetseiten</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Long-term effects of an information search on vaccine-critical Internet sites</trans-title>]. <source>Prävention</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. English version available from first author.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0272989X12452342">
<label>39.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brinkmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Betsch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wild</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A sampling approach to biases in conditional probability judgments: beyond base rate neglect and statistical format</article-title>. <source>J Exp Psychol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0272989X12452342">
<label>40.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kahneman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tversky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>On the psychology of prediction</article-title>. <source>Psychol Rev</source>. <year>1973</year>;<volume>80</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>