<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SIR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsir</journal-id>
<journal-title>Studies in Religion/Sciences Religieuses</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0008-4298</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2042-0587</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0008429813491188t</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0008429813491188t</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews / Comptes rendus</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>God, Sex and Gender: An Introduction</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>John R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0008429813491188t"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0008429813491188t">Department of Philosophy, Carleton University</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Environmentalism as Religion: A Fruitful Concept?</issue-title>
<fpage>419</fpage>
<lpage>420</lpage>
<product>
<source>God, Sex and Gender: An Introduction</source> <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Thatcher</surname>
<given-names>Adrian</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <publisher-loc>Chichester, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>. xii + <page-count count="271"/> pp.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) / Le(s) auteur(s), 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The Canadian Corporation for Studies in Religion</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Written as a text for post-secondary courses, this book aims to provide “a comprehensive and consistent theological understanding of sexuality and gender, which is broad, contemporary, undogmatic, questioning, inclusive, and relevant to readers’ interests, needs, and experience” (xi). It includes questions and comments (i.e., answers) as well as suggested activities to help students assimilate the subject matter.</p>
<p>Part one (of five) explains the meanings of “sex,” “gender” and “theology.” The author contends that for most of Christian history there was just one sex – man – which included females, who were considered inferior, as well as superior males. Gender was a continuum from masculinity to effeminacy to femininity. Theology has four sources: Scripture, tradition, reason and experience. Interpretations of the first two need to be consistent with the other two.</p>
<p>Part two contains a theological analysis of sex. While being realistic about the danger of excessive lust, it cites the Song of Songs in favor of a positive appreciation of sexual desire and criticizes the New Testament passages that value virginity over marriage. Several theological metaphors are used to characterize marriage, including covenant, Trinitarian relationships and eucharist. In his questions and comments in this section, the author admits that his readers are unlikely to find these metaphors convincing.</p>
<p>Part three deals with theology and gender. It describes God as neither male nor female and “Christ’s human nature [as] not humanity in its male form, but humanity as such” (124). So there is no good theological reason for women to be excluded from the priesthood. In applying the concept of the body of Christ to gender relations, the author resorts to provocative language such as “when members of Christ’s body have sex with their partners, <italic>Christ has sex with them as well!</italic>” (136), “Does the body of Christ have breasts?” (142) and “Does the body of Christ have balls?” (142).</p>
<p>Part four analyzes same-sex love. It considers the theological reasons for the traditional prohibition of same-sex relationships, including marriage, to be at best problematic, and in the author’s view quite inadequate. Part five deals with virginity, celibacy and chastity. It argues that all the reasons for the R.C. teaching on contraception are unconvincing. Against the traditional Christian teaching that the satisfaction of sexual desire should take place only in marriage, the author proposes “a third, intermediate state of life between singleness and marriage. … straight people on their way to marriage may be free to have contracepted sex” (209). The former custom of betrothal should be revived to legitimate this intermediate state.</p>
<p>Despite its claim to comprehensiveness, the book has some important omissions. There is no mention of the social sciences, especially sociology and psychology, or medical sciences such as psychoanalysis as resources for two of the sources of theology, reason and experience. Non-marital sexual activities and relationships are hardly mentioned, even though the author “take[s] for granted that all readers, with the exception of one or two saints, and one or two liars, will have had sex before they marry” (212), and there is no analysis of divorce and remarriage.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>John R. Williams</sig>
<sig>Department of Philosophy, Carleton University</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>