<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RME</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sprme</journal-id>
<journal-title>Recherche et Applications en Marketing (English Edition)</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2051-5707</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2051-5707</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2051570713487480</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2051570713487480</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The impact of telepresence in an online ad on forming attitudes towards the product: The relevance of the traditional experiential approach</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Debbabi</surname><given-names>Sana</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-2051570713487480">IUT of Tours, VALLOREM (EA6296), François Rabelais University-Tours, France</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Baile</surname><given-names>Serge</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-2051570713487480">TBS, Toulouse University &amp; Aix Marseille University, IAE Aix en Provence, CERGAM (EA 4225), France</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>des Garets</surname><given-names>Véronique</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff3-2051570713487480">IAE of Tours, VALLOREM (EA6296), François Rabelais University-Tours, France</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Roehrich</surname><given-names>Gilles</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff4-2051570713487480">CERAG UMR 5820 - IAE, University Grenoble Alpes, France</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-2051570713487480">Sana Debbabi, Associate Professor, IUT of Tours – François Rabelais University–Tours, 29, Rue du Pont Volant 37082 Tours, France. Email: <email>sana.debbabi@univ-tours.fr</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>24</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Association Française du Marketing</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This study proposes a conceptual model for understanding the impact of telepresence in an online ad on the process of forming attitudes towards the product. The model takes the traditional experiential approach as its frame of reference. It formulates two interdependent attitude formation processes in a telepresence situation: the first cognitive, the second affective. The model is tested by means of a quasi-experiment. The results confirm the hypotheses of direct and indirect causality among the variables comprising the two processes. This causal analysis allows us to carry out a conceptual diagnosis and to make various recommendations.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>3D advertising</kwd>
<kwd>attitude towards the product</kwd>
<kwd>role taking</kwd>
<kwd>telepresence</kwd>
<kwd>virtual direct experience</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-2051570713487480" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>In the marketing literature, direct experience, i.e. ‘consumer’s first usage experience with a product’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr100-2051570713487480">Singh et al., 2000</xref>) has always been considered to have a greater effect than indirect experience (from advertising or word of mouth) on the formation of strong beliefs and attitudes towards the product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-2051570713487480">Berger and Mitchell, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-2051570713487480">Marks and Kamins, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr104-2051570713487480">Smith and Swinyard, 1983</xref>). While virtual experience is similar to indirect experience because they are both produced via media, virtual experience becomes similar to direct experience through the web’s capacity to provide a virtual reality for different types of applications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2002</xref>). The implementation of new interactive technologies for display in three dimensions (3D) enables this virtual experience and points to a greater impact on the formation of consumers’ beliefs and attitudes toward a product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-2051570713487480">Hand, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-2051570713487480">Hughes et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-2051570713487480">Mirapaul, 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>The study of the impact of the display format on consumer responses is increasingly attracting the attention of marketing researchers. 3D advertising is valued for its capacity to arouse telepresence in the consumer in virtual environments, where telepresence is defined as ‘the experience of presence in a virtual environment by means of communication technologies’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-2051570713487480">Steuer, 1992</xref>: 76). Exposure to 3D advertising thus allows consumers to ‘surrender’ to this environment and to look at products and obtain knowledge about them without going to a store. New experience of a product, so-called virtual experience, can thus arise (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-2051570713487480">Edwards and Gangadharbatla, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-2051570713487480">Jiang and Benbasat, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-2051570713487480">Klein, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>In the context of television advertising, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnis and Jaworski (1989)</xref> introduced the concept of ‘role-taking’ defined as ‘an experience in which the individual places the self into the ad or product experience’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">1989</xref>:13). This concept is similar to that of telepresence in internet advertising. Indeed, both concepts refer to the displacement of the person from his or her immediate environment to the environment created by the ad for an experience of the product. The present study is part of a research field that seeks to explore the implications of telepresence. More specifically, the objective of this study is to better understand the mechanisms by which <italic>telepresence impacts the formation of attitudes toward the product in the context of internet advertising</italic>.</p>
<p>This influence on the perceptual, cognitive, emotional and behavioral responses of an individual to a stimulus has been studied in the areas of marketing, human–computer interaction and information systems. However, the impact of telepresence on the formation of attitudes toward products is a relatively unexplored area of   research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-2051570713487480">Edwards and Gangadharbatla, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-2051570713487480">Klein, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-2051570713487480">Jiang and Benbasat, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-2051570713487480">Debbabi et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>There is a connection between the present study and research on the influence of television advertising on attitudes toward products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnis and Jaworski, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr104-2051570713487480">Smith and Swinyard, 1983</xref>). However, our study does not intend making a comparison between the effect of telepresence in an online ad and the effect of role-taking in a TV ad. Rather our aim is to build on the theoretical connections between the two concepts so as to better understand the consequences of telepresence.</p>
<p>Virtual experience of the product stemming from telepresence is more convincing than indirect experience arising from role-taking in a television commercial. Indeed, unlike a TV ad, 3D advertising enables the individual to interact with the product. The person thus becomes a ‘tele-actor’ and not simply a viewer in relation to the message he or she receives. The mechanisms of the influence of telepresence on attitude are therefore specific to this type of experience.</p>
<p>As a first step, we present an overview of studies that have focused on the potential of the concept of telepresence. We then look at the similarities between the concept of telepresence in an Internet ad and the concept of role-taking in a television commercial. These similarities are a point of departure for understanding the effects of telepresence. The experiential approach of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnis and Jaworski (1989)</xref>, which explains the impact of role taking on attitude formation, serves therefore as a theoretical reference point. We next put forward a model describing the effect of telepresence on the attitude towards the product. Finally, we present and discuss the main findings and their theoretical and managerial implications.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-2051570713487480">
<title>Literature review</title>
<sec id="section3-2051570713487480">
<title>Telepresence</title>
<p>Several studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-2051570713487480">Biocca, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-2051570713487480">Klein, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-2051570713487480">Steuer, 1992</xref>) draw attention to the fact that a user whose perception is mediated by a communication technology necessarily perceives two environments: the one real (physical), the other virtual (mediated). Telepresence is experienced by the user when the perception mediated by the technology takes precedence over the unmediated perception. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-2051570713487480">Lombard and Ditton (1997)</xref> consider that telepresence is ‘the perceptual illusion of non-mediation’. Debbabi and Baile say that telepresence is ‘a perception of presence in a mediated environment that appears as if it was less mediated or real’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-2051570713487480">2005</xref>: 74). Telepresence is an intrinsically motivating activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-2051570713487480">Jeandrain, 2001</xref>) and an exciting and emotionally intense experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-2051570713487480">Grigorovici, 2003</xref>), and is determined by the characteristics of the media and of the user (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-2051570713487480">Campbell et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-2051570713487480">Lessiter et al., 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>The characteristics of a medium is defined by its content and form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-2051570713487480">Heeter, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-2051570713487480">Lombard and Ditton, 1997</xref>). The content corresponds to the use of conventions pertaining to the medium and to the nature of the task or activity to be carried out (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-2051570713487480">Lombard and Ditton, 1997</xref>). The form of the medium depends on its richness and interactivity. Media richness refers to the number of senses stimulated during the presentation of information and to the quality/resolution of this presentation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-2051570713487480">Steuer, 1992</xref>). Interactivity is defined by Steuer as ‘the extent to which users can participate in modifying the form and content of the mediated environment in real time’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-2051570713487480">1992</xref>: 14).</p>
<p>The characteristics of the user include perceptual and cognitive ability, attention, duration of exposure and/or its interaction, and familiarity with mediated environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-2051570713487480">Lessiter et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr112-2051570713487480">Witmer and Singer, 1998</xref>).</p>
<p>3D advertising is in this sense considered as a source of stimulation of telepresence. It offers the Internet user the possibility of interacting with the product, and meets his or her requirements in terms of observation and manipulation of the product: rotation, ‘zoom in’, ‘zoom out’, etc. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-2051570713487480">Hand, 1997</xref>). Researchers have shown that 3D advertising influences learning, product knowledge, the strength of beliefs about the attributes of the product, confidence in beliefs and attitudes, and confidence in the attitude toward the brand and the product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-2051570713487480">Debbabi et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-2051570713487480">Biocca and Daugherty, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-2051570713487480">Klein, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-2051570713487480">2002</xref>). From a perceptual point of view, telepresence in a 3D advertisement propels the individual towards direct experience of the product and to developing a virtual direct experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-2051570713487480">Griffith and Chen, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-2051570713487480">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-2051570713487480">Klein, 2003</xref>). Griffith and Chen define virtual direct experience as ‘the conveyance of experiential product attributes in an on-line simulation of a direct experience’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-2051570713487480">2004</xref>: 56). Li et al. instead offer a subjective conceptualization of virtual direct experience: ‘a psychological and emotional state that consumers undergo while interacting with products in a 3D environment’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">2001</xref>: 14). Although this experience is not poly-sensory, it is more gratifying than the indirect experience produced by means of posters, television ads, 2D photos of products on the internet and non-interactive 3D animations online, in the cinema or on television (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2002</xref>). Indeed, it is these intentional and interactive manipulations of the product that give this experience its particular force.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-2051570713487480">Li et al. (2002)</xref> show that the virtual experience is only experienced by telepresent subjects in a virtual environment that allows interaction with the product. Indeed, through the technology’s loss of salience, telepresence gives the person the impression of being in direct contact with the product. This assimilation can lead to interesting effects on consumer behavior, and more specifically on the processing of information about the product.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-2051570713487480">
<title>Theoretical findings of the literature review</title>
<p>The literature review has brought out the important role of telepresence in the creation of a virtual direct experience with the product. Are there rules that allow the creators of advertising messages to foster telepresence with certainty? What are the likely consequences of such telepresence in terms of information processing?</p>
<p>Three observations, derived from the literature, prompt these questions.</p>
<sec id="section5-2051570713487480">
<title>First observation: 3D gives rise to more telepresence</title>
<p>Some studies have investigated the impact of the advertising richness and interactivity on telepresence. More specifically, they examine the format of the presentation of the product (3D or 2D). 3D ads are considered richer – higher digital resolution of the product display and the ability to zoom in on the product – and more interactive – possibility of manipulating the product – than 2D ads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-2051570713487480">Hopkins and Raymond, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-2051570713487480">Klein, 2003</xref>). The findings of these studies show that the level of telepresence is higher for 3D than for 2D advertisements.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-2051570713487480">
<title>Second observation: Influence on attitude depends on the ads richness and interactivity</title>
<p>Some work has focused on measuring the effectiveness of rich, interactive ads in simulating of direct experience of the product. The results show that these two characteristics positively influence the intensity of the consumer’s cognitive, affective and conative responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-2051570713487480">Fiore and Jin, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-2051570713487480">Griffith and Chen, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr106-2051570713487480">Suh and Lee, 2005</xref>). Certain effects are similar to those found by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr104-2051570713487480">Smith and Swinyard (1983)</xref> in relation to direct experience: learning, the strength of and confidence in beliefs about the product, and confidence in the attitude toward the product.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-2051570713487480">
<title>Third observation: Telepresence enhances the impact of richness and interactivity</title>
<p>Finally, some studies contribute to understanding consumer responses to the richness and interactivity of advertising by investigating the role of telepresence. Research in this area shows that telepresence conveys the effects of the richness and interactivity effects of the ad to the internet user’s responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-2051570713487480">Debbabi et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-2051570713487480">Hopkins and Raymond, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-2051570713487480">Kim, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-2051570713487480">Kim and Biocca, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-2051570713487480">Lombard and Ditton, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-2051570713487480">Klein, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>The literature review highlights the impact of telepresence on the attitude towards the product. It also shows that few studies have modeled these influence mechanisms on the formation of attitudes. The studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-2051570713487480">Hopkins and Raymond (2004)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-2051570713487480">Grigorovici (2003)</xref> provide a first attempt to model the process of attitude formation in a situation where telepresence occurs. However, these studies have a number of shortcomings, in that they explain attitude formation by purely affective mechanisms without taking cognitive mechanisms into account. Yet the role of the latter in experience is undeniable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-2051570713487480">Derbaix and Pham, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-2051570713487480">Eagly and Chaiken, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr103-2051570713487480">Smith and Swinyard, 1982</xref>).</p>
<p>Given these facts, the aim of this study is to provide a better understanding of the telepresence effects on the attitude towards the product. On the one hand, the study of the affective influence mechanisms of telepresence on attitude towards the product needs to be deepened. On the other hand, to remedy the shortcomings in the studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-2051570713487480">Hopkins and Raymond (2004)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-2051570713487480">Grigorovici (2003)</xref>, the effect of telepresence on attitude cannot be fully explained by purely affective mechanisms. The proposed modeling process also takes into account cognitive mechanisms affecting attitude formation, and shows the complementarity and interdependence of the cognitive and emotional models in attitude formation in order to better understand virtual experience through telepresence in an internet ad. This work is thus situated within an original research approach intended to provide answers to the following question: <italic>how does telepresence influence the formation of attitudes toward the product in the context of internet advertising?</italic></p>
<p>To better explain the effects of telepresence, it is appropriate to use a stream of research dealing with the process of attitude formation, focusing on the experience during exposure to advertising, which mobilizes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnis and Jaworski’s (1989)</xref> integrative model. In that way our study introduces the indirect experience of the product after exposure to a TV ad, known as ‘role-taking’.</p>
<p>Role-taking is the projection of an individual into a particular role in an advertisement. It helps create an experience between the individual and the product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-2051570713487480">Krugman, 1965</xref>), and allows the person to access the distinctive and characteristic ‘world’ of the product.</p>
<p>Although the concept of role-taking is traditionally used in the context of TV advertising, it shares many features with telepresence that merit being developed, because they underlie our choice of the MacInnis and Jaworski model as the conceptual framework of this study.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-2051570713487480">
<title>Telepresence and role-taking: Conceptual similarities</title>
<p>According to MacInnis and Jaworski, role-taking corresponds to a high level of information processing during which ‘the individual relates information about the brand to the self’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">1989</xref>: 13). The person identifies with the role described in the advertisement and anticipates the consequences of using the product. This definition implies a shift of the individual from his or her physical environment to the environment created by the ad. Role-taking also implies that the media appears invisible to the individual.</p>
<p>The conceptualization of role-taking is similar to that of telepresence, which is defined by Lombard and Ditton as a ‘perceptual illusion of non-mediation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-2051570713487480">1997</xref>: 57). For <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-2051570713487480">Lombard (2000)</xref>, telepresence is a subjective perception of an experience created by technology with objects and/or events. Although this perception is subjective, it allows the person to construct an interpretation of the experience of objects or events in the virtual environment. It consists of a form of exposure suited to role projects, and partly explains experiential behavior, since it represents a situation in which the individual is involved, transported and projected into the experience of the product. Direct virtual experience arising from telepresence can be viewed as a form of role-taking appropriate to the context of interactive advertising on the internet.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-2051570713487480">
<title>Telepresence and role-taking: similarities in their determinants</title>
<p>Telepresence and role-taking have two common antecedents: ability and motivation. Ability depends on familiarity with the product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-2051570713487480">Anderson and Jolson, 1980</xref>) and the medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-2051570713487480">Lombard and Ditton, 1997</xref>), on the degree of difficulty of the message (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr115-2051570713487480">Yalch and Elmore-Yalch, 1984</xref>), and on interaction with the virtual environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-2051570713487480">Billinhurst and Weghorst, 1995</xref>). Sustainable and/or situational motivation determines the level of attention to the advertising stimulus, which is a prerequisite for role-taking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnis and Jaworski, 1989</xref>) and telepresence. Indeed, ‘telepresence may vary across a range of values that depends in part on the allocation of attentional resources’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr112-2051570713487480">Witmer and Singer, 1998</xref>).</p>
<p>3D interactive ad characteristics favor factors that initiate information processing and determine role-taking in an advertisement, namely opportunity, ability and motivation. On the one hand, the interactivity of the ad allows the internet user to control the speed of its transmission, a determining factor of opportunity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-2051570713487480">Chaiken and Eagly, 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-2051570713487480">Krugman, 1965</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr114-2051570713487480">Wright, 1974</xref>). Opportunity is also augmented by providing the consumer with textual information and interactive displays in relation to the product. On the other hand, controlling the order of presentation of information and interaction with the product in the mediated 3D virtual environment facilitates understanding of product information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-2051570713487480">Ariely, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-2051570713487480">Ayerson 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-2051570713487480">Macias, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr88-2051570713487480">Najjar, 1996</xref>). The individual ability to interpret the information contained in product advertising is thus reinforced. In addition, interactive advertising on the internet gives rise to situational motivation through its perceived novelty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-2051570713487480">Edwards and Gangadharbatla, 2001</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section10-2051570713487480">
<title>Telepresence and role-taking: Similarities in their consequences</title>
<p>Telepresence and role-taking influence similar variables, such as beliefs and attitudes toward the product, attitude towards the ad and emotions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-2051570713487480">Campbell et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-2051570713487480">Debbabi et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-2051570713487480">Grigorovici, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-2051570713487480">Hopkins and Raymond, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-2051570713487480">Kim and Biocca, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-2051570713487480">Klein, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>Studying the similarities between the two concepts suggests that telepresence is a situation suited to role-taking in online advertising: it expresses a state of favorable attention to role-taking, and in a telepresence situation, people have the opportunity to process information, a prerequisite for role-taking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnis and Jaworski, 1989</xref>). The opportunity to process information depends on an individual’s ability to control the transmission rate of the message, as well as the amount and type of information (image and text) provided (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr114-2051570713487480">Wright, 1974</xref>). Yet, with telepresence, these two factors are enhanced by interactivity and richness of online advertising. In addition, ads favoring telepresence would orientate experiential needs and contribute to role-taking, because they are based on interactive images of the product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnis and Jaworski, 1989</xref>).</p>
<p>In conclusion, these findings argue in favor of the MacInnis and Jaworski model. We mobilize this model in this study to explain the effect of telepresence on the formation of attitudes toward the product. More specifically, it supports the premise that information processing, initiated by role-taking, accounts for the likely effect of telepresence on attitude towards the product.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-2051570713487480">
<title>Research model and hypotheses</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnis and Jaworski (1989)</xref> emphasize the importance of the role of emotions during role-taking in the formation process of attitude toward the product. Emotions are produced by certain aspects of the execution of the ad (scenarios giving rise to emotions related to consuming, or not consuming, the product). These authors point out that individuals engaged in role-taking experience more intense emotions. Role-taking is in this sense more experiential than analytical. The emotions felt partly affect attitude towards the product through the mediation of beliefs about the product and of the attitude towards the ad (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnis and Jaworski, 1989</xref>).</p>
<p>In an interactive internet ad context, telepresence projects the individual into a virtual direct experience. This virtual experience is of interest on two counts. Being perceptually similar to direct experience, it results not only in the formation of beliefs about the product but also in arousal and a cheerful frame of mind. Indeed, it enables the person to anticipate the experience of using the product. Telepresence thus reproduces some of the pleasures and enjoyment experienced when consuming the product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-2051570713487480">Edwards and Gangadharbatla, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-2051570713487480">Grigorovici, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-2051570713487480">Jones et al., 2008</xref>). Certain characteristics of the internet environment, especially its interactivity, intensify these feelings because they generate positive emotional reactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-2051570713487480">Hoffman and Novak, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-2051570713487480">Jones et al., 2008</xref>). In short, emotions play an important role in the virtual experience, and should therefore be taken into account by the research model.</p>
<p>The experiential approach and its findings consequently offer a conceptual framework for explaining the effects of telepresence on the attitude developed by the customer toward the product through two processes, one cognitive and the other emotional. The cognitive process results from the virtual direct experience and is based on beliefs about the product formed during this experience. The emotional process results from the parallel effects of exposure to the internet, the advertising features and the virtual direct experience. It is based on the emotions triggered by navigating in the ad and on the attitude towards the ad.</p>
<p>The experiential approach adopted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-2051570713487480">Izard (1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-2051570713487480">1977</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-2051570713487480">Meyers-Levy and Malavyia (1999)</xref> recognizes the interdependence between the cognitive and emotional processes. For these authors, emotions are an experiential and motivational process that initiates and guides the learning process. Pleasurable and stimulating emotions felt during the virtual experience draw the person’s attention to the positive consequences of direct experience of the product, and therefore induce him or her to reassess the product. These emotions influence not only beliefs about the product, but also the evaluation of the ad. It is thus plausible that telepresence, though the emotions, partly influences beliefs about the product as well as the attitude toward the ad.</p>
<p>The research model is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2051570713487480">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig1-2051570713487480" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Research model.</p>
<p><bold>TELP:</bold> telepresence</p>
<p><bold>EMO</bold>: emotions triggered by navigating in the ad</p>
<p><bold>Cp</bold>: beliefs about the product</p>
<p><bold>Ap</bold>: attitude toward the product</p>
<p><bold>Aad</bold>: attitude toward the ad</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<sec id="section12-2051570713487480">
<title>Direct effect of telepresence on cognitive and affective mediators of the formation of attitude towards the product</title>
<sec id="section13-2051570713487480">
<title>Relationship between telepresence and product beliefs</title>
<p>For <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr103-2051570713487480">Smith and Swinyard (1982)</xref> direct experience encourages evaluation of the product attributes, because it is based on sensorial inspection of the product, though which the individual accepts the information provided. Direct experience thus facilitates the formation of product beliefs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-2051570713487480">Kempf and Smith, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr102-2051570713487480">Smith, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr113-2051570713487480">Wright and Lynch, 1995</xref>).</p>
<p>In the case of a 3D advertisement on the internet, telepresence helps create a virtual experience, ‘a way of experiencing the product attributes’, and anticipation of the consumption experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-2051570713487480">Griffith and Chen, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-2051570713487480">Hyun and O’Keefe, 2012</xref>). In this context, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-2051570713487480">Cauberghe et al. (2011)</xref> show that telepresence facilitates the processing of information. They note that information processing is not completely objective, but is positively influenced by the enjoyable virtual experience of interacting with the product. In the opinion of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-2051570713487480">Hyun and O’Keefe (2012)</xref>, telepresence conveys the positive effect of the virtualization of product-related information on cognitive responses. The ‘telepresent’ individual tends to accept more readily the information contained in the advertisement. It may therefore be assumed that telepresence favors the formation of product beliefs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-2051570713487480">
<title>Relationship between telepresence and the emotions produced by navigating in the advertisement</title>
<p>Various authors have shown that telepresence gives rise to two types of positive emotions: pleasure and arousal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-2051570713487480">Freeman and Avons, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-2051570713487480">Grigorovici, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-2051570713487480">Heeter, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-2051570713487480">Pugnetti et al., 2001</xref>). These two emotions are triggered in part by anticipation of using the product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-2051570713487480">Havlena and Holbrook, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-2051570713487480">Jones et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-2051570713487480">Kempf and Smith, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-2051570713487480">Mano and Oliver, 1993</xref>) and by the positive effects of interactivity and exposure to the medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-2051570713487480">Diesbach and Jeandrain, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-2051570713487480">Hoffman and Novak, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr101-2051570713487480">Singh et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>The perceived novelty of 3D advertising and the state of telepresence can also explain the pleasure felt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-2051570713487480">Edwards and Gangadharbatla, 2001</xref>). According to Bourgeon and Filser ‘the pleasure principle is crucial to the satisfaction derived from the experience’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-2051570713487480">1995</xref>: 7). The virtual direct experience is thus perceived as pleasurable. It confers objective benefits while producing positive emotional and subjective reactions. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-2051570713487480">Nah et al. (2011)</xref> have recently shown that telepresence has a positive influence on the pleasure felt while viewing a 3D advertisement. The results of their study also confirm that the pleasure is more intense with a 3D ad than a 2D ad.</p>
<p>Up until now, studies show that the emotions triggered by an e-advertisement, presenting a product in a rich and interactive manner, are positive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-2051570713487480">Edwards and Gangadharbatla, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-2051570713487480">Grigorovici, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-2051570713487480">Nah et al., 2011</xref>). In this same context, telepresence seems to exert a positive effect on the emotions produced by navigating through the ad.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-2051570713487480">
<title>Relationship between telepresence and the attitude toward the ad</title>
<p>Telepresence helps create an experience characterized by positive emotions (pleasure and arousal) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-2051570713487480">Grigorovici, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-2051570713487480">Jones, et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-2051570713487480">Pugnetti et al., 2001</xref>). Advertising in this context triggers positive emotions such as pleasure and tends to be liked by the consumer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-2051570713487480">Cho and Stoot, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-2051570713487480">Homer and Yoon, 1992</xref>). It is therefore reasonable to assume that an advertisement which gives rise to telepresence (a pleasant and stimulating experience) is liked by the internet user. Suggesting that telepresence positively influences the formation of attitudes towards advertising is, in other words, a hypothesis consistent with the established findings.</p>
<p>In accord with these propositions, this hypothesis (H1) is broken down into three sub-hypotheses (H1a, H1b et H1c) relating to the various direct effects of telepresence.</p>
<list id="list1-2051570713487480" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>H1: Telepresence exerts an influence on:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p> a – beliefs about the product attributes</p></list-item>
<list-item><p> b – the attitude towards the ad</p></list-item>
<list-item><p> c – the emotions produced by navigating in the ad.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-2051570713487480">
<title>Indirect effects of telepresence on product beliefs and attitude toward the advertisement: The role of emotions</title>
<sec id="section17-2051570713487480">
<title>Relationship between emotions and product beliefs</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnis and Jaworski (1989)</xref> recognize that the cognitive and affective processes are interdependent during role-taking in an ad. These authors suggest that the emotions generated by experiencing the product influence beliefs about it in a role-taking situation. Thus the affective and cognitive dimensions of the experience are based on dependent systems. Along the same lines, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr111-2051570713487480">Westbrook and Oliver (1991)</xref> view emotions as a source of motivation that influences memory and thought processes. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-2051570713487480">Izard (1972)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr107-2051570713487480">Tomkins (1962)</xref> consider emotion to be a source of information that guides the cognitive process.</p>
<p>Hence, and in accordance with the findings of studies establishing that the emotions triggered by an advertisement presenting a product in a rich and interactive manner are positive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-2051570713487480">Edwards and Gangadharbatla, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-2051570713487480">Grigorovici, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-2051570713487480">Nah et al., 2011</xref>), it is logical to assume that their effects on beliefs about the product are also positive. The emotions experienced thus allow the individual to modify his or her product assessment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-2051570713487480">Izard, 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr107-2051570713487480">Tomkins, 1962</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-2051570713487480">
<title>Relationship between emotions and attitude toward the advertisement</title>
<p>Emotions are involved in the formation of the attitude toward an ad (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-2051570713487480">Burke and Edell, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-2051570713487480">Cho and Stout, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-2051570713487480">Homer and Yoon, 1992</xref>). People tend to like advertisements that generate positive emotions. The emotions produced by telepresence, interactivity and the perceived novelty of an ad are positive (pleasure and arousal) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-2051570713487480">Freeman and Avons, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-2051570713487480">Grigorovici, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-2051570713487480">Heeter, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-2051570713487480">Nah et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-2051570713487480">Pugnetti et al., 2001</xref>). It is thus legitimate to hypothesize that the emotions triggered while navigating the ad are transferred to it.</p>
<p>These two propositions lead us to break down this hypothesis into two sub-hypotheses (H2a and H2b) concerning the direct effects of emotions.</p>
<list id="list2-2051570713487480" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>H2: The emotions triggered by navigating in the ad have a positive effect on:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>A – beliefs about the product attributes</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>B – the attitude toward the ad.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-2051570713487480">
<title>The mediating role of the emotions triggered by navigating in the ad</title>
<p>Telepresence promotes the formation of product-beliefs (H1a). It also has a positive effect on emotions (H1c). Because emotions positively guide the formation of beliefs (H2a), it is reasonable to assume that telepresence has a positive indirect effect on beliefs via the emotions generated.</p>
<p>Telepresence and emotions also have a combined positive impact on attitude toward an ad (H1b and H2b). Thus the hypothesis that the emotions triggered by navigating in the ad play a mediating role in relation to the influence of telepresence on the attitude toward the ad is required to validate the structure of the model’s causal relationships. This hypothesis (H3) states that:</p>
<list id="list3-2051570713487480" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>H3: Emotions act as a partial mediator of the influence of telepresence on:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p> a – beliefs about product attributes</p></list-item>
<list-item><p> b – attitude towards the ad.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-2051570713487480">
<title>Direct and indirect effects of emotions on attitude toward the product</title>
<p>The literature review reveals the effect of emotions on attitude toward a product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-2051570713487480">Aaker et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-2051570713487480">Burke and Edell, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-2051570713487480">Homer and Yoon, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnis and Jaworski, 1989</xref>). Emotions triggered by navigating the ad and particularly through direct virtual experience of the product will therefore be transferred to the product.</p>
<p>For <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnis and Jaworski (1989)</xref>, the attitude towards the product has the same polarity as the emotions experienced. However, the experience of browsing a website in general, and the direct virtual experience of the product in particular, produce intense positive emotions (pleasure and arousal) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-2051570713487480">Diesbach and Jeandrain, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-2051570713487480">Grigorovici, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-2051570713487480">Müller, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-2051570713487480">Nah et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr101-2051570713487480">Singh et al., 2005</xref>). Hypothesis (H4) states that:</p>
<list id="list4-2051570713487480" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>H4: The emotions triggered by navigating in the ad have a positive effect on attitude toward the product.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The experiential approach explains the formation of attitude toward the product by the indirect positive effect of emotions conveyed by product-beliefs and the attitude towards the ad. This approach supports hypothesis (H5), which states that this process is also valid in the context of a virtual experience arising from telepresence.</p>
<list id="list5-2051570713487480" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>H5: The influence of emotions on attitude toward the product is partially conveyed by:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p> a – beliefs about the attributes of the product (H5a), and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p> b – the attitude towards the ad (H5b).</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-2051570713487480" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methodology</title>
<p>The research methodology successively considers the creation of advertising stimuli, the choice of measurement scales and the collection of data.</p>
<sec id="section22-2051570713487480">
<title>Experimental design</title>
<p>To ensure a good level of telepresence, this study tests the model on an original terrain, that of a 3D ad (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-2051570713487480">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-2051570713487480">Debbabi et al., 2010</xref>). Although it does not allow the internet user to have a poly-sensory experience of product, it enables him or her to simulate a direct experience of the product.</p>
<p>Thus the design of a 3D ad should take into account various experimental considerations to enable the content of the metrics to be validated. First, it was important to choose a product that is advertised. Accordingly, we opted for a geometric product, following the recommendations for classifications proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-2051570713487480">Klatzky et al. (1991)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-2051570713487480">McCabe and Nowlis (2001)</xref>. The existence of two product categories – geometric and material – led us to choose a wristwatch for the experiment, i.e. a product whose geometric attributes, unlike material products, can, in accordance with the principle proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-2051570713487480">Klatzky et al. (1991)</xref>, be sufficiently well evaluated visually. Previous studies have shown the effectiveness of 3D advertising for this type of product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-2051570713487480">Klein, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-2051570713487480">2002</xref>). The choice of a watch as a geometric product was validated in a pretest. Respondents were asked to say whether they had any difficulty evaluating the product without actually touching it.</p>
<p>Second, since the evaluations of respondents of different gender might, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-2051570713487480">Kisielius and Sternthal (1984)</xref> suggest, be subject to different levels of response, it was necessary to choose one watch model for women and another for men so as to reduce possible perceptual bias.</p>
<p>Third, we decided to avoid the impact of a known brand on the product evaluation. We therefore created a non-existent brand without any luxury attributes.</p>
<p>Fourth, on the basis of 53 non-directive interviews, we needed to evaluate the qualifiers used to describe the product attributes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-2051570713487480">Fishbein and Ajzen, 1975</xref>). Frequently mentioned attributes were presented in the ad and used to measure beliefs about the product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-2051570713487480">Kempf and Smith 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr102-2051570713487480">Smith 1993</xref>). In order to inform the participants of the importance of these characteristics, certain information considered helpful for their understanding and necessary for the proper conduct of experiments was provided. These included the texture of the product, the colors available, its weight, water resistance and the duration of its warranty.</p>
<p>Fifth, we decided not to specify the price of these products, so as to avoid introducing a further perceptual bias through the financial aspect being taken into account when evaluating the product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-2051570713487480">Bauer, 1960</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-2051570713487480">Rao and Monroe, 1988</xref>). Respondents were therefore invited to assume that the price of the two watches was whatever seemed appropriate.</p>
<p>These various considerations were largely taken into account in the design of the website. The first page introduces the subject of the research and shows a photograph of two watch models, respectively for men and women, in order to involve these two targets in the process of evaluating a known object. This page gives the name of the brand and allows the participants to display each of the two products by clicking on them. The second page shows a 3D presentation of the product, information about the product characteristics, various advertisements designed on the basis the attributes selected, and a reference, specific to this study, to the ‘appropriate price’, together with a reminder of the brand name. The two website pages for each ad are in a neutral color and white.</p>
<p>Finally, to avoid the negative effect of the perceived difficulty of using the 3D format on the user’s attitude (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-2051570713487480">Davis, 1989</xref>: 320), we created a training website for 3D interaction. Participants in the experiment were invited to interact with a test product (a can), following the explanations provided on how to use 3D interactive tools. This session took place prior to displaying the 3D ad. No problems using the 3D format was found. By the end of this training session, none of the participants had any problem using the 3D format.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-2051570713487480">
<title>Measurement of research variables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-2051570713487480">Appendix 1</xref>)</title>
<sec id="section24-2051570713487480">
<title>Measurement of the variable ‘attitude toward the product’ - [Ap]</title>
<p>To measure the overall attitude towards the product, we decided to use <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-2051570713487480">Munch and Swasy’s (1988)</xref> one-dimensional scale. This scale is consistent with our holistic approach to attitude towards the product, as it transcribes an overall opinion of the product. The scale measures a construct containing three items.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-2051570713487480">
<title>Measurement of the variable ‘beliefs about the product attributes’ – [Cp]</title>
<p>These beliefs are measured by a construct comprising several attributes measured by scales with seven-point intervals, as suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr95-2051570713487480">Raden (1985)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-2051570713487480">Klein (2003)</xref>. The six attributes of the construct measure the degree of the participants’ agreement or disagreement with statements about the perception of the product, namely the watch.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-2051570713487480">
<title>Measurement of the variable ‘attitude towards the ad’ – [Aad]</title>
<p>Attitude towards the ad is measured by a three-item construct taken from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-2051570713487480">Derbaix’s (1995)</xref> scale. This construct is assumed to be one-dimensional.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-2051570713487480">
<title>Measurement of the variable ‘emotions’ - [EMO]</title>
<p>Emotions were measured using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-2051570713487480">Mehrabian and Russell’s (1974)</xref> pleasure, arousal, domination (PAD) scale. The use of the PAD scale is recommended in studies on the influence of the situation on behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-2051570713487480">Lutz and Kakkar, 1975</xref>). The PAD scale also better represents the experience of using the product and provides emotional profiles specific to the experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-2051570713487480">Havlena and Holbrook, 1986</xref>). In addition, the advantage of using it in an advertising context was shown by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-2051570713487480">Morris and McMullen (1994)</xref>. The PAD scale could therefore offer a better representation of virtual direct experience involving emotions.</p>
<p>However, the ‘domination’ dimension was removed from the measurement scale because it measures the perceived control by the internet user over his or her actions in a virtual environment. This variable would then be considered as a determinant and not a consequence of telepresence.</p>
<p>The 12 original ‘bipolar’ attributes of each dimension (pleasure and arousal) were measured using a seven-point semantic differential scale.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section28-2051570713487480">
<title>Measurement of the variable ‘telepresence’ – [TELP]</title>
<p>The concept of telepresence was measured using the one-dimensional scale developed and validated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-2051570713487480">Klein (2003)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr89-2051570713487480">Novak et al. (2000)</xref> in the same context. The construct comprises seven items measured on a seven-point interval scale.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-2051570713487480">
<title>Data collection</title>
<p>A large sample (<italic>n</italic> = 353) of students (40% male and 60% female), doing bachelor’s, master’s or doctorate degrees in management, agreed to participate in the experiment. The respondents were told about the value of their collaboration and received instructions about the conduct of the experiment. They were asked to choose and display an ad. At the end of the experiment, they completed a questionnaire containing the different items of the measurement scale used in the study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section30-2051570713487480" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Examination of the results took place in two stages. The first involved validating the research model’s variables using preliminary analyses, and the second went on to test the research hypotheses.</p>
<sec id="section31-2051570713487480">
<title>Results of the preliminary analyses</title>
<p>The usual statistical analyses for each of the constructs measuring the research variables were implemented to clarify their content validity and reliability. In the first step, a Principal Component Factor Analysis (PCFA) with Promax rotation (using SPSS software) was performed to explore the five constructs and identify an optimal one-dimensional structure of the attributes making a high contribution (&gt; 0.5). Once the structure validity was established, in a second step the calculation of Cronbach’s alpha allowed its reliability to be evaluated. Finally, a Confirmatory Factor Analysis (using STATISTICA software) was carried out to confirm the structure of the five constructs, and test their independence in the research model.</p>
<sec id="section32-2051570713487480">
<title>PCFA results</title>
<p>The results of the PCFA of the seven items of the construct measuring telepresence led to the elimination of items 6 and 7 (<italic>I forgot about my immediate surroundings when I was navigating through the exercise</italic>; and, <italic>When the computer exercise ended, I felt like I came back to the ‘real world’ after a journey</italic>), because of their low representation quality, which revealed a certain ambiguity in their wording. The five items retained have high contributions on a first-order factor, which account for 62.90% of the total variance. This factor measures the ‘Telepresence’ variable [TELP].</p>
<p>The PCFA results of the two constructs, measuring attitude towards the product and attitude toward the ad, confirm their one-dimensional factor structure. The high contributions of the three attributes of the construct measuring attitude toward the product account for 82.1% of the total variance. This factor measures the variable ‘Attitude/product’ [Ap]. Similarly, the three attributes of the construct measuring attitude toward the ad account for 82.25% of the total variance. This factor measures the variable ‘Attitude/advertisement’ [Aad].</p>
<p>The PCFA results of the six items of the construct measuring product beliefs show low contributions from items 3 and 5 (<italic>this product will suit you well</italic>, and <italic>this product is fashionable</italic>), whose wording is too general. The four items retained have high contributions on a first-order factor and explain 59.30% of the total variance. This factor measures the variable ‘Beliefs/product’ [Cp].</p>
<p>The PCFA of the 12 attributes measuring emotions (pleasure and arousal) reconstruct a general factor, whose variance (66.17%) is explained by a linear component, the high contributions of which reflect only five attributes (combining the attributes pleasure and arousal). This component refers to the variable ‘emotions’ [EMO]. The results show that seven attributes are rejected in the specific components of ‘emotion’ and are not included in this study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section33-2051570713487480">
<title>Results of the reliability test</title>
<p>The reliability of each of the five constructs, measured using Cronbach’s alpha (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-2051570713487480">1951</xref>), is statistically verified for each of the five research variables. The calculated coefficients are high and above the norm (0.80) recommended by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr90-2051570713487480">Nunnally (1978)</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section34-2051570713487480">
<title>Results of the Confirmatory Factor Analysis</title>
<p>The results of the CFA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table7-2051570713487480">Appendix 2</xref>) carried out for each of these constructs, using STATISTICA 7.0 software, confirm the existence of (statistically significant) weights greater than 0.50 for each attribute. To complement the reliability study, the Jöreskog coefficients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-2051570713487480">Fornell and Larcker, 1981</xref>) confirm the high reliability of the measurement instruments. Thus the convergent and discriminant validities of the constructs were verified, consistently with the established standards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-2051570713487480">Evrard et al., 1997</xref>), and particularly with that of the average variance extracted (AVE), calculated for each measurement scale, which is greater here than the square of its correlation with the other constructs.</p>
<p>To estimate the goodness of fit of the model to the data, a CFA was carried out on the measurement model. Assessment of the adequacy of the model, and of a general hypothesis of fit in relation to the empirical data, was done through a combination of indices concerning the estimation of absolute fit (χ<sup>2</sup>, GFI, AGFI, RMR and RMSEA), incremental fit (NFI, CFI, TLI, IFI), and parsimonious fit (χ<sup>2</sup>/df). The model’s goodness of fit (the fit of the data to relationships studied) is generally acceptable and meets the theoretical requirements, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-2051570713487480">Arbuckle and Wothke (2000)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-2051570713487480">Roussel et al. (2002)</xref>. On the one hand, the null hypothesis of the existence of assumed causality relationships is verified by the value of χ<sup>2</sup>/d.f. equal to 2.46 (lower than the norm of 5), and the value of P(χ<sup>2</sup>) equal to 14% (greater than the acceptable norm of 5%), showing that the model is parsimonious. On the other hand, the absolute fit of the model is verified first by the values of GFI (.90), AGFI (.85) and RMR (.038), which are close to the agreed norms, and, second, by the value of RMSEA (7%), which is slightly higher than the norm of 5%. These intermediate results are consistent with those of studies that help validate the constructs, which are often difficult to confirm from an empirical or experimental standpoint, in the research field of e-marketing or information systems (IS) users (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-2051570713487480">Baile and Louati, 2010</xref>). Note also that the validation of parsimonious fit is not necessary for this exploratory study, even with NFI and CFI coefficients of 0.90 and 0.92, which are higher than the norms.</p>
<p>To summarize, the structure of the research model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2051570713487480">Figure 1</xref>) is verified by the existence of linear relationships between variables estimated using the Maximum Likelihood method, which, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-2051570713487480">Chou and Bentler (1996)</xref>, is the most suitable from the standpoint of the quality of the estimates, and is also the most referenced in e-Marketing and management information systems (MIS) research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-2051570713487480">Chin and Todd, 1995</xref>). These relationships significantly explain (p &lt; 1%) all of the model’s explanatory variables, with the following coefficients of determination (R<sup>2</sup>) of explained variance: R<sup>2</sup> [Ap] = 24%, R<sup>2</sup> [Cp] = 15.3%, R<sup>2</sup> [EMO] = 16.5% and R<sup>2</sup> [Aad] = 6.8%. The relationships postulated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2051570713487480">Figure 1</xref> will now be addressed in testing our research hypotheses.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section35-2051570713487480">
<title>Results of testing research hypotheses</title>
<p>The Maximum Likelihood estimation method (using STATISTICA version 7.0) was used to test the general structural model for all linear relationships studied. The results of testing the general research model are presented in the following sections. For clarity, the results for the direct and indirect links postulated by the model are presented successively.</p>
<sec id="section36-2051570713487480">
<title>Testing the effects of telepresence on mediators of formation of attitude towards the product</title>
<p>The results of testing the complete structural model are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-2051570713487480">Table 1</xref>. They show the significant positive influence of telepresence on perceived beliefs in relation to the product attributes, on the attitude toward the ad and on perceived emotions. Thus hypotheses H1a, H1b and H1c are confirmed.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-2051570713487480" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Results of testing the complete model.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-2051570713487480" xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Estimated parameter (c)</th>
<th align="center">Significance</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>TELP ➝ Cp</td>
<td>0.154 (<italic>t</italic> = 3.835) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TELP ➝ Aad</td>
<td>0.247 (<italic>t</italic> = 6.545) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TELP ➝ EMO</td>
<td>0.404 (<italic>t</italic> = 11.681) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>EMO ➝ Cp</td>
<td>0.272 (<italic>t</italic> = 7.237) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>EMO ➝ Aad</td>
<td>0.379 (<italic>t</italic> = 11.235) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>EMO ➝ Ap</td>
<td>0.234 (<italic>t</italic> = 7.010) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The results also confirm the positive influence of emotions on product beliefs, on attitude toward the ad, and on attitude toward the product. Thus hypotheses H2a, H2b and H4 are confirmed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section37-2051570713487480">
<title>Testing the indirect effect of telepresence on product beliefs: The mediating role of emotions</title>
<p>Showing the mediating role of a variable is based on a specific procedure proposed and formalized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-2051570713487480">Baron and Kenny (1986)</xref>. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-2051570713487480">Roussel et al (2002)</xref>, this procedure has the advantage of a simple, clear and rigorous approach. It requires a series of four successive tests, to:</p>
<list id="list6-2051570713487480" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Show that the link (c) between the independent variable X and the dependent variable Y is significant, so as to ensure the existence of an effect to be conveyed.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Show that the independent variable X has a significant impact (a) on the mediating variable M.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Show that the relationship between the mediating variable and the dependent variable Y is significant. This involves implementing a regression of Y on both M and X. In controlling X, the coefficient (b) between M and Y should remain significant.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Check whether the mediation is total or partial and implement a Sobel test<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-2051570713487480">1</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr93-2051570713487480">Preacher and Hayes, 2004</xref>). If the link between the independent variable and the dependent variable (c′) is zero, the mediation is total. If c′&lt; c, the mediation is partial. Otherwise there is no mediating effect.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Consistently with this procedure, the results presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-2051570713487480">Table 2</xref> show that telepresence has a significant positive influence on emotions (a) and on product beliefs (c). The relationship between emotions and product beliefs (b) is also positive and significant. However, the effect of telepresence on beliefs (c′) decreased when we statistically controlled emotions (c′ &lt; c). Emotions therefore play a partial mediator role for the influence of telepresence on product beliefs. To confirm this mediation, we carried out a Sobel test. The results show that the indirect effect of telepresence on product beliefs via emotions is significantly different from zero (z = 8.068 &gt; 1.96; <italic>p</italic> = 0.000). Thus, hypothesis H3a is confirmed.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-2051570713487480" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mediating effect of emotions on the influence of telepresence on Cp.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-2051570713487480" xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Stage</th>
<th align="center">Estimated parameter</th>
<th align="center">Significance</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">1</td>
<td>TELP (c) Cp</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.501 (<italic>t</italic> = 9.561) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img1.tif"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">2</td>
<td>TELP (a) EMO</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.513 (<italic>t</italic> = 10.405) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img2.tif"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">3</td>
<td>EMO (b) Cp</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.663 (<italic>t</italic> =12.779) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img3.tif"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">4</td>
<td>TELP (c′) Cp</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.137 (<italic>t</italic> = 2.229) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.026)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img4.tif"/></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section38-2051570713487480">
<title>Indirect effect of telepresence on attitude toward the ad: The mediating role of emotions</title>
<p>The results presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-2051570713487480">Table 3</xref> show that telepresence has a significant positive influence on emotions (a) and the attitude towards the ad (c). They also show that the relationship between emotions and attitude towards the ad (b) by controlling telepresence is positive and significant and that the effect of telepresence on attitude toward the ad (c′) decreases when one statistically controls emotions (c′ &lt; c). The results of the Sobel test show that the indirect effect of telepresence on attitude toward the ad via emotions is significantly different from zero (z = 7702 &gt; 1.96; <italic>p</italic> = 0.000). Therefore, hypothesis H3b is confirmed.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-2051570713487480" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mediating effect of emotions on the influence of telepresence on the Aad.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-2051570713487480" xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Stage</th>
<th align="center">Estimated parameter</th>
<th align="center">Significance</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">1</td>
<td>TELP (c) Aad</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.532 (<italic>t</italic> = 10.785) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img5.tif"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">2</td>
<td>TELP (a) EMO</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.513 (<italic>t</italic> = 10.405) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img6.tif"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">3</td>
<td>EMO (b) Aad</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.600 (<italic>t</italic> =11.328) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img7.tif"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">4</td>
<td>TELP (c′) Aad</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.228 (<italic>t</italic> = 3.795) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img8.tif"/></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section39-2051570713487480">
<title>Testing the indirect effect of emotions on attitude toward the product: The mediating role of product beliefs</title>
<p>The results (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-2051570713487480">Table 4</xref>) show that the effect of emotions on attitude toward the product (c′) decreases when we control product beliefs (c′ &lt; c). The results of the Sobel test confirm this indirect effect (z = 7.041&gt; 1.96; <italic>p</italic> = 0.000). Beliefs thus partially convey the influence of emotions on attitude toward the product. Thus, hypothesis H5a is confirmed.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-2051570713487480" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mediating effect of Cp on the influence of emotions on Ap.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-2051570713487480" xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Stage</th>
<th align="center">Estimated parameter</th>
<th align="center">Significance</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">1</td>
<td>EMO (c) Ap</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.741 (<italic>t</italic> = 22.787) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img9.tif"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">2</td>
<td>EMO (a) Cp</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.703 (<italic>t</italic> = 28.710) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img10.tif"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">3</td>
<td>Cp (b) Ap</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.504 (<italic>t</italic> = 7.263) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img11.tif"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">4</td>
<td>Emo (c′) Ap</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.374 (<italic>t</italic> = 5.312) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img12.tif"/></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section40-2051570713487480">
<title>Testing the indirect effect of emotions on attitude toward the product: The mediating role of attitude toward the ad</title>
<p>The results also confirm the indirect effect of emotions on attitude toward the product via the attitude towards the ad (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-2051570713487480">Table 5</xref>). The effect of emotions on attitude toward the product (c′) decreases when we control attitude toward the ad (c′ &lt; c). The Sobel test was significant (z = 5.996 &gt; 1.96; <italic>p</italic> = 0.000). Hypothesis H5b is therefore confirmed.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-2051570713487480" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mediating effect of Aad on the influence of emotions on Ap.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-2051570713487480" xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Stage</th>
<th align="center">Estimated parameter</th>
<th align="center">Signification</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">1</td>
<td>EMO (c) Ap</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.741 (<italic>t</italic> = 22.787) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img13.tif"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">2</td>
<td>EMO (a) Aad</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.720 (<italic>t</italic> = 29.792) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img14.tif"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">3</td>
<td>Aad (b) Ap</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.432 (<italic>t</italic> = 6.122) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img15.tif"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">4</td>
<td>Emo (c′) Ap</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.429 (<italic>t</italic> = 6.131) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-img16.tif"/></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section41-2051570713487480" sec-type="discussion|conclusions">
<title>Discussion and conclusion</title>
<p>This study confirms the value of using the role-taking experience to understand the effect of telepresence on the formation of attitude toward the product. The results show that telepresence has the same patterns of influence as role-taking on the formation of attitude. Two interdependent attitude formation routes were identified.</p>
<p>The first of these is cognitive, via product beliefs: interactivity helps arouse the situational interest of consumers to process information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-2051570713487480">Grigorovici, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-2051570713487480">Jeandrain, 2001</xref>). Telepresence thus expresses a state of attention and involvement. The person absorbed in interacting with the product is projected into the virtual experience. He or she is thus led to process the information contained in the ad. This information processing is facilitated through interactivity with the presentation of the product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-2051570713487480">Ayerson 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-2051570713487480">Macias, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr88-2051570713487480">Najjar, 1996</xref>). The virtual experience is similar to the direct experience, thereby contributing to the formation of beliefs about product. The attitude towards the product is formed, therefore, via the first route based on cognitive product beliefs.</p>
<p>The second route is affective, via emotions and the attitude towards the ad: telepresence is a means of access to an experience comparable to a kind of virtual use of the product. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-2051570713487480">Holbrook and Hirschman’s (1982)</xref> experiential approach, using the product yields pleasure and arousal for the person concerned. Thus telepresence reproduces emotions felt during direct experience of the product. Interactivity, the perceived novelty of the experience, and the effect of exposure to the medium also explain the positive polarity of these emotions. The formation of favorable attitudes toward the ad and in relation to the product is, consequently, based on an affective transfer mechanism.</p>
<p>The results of the study also show that the traditional experiential approach is applicable in the context of an internet ad in general and a telepresence situation in particular. They confirm the interdependence between the cognitive and emotional attitude formation processes, proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnis and Jaworski (1989)</xref> with regard to role-taking and by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-2051570713487480">Meyers-Levy and Malavyia (1999)</xref>. The results also show that telepresence influences product beliefs via the emotions felt. The visual elements and the emotions they arouse therefore shape the key message (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-2051570713487480">Edens and McCormick, 2000</xref>). Product beliefs are thus adapted to the emotions felt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-2051570713487480">Damasio, 1994</xref>). Our results limit the application of traditional theories of judgement in the context of internet advertising (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-2051570713487480">Fishbein and Ajzen, 1975</xref>). They confirm the validity of the ‘affect as information’ hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-2051570713487480">Clore et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr98-2051570713487480">Schwartz and Clore, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr99-2051570713487480">Schwartz et al., 1991</xref>). Contrary to what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-2051570713487480">Koufaris (2002)</xref> argues and in agreement with the suggestions made by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-2051570713487480">Clore (1992)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-2051570713487480">Pham (1998)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-2051570713487480">Pham et al. (2001)</xref>, the emotional reactions triggered by an ad influence the formation of cognitive responses to the product.</p>
<p>The results of testing hypothesis H5a further underline this interdependence by showing that product beliefs convey the positive effect of emotions on the attitude toward the product. Thus these results support the application of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-2051570713487480">MacInnnis and Jaworski’s (1989)</xref> inclusive approach in a role-taking situation in the context of a rich interactive internet ad. Telepresence is therefore a form of exposure suited to role projection. The formation of attitude toward the product, in the case of telepresence in an ad, therefore results from the combined effect of cognitive and emotional reactions.</p>
<p>Apart from its theoretical interest, to be specific, understanding the impact of telepresence on attitude formation, this study is also relevant in practice. The results highlight the benefits that marketing managers can derive from designing websites that promote telepresence.</p>
<p>First, telepresence arouses experiential reactions. By procuring gratification, telepresence is an effective way of increasing the satisfaction of internet users seeking hedonic benefits through visiting a website. This extra gratification could increase the return rate and the sales potential of a commercial site. Second, telepresence involves the user in the advertising message and leads him or her to form a favorable attitude toward the ad. It is therefore a practical solution for persuading the maximum number of internet users. And finally, it is conducive to the formation of a favorable attitude towards the product, since the emotions felt during this experience are transferred to the product.</p>
<p>Marketing managers and analysts are therefore advised to design websites promoting telepresence, and to provide internet users with virtual environments simulating the direct experience of the product. To achieve this, two ingredients are essential: the interactivity of the presentation of the product (e.g. a 3D format) and the richness of the information provided. The use of various types of information calling upon different senses is strongly recommended for increasing the verisimilitude of the experience.</p>
<p>The advantages of telepresence do not only concern organizations that operate on the internet. Practitioners interested in testing virtual prototypes of new products may also benefit from it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr108-2051570713487480">Urban et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr109-2051570713487480">Urban et al., 1997</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section42-2051570713487480">
<title>Limitations and future research</title>
<p>Like all research, this study has its limitations. On the one hand, the negative impact of the time taken to download applets in 3D on the virtual control of the display was not taken into account (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr110-2051570713487480">Weinberg, 1995</xref>). To remedy this problem, the experiment used two connection methods: the first consisting of downloading applets on the internet before the experiment, thus speeding up downloading when the participants connected to the websites; and the second, using a local connection. Thus, the results of this study are applicable when the download speed is not a serious constraint.</p>
<p>The impact of the participants’ demographic characteristics was not been taken into account in this study. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-2051570713487480">Lightner (2003)</xref> has shown the importance of the effect of demographic characteristics on the buying behavior of online users. In our study, the sample consisted of students (60% female) with a relatively similar level of education. The results are therefore not comparable to those of other studies using samples with different demographic characteristics.</p>
<p>Although training the participants avoided the negative effects of the perceived difficulty of using 3D interactions, it might nonetheless risk altering how they processed the information. Its impact on the influence relationships proposed in the research model was not evaluated by means of comparison with a group without any training. However, this risk may be considered low, because the duration of the training was short.</p>
<p>Using the PAD scale to measure the emotions aroused by telepresence did not allow us validate the postulated two-dimensional structure – five of the 12 attributes were retained to validate an original construct. This construct here measures a specific affective response, as defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-2051570713487480">Bagozzi et al (1999)</xref>, to the environment. Research shows that the problem of ‘dimensionality of emotion’ has still not been resolved – the researchers do not necessarily use the same dimensions of emotion. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-2051570713487480">Lemoine and Albertini (2000)</xref> validate a structure of the original construct of the PAD scale, with only three attributes describing two emotional components (pleasure and arousal). Hence the absence of internal validity (for the original structure of this construct) should lead to caution in the use of emotion. Further research is therefore needed, on the one hand, to improve the quality of reproduction of this scale and, on the other, to adapt it to the experimental context that confronts the purchaser in a virtual environment.</p>
<p>Finally, this study imposed a high level of telepresence so as to better understand the effect of this variable on attitude formation. Taking into account two levels of telepresence would have enabled us to add greater precision to the results. A comparative study of the effects of the level of telepresence (low vs. high) on the intensity of the relationships between the variables of the attitude formation process is currently underway. In it, the level of telepresence is varied by changing the ad format (3D vs. 2D).</p>
<p>These various points suggest a number of possibilities for future research. From a conceptual standpoint, several lines of research are promising. In particular it would be interesting to identify and include elements (such as mood, involvement, etc.) upstream of the emotions experienced during navigation so as to improve our understanding of the effects of telepresence on attitude. So far, research has shown that telepresence has a positive effect on the emotions triggered by navigating in a rich interactive advertisement for a product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-2051570713487480">Edwards and Gangadharbatla, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-2051570713487480">Grigorovici, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-2051570713487480">Li et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-2051570713487480">Nah et al., 2011</xref>). It would make sense to test whether telepresence reinforces a negative emotion when navigating in a shocking advertisement.</p>
<p>Similarly, it would be interesting to see whether the product category – geometric vs. material or utilitarian vs. hedonic – moderates the attitude formation process. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-2051570713487480">Li et al. (2002)</xref> show that 3D advertising is more effective in than 2D in the case of a geometrical product, though <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-2051570713487480">Klein (2003)</xref> suggests that this effectiveness is limited to research products. A comparative approach could therefore identify situations where telepresence is effective in terms of influencing the attitude towards the product.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<table-wrap id="table6-2051570713487480" position="float">
<label>Appendix 1.</label>
<caption><p>Measurement scales used</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-2051570713487480" xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Constructs</th>
<th align="center">Items</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Measurement scale of beliefs about the attributes of the watch (6 items) –<bold>[Cp]</bold></td>
<td>– This watch is aesthetic (Cp1).<break/>– This watch is comfortable to wear (Cp2).<break/>– <italic>This watch will suit you well.<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-2051570713487480">*</xref></italic>
<break/>– This watch is functional (Cp4).<break/>– <italic>This watch is fashionable.<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-2051570713487480">*</xref></italic>
<break/>– The strap of this watch is of good quality (Cp6).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Measurement scale of attitude toward the ad (3 items) – <bold>[Aad]</bold></td>
<td>– ‘This ad leaves me totally indifferent’ – ‘This ad does not leave me totally indifferent’ (Aad1)<break/>– ‘I really like this ad’ – ‘I really dislike this ad’ (Aad2)<break/>– ‘I would willingly see this ad again’ – ‘I have no wish to see this ad again’ (Aad3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Measurement scale of attitude toward the product (3 items) – <bold>[Ap]</bold></td>
<td>– ‘My opinion of this watch is’: Good–Bad (Ap1)<break/>– ‘I don’t like this watch at all’ – ‘I like this watch very much’ (Ap2)<break/>– ‘This watch is pleasant’ – ‘This watch is unpleasant’ (Ap3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Measurement scale of emotions (12 items) <bold>[EMO]</bold></td>
<td>– Happy–Unhappy (EMO1)<break/>– Unaroused–Aroused (EMO2)<break/>– <italic>Melancholic –Contented</italic> <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-2051570713487480">*</xref>
<break/>– Excited–Calm (EMO4)<break/>– Annoyed–Pleased (EMO5)<break/>– Relaxed–Stimulated (EMO6)<break/>– <italic>Despairing–Hopeful<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-2051570713487480">*</xref></italic>
<break/>– <italic>Satisfied–Unsatisfied<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-2051570713487480">*</xref></italic>
<break/>– <italic>Dull–Jittery<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-2051570713487480">*</xref></italic>
<break/>– <italic>Sleepy–Wide awake<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-2051570713487480">*</xref></italic>
<break/>– <italic>Sluggish–Frenzied<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-2051570713487480">*</xref></italic>
<break/>– <italic>Bored–Relaxed<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-2051570713487480">*</xref></italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Measurement scale of telepresence (7 items) <bold>[TELP]</bold></td>
<td>– During the exercise, I felt I was in the world the computer created (TELP 1)<break/>– During the exercise, I forgot I was in the middle of an experiment (TELP2)<break/>– During the exercise, my body was in the room but my mind was inside the world created by the computer (TELP3)<break/>– The computer–generated world seemed to me ‘somewhere I visited’ rather than ‘something I saw’ (TELP4)<break/>– I felt I was more in the ‘computer world’ than the real world around me when I was going through the exercise (TELP5)<break/>– <italic>I forgot about my immediate surroundings when I was navigating through the exercise.<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-2051570713487480">*</xref></italic>
<break/>– <italic>When the computer exercise was over, I felt like I came back to the real world after a journey.</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-2051570713487480">*</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-2051570713487480">
<label>*</label>
<p>Items in italics were not included in the analysis because of their low factor contribution</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table7-2051570713487480" position="float">
<label>Appendix 2.</label>
<caption><p>Results of the CFA on the measurement scales.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table7-2051570713487480" xlink:href="10.1177_2051570713487480-table7.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Estimation parameter</th>
<th align="center">Estimation parameter</th>
<th align="center">Standard error</th>
<th align="center">Stat T</th>
<th align="center">Probability level</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>(TELP)-1-&gt;[TELP1]</td>
<td>0.682</td>
<td>0.034</td>
<td>19.939</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(TELP)-2-&gt;[TELP2]</td>
<td>0.688</td>
<td>0.034</td>
<td>20.398</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(TELP)-3-&gt;[TELP3]</td>
<td>0.759</td>
<td>0.029</td>
<td>26.133</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(TELP)-4-&gt;[TELP4]</td>
<td>0.745</td>
<td>0.030</td>
<td>24.882</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(TELP)-5-&gt;[TELP5]</td>
<td>0.691</td>
<td>0.034</td>
<td>20.569</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(EMO)-11-&gt;[EMO1]</td>
<td>0.816</td>
<td>0.023</td>
<td>35.472</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(EMO)-12-&gt;[EMO2]</td>
<td>0.797</td>
<td>0.024</td>
<td>32.694</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(EMO)-13-&gt;[EMO4]</td>
<td>0.640</td>
<td>0.035</td>
<td>18.028</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(EMO)-14-&gt;[EMO5]</td>
<td>0.586</td>
<td>0.039</td>
<td>15.076</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(EMO)-15-&gt;[EMO6]</td>
<td>0.733</td>
<td>0.029</td>
<td>25.215</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(Cp)-16-&gt;[Cp1]</td>
<td>0.765</td>
<td>0.029</td>
<td>26.621</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(Cp)-17-&gt;[Cp2]</td>
<td>0.682</td>
<td>0.034</td>
<td>19.934</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(Cp)-18-&gt;[Cp4]</td>
<td>0.720</td>
<td>0.032</td>
<td>22.734</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(Cp)-19-&gt;[Cp6]</td>
<td>0.658</td>
<td>0.036</td>
<td>18.420</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(Ap)-20-&gt;[Ap1]</td>
<td>0.876</td>
<td>0.017</td>
<td>51.266</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(Ap)-21-&gt;[Ap2]</td>
<td>0.848</td>
<td>0.019</td>
<td>44.480</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(Ap)-22-&gt;[Ap3]</td>
<td>0.811</td>
<td>0.022</td>
<td>37.068</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(Aad)-23-&gt;[AD1]</td>
<td>0.781</td>
<td>0.027</td>
<td>29.170</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(Aad)-24-&gt;[AD2]</td>
<td>0.830</td>
<td>0.024</td>
<td>35.013</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>(Aad)-25-&gt;[AD3]</td>
<td>0.754</td>
<td>0.029</td>
<td>26.429</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-2051570713487480">
<p><bold>TELP</bold>: telepresence</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-2051570713487480">
<p><bold>EMO</bold>: emotions triggered by navigating in the ad</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-2051570713487480">
<p><bold>Cp</bold>: beliefs about the product attributes</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-2051570713487480">
<p><bold>Ap</bold>: attitude toward the product</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-2051570713487480">
<p><bold>Aad</bold>: attitude toward the ad</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</app-group>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of conflicting interest</label>
<p>The author declares that there is no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1-2051570713487480">
<label>1.</label>
<p>The Sobel test aims to verify whether the indirect effect of X on Y via M is significantly different from zero. For <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr93-2051570713487480">Preacher and Hayes (2004)</xref>, this test is applicable when the sample size is greater than 50 observations, which is the case in our study. It is then a matter of calculating a ratio z and checking whether its value is greater than or equal to 1.96 for a 5% significance level.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aaker</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stayman</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hagerty</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Warmth in advertising: measurement, impact, and sequences effects</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jolson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Technical wording in advertising: implications for market segmentation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing</source> <volume>44</volume> (<issue>Winter</issue>): <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arbuckle</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wothke</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>AMOS 4.0 User’s Guide</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SmallWaters Corp.-SPSS Inc</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ariely</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Controlling the information flow: Effects on consumers’ decision making and preferences</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ayerson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Reviewing the research on hypermedia-based learning</article-title>. <source>Journal of Research on Computing in Education</source> <volume>28</volume> (<issue>Summer</issue>): <fpage>500</fpage>–<lpage>525</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bagozzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Copinath</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nyer</surname><given-names>PU</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The role of emotions in marketing</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>184</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baile</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Louati</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>L’efficience du SI utilisateur final: un modèle de causalité de la qualité de service sur la satisfaction</article-title>. <source>Système d’Information &amp; Management</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>The moderator–mediator variable distinction in social psychological research: Conceptual, strategic and statistical considerations</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source> <volume>51</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1182</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1960</year>) <article-title>Consumer behaviour as risk taking</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Proceedings of The American Marketing Association, Dynamic Marketing for a changing World</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Marketing Association</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>The effect on advertising on attitude accessibility, attitude confidence, and the attitude behaviour relationship</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source> <volume>2</volume> (<issue>September</issue>): <fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>279</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Billinhurst</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weghorst</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The use of sketch maps to measure cognitive maps virtual of environments</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceeding of Virtual Reality Annual International Symposium (VRAIS ‘95)</conf-name>. <conf-loc>Washington, DC: IEEE Computer Society</conf-loc>, pp.<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Biocca</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The Cyber’s dilemma: Progressive embodiment in virtual environments</article-title>. <source>Journal of Computer Mediated Communication</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>). Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.207.201.161.120/jcmc/vol2/">www.207.201.161.120/jcmc/vol2/</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 13 March 2007</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Biocca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daugherty</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Experiential e-commerce: Relationship of physical and social presence to consumer learning, attitudes, and decision-making</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of Presence Conference</conf-name>, <conf-date>May</conf-date>, <conf-loc>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bourgeon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Filser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Les apports du modèle expérientiel à l’analyse du comportement dans le domaine culturel</article-title>. <source>Recherche et Applications en Marketing</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>The impact of feelings on ad-based affect and cognition</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing Research</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Deconstructing and operationalizing interactivity: An online advertising perspective</article-title>. <source>Journal of Information Technology Theory and Application</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cauberghe</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Geuens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Pelsmacker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Context effects of TV programme-induced interactivity and telepresence on advertising responses</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Advertising</source> <volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>641</fpage>–<lpage>663</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chaiken</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eagly</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Communication modality as a determinant of message persuasiveness and message comprehensibility</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>605</fpage>–<lpage>614</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>On the use, usefulness, and ease of use of structural equation modeling in MIS research</article-title>. <source>MIS Quarterly</source> <volume>19</volume> (<issue>June</issue>): <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>An extended perspective on the role of emotion in advertising processing</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>McAlister</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rothschild</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Advances in Consumer Research</source>, <volume>20</volume>. <publisher-loc>Provo, UT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Association for Consumer Research</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>692</fpage>–<lpage>697</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bentler</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Estimates and tests in structural equation modeling</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hoyle</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Structural Equation Modelling</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clore</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Cognitive phenomenology: Feelings and the construction of judgment</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tesser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Construction of Social Judgment</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clore</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wyer</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dienes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gasper</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gohm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Isbell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Affective feelings as feedback: Some cognitive consequences</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clore</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Theories of Mood and Cognition: A User’s Handbook</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cronbach</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1951</year>) <article-title>Coefficient alpha and the internal structure of tests</article-title>. <source>Psychometrica</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Damasio</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Descartes’ error: Emotion</article-title>. In: <source>Reason and The Human Brain</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Grosset/Putnam</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Perceived usefulness, perceived ease of use and user acceptance of technology</article-title>. <source>MIS Quarterly</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>339</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Debbabi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baile</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Creating Telepresence in Virtual Environments: Overview and Critical Perspectives</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>(ed.) <source>The Encyclopedia of Virtual Communities and Technologies</source>. <publisher-loc>USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Idea Group Reference</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Debbabi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daassi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baile</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Effect of online 3D advertising on consumer responses: The mediating role of telepresence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing Management</source> <volume>26</volume>(<issue>9–10</issue>): <fpage>967</fpage>–<lpage>992</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Derbaix</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>L’impact des réactions affectives induites par les messages publicitaires: une analyse tenant compte de l’implication</article-title>. <source>Recherche et Applications en Marketing</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Derbaix</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Pour un développement des mesures de l’affectif en marketing: synthèse des pré-requis</article-title>. <source>Recherche et Applications en Marketing</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Diesbach</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jeandrain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Online immersion and emotional reactions online: Proposal of an integrative model</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Yong-Uon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Youjae</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Asian Advances in Consumer Research</source> <volume>6</volume>. <publisher-loc>Duluth, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Association for Consumer Research</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>244</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eagly</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chaiken</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>The Psychology of Attitudes</source>. <publisher-loc>Texas</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harcourt, Brace, Jovanovich</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edens</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>How do adolescent process advertisements? The influence of ad characteristics, processing objective and gender</article-title>. <source>Contemporary Educational Psychology</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>450</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gangadharbatla</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The novelty of 3D product presentations online</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interactive Advertising</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Evrard</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pras</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Market – études et recherches en marketing</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nathan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jim</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Influence of image interactivity technology on approach responses towards an online retailer</article-title>. <source>Internet Research: Electronic Networking Applications and Policy</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fishbein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ajzen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <source>Beliefs, Attitudes, Intention and Behavior: An Introduction to Theory and Research</source>. <publisher-loc>Reading, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Addison-Wesley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fornel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larcker</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Evaluating structural equation models with unobservable variables and measurement error</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing Research</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Avons</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Using behaviour realism to estimate presence: A study of the utility of postural responses to motion stimuli</article-title>. <source>Presence</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The influence of virtual direct experience (VDE) on on-line ad message effectiveness</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advertising</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grigorovici</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Persuasive effects of presence in immersive virtual environments</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Riva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davide</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ijsselsteijn</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Being There: Concepts, Effects and Measurement of User Presence in Synthetic Environments</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ios Press</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hand</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A survey of 3D interaction techniques</article-title>. <source>Computer Graphics Forum</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Havlena</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holbrook</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>The varieties of consumption experience: Comparing two typologies of emotions in consumer behavior</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source> <volume>13</volume> (<issue>December</issue>): <fpage>394</fpage>–<lpage>404</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heeter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>‘Being there: The subjective experience of presence</article-title>. <source>Presence: Teleoperators and Virtual Environments</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>262</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heeter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Communication research on consumer VR</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Biocca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Communication in the Age of Virtuality</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heeter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Interactivity in the context of designed experiences</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interactive Advertising</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jiad.org">www.jiad.org</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 13 March 2007</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>How to acquire customers on the web</article-title>. <source>Harvard Business Review</source> <volume>78</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Marketing in hypermedia computer-mediated environments: Conceptual foundations</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing</source> <volume>60</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holbrook</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hirschman</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>The experiential aspects of consumption: Consumer fantasies, feelings, and fun</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source> <volume>9</volume> (<issue>September</issue>): <fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Homer</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Message framing and the interrelationships among ad-based feelings, affect, and cognition</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advertising</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Consumer responses to perceived telepresence in the online advertising environment: the moderating role of involvement</article-title>. <source>Marketing Theory</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brusilovsky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Adaptive navigation support in 3D e-commerce activities</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <conf-name>Proceedings of Workshop on Recommendation and Personalization in eCommerce at the 2nd International Conference on Adaptive Hypermedia and Adaptive Web-Based Systems (AH’2002)</conf-name>. <conf-loc>Malaga</conf-loc>, pp.<fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyun</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Keefe</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Virtual destination image: Testing a telepresence model</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business Research</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Izard</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1972</year>) <source>The Face of Emotion</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Appleton-Century-Crofts</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Izard</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>) <source>Human Emotions</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>EJ Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jeandrain</surname><given-names>A-C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Consumer reactions in a realistic virtual shop: Influence of buying style</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interactive Advertising</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benbasat</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Virtual product experience: Effects of visual and functional control of products on perceived diagnosticity and flow in electronic shopping</article-title>. <source>Journal of Management Information Sys</source>tems <volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vallaster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Creating emotions via B2C websites</article-title>. <source>Business Horizons</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>419</fpage>–<lpage>428</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kempf</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Consumer processing of product trial and the influence of prior advertising: A structural modeling approach</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing Research</source> <volume>35</volume> (<issue>August</issue>): <fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Effects of presence on memory and persuasion</source>. PhD thesis, <publisher-name>University of North California</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Chapel Hill</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Biocca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Telepresence via television: Two dimensions of telepresence may have different connections to memory and persuasion</article-title>. <source>Journal of Computer Mediated Communication</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>). Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol3/issue2/kim.html">jcmc.indiana.edu/vol3/issue2/kim.html</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 24 May 2007</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kisielius</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sternthal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Detecting and explaining vividness effects in attitudinal judgments</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing Research</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klatzky</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lederman</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matula</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Imagined haptic exploration in judgments of object properties</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Memory and Cognition</source> <volume>17</volume> (<issue>March</issue>): <fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Evaluating the potential of interactive media through a new lens: search versus experience goods</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business Research</source> <volume>41</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Creating virtual experiences: The role of telepresence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interactive Marketing</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koufaris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Applying the technology acceptance model and flow theory to online consumer behavior</article-title>. <source>Information Systems Research</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krugman</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1965</year>) <article-title>The impact of television advertising: Learning without involvement</article-title>. <source>Public Opinion Quarterly</source> <volume>29</volume> (<issue>Fall</issue>): <fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>356</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lemoine</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albertini</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>La prise en compte des variables situationnelles dans les politiques d’approvisionnement des distributeurs</article-title>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the 1st International Congres in Marketing Trends, ESCP-EAP</conf-name>, <conf-date>November</conf-date>, <conf-loc>Paris</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lessiter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keogh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davidoff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A cross-media presence questionnaire: The ITC-sense of presence inventory</article-title>. <source>Presence: Teloperators &amp; Virtual Environments</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>282</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daugherty</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Biocca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Characteristics of virtual experience in electronic commerce: A protocol analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interactive Marketing</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daugherty</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Biocca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Impact of 3-D advertising on product knowledge, brand attitude and purchase intention: The mediating role of presence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advertising</source> <volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lightner</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>What users want in e-commerce design: Effects of age, education and income</article-title>, <source>Ergonomics</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1–3</issue>): <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lombard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Resources for the study of presence: Presence explication</article-title>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nimbus.temple.edu/~mlombard/Presence/explicat.htm">nimbus.temple.edu/~mlombard/Presence/explicat.htm</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 3 September 2000</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lombard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ditton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>At the heart of it all: The concept of presence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>). Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ascusc.org/jcmc/vol3/issue2/lombard.html">www.ascusc.org/jcmc/vol3/issue2/lombard.html</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 13 March 2007</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kakkar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>The psychological situation as a determinant of consumer behavior</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Schlinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Advances in Consumer Research</source>, <volume>2</volume>. <publisher-loc>Missouri</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Association for Consumer Research</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>453</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nowlis</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Information integration across online and offline shopping environments and its effects on consumers’ purchase decisions</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Biocca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <conf-name>Proceedings of the Experiential E-Commerce Conference (CD-ROM)</conf-name>. <conf-loc>East Lansing, MI: Michigan State University</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Macias</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A preliminary structural equation model of comprehension and persuasion on interactive advertising brand web sites</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interactive Advertising</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>MacInnis</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jaworski</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Information processing from advertisements: Toward an integrative framework</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing</source> <volume>53</volume> (<issue>October</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Assessing the dimensionality and structure of the consumption experience: evaluation, feeling and satisfaction</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>451</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kamins</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>The use of product sampling and advertising: Effects of sequence of exposure and degree of advertising claim exaggeration on consumers’ belief strength, belief confidence and attitudes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing Research</source> <volume>25</volume> (<issue>August</issue>): <fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mehrabian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <source>An Approach to Environmental Psychology</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Meyers-Levy</surname></name>
<name><surname>Malaviya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Consumers’ processing of persuasive advertisements: An integrative framework of persuasion theories</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing</source> <volume>63</volume> (<issue>special issue</issue>): <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mirapaul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>3-D space as new frontier</article-title>. <source>The New York Times on the Web</source>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/technology/05SPAC.html">www.nytimes.com/2000/10/05/technology/05SPAC.html</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 13 March 2007</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr84-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McMullen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Measuring multiple emotion responses to single television commercial</article-title>. <source>Advances in Consumer Research</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr85-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>L’effet de la visite d’un site Internet sur l’image de marque</source>. PhD thesis, <publisher-name>Université Paul Cézanne</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Aix-Marseille III</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr86-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Munch</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swasy</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Rhetorical question, summarization frequency, and argument strength effects on recall</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr87-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nah</surname><given-names>F-HF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eschenbrenner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeWester</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Enhancing brand equity through flow and telepresence: A comparison of 2D and 3D virtual worlds</article-title>. <source>MIS Quarterly</source> <volume>35</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>731</fpage>–<lpage>747</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr88-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Najjar</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Multimedia information and learning</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Multimedia and Hypermedia</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr89-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>Y-F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Measuring the customer experience in online environments: A structural modeling approach</article-title>. <source>Marketing Science</source> <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr90-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nunnally</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <source>Psychometric Theory</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr91-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Representativeness, relevance, and the use of feelings in decision making</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source> <volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr92-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pracejus</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Affect monitoring and the primacy of feelings in judgment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source> <volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr93-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Preacher</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>SPSS and SAS procedures for estimating indirect effects in simple mediation models</article-title>. <source>Behavior Research Methods, Instruments and Computers</source> <volume>36</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>731</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr94-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pugnetti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meehan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mendozzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Psychophysiological correlates of virtual reality: A review</article-title>. <source>Presence</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>384</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr95-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Raden</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Strength related attitude dimensions</article-title>. <source>Social Psychology Quarterly</source> <volume>48</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>312</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr96-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>A. R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Monore</surname><given-names>K. B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>The moderating effect of prior knowledge on cue utilization in product evaluations</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr97-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roussel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Durrieu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campoy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>El Akermi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Méthode d’équations structurelles: recherche et applications en Gestion</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Economica</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr98-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clore</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>How do I feel about it? Informative functions of affective states</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forgas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Affect, Cognition, and Social Behaviour</source>. <publisher-loc>Toronto, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hogrefe</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr99-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bless</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bohner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Mood and persuasion: Affective states influence the processing of persuasive communications</article-title>. <source>Advances in Experimental Social Psychology</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr100-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A comparative analysis of three communication formats: Advertising, infomercial and direct experience</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advertising</source> <volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr101-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dalal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A Communication view of web page perception</article-title>. <source>Journal of Current Issues and Research in Advertising</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr102-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Integrating information from advertising and product trial: Processes and effects on consumer responses to product information</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing Research</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr103-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swinyard</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Information response models: An integrated approach</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr104-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swinyard</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Attitude behaviour consistency: The impact of product trial versus advertising</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing Research</source> <volume>20</volume> (<month>August</month>): <fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr105-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steuer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Defining virtual reality: Dimensions determining telepresence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Communication</source> <volume>42</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr106-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The effects of virtual reality on consumer learning: an empirical investigation</article-title>. <source>MIS Quarterly</source> <volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>673</fpage>–<lpage>697</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr107-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tomkins</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1962</year>) <source>Affect, Imagery, Consciousness</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr108-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Premarket forecasting of really-new products</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing</source> <volume>60</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr109-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qualls</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chicos</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Validation and lessons from the field: Application of information acceleration</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marketing Research</source> <volume>34</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr110-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Don’t keep your internet customers waiting too long at the (virtual) front door</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interactive Marketing</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr111-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Westbrook</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>The dimensionality of consumer emotion patterns and consumer satisfaction</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source>, <volume>June</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr112-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Witmer</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Measuring presence in virtual environments: A presence questionnaire</article-title>. <source>Presence</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr113-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Communication advertising versus direct experience when both search and experience attribute are present</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>708</fpage>–<lpage>718</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr114-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>The harassed decision maker: Time pressures, distraction, and the use of evidence</article-title>, <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>561</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr115-2051570713487480">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yalch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elmore-Yalch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>The effect of numbers on the route of persuasion</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source> <volume>11</volume> (<issue>June</issue>): <fpage>522</fpage>–<lpage>527</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>