<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjsa</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Social Archaeology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1469-6053</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-2951</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1469605311433368</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1469605311433368</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The <italic>kouros</italic> of Keratea: Constructing subaltern pasts in contemporary Greece</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Plantzos</surname><given-names>Dimitris</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1469605311433368"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1469605311433368">Department of History and Archaeology, University of Ioannina, Greece</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1469605311433368">Dimitris Plantzos, 66 Ethnikis Antistasis Street, GR 17237 Daphne, Greece Email: <email>dplantzo@cc.uoi.gr</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>220</fpage>
<lpage>244</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Classical antiquity has been deployed in contemporary Greece as an agent of national-identity forging, and images of archaeological artifacts often feature in the public discourse, used to support state ideologies and promote national culture at home and abroad. This article, however, deals with a number of recently circulated images, designed in the margins of modern society in order to convey a defiantly anti-state message. Such images are manipulated according to the strategies devised and repeatedly applied by nationalist rhetoric in the nineteenth and the twentieth centuries, though their outcome is markedly different: rather than promoting historical continuity and social cohesion they create a disturbing sense of rupture. These irreverent images are projected as ‘minority reports’ against hitherto established ideologies, challenging their hegemony by adopting their own technologies of normalization and assimilationism. As weapons against the supremacy of the state, these performative declarations of a peculiar anti-state nationalism seem to threaten the integrity of the nation state considerably more than other, external forces are feared to do.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>classical antiquity</kwd>
<kwd>classical reception</kwd>
<kwd>globalization</kwd>
<kwd>Greece</kwd>
<kwd>local identities</kwd>
<kwd>nationalism</kwd>
<kwd>postcoloniality</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A poster featuring an ancient Greek statue was widely circulated in Athens in late March and April 2011 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1469605311433368">Figure 1</xref>). Posters showing pieces of classical art are not rare in contemporary Greece: ancient ruins, fragmentary statues or dilapidated pots have been invariably used to promote anything from food and drink to the country’s own tourist attractions. This particular poster, however, was a rather special case as it was issued to advertise the ‘Keratea Resistance Festival’, a three-day long series of concerts, theater performances, art exhibitions, ‘workshops’ and other cultural events organized by local groups in a town of about 7000 inhabitants in the south-eastern part of the Attic peninsula, approximately 40 km southeast of the Greek capital city of Athens. Strong protests, often resorting to violence and sabotage, erupted in the area in December 2010 following the Greek government’s decision to build a sanitary landfill in Keratea’s vicinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1469605311433368">Athens News Web, 2011</xref>). As local groups were reinforced by sympathizers from the wider region, violent clashes with riot police ensued, while the Greek government insisted that the construction of the landfill would go ahead as planned. Night after night stones and fire bottles (‘Molotov cocktails’) were thrown against law enforcement officers, police cars were damaged and the area’s main thoroughfares were sabotaged in order to prevent construction workers from accessing the site where the landfill was to be built. At least once, the family of a local policeman was terrorized by the ‘rebels’ when they threatened to burn his home.
<fig id="fig1-1469605311433368" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Poster of the ‘Keratea Resistance Festival’ (April 2011). Source: tribe4mian.wordpress.com.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1469605311433368-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>According to the police, by mid-April 2011, ‘approximately 1200 people participated in the clashes in various ways, throwing thousands of fire bottles against the police’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1469605311433368">Souliotis and Onisenko, 2011</xref>). Given that ‘the struggle spirit of the Keratea citizens […] has no limits’ (as the Anglophone blog <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1469605311433368">keeptalkinggreece, 2011</xref>, was reporting at the time), clashes went on for several months, until the state seemed to withdraw, perhaps temporarily, seeking to settle the matter in court. Keratea, and especially the site of Ovriokastro (‘Fortress of the Jew’) where the landfill was to be situated, was declared by its inhabitants to be in a state of siege, and the withdrawal of the construction teams and police forces from the area in April 2011 was greeted by the locals as ‘liberation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1469605311433368">Sxoliastesxwrissynora, 2011</xref>). Playing with the site’s name, they were able to declare Ovriokastro an <italic>aparto kastro</italic> (‘unconquerable fortress’). It was in this context that ‘the largest resistance festival in Greek chronicles’, as the Keratea festival was dubbed by its organizing committee (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1469605311433368">Roadartist, 2011</xref>), took place and an ancient Greek statue found its way to the epicenter of modern controversy. As it happens, the statue in question is the so-called ‘<italic>kouros</italic> of Keratea’, a statue of a youth made in the mid-sixth century BC, presumably as the funerary monument of a young man (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1469605311433368">Figure 2</xref>). Its afterlife as the symbol of anti-state resistance in the hands of a small local community in the early twenty-first century AD provides ample opportunity to study the ways classical heritage is received in a contemporary world where the ‘classical’ is itself in desperate need of reaffirming its identity. The <italic>kouros</italic> was by no means a stranger to this controversy when the poster was circulated: antiquities excavated in the area have long been employed in the debate over the landfill and, more generally, Keratea’s exceptional standing in modern Greek culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1469605311433368">Antixyta, 2011a</xref>, where the <italic>kouros</italic> is prominently featured in a ‘15-year-old struggle’ employing ‘books, art, culture’).
<fig id="fig2-1469605311433368" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>The <italic>kouros</italic> of Keratea (Athens, National Archaeological Museum inv. no. 1904). Photo: author.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1469605311433368-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<sec id="sec1-1469605311433368"><title>The <italic>kouros</italic> and the nation</title>
<p>The National Archaeological Museum in Athens was built between 1866 and 1889 based on plans designed by German architect Ludwig Lange, later amended by the father of Greek neo-classical architecture, Ernst Ziller (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1469605311433368">Kaltsas, 2007</xref>: 15–23). Ziller, the Saxon architect whose aesthetic shaped much of bourgeois Greek sensibility towards the antique and the ways it can be revived within modern taste, was ultimately responsible for the Museum’s monumental façade in the form of a four-pillared porch in full Ionic order and the building’s overall tame neo-classical outlook (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1469605311433368">Kardamitsi-Adami, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1469605311433368">Kasimati, 2010</xref>). The Museum houses an impressive range of ancient Greek artifacts, as well as archaeological remains of several prehistoric cultures once active in the Aegean, generally considered as ‘Greek’ – including Cycladic figurines and vessels from the third millennium BC and the famous Santorini frescoes from the second millennium BC. Through systematic classification, linear display and a somewhat esoteric labeling system the artifacts in question are presented to the public as tangible evidence of the nation’s trajectory through the ages and, ultimately, as proof – should any be needed – of Greece’s privileged position as the owner, keeper and beneficiary of (its) classical heritage. As Yannis Hamilakis has shown, state archaeology in Greece has been entrusted, since the early nineteenth century, with the task of ‘rediscovering’ classical heritage so that Greeks may ‘portray themselves to themselves and to others as the heirs of that heritage’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1469605311433368">Hamilakis, 2007</xref>: 76). The neo-classical ideal, created in the royal courts and upper-middle-class mansions of Europe but happily transplanted in the desolate plains of a fledgling nation state striving to establish itself as an agent of modernity, suggested that every scrap of ancient Greece, every pot, statue or ruin reminded the world at large that modern Greece was the land where it all began, where the very cradle of western civilization in fact lay. Tarnished by the effects of globalization and the overall de-westernization of world culture, nowadays the neo-classical aesthetic seems alive – or mechanically resuscitated in fact – solely in Greece, where it is continuously being redeployed as a reminder of the country’s existence. More than that, classical antiquity is employed in contemporary Greece as a disciplinary device both at home and abroad, as a forceful reaction against the disapproving gaze of the West. Following a course already mapped in the 1930s, and emulating cultural strategies enforced in other European as well as non-European countries, Greek antiquity has been largely used as a yardstick for the nation’s cohesion as well as a measure of its simultaneous desire for and antithesis to the West (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1469605311433368">Plantzos, 2008</xref>). As a result, Greek modernity appears at once colonialist and colonized, an essentialist identity produced through the intensive reinvention and systematic appropriation of (its) classical past (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1469605311433368">Hamilakis, 2007</xref>: 19–21).</p>
<p>One of the National Museum’s less celebrated artifacts is the ‘<italic>kouros</italic> of Keratea’: found in 1893, the marble statue is considered to be a reworked or unfinished specimen of sixth-century BC Athenian sculpture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1469605311433368">Kaltsas, 2001</xref>: 46). This, and the fragmentary state of the piece (it is missing its lower legs and arms, and bears severe breaks along the left thigh and across the face), has kept the statue in relative obscurity compared to some of its counterparts displayed in the same museum. A <italic>kouros</italic> is the statue of a youth, named after the ancient Greek word for ‘boy’. The type appeared in Greek sculpture in the later seventh century BC and remained in circulation until the early decades of the fifth. Adopted by all major sculpture workshops in Greece at the time – from Athens, the Peloponnese and the Islands to the Greek cities of Asia Minor, including examples from Northern Greece and Cyprus – the <italic>kouros</italic>, alongside its female counterpart, the <italic>kore</italic> (‘maiden’) – are supposed to stand as symbols of human nature at its highest. Beautiful, strong and lively, these boys cut in marble or, more rarely, cast in bronze express the aristocratic ideals of Early Greece, at the time we usually identify as the ‘Archaic period’ (<italic>c</italic>.700–480 BC).</p>
<p>A beautiful body and a brave soul were the ultimate ideals of the Greek aristocracy of the Archaic period, promoting for itself a genealogy going back to the heroic model as described by Homer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1469605311433368">Murray, 1993</xref>: 201–219). The <italic>kouroi</italic> were used to diffuse the aristocratic imagery and the ideology it promoted. They were mostly set up in sanctuaries as votives or in cemeteries (as the specimen from Keratea most certainly was) as burial monuments. Though not portraits of the deceased men as such, the burial <italic>kouroi</italic> were thought to express the essence of their existence. They were usually accompanied by epitaphs naming the deceased and referring to the statue in the first person, as if it was <italic>it</italic>, the statue, addressing the passers-by (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1469605311433368">Svenbro, 1993</xref>). In a famous example, the surviving epitaph of the <italic>kouros</italic> found in Anavyssos, a town a few kilometers south of Keratea, invites the viewer to ‘stand and weep’ for Kroisos – the tomb’s occupant and the statue’s subject – whom Ares ‘destroyed as he was fighting in the front line’, protecting his homeland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1469605311433368">Kaltsas, 2001</xref>: 58). The <italic>kouros</italic> of Anavyssos, also exhibited in the National Museum in Athens, displays some of the basic traits of the type: the youth’s virility and courage, underlined by his idealized beauty and the fact of his premature death (suggested on the sculpture by the soldier’s felt cap the boy is shown wearing; in fact this cap is the only piece of clothing given to him). Well brought up, virtuous and brave, plus mourned by a family with enough means to erect these costly monuments, the youths portrayed by the <italic>kouroi</italic> represented to the whole of Greece the qualities of their class, displaying them for anyone to see in the open air of the community’s cemetery.</p>
<p>In the framework of ancient Greek culture, however, the <italic>kouros</italic> may not be viewed outside the pederastic ethos that shaped much of Archaic Greece (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1469605311433368">Dover, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1469605311433368">Skinner, 2005</xref>: 45–147). While modern scholarship is in great difficulty explaining a deeply disturbing possibility – that good-looking boys such as Kroisos may in fact have been sodomized by their elders on the way to their glorious deaths – some facts seem quite clear. Regardless of whether we side with the postmodern/deconstructionist view that homosexuality was not an issue in classical Greece as it is in modernity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1469605311433368">Halperin, 1990</xref>, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1469605311433368">Foucault, 1978</xref>) or with the modern/historicist one that recognizes ‘Greek Love’ as a fact of life in ancient Greece as in any society (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1469605311433368">Davidson, 2008</xref>), we are nevertheless forced to admit that Greek statues of naked men – as well as those of splendidly dressed, bejeweled Greek maidens – are sensual as much as they are ideal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1469605311433368">Osborne, 2011</xref>: 27–54; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1469605311433368">Squire, 2011</xref>). Whereas the logistics of eternity seem never to have left the minds of Greek sculptors and their patrons, the technologies of earthly love (from courtship to seduction to full-on sexual intercourse) prove to be part of Greek art as much as anything. Nudity, usually reserved for men but also generally acceptable for women after the mid-fourth century BC, was employed to attract attention to the body, its beauty and potential, and this marked the reception of Greek art by its contemporaries as well as by the creators of western aesthetics since the Renaissance.</p>
<p>When Johann Joachim Winckelmann cast his homoerotic gaze onto Greek sculpture – admittedly not the abstract and primitive-looking <italic>kouroi</italic> but the heavily idealized second-hand versions of classical sculpture as copied for Roman clientele in the first centuries AD – it all seemed to be making perfect sense (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1469605311433368">Potts, 2000</xref>: 113–144). Those bodies were able to function both as cultural symbols and objects of desire, and this was, according to Winckelmann’s strongly Romantic views, the essence of Greek art, as well as the secret of its success. Pederastic imagery was thus gradually admitted into the mainstream; after all, western culture was where women were also allowed to cast their own erotic gazes towards their own objects of desire. Somehow, however, the <italic>kouroi</italic> have never managed to escape their homosexual connotations as we are reminded by a <italic>GayMap of Athens, Mykonos and Thessaloniki</italic> published in 2011: featuring the <italic>kouros</italic> of Anavyssos on the cover, it allows its user to interchange the image of the statue with one of a present-day underwear model lurking behind it (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1469605311433368">Figure 3</xref>).
<fig id="fig3-1469605311433368" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><italic>Gay Map 2011</italic> featuring the <italic>kouros</italic> of Anavyssos next to the Parthenon (May 2011).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1469605311433368-fig3.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>In mainstream Greek culture, classical statuary functions, needless to say, as guarantor of the nation’s longevity and reminder of Greece’s exceptional outlook: a procession of ‘Kroisos-lookalikes’ greeted an unsuspecting international audience during the opening ceremony of the Athens 2004 Olympic Games, raising more than a few eyebrows at such unabashed display of full frontal nudity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1469605311433368">Figure 4</xref>). In true Winckelmann-esque fashion, the parade equated (classical) Greek art with the totality of Greek culture – classical as well as prehistoric, post-antique or contemporary even – restating the by then well-rehearsed arguments of historical continuity and aesthetic affinity with the nation’s classical heritage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1469605311433368">Plantzos, 2008</xref>: 11–14). Such visual or verbal rhetoric is the expression of a centrally designed and deployed elite nationalism subordinating all other regions and all other ideas to the needs and ideas of the capital: as it was Athenian rather than Greek art that took precedent in the 2004 Olympic pageant, so it is the Acropolis that stands for all things Greek on the cover of the <italic>GayMap 2011</italic> as in so many other publications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1469605311433368">Yalouri, 2001</xref>: 77–100), and it is the metropolitan, ‘national’ museum in Athens where the <italic>kouroi</italic> from Anavyssos and Keratea (as well as so many antiquities from Mycenae, Santorini and the rest of Greece) are kept in order to compose a coherent, authoritative and self-assured nationalist narrative. Homosexuality and pederasty are of course nowhere to be found in modern state discourse. Ancient Greeks have been severely down-sexed in this aspect: no initiation bonds, no ‘Army of Lovers’, no male-to-male prostitution (it is no wonder then that James Davidson finds that only in modern Greece some seem to believe that ‘Greek men just held hands’; 2008: 122).
<fig id="fig4-1469605311433368" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Greek athletes posing as <italic>kouroi</italic> at the opening ceremony of the Olympic Games in Athens (August 2004). Source: Athens 2004 – Michalis Toubis S.A.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1469605311433368-fig4.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>To this quasi-colonization of images as well as ideas by the national state, the inhabitants of Keratea react by attempting a colonization of their own. A systematic attempt to re-appropriate their native <italic>kouros</italic> is in process, expressed through the poster mentioned earlier (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1469605311433368">Figure 1</xref>) and other means to be discussed in the following sections of this article. This attempt at redefining a local cultural identity – as opposed to a national one – as well as renegotiating the relationship between people, things, and the state is symptomatic of a deep cultural crisis in Greek society, one that the recent economic crisis has brought out in the open: as social cohesion is crumbling under the pressure of economic collapse and the inability of hitherto powerful ideologies to safeguard national unity, state archaeology (centrally controlled notions regarding the nation’s history and its remains) is replaced by local archaeolog<italic>ies</italic>, counter-discourses that question the validity of the old narratives and threaten their very core. As a discourse controlled by the national state, archaeology is deployed as a purely pedagogical device using the distant past in order to inform, instruct and discipline the present. As Homi Bhabha has observed, this creates a tension of temporal rather than historical nature within what he calls ‘the locality of culture’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1469605311433368">1994</xref>: 199–244). The narrative address of the nation is thus threatened by a performative representation of the cultural and the social, a counter-narrative that challenges the nation’s monolithic qualities. This makes the nation appear as a split image of itself:
<disp-quote>
<p>… a form of living that is more complex than ‘community’; more symbolic than ‘society’; […] more hybrid in the articulation of cultural differences and identifications – gender, race or class – than can be represented in any hierarchical or binary restructuring of social antagonism. (1994: 200–201)</p></disp-quote>It might be worth our while to investigate how the <italic>kouros</italic> of Keratea could allow us to chart this tension between the pedagogical and the performative within Greek society.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1469605311433368"><title>Greece between the local and the global</title>
<p>The establishment of Greece as a ‘model kingdom’ in the 1830s, a modern nation state of highly idealistic conception albeit endowed with a rather grim predicament, unleashed a considerable amount of political capital. Its management was negotiated between the Bavarian aristocracy, transplanted in Greece on the appointment of King Otto as the country’s first monarch, on the one hand and the Greek elites on the other, themselves newly arrived from other parts of Europe or the Ottoman Empire itself, where they had cultivated a national identity inspired by their own versions of the Enlightenment, mixed with generous servings of German Romanticism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1469605311433368">Herzfeld, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1469605311433368">Skopetea, 1988</xref>). As soon as the new state was inaugurated, however, it became abundantly clear to anyone involved that it could not possibly fulfill its ostensibly Philhellenic, deeply Orientalist and – quite frankly – utopian destiny. Greece’s inability to espouse modernity (mostly because it could not truly measure up to the standards set by the phantasm of classical <italic>Hellas</italic> to which the modern state owed its existence) exasperated its former supporters who were now feeling that the country’s modernity was destined to remain ‘incomplete’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1469605311433368">Gourgouris, 1996</xref>: 122–154). Accusations of incomplete or inadequate modernity are not of course uncommon in colonialist rhetoric deployed against insubordinate natives refusing to be modernized – be they Greek, Indian, Egyptian or Brazilian (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1469605311433368">Buell, 1994</xref>: 325–343). Throughout the twentieth century, national peripheral cultures retaliated through the promotion of their exceptional value, usually rooted on a largely invented historical past and an impressive array of cultural remains. These disciplinary measures were taken simultaneously abroad and at home where the local intellectuals were invariably faced with an amorphous mass of backward, uneducated, deplorably cultureless and thoroughly un-modern peasantry forming the population of which they were posing as leaders. Ironically enough, it was the culture of this backward peasantry that these self-appointed intelligentsias were using – suitably edited for general consumption, of course – in order to prove their country’s (and their own) international significance and forge a mutually exclusive national identity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1469605311433368">Herzfeld, 1987</xref>: 1–27).</p>
<p>As Frederick Buell has shown in his discussion of India, Japan and other cultures in the periphery of western modernity, such essentializing strategies deployed on behalf of a specific country’s intellectuals are meant to promote cultural continuity as a weapon against their nation’s foes and at the same time pose it as a question central to their people’s existence. In Greece these efforts were largely systematized by the so-called 1930s generation, whose initiative managed to create new ways of thinking ‘Greekness’ within the framework of ‘modernity’ and the ‘West’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1469605311433368">Leontis, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1469605311433368">Tziovas, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1469605311433368">2011</xref>). Combining the national with the modern in a new aesthetic form that would be acceptable both at home and abroad was the task undertaken by the intellectuals of the 1930s generation at the same time when similar movements were developing elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1469605311433368">Colla, 2007</xref>: 234–272; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1469605311433368">Mitter, 2007</xref>). In most of those cases the national self is composed by a fusion of natural environment with the sense of a long and significant historical past. In the case of Greece (though also in those of Egypt or Italy, for example), antiquities were enlisted to supply the visual links to the nation’s past since they formed part of the natural landscape the nation could be seen to inhabit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1469605311433368">Plantzos, 2008</xref>: 20–26). Archaeological artifacts, in particular, like the <italic>kouroi</italic> from Anavyssos and Keratea or the numerous bronzes discovered in the depths of the Aegean Sea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1469605311433368">Kaltsas, 2007</xref>: 276–279), were thought to verify the nation’s ties both to its land and its history as they were gradually being unburied from the very soil such grossly romanticized rhetoric was praising.</p>
<p>In Greece, this kind of concern with the territoriality of the nation, what Thongchai Winichakul has called with reference to nineteenth-century Siam a nation’s ‘Geo-Body’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1469605311433368">Thongchai, 1994</xref>: esp. 16–19,164–174), has now become commonplace. Long before the emotive response to the land displayed ad nauseam by the members of the 1930s generation and other intellectuals and artists since their time, the invention of Greek national space as a ‘natural entity’ to which Greeks belong emotionally and spiritually (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1469605311433368">Sack, 1986</xref>) had led to the creation of a monumental national landscape reinforcing the state’s cohesion and representing its political substance, let alone its historical destiny (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1469605311433368">Peckham, 2001</xref>: 21–37).</p>
<p>The rediscovery of Hellas by the West, albeit on the soil now inhabited by contemporary Greeks, was part of a project on self-awareness, as well as an act of ‘cultural forgetting’, whereby affiliation led to appropriation and exclusion of the ‘natives’ who thus found they had been given a cultural ideal only to be robbed of it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1469605311433368">Goldhill, 2011</xref>: 9–17; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1469605311433368">Marchand, 1996</xref>). If modern Greece was the result of the colonization of classical antiquity by western European Philhellenism, its survival came quickly to depend on the counter-colonization of ‘its’ heritage against those competing for its ownership (of course this enterprise was always advertised as mere ‘de-colonization’, history’s liberation from the overbearing control of the West, with the debate over the ‘repatriation’ of the Elgin marbles being the most famous example: see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1469605311433368">Hamilakis, 2007</xref>: 243–286). To this end, Greece undertakes its own archaeology as a means of surviving in a rapidly changing world system and – ultimately – claiming new kinds of centrality in it. Archaeology is in charge of the production of ancient cultural remains and modern landscapes as cultural <italic>topoi</italic>, sites of national convergence and (often enough as we shall see in the next section) conflict. These are promoted as the nation’s eternal contribution to world civilization as well as the country’s temporal attractions that render it unique world wide. In other words, the Greeks have realized that in order to decolonize (their) classical heritage they need to colonize it anew. As a national project, archaeology in Greece therefore acquires an emancipatory role. And, as several theoreticians writing on nationalism in the 1990s pointed out, the nation becomes sovereign precisely at the moment when its modernity is ‘imagined’ or ‘invented’ on the basis of its antiquity, and its sovereignty stands even when the state is under the political, economic, or cultural control of a distant metropolis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1469605311433368">Chatterjee, 1993</xref>: 3–13, on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1469605311433368">Anderson, 1991</xref>).</p>
<p>Even though self-generated cultural stereotypes tend to backfire from time to time (how many modern Greeks do we know who can actually pass as <italic>kouroi</italic>?), they still form a great part of a country’s identity: admittedly, it is difficult to think of Greece without its Parthenon, its sun and its sea – and this might not be a bad thing altogether. In a famously irreverent paper published in 2002, Michael Herzfeld – inspired, to a certain extent, by Thongchai’s exploration of Thai nationhood through the geographical discourses that shaped Siam – described Greece (which he compared to countries such as Thailand, Japan or Mexico) as a ‘crypto-colony’, a ‘buffer zone between the colonized lands and those as yet untamed’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1469605311433368">Herzfeld, 2002</xref>: 900). ‘Crypto-colonies’ are only nominally independent: although they were never colonized in the strict historical sense, they appear to be constantly feeling the need to revolt against the political, economic and cultural supremacy of the West. Itself a product of neo-classicism, Greece feels that ‘its’ heritage must be reclaimed. The ideological strategies deployed by Greek intellectuals such as those of the 1930s generation and their followers to the present day, as well as the standard political rhetoric of the state, are meant to underline the cultural debt owed to Greece <italic>by</italic> the West, thus balancing the country’s real or perceived shortcomings. As the world economic crisis of 2008 seemed to loom over Greece, eventually leading to a combined EU-IMF intervention in early 2010, the country’s international standing, as well as social peace within its borders, faced significant challenges. Greece’s neo-classical dream was heavily criticized – indeed, ridiculed – by friends and foes alike who became more and more aggravated with the unreliable debtor in their midst, as if the centuries-old tyranny of classical heritage (all those names and dates, not to mention the teaching of dead languages successive generations of schoolchildren worldwide had to endure) finally ended in a cloud of smoke. (Admittedly, the nastiest offence was instigated by the German magazine <italic>Focus</italic> in early 2010 when it published on its cover a digitally manipulated image of Venus de Milo showing the middle finger under the overhead ‘Deceivers in the European Family’; <italic>GR </italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1469605311433368"><italic>Reporter</italic>, 2010</xref>.) To the onslaught of criticism, the Greek authorities and the country’s intellectuals retaliated (mostly) with pompous archaeophile rhetoric and further reminding of the classical past, as with the opening and promotion of the new museum for the Acropolis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1469605311433368">Plantzos, 2011</xref>). As Europe’s former colonial powers are increasingly called in to supervise Greece’s attempts to modernize its economy (in what to some may seem a futile battle against a staggering public deficit and the inevitable predicament of a debt service default), many Greeks – encouraged by the heavy-going rhetoric of some of the country’s most high-profiled intellectuals – seem to realize that their country’s nominal independence is in fact contingent on the political instruction and financial support of the very foreigners they are brought up to despise. ‘Nous devenons une colonie de Bruxelles’, said Greek psychiatrist Dimitris Ploumidis to French daily <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1469605311433368"><italic>Le Monde</italic> in October 2011</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1469605311433368"><italic>Le Monde</italic>, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>While the Greek state was fighting not to lose any more credibility abroad, it was beginning to face strong resistance from interested parties at home, resenting most of the economic and administrative reforms the country’s (‘colonialist’) debtors were suggesting – or ‘demanding’, depending on who your source is. Workers’ unions, various minorities or entire regions raised their voice, often their hands as well, against the state they accused of ‘unpatriotic behavior’ or even ‘treason’ (see the essays in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1469605311433368">Papailias, 2011</xref>). In the case of Keratea the revolt involved reclaiming the local archaeological heritage as if its people realized that emphasis on continuity between ancient and modern Greece is essential if only in order to remind the world that the country is still inhabited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1469605311433368">Herzfeld, 2002</xref>: 919).</p>
<p>Inhabited by whom? A significant facet in the Keratea conflict is the way the local population puts forward its ethnic disassociation from the Greek national body. Throughout the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries the inhabitants of the Messogeia (‘inland’) area in Attica, where Keratea is situated, identified themselves as <italic>Arvanites</italic>, a population group originating from Albanian settlers who moved towards the southern parts of Greece (Boeotia, Attica, Peloponnese and the Islands) at different times between the thirteenth and the sixteenth century AD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1469605311433368">Jochalas, 1971</xref>). Their chief distinguishing feature is their language, <italic>Arvanitika</italic>, an Albanian dialect. In the course of the twentieth century, Arvanites underwent a process of assimilation and for several decades have been identifying themselves as Greeks. This assimilation was part of the long process of Hellenization of modern Greece as a nation state in the late nineteenth and throughout the twentieth century, during which ‘Hellenic’ cultural characteristics were retrospectively imposed on the local populations regardless of their individual traditions, while at the same time certain appealing traits of local culture (such as particular types of dress, food or architecture) were usurped by the metropolitan elites seeking to embellish their recent past (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1469605311433368">Bintliff, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1469605311433368">Gefou-Madianou, 1999</xref>). Though dormant, some of these cultural features, such as the Arvanitika language and the collective memory of non-Greek dissent, can be reactivated whenever the community feels threatened. As Dimitra Gefou-Madianou has argued, the Mesogitic communities have been grossly marginalized by the Athenian elites; this has led them, however, to articulate a quite aggressive counter-discourse, in an attempt to claim back their own traditions, thus asserting their cultural superiority against Athens (1999: 428–429).</p>
<p>Such counter-discourses are evident in the rhetoric surrounding the Keratea conflict, which seeks to attribute the bellicose nature of its inhabitants to their ethnic differentiation, thus justifying their cries for ‘liberation’ against the oppressive state: in a short audio clip widely circulated in February 2011 through YouTube and other social media, an eight-year-old girl identifying herself as Irene (a common Greek name meaning ‘Peace’) is heard saying, in Greek,
<disp-quote>
<p>… my name is Irene but down here we are having war. […] I am not afraid [i.e. of the riot police] because I am an Arvanitissa. The Arvanites are not afraid, they will never be afraid, and they were never afraid in the past. […] I’m here because I want to participate in the fight. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1469605311433368">Forkeratea, 2011</xref>)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Forging a local identity thus becomes a risky business (Irene describes at length riot police firing stun grenades outside her home), a thrilling adventure involving healthy portions of a suitable past, duly symbolized by carefully selected iconic artifacts: an electronic ‘Christmas card’ issued by the blog Antixyta (‘anti-landfill’) in December 2010, thus a few months before the poster discussed in the beginning of this article, features the Keratea <italic>kouros</italic> in anti-gas gear and Santa Claus cap (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1469605311433368">Figure 5</xref>). The inscription ‘Merry X.MAT.s’ alludes to Greek riot police (known as ‘MAT’ after its initials) and the mask to their alleged abuse of tear gas against activists. Although no fire bottles are in sight, we may assume that the <italic>kouros</italic> is conscripted in the fight against the (alien) central state, ready to fight for his place of birth, and at the same time mocking the state’s arsenal – he is well prepared and, like Irene, ‘not afraid’! A few months later, following an outburst of violent clashes between activists and the police in Athens’ central Syndagma Square on 28–29 June, one of the square’s statues, a bronze wrestler in classicizing style erected in 1884, was found ‘disguised’ like an activist: the boy, originally naked in true Greek fashion, was now given a cyclist’s helmet, a red-scarf (presumably to protect him from tear gas), and a fire bottle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1469605311433368">Figure 6</xref>).
<fig id="fig5-1469605311433368" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>‘Merry X.MAT.s’. An electronic Christmas card issued by the Antixyta blog in December 2010. Source: antixyta.blogspot.com.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1469605311433368-fig5.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig6-1469605311433368" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Athens, Syndagma Square. A neo-classical statue of a youth disguised as an activist in June 2011. Photo: poliplane.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1469605311433368-fig6.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>As Thongchai has shown, symbols employed in cultural wars over identity are endowed with the inherent potential for multiple signification (1994: 170–171). It is often the case, and Greece is certainly not an exception here, that specific symbolic elements can be claimed by different groups which proceed to invest them with novel (or revived) meanings and significations. Eastern Attica is a case in point, where local <italic>retsina</italic> wine, once a symbol of un-Hellenic backwardness, has been subsequently elevated into a vital element of Greekness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1469605311433368">Gefou-Madianou, 1999</xref>). Food, in general, has been found to have been essential in the production of national or ethnic identities in the margins of the hegemonic discourse in Greece, catering for the ethnically different or the marginalized, within a wider framework of multiculturalism and globalization (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1469605311433368">Yiakoumaki, 2006</xref>). This is where indigenous archaeologies, created by local communities in response to particular needs or contingencies and in conflict with the centrality of the official archaeological discourse, find their application. Though appropriated by Hellenism, and the modern state’s neo-classical aspirations, the Keratea <italic>kouros</italic> is reclaimed with a vengeance. Its emergence from the soil of Keratea makes the statue part of the local culture, even though the latter is the proud offspring of later settlers! In this constant dialectic of re- and de-appropriation, individual features of the ancient artifact are singled out in order to be highlighted or, in contrast, silenced. The boy, on whose grave the <italic>kouros</italic> once stood, died (one wants to presume) a glorious death fighting for his home territory, so he is a convenient champion of the present-day inhabitants fighting for the integrity of the very <italic>same</italic> soil. So far so good. On the other hand, the boy must have been an aristocrat and he was certainly of no Albanian extraction, so these features are edited out. Moreover, he was quite possibly engaging in pederasty but one had better leave sleeping dogs lie. What this exercise seems to show is that the epicenter of the symbolism at work here is the recently discovered artifact, <italic>not</italic> its cultural history before its burial: the ancient owner of the <italic>kouros</italic>, the man who made ‘him’, those who paid for the statue and those who gazed at it <italic>then</italic>, do not come into the modern equation. Meaning seems to be generated by present retellings of the artifact’s story (not by the rewriting of its history many of us deplore). And the agency this meaning is imbued with lies with the <italic>statue</italic> itself, unearthed – in fact <italic>reborn</italic> – in the not-so-distant past as if in order to confirm the rights of the area’s present inhabitants to their land (and to an exceptional cultural identity).</p>
<p>This blatant display of non-linearity on behalf of a local community, such as Keratea, building its own cultural tradition based on the availability of stock myths and icons, might seem as mere opportunism to an academic trained to assess cultural phenomena based on measurable quantities and facts that may reasonably be established. As the poster in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1469605311433368">Figure 5</xref> shows, however, the idea of playful mockery of the very icons one venerates is not entirely strange to those who ‘fight for Keratea’. Nor is the inherent irony of the whole exercise altogether missed by the modern users of the <italic>kouros</italic>, or of the boy in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1469605311433368">Figure 6</xref>. Random as it may seem, the mixing of ancient and modern stereotypes on masculinity as a synonym for fighting spirit with a relaxed parodying of these same stereotypes may prove extremely subversive. Self-parody works for its instigators, and the joke is invariably on ‘the other guy’, in this case the central state whose national image depends on the integrity of the neo-classical premise on which this image rests (and which the state, through its official representatives, takes rather too seriously). By allowing himself to appear in combat gear, the Keratea <italic>kouros</italic> clearly states his affiliations and sympathies, turning against the central state and its official archaeologies holding him hostage in the metropolitan National Museum in Athens, alongside his ‘brothers’, the other <italic>kouroi</italic> from the Mesogitic plain. Historical awareness, as well as the <italic>performance</italic> of history, has been a task increasingly offered or claimed by the mass public throughout the twentieth century, thus seizing history and archaeology from the hands of the academy and its hitherto privileged representatives. This has led to novel, albeit academically ‘unsound’, modes through which to express one’s relationship to temporality and history, mostly through difference and irony. All images discussed in this article are the products of a certain ‘double vision’; they carry an inherent ambivalence towards the past, and – as Stephen Bann has shown – ought to be viewed as exhibits in what he termed the ‘Ironic Museum’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1469605311433368">1995</xref>).</p>
<p>It seems, therefore, that crypto-colonial discourses are constantly reinvented and redeployed, not only by Greece’s hegemonic intellectuals against the cultural and political superiority of the West, but also by local communities imagining the state to which they belong as an evil stepmother. The ways that crypto-colonial and nationalist discourses are deployed even <italic>within</italic> the national state, so that ethnic or cultural minorities may be provided with the means necessary in order to satisfy their particularist needs, are the topic of the last section in this article.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1469605311433368"><title>National vs cultural landscapes</title>
<p>On 22 March 2011, students from the School of Fine Arts in Athens joined the protests against the landfill by creating a replica of the Keratea <italic>kouros</italic> out of recycled refuse which they displayed at the square in front of the National Archaeological Museum where the original statue is kept (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1469605311433368">Antixyta, 2011b</xref>). According to their statements to the Greek press, by using plastic and other ephemeral and humble materials collected from the garbage, the young students wished to convey to the public their own understanding of the way the central state treats Greece’s ancient culture: like a ‘heap of garbage’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1469605311433368">Eleftherotypia, 2011</xref>). Arguing that society develops through ‘culture’ and not through ‘state bureaucracy’, the activists managed to hit their enemy where it hurts. Claiming that the area of Ovriokastro is an archaeological site, and connecting the <italic>kouros</italic> with it – though its actual findspot is unrelated – the activists made the most of the potential carried by cultural imagery. For a loss to be articulated, mourned, and ultimately avenged, a territorial entity has to be invented, a cultural identity forged, and a continuous historical past, preferably one associated with a particularly meaningful natural and cultural setting, has to be constructed in retrospect. The <italic>kouros</italic> is thus constructed as an emblem of local exceptionalism: even though the statue is not the sole artifact ever discovered in the area, not even the only <italic>kouros</italic> or the most important one for that matter, it features exclusively on material released by the activists. Needless to say, the students’ protest was widely covered by blogs championing the anti-landfill cause. By reiterating the all too familiar by now romanticized notions of a people’s ties with ‘its’ soil, the people of Keratea managed to inverse the process of a land’s nationalization, in a way constructing the central state as a colonial power threatening the political and cultural freedom of a people over whom it has no legitimate authority.</p>
<p>Keratea is thus reinvented as a cultural landscape, where the community’s ‘authentic’ culture is kept alive. Cultural landscapes, be they natural or man-made monuments, archaeological sites, places of real or imaginary historical significance, are launched as loci of collective memory. Antiquity is exploited by communities as part of their cultural capital, in order to tackle challenges on many levels – regional, national, and global (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1469605311433368">Fortunati and Lamberti, 2010</xref>). Institutional archaeology, though by definition in charge of such historical and spatial production, is questioned in Keratea as a colonial agent: by displaying the recycled <italic>kouros</italic> outside the National Museum, the activists challenge the state’s hold over local pasts. This way, sites, monuments and their interpretations enter the collective imaginary only to be renegotiated and reshaped. The empowerment of the local Geo-Body through intensive appropriation of the soil it inhabits and the relics it has come to possess strengthens the sense of common identity (national, local, communal, or other) and renders its fetishism irresistible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1469605311433368">Anderson, 1991</xref>: 131–132; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1469605311433368">Thongchai, 1994</xref>: 131).</p>
<p>Even though the integrity of the landscape (historical and natural) seems to have been turned into a site of conflict between the central state and several local communities in Greece, such as Keratea, the latter appear to have abused the land they occupy as much as the state is alleged to be intending to do. Eastern Attica, where Keratea is situated, emerges as the champion in what in Greek is called <italic>authaireti domisi</italic>; that is, building without state permission (a permit issued by the state is ostensibly required for any kind of building work in the country). In Keratea, in particular, it would appear that unauthorized building is the norm rather than the exception, with an estimated 22,000 buildings out of a total of 27,000 currently existing in the area (that is a staggering 80% overall) lacking the necessary legal authorization (and of course exempted from state and municipal taxes, local rates or any kind of contribution to an otherwise much promoted communal life; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1469605311433368">Forkeratea, 2009</xref>). Rather than being treated as a source of collective shame or a problem that needs to be addressed according to state law and common sense, illegal building has acquired in recent years, especially in communities such as Keratea where it appears most widespread, the status of yet another form of anti-state protest (and yet another demonstration of ethnic diversity, a sort of ‘Arvanites vs Hellenic Greeks’ discourse over land use). Illegal building is often featured in the strong rhetoric of dissidence widely employed by local communities against a central state they perceive as alien and illegitimate. Voiced as expressions of an often violent anti-state, anti-western and ultimately anti-modern anger, such rhetoric threatens the neo-classical foundations of modern Greece and at the same time, quite ironically, confirms those suspecting both the state and its subjects of an ‘incomplete’ commitment to modernity and its goals. Although such outbursts of disobedience (refusal to pay motorway tolls and metro fares, vandalizing state monuments and sabotaging public infrastructure; see Dalakoglou in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1469605311433368">Papailias, 2011</xref>) have in Greece as well as elsewhere been dismissed as emotive, irrational and alarmingly apolitical responses to the current ‘state of things’ that are unsuitable to a modern society’s needs and aspirations, it could be argued that it is through such expressions of public angst that new political subjects arise, as well as their modes of representation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1469605311433368">Gavriilidis, 2009</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1469605311433368">Gallant, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1469605311433368">Gourgouris, 2011</xref>). Despite the danger of succumbing to the inherent Romanticism of these projects, we must admit their efficiency in communication, especially with modern technologies such as mobile phones and the internet, and their ability to appropriate, rehabilitate and relaunch imageries devised previously and for different causes. As the examples discussed here show, these strategies are proving instrumental for the construction of cultural and political identities in the margins of modernity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1469605311433368"><title>From national art to cultural displacement</title>
<p>The new subjects emerging from the cracks of the nation state, be they localist Geo-Bodies and communities defined by ethnic background such as that activated in Keratea or collectives identified by gender or sexuality, have devised novel ways of appropriating ‘national’ art, ways that would appear suitable to their social marginality. National art is by definition used as a pedagogical device, aiming to produce and discipline the national subject. Classical art in Greece, as well as other forms of traditional art such as Byzantine or folk art, has been liberally employed in the formation of a modern Greek identity that was thought suitable to the nation’s needs. As a disciplinary tool, the classical aesthetic – the advocated supremacy of the classical in all expressions of modern life – has systematically been deployed as a top-down intervention against those ideological discourses threatening (or seemingly so) the integrity of the national ideological framework by advantaging unevenness and difference within the national body (rather than a much advertised hegemonic normality). Even though these new, peripheral appropriations of classical art (the Keratea <italic>kouros</italic> on ‘resistance’ posters, the Anavyssos <italic>kouros</italic> on gay pamphlets) employ pretty much the same old techniques of cultural appropriation (namely promoting the image and presuming the ideas it is supposed to convey), they realize a significant change in the standard discourse on classical culture, perhaps one imperceptible to its very instigators. In the words of Homi Bhabha again, such appropriation of hegemonic culture by the social margins
<disp-quote>
<p>… forces us to confront the concept of culture outside <italic>objets d’art</italic> or beyond the canonization of the ‘idea’ of aesthetics, to engage with culture as an uneven, incomplete production of meaning and value […] produced in the act of social survival. (1994: 246–247)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>When deployed by the state, the <italic>kouros</italic> of Keratea conveys a sense of national antiquity, continuity and cohesion, a sense of self-proven importance at once advertised abroad and at home. As seen above (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1469605311433368">Figure 4</xref>), the <italic>kouros</italic> has been effectively used as a simulacrum of national prowess, as a logo promoting state patrimony (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1469605311433368">Anderson, 1991</xref>: 182). In the hands of the Keratea ‘rebels’ or the Greek gay community, on the other hand, the <italic>kouroi</italic> are still used as logos, employed as they are in thoroughly unimaginative ways, monotonously repeating nationalist uses of imagery since the nineteenth century. Yet, these ‘new’ images manage to convey a sense of irreverence and uneasiness, coming across as uncomfortable or disturbing – and taking culture to the streets (as the Christmas card in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1469605311433368">Figure 5</xref> has done).</p>
<p>Whereas in Keratea the activist discourse places an emphasis on the <italic>kouros</italic>’s masculine qualities – he is now as able to fight and overwhelm his opponent as he was then, even if he has to fight to the death – <italic>GayMap 2011</italic> chooses a different course: that virility is still an issue goes without saying, though in the <italic>Map</italic> the idea of getting in touch with Greece’s historical self acquires a wholly different meaning. Mapping the nation, we are told, has been essential in its making (or ‘imagining’) as a historical agent, so we are entitled to think that <italic>GayMap</italic> maps Greece as a queer nation instead, still awesomely ancient and solidly historical, though able to afford modern glories as well, if only one ventures to explore the back alleys of downtown Athens or Mykonos. A modern collective identity is thus confirmed through the imagining of a collective past. Archaeology is declassicalized, and history is performed rather than recited in an attempt to articulate a solid, emphatically assertive sexual subjectivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1469605311433368">Bravmann, 1997</xref>: 97–121). More to the point, the ironic treatment of the iconic <italic>kouros</italic> on the <italic>Map</italic>’s cover seems to claim, quite convincingly, and in a thoroughly unmodern way, that if some mainstream images employing antiquity in order to advertise national continuity seem to us somewhat queer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1469605311433368">Figure 4</xref>), that is because they <italic>are</italic>.</p>
<p>What the Keratea and <italic>GayMap</italic> images have in common, besides their use of the same type of archaeological artifact, is a subversive determination to re-enact culture as a weapon against the forces of normalization employed by metropolitan authority. In that sense, they share a visible element of queerness: they both adopt a performative, highly ironic and devastatingly playful approach to classical culture, a culture that is by now thoroughly sanctified by both the nationalist rhetoric within Greece and the neo-classical aesthetic patented in the West. Even though this kind of appropriation might be easily dismissed as unwarranted trivialization of classical imagery, it ought to be assessed as an attempt to organize a new technology of cultural identity. Through their recolonized images, the <italic>kouroi</italic> are rendered into ‘entangled objects’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1469605311433368">Thomas, 1991</xref>), artifacts actively recontextualized, re-authored even, used to articulate new cultural significations dedicated to a frustrated attempt at quasi-nationalist emancipation. With their meaning of national excellence assumed to be manifest to all, the <italic>kouroi</italic> as displayed at the National Museum in Athens or the posters in Keratea (not to mention the <italic>GayMap</italic> cover) draw upon different genealogies of representation in order to achieve different, indeed opposite goals. More than confirming James Clifford’s old suspicion that, perhaps, ‘we should attempt to think of cultures not as organically unified or traditionally continuous but rather as negotiated, present processes’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1469605311433368">1988</xref>: 273), these discursive formations, articulated as ‘minority reports’ at once separate and separatist, can be seen to deal a fatal blow to the central state’s assimilationist rhetoric of neo-classical normativity.</p>
<p>Whereas state archaeology in Greece has to prove the historicity of the classical past in order to substantiate the ‘Western-ness’ of the Greek present, the minority histories recounted by the <italic>kouroi</italic> as analyzed in this article lead to the construction of a different, emancipatory version of the same past, one we could call ‘subaltern’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1469605311433368">Chakrabarty, 2008</xref>: 97–113). Subaltern pasts are performative reconstructions of narratives hitherto accepted as ‘major’, hegemonic, by socially or culturally marginal groups. Hijacked away from the dominant institutions that once deployed them as agents of normalization, these reconstructed narratives are used to destroy the very sense of cultural inertia they were so instrumental in creating. Culture, rather than being a safe haven of national convergence, is turned once again into a site of conflict and national art becomes a key weapon in anti-state nationalism. If the nation state is – as many fear and some might even wish – finally reaching its historical termination, this ought not to be attributed to the evil forces of globalization, as standard nationalistic rhetoric would have it, but to the replication of nationalism’s irresistible strategies of cultural appropriation by its former subjects, wishing to counter-colonize their vital space within the national geographical or cultural territory. Quite unthinkably, the <italic>kouroi</italic> shed the dust of neo-classical admiration clouding their primitive appeal and emerge as enunciators of cultural identities in the making. More than cultural symbols, these newly authored bodies seem desirable once again. And Winckelmann is, presumably, smiling in his grave.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>Michael Herzfeld and Dimitris Papanikolaou discussed with me different aspects of this topic while my work was in progress. Angeliki Koufou made a number of useful suggestions, and Panos Tsaligopoulos read an earlier version of this article. Finally, three anonymous reviewers offered invaluable comments on previous drafts. I am grateful to them all, as well as to the <italic>JSA</italic> editor, for their help.</p></ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and Spread of Nationalism</source>, <edition>rev. edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Antixyta</collab> (<year>2011a</year>) <source>15 years (1996–2011) of struggle of the inhabitants of Keratea against the landfill through books, art, culture</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://antixyta.blogspot.com/2011/03/15-1996-2011.html">http://antixyta.blogspot.com/2011/03/15-1996-2011.html</ext-link> (in Greek; accessed October 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Antixyta</collab> (<year>2011b</year>) <source>Exhibition by students of the Higher School of Fine Arts in support of the struggle of the people of Keratea</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://antixyta.blogspot.com/2011/04/blog-post_20.html">http://antixyta.blogspot.com/2011/04/blog-post_20.html</ext-link> (in Greek; accessed October 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Athens News Web</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Residents clash with riot police in Keratea</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.athensnews.gr/portal/9/35903">http://www.athensnews.gr/portal/9/35903</ext-link> (accessed October 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>History as competence and performance: Notes on the Ironic Museum</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ankersmit</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kellner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>A New Philosophy of History</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Reaktion Books</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhabha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>The Location of Culture</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bintliff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The ethnoarchaeology of a ‘passive’ ethnicity: The Arvanites of Central Greece</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilakis</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>The Usable Past: Greek Metahistories</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lexington Books</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bravmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Queer Fictions of the Past: History, Culture and Difference</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buell</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>National Culture and the New Global System</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakrabarty</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Provincializing Europe: Postcolonial Thought and Historical Difference</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>The Nation and its Fragments: Colonial and Postcolonial Histories</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <source>The Predicament of Culture: Twentieth-Century Ethnography, Literature, and Art</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colla</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Conflicted Antiquities: Egyptology, Egyptomania, Egyptian Modernity</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>The Greeks and Greek Love</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Phoenix</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dover</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <source>Greek Homosexuality</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Eleftherotypia</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Keratea – a kouros of their own</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.enet.gr/?i=news.el.article&amp;id=261376">http://www.enet.gr/?i=news.el.article&amp;id=261376</ext-link> (in Greek; accessed October 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Forkeratea</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Keratea: Illegal building is the rule</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://forkeratea.blogspot.com/2009/12/blog-post_20.html">http://forkeratea.blogspot.com/2009/12/blog-post_20.html</ext-link> (in Greek; accessed October 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Forkeratea</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>My name is Irene, but down here we are at war</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://forkeratea.blogspot.com/2011/02/blog-post_4143.html">http://forkeratea.blogspot.com/2011/02/blog-post_4143.html</ext-link> (in Greek; accessed October 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fortunati</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamberti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Cultural memories: The making of Europe</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Erill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nünning</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>A Companion to Cultural Memory Studies</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>De Gruyter</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foucault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <source>The History of Sexuality. Volume I: An Introduction</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Vintage Books</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallant</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Collective action and atomistic actors: Labor unions, strikes, and crime in Greece in the post-war era</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Constas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stavrou</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Greece Prepares for the 21st Century</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gavriilidis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Greek riots 2008: A mobile Tiananmen</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Economides</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Monastiriotis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>The Return of Street Politics? Essays on the December Riots in Greece</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Hellenic Observatory, LSE</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gefou-Madianou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Cultural polyphony and identity formation: Negotiating tradition in Attica</article-title>. <source>American Ethnologist</source> <volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>412</fpage>–<lpage>439</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldhill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Victorian Culture and Classical Antiquity. Art, Opera, Fiction, and the Proclamation of Modernity</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gourgouris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Dream Nation: Enlightenment, Colonization and the Institution of Modern Greece</source>. <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gourgouris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Indignant politics in Athens: Democracy out of rage</article-title>. <source><italic>Greek</italic> <italic>Left Review</italic></source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://greekleftreview.wordpress.com/2011/07/17/indignant-politics-in-athens-%e2%80%93-democracy-out-of-rage/#more-1175">http://greekleftreview.wordpress.com/2011/07/17/indignant-politics-in-athens-%e2%80%93-democracy-out-of-rage/#more-1175</ext-link> (accessed October 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>GR</surname><given-names>Reporter</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Greece responds to Germany’s media slap</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.grreporter.info/en/greece_responds_germanys_media_slap/2136">http://www.grreporter.info/en/greece_responds_germanys_media_slap/2136</ext-link> (accessed October 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halperin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>One Hundred Years of Homosexuality</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamilakis</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>The Nation and its Ruins: Antiquity, Archaeology, and National Imagination in Greece</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herzfeld</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <source>Ours Once More: Folklore, Ideology, and the Making of Modern Greece</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pella</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herzfeld</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <source>Anthropology through the Looking Glass: Critical Ethnography in the Margins of Europe</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herzfeld</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The absent presence: Discourses of crypto-colonialism</article-title>. <source>South Atlantic Quarterly</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>899</fpage>–<lpage>926</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jochalas</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>Über die Einwanderung der Albaner in Griechenland</article-title>. <source>Beiträge zur Kenntnis Sudosteuropas und des nähen Orients</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaltsas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Εθνικό Αρχαιολογικό Μουσείο: Tα Γλυπτά</source> <comment>[National Archaeological Museum: The sculpture]</comment>. <publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kapon</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaltsas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>The National Archaeological Museum</source>. <publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John S Latsis Public Benefit Foundation</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kardamitsi-Adami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Έρνστ Τσίλλερ 1837–1923: Η Τέχνη του Κλασικού <italic>[Ernst Ziller 1837–1923: The art of the classical]</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Melissa</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Kasimati</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) (<year>2010</year>) <source>Ερνέστος Τσίλλερ, Αρχιτέκτων (1837–1923)</source> <comment>[Ernst Ziller, Architect (1837–1923)]</comment>. <publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Picture Gallery</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Keeptalkinggreece</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Keratea landfill: Non-stop protest with 2m deep trench in the middle of the road</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.keeptalkinggreece.com/2011/04/14/keratea-landfill-non-stop-protest-with-2m-deep-trench-in-the-middle-of-the-road/">http://www.keeptalkinggreece.com/2011/04/14/keratea-landfill-non-stop-protest-with-2m-deep-trench-in-the-middle-of-the-road/</ext-link> (accessed October 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><collab><italic>Le Monde</italic></collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Nous devenons une colonie de Bruxelles</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lemonde.fr/crise-financiere/article/2011/10/25/nous-devenons-une-colonie-de-bruxelles_1593493_1581613.html">http://www.lemonde.fr/crise-financiere/article/2011/10/25/nous-devenons-une-colonie-de-bruxelles_1593493_1581613.html</ext-link> (accessed October 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leontis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Topographies of Hellenism. Mapping the Homeland</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchand</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Archaeology and Philhellenism in Germany, 1750–1970</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>The Triumph of Modernism. India’s Artists and the Avant-Garde, 1922–1947</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Reaktion Books</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>Early Greece</source>, <edition>2nd edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fontana</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>The History Written on the Classical Greek Body</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papailias</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Beyond the ‘Greek crisis’: Histories, rhetorics, politics</article-title>. <source><italic>Cultural Anthropology </italic>Virtual Issue</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://culanth.org/?q=node/432">http://culanth.org/?q=node/432</ext-link> (posted November 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peckham</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>National Histories, Natural States. Nationalism and the Politics of Place in Greece</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Tauris</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plantzos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Archaeology and Hellenic Identity, 1896–2004: The frustrated vision</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Damaskos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Plantzos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>A Singular Antiquity: Archaeology and Hellenic Identity in 20th-Century Greece</source>. <publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Benaki Museum</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plantzos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Behold the raking geison: The new Acropolis Museum and its context-free archaeologies</article-title>. <source>Antiquity</source> <volume>85</volume>(<issue>328</issue>): <fpage>613</fpage>–<lpage>625</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Potts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Flesh and the Ideal: Winckelmann and the Origins of Art History</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Roadartist</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Keratea Art Resistance Festival</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://roadartist.blogspot.com/2011/04/keratea-art-resistance-festival-8--9-10.html">http://roadartist.blogspot.com/2011/04/keratea-art-resistance-festival-8--9-10.html</ext-link> (accessed October 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sack</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <source>Human Territoriality: Its Theory and History</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Sexuality in Greek and Roman Culture</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skopetea</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <source>Το «Πρότυπο Βασίλειο» και η Μεγάλη Ιδέα. Όψεις του εθνικού προβλήματος στην Ελλάδα (1830–1880</source>) <comment>[The ‘model kingdom’ and the great idea. Aspects of the national problem in Greece (1830–1880)]</comment>. <publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polytypo</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souliotis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Onisenko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Policemen want out of Keratea</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://news.kathimerini.gr/4dcgi/_w_articles_ell_1_17/04/2011_439325">http://news.kathimerini.gr/4dcgi/_w_articles_ell_1_17/04/2011_439325</ext-link> (accessed October 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Squire</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>The Art of the Body: Antiquity and its Legacy</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Svenbro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>Phrasikleia: An Anthropology of Reading in Ancient Greece</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Sxoliastesxwrissynora</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Keratea: The unconquerable Ovriokastro. Scenes from the glorious liberation</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sxoliastesxwrissynora.wordpress.com/2011/04/20/">http://sxoliastesxwrissynora.wordpress.com/2011/04/20/</ext-link> (in Greek; accessed October 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>Entangled Objects: Exchange, Material Culture, and Colonialism in the Pacific</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thongchai</surname><given-names>Winichakul</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Siam Mapped: A History of the Geo-body of a Nation</source>. <publisher-loc>Honolulu</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Hawai’i Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tziovas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>Οι Μεταμορφώσεις του Εθνισμού και το Ιδεολόγημα της Ελληνικότητας στο Μεσοπόλεμο</source> <comment>[The transformations of nationism and the ideology of Greekness in the inter-war period]</comment>. <publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Odysseas</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tziovas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Ο Μύθος της Γενιάς του Τριάντα. Νεοτερικότητα, ελληνικότητα και πολιτισμική ιδεολογία</source> <comment>[The myth of the generation of the thirties. Modernity, Greekness and cultural ideology]</comment>. <publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polis</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yalouri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>The Acropolis. Global Fame, Local Claim</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Berg</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1469605311433368"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yiakoumaki</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>‘Local,’ ‘ethnic,’ and ‘rural’ food: On the emergence of cultural diversity in Greece since its integration in the European Union</article-title>. <source>Journal of Modern Greek Studies</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>445</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<bio><title>Author Biography</title>
<p><bold>Dimitris Plantzos</bold> is Assistant Professor of Classical Archaeology at the University of Ioannina and co-director of the Argos Orestikon Excavation Project in the Prefecture of Kastoria, Greece (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.argosorestikonproject.org/">http://www.argosorestikonproject.org/</ext-link>). He has published on Greek art, the development of classical archaeology in the twentieth century, and on modern receptions of classical heritage. His current research examines official and unofficial archaeologies in contemporary Greece and the ways these are deployed as emancipatory devices at home and abroad.</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>