<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjcm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Composite Materials</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9983</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1530-793X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0021998312454903</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0021998312454903</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Mechanical properties of randomly oriented snake grass fiber with banana and coir fiber-reinforced hybrid composites</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Sathishkumar</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0021998312454903">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0021998312454903"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Navaneethakrishnan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0021998312454903">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0021998312454903">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0021998312454903">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0021998312454903"><label>1</label>Department of Mechanical Engineering, Kongu Engineering College, Erode, Tamilnadu, India</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0021998312454903"><label>2</label>Department of Mechatronics Engineering, Kongu Engineering College, Erode, Tamilnadu, India</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0021998312454903"><label>3</label>Director, EBET Group of Institutions, Kangeyam, Tamilnadu, India</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0021998312454903">TP Sathishkumar, Department of Mechanical Engineering, Kongu Engineering College, Erode, Tamilnadu, India. Email: <email>tpsathish@kongu.ac.in</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>18</issue>
<fpage>2181</fpage>
<lpage>2191</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Composite materials are extensively used in the structural applications due to its enhanced load-bearing capabilities. Mostly, the mechanical properties of the natural fiber-reinforced hybrid composites are better than the single fiber-reinforced composites and almost equal to the synthetic fiber composites. This paper presents the extraction and preparation methodology of the isophtallic polyester composites using the naturally available fibers like snake grass, banana and coir fibers. The tensile and flexural properties of the snake grass fiber-reinforced composites are compared with the snake grass/banana and snake grass/coir fiber-reinforced hybrid composites. The stress–strain curves of the snake grass, snake grass/banana and snake grass/coir fiber composites and the fiber pull-outs in the fractured specimen are analyzed for the higher and lower mechanical properties. The result shows that the snake grass/banana and snake grass/coir fiber composites have the maximum tensile and flexural properties when compared with the snake grass fiber composites.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Natural fiber</kwd>
<kwd>hybrid composites</kwd>
<kwd>mechanical properties</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0021998312454903" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Natural fiber-reinforced composites are prepared by reinforcing the natural fibers with suitable matrix. The natural fibers such as sisal, coir, banana, vakka, date, bamboo, elephant grass, flax, hemp, jute, abaca, pineapple, <italic>Sanasevieria trifasciata</italic> and husk fiber are the widely used fibers for preparing the composites. These fibers also have several technical advantages such as low density, good strength and high modulus, moderate preparation cost and easiness for handling. The several methodologies are implemented to extract the new fibers from the naturally available plants and used to prepare the single fiber composite and hybrid composites. The polyester-based natural fiber-reinforced composites are widely used for preparing the single fiber and hybrid fiber reinforced composites. The natural fibers are differently oriented in polymer matrices which have several advantages such as light weight, moderate preparation cost and easy for preparing the composites. The snake grass (SG) fibers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref></sup> were extracted using the simple water retting process and the tensile properties of these natural fibers were measured according to the standards. The SG fiber were used to prepare the randomly oriented fiber-reinforced polyester composites by hand lay-up method followed by compression molding process and the mechanical properties were studied for various fiber lengths with various fiber volume fractions. The maximum mechanical properties were found at 25% volume fraction of the fiber.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref></sup> The same manufacturing technique was implemented to prepare the sisal fiber-reinforced polyester composites for the longitudinal and randomly oriented fiber content ranging from 0 to 30%. The tensile properties of the randomly oriented fiber composites were found lower than the longitudinally oriented fibers composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0021998312454903">2</xref></sup> The same preparation methodology was adopted for the coir fiber polyester composites. The mechanical properties were studied for the various fiber lengths and fiber contents. The optimum mechanical parameters were also found for making the composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0021998312454903">3</xref></sup> The jute fibers were treated with the oxygen plasma to prepare the polyester composites using the hand layup technique with the constant volume fiber fractions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0021998312454903">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>In hybrid composites, the randomly oriented intimately mixed short sisal/banana fibers reinforced polymer-based hybrid composites were prepared by the simple hand layup method. The volume fraction of the fiber was kept at 40% and the relative volume fraction was varied for 1 : 1, 3 : 1 and 1 : 3 ratios. The relative volume fraction varies the mechanical properties and the maximum stress transfer occurred between the fiber and matrix at a relative volume fraction of 3 : 1.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0021998312454903">5</xref></sup> The randomly oriented intimately mixed short roselle/sisal fiber reinforced polymer-based hybrid composites were developed with constant weight ratio of 1 : 1 at various fiber contents. The mechanical properties were studied with and without water absorption of the composites. The maximum mechanical properties were obtained for the dry condition than the wet condition.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0021998312454903">6</xref></sup> The woven mat and randomly oriented banana/Kenaf fiber polyester-based hybrid composites have the maximum tensile properties at 40% fiber volume fraction.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0021998312454903">7</xref></sup> These composites were prepared with the chemical treatments of alkaline and sodium laulryl sulfate. The sodium laulryl sulfate treatment improves the mechanical properties in both random mix and woven mix hybrid composites. The mechanical properties of the chemically treated palm/coir fiber reinforced polypropylene composites have better than the raw ones, also the coir fiber composites yield better mechanical properties compared with the palm ones.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0021998312454903">8</xref></sup> During the composite preparation, the tri-layer and bi-layer fiber lamina concept was utilized to prepare the oil palm/jute fiber hybrid composites with the constant relative volume fraction of 1:1. The maximum tensile and flexural properties were obtained for the tri-layer lamina concept when compared with the bi-layer composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0021998312454903">9</xref></sup> Also, the short bagasse/coir fiber hybrid epoxy novolac composites were prepared by tri-layer and by-layer patterns. The maximum tensile and flexural properties were obtained for the tri-layer as well as for the bi-layer pattern composites. The storage, loss modulus and damping behaviors were measured and the results were compared.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0021998312454903">10</xref></sup></p>
<p>The thickness swelling and water absorption levels were studied for the oil palm empty fruit bunches (EFB)/jute fibers epoxy composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0021998312454903">11</xref></sup> The relative fiber volume fraction of 3 : 1 was used to prepare the composites and the water absorption of jute/EFB/jute was moderately less than the EFB/jute/EFB patterns composites. The roselle/sisal fibers hybrid composite was prepared with the different fiber lengths and fiber weight contents to study the mechanical properties. The fiber length increases the mechanical properties, also the glass fiber composites were developed with different weight contents and the results were compared with the natural fiber hybrid composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0021998312454903">12</xref></sup> The jute and rockwool fiber composites and jute/rockwool hybrid fibers phenol formaldehyde composites were developed with the different fiber contents and the mechanical properties were discussed for the single and hybrid fiber composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0021998312454903">13</xref></sup> The composite solid cones were developed using the oil palm/coir fiber-reinforced hybrid composites, the energy absorption and failure mechanism for different modes were studied.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0021998312454903">14</xref></sup></p>
<p>Many researchers attempted on synthetic/natural fiber reinforced in polyester and epoxy to develop the hybrid composites for improving the mechanical properties. For example, the passenger car bumper beam was developed using the kenaf/glass fiber-reinforced hybrid composites. The kenaf/glass fibers composites have high tensile and flexural modulus than the glass mat thermoplastic. But its impact strength was slightly lower than the glass mat thermoplastic.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0021998312454903">15</xref></sup> The impact properties of various glass/plant fiber composites were discussed and the mechanical properties were studied on the glass/flax fiber hybrid composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0021998312454903">16</xref></sup> The mechanical properties of glass/wollastonite fiber-reinforced polypropylene hybrid composites were found closer to the glass fiber composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0021998312454903">17</xref></sup> The failure strain of the hybrid composites increased slightly with the increase in the relative volume fraction of the wollastonite fiber. Also the various natural fibers such as hemp, flax and kenaf with glass fibers-reinforced epoxy composites were analyzed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0021998312454903">18</xref></sup> The durability of fatigue behaviors under cyclic tensile load were studied on bamboo and bamboo/glass fiber polypropylene composite. After the hydrothermal aging, the mechanical properties were moderately reduced.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0021998312454903">19</xref></sup> The mechanical properties were improved by adding the carbon fiber in the sisal fiber-reinforced polyester composites. But chemically treated sisal fiber hybrid composites have maximum properties than the raw fiber composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0021998312454903">20</xref></sup> The flexural and fatigue behavior of the hand laminated hemp/glass fiber reinforced polypropylene composite were prepared and it shows that the mechanical properties of hybrid composites were better than the non-hybrid composites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0021998312454903">21</xref></sup> So it was concluded from the several literatures that the mechanical properties of the hybrid composites were better than the single-fiber composites. The different layer patterns were utilized to develop the various hybrid composites and the results were discussed for various plant fibers with polyester, epoxy and polypropylene matrix composites.</p>
<p>Overall, the natural fibers were reinforced in the matrix with random orientation form in the mould and the composites with different fiber contents were prepared. Further, for improving the mechanical properties of the composites, two fibers were hybridized to prepare the hybrid composites. In those hybrid composites, the different relative fiber volume fraction was utilized to prepare the composites and the mechanical properties were evaluated. The relative fiber volume fraction of 1 : 1 was found better than the 1 : 2, 2 : 1, 3 : 1 and 1 : 3 ratios. Also, it was confirmed that by hybridizing the natural fibers with either natural or synthetic fibers, the properties can be enhanced than the non-hybrid fibers composites. Also, the maximum mechanical properties were obtained in short fiber-reinforced composites than the long fiber composites.</p>
<p>In this paper, the newly identified SG fiber,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref></sup> banana and coir fibers are hybridized to prepare the hybrid composites with the tri-layer pattern and the analysis is made to evaluate its mechanical properties as similar to the available literatures. The simple hand lay-up technique is utilized to prepare the composites with the various fiber volume fractions at constant fiber length of 30 mm. The fiber pull-outs of the fractured specimens are also analyzed for its higher and lower mechanical properties. The traditionally available fiber like banana and coir fibers are mixed with the SG fiber to prepare the composites and its mechanical properties are studied.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0021998312454903" sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title>
<sec id="sec3-0021998312454903"><title>Fiber</title>
<p>The SG fiber is a newly identified fiber from the southern part of the India and this fiber is extracted by simple water retting process.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref></sup> The sisal and coir fiber is collected from the local resources. The physical and chemical properties of these fibers are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0021998312454903">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0021998312454903">Table 2</xref>. The lignin, pectin and microfibril angle plays an important role in the mechanical properties of the fiber and composites. In this, microfibril angle of SG is lower than the sisal and coir fiber. The fiber and matrix adhesion is also determined by the lignin content in the fibers. The lignin content for the SG fiber is low when compared with the other fibers.
<table-wrap id="table1-0021998312454903" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>The unique mechanical characteristics of snake grass, banana, and coir fibers</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0021998312454903" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312454903-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Fiber name</th>
<th>Density (kg/m<sup>3</sup>)</th>
<th>Diameter (µm)</th>
<th>Tensile strength (MPa)</th>
<th>Tensile modulus (GPa)</th>
<th>% elongation</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Snake grass<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref></sup></td>
<td>887</td>
<td>45–250</td>
<td>287–545</td>
<td>9.7</td>
<td>2.87</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Banana<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0021998312454903">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0021998312454903">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0021998312454903">9</xref></sup></td>
<td>1350</td>
<td>80–250</td>
<td>529–759</td>
<td>8.2</td>
<td>1–3.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Coir<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0021998312454903">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0021998312454903">22</xref></sup></td>
<td>1200</td>
<td>175–220</td>
<td>108–252</td>
<td>4-6</td>
<td>15–40</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-0021998312454903" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>The chemical composition of snake grass, banana, and coir fibers</p></caption><graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0021998312454903" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312454903-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Fiber name</th><th>Cellulous content (%)</th><th>Lignin content (%)</th><th>Hemicelluloses (or pentosan) (%)</th><th>Pectin (%)</th><th>Ash (%)</th><th>Microfibrillar angle (°)</th><th>Lumen size (µm)</th><th>Moisture content</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Snake grass<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref></sup></td>
<td>65–75</td>
<td>5.84</td>
<td>11.5</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>10.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Banana<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0021998312454903">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0021998312454903">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0021998312454903">9</xref></sup></td>
<td>63–64</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>10–24</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>0.6–1</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>10–12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Coir<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0021998312454903">5</xref>,22</sup></td>
<td>32–43</td>
<td>40–45</td>
<td>0.15–0.25</td>
<td>3–4</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>30–49</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0021998312454903"><title>Polyester resin</title>
<p>Commercially available unsaturated polyester resin with the standard properties, along with the curing agent, is used to prepare the composites as similar to previous literatures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0021998312454903"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0021998312454903">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0021998312454903">6</xref></sup> Catalyst of methyl ethyl ketone peroxide and accelerators of cobalt naphthalene are used as the curing agent material.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0021998312454903">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0021998312454903">6</xref></sup> This polyester resin is one of the most economical resin that has very low water absorbing capabilities and excellent bonding tendency as well as enhanced mechanical properties. The distinctive properties of the isophthallic polyester resins are a density of 1125 kg/m<sup>3</sup>, specific gravity of 1.2, tensile strength of 18 MPa and the tensile modulus of 0.8 GPa. These properties were tested in IIT Madras, India.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0021998312454903"><title>Preparation of composite</title>
<p>The hybrid composites are prepared by the simple hand layup technique with the random fiber orientation. The fibers are randomly oriented in the mould<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0021998312454903">6</xref></sup> and the resin has poured into the cavity. The tri-laying pattern of SG with snake grass/banana (SG/B) and snake grass/coir (SG/C) fiber hybrid composites are used to prepare the composites as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0021998312454903">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0021998312454903">2</xref>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0021998312454903">10</xref></sup> The fibers are then chopped into the required length to prepare the composites. The composites are also prepared with the different fiber volume fractions from 10 to 30% by maintaining the relative volume fraction of fiber as 1 : 1. Two separate layers are prepared and placed one over another in the steel mold. For curing the composite, 1% of the catalyst and the accelerators<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0021998312454903">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0021998312454903">6</xref></sup> are mixed in the isophthallic polyester resin. Then the resin is poured over the layered fibers that are present inside the mold and it is imprecated through out the layered fibers. During the composite preparation the air bubbles are removed carefully by using a roller as suggested in the literatures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0021998312454903">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0021998312454903">6</xref></sup> The mold is closed and then it is placed on the hydraulic press, a compressive pressure (5 bar) is applied for 8 hours over the mold at the atmospheric temperature. The final dimension of the composite plate (230 mm ×  200 mm × 4 mm) is obtained from the mold after solidification. The composite plate is then post-cured for 1 hour in oven (60℃) and the final shape of the composite plate is obtained.
<fig id="fig1-0021998312454903" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Tri-laying pattern of snake grass/banana (SG/B) fibers reinforce composite.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312454903-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-0021998312454903" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Tri-laying pattern of snake grass/coir (SG/C) fibers reinforce composite.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312454903-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0021998312454903"><title>Tensile testing of the composite</title>
<p>Tensile properties such as tensile strength, tensile (elastic) modulus, tensile load and elongation at break for the composites are measured based on the ASTM D 638 standards.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0021998312454903">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0021998312454903">6</xref></sup> The required specimens are machined to a standard size of 165 mm × 13 mm × 4 mm for a gage length of 50 mm. The electronic tensometer setup is used to perform the tensile testing with a cross-head speed of 1 mm/min using the load cell of 5 kN.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref></sup> The results are standardized based on the five identical test specimens, which are utilized for each testing.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0021998312454903"><title>Flexural testing of the composite</title>
<p>Three-point bending flexural testing is conducted according to the ASTM D 790 standards,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0021998312454903">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0021998312454903">6</xref></sup> to evaluate the flexural properties like flexural strength, flexural modulus, flexural load and deflection at break of the composites. The test specimens are machined for the standard dimensions of 128 mm × 12 mm × 4 mm with the span to the depth ratio of the specimens as 32:1. For this testing, five identical test specimens are prepared and tested with the load cell of 6 kN with the cross-head speed of 2.5 mm/min.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0021998312454903"><title>Scanning electron microscope</title>
<p>The micro-structural failures of the tensile and flexural fractured composite specimens are studied and analyzed for the fiber pull outs in the cross section through the scanning electron microscope (SEM) of model JEOL JSM-6390. The following specifications are used for scanning the image: (a) Resolution (3.0 nm (Acc V 30 kV, WD 8 mm, and SEI), (b) Magnification (5X (WD 48 mm or less) and (c) Electron gun (Accelerating voltage: 0.5 to 30 kV and Filament: Pre-Centered tungsten hairpin filament).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0021998312454903" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title>
<sec id="sec10-0021998312454903"><title>Effect of tensile properties</title>
<p>The tensile properties such as tensile strength and modulus of SG, SG/B and SG/C fiber-reinforced isophthallic polyester hybrid composites are prepared for the various fiber volume fractions (<italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>) with 30 mm fiber length and the resulting tensile strength comparison plot is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0021998312454903">Figure 3</xref>. At 10% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, the maximum tensile strength of 21.2 MPa is obtained for the SG/C composite. The percentage improvement between the SG to SG/C and SG to SG/B composites are 9.89% and 7.3%, respectively. There is no significant percentage improvement visible in the composites due to the less fiber accumulation. At 15% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, the tensile strength of the SG/B fiber composite is higher than the SG and SG/C fiber composites. The percentage improvement between the SG to SG/B and SG/C to SG/B fiber composites are 34.02% and 13.69%, respectively. The more fibers content in the composites increases the tensile strength. The maximum tensile strength of 48.6 MPa is obtained in the SG/B fiber composite at 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>. The percentage improvement between the SG to SG/B and SG/C to SG/B are 40.32% and 18.93%, respectively. It is clearly visible that the fiber accumulation increases the tensile strength of the SG/B hybrid composites compared to the SG/C and SG composites. The tensile strength of the SG and SG/C fiber composites increases continuously up to 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> and decreases when the fiber content increases. The reason is that the matrix content is highly reduced by the accumulation of excess fibers in the composites and also due to the significant longitudinal load transfer and stress transfer between the fibers. The maximum tensile strength for the SG and SG/C fiber composites are 36.2 MPa and 44 MPa, which are obtained at 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>. At 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, the tensile strength is more for the SG/C and SG fiber composites compared to the SG/B fiber hybrid composite. The diameter of the banana fibers and SG fibers are less when compared with the other fibers which lead to the more accumulation of fibers in the hybrid composites. So the tensile properties of SG/C and SG/B fiber hybrid composites are better than the other natural fiber hybrid composite like the sisal/banana fiber<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0021998312454903">5</xref></sup> and roselle/sisal fiber<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0021998312454903">6</xref></sup> hybrid composites.
<fig id="fig3-0021998312454903" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Effect of tensile strength versus volume fraction of snake grass (SG), snake grass/banana (SG/B) and snake grass/coir (SG/C) fibers reinforced hybrid composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312454903-fig3.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0021998312454903">Figure 4</xref>, it is clear that the tensile modulus of SG/B fiber composite is higher than the SG and SG/C fiber composite for all fiber volume fractions. The percentage improvement of the SG to SG/B and SG/C to SG/B is 38.7% and 11.35%, respectively, at 10% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>. The increase in the fiber volume fraction (10%–20%) increases the tensile modulus for the SG/C and SG/B hybrid composite. The maximum tensile modulus is obtained for the SG composite at 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, whereas SG/C and SG/B hybrid composites are at 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>. At 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, the percentage improvement of the tensile modulus between the SG to SG/B and SG/C to SG/B are 41% and 7.5%, respectively.
<fig id="fig4-0021998312454903" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Effect of tensile modulus versus volume fraction of snake grass (SG), snake grass/banana (SG/B) and snake grass/coir (SG/C) fibers reinforced hybrid composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312454903-fig4.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0021998312454903"><title>Stress–strain curves for various fiber hybrid composites</title>
<p>The stress–strain curve for the SG and SG/C at 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> and SG/B at 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> fiber-reinforced hybrid composites are compared and the comparison is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0021998312454903">Figure 5</xref>. The increment of the stress value is low due to the high strain rate in the SG and SG/C fiber composites and a maximum stress of 36.2 MPa and 44 MPa are obtained when the strain rate is 0.0746 and 0.0996, respectively. The maximum stress–strain curve for the SG/B fiber-reinforced composite is almost linear and the stress is directly proportional to the strain. The maximum stress obtained for the SG/B fiber composites is 48.6 MPa. Comparatively, the SG/C fiber hybrid composite has the higher stress rate than the SG/B fiber composite, but it is almost equal to SG fiber composites. Hence, the maximum stress is obtained for the SG/B fiber hybrid composites at 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>.
<fig id="fig5-0021998312454903" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Stress–strain curve for snake grass (SG), snake grass/banana (SG/B) and snake grass/coir (SG/C) fiber-reinforced hybrid composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312454903-fig5.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0021998312454903"><title>Effect of flexural properties</title>
<p>The flexural properties such as flexural strength and modulus of the SG, SG/B and SG/C fiber-reinforced isophthallic polyester hybrid composites are investigated for the various fiber volume fractions at 30 mm fiber length. From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0021998312454903">Figure 6</xref>, it is clear that the maximum flexural strength of 41.9 MPa is obtained for the SG/B composite at 10% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>. The percentage improvement between the SG to SG/B and SG/C to SG/B composites are 26.4% and 24.8%, respectively. Above 15% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, the flexural strength of the SG/C fiber composite is higher than the SG and SG/B fiber composite. At 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, the maximum flexural strength is obtained for the SG/C fiber composites and the percentage improvement between the SG to SG/C and SG/B to SG/C fiber composites are 46.6% and 42.2%, respectively. The flexural strength is more in the SG/C fiber hybrid composites due to the higher fiber accumulation in the composites at 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>.
<fig id="fig6-0021998312454903" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Effect of flexural strength versus volume fraction of the snake grass (SG), snake grass/banana (SG/B) and snake grass/coir (SG/C) fiber-reinforced hybrid composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312454903-fig6.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0021998312454903">Figure 7</xref> shows the comparison of the maximum flexural modulus between the SG, SG/B and SG/C fibers reinforced hybrid composites for the various volume fractions. The flexural modulus is increased linearly up to 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> for the SG and SG/C fibers hybrid composites and up to 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> for the SG/B fiber composites. At 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, the maximum flexural modulus is obtained for the SG/B fiber composite than other composites and the percentage improvement between the SG/B to SG and SG/B to SG/C fiber composites are 0.6% and 34.7%, respectively. The increase in fiber content in the SG/B composite (more than 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>) decreases the flexural modulus. Due to the more accumulation of the fiber in the composites, the maximum flexural modulus is obtained at 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> for the SG fiber composite. The percentage improvement between the SG to SG/B and SG to SG/C fiber composites are 65.15% and 45.91%, respectively. Hence, it has better lateral load transfer between the fibers in the matrix. Also, the flexural properties were better than other natural fiber composites likes the SG,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312454903">1</xref></sup> sisal/banana fiber<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0021998312454903">5</xref></sup> and roselle/sisal fiber<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0021998312454903">6</xref></sup> hybrid composites.
<fig id="fig7-0021998312454903" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Effect of flexural modulus versus volume fraction of the snake grass (SG), snake grass/banana (SG/B) and snake grass/coir (SG/C) fiber-reinforced composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312454903-fig7.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Compiling the results from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0021998312454903">Figures 3</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0021998312454903">7</xref>, the tensile and flexural properties of the single fiber-reinforced composites is highly dominated by the hybrid fiber-reinforced composites. At 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, the percentage improvement in the tensile strength for the SG to SG/C and SG to SG/B composites are 40% and 26.4%, respectively. The maximum tensile strength is obtained in the SG/B fiber-reinforced hybrid composites at 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>. Above 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, increasing fiber content reduces the tensile and flexural properties of the SG/B fiber composite. The SG/C fiber composites have the maximum flexural strength than the other composites, but the flexural modulus is lower than the SG/B fiber composite at 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>. Here, the flexural strength percentage difference between the SG and SG/C fiber composites is almost 44.6% at 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>. But the mechanical properties at volume fraction of 25%, 25% and 20% of SG, SG/B and SG/C fiber composites were decreased because the fibers agglomeration in the composites increased. It is clear that the flexural strength has notable increment with the increase in the SG/C fiber contents than the SG and SG/B fiber hybrid composites. It is also noticed that the tensile, flexural strength and modulus of hybrid composite is always higher than the single-fiber composite. These results also evident that the two different characteristic materials are combined together which will give the pleasurable materials characteristics.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-0021998312454903"><title>SEM test</title>
<p>The fractured specimen from the tensile and flexural testing of the SG fiber composite, SG/B and SG/C fiber hybrid composites are analyzed using SEM. One half of the fractured specimen is utilized to prepare the dog-bone-shaped standard specimen. The length of the specimen from the fractured end is considered up to 30 mm to ensure the safer mounting.</p>
<sec id="sec14-0021998312454903"><title>Effect of tensile fractured specimen</title>
<p>The SEM micrograph for the tensile fractured SG fiber composites, SG/B and SG/C fiber hybrid composites are compared with the lower and higher fiber volume fractions in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0021998312454903">Figure 8</xref>. Fiber pull-outs are evident from the micrograph, in particular SG, SG/C and SG/B at 10% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, also fiber pull-outs is more compared to 25% and 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, respectively. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0021998312454903">Figure 8(a)</xref> shows the fiber pull-outs in SG at 10% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>. The SG/C and SG/B fiber-laying pattern in the composites is clearly visible in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0021998312454903">Figure 8(c) and (f)</xref>. The hole size of the fiber pull–outs in the SG/C fiber is greater than the SG/B and SG fiber composite at 10% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0021998312454903">Figure 8(c)</xref>), because the diameter of the coir fiber is greater than that of the banana and SG. SG/C at 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> and SG/B at 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> fiber hybrid composites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0021998312454903">Figure 8(d) and (f)</xref>) have more accumulation of fibers content and also have less fiber pulls-outs than at 10% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> fiber composites. Due to the hybridization, the interfacial area between the fiber and matrix is higher, also the intra-fiber delamination is found to be predominant in all the composites. The fiber delamination at the interphase for the SG/C fiber composite is very less when compared to the SG/B fiber composite. The fiber wetting is higher than the 10% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> for the higher fiber loading case, SG/B fiber undergoes individual fiber breakage and delamination appreciably due to the strong interphase. It is evident from the micrograph that the adhesive area between the fiber and matrix and the percentage improvement of the tensile strength between the single fiber and hybrid fiber composites are higher.
<fig id="fig8-0021998312454903" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Tensile fractured image of snake grass (SG), snake grass/banana (SG/B) and snake grass/coir (SG/C) fiber-reinforced hybrid composites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312454903-fig8.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-0021998312454903"><title>Effect of flexural fractured specimen</title>
<p>The SEM micrograph for the flexural fractured SG fiber composites, SG/B and SG/C fiber hybrid composites are compared with the lower and higher fiber volume fractions in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0021998312454903">Figure 9</xref>. Due to the flexural load, the interphase delamination is found at the cross section of the composite. More fiber pull-outs is observed in the SG, SG/C and SG/B fiber composite at 10% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> due to the less fiber accumulations in the composites. Fiber undergoes the minimal breakage due to the predominance of fiber pull-outs. Individual fiber delamination is not found so frequently in the lower volume fractions of the composites, but rarely visible. Flexural strength is very less due to the poor stress transfer between the fiber and the matrix at the interphase region of the composites. But at 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> flexural fractured specimen, the fiber pull-outs behavior of the composite occurs rarely when compared with the 10% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>. SG/C fiber composite have the higher fiber breakage than the SG/B and SG fiber composites. This indicates that there is a good interaction between the fiber and matrix at the interphase. Stress transfer between the reinforcement and the fiber is appreciable, which is also evident from the flexural strength values at 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>. Fiber breakage occurs very frequently in both tensile and compressive regions due to the less fiber pull-outs and particularly higher fiber accumulation leads to the better adhesion at the interphase region. Due to the minimal fiber pull-outs in the composites, the fiber breakage is higher and the individual fiber delamination is also predominant due to the same reason.
<fig id="fig9-0021998312454903" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Flexural fractured image of snake grass (SG), snake grass/banana (SG/B) and snake grass/coir (SG/C) fiber-reinforced hybrid composite.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312454903-fig9.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Compiling the results from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0021998312454903">Figures 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0021998312454903">9</xref>, the image analysis of the tensile and flexural fractured specimen proves that the fiber pull-outs and fiber delamination affects the tensile and flexural properties of the single fiber and hybrid fiber composites. The maximum strength in any composites can be obtained by adding more than one fiber in the composites. The SG/B fiber composites carry sufficient load in the longitudinal direction that leads to the maximum tensile strength. Also, the SG/C fiber composites withstand higher bending load and it can be used for the structural applications.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec16-0021998312454903" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The SG, banana and coir fibers are chopped into the required length to prepare the hybrid composites using the isophthallic polyester resin in the present work. The mechanical properties are evaluated based on the ASTM standards. The following conclusions are made based on the extensive experimental work.
<list id="list1-0021998312454903" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The maximum tensile strength and modulus is obtained for the SG/B and SG/C fiber hybrid composites at 20% and 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, respectively. The tensile strength for the SG/B is higher than the SG/C fiber-reinforced composites. The maximum tensile modulus is obtained for the SG/B and SG/C fiber-reinforced hybrid composites at 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The maximum flexural strength and modulus are obtained for the SG/B and SG/C fiber hybrid composites at 20% and 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> when compared with the SG fiber composites. The flexural strength in SG/C is higher than the SG/B fiber-reinforced hybrid composites, but the maximum flexural modulus is obtained for the SG fiber-reinforced composites at 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>, which is closer to the SG/B fiber composites at 20% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The SEM micrograph for the tensile and flexural fractured specimens are analyzed for the fiber delamination, matrix crack and fibers pull outs during the loading at 10%, 20% and 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> of the composites, respectively. Higher mechanical strength has the lesser fiber pull outs, due to the more accumulation of fiber being wetted in the matrix and also it transfers higher load.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>Overall, it can be concluded that the 20% volume fraction of SG/B fiber hybrid composites have the maximum tensile properties and SG/C fiber hybrid composites have the maximum flexural strength; so that the mechanical properties of the composites depends upon the fiber volume fraction and at more than 25% <italic>V</italic><sub>f</sub> the mechanical properties started sloping down from its higher values. This work is adding evidence that the maximum strength of any composite can be obtained by adding more than one fiber in the composites.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec17-0021998312454903"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec18-0021998312454903"><title>Conflict of Interest</title>
<p>None declared</p>
</sec>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0021998312454903"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sathishkumar</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Navaneethakrishnan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tensile and flexural properties of snake grass natural fiber reinforced isophthallic polyester composites</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>72</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1183</fpage>–<lpage>1190</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0021998312454903"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Filho</surname><given-names>RDT</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A review on sisal fibre reinforced polymer composites</article-title>. <source>Revista Brasileira de Engenharia Agrícola e Ambiental</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>379</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0021998312454903"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jayabal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of fiber parameters on tensile, flexural, and impact properties of nonwoven coir–polyester composites</article-title>. <source>Int J Adv Manuf Technol</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>639</fpage>–<lpage>648</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0021998312454903"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarikanat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sever</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of the low and radio frequency oxygen plasma treatment of jute fibre on mechanical properties of jute fibre/polyester composite</article-title>. <source>Fibres Polym</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1159</fpage>–<lpage>1164</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0021998312454903"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Idicula</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic mechanical analysis of randomly oriented intimately mixed short banana/sisal hybrid fiber reinforced polyester composites</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>1077</fpage>–<lpage>1087</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0021998312454903"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Athijayaman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiruchitrambalam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of moisture absorption on the mechanical properties of randomly oriented natural fibers/polyester hybrid composite</article-title>. <source>Mater Sci Eng A</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>517</volume>: <fpage>344</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0021998312454903"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thiruchitrambalam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alavudeen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Athijayamani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Improving mechanical properties of banana/kenaf polyester hybrid composites using sodium lauryl sulfate treatment</article-title>. <source>Mater Phys Mech</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0021998312454903"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physico-mechanical properties of chemically treated palm and coir fiber reinforced polypropylene composites</article-title>. <source>Bioresour Technol</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>100</volume>(<issue>20</issue>): <fpage>4903</fpage>–<lpage>4906</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0021998312454903"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jawaid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdul Khalil</surname><given-names>HPS</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu Bakar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Chemical resistance, void content and tensile properties of oil palm/jute fiber reinforced polymer hybrid composites</article-title>. <source>Mater Design</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1016</fpage>–<lpage>1021</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0021998312454903"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saw</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkhel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Choudhury</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic mechanical analysis of randomly oriented short bagasse/coir hybrid fibre-reinforced epoxy novolac composites</article-title>. <source>Fibres Polym</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>506</fpage>–<lpage>513</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0021998312454903"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jawaid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdul Khalil</surname><given-names>HPS</given-names></name><name><surname>Noorunnisa Khanam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Hybrid composites made from oil palm empty fruit bunches jute fibres: water absorption, thickness swelling and density behaviours</article-title>. <source>J Polym Environ</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0021998312454903"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Athijayaman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiruchitrambalam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Manikandan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanical properties of natural fibers reinforced polyester hybrid composite</article-title>. <source>Int J Plast Technol</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0021998312454903"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bulent</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hybrid effect in the mechanical properties of jute/rockwool hybrid fibers reinforced phenol formaldehyde composites</article-title>. <source>Fibres Polym</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>464</fpage>–<lpage>473</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0021998312454903"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahdi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamouda</surname><given-names>ASM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Quasi-static crushing behaviour of hybrid and non-hybrid natural fibre composite solid cones</article-title>. <source>Compos Struct</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>647</fpage>–<lpage>663</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0021998312454903"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davoodi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapuan</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanical properties of hybrid kenaf/glass reinforced epoxy composite for passenger car bumper beam</article-title>. <source>Mater Design</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>4927</fpage>–<lpage>4932</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0021998312454903"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santulli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact properties of glass/plant fibre hybrid laminates</article-title>. <source>J Mater Sci</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>3699</fpage>–<lpage>3707</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0021998312454903"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Himani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Purnima</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Development of glass fiber, wollastonite reinforced polypropylene hybrid composites: mechanical properties and morphology</article-title>. <source>Mater Sci Eng A</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>527</volume>: <fpage>1946</fpage>–<lpage>1951</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0021998312454903"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cicala</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cristaldi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Recca</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Properties and performances of various hybrid glass/natural fiber composites for curved pipes</article-title>. <source>Mater Design</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>2538</fpage>–<lpage>2542</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0021998312454903"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thwe</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Durability of bamboo-glass fiber reinforced polymer matrix hybrid composites</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0021998312454903"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noorunnisa Khanam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdul Khalil</surname><given-names>HPS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jawaid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sisal/carbon fiber reinforced hybrids composites: tensile, flexural and chemical resistance properties</article-title>. <source>J Polym Environ</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>727</fpage>–<lpage>733</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0021998312454903"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>PNB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>JAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Flexural behaviour of hybrid laminates composites</article-title>. <source>Compos Pt A</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1612</fpage>–<lpage>1620</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0021998312454903"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Varughese</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanical properties of sisal/oil palm hybrid fiber reinforced natural rubber composite</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>955</fpage>–<lpage>965</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>