<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AIP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spaip</journal-id>
<journal-title>AADE in Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2325-1603</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2325-5161</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2325160313481964</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2325160313481964</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Departments</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Capsules</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Statins and Diabetes</article-title>
<subtitle>A Closer Look</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Meece</surname><given-names>Jerry</given-names></name>
<degrees>RPH, CDE, FACA</degrees>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>1</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>25</fpage>
<lpage>27</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 by the American Association of Diabetes Educators</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Association of Diabetes Educators</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig id="fig1-2325160313481964" position="float">
<graphic id="img1-2325160313481964" xlink:href="10.1177_2325160313481964-img1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>On February 28, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-2325160313481964">2012</xref>, the FDA issued a statement modifying the warnings placed on all statin drugs regarding increases in blood glucose levels associated with this drug class.</p>
<p>After almost a year of controversy, debates, and comments concerning the modified labeling, many clinicians are still trying to determine what the FDA statement means for their patients. This article attempts to look at the subject of statins and their effect on blood glucose in the current light and provide some perspective about benefits versus risk.</p>
<p>The most significant question arising out of the FDA’s modified labeling of statins is whether the data support their use as primary prevention in patients who do not have heart disease but do have elevated cholesterol levels in spite of lifestyle modifications such as physical activity and healthier eating. Access to the Internet, 24-hour news coverage, and sensational journalism headlining health care has created a heightened awareness surrounding the class of statin drugs, which in turn has patients bringing questions of safety and effectiveness into our offices.</p>
<sec id="section1-2325160313481964">
<title>Do Statins Cause Diabetes?</title>
<p>For years statin medications have been the backbone of treatment for high cholesterol levels and have been extremely effective in this role, especially for secondary prevention of cardiovascular events such as myocardial infarction or stroke in patients with heart disease. More than 20 million Americans take statins—approximately 50% of men age 65 to 74 and 40% of women age 75 and older—making the use of this drug a significant issue for our patients.</p>
<p>The FDA states the following about the entire statin class of drugs: “Increases in blood sugar levels (hyperglycemia) have been reported with statin use. The FDA is also aware of studies showing that patients being treated with statins may have a small risk of increased blood sugar levels and of being diagnosed with type 2 diabetes mellitus.”</p>
<p>To support this warning, the FDA cited the results from several meta-analyses along with epidemiological and observational data including the Justification for the Use of Statins in Primary Prevention: An Intervention Trial Evaluating Rosuvastatin (JUPITER) study. This study looked at rosuvastatin 20 mg versus placebo in prevention of cardiovascular events.</p>
<p>With these data, the FDA was able to identify a small but significantly increased risk for incident diabetes associated with statin use. The percentage increase in new diabetes cases identified by investigators ranged from 9% to 15% in a large compilation of observational and post hoc studies to 24% in the JUPITER study, possibly the most closely followed study of the group.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>It does appear that the higher the dose of statin, the greater the risk for diabetes, but also the greater the benefit as far as reducing cardiovascular events.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Everyone seems to be in agreement that statins do increase blood glucose levels to the point of “causing diabetes.” However, different studies show different levels of risk depending on which statins were used, the dose of the statin, who the patient was, what the baseline blood glucose levels were, and so on. What remains to be fleshed out, and likely will be in the near future with other studies, is how much did statins in these studies really raise blood glucose, in what populations, and what other factors were involved? Because the trials cited were not designed to study this aspect of statin therapy, true causation of blood glucose elevations could not be resolved. It does appear that the higher the dose of the statin, the greater the risk for diabetes, but also the greater the benefit as far as reducing cardiovascular events.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-2325160313481964">
<title>Risks and Benefits</title>
<p>While there are many drugs that do exacerbate diabetes management, such as prednisone and niacin, the increase in blood glucose observed in the statin trials was relatively small. In addition, there was no overall effect making diabetes harder to manage or control. Furthermore, the difference in A1C was extremely small. In the JUPITER trial the A1C was 5.8% in the placebo group and 5.9% in the rosuvastatin group. On the other hand, the JUPITER trial did show a significant reduction in both groups for the primary endpoint of the trial, which was reduction in cardiovascular events. Participants in the high cardiovascular risk group who were identified with 1 or more of the major risk factors of metabolic syndrome—impaired fasting glucose, body mass index 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup> or higher, or A1C greater than 6%—had a 39% reduction in cardiovascular events, a 36% decrease in venous thromboembolism, and a 17% decrease in total mortality along with the 24% increase in diabetes. For the group of participants with no major diabetes risk factors, there was a 52% reduction in the primary endpoint, a 53% reduction in venous thromboembolism, a 22% reduction in total mortality, and <italic>no increase</italic> in diagnosed cases of diabetes. It’s also important to note that study subjects for JUPITER were allowed into the trial with fasting blood glucose values up to 125 mg/dL, meaning that you could easily enter the trial with a blood glucose level of 124 mg/dL and move to 127 mg/dL, thus becoming one of the newly diagnosed diabetes cases.</p>
<p>So the conclusion that seems to be drawn from all the meta-analyses is that in someone with prediabetes or metabolic syndrome, statins could potentially move a patient to a diagnosis of diabetes. But we also have to remember that cardiovascular risk is elevated along a continuum. In other words, it’s not that at 120 mg/dL you’re healthy and at 126 mg/dL you’re not. It would take very little to move a participant from prediabetes the few extra mg/dL to a diagnosis of diabetes in any of the trials.</p>
<fig id="fig2-2325160313481964" position="float">
<graphic id="img2-2325160313481964" xlink:href="10.1177_2325160313481964-img2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-2325160313481964">
<title>The Bottom Line</title>
<p>The benefits of statins are clear and the increased risk of moving blood glucose levels up a few points is small. Statins in these trials were extremely effective in reducing cardiovascular events in populations with increased risk of diabetes and were also effective in reducing cardiovascular events in those who had low risk for diabetes.</p>
<p>The final thoughts on these data come from 2 of the principals who have been at the center of the discussions on this issue for over a year. Dr Paul Ridker, lead investigator for the JUPITER trial along with other researchers, thinks the message is clear. The risk of developing diabetes with statin therapy is limited to patients already at high risk for developing diabetes, such as those with impaired fasting glucose, metabolic syndrome, severe obesity, or raised A1C levels. However in these high-risk patients as well as the entire study cohort, the benefits of statin therapy exceeded the risk of diabetes and should reassure clinicians about the use of statins for the primary prevention of myocardial infarction, stroke, and cardiovascular death. The benefit of cardiovascular events prevented is greater than the risk of causing diabetes.</p>
<p>Amy G. Egan, MD, MPH, deputy director for safety in FDA’s Division of Metabolism and Endocrinology Products, states, “The new information should not scare people off statins. We are not recommending that patients be discontinued from their statin therapy based on a small increase in blood sugar levels. Rather, elevations in blood sugar levels should be treated with dietary and lifestyle management and/or adjustment or initiation of antidiabetic therapies. We do not consider this a reason to not continue or not initiate statins, particularly in the diabetic population where patients are at increased risk for major adverse cardiovascular events and statin therapy has been shown to reduce that risk.”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-2325160313481964">
<title>Patient Messages</title>
<p>So how does this change our interaction with our prediabetes and diabetes patients? The message probably doesn’t change much for people with diabetes where it might create a minor bump in blood glucose levels. Since these patients have a greater risk of cardiovascular disease than others, there really needs to be a pretty good reason for not using a statin. As always, blood glucose levels need to be monitored and adjustments made accordingly. Lifestyle modification remains the cornerstone of risk reduction for both diabetes and cardiovascular disease. What might change is that ramping up statin doses without paying attention to what the glucose is doing may not be the best thing to do.</p>
<p>As for our patients with prediabetes, this may give us the chance to reinforce the message of healthy eating and physical activity. An encounter could go something like this: “This statin drug is going to lower your risk of cardiovascular events, but it may slightly increase your risk of diabetes. Could we talk about how your diet, physical activity, and other lifestyle changes might be modified in order to make all of this work better?”</p>
<p>There are currently several other studies out there that may possibly address whether one statin produces greater cardiovascular benefits than others related to diabetes risk or how much a particular statin actually raises blood glucose in various populations. Stay tuned.</p>
<fig id="fig3-2325160313481964" position="float">
<graphic id="img3-2325160313481964" xlink:href="10.1177_2325160313481964-img3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<p>Jerry Meece, RPh, CDE, FACA, is director of clinical services with Plaza Pharmacy and Wellness Center in Gainesville, TX.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-2325160313481964">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>FDA expands advice on statin risks</collab>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/downloads/ForConsumers/ConsumerUpdates/UCM293705.pdf">http://www.fda.gov/downloads/ForConsumers/ConsumerUpdates/UCM293705.pdf</ext-link>. Published <month>February</month> <day>12</day>, <year>2012</year>. <access-date>Accessed February 27, 2013</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-2325160313481964">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>Food and Drug Administration</collab>. <article-title>FDA drug safety communication: important safety label changes to cholesterol-lowering statin drugs</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/Drugs/DrugSafety/ucm293101.htm">http://www.fda.gov/Drugs/DrugSafety/ucm293101.htm</ext-link>. Published <month>February</month> <day>28</day>, <year>2012</year>. <access-date>Accessed February 27, 2013</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-2325160313481964">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ridker</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pradhan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacFayden</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Libby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glynn</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cardiovascular benefits and diabetes risks of statin therapy in primary prevention: an analysis from the JUPITER trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>380</volume>(<issue>9841</issue>):<fpage>565</fpage>-<lpage>571</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>