<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NEJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spnej</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nurs Ethics</journal-id>
<journal-title>Nursing Ethics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0969-7330</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0989</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0969733011425970</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0969733011425970</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Patient dignity and its related factors in heart failure patients</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bagheri</surname>
<given-names>Hossein</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff1-0969733011425970">Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Iran</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Yaghmaei</surname>
<given-names>Farideh</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff2-0969733011425970">Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Iran</aff>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0969733011425970"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ashktorab</surname>
<given-names>Tahereh</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff3-0969733011425970">Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Iran</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zayeri</surname>
<given-names>Farid</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff4-0969733011425970">Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Iran</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0969733011425970">Farideh Yaghmaei, Faculty of Nursing and Midwifery, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Vali-asr street, Tehran 3613616919, Iran Email: <email>farideh_y2002@yahoo.com</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>316</fpage>
<lpage>327</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Maintenance and promotion of patient dignity is an ethical responsibility of healthcare workers. The aim of this study was to investigate patient dignity and related factors in patients with heart failure. In this qualitative study, 22 patients with heart failure were chosen by purposive sampling and semi-structured interviews were conducted until data saturation. Factors related to patient dignity were divided into two main categories: patient/care index and resources. Intrapersonal features (inherent characteristics and individual beliefs) and interpersonal interactions (communication, respect, enough information, privacy, and authority) were classified as components of the patient/care index category. Human resources (management and staff) and environmental resources (facilities and physical space) were classified as components of the resources category. The results will increase healthcare staff's understanding of patient dignity and its related factors, and provide information regarding the development of systems and processes that support patients in ways that are consistent with these values.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Heart failure</kwd>
<kwd>dignity</kwd>
<kwd>dignity-related factors</kwd>
<kwd>qualitative study</kwd>
<kwd>ethics</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0969733011425970">
<title>Background</title>
<p>Heart failure is a growing problem. It affects patients, families, and community networks. Heart failure reduces functional capacity and affects the social life of patients.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0969733011425970">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0969733011425970">2</xref>
</sup> It is the most important cause of disability.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0969733011425970">3</xref>
</sup> The Disease Management Center reports the prevalence of heart failure in 18 of Iran’s provinces as 3337 per 100,000.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0969733011425970">4</xref>
</sup> Based on studies in Iran, 25% of hospitalized patients in cardiac wards are diagnosed with heart failure.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0969733011425970">4</xref>
</sup> Heart failure represents a modern epidemic.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0969733011425970">5</xref>
</sup> In the United States, 5 million people currently suffer from heart failure, 500,000 new patients are diagnosed annually, and the prevalence of heart disease is expected to double in the next 30 years.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0969733011425970">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0969733011425970"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0969733011425970">8</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The physical signs and disability associated with heart failure can cause social isolation, affect patient roles in family and social life, and decrease life satisfaction.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0969733011425970">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0969733011425970">10</xref>
</sup> Disabled patients must depend on others for normal activities and self-care.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0969733011425970">10</xref>
</sup> Patients who perceive themselves as a burden to others often believe that their lives lack purpose or meaning, or that others consider them no longer worthy of respect or esteem.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0969733011425970">11</xref>
</sup> Compared with other chronic diseases, heart failure causes more damage in the functional roles of individuals in social, family, and marital relationships, as well as professional performance.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0969733011425970">12</xref>
</sup> Compared with cancer patients, heart failure patients live longer with their disability.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0969733011425970">13</xref>
</sup> Heart failure patients sometimes perceive healthcare staff as inattentive to their needs, feel forgotten by others, and see their dignity as destroyed; thus, increasing their vulnerability and other problems.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0969733011425970">14</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Identifying and strengthening patient dignity can increase patients’ confidence and satisfaction with care, enhance nursing care, reduce length of hospitalization, and improve patient outcomes. Destruction of patient dignity can decrease the physical and mental health of patients.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0969733011425970">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0969733011425970">16</xref>
</sup> Prior studies on the dignity concept have been done in acute care, intensive care, and end-of-life settings or in elderly patients, but not in patients with heart failure.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0969733011425970">17</xref>
</sup> The present study, which was carried out to investigate perceptions of patient dignity and related factors in patients with heart failure, is the first to address the information gap about concepts of patient dignity in patients with heart failure. The present study is a part of a broad research effort employing qualitative and quantitative methods for data collection and analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0969733011425970">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section3-0969733011425970">
<title>Methodology</title>
<p>We employed a qualitative summative content analysis design. Qualitative content analysis is one of numerous research methods used to analyse text data. Typically, a study using a summative approach to qualitative content analysis starts with identifying and quantifying certain words or content in text by hand or by computer with the purpose of understanding the contextual use of the words or content.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0969733011425970">18</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<sec id="section4-0969733011425970">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>The study was performed in Tehran, Iran. Twenty-two in-patients from cardiac wards in hospitals affiliated with Tehran University (Hazrate Rasoolakram and Shariati Hospitals) and Shahid Beheshti (Imam Hossein Hospital) were chosen by purposive sampling. Criteria for study entry were heart failure consistent with the New York Heart Association class II to IV,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0969733011425970">19</xref>
</sup> ability to speak Persian, and absence of signs of delirium or dementia that would interfere with informed consent or completion of the interview.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0969733011425970">
<title>Ethical considerations</title>
<p>This study was approved by the Research Committee of Shahid Beheshti University and was conducted after obtaining written consent from participants. Each participant was informed of the purpose and nature of the research and the time commitment required, and was assured of confidentiality and anonymity. Patients were informed that there was no obligation to take part in the study and that their care and treatment would be unaffected by their decision. Interviews took place while participants were in the hospital and were conducted individually in a private, comfortable setting. All interviews were recorded with the consent of participants and were transcribed verbatim by the researcher soon after the interview.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0969733011425970">
<title>Data collection</title>
<p>Interviews were conducted over a period of about 4 months. Investigators were unacquainted with study participants prior to interviews. A semi-structured interview was conducted with each participant. In order to help participants feel at ease, the interview began with a general question. Based on an interview guide that was successful in test interviews, successive questions progressed to specific topics. Interview times ranged from 15 to 45 minutes and averaged 30 minutes. </p>
<p>The following three main questions were asked of participants:<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>the meaning of patient dignity;</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>how patients’ dignity is promoted; and</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>how patients’ dignity is threatened.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
<p>The data were considered saturated when no new concepts emerged after the 22nd interview.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0969733011425970">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>A qualitative content analysis was performed using methods described by Hsieh and Shannon.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0969733011425970">18</xref>
</sup> A summative approach to qualitative content analysis has certain advantages. It is an unobtrusive and non-reactive way to study the phenomenon of interest, and can provide basic insights into how words are actually used.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0969733011425970">18</xref>
</sup> In this study, the researcher read the responses of participants carefully and important statements were extracted from participants’ phrases by hand, particularly from sentences that contained the word ‘dignity’, and were coded. Then, similar codes were merged as themes and similar themes were placed in a subcategory. Finally, the subcategories with common properties were located in two categories, ‘patient/care index’ and ‘resources’. To validate the coding, the member-checking method was used and the codes were reviewed by some of the participants and a peer group of secondary raters.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0969733011425970">
<title>Results</title>
<p>This section presents the findings on the meaning of patient dignity and also factors related to the maintenance of patient dignity from the perspective of patients with heart failure. The demographic characteristics of participants are displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0969733011425970">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0969733011425970" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Characteristics of sample (<italic>N</italic> = 22).</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0969733011425970" xlink:href="10.1177_0969733011425970-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>Mean, <italic>N</italic> (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">
<italic>Age (years)</italic>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Below 50</td>
<td>6 (28)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 50–59</td>
<td>8 (36)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Over 60</td>
<td>8 (36)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">
<italic>Sex</italic>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male</td>
<td>17 (77)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td>5 (23)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">
<italic>Education</italic>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Illiterate</td>
<td>4 (18)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Below diploma</td>
<td>15 (68)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Graduate</td>
<td>3 (14)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">
<italic>Occupation</italic>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Housewife</td>
<td>5 (22)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Employee</td>
<td>3 (15)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Self-employment</td>
<td>14 (63)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">
<italic>Number of children</italic>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> &lt; 2</td>
<td>6 (28)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 3–5</td>
<td>8 (36)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> &gt; 5</td>
<td>8 (36)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">
<italic>NYHA functional class</italic>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> NYHA II </td>
<td>14 (63.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> NYHA III</td>
<td>7 (31.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> NYHA IV</td>
<td>1 (4.5)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0969733011425970">
<p>NYHA: New York Heart Association.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section9-0969733011425970">
<title>The meaning of patient dignity</title>
<p>In response to the first question, the meaning of patient dignity, participants stated that it means being considered as a unique human being and being treated with respect, and that it also means having forgiveness.</p>
<p>Participants believed that a way in which their dignity can be promoted is by ensuring that they are valued as human beings, that all individuals are considered equal, and that money and status do not confer dignity.<disp-quote>
<p>A person may be poor, may be rich. I shouldn’t prefer rich to poor. Both must be accepted as a human being. So, we must respect the individual as a valued person.</p>
<p>(Patient 10)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Some participants also mentioned that they expect staff to respect them, and when the staff do respect them, they feel valued. This was a part of the participants’ notion of patient dignity. One participant reflected:<disp-quote>
<p>The dignity means, they respect me, as I respect them.</p>
<p>(Patient 6)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Also, forgiveness was highlighted by some participants as one of the meanings of patient dignity.<disp-quote>
<p>Dignity meant forgiveness in the world to move the wheel of life. Forgiveness is at the head of things.</p>
<p>(Patient 14)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0969733011425970">
<title>Factors enhancing or threatening dignity</title>
<p>Responses to the second and third questions, factors enhancing or threatening patient dignity, were classified into two main categories: ‘patient/care index’ and ‘resources’.</p>
<p>Intrapersonal features (inherent characteristics and individual beliefs) and interpersonal interactions (communication, respect, enough information, privacy and authority) were classified as subcategories of the ‘patient/care index’. Also, human resources (management and staff) and environmental resources (facilities and physical space) were classified as subcategories of ‘resources’ (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0969733011425970">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0969733011425970" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Factors identified by patients with heart failure as related to patient dignity.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0969733011425970" xlink:href="10.1177_0969733011425970-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Patient/care index</th>
<th>Resources</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<italic>Intrapersonal features</italic>
</td>
<td>
<italic>Human resources</italic>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Inherent characteristics</td>
<td> Management</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Individual beliefs</td>
<td> Staff</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<italic>Interpersonal interactions</italic>
</td>
<td>
<italic>Environmental resources </italic>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Communication</td>
<td> Facilities</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Respect</td>
<td> Physical space</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Enough information</td>
<td> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Privacy</td>
<td> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Authority</td>
<td> </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section11-0969733011425970">
<title>Patient/care index</title>
<p>The first category, patient/care index, was based on participants’ descriptions of factors that are related to individual (patient/healthcare worker) characteristics and staff behaviour. This category included two subcategories: ‘intrapersonal features’ and ‘interpersonal interactions’.</p>
<sec id="section12-0969733011425970">
<title>Intrapersonal features</title>
<p>Intrapersonal features, the first subcategory, is organized around internal characteristics of the individual (patient/healthcare worker). Inherent characteristics and individual beliefs were two themes within the intrapersonal features subcategory.</p>
<sec id="section12a-0969733011425970">
<title>Inherent characteristics</title>
<sec id="section12b-0969733011425970">
<title>Modesty</title>
<p>Participants stated that, despite having some privileges such as social status and money, modesty can represent individual dignity. They believed that any person who is higher in age, education, status, or authority should be more modest. For example, one participant stated this proverb:<disp-quote>
<p>It is believed whatever the tree gets bigger, his arms become more bent.</p>
<p>(Patient 17)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12c-0969733011425970">
<title>Responsibility</title>
<p>Another factor identified in participants’ statements as an inherent characteristic was responsibility. From the perspective of some participants, a sense of responsibility on behalf of staff for carrying out their duties is considered a factor of patient satisfaction and enhancing dignity. In other words, patients believed that staff behaved with the utmost kindness despite the many problems, such as number of patients and work overload, that they had in the ward.<disp-quote>
<p>Eleven and a half hours last night I came here. They were treated with kindness despite of a world of problems in the ward. I saw they were trying.</p>
<p>(Patient 1)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12d-0969733011425970">
<title>Empathy</title>
<p>Understanding patients and being able to empathize with them was one of the themes expressed by participants. An empathetic environment promotes the worth and dignity of patients.<disp-quote>
<p>If I tell him/her I have problem, he/she must think it is his/her problem and try to solve it.</p>
<p>(Patient 16)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12e-0969733011425970">
<title>Individual beliefs</title>
<sec id="section12f-0969733011425970">
<title>Equality</title>
<p>Individual beliefs about human beings and equality was an important dignity-related factor. Patients believed that all human beings are born with equal dignity and have equal rights, and healthcare staff should behave with such beliefs.<disp-quote>
<p>We need to value all people. Because humans are best.</p>
<p>(Patient 13)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>and<disp-quote>
<p>We all must be seen by equal eyes. For example, that man, who is moaning, from the medical view, is a patient. We all need doctors, need nurses, need services.</p>
<p>(Patient 7)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0969733011425970">
<title>Interpersonal interactions</title>
<p>The second subcategory, interpersonal interactions, is based on how staff behaviour can affect patient dignity. Communication, respect, enough information, privacy, and authority were themes that were identified by participants in this subcategory.</p>
<sec id="section12g-0969733011425970">
<title>Communication</title>
<p>Communication was one of the most important issues identified by participants. Good communication is an essential ingredient for providing the best quality of health care and patient satisfaction. It can cause a sense of happiness and value in patients.<disp-quote>
<p>He said: I am here to take care of you. Tell me anything you need. I’m here because you have heart disease. This may result in a problem for you. I was so happy. Because he saw that I am valuable.</p>
<p>(Patient 9)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<sec id="section12q-0969733011425970">
<title>Respect</title>
<p>Maintaining patient dignity requires staff to heed patient desires. Participants stated that mutual respect in communication is one of their most important desires. They wanted to be treated with respect when staff spoke to them or did their tasks. Patients’ experience of dignity is fostered when staff treat them with respect.<disp-quote>
<p>A patient doesn't want anything except respect and dignity. We should respect who we're talking to.</p>
<p>(Patient 14)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12h-0969733011425970">
<title>Enough information</title>
<p>One of the ways in which participants felt valued was by being given enough time to discuss with staff their condition and its treatment. This promotes a sense of satisfaction and maintains dignity. Some participants expressed that some of the staff listened to them and that they received the necessary information about their disease, which helped to calm them. <disp-quote>
<p>Until the second day, I didn’t know I had a stroke. When I asked the nurse why my blood pressure goes up and down, he said: Excuse me, because you had a stroke, part of your heart is not working and we gave you a drug and these drugs make your pressure go up and down. Don’t worry.</p>
<p>(Patient 5)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12i-0969733011425970">
<title>Privacy</title>
<p>Patient privacy was often remembered by some participants. Patients like their body to be covered as much as possible when care is being given. Exposure of the body was one factor that threatened patient dignity. According to one patient:<disp-quote>
<p>For example, the week before I went angiography. Well, I had an open back shirt, I was embarrassed.</p>
<p>(Patient 11)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12j-0969733011425970">
<title>Authority</title>
<p>More authority and freedom to perform daily activities were seen to convey a sense of worth and value for patients. It seems that giving this freedom, with the necessary limitations, can help maintain or enhance a sense of value in patients. One participant said:<disp-quote>
<p>For example, nights, when we want sleep, we are free and time is for ourselves. They say don’t bother your friend, you are free, do you want to sleep or increase the sound of the TV, you can do whatever you want, but don’t bother your room mate. Your bedstead is for yourself. He doesn’t tell us why you don’t have sleep or you must go sleep.</p>
<p>(Patient 9)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0969733011425970">
<title>Resources</title>
<p>The second category, resources, includes content in which participants describe how quality and quantity of resources improves personal dignity. Resources played an essential role in patient dignity and include two subcategories: ‘human resources’ and ‘environmental resources’.</p>
<sec id="section15-0969733011425970">
<title>Human resources</title>
<p>Human resources, the first subcategory, is organized around how quality of management structure and number of staff can improve patient dignity. Management and staff were important themes identified by participants in this subcategory.</p>
<sec id="section15a-0969733011425970">
<title>Management</title>
<sec id="section15b-0969733011425970">
<title>Management structure</title>
<p>From the perspective of participants, management structure within a ward has an important effect on patients’ dignity and interactions between manager and patients. In other words, the more powerful the manager is in the regularization and management of the ward, the more satisfied the patient.</p>
<p>One patient said:<disp-quote>
<p>Nowadays, the communication and personality of people is improving. It depends on how much a nurse, as manager, has power. If he/she has power, they don’t allow anything to happen.</p>
<p>(Patient 17)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15c-0969733011425970">
<title>Bureaucracy</title>
<p>Regulations and increased bureaucracy were also cited as threatening factors to patients’ satisfaction and the quality of communications between staff and their patients, and therefore influence the sense of value and dignity experienced by patients. Participants recognized that regulations in the hospital can reduce patients’ freedom:<disp-quote>
<p>The first time I became angry with the hospital system, because of its cumbersome regulations and bureaucracy.</p>
<p>(Patient 7)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15d-0969733011425970">
<title>Staff</title>
<sec id="section15f-0969733011425970">
<title>Lack of staff</title>
<p>Lack of staff and fatigued staff were commonly cited by participants as an obstacle to providing adequate and appropriate care. Although staff are accustomed to fatigue, lack of staff and a large number of patients, these factors can interfere with the communication between staff and patients and subsequently have a negative effect on the patients’ sense of worth.<disp-quote>
<p>If they are unable to provide adequate care, it is due to lack of staff and their fatigue.</p>
<p>(Patient 1)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Also, another patient in this area said:<disp-quote>
<p>… nurse come back and tells me that what are you doing. If a nurse says this sometimes, it is because of the number of patients in ward.</p>
<p>(Patient 7)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15h-0969733011425970">
<title>Cleanliness of staff</title>
<p>The appearance and cleanliness of staff were valued. Some patients expressed that a free-standing and clean appearance of staff was important in creating comfortable and satisfactory communication between patients and healthcare personnel.<disp-quote>
<p>I’ve seen it before, the doctor wore a simple gown and shoes which were very simple, clean and convenient. This can cause a sense of satisfaction for me.</p>
<p>(Patient 1)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0969733011425970">
<title>Environmental resources</title>
<p>The second subcategory, environmental resources, includes participants’ expressions about adequate facilities and the quality of physical space. Facilities and physical space were two themes of environmental resources.</p>
<sec id="section16a-0969733011425970">
<title>Facilities</title>
<p>Participants unanimously expressed the importance of availability of basic facilities. For example, the lack of facilities such as lavatories was one of the patients’ complaints. One patient said:<disp-quote>
<p>For example, here, there is a lavatory for some patients in a room. It is both lavatory and a place for dish washing. We are patients and it is out of our control. Now, for example, we are prisoners here, whether or not we need the lavatory?</p>
<p>(Patient 9)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16b-0969733011425970">
<title>Physical space</title>
<p>From the patient’s perspective, the physical environment of the ward, notably cleaning and lighting, was a factor that affected patient dignity and helped patients feel comfortable and valued.</p>
<p>For example, one patient stated:<disp-quote>
<p>Of course, we still have a lack of things. You see, when they are cleaning the building, they should clean it more. The cleaning of environment should be of importance for staff. This is important.</p>
<p>(Patient 18)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Regarding lighting, another participant believed that:<disp-quote>
<p>Yesterday, when I came to this unit, I had been mourning for the lights here. I am used to read books. When I was in CCU, I was comfortable because it was clear. But it is not here.</p>
<p>(Patient 5)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The results show that patient dignity means being treated with respect, being considered as a unique human being and having forgiveness. Intrapersonal features (inherent characteristics and individual beliefs), interpersonal interactions (staff behaviour), and quality of human and environment resources impacted on patient dignity.</p>
<p>In other words, having characteristics such as modesty, responsibility, empathy, and positive beliefs about human beings and human equality is important in creating a sense of worthiness. Also, communication, respect, enough information, privacy, and authority are factors associated with staff behaviour that make patients feel comfortable and valued. On the other hand, lack of staff, large number of patients, fatigued staff, regulations, and bureaucracy in hospitals can threaten patients’ sense of worth.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0969733011425970">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Participants in this study expressed different meanings of patient dignity. While many efforts have been made to define dignity, the concept remains unclear,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0969733011425970">20</xref>
</sup> complex, and multidimensional.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0969733011425970">17</xref>
</sup> There appears to be some confusion about the precise meaning and application of the dignity concept.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0969733011425970">21</xref>
</sup> Some meanings of patient dignity identified in this study are supported by previous research, including being considered as a unique human being,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0969733011425970">22</xref>
</sup> being treated with respect,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0969733011425970">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0969733011425970">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0969733011425970">24</xref>
</sup> and having forgiveness.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0969733011425970">25</xref>
</sup> </p>
<p>Considering patients as human beings when providing treatment and care is consistent with the concept of seeing a patient as a human being rather than an object.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0969733011425970">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0969733011425970">26</xref>
</sup> Other investigators in this area have emphasized human dignity as an ethical duty and a human right,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0969733011425970">16</xref>
</sup> and an inherent subjective element of human existence.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0969733011425970">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0969733011425970">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0969733011425970">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0969733011425970">26</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0969733011425970"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0969733011425970">28</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Heart failure patients expect healthcare staff to see and hear them as unique human beings.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0969733011425970">29</xref>
</sup> Baillie<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0969733011425970">17</xref>
</sup> defined human dignity as an inalienable right of all people, and other studies have confirmed this concept.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0969733011425970">26</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0969733011425970"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0969733011425970">28</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>However, because the participants were asked their view on the meaning of ‘patient dignity’, some responses were similar to their responses about factors associated with maintaining and promoting dignity, such as treating patients with respect and considering all people as unique human beings.</p>
<p>In this study, one factor enhancing or threatening patient dignity was intrapersonal features. This included modesty, responsibility, and empathy, as well as individual beliefs and attitudes about equality of all human beings.</p>
<p>Beliefs held by heart failure patients about factors related to dignity are derived from intrapersonal factors. In addition, patients may have particular individual beliefs about what constitutes dignity.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0969733011425970">16</xref>
</sup> Modesty, honesty, responsibility, patience, and kindness are important elements common to all cultures and are associated with individual lives.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0969733011425970">16</xref>
</sup> In this regard, Matiti and Trorey<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0969733011425970">30</xref>
</sup> believe that dignity is a social and cultural concept, and expectations associated with maintaining dignity are based on attitudes, values, and perceptions of individuals.</p>
<p>In this study, communication, respect, and privacy were identified as elements of interpersonal interaction. According to Jacobson’s theory, social status must be viewed within the context of the community, and includes two components: (1) dignity of self, including self-confidence and self-respect, expressed through interpersonal communication and (2) dignity in relation, referring to transferring process and reflection of value through words and actions according to the time and place.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0969733011425970">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0969733011425970">20</xref>
</sup> Dignity is therefore rooted in our communications and social relationships.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0969733011425970">31</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Sundin et al.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0969733011425970">29</xref>
</sup> found that when heart failure patients perceive a lack of communication, support or care, they lose a sense of personal value and may feel despair because of their dependence on the good will of others. This leads to worries about the future and unwanted changes in their lives because of their disease.</p>
<p>From the perspective of heart failure patients, in addition to communication, respect is also expected from staff. Jacelon et al.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0969733011425970">23</xref>
</sup> believe that the central idea of the behavioural component of dignity is related to action that ‘shows respect’. Thus, if staff demonstrate respectful behaviour when providing care, for example treating patients as equals, prompting attention, and being sensitive when performing a procedure, a part of patients’ expectations will be met,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0969733011425970">30</xref>
</sup> which can enhance a sense of value in patients. When heart failure patients do not perceive staff as empathetic or when staff are not affable and friendly, patients feel insecure and view staff as disrespectful.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0969733011425970">29</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Participants in this study were satisfied when healthcare staff took enough time to talk about their disease and received more information. One of the interactions that makes patients feel valued and in control is explaining and giving disease-related information to patients.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0969733011425970">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0969733011425970">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0969733011425970">32</xref>
</sup> Heart failure patients who receive continual support from staff and receive necessary information, or who are treated with dignity and friendliness, feel comfort, hope, and confidence.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0969733011425970">29</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>In this study, lack of privacy, for example bodily exposure in hospital, is recognized as a factor that threatens dignity. Wearing gowns increased vulnerability because of potential bodily exposure, but staff were largely unaware of how seriously this affected patients’ dignity.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0969733011425970">17</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>In this regard, Mann<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0969733011425970">33</xref>
</sup> suggested four categories of threats to dignity: (1) when a person is not seen as having value; (2) when a person is seen only as a member of a group; (3) when a person’s privacy is threatened; and (4) when a person is humiliated. Jacobson<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0969733011425970">20</xref>
</sup> confirmed this and stated that threats to dignity can take many forms, for example verbal or non-verbal, and can be manifested covertly as a lack of concern for or indifference to the problems of poor and disabled people or overtly by humiliating others. As in other studies,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0969733011425970">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0969733011425970">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0969733011425970">32</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0969733011425970"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0969733011425970"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0969733011425970"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0969733011425970"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0969733011425970"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0969733011425970">38</xref>
</sup> privacy is an important factor in maintaining dignity.</p>
<p>Participants in this study stated that both the quantity of resources (lack of staff and number of facilities) and the quality of resources (fatigued staff, management structure, and the cleanliness and lighting of the ward) are important factors that affect the patient’s dignity. Research suggests that the basic requirements of the institutions influence the limits of the preservation of dignity.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0969733011425970">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0969733011425970">22</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Other investigators addressing these domains agree that in the area of management, regulations and bureaucracy affect feelings of self-worth and patients’ perceptions of dignity.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0969733011425970">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0969733011425970">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0969733011425970">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0969733011425970">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0969733011425970">39</xref>
</sup> Also, patients believe that they do not receive the necessary and expected care from their care providers owing to limited resources and heavy staff workload.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0969733011425970">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0969733011425970">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0969733011425970">39</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>In this study, cleaning and lighting of the physical environment were highlighted in particular as effective factors of environmental resources in maintaining and promoting feelings of worth. Previous researches support the findings that appropriate physical environment, cleanliness, aesthetics of surroundings, and characteristics of units are important in promoting dignity.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0969733011425970">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0969733011425970">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0969733011425970">28</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0969733011425970">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Our results show that, for heart failure patients, the concept of dignity is complex and multidimensional. The patient/care index and resources are important in preserving and promoting the dignity of heart failure patients. The efforts of healthcare providers should enhance accountability, consider all patients as human beings, and promote respectful interactions with patients. Management structures should support and provide authority for improvements to facilities and proper maintenance of environmental resources. These factors support human and social rights, which maintain and promote the dignity of patients.</p>
<p>As few studies have been conducted about patient dignity in heart failure patients, the results of this study have contributed to this limitation of knowledge. This study affirms the importance of careful evaluation of individual patients to determine their needs in relation to dignity. We hope that these results will help to promote actions by care staff that honour and support patient dignity, resulting in benefits to patients.</p>
<p>A limitation of this study was that the dignity concept was based entirely on subjective views of participants and not on observed practice of staff in hospital wards. It is possible that application of other research approaches would reveal more information about the dignity concept in this population. Also, this study was conducted in Iran, and strategies to preserve and promote patient dignity may differ for patients from other cultures.</p>
<p>This study has implications in various settings of the healthcare system. It highlights the role of managerial, educational, and practice policies in the maintenance of patient dignity. The organizational and nursing managers are key factors in how staff, facilities, physical space, and care are organized and delivered, both quantitatively and qualitatively, in order to maintain dignity. In clinical practice, healthcare providers could be taught about factors related to dignity in interpersonal interactions with patients, and so act with dignity.</p>
<p>During undergraduate education, nursing students should be taught factors and strategies that meet patients’ expectations of how they would like their dignity to be maintained. This will help develop dignified nursing practice. The results of this study also may be used for developing of instruments for evaluating patient dignity. It is suggested that further studies using different methodologies may be useful in formulating strategies for the maintenance of patient dignity.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>The authors would like to thank all the participants in this study and Shahid Beheshti University in Tehran for financial support for this research.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn1-0969733011425970">
<p>This research was supported by funding from Shahid Beheshti University, Tehran.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn2-0969733011425970">
<p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0969733011425970">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Faith-Pratt</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nancy</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lindsey</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The lived experience of heart failure at the end of life: A systematic literature review</article-title>. <source>Health Soc Work</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0969733011425970">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>DSF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>DTF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kwong</surname>
<given-names>ANT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Woo</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name></person-group> <article-title>Living with chronic heart failure: A review of qualitative studies of older people</article-title>. <source>J Advan Nurs</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>474</fpage>–<lpage>483</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0969733011425970">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Verdiani</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ognibene</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rutili</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>NT-ProBNP reduction percentage during hospital stay predicts long-term mortality and readmission in heart failure patients</article-title>. <source>J Cardiovasc Med (Hagerstown, MD)</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>694</fpage>–<lpage>699</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0969733011425970">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rahnavard</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zolfaghari</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kazemnejad</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hatami-poor</surname>
<given-names>Kh</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An investigation of quality of life and factors affecting it in the patients with congestive heart failure</article-title>. <source>Hayat</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0969733011425970">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Boyde</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tuckett</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Learning for heart failure patients</article-title>. <source>J Clin Nurs</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>2030</fpage>–<lpage>2039</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0969733011425970">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Santos</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Plewka</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brofman</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Quality of life and clinical indicators in heart failure: A multivariate analysis</article-title>. <source>Arq Bras Cardio</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0969733011425970">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zambroski</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Moser</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bhat</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ziegler</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Impact of symptom prevalence and symptom burden on quality of life in patients with heart failure</article-title>. <source>Eu J Cardiovas Nurs</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0969733011425970">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wingate</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wiegand</surname>
<given-names>DLM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>End-of-life care in the critical care unit for patients with heart failure</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Nurse</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0969733011425970">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pihl</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fridlund</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Martensson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Patients’ experiences of physical limitations in daily life activities when suffering from chronic heart failure; A phenomenographic analysis</article-title>. <source>Scand J Caring Sci</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0969733011425970">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Molly</surname>
<given-names>GY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnston</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Witham</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Family care giving and CHF</article-title>. <source>Eur J Heart Fail</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>592</fpage>–<lpage>603</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0969733011425970">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chochinov</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krisjanson</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<name>
<surname>Hack</surname>
<given-names>TF</given-names>
</name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dignity in the terminally ill: Revisited</article-title>. <source>J Palliat Med</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>666</fpage>–<lpage>672</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0969733011425970">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Corvera-Tindel</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Doering</surname>
<given-names>LV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aqulino</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roper</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dracup</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>The role of physical functioning and depression in quality of life in patients with heart failure</article-title>. <source>J Card Fail</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0969733011425970">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cortis</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Palliative and supportive needs of older adults with heart failure</article-title>. <source>Int Nurs Rev</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0969733011425970">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nordgren</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Asp</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fagerberg</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An exploration of the phenomenon of formal care from the perspective of middle-aged heart failure patients</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cardiovas Nurs</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>129</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0969733011425970">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Walsh</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kowanko</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nurses’ and patients’ perceptions of dignity</article-title>. <source>Int J Nurs Pract</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0969733011425970">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>KK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dignity, respect for dignity, and dignity conserving in palliative care</article-title>. <source>Hong Kong Soc Palliat Med</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0969733011425970">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baillie</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Patient dignity in an acute hospital setting: A case study</article-title>. <source>Int J Nurs Stud</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0969733011425970">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hsieh</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shannon</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Three approaches to qualitative content analysis</article-title>. <source>Qual Health Res</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1277</fpage>–<lpage>1288</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0969733011425970">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Raphael</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Briscoe</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Davies</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Limitations of the New York Heart Association functional classification system and self-reported walking distances in chronic heart failure</article-title>. <source>Heart</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>476</fpage>–<lpage>482</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0969733011425970">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jacobson</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dignity and health: A review</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>292</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0969733011425970">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wainwright</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gallagher</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>On different types of dignity in nursing care: a critique of Nordenfelt</article-title>. <source>Nurs Philos</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0969733011425970">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Woolhead</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Calnan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dieppe</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tadd</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dignity in older age: what do older people in the United Kingdom think?</article-title> <source>Age Ageing</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0969733011425970">
<label>23</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jacelon</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Connelly</surname>
<given-names>TW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Proulx</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name></person-group>. <article-title>A concept analysis of dignity for older adults</article-title>. <source>J Adv Nurs</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0969733011425970">
<label>24</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pleschberger</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dignity and the challenge of dying in nursing homes: The residents’ view</article-title>. <source>Age Ageing</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0969733011425970">
<label>25</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sulmasy</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>At wit's end: Forgiveness, dignity, and the care of the dying</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0969733011425970">
<label>26</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Widang</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fridlund</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Self-respect, dignity and confidence: Conceptions of integrity among male patients</article-title>. <source>J Adv Nurs</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0969733011425970">
<label>27</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Berglund</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Anne-Cathrine</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Randers</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dignity not fully upheld when seeking health care: Experiences expressed by individuals suffering from Ehlers–Danlos syndrome</article-title>. <source>Disabil Rehabil</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0969733011425970">
<label>28</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sletteb</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Caspari</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lohne</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aasgaard</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Naden</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name></person-group>. <article-title>Dignity in the life of people with head injuries</article-title>. <source>J Adv Nurs</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>2426</fpage>–<lpage>2433</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0969733011425970">
<label>29</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sundin</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bruce</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barremo</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Elderly women’s experiences of support when living with congestive heart failure</article-title>. <source>Int J Qual Stud Health Well-being</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>5064</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0969733011425970">
<label>30</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Matiti</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Trorey</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Patients’ expectations of the maintenance of their dignity</article-title>. <source>J Clin Nurs</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>2709</fpage>–<lpage>2717</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0969733011425970">
<label>31</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>GN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chochinov</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dignity-based approaches in the care of terminally ill patients</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Support Palliat Care</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0969733011425970">
<label>32</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dawood</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gallini</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Using discovery interviews to understand the patient experience</article-title>. <source>Nurs Manag</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0969733011425970">
<label>33</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mann</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dignity and health: The UDHR’s revolutionary first article</article-title>. <source>Health Hum Rights</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0969733011425970">
<label>34</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gallagher</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seedhouse</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dignity in care: the views of patients and relatives</article-title>. <source>Nurs Times</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0969733011425970">
<label>35</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chochinov</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hack</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McClement</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kristjanson</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harlos</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name></person-group>. <article-title>Dignity in the terminally ill: A developing empirical model</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0969733011425970">
<label>36</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Woolhead</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tadd</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Boix-Ferrer</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Tu or Vous?: A European qualitative study of dignity and communication with older people in health and social care settings</article-title>. <source>Patient Educ Couns</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0969733011425970">
<label>37</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Henderson</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Van</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pearson</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Maintenance of patients’ dignity during hospitalization: Comparison of staff–patient observations and patient feedback through interviews</article-title>. <source>Int J Nurs Pract</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0969733011425970">
<label>38</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wadensten</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ahlstrim</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The struggle for dignity by people with severe functional disabilities</article-title>. <source>Nurs Ethics</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>465</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0969733011425970">
<label>39</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stabell</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Naden</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Patients’ dignity in a rehabilitation ward: Ethical challenges for nursing staff</article-title>. <source>Nurs Ethics</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>236</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>