<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIC</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjic</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Intensive Care Med</journal-id>
         <journal-title>Journal of Intensive Care Medicine</journal-title>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">0885-0666</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">1525-1489</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1559827612445707</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1559827612445707</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Editorial</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Extreme Obesity in the Intensive Care Unit</article-title>
            <subtitle>The Malignant Obesity Hypoventilation Syndrome</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Muñoz</surname>
                  <given-names>Sebastian</given-names>
               </name>
               <degrees>MS</degrees>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1559827612445707">1</xref>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1559827612445707">2</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Nowzaradan</surname>
                  <given-names>Younan</given-names>
               </name>
               <degrees>MD, FACS</degrees>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1559827612445707">3</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Varon</surname>
                  <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
               </name>
               <degrees>MD, FACP, FCCP, FCCM</degrees>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1559827612445707">4</xref>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-1559827612445707">5</xref>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6-1559827612445707">6</xref>
               <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1559827612445707"/>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <aff id="aff1-1559827612445707">
            <label>1</label>Dorrington Medical Associates, PA Houston, TX, USA</aff>
         <aff id="aff2-1559827612445707">
            <label>2</label>Universidad de Sonora, Department of Medicine and Health Sciences. Hermosillo, Sonora, México</aff>
         <aff id="aff3-1559827612445707">
            <label>3</label>Bariatric Center of Excellence, University General Hospital, Houston, TX, USA</aff>
         <aff id="aff4-1559827612445707">
            <label>4</label>University General Hospital, Houston, TX, USA</aff>
         <aff id="aff5-1559827612445707">
            <label>5</label>The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston, Department of Acute and Continuing Care, Houston, TX, USA</aff>
         <aff id="aff6-1559827612445707">
            <label>6</label>The University of Texas Medical Branch at Galveston, Department of Medicine, Galveston, TX, USA</aff>
         <author-notes>
            <corresp id="corresp1-1559827612445707">Joseph Varon, The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston, 2219 Dorrington Street, Houston, TX 77030, USA. Email: <email xlink:type="simple">Joseph.Varon@uth.tmc.edu</email>
            </corresp>
         </author-notes>
         <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
            <month>3</month>
            <year>2013</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>28</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <fpage>134</fpage>
         <lpage>135</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>extreme obesity</kwd>
            <kwd>obesity hypoventilation syndrome</kwd>
            <kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
            <kwd>multiorgan system dysfunction</kwd>
            <kwd>malignant obesity hypoventilation syndrome</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-wrap>
            <custom-meta xlink:type="simple">
               <meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
               <meta-value>March/April 2013</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-wrap>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Extreme obesity is currently a common medical condition. It is defined as having a body mass index (BMI) of &gt;40 kg/m<sup>2</sup> and is associated with an increased risk of mortality.<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1559827612445707">1</xref>
         </sup> A review of the clinical literature has shown that extreme obese patients are commonly admitted to the intensive care unit (ICU) for obstructive airway disease, pneumonia, and sepsis.<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1559827612445707">2</xref>
         </sup> A recent study found that patients with a BMI of &gt;40 kg/m<sup>2</sup> required greater mechanical ventilation and, therefore, a corresponding prolonged stay in the ICU.<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1559827612445707">3</xref>
         </sup>
      </p>
      <p>What are the other factors affecting the outcome of extreme obese patients in the ICU? In this issue of the <italic>Journal of Intensive Care Medicine</italic>, a new obesity-related condition among patients in the ICU with obesity hypoventilation syndrome (OHS) is now being described. The OHS is defined as the triad of obesity, daytime hypoventilation, and sleep-disordered breathing in the absence of an alternative neuromuscular, mechanical, or metabolic explanation for the hypoventilation episodes.<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1559827612445707">4</xref>
         </sup> Given this definition, a subtype condition has been identified in the extreme obese patients who had hypercapnic respiratory failure and multiorgan system dysfunction related to obesity, labeled as malignant obesity hypoventilation syndrome (MOHS).</p>
      <p>Marik and Desai coined this new term using a retrospective electronic chart review of 61 patients admitted to the ICU with a BMI of &gt;40 kg/m<sup>2</sup> and a PaCO<sub>2</sub> greater than 45 mm Hg in patients admitted with hypercapnic respiratory failure.<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1559827612445707">5</xref>
         </sup> Supporting the description of MOHS, a statistical analysis of the documentation from this study confirmed the presence of multisystem disorder in extreme obesity by finding that 86% of the patients had congestive heart failure treated with diuretics, 71% had left ventricular failure, 61% had left ventricular diastolic dysfunction, 77% had pulmonary hypertension above 45 mm Hg, 90% had essential hypertension, and 64% had abnormal liver function tests and diagnosed with nonalcoholic steatohepatitis. Moreover, this retrospective study showed that based on the clinical documentation, these patients fit the clinical criteria for OHS, however, only 3 were diagnosed with this condition and the remaining (75%) were diagnosed with and treated for chronic obstructive lung disease (COPD).</p>
      <p>A primary question that arises after reading the study of Marik and Desai is “Are patients with extreme obesity admitted to the ICU with a diagnosis of COPD/asthma being misdiagnosed when in fact they could have unrecognized OHS?” It is known that patients with extreme obesity statistically have hypercapnic respiratory failure that increases the length of stay in the ICU due to prolonged necessity for mechanical ventilation.<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1559827612445707">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1559827612445707">3</xref>
         </sup> It is also well known that hypoventilation and oxygen disturbances are related to obesity even if there is no intrinsic lung disease.<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1559827612445707">6</xref>
         </sup> Therefore, mechanical ventilation in the extreme obese patient is one of many challenges clinicians face since the increase in the prevalence of obesity, with a corresponding increase in ICU admissions.</p>
      <p>It is very concerning that only 3 of 61 patients had a confirmed diagnosis of OHS. More interestingly, the management of extreme obese patients with bilevel positive airway pressure (BiPAP) in this study failed in 23% of the patients, thus requiring mechanical ventilation. This was an unexpected finding which highlights again the challenge of managing respiratory failure and the use of mechanical ventilation in extremely obese patients. What would have happened if OHS was part of the medical history of these patients admitted to the ICU?</p>
      <p>It is well known that extremely obese patients with concomitant untreated obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) present cardiorespiratory deconditioning.<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1559827612445707">7</xref>
         </sup> Therefore, the failure to be diagnosed with OSA and OHS, which are disorders that should be readily recognized by a critical care clinician give cause for another alarming situation in the management of extremely obese patients. More alarming is that 75% of the patients admitted to the ICU with hypercapnic respiratory failure failed to receive the appropriate diagnosis of OHS and were in fact misdiagnosed as having COPD and asthma when the clinical documentation suggests that OHS is the more likely diagnosis.</p>
      <p>As extreme obesity is increasing, it is important to consider recommending bariatric surgery as a treatment for the patient’s condition. It is one of the only known effective weight loss treatments in these patients. The effectiveness of weight loss in this population has shown clinical improvement in the presence of diabetes, hypertension, and OSA.<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1559827612445707">8</xref>
         </sup> Needless to say is that during surgery, the presence of OHS, OSA, and now MOHS must be identified and taken into consideration for accurate ventilation of these patients, both intraoperatively and postoperatively to improve clinical outcomes in the ICU.</p>
      <p>The study by Marik and Desai is extremely important as it suggests an in-depth evaluation of the morbidly obese patients in the ICU and identifying known diagnoses associated with extreme obese patients when admitted to a critical care unit. It also emphasizes the need for clinicians to become aware of the presence of this syndrome and to start focusing on the recognition of MOHS and the appropriate management of the multiorgan dysfunction and its prognostic implications upon admission to the ICU.</p>
   </body>
   <back>
      <fn-group>
         <fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-1559827612445707">
            <label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
            <p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1559827612445707">
            <label>Funding</label>
            <p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="bibr1-1559827612445707">
            <label>1</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Adams</surname>
                     <given-names>KF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Schatzkin</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Harris</surname>
                     <given-names>TB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Overweight, obesity, and mortality in a large prospective cohort of persons 50 to 71 years old</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>355</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>763</fpage>–<lpage>778</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr2-1559827612445707">
            <label>2</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>El-Solh</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Sikka</surname>
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bozkanat</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Jaafar</surname>
                     <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Davies</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Morbid obesity in the medical ICU</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>120</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1989</fpage>–<lpage>1997</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr3-1559827612445707">
            <label>3</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Martino</surname>
                     <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Stapleton</surname>
                     <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Wang</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Extreme obesity and outcomes in critically ill patients</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>140</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1198</fpage>–<lpage>1206</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr4-1559827612445707">
            <label>4</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Mokhlesi</surname>
                     <given-names>B.</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group> 
               <article-title>Obesity hypoventilation syndrome: a state-of-the-art review</article-title>. <source>Respir Care</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1347</fpage>–<lpage>1362</lpage>; <comment>discussion 63-65</comment>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr5-1559827612445707">
            <label>5</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Marik</surname>
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Desai</surname>
                     <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Characteristics of patients with the “Malignant Obesity Hypoventilation Syndrome” admitted to the ICU [published online ahead of print May 6, 2012]</article-title>. <source>JICM</source>. <year>2012</year>. </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr6-1559827612445707">
            <label>6</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Banerjee</surname>
                     <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Yee</surname>
                     <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Piper</surname>
                     <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Zwillich</surname>
                     <given-names>CW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Grunstein</surname>
                     <given-names>RR</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Obesity hypoventilation syndrome: hypoxemia during continuous positive airway pressure</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>131</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1678</fpage>–<lpage>1684</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr7-1559827612445707">
            <label>7</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Vanhecke</surname>
                     <given-names>TE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Franklin</surname>
                     <given-names>BA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Zalesin</surname>
                     <given-names>KC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Cardiorespiratory fitness and obstructive sleep apnea syndrome in morbidly obese patients</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr8-1559827612445707">
            <label>8</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Buchwald</surname>
                     <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Avidor</surname>
                     <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Braunwald</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Bariatric surgery: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>292</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1724</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>