<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjir</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Industrial Relations</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1856</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1472-9296</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022185612442283</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0022185612442283</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Industrial Legislation in 2011</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>McCrystal</surname><given-names>Shae</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0022185612442283"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0022185612442283">University of Sydney, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Orchiston</surname><given-names>Tashina</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-0022185612442283">University of Sydney, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0022185612442283">Shae McCrystal, Sydney Law School, Building F10, University of Sydney, Sydney 2006, NSW, Australia. [email: <email>shae.mccrystal@sydney.edu.au</email>]</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>54</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<issue-title>Annual Review of Industrial Relations</issue-title>
<issue-title>Guest Editor: Rae Cooper</issue-title>
<fpage>277</fpage>
<lpage>292</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Australian Labour and Employment Relations Association (ALERA), SAGE Publications Ltd, Los Angeles, London, New Delhi, Singapore and Washington DC</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">ALERA</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Consolidation and industry-specific legislation were two general themes in 2011 federal developments, signifying a shift in the legislative agenda after the implementation of the Fair Work Act 2009 (Cth). Starting with the first theme, this article considers: steps towards streamlining federal equality law; the progress and pitfalls in the occupational health and safety harmonization process; and proposed enhancements to the national paid parental leave system, including steps to resolve teething problems caused by the interaction between Paid Parental Leave and Fair Work legislation. Second, we review industry-specific developments. These include: a Bill to introduce a ‘safe rates’ regime and allow for independent contractor collective bargaining in the road transport sector; and a Bill to extend the bulk of Fair Work Act 2009 (Cth) protections to textile, clothing and footwear industry contractors and make it easier for these workers to recover unpaid debts across the supply chain. Third, we summarize relevant state developments, which were diverse in focus.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Australian industrial relations</kwd>
<kwd>building and construction industry</kwd>
<kwd>clothing and footwear industry</kwd>
<kwd>discrimination</kwd>
<kwd>equality</kwd>
<kwd>occupational health and safety harmonization</kwd>
<kwd>paid parental leave</kwd>
<kwd>textile</kwd>
<kwd>transport industry</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0022185612442283" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Developments in federal industrial relations legislation in 2011 were more incremental than in the previous few years. With the Fair Work Act 2009 (Cth) (FW Act) bedded down ahead of a scheduled legislative review in 2012, focus shifted to national consolidation in other areas, including: federal discrimination law; the work health and safety harmonization process; and implementation problems with the paid parental leave scheme that commenced operation at the beginning of the year.</p>
<p>There was also a partial shift in focus from national-level to industry-specific legislation, as exemplified by the Fair Work (Textile, Clothing and Footwear Industry) Bill 2011, the Road Safety Remuneration Bill 2011 and Coal Mining Industry (Long Service Leave) Legislation Amendment Act 2011. This last Act, which is not discussed in this article, finalized a uniform portable statutory long service leave scheme for the black coal mining industry applicable to eligible full-time, part-time and casual employees. The federal government’s proposed changes to building and construction legislation also returned to the legislative agenda.</p>
<p>At state level, New South Wales (NSW) was again the standout, passing a raft of industrial legislation predominantly relating to public sector employment. In the remaining states and territories: Victoria scaled down the powers of its Equal Opportunity Commission and expanded discrimination exceptions for religious institution employers; the Australian Capital Territory (ACT) passed workplace privacy legislation; Western Australia (WA) implemented changes to its workers’ compensation regime and construction industry portable paid long service leave scheme; and the Northern Territory (NT) amended its public sector legislation; and Tasmania (Tas) modified eligibility requirements for long service leave.</p>
<p>This review will outline changes to federal discrimination legislation, including: progress with respect to consolidation of the four substantive Acts; progress and setbacks in harmonizing work health and safety laws; and changes proposed after the first year of operation of the paid parental leave scheme. Proposed legislative changes at industry level will then be examined, before a round-up of developments in the states.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec2-0022185612442283"><title>Developments in Discrimination and Equality Law</title>
<p>As pre-empted in last year’s review (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022185612442283">McCrystal and Smith, 2011</xref>), the Sex and Age Discrimination Amendment Act 2011 was passed by the Federal Parliament, giving effect to the recommendations made by the Senate Standing Committee on Legal and Constitutional Affairs in its 2008 <italic>Inquiry into the Effectiveness of the Sex Discrimination Act in Eliminating Discrimination and Promoting Gender Equality</italic>.</p>
<p>Amendments to the Sex Discrimination Act 1984 (SD Act) include greater protection from discrimination on the grounds of family responsibilities and breastfeeding, and extended sexual harassment coverage. Protection on the basis of family responsibilities had been limited to direct discrimination and to termination only. There were also some limitations on men using any of the protections under the SD Act, including the family responsibilities protections. Following the changes, the family responsibilities ground extends to all areas of work, including contracting, and the Act applies equally to male and female workers. However, protection on the ground of family responsibilities was not extended to indirect discrimination (SD Act s. 7A) – a concession made by the government in order to secure the Bill’s passage. This leaves federal protection out of step with existing protections available under most of the states’ and territories’ discrimination acts, which prohibit indirect family responsibilities discrimination. Conversely, the inclusion of breastfeeding as a specific attribute extends to both direct and indirect discrimination, and applies in the other areas of life covered by the SD Act (SD Act s. 7AA(2)).</p>
<p>With respect to sexual harassment, the amendments have removed the necessity of proving that a reasonable person would have anticipated that the harassed person would be offended, humiliated or hurt by the conduct. It is now sufficient to show that a reasonable person would have anticipated <italic>the possibility</italic> of causing offence, humiliation or intimidation (SD Act s. 28A). The new SD Act s. 28G(2) extends the prohibition on sexual harassment to customers and clients seeking or receiving the supply of goods and services, expanding on the previous protection, which applied to sexual harassment by service providers only. Additionally, the amendments extended sexual harassment cover to two further situations: first, harassment by a staff member of an educational institution towards a student of another educational institution, provided the sexual harassment occurs in connection with the harasser’s employment; and, second, harassment by an adult student of an educational institution with respect to a student or a staff member at another educational institution, where the sexual harassment occurs in connection with the harasser being a student of their educational institution (SD Act s. 28F).</p>
<p>Amendments to the Age Discrimination Act 2004 establish the full-time position of Age Discrimination Commissioner (currently Susan Ryan), to serve a maximum appointment of seven years, and allow the Minister to appoint an acting Commissioner in the event that the Commissioner is absent or cannot fulfil their functions for another reason.</p>
<p>Future legislative change in the area of federal equality law is likely as a result of current efforts to consolidate federal discrimination legislation. At the time of writing, the Commonwealth Attorney-General’s Department had released a discussion paper and was engaging in national community consultation, with an exposure draft of the new legislation due for release in early 2012. Due to constitutional limitations, the new Act will not replace existing state and territory discrimination laws. However, the Attorney-General’s Department has stated its intention to streamline and simplify current federal discrimination law for the benefit of employers, creating a new equality law to replace the existing four discrimination statutes. Two aspects of the proposed legislation are certain: no existing protections will be lost; and two new protected grounds will be included – sexual orientation and gender identity.</p>
<p>Legislation is also expected in early 2012 to amend and rename the Equal Opportunity in the Workplace Act 1999 and associated Equality Opportunity in the Workplace Agency (EOWA) (Thomson Reuters, 2011). The new Act will be called the Workplace Gender Equality Act (WGE Act) and will establish the Workplace Gender Equality Agency (WGEA). The federal government has announced that the legislation will require businesses to report on flexibility measures for male and female employees, pay equity, and the actual gender composition figures of boards and management. It will also remove the ability of the EOWA Director to waive reporting requirements for organizations who have met certain prerequisites; all organizations with more than 100 employees will be required to report annually, through a new online portal. WGEA will be given powers to conduct compliance ‘spot checks’ and businesses will have to make annual gender equality reports available to their employees and shareholders. As an added compliance incentive, businesses who do not meet their responsibilities under the WGE Act will be ineligible for government grants or other assistance and unable to receive government contracts. The new reporting regime is scheduled to commence in 2013 Ellis (2011).</p></sec>
<sec id="sec3-0022185612442283"><title>Harmonization of Occupational Health and Safety Laws</title>
<p>Continuing the theme of national consolidation, the process of harmonization of Australia’s differing occupational health and safety (OHS) laws progressed throughout 2011, with an ambitious scheduled commencement date of 1 January 2012. The history of the harmonization process and a brief summary of the substance of the proposed new regime are set out in last year’s review (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022185612442283">McCrystal and Smith, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>The harmonization process depends upon the passage by each of the states and territories of model legislation developed by Safe Work Australia (SWA): the Work Health and Safety Act. The key feature of the model legislation is the imposition of a primary duty of care on a person ‘conducting a business or undertaking’ to ensure, ‘so far as reasonably practicable’, the health and safety of ‘workers engaged or caused to be engaged by the person’ and ‘workers whose activities in carrying out work are influenced or directed by the person’ while the workers are at work (clauses 18 and 19). This primary duty is supplemented by a range of specific duties applicable to a broader range of persons (clauses 20–29) and an obligation on officers of businesses or undertakings to exercise due diligence in ensuring that the business or undertaking complies with any duty or obligations under the Act (clause 27).</p>
<p>During 2011, SWA continued to work on model regulations and codes of practice, releasing draft versions for public comment in September. Of particular note is the draft code of practice on <italic>Work Health and Safety Consultation, Co-Operation and Co-Ordination</italic>. It provides guidance on the implementation of the obligation in clause 46 of the model Act for duty-holders to consult, cooperate and coordinate activities with all other persons who have a duty in relation to the same matter. The draft code makes it clear that this innovative feature of the model legislation imposes a concrete horizontal obligation on duty-holders to work cooperatively in areas of common responsibility. Other developments in 2011 include the <italic>National Compliance and Enforcement Policy</italic> to coordinate a nationally consistent approach to compliance and enforcement across jurisdictions, and <italic>Transitional Principles for Implementing the Model WHS Act</italic> to encourage harmonized transitional arrangements among the states. Under the transitional principles, sectors where the regulations introduce ‘a new or significantly different set of duties’ have been given an additional 12 months to comply with the new laws.</p>
<p>At the time of writing, the model legislation had been introduced into Parliament in seven jurisdictions (the Commonwealth, the ACT, NSW, the NT, Queensland, South Australia (SA) and Tasmania), and passed in five: the ACT, the Commonwealth, the NT, NSW and Queensland. Debate on the legislation in SA and Tasmania has been postponed until their respective parliaments resume in 2012. The Victorian government has indicated that it will not adopt the model legislation until further analysis of the proposed legislation, and has called for a 12-month implementation delay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0022185612442283">Rich-Phillips, 2011</xref>). The WA government has also indicated that it will not adopt the model legislation until 2012, and that it will most likely amend some of the substantive terms of the legislation upon implementation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0022185612442283">Work Safe WA, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>The potential that some states will not implement the model legislation at all is a substantial threat to the harmonization process. Equally, in some states, variations to the text of the legislation may be made. This is foreshadowed in WA and has already occurred in NSW. In NSW in October 2010, the Australian Labor Party (ALP) government had indicated that it would not implement the model legislation without changes to the manner by which contravention of the primary duty of care is established (insisting on a shift of onus to the employer once breach is found) and the range of parties able to bring prosecutions under the Act (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022185612442283">McCrystal and Smith, 2011</xref>: 292–294). When the ALP lost office in March 2011, a Liberal–National Coalition came to power, which had expressed public support for the model Act (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0022185612442283"><italic>Workplace Express</italic>, 2011a</xref>). It introduced the model legislation in full to the NSW Parliament, and amendments to the existing Occupational Health and Safety Act 2000 (OHS Act) that would implement the primary duty and remove union-led prosecutions before 1 January 2012. However, the ALP combined with the Greens and other minor parties in the NSW Upper House to amend the Bill to retain union-led prosecutions of category one and category two offences (the most serious offence levels<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0022185612442283">1</xref></sup>) where the relevant regulator has declined to follow the advice of the Director of Public Prosecutions to bring proceedings (Work Health and Safety Act 2011 (NSW) s. 230(1)(c), 230(3)). The attempt to abolish union-led prosecutions from pre-existing NSW legislation was also rejected by the Upper House. The amended Acts were subsequently passed by the NSW Lower House.</p>
<p>The Work Health and Safety Act 2011 (NSW) (WHS Act) commenced operation on 1 January 2012. The regulator under the NSW Act is WorkCover NSW and, specifically for mining and coal workplaces, the head of the Department of Trade and Investment, Regional Infrastructure and Services. The changes to the OHS Act took effect from 7 June 2011, implementing the primary and associated duties, removing the shifting onus of proof for contraventions of the statute and implementing the obligation of due diligence on corporate officers. The OHS Act and associated regulations were repealed by the commencement of the WHS Act, although the NSW Parliament has retained the capacity to maintain the currency of regulations made under the repealed OHS Act by declaration; and pre-existing industry codes of practice remain in effect.</p>
<p>There are additional features of the NSW Act worth noting. Historically, jurisdiction over OHS matters in NSW has rested with the NSW Industrial Relations Court. The WHS Act almost entirely removes the OHS jurisdiction of the Court, except with respect to category three offences, the lowest level of offence under the Act. Further, NSW has not repealed its myriad industry-specific OHS legislation. For example, both the Mine Health and Safety Act 2004 and the Coal Mine Health and Safety Act 2002 have been retained, although the separate Boards established under these Acts have been abolished and replaced by a new Mining Competence Board.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0022185612442283">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>In contrast to NSW, the model legislation was passed without substantive changes in Queensland, the ACT and the NT and commenced on 1 January 2012. Under the Queensland Act, the relevant regulator is Workplace Health and Safety Queensland. Industry-specific OHS legislation in Queensland was reviewed in the process of passing the model legislation, leading to the repeal of some legislation (e.g. the Dangerous Goods Safety Management Act 2001) and the amendment of other Acts to ensure consistency with the new Act (e.g. the Electrical Safety Act 2002). In the ACT, the relevant regulator is Worksafe ACT. Pre-existing ACT OHS provisions allowing for union-led prosecutions were not maintained. In the NT, the relevant regulator is the Work Health Authority.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec4-0022185612442283"><title>Paid Parental Leave and Unpaid Leave Entitlements</title>
<p>The paid parental leave scheme implemented by the Paid Parental Leave Act 2010 (PPL Act) commenced operation on 1 January 2011. The substance of the scheme was reported in last year’s review essay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022185612442283">McCrystal and Smith, 2011</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022185612442283">Baird and Williamson, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0022185612442283">McCarthy et al., 2011</xref>). It entitles eligible workers who are primary carers to 18 weeks of government-funded payments upon the birth or adoption of a child. Employers took over the PPL Act paymaster function in July 2011 and now administer payments to eligible employees.</p>
<p>After the first 10 months of operation of the new scheme, legislation was introduced into the Federal Parliament to make post-implementation amendments to the PPL Act and the FW Act. The Paid Parental Leave and Other Legislation Amendment (Consolidation) Bill 2011 proposes a range of administrative amendments to the PPL Act to improve its clarity and consistency. It also proposes amendments to the FW Act with respect to flexibility around the date at which unpaid parental leave may be taken, and inserts return-to-work notice periods with respect to the early end of unpaid parental leave due to stillbirth or infant death. Two further substantive amendments will resolve existing difficulties with the PPL Act and its interaction with the FW Act.</p>
<p>First, the amendments will modify the ‘work test’, which determines eligibility for the parental leave payment, to fix a problem with the operation of the PPL Act in relation to women who experience difficulties working during a pregnancy. Under the work test, a claimant cannot have had an unpaid break of more than eight weeks during the preceding 13 months and must demonstrate sufficient paid hours throughout the remainder of the period. This could impact a female claimant who is unable to perform paid work during her pregnancy, or a substantial period of her pregnancy, due to a pregnancy-related complication. Under proposed s. 36A of the PPL Act, where the applicant for the payment is the birth mother of the child, they may be taken to have satisfied the work test if the Secretary of the Department of Families, Housing, Community Services and Indigenous Affairs is satisfied that they would have fulfilled the work test but did not because the child was born prematurely, or because of pregnancy-related complications or illness that prevented them from performing paid work.</p>
<p>Second, the PPL Act allows for a claimant to perform up to 10 days of paid work (‘keeping in touch’ days) while receiving parental leave payments where both the employee and employer agree (PPL Act ss 49–50). Under the current PPL Act, these days cannot be taken within 14 days after the day that the child was born. The amendments will extend this period to 42 days, unless the claimant suggests or requests an earlier day (which cannot be within the first 14 days) (proposed new s. 50(c)). The explanatory memorandum to the Bill notes that this provision is to ‘enable an uninterrupted six-week period for the caring parent to bond with the child’ but in a manner that retains ‘flexibility for employees’. Amendments are also proposed to the FW Act to fix an inconsistency between the PPL Act, which allows for ‘keeping in touch’ days, and the unpaid parental leave provisions of the FW Act, which require unpaid parental leave to be taken in a single continuous period (FW Act s. 71(2)). The amendments will insert a new s. 79A into the FW Act providing that the parental leave provisions do not prevent an employee from performing work on a ‘keeping in touch’ day during unpaid parental leave, and that such a day does not break the continuity of a period of unpaid parental leave.</p>
<p>Additionally, the federal government has announced that from 1 January 2013, eligible fathers and partners will also be entitled to two weeks of government-funded payments at the rate of minimum wage while on leave from work upon the birth or adoption of a child (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0022185612442283">Australian Government, 2011</xref>). Legislation to provide for these payments should be introduced into the Federal Parliament in 2012.</p>
<p>Consolidation of discrimination laws, harmonization of work health and safety laws, and consistency between the PPL Act and the FW Act are developments designed to streamline and consolidate legislation with a national impact. However, recognition of the need for industry-focused regulation, particularly in industries with relatively high numbers of independent contractor workers, was also a theme of 2011. The discussion will now look at proposed changes in three industries: transport; clothing, textile and footwear; and building and construction, before examining state developments.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec5-0022185612442283"><title>Transport Industry – ‘Safe Rates’</title>
<p>Health and safety in the Australian long-haul road transport sector has been an ongoing matter of concern for federal and state regulators. Subcontracting arrangements, intense competition, downward price pressures from clients and the prevalence of owner-drivers in the industry have long been recognized as factors that can substantially compromise health and safety (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0022185612442283">Quinlan, 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>In November 2011, the Road Safety Remuneration Bill 2011 (RSR Bill) was introduced into Federal Parliament. The Bill had its genesis in a 2008 report of the National Transport Commission (NTC), prepared in response to a request from the Australian Transport Council (a state and federal ministerial forum) to examine the underlying causes of unsafe practices in the road transport industry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0022185612442283">NTC, 2008</xref>). The report found a connection between payment rates and health and safety in long-haul road transport, and proposed a number of mechanisms to establish a minimum ‘safe rates’ regime for both owner-drivers and employee drivers in the industry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0022185612442283">NTC, 2008</xref>). In response, the federal government established the Safe Rates Advisory Group and published a directions paper in November 2010 canvassing a range of regulatory initiatives, including the introduction of minimum payment rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0022185612442283">Australian Government, 2010</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0022185612442283">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>The RSR Bill proposes the establishment of an independent Road Safety Remuneration Tribunal, consisting of a President (who is also a Deputy Presidential member of Fair Work Australia (FWA)), at least two (but not more than four) FWA members holding dual appointments, and at least two (but not more than four) industry experts holding part-time appointments (RSR Bill Part 6). The Tribunal will have a range of functions, including the power to: set minimum remuneration rates for employee and independent contractors in the industry; approve collective agreements for independent contractors; conciliate and, by consent, arbitrate disputes; and conduct research into remuneration-related matters that may affect safety in the industry (RSR Bill clause 80). The legislation will cover all employee and independent contractor drivers (individuals and those operating in corporate form) within the limits of the Federal Parliament’s legislative competence (RSR Bill clauses 5–8).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0022185612442283">4</xref></sup> This will only exclude sole trader drivers working exclusively within one state who are engaged by a business that does not operate in corporate form (e.g. sole traders or partnerships).</p>
<p>The establishment of minimum rates and the approval of collective agreements will be significant developments if the legislation is passed. Minimum rates will be set through ‘road safety remuneration orders’, which may be made by the Tribunal either acting on its own initiative or on application by an interested party (a driver, an employer or hirer of a driver, a supply chain participant, or a relevant industrial association) (RSR Bill clause 19). Once the Tribunal has complied with consultation requirements, an order may be made with respect to: minimum remuneration and other entitlements for employees and contractors; conditions for loading and unloading (including waiting times), hours, load limits and payment methods; and methods for reducing or removing remuneration-related incentives, pressures and practices that contribute to unsafe work practices (RSR Bill clause 27). Orders are binding (and may impose obligations on participants in relevant supply chains). For employees, orders will apply to the extent that any relevant award, agreement, order or instrument is less beneficial than the order; for contractors, orders will apply regardless of the terms of any road transport contract to which they are a party (RSR Bill clauses 12, 13). These proposals are groundbreaking because outside of outworker regulation under the FW Act, they establish the first national system for minimum wage and conditions protections for a class of independent contractor workers.</p>
<p>Equally unprecedented is the proposal to allow for the creation of enforceable enterprise-level collective agreements for independent contractors in the road transport sector. Under proposed clause 33 of the RSR Bill, the Tribunal may grant a ‘safe remuneration approval’ for a ‘road transport collective agreement’ under which a collective of contractor road transport drivers and a hirer, or potential hirer, of those drivers agree about remuneration and related conditions for the services to be provided by those drivers. Such an approval may only be made where a road safety remuneration order is otherwise in effect with respect to the relevant drivers, a majority of the drivers will be better off under the agreement than the order and have approved the agreement, and the agreement includes a method for adjusting remuneration levels where it operates for more than one year (RSR Bill clause 34). The significance of this proposed reform is that it provides a mechanism for the <italic>enforcement</italic> of such collective agreements, and a <italic>safety net</italic> against which they can be negotiated. However, there is nothing in the proposed legislation to deal with the problem that the collective setting of remuneration for contractors in this manner could potentially constitute anti-competitive conduct under the Competition and Consumer Act 2010 (Cth) (CC Act) (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022185612442283">McCrystal, 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0022185612442283">2009</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0022185612442283">5</xref></sup> At the time of writing, neither the RSR Bill nor its companion consequential amendments Bill create an exemption from the CC Act for these purposes. The Bill had not yet been debated, and this problem will hopefully be addressed during the Bill’s passage through the Federal Parliament in 2012.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec6-0022185612442283"><title>Textile, Clothing and Footwear Industry</title>
<p>Also introduced in November, the Fair Work Amendment (Textile, Clothing and Footwear Industry) Bill 2011 (TCF Bill) will increase protection for outworkers in the textile, clothing and footwear industry, bringing independent contractor outworkers under the terms of the FW Act (with some exceptions). The TCF Bill extends the bulk of FW Act terms and conditions to most contractor textile clothing and footwear outworkers as if they were employees. This will extend the present protection of these workers to the majority of the Act, removing a significant legal difference in their treatment when compared to employee outworkers. The Bill also deals with the rights of outworkers to recover unpaid moneys from almost any party in a supply chain of contracts stretching up to (but not including) the ultimate retailer, and provides for the creation of mandatory legal obligations in the form of a code that can bind all parties in the relevant supply chain up to and including the ultimate retailer.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec7-0022185612442283"><title>Building and Construction Industry</title>
<p>As reported in last year’s review (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022185612442283">McCrystal and Smith, 2011</xref>), legislation introduced by the federal government in 2009 to repeal industry-specific regulation of the building and construction industry, abolish the Australian Building and Construction Commission (BC Commission) and establish a new federal agency to oversee industrial relations in the industry (Office of the Fair Work Building Industry Inspectorate) lapsed when the Federal Parliament was dissolved for the 2010 federal election. In November 2011, the federal government reintroduced the Bill into Parliament. The new Bill largely mirrors the earlier Bill, retaining the controversial compulsory examination powers (vested in the new agency and subject to oversight by the Commonwealth ombudsman) that led to the Bill’s demise in 2010 when the federal government was unable to secure the support of the Greens to their inclusion. A five-year sunset clause on the compulsory examination powers included in the original Bill has been reduced to three years in the new Bill. At the end of 2011, it remained to be seen if this change would be enough to secure sufficient Green and Independent support to pass the Bill. Amendments proposed by the Greens to remove the compulsory examination powers suggest that the stalemate will continue in 2012.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec8-0022185612442283"><title>Developments in the States and Territories</title>
<sec id="sec9-0022185612442283"><title>New South Wales</title>
<p>In <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022185612442283">NSW, the O’Farrell Coalition government elected in March 2011</xref> began implementing its legislative agenda with respect to regulation of the public sector. In June, Parliament passed the Industrial Relations Amendment (Public Sector Conditions of Employment) Act 2011, inserting s. 146C into the NSW Industrial Relations Act 1996 (IR Act) to substantially reduce the discretion of the NSW Industrial Relations Commission (NSWIRC) when exercising arbitral functions with respect to employment conditions in the public sector. In making any award or order with respect to public sector employees (including an award, approval of an enterprise agreement, flow-on of national wage cases or during dispute resolution), the NSWIRC must give effect to any applicable government policy on conditions of employment declared by the regulations (IR Act s. 146C(1) and (8)). Any award or order inconsistent with this obligation has no effect (IR Act s. 146C(3)). This amendment was swiftly followed with the Industrial Relations (Public Sector Conditions of Employment) Regulation 2011, which sets out the first declaration for the purposes of s. 146C. Under the declaration, public sector employees may only be awarded increases in remuneration or other conditions of employment that do not increase employee-related costs by more than 2.5% per annum, unless any increase above that amount is fully offset by employee-related cost savings (which cannot be found by decreasing guaranteed minimum conditions of employment related to leave and superannuation payments).</p>
<p>According to the Second Reading Speech (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022185612442283">NSW Parliament, 2011</xref>: 24 May, 889), the goal of the legislation was to prevent the NSWIRC from ‘disregarding’ government wages policy when exercising its discretion, and to support the achievement of ‘budgetary objectives’. However, the legislation and its associated regulation went further than this, effectively imposing a cap on any increases to public service salaries and conditions that cumulatively exceed 2.5% per annum unless those increases are completely offset by other savings. This means that to some extent the NSWIRC is no longer an ‘independent’ umpire in resolving disputes over pay and conditions between the public service and their employer – the government – but must comply with the dictates of the government in setting awards, approving enterprise agreements and resolving disputes. A challenge to the constitutional validity of the amending Act and the relevant regulation was dismissed by a Full Bench of the NSW Industrial Court on the basis that the Act only applies to the NSWIRC, an arbitral tribunal, and has no effect on the body when constituted as a Court. In late November, the NSW Public Sector Association applied to the High Court for special leave to appeal this decision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0022185612442283"><italic>Workplace Express</italic>, 2011b</xref>).</p>
<p>The fettering of the discretion of the NSWIRC, combined with the abolition of most of the jurisdiction of the NSW Industrial Court with respect to work health and safety (discussed earlier), has raised questions over the future of this long-standing NSW institution. In November 2011, the NSW Legislative Council’s Standing Committee on Law and Justice commenced an inquiry into ‘Opportunities to Consolidate Tribunals in NSW’. Its remit involves consideration of the current and forecast workload of the NSWIRC and Industrial Court.</p>
<p>Three other pieces of legislation passed in NSW in 2011 are worthy of note. In October, amendments to the Public Sector Employment and Management Act 2002 (PS Act) took effect. The amendments set out ‘core values’ for the NSW public sector with respect to integrity, trust, service and accountability (PS Act s. 3B) and established a new office, the Public Service Commissioner, to, among other things, promote and maintain the core values (PS Act ss 3C(1), 3D). The Public Sector Commissioner will be advised by a Public Service Commission Advisory Board (PS Act s. 3Q). In late November, amendments to the Industrial Relations Act 1996 (NSW) were passed, which will enable the NSWIRC to repeal obsolete NSW awards in full or in part, reversing the unusual provisions that were inserted into the Act in 2010 that stopped the NSWIRC from abolishing obsolete awards that no longer applied to anyone (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022185612442283">McCrystal and Smith, 2011</xref>). Finally, the Police Amendment (Death and Disability) Act 2011 was passed just before the NSW Parliament rose for the year, despite fierce opposition and threats to strike by NSW police (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0022185612442283">Bennett, 2011</xref>). The Act terminated an existing award-based scheme providing death and disability payments to injured or killed police officers, replacing it with an insurance-based model regulated by the Police Act 1990. It also amended the IR Act to remove the jurisdiction of the NSWIRC over police death and disability payments.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec10-0022185612442283"><title>Victoria</title>
<p>In Victoria, the Liberal government amended the Equal Opportunity Amendment Act 2011, winding back some of the more beneficial aspects of the Equal Opportunity Act 2010 (EO Act) that had been introduced by the previous Labor government (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022185612442283">McCrystal and Smith, 2011</xref>), but had not yet commenced when the Amendment Act was passed. Under the changes, the Victorian Equal Opportunity Commission (VEOC) has been stripped of its power to conduct public inquiries in relation to serious discrimination, sexual harassment or victimization matters involving a particular class or group (EO Act s. 129). The changes also restrict its ability to commence investigations into contraventions of the Act. Under the 2010 changes, VEOC was empowered to conduct investigations into serious possible contraventions of the EO Act relating to a class or group of persons where it would advance the Act’s objects. Now, it may only conduct such an investigation if it meets two further requirements: the issue cannot reasonably be expected to be resolved by dispute resolution or the Victorian Civil and Administrative Tribunal, and VEOC has reasonable grounds to suspect a contravention has occurred (EO Act s. 127). Other notable changes to the EO Act include the removal of the inherent requirements test in the exception for discrimination in employment in relation to religious institutions, making it possible for religious institutions to discriminate on the basis of religious belief or activity, sex, sexual orientation, lawful sexual activity, marital status, parental status or gender identity, regardless of whether adherence to religious doctrines is an inherent requirement of the particular position. Instead, discrimination on the basis of these attributes will be justifiable provided that it conforms to the doctrines of the religion and is reasonably necessary to avoid injury to adherents of the religion (EO Act ss 82–83).</p>
<p>The Victorian Parliament also amended the Public Holidays Act 1993 to allow non-metropolitan councils to make a request to the Minister nominating alternative public holidays in lieu of Melbourne Cup Day, either two half-days or one whole day. Second, the Shop Trading Reform Act 1996 was amended to remove shop trading restrictions on Easter Sunday.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec11-0022185612442283"><title>Australian Capital Territory</title>
<p>The passage of the Workplace Privacy Act 2011 (WP Act) was the major reform in the ACT. The WP Act regulates the collection and use of workplace surveillance information, bringing the ACT into line with Victoria and NSW, which have similar legislation. WP Act s. 13 makes it unlawful to conduct workplace surveillance unless written notice is provided to workers (defined broadly to include employees, contractors and volunteers). Notice must be given 14 days in advance (or a lesser period if the worker agrees), and must give details about the type of surveillance device that will be used, period of surveillance and the use of data obtained. Certain private ‘non-work’ areas are deemed off-limits from surveillance, including toilets, changing rooms, showers and prayer rooms (s. 41). Covert surveillance is permissible in relation to suspected illegal activity, but only with the permission of a magistrate (ss 26–28).</p></sec>
<sec id="sec12-0022185612442283"><title>Northern Territory</title>
<p>The major legislative development in the NT in 2011 was amendments to the Public Sector Employment and Management Act in relation to public sector employment. The amendments inserted two major new Parts into the Act. The new Part 1A deals with general public sector principles, including an ‘administration management principle’, a ‘human resource management principle’ (implementing the ‘merit principle’ and the ‘equality of employment opportunity principle’) and the ‘performance and conduct principle’. The new Part 7 implements a new statutory process for managing employee performance and inability in the NT public service.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec13-0022185612442283"><title>Western Australia</title>
<p>The WA Parliament implemented major changes to the Workers’ Compensation and Injury Management Act 1981 (WCIM Act), in response to recommendations made by WorkCover WA in its 2009 legislative review. The changes include providing common law safety net entitlements for injured workers who are employed by uninsured employers, and streamlining the dispute resolution framework to ensure it is ‘timely’, ‘accessible’ and ‘minimizes costs’. This includes vesting the Director of the newly named Workers’ Compensation Conciliation Service with the power to fast-track matters where conciliation is unlikely to result in benefit to the parties (WCIM Act s. 182H), and empowering conciliators to compel parties to attend conciliation, answer questions and produce documents (WCIM Act s. 182J).</p>
<p>The WA Parliament also amended the Construction Industry Portable Paid Long Service Leave Act 1985 to remove ambiguities in the Act’s operation, create civil penalty provisions for contravention of portable long service leave scheme requirements and allow the Minister to appoint two members to the Industry Board that oversees the scheme.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec14-0022185612442283"><title>Tasmania</title>
<p>Amendments to the Tasmanian Long Service Leave Act 1976 brought the long service leave entitlements of Tasmanian employees more in line with other states by reducing the minimum qualifying period for access to long service leave from 15 years to 10 years of service (see ss. 8(2) &amp; 12(10)(a)).</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec15-0022185612442283"><title>Conclusion: Future Developments in Federal Legislation</title>
<p>In terms of achieving nationally consistent legislation in the regulation of industrial relations, 2011 was a disappointing year. Progress towards nationally harmonized work health and safety laws commencing on 1 January 2012 was effectively scuttled by failures to introduce the model legislation in Victoria and WA, and parliamentary delay in SA and Tasmania. While a set of harmonized laws, codes and regulations commenced operation in the rest of Australia on 1 January 2012, the laws contain some regional variations. With respect to discrimination laws, the proposed 2012 consolidation of federal legislation will simplify this complex area of law, but will not remove the existence of confusing overlaps and differentiation between state and federal legislation.</p>
<p>However, 2011 also saw the introduction into the Federal Parliament of two promising federal Bills containing industry-level reforms to solve long-standing problems with respect to the use of contractor outworkers in the clothing, textile and footwear industry, and unsafe payment rates in the transport industry. While adopting distinct regulatory techniques suited to the different levels of vulnerability of workers in these industries, both Bills essentially seek to tackle the problems caused by the use of contractor workers to drive down pay and condition levels. If passed in 2012, both Bills will constitute major reforms within these industries.</p>
<p>This review reveals that while there have been very few actual legislative developments passed through the Federal Parliament in 2011, a heavy parliamentary legislative agenda already exists for 2012. In addition, the federal government has foreshadowed a range of further legislative changes. There will be a post-implementation review of the FW Act, focusing on whether there is ‘evidence’ establishing the need for amendments to the Act (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0022185612442283"><italic>Workplace Express</italic>, 2011c</xref>). The terms of reference for the review include an examination of the extent to which the FW Act is operating as intended in the objects of the Act, and areas where the evidence suggests that the operation of the Act could be improved. The review will not address issues arising under the modern award system, as FWA will undertake a separate review of modern awards in 2012. The Workplace Relations Ministers Council has commenced development of a long service leave standard for the FW Act National Employment Standards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0022185612442283">WRMC, 2011</xref>). It is also expected that legislation will be introduced to implement the ALP’s ‘Protecting Workers’ Entitlements’ electoral promise from the 2010 federal election, involving legislation to enshrine the protection of accrued employment entitlements in the event of the liquidation of a company (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0022185612442283">Gillard and ALP, 2010</xref>).</p></sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec16-0022185612442283"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec>
<notes><title>Notes</title>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1-0022185612442283"><label>1</label><p>There are three levels of offences under the Model Work Health and Safety Bill. Category one offences are the most serious, involving a breach of duty with a high level of risk of serious harm along with recklessness or gross negligence by the duty-holder. Category two offences apply where there is a high risk of serious harm without recklessness or gross negligence, and Category three offences involve a breach of duty under the legislation without the earlier aggravating factors.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn2-0022185612442283"><label>2</label><p>These changes were implemented by the Work Health and Safety Legislation Amendment Act 2011. The amendments clarify the relationship between the Mine Health and Safety Act 2004, the Coal Mine Health and Safety Act 2002 and the WHS Act, such that the protections under the WHS Act prevail in the event of inconsistencies.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn3-0022185612442283"><label>3</label><p>The history of reform in the Australian long-haul road transport sector is set out in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0022185612442283">Johnson (2012)</xref>.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn4-0022185612442283"><label>4</label><p>The Bill will cover all dealings between employee and contractor transport drivers: with constitutional corporations; with the Commonwealth; in the territories (or for the purposes of a territory); and in interstate trade and commerce.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn5-0022185612442283"><label>5</label><p>See, for example, <italic>Gallagher &amp; Ors v Pioneer Concrete (NSW) Pty Ltd</italic> (1993) 113 ALR 159, in which the collective arrangements of a group of truck owner-drivers were found to breach the anti-competitive conduct provisions of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) (now the Competition and Consumer Act 2010 (Cth)).</p></fn></fn-group></notes>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Attorney-General’s Department (2011) <italic>Consolidation of Commonwealth Anti-Discrimination Laws – Discussion Paper</italic>. Canberra: Commonwealth of Australia</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Australian Government</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Safe Rates, Safe Roads</source>, <publisher-loc>Canberra</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Commonwealth of Australia</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Australian Government</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Paid Parental Leave: Dad and Partner Pay</source>, <publisher-loc>Canberra</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Commonwealth of Australia</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Women, work and industrial relations in 2010</article-title>. <source>Journal of Industrial Relations</source> <volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Bennett A (2011) NSW police warn of strike over compo. <italic>The Sydney Morning Herald</italic>, 22 November</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Ellis K (2011) Minister announces the way forward for women in the workplace. Press release, Commonwealth of Australia, 9 March</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Gillard J and ALP (Australian Labor Party) (2010) <italic>Protecting Workers’ Entitlements Package</italic>. Canberra: ALP</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Developing legislative protection for owner drivers in Australia: The long road to regulatory best practice</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Fudge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McCrystal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sankaran</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source>Challenging the Legal Boundaries of Work Regulation</source>, <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hart Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Parental Leave: A User Friendly Guide</source>, <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Thomson Reuters</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>McCrystal S (2007) Collective bargaining by independent contractors: Challenges from labour law. <italic>Australian Journal of Labour Law</italic> 20: 1</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>McCrystal S (2009) Is there a ‘public benefit’ in improving working conditions for independent contractors? Collective bargaining and the <italic>Trade Practices Act 1974</italic> (Cth). <italic>Federal Law Review</italic> 37: 264</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCrystal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Industrial legislation in 2010</article-title>. <source>Journal of Industrial Relations</source> <volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>288</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>National Transport Commission (NTC)</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Safe Payments: Addressing the Underlying Causes of Unsafe Practices in the Road Transport Industry</source>, <publisher-loc>Melbourne</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NTC</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>New South Wales (NSW) Parliament (2011) <italic>Parliamentary Debates</italic>. Sydney: Government Printer</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Report of Inquiry into Safety in the Long Haul Trucking Industry</source>, <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Motor Accidents Authority of New South Wales</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rich-Phillips</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Press Release: Victoria Calls for Delay to National Occupational Health and Safety Harmonisation</source>, <publisher-loc>Victoria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Victoria State Government</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Thomson Reuters (2011) Discrimination alert. Issue 385, 20 October. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.thomsonreuters.com.au">www.thomsonreuters.com.au</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Work Safe Western Australia (WA) (2011) Statement from the Worksafe Western Australian Commissioner. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.commerce.wa.gov.au/worksafe/Content/About_Us/Legislation/National_model_act_FAQs.html">www.commerce.wa.gov.au/worksafe/Content/About_Us/Legislation/National_model_act_FAQs.html</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="other"><comment><italic>Workplace Express</italic> (2011a) NSW’s harmonisation backflip a ‘sticking point’ only. 25 February. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.workplaceexpress.com.au">www.workplaceexpress.com.au</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="other"><comment><italic>Workplace Express</italic> (2011b) Union continues public sector wage cap legislation fight in High Court. 30 November. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.workplaceexpress.com.au">www.workplaceexpress.com.au</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="other"><comment><italic>Workplace Express</italic> (2011c) DEEWR won’t conduct review, says Evans. 22 September. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.workplaceexpress.com.au">www.workplaceexpress.com.au</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0022185612442283"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Workplace Relations Ministers Council (WRMC) (2011) Communiqué 85. 10 August</comment>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>