<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EHQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spehq</journal-id>
<journal-title>European History Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0265-6914</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7110</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0265691411428783o</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0265691411428783o</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A. R. Disney, <italic>A History of Portugal and the Portuguese Empire: From Beginnings to 1807</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>Cátia</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0265691411428783o">Leiden University</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>140</fpage>
<lpage>141</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0265691411428783o"><title>A. R. Disney, <italic>A History of Portugal and the Portuguese Empire: From Beginnings to 1807</italic>, 2 volume set, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009; 416 pp., 8 maps (Volume 1); 480 pp., 19 maps (Volume 2); 9780521762328, £90.00 (hbk); 9780521746120, £31.99 (pbk)</title>
<p>Anthony Disney’s new work proposes to join a narrative about the history of Portugal with the Portuguese expansion overseas, within a chronological span from the Iron Age up to 1807, the year in which the Portuguese court moved to the colony of Brazil to avoid the Napoleonic invasions in Europe. This all-encompassing work has been divided into two volumes of comparable size, the first dedicated to the History of Portugal, the second to the History of the Portuguese Empire.</p>
<p>In the first volume of this impressive work, Disney presents the reader with 14 chapters on the history of continental Portugal. The common feature in all of these chapters is the author’s preference for developments provoked by political events or political figures of relevance, as was the case of specific kings or queens and their closest advisers. In his mostly political narrative, the author raises issues of an economic nature but only to the extent that they served, or were the consequence of, political action. That is certainly the case in the chapters where he writes about the <italic>Reconquista</italic> or the movement of expansion overseas. Few references are made to subjects of a social or cultural nature.</p>
<p>In the second volume, Disney focuses his attention on the Portuguese Empire, using 12 chapters to link geographical expansion with the formation of specific colonies, and these two issues with developments happening in the court in Lisbon, some of them already described in volume one. As in the first part of his work, in the second volume Disney pays special attention to political developments and their economic consequences for the Portuguese Empire by stressing the link between political decision-making processes, diplomacy and specific economic developments. Society, culture or mentalities get short shrift, apart from the Jesuit contribution to the construction of a colony in Brazil, which is mostly presented as a political and economic event.</p>
<p>Following in the footsteps of the histories of Portugal and its empire by Boxer, Bethencourt and Curto, Livermore, Newitt, Oliveira Marques, Payne and Russell-Wood, Disney’s two-volume narrative offers an excellent survey of the history of Portugal and its empire, based on extensive primary and secondary research and many years of academic dedication. However, three limitations need to be mentioned.</p>
<p>First, Disney has made a clear choice to build his narrative around political and diplomatic events with some mentions of economic developments. This choice means that his knowledgeable work largely overlooks the considerable scholarship on social issues, cultural developments and mentalities, most of it available in English in the form of articles in specialized journals. This preference does not affect the intrinsic quality of Disney’s volumes, but it does reduce their value as an overview of the current state of the literature on Portuguese history.</p>
<p>Second, Disney’s attempt to build a narrative that appeals to students and specialists as well as a broader public, clearly determined his choice to organize the volumes as chronologically as possible, rather than thematically. This makes his narrative accessible and easy to read. On the down side, we would have to mention the limited contribution of this work to the historical debate, since most of the important historical disputes covered by the author have been confined to succinct footnotes (see the example about the author’s evaluation of the 1383–85 ‘revolution’).</p>
<p>Last, but certainly not least, the mostly chronological approach to the issue of Portuguese empire-building makes it difficult to discern the dynamics of this process. This is a weakness in Disney’s approach, certainly at a time when most literature on European overseas expansion tends to link these events to highly dynamic historical processes, such as the ‘birth’ of globalization or the ‘rise of the West’. By avoiding engagement with these debates, Disney leaves it to a future generation of researchers to take part in them. All in all, this two-volume work offers a significant contribution to the study of the history of Portugal and its empire. It is to be recommended for undergraduates, graduates and the general public interested in Portuguese history.</p>
<p><bold>Cátia Antunes</bold>, <italic>Leiden University</italic></p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>