<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcrs</journal-id>
<journal-title>Critical Sociology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0896-9205</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1569-1632</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0896920511419905</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0896920511419905</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Symposium: Critical Analyses from Latin America</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The United States and Latin America: Beyond Free Trade</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Figueredo</surname><given-names>Darío Salinas</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0896920511419905">Universidad Iberoamericana, Mexico</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0896920511419905">Darío Salinas Figueredo, Universidad Iberoamericana, Prolongación Paseo de la Reforma 880, Lomas de Santa Fe, 01219, Mexico City, Mexico Email: <email>dario.salinas@uia.mx</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>38</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>195</fpage>
<lpage>204</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Trade policies have long been configured into the history of Latin America. In virtually all such policies, US interests can be readily discerned. Recent experiences in a neoliberal context have witnessed a rearrangement of interests, forces, and scenarios at the global level. The weakening of the role of the state in allocating resources and in defining national agendas has been notable. Wherever proposals for democratization have appeared and have sought to distance themselves from hegemonic policies, the issues of free trade and commerce begin to reveal important aspects of interrelationship between development, regional integration, cooperation, and security.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>domination</kwd>
<kwd>free trade agreements</kwd>
<kwd>globalization</kwd>
<kwd>hegemony</kwd>
<kwd>Latin America</kwd>
<kwd>security</kwd>
<kwd>sociology</kwd>
<kwd>US policy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0896920511419905" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Regional integration processes in Latin America have historically been diverse in their implications, reach, and ultimate ends. This notwithstanding, all of them have displayed noticeable deficits regarding those factors most beneficial for development. There have been various policies in the sphere of commerce that have been configured into our regional history and in virtually all of them, US national interests can be readily identified. The most recent experiences have been implemented in a neoliberal context, characterized by the preeminent role of the market in defining priorities along with a lesser role of the state in allocating resources, all of which has resulted in the reduction of state influence in defining national economic agendas.</p>
<p>The new generation of regional trade agreements has been inspired, as a general rule, by a liberal criterion for international trade. It is assumed that each economy should specialize in the production of goods in which it has ‘comparative advantages’ and should therefore import those goods for which it does not. While the political-economic interconnections of all this inspire views from differing perspectives, there is broad recognition of the phenomenon of increasing globalization, economic liberalization processes, and a trend towards financial as well as trade deregulation.</p>
<p>Amidst the vast asymmetries of the global North–South relationship, the economies of developed capitalism may be characterized to a large extent by their struggles to guarantee spheres of regional influence over the underdeveloped economies. It therefore comes as little surprise that the United States fosters policies directed toward the rest of the hemisphere with this agenda in mind. This can especially be seen in two main policy priorities. On the one hand, there is a push for free trade agreements in their bilateral or sub-regional variations. On the other hand, the Free Trade Area of the Americas (FTAA) whose general logic was rooted in the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) emerged as a foundation for the strategic design of a North–South negotiation model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0896920511419905">Estay and Sanchez, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>In order to reflect on this, it would not be sufficient to build an analysis merely upon the specific results and concrete impacts derived from integration proposals. Rather than limiting our focus to the empirical details of these policies, we will instead be primarily concerned with identifying the fundamental premises that drive these ongoing projects, in order to reflect upon their larger significance. I particularly wish to explore the reasons why multidirectional movements in development and integration have occurred and continue to unfold. In doing so, I wish to identify the underlying political-economic realities which strongly impact the political field of proposals.</p>
<p>There is evidently an ongoing regional debate surrounding the formulation of criteria and the development of policies in the face of these unfolding dynamics. In the crisis-ridden context of the prevailing model, it can be seen that a complex process of reconceptualization of trade, development, and integration is now beginning to take place. One of the central axes of this process points to the need to recover the regulatory capacity of the state. This requires substantial reflection on what sort of state is necessary to accomplish this, while at the same time ensuring an overall strategic view of development and self-determination over the use of national resources.</p>
<p>Any focus on current Latin American political processes from a regional perspective has to consider the political notion of integration. On the one hand, it crystallizes better than any other concept memories of development and regional efforts to achieve political relations based upon cooperation and unity. On the other hand, the current regional order based in the hegemonic criteria of the ‘Washington Consensus’ calls on the region to narrowly pursue its ‘competitive advantages’. These advantages are presented as providing the most ‘realistic’ path for attaining development. Our analysis of the potential challenges that this neoliberal formula presents is based upon a critique of the commodification of social relations, both domestic and those proper to the international sphere in the context of increasing globalization.</p>
<p>The political and financial visions of hegemonic integration are blatantly opposed to principles of cooperation and economic and trade complementarity, as well as to the geographic and geopolitical considerations that seek to encourage regional development for maximum social development of our peoples. Instead, such strategies accentuate the ambiguities in the analysis of integration processes because of the need to contain conflicting political visions. It is essential to underscore that the assumptions, criteria, actions, and institutional instruments for regional integration are all ultimately political decisions.</p>
<p>While the specific political atmosphere in Latin America varies from country to country, it is relatively easy to see that the current regional scenario has produced a new trend towards links with more developed countries, especially the United States. There has been a discernable shift in political discourse under the eclipse of neoliberal modernization and this can be found throughout the region’s domestic and foreign policies. In some cases, signals of depletion can be clearly observed in the faltering capacity to gather consensus and this is particularly evident in the electoral arenas. Not too long ago, it was easier to obtain this kind of compliance. Examples include the experiences of Fernando Henrique Cardoso in Brazil, Abdalá Bucarám in Ecuador, Alberto Fujimori in Peru, Gonzalo Sánchez de Losada in Bolivia, and Carlos S. Menem in Argentina. These cases suffice to remind us how the social consent previously won from voters in search of the promises of ‘neoliberal modernization’ and ‘trade liberalization’ is now far less likely. Indeed, it is more accurate to say that proposed government policies now generally seek to distance themselves from these previous political practices. The newly emerging political processes in the region now seek to reorient integration and development policies, something that inevitably increases tensions with Washington.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0896920511419905">
<title>Global Power, Domination and ‘Free Trade’</title>
<p>If we look back in recent history, the end of the Cold War produced an important rearrangement of forces on the international level. With a more endogenous reading of the challenges prevailing for its own development and security, US policy was generally geared towards visibly affirming its hegemony in the world system, thus generating the appearance of a unipolar superpower. Despite its immense power wielded in major invasions of Afghanistan and Iraq, it has paradoxically not been able to win a single war.</p>
<p>Enhancing this process of concentration of military force was the US policy aimed at broadening the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO). After the Warsaw Pact disappeared with the demise of socialism in Eastern Europe, NATO was ostensibly left without the enemies that brought it to life. It thus found itself deprived of a purpose. Given the overwhelming strength of the triumphant capitalist system, the formulation of a new role for the military alliance came into focus. Russia, as the newest member of the so-called G8, coincided with the European and American consensus as they set about to destroy the former Yugoslavia. Under these new circumstances, the alliance refocused its defense of Western interests against threats both old and emergent to the system as a whole. This dense itinerary of strategic rearmament required absolutely no political need for legitimation or even discussion. Instead, it was a trail of deeds that in the absence of geopolitical counterweight amounted to the post-Cold War victor’s ‘right’.</p>
<p>This entire array of phenomena corresponded to a rapid transition from the prior bipolar reality to the current scenario that is wholly subordinate to US hegemony. It was precisely in this context that the United States intervention in the independence war of Kosovo became felt, as well as in the move to incorporate the Ukraine and Georgia into NATO, and later to deploy anti-missile armaments in Poland. The process became ever more evident after the 9/11 attacks through the invocation of national security in the face of terrorist threats worldwide (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0896920511419905">Chossudovsky, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>If we look at this from a purely economic perspective, however, the same system becomes projected somewhat differently as a conflictual and multipolar one composed of several economic and political centers. In this sense, the old bipolar order gave way to the creation of zones of economic, financial, commercial, and geopolitical influence by the capitalist powers. The need for consolidating these spheres in order to enhance the global power of each economic pole emerged as the new dynamic.</p>
<p>These facets signified a more complex process of redesign inside the new model of domination. At first glance it may seem to present little problem for Latin America, since apart from Cuba most of the region was not considered to be a US adversary. Indeed, the fall of the Berlin Wall initially seemed to usher in a newfound sense that Latin America was no longer a priority area for US foreign policy. For some authors, however, the state of the US economy at the end of the Cold War, together with the necessity of being more competitive in the global system, now compelled Washington to further expand its markets and to improve the efficiency of certain industries, especially in the manufacturing sector (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0896920511419905">Smith, 1997</xref>). These figured among the factors that led the United States to relaunch the pursuit of ‘free trade’ in the region with the ultimate aim of consolidating its hold over a free trade area throughout the entire Western hemisphere.</p>
<p>This soon proved to be the major regional issue. The Free Trade Area of the Americas (FTAA) attempted to build off the Canada–United States Free Trade Agreement of 1988 that later had provided the political conditions to pull Mexico into the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) in 1992. That treaty was destined to come into effect just two years later and became considered a pioneering treaty given its grouping of economies of vastly different sizes into a single commercial bloc. This provided the laboratory for ultimately seeking the incorporation of economies of all different sizes and diverse degrees of development into a tighter commercial orbit.</p>
<p>Throughout Latin America, there has not been a single forum where the prevailing rhetoric has not proclaimed the potential benefits for our economies, provided that the institutional conditions necessary to turn the region into a complete Free Trade Area are created. This conception began with the ‘Initiative for the Americas’ announced on 27 June 1990 by President Bush, Sr. It was during the Clinton Administration in 1994 at the Summit of the Americas in Miami that the initiative fully emerged as a ‘Free Trade Agreement for the Americas’, a consolidation of the policy emphasis first set forth in 1989 under the rubric of the ‘Washington Consensus’. Since that time, the push for free trade policies has become increasingly commonplace as a guiding rule in the articulation of economic, commercial, and financial reforms throughout the region.</p>
<p>After the crisis of the ‘lost decade of development’, as it was dubbed by the Economic Commission for Latin America and the Caribbean (ECLAC), Latin American governments of the 1990s devoted themselves to synchronizing with the new global reality through the pursuit of a broad liberalization of markets, privatization, and more open, integrated economies. This wave abandoned concern for internal markets that had been at the leading edge of development policy during the prior four decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0896920511419905">CEPAL, 1994</xref>). The overriding emphasis during this period was on a systemic readjustment of capitalism to coincide with the strengthening of the market, the commodification of public institutions, an emphasis on financial investment over productive investment, an intentional erosion of the regulatory capacity of the state, and a virtually total emphasis on the export-led sectors of the economy.</p>
<p>The first to occur in terms of political decision-making was the unilateral implementation of economic liberalization in accordance with a whole list of agreements geared towards ‘economic complementarity’ so as to encourage increased capital flows. This was all regarded as a step towards the new ways of development and it did in fact consolidate an entirely new segmentation of the region in economic and commercial terms.</p>
<p>In the analytical estimation of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0896920511419905">McClerry (1997</xref>: 118), the project of hemispheric liberalization was formulated to combat ‘fears’ on the part of Latin America’s political elites about the possibility of being excluded from the new era of development. These elites are none other than the new dominant classes that became reconstituted under the influx of financial capital, who fed the ideology of the market and showed misgivings about the re-orientation of post-Cold War capital investments, which either fictitiously or actually were now flowing mostly to the former Eastern socialist countries rather than to Latin America. After all, such a powerful new vision founded on free market principles, spreading as an ideology virtually without any counterweight, was totally congruent with the new ‘political class’ now at the helm of the former socialist countries. The development expectations of the former members of the Council for Mutual Economic Assistance (CMEA) had by now radically changed. Nevertheless, US interest in determining a liberalization policy for Latin America and the Caribbean now had as a backdrop other more specific political issues such as drug trafficking, undocumented migration, payment of foreign debt, greater political stability by means of supporting the installation of liberal democracies, and above all the general interest in ratifying that the region formed part of its sphere of influence and domination.</p>
<p>To think of a free trade area that comprised all of the Americas would require, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0896920511419905">McClerry’s (1997</xref>: 136) reasoning, a careful mix of incentives and sanctions according to the well-known practice of combining the ‘good neighbor’ policy with threats of using the ‘big stick’. This time, it was all about fostering a preconfigured schema to promote trade negotiations. On the one hand, the incentive included the strengthening of trade liberalization and economic reforms already started by international financial agencies since the 1980s so as to promote payment of the region’s debt. A key ‘carrot’ part of the offer was that fulfillment of these conditions would at some point lead to increased access to the US market. The punitive portion of the package amounted to a twofold threat. On the one hand, reluctant Latin American countries that were reticent to conform ran the risk of remaining excluded from hypothetical future agreements. On the other hand, a clear signal was being sent toward the economic powers of Europe and Asia; namely, that if multilateralism failed, a shift to bilateral measures would be forthcoming.</p>
<p>The ensuing political card game designed to advance US interests involved opening up a second front, consisting of bilateral negotiations with countries or sub-regions in the Americas. This was borne out by the various FTAs signed after NAFTA, first including Chile, and subsequently, Central America, Peru, Panama and Colombia, with the latter still pending approval and ratification by the US Congress at the time this article was written.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0896920511419905">
<title>Indicators and Referents</title>
<p>Any initial glance at the data on US commercial activities with Latin America quickly reveals that Latin American economies represent a percentage of total US trade that is much less than the percentage other regions represent. According to World Trade Organization figures, the trade flow of commodities from the United States to Latin America in 2006 amounted to nearly US$88.4 billion or about 8.5% of the total exports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0896920511419905">WTO, 2007</xref>). For its part, the United States imported from Latin America (excluding Mexico and the Caribbean) US$140.6 billion that same year, which represents 7.3% of the total.</p>
<p>US trade data indicate that the region of Latin America is fourth in importance for both imports and exports. In addition, what needs to be emphasized is the considerable gap that exists between the third and fourth places in this regard. The sub-region of greatest importance is the greater North American region which in 2006 accounted for around US$635.4 billion or about 37% of its exports. That was followed by Asia at around US$280.2 billion or about 27.6% and the European market at US$238.9 billion or 23.6% of the total. According to WTO data, Asia was the region from where the largest number of imported goods originated for 2006 which totaled US$716.4 billion or 37.3%, followed by North America at US$508.4 billion or 26.5% (OMC, 2007). Europe then follows with US$370.2 billion or 19.3%, leaving Latin America at only US$140.6 billion or 7.3%. Comparing this 2006 data with 2000, imports went from 6.2% to 7.3% and exports from 7.5% to 8.5%, respectively. This indicates that Latin America essentially retained the same relative position of importance for US trade.</p>
<p>The previous argument is further reinforced if we look at the data across a longer stretch of time, namely from 1996–2006. Here, we see that the percentage increase of total commodities of the United States exchanged with Latin America barely grew from 15.4% to 17.8% in imports and from 17.4% to 21.4% in exports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0896920511419905">United Nations, 2008</xref>). This leads us to conclude that the concerted economic diplomacy being pursued in favor of free trade did not have a corresponding impact on the trade figures.</p>
<p>Other data, however, show a quite different tendency within the intra-NAFTA arena, where there has been a considerable increase of commercial flow. According to data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0896920511419905">UNCTAD (2007)</xref>, exports in 1990 reached US$226 billion, while a decade later the transactions had grown to US$676.142 billion, which represented an increase of 209%. By 2005, the figure had risen to US$824.5 billion. All of this is generally considered positive in the prevailing discourse.</p>
<p>If, however, the ultimate aim of free trade agreements is to convert trade into a lever for driving development, some results suggest a different panorama. In this regard, it could be pointed out that for 1990 (four years before NAFTA came into operation), Mexican exports to the US already represented 69.3% of the total. By 2006, this grew to an estimated 84.7% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0896920511419905">Secretaría de Economía, 2008</xref>). In a free trade agreement between economically unequal partners, the result has been an increase of dependency for Mexico.</p>
<p>Other aspects in this same line of reasoning relate to the expansion of exports and the possible effects on absorption of the labor force, the magnitude of productive investments, the link between exports and growth, the issue of salary levels, and the impact on distribution patterns and poverty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0896920511419905">Puyana, 2003</xref>). It seems as though with the implementation of this overall model, the asymmetries have basically deepened, so much so that World Bank and IMF data have demonstrated that Latin America is the global region with the highest level of social inequality. In the face of this analysis, those who previously worked to systematically reduce the state’s role in economic affairs now figure among those who clamor for state intervention.</p>
<p>Beginning with the 1982 debt crisis, and then in a more organic and generalized manner after 1989 when the criteria of economic liberalism strategically came to guide policy making, our countries entered headlong into deregulation and dismantlement of state presence in commercial and financial activities, as well as in manufacturing and industry. Once put into practice, this idea prevailed under the notion that state interventionism hindered the market’s ability to optimally allocate resources for overall development. It was commonly assumed that the very expansion of growth would produce trickle-down effects throughout the whole of society. Nevertheless, it is worth bearing in mind that the growth has been rather erratic, considering the ideological projection of the model and given that the distributive impact was never considered to be among its great virtues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0896920511419905">Salinas and Tetelboin, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>We should remember that no Latin American society after the ‘lost decade’ has been exempt from the impact that the increased inequality has signified. Ongoing reproduction of its conditions of production has led to increasing concentration of wealth. This is a point which must be underscored in terms of qualifying the development model that was being imposed by the capitalist system throughout this period and whose core characteristic is its incapacity to acceptably distribute income and power (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0896920511419905">Ffrench-Davis, 2005</xref>). If the prevailing policies in our countries have been devoted to promote, implement, and reproduce the capitalist experience in its neoliberal configuration, the results now point us to reconsider the role of political power beyond that of restoring the regulatory role of the state. Our inquiry is indispensable for paving the way to any project that seeks to advance an alternative to the hegemonic model of development and integration.</p>
<p>We should not neglect to mention that those Latin American countries that report a higher percentage of trade with the United States are not at all the ones that signed free trade agreements. I refer here to the cases of Brazil and Venezuela. Exports from the US to these countries represented 1.9% and 0.9% respectively in 2006. The corresponding imports into the US for the same period were 2.0% and 1.5% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0896920511419905">UNCTAD, 2007</xref>). It is particularly noteworthy since the governments of both these countries during this period were relatively critical of the Washington Consensus. Brazil and Venezuela have also been important actors in fostering various regional integration proposals such as the Bolivarian Alternative for the Americas (ALBA), Union of South American Nations (UNASUR), and Bank of the South. They also have favored the South American Council of Defense. These projects, together with others such as Petrocaribe and Telesur represent critical political positions in defiance of US hegemony.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0896920511419905">
<title>The Political Background</title>
<p>A central question arises from the foregoing analysis, namely, why has the US so vigorously pursued its free trade policies if the total commercial flows are so relatively insignificant? It is becoming ever clearer that whoever has economic hegemony and the available technological knowhow to develop the core driving principles that coincide with their interests are positioned by this supremacy to make them universal. The key issue in this context is political will and the capacity to protect a country’s internal market.</p>
<p>Hence, the main thrust of policies emanating from the more developed countries, especially the United States, is to orient the relations with our economies. They enlist the active participation of regional mass media to promote the slogan ‘export or die’. Most Latin American leaders have assimilated the mantra as if it were an absolute truth. At the same time, the developed countries themselves practice protectionist policies or maintain subsidy programs on those commodities that are precisely those goods being produced in Latin America.</p>
<p>As a parallel component of this endogenous policy, they have insisted on labor reforms under the supposed need for flexibility that needs to go hand in hand with increasing competitiveness. Given the prevailing lack of technology in the Latin American reality, challenges in competitiveness have been dealt with by increases in the rate of pauperization and further cheapening of the available labor force. Beyond the adverse impact this has on poverty rates and on reproducing the regressive pattern of distribution is the growing tendency of forcing most newly created jobs into the informal sector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0896920511419905">Secretariado de la Comisión para la Cooperación Laboral en América del Norte, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>It is here where foreign investment appears in the prevailing discourse as the key to development. This remains, of course, an empty statement since the capital sources neither abound nor arrive as boasted. When they do enter, it is precisely on account of the cheapening of the labor force, together with the need for cheap natural resources.</p>
<p>In the post-Cold War era, the most industrialized countries accorded greater importance than in the past to the need to access natural resources. This priority can be seen in US policy towards the region and is understood as one of the fundamental geostrategic elements for their security. To the extent plausible, their intention is to secure the free flow of trade and investments into activities linked to these strategic natural resources, notably including access to oil and minerals exploration, as well as the provision for exploring potential biodiversity resources. These moves, inscribed in the framework of relations that exist between unequal economies, are not secondary but rather central aims in the configuration of the US strategy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0896920511419905">De la Reza, 2006</xref>). This further explains why the US views with suspicion all alternative programs aiming to create trading blocs or initiatives for the diversification of trade agreements.</p>
<p>In this sense, trade agreements must not necessarily be read as an end unto themselves, but rather as components of a more general hegemonic strategy. In practical terms, the objectives we have noted revolve around the imperative of avoiding all kinds of restrictions to access and to secure the participation of transnational capital in every facet of the process, including the exploration and prior knowledge of all prospectively available resources. From there, the aim is to have governments give national treatment to US suppliers for purchases performed by state enterprises; for instance, the oil companies, as well as the entire sphere of natural resources such as hydrocarbon sources, gas, copper, nickel, silver or water reservoirs, etc. This has been particularly telling in countries such as Venezuela, Colombia, Ecuador, and Mexico who supply energy resources to the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0896920511419905">Council on Foreign Relations, 2008</xref>). If Latin American governments project low-profile policies regarding self-determination and sovereignty over their resources, the scenarios of confrontation with the US policy tend to blur and, correlatively, the bonds of dependency tend to increase and tighten.</p>
<p>One of the elements that have fueled supportive tendencies for ‘free trade’ agreements is the clamor for hemispheric security that formed part of the US response to the 9/11 attacks. In effect, the conceptions of security and economic trade policy have constituted a geostrategic unity with inseparable components. This provided the integral basis for viewing the expansion of world trade as part of US national security. In this sense, there is effectively a hegemonic projection in place that identifies the unfolding of the entire world’s future with specific criteria that conform to the political economy of the world’s main superpower.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0896920511419905" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion: Does Latin America Matter?</title>
<p>It is frequently heard in the mass media and official circles alike that Latin America no longer figures prominently among US priorities. This notion gains even greater notoriety when little reference is made to the region during high-profile electoral campaigns. In reality, however, the notion is only half true. Beyond the analysis of electoral sociology that tends to stay fixated on the present, there are more long term aspects that require consideration at the level of political economy. It is important to bear in mind that all of the fundamental decisions of US policy sooner or later have an important impact on the region, though not necessarily in a positive way.</p>
<p>I suggest that there are at least three basic referents that are difficult to ignore. There is the debacle of a model in financial crisis, perhaps initially and symbolically linked to the fall of Lehman Brothers; there is the depth to which the US foreign policy has been publicly discredited following the Bush administrations; and there is a political shift to a Democratic Party administration headed by President Barack Obama. In this context, we cannot overlook the global scenario of capitalism nor can we discard the possibility of an emergent alternative even more non-inclusive than the one known as the Washington Consensus. This will only happen if the most advanced social sectors fail to rise to the occasion in articulating national policies with renewed state presence that can constitute an alternative.</p>
<p>As for the financial crisis, we likely do not yet have all of the elements on the table to fully evaluate its impact. At the very least, we know that the current crisis is more than just financial in nature. Given the historic relations of dependency, those economies whose trade is most closely tied to the US market will surely suffer the most negative consequences. This scenario is especially probable if we consider those most deregulated countries which tend to export primary commodities under trade agreements and treaties signed with Washington. Conversely, those economies more committed to alternative integration processes such those engaged in the ALBA project will undoubtedly experience complications. But they will exhibit a greater potential to establish their own development criteria and more autonomous cooperation policies.</p>
<p>The results of the 2008 US elections provided a new reference point after the unfortunate years of Republican Party reign under the Bush, Jr administration. The collapse of Bush’s policies created a need to change Washington’s own image. Obama’s triumph implied the possibility of a less tense environment for political discussion of the problems and differences prevailing in the Western hemisphere. Many analysts certainly anticipated a toning down of the most aggressive aspects of US policy toward the region.</p>
<p>Placing electoral sociology aside, however, it does not seem reasonable to think that a change of US administrations can lead to deep transformations. Had Obama not anticipated the strategic continuities according to the central characteristics that define the American political and electoral system, he would not have gained the nomination of his party. We had no illusion in this regard, as it was clear that the fundamental elements of his campaign were not defined in opposition to the constitutive interests of the power structure. His distancing from the Republicans and specifically from his immediate opponent was not tantamount to climbing into a trench to oppose the US ruling class and its global interests. The burden of the American political and electoral system continuity under president Obama’s administration is heavier than any possibility of an important shift (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0896920511419905">The White House, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>From a Latin American perspective, there is no evidence that the Obama administration intends to fully lift the blockade on Cuba, nor have we noticed any substantive elements that might indicate a possible modification of the prevailing conceptions on security and immigration. There is no sense of retreating from the preemptive war on terrorism or rolling back the interventionist policy known as Plan Colombia. Nor can we anticipate his withdrawing the Fourth Fleet from Latin America’s waters, closing military bases on Latin American soil, or even reconsidering the fundamental parameters for pursuing free trade agreements or free market policies in general. There are no signs of changed behavior with respect to actions taken by the previous administration to destabilize the political processes of Bolivia, Ecuador, and Venezuela. The behavior of Washington following the coup in Honduras against a legitimately elected government has been perhaps the most emblematic expression of the modus operandi of a Democratic administration. The Honduran crisis revealed the underlying US policy to retain a strategic line of continuity, despite the fact that the Latin American community totally rejected the coup. Although Washington did not immediately recognize the regime that overthrew the constitutional president, the visible behavior of the US with respect to the coup made it clear that the Obama administration had brought about no paradigm shift in foreign policy towards the region.</p>
<p>All of these referents suggest that new forms of regional integration can plausibly be expected to gain currency and the promising signs include the prospects for electing additional progressive governments. If this continues, it is likely to favor more endogenous proposals for deepening democratization and regional cooperation. But at the same time, very complex challenges remain in place (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0896920511419905">Bell Lara and Della Buono, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>No one doubts the difference that can be easily perceived between the previous Republican administration and the current projections of its Democratic successor. Perhaps the most coherent interpretation consists in attempting a reading of this change in terms of the search for a ‘new strategy’ that might recompose an eroded US hegemony. To the extent that Latin America remains aloof to the influences exerted by US policy, we can imagine the scenario where the situation will amount to a problem for American control and consequently a threat to the progressive governments of the region.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>This article summarizes the author’s lectures and discussions in the Working Group on the United States in the Latin American Council of Social Sciences, CLACSO. The analysis is a byproduct of research on governability and political institutions in Latin America conducted at the Universidad Iberoamericana, UIA. The author thanks Adán Baltazar Garcia Fajardo for his collaboration in the revision and updating of this article published in English.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bell Lara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dello Buono</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2007</year>) <source>Neoliberalismo y luchas sociales en América Latina</source>. <publisher-loc>Bogotá</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ediciones Ántropos</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>CEPAL</collab> (<year>1994</year>) <source>El Regionalismo abierto en América Latina y el Caribe. La integración económica al servicio de la transformación productiva con equidad</source>. <publisher-loc>Santiago de Chile</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Naciones Unidas</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chossudovsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Guerra y Globalización</source>. <publisher-loc>Mexico</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Siglo XXI Editores</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Council on Foreign Relations</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <source>U.S.–Latin America Relations: A New Direction for a New Reality</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Council on Foreign Relations</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De la Reza</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>La integración económica entre países dispares. Un caso de sistema complejo</article-title>. <source>Perfiles Latinoamericanos</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Estay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Una revisión general del ALCA y sus implicaciones</article-title>. <source>El ALCA y sus peligros para América Latina</source>. <publisher-loc>Buenos Aires</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Consejo Latinoamericano de Ciencias Sociales, CLACSO</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ffrench-Davis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Reformas para América Latina. Después del fundamentalismo neoliberal</source>. <publisher-loc>Argentina</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CEPAL-Siglo XXI Editores</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McClerry</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Promoción de la integración regional por parte de Estados Unidos: Intereses y percepciones</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Shoji</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>¿Cooperación o rivalidad? Integración regional en las Américas y la Cuenca del Pacífico</source>. <publisher-loc>Mexico</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CIDAC/Porrúa</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Puyana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Las relaciones de América Latina en el umbral del siglo XXI: Entre la globalización y la fuerza centrípeta de estados Unidos, pensando en ALCA</article-title>. <source>Perfiles Latinoamericanos</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tetelboin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Las condiciones de la política social en América Latina</article-title>. <source>Papeles de Población</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>44</issue>): <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Secretaría de Economía</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Exportaciones totales de México</source>. <comment>Subsecretaría de Negociaciones Comerciales Internacionales</comment>. <day>26</day> <month>May</month>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.economia.gob.mx">www.economia.gob.mx</ext-link></comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Secretariado de la Comisión para la Cooperación Laboral</collab>. (<year>2007</year>) <source>Mercados Laborales</source>, <edition>3rd edn.</edition> <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Secretariado de la Comisión para la Cooperación Laboral</publisher-name>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.naalc.org">www.naalc.org</ext-link></comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>¿Cooperación o rivalidad? Asuntos y temas</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Shoji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>¿Cooperación o rivalidad? Integración regional en las Américas y la Cuenca del Pacífico</source>. <publisher-loc>Mexico</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CIDAC/Porrúa</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>The White House</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>The National Security Strategy</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The White House</publisher-name>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/rss_viewer/national_security_strategy.pdf">http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/rss_viewer/national_security_strategy.pdf</ext-link></comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>UNCTAD</collab> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Handbook of Statistics 2006– 07</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>United Nations</publisher-name>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.unctad.org/en/docs/tdstat31_en.pdf">http://www.unctad.org/en/docs/tdstat31_en.pdf</ext-link></comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>United Nations</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <source>International Merchandise Trade Statistics</source>. <access-date>Retrieved 10 August 2011</access-date> (<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://comtrade.un.org/pb/CountryPages.aspx?y=2006">http://comtrade.un.org/pb/CountryPages.aspx?y=2006</ext-link></comment>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0896920511419905">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>WTO</collab> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Estadísticas de Comercio Internacional, 2007</source>. <comment>Organización mundial de Comercio. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wto.org">www.wto.org</ext-link></comment>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>