<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EEG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">speeg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical EEG and Neuroscience</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1550-0594</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1550059412451215</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1550059412451215</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Analysis of Frequency Domain of EEG Signals in Clinical Location of Epileptic Focus</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>Xiaoying</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1550059412451215">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>Li</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1550059412451215">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Weifeng</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1550059412451215">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>Yuhua</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1550059412451215">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1550059412451215"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Duanduan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1550059412451215">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Tianxin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1550059412451215">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>Yanjun</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1550059412451215">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1550059412451215">
<label>1</label>School of Life Science and Technology, Beijing Institute of Technology, Beijing, China</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1550059412451215">
<label>2</label>Biomechanics and Medical Information Institute, Beijing University of Technology, Beijing, China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1550059412451215">Yuhua Peng, School of Life Science and Technology, Beijing Institute of Technology, 100081 Beijing, China. Email: <email>pengyuhua@bit.edu.cn</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>44</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>25</fpage>
<lpage>30</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>7</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>11</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>7</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© EEG and Clinical Neuroscience Society (ECNS) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">EEG and Clinical Neuroscience Society</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>As a suddenly abnormal discharge of brain neurons, epilepsy can lead to encephalographic (EEG) abnormalities. Data of 3 epileptic patients recorded by depth intracranial electrodes are analyzed with time–frequency algorithms to observe the abnormal changes in different frequency ranges. Comparing the frequency domain of the normal and epileptic signals that contain several periods of clinical seizures and intervals, a remarkable range of high frequency is identified and corresponds to the seizure. According to the corresponding position of those channels that produced abnormal signals, the epileptic focus is determined theoretically and verified by comparison with the clinical diagnosis and surgical results. Furthermore, the order of the presence of different frequency ranges is listed. The finding proposed in this study could be a fresh method to improve the diagnosis of epilepsy.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>epilepsy</kwd>
<kwd>EEG</kwd>
<kwd>time–frequency analysis</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1550059412451215">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Epileptic seizure can be regarded as an abnormal and excessive neuronal discharge caused by ultra-synchronization of neuronal activity. Because of the variety of pathogenesis, the high incidence of disease, and the visible symptoms, epilepsy severely impacts the patients’ normal life activities and could be fatal. The diagnosis of epilepsy is one of the most important aspects in modern medicine.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1550059412451215">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>As reported, 80% of patients with epilepsy have EEG abnormalities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1550059412451215">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1550059412451215">2</xref></sup> For that reason, EEG is a crucial approach to evaluate epilepsy. Although the diagnosis of epilepsy depends on individual medical history, the EEG is an essential means of detection and diagnosis. Especially taking into account the difficulties of clinical diagnosis of atypical seizures, the function of EEG is more prominent and sometimes plays a decisive role.</p>
<p>The current diagnosis of epilepsy mainly relies on the video EEG. Medical doctors monitor the real-time EEG signal in time domain and the real-time surveillance video of patients. Since the focus is on the detection of the spike and sharp waves,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1550059412451215">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1550059412451215">4</xref></sup> this is an empirical method. However, the time-domain characteristics of EEG signal are not obvious and usually are accompanied by strong artifacts, including eye signals, myoelectricity and electrocardio signals. Additionally, epilepsy is paroxysmal and brief, with unpredictable initiation and termination of the signal. Therefore, it is difficult to capture the time-domain signal of the seizure in real-time monitoring or to guarantee high accuracy.</p>
<p>Due to the difficulty of monitoring time-domain signals, researchers have investigated the frequency domain of EEG signals of patients with epilepsy. In the past, the EEG signal was defined as low amplitude with a frequency below 50 Hz. However, most biological signals have such a frequency range, and the high-frequency characteristic of the EEG signal was neglected. With the rapid development of EEG technology, it has been discovered that EEG is more profound and more comprehensive. In 1992, Fisher and others found high-frequency (up to 150 Hz) signals when collecting seizure signals of new cortical areas of the brain, named ripple.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1550059412451215">5</xref></sup> More and more experiments show that by recording the broadband electrophysiological signals of patients with medial temporal lobe epilepsy and the epileptic rat model, pathological high-frequency oscillations with a distinct frequency higher than 80 Hz could be found. The frequency range of 80 to 200 Hz is defined as high-frequency ripple oscillations, while the frequency range of 200 to 600 Hz is regarded as high-frequency oscillations with pathological features and named as the fast ripples (FRs).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1550059412451215">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1550059412451215">7</xref></sup> Moreover, high-frequency oscillations are usually associated with other epileptic seizure events, such as interictal spikes and the attack of γ frequency oscillations which are traditionally related to the seizure. Therefore, high-frequency oscillations could be considered as a special marker<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1550059412451215">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1550059412451215">9</xref></sup> of the epileptic focus.</p>
<p>This high-frequency oscillation can be recorded by microelectrode (surface contact area 70 μm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1550059412451215">2</xref></sup>) or large electrode (surface contact area &gt;80 μm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1550059412451215">2</xref></sup>). High-frequency ripple oscillation is usually found in the normal rat’s cortex, hippocampus and nose, and also seen in epileptic patients’ epileptic foci and their neighboring hippocampi, while high-frequency oscillations of 250 to 500 Hz are usually found in normal rodent and human brain and are related to somatic sensory stimulation and information processing. Therefore, the change in characteristics of high-frequency oscillation is theoretically available to detect and localize the seizure.</p>
<p>This study analyzed the variation of frequency-domain characteristics of abnormal EEG signals collected from patients with epilepsy, using intracranial electrodes, and identified the functions of the high-frequency signal to determine the clinical epileptic focus. The whole range of frequency may be impacted by the abnormal epileptic signal. In this study, in order to eliminate low-frequency noise and power-line interference, the EEG signals were preprocessed by software “NicoletOne”, with a low cutting frequency of 0.7 Hz and a notching frequency of 50 Hz. Then, filtered signals were analysed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1550059412451215" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>Three epileptic patients’ EEGs were supplied by the People’s Hospital of Peking University, China. Those signals were extracted by depth intracranial electrodes (Fude Medical Electronics Device Company, Xi′an, China) and acquired by “<italic>NicoletOne</italic> Monitor” recording system (Nicolet Digital Medical Technology Company). The EEG signals were sampled at 1024 Hz. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1550059412451215">Figure 1</xref> shows the position of the intracranial electrodes. Six electrodes were located in the right prefrontal and 4 intracranial electrodes in the right temporal lobe, corresponding to channels 1 to 10. Analysis of those signals, from different channels, showed their location in the cerebral cortex shown. While blind to the previous diagnosis, we analyzed time–frequency using a custom-designed Matlab program.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1550059412451215" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The location of the intracranial electrodes.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1550059412451215-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Clinically, the epilepsy areas were roughly estimated by the EEG signals from the cortical electrodes. Then they were more accurately located using 10 intracranial electrodes and 2 cortical electrodes. Moreover, an ECG channel was positioned to record the sampling rate. Based on spikes in the time-domain signals and areas of interest in the magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), the epileptic focus was determined and surgically removed.</p>
<p>The EEG data we analyzed were extracted from the intracranial electrodes. In order to find in which channels the epileptic signals occurred, and which frequency range could be a special marker of epileptic signals, the frequency-domain characteristics were extracted. The theoretic epileptic focus is identified by the corresponding channels in which the epileptic signals take place earliest. The analysis results are compared with the results of surgery to judge the validity and clinical significance.</p>
<p>Time–frequency algorithms are used to observe the variation of frequency-domain characteristics. As verified in previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1550059412451215">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1550059412451215"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1550059412451215">7</xref></sup>, the power of EEG’s frequency-domain can be elevated by seizure. The onset and ending of the seizure can be determined roughly by observing the change in the frequency power.</p>
<p>The frequency signals of 12 channel EEGs are obtained through fast Fourier transform (FFT). The signals of the 10 channels of intracranial electrodes are the key information in this study. The elevation of the whole frequency domain during the seizure has been verified in earlier work.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1550059412451215">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1550059412451215">9</xref></sup> The sum of the absolute values of the frequency amplitudes S<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = <inline-formula id="inline-formula1-1550059412451215">
<mml:math id="mml-inline1-1550059412451215">
<mml:mi>∫</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ω</mml:mi>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>, where X(<inline-formula id="inline-formula2-1550059412451215">
<mml:math id="mml-inline2-1550059412451215">
<mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ω</mml:mi>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>) is the FFT of the EEG signal, is used to estimate the overall power of every channel. From the change in this value, the time range of seizures can be determined approximately. After the estimation of the time range, a sequence of signals which contains interval, initial seizure, and seizure period can be determined. This sequence is used to improve the accuracy of detection and analysis.</p>
<p>Usually, the periodogram is one of the most commonly used methods to estimate the spectrum. However, the estimated variance of this method is too large, especially for nonstationary EEG signals. In this study, a proper spectrum estimation algorithm is used to obtain the spectrum of the frequency signals.</p>
<p>The Welch spectrum estimation algorithm is an improved method. It uses subwindows to separate a N-length data <italic>X<sub>N</sub>
</italic>(<italic>n</italic>) into L segments, length of <italic>M</italic>, and allow overlaps between each segment. The power spectrum of each segment <italic>P<sub>i</sub>
</italic> (ω) was calculated, then the average of them <italic>P</italic>
<sub>aver</sub>(<italic>ω</italic>) was obtained by equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1550059412451215">1</xref>).</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1550059412451215">
<label>1</label>
<mml:math id="mml-disp1-1550059412451215">
<mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false" stretchy="false">∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:munderover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-1550059412451215" xlink:href="10.1177_1550059412451215-eq1.tif"/> 
</disp-formula>
Through this process, the variance of the power spectrum could be reduced to 1/<italic>L</italic> of the original. Therefore, because of the outstanding variance characteristics and the adjustable resolution, the Welch spectrum estimation algorithm is chosen to calculate the spectrum of the signal in each channel. A complete section of epileptic signal has been intercepted above. Signals are incised into 5 sequential parts containing the initial position of the seizure, and every part contains a 5-second period which corresponds 5120 signal points. This measurement can improve the results to be more observable and comparable. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1550059412451215">Figure 3</xref> illustrates the variation of the power value for every channel’s signal in a continuous series of time.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1550059412451215" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>The matrix of the energy distribution of 10 channels with time. The vertical axis represents channels from 1 to 10 and the horizontal axis represents time. The color represents the value of S<italic>
<sub>i</sub>
</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and is set as follows: deep red, S<italic>
<sub>i</sub>
</italic>(t) &gt;15; color scale, 13 ≤ S<italic>
<sub>i</sub>
</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) ≤15; and deep blue, S<sub>i</sub>(<italic>t</italic>)&lt; 13. (See online color publication).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1550059412451215-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-1550059412451215" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>The change of the energy of the spectrum during 2 typical seizures (A and B, respectively) from 1 patient. The vertical axis represents channels from 1 to 10 and the horizontal axis is frequency. Sp<italic>
<sub>i</sub>
</italic>(<italic>h</italic>) is calculated as the value of the power of h Hz using the Welch Spectrum Estimation in channel <italic>i</italic>. The logarithm of the value is used in order to make convenience of processing. The logarithmic value of Sp<italic>
<sub>i</sub>
</italic>(<italic>h</italic>) is between 30 and −30. Four images from top to bottom both in A and B are collected at different continuous time ranges during seizures. All values more than 0 are represented with deep red color while the values less than −20 are represented with deep blue (See online color publication). The color scale presents different values between 0 and −20.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1550059412451215-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1550059412451215">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Each patient had 6 seizures during the period of clinical monitoring. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1550059412451215">Figure 2</xref> indicates the variation of the absolute value in accordance with the time for each channel during one seizure. The figure is made up by a matrix in which each row represents a channel and the horizontal axis represents time. Each pixel represents the sum S<italic>
<sub>i</sub>
</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) of the absolute value of all frequency amplitudes of channel <italic>i</italic>th’s signal at time <italic>t</italic>. The value of S<italic>
<sub>i</sub>
</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) is between 10 and 18. When the value is more than 15, the color of the pixel is deep red, while it is deep blue when less than 13. (See online color publication). The color is set according to the color scale in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1550059412451215">Figure 2</xref> when the value is between 13 and 15. From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1550059412451215">Figure 2</xref>, the approximate time range of the seizure can be determined and facilitates the test section’s interception.</p>
<p>According to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1550059412451215">Figure 2</xref>, the period of a whole process of the epilepsy can be determined roughly and is between 20 and 55 seconds in 10 channels including the intermission, the onset, and the ending. As some artifact is inevitable, these frequency-domain signals cannot be used to determine the variation of the frequency characteristics.</p>
<p>All the abnormal signals during the seizure are processed by the proposed methods. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1550059412451215">Figure 3</xref> illustrates the variation of the frequency power of the signal in each channel during different periods of 2 typical seizures. Every period of a whole sample section includes 20-second signals, containing a complete epileptic seizure extracted by the 10 intracranial eletrodes, and it is broken down into 4 parts, 5 seconds for every part. Since the ending of the seizure is not as important as the other parts, the section does not contain the termination. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1550059412451215">Figure 3</xref> shows the energy during 2 typical seizures, respectively, in A and B. Four continuous time ranges are shown from top to bottom in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1550059412451215">Figure 3A</xref> and B</p>
<p>From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1550059412451215">Figure 3</xref>, the abnormal frequency signals are found in the last 4 channels, corresponding to the area of the right temporal cortex. Before every seizure, the power of 30 to 80 Hz frequency-domain increased distinctly in all 4 temporal channels, which means this range of frequency signals can forecast the seizure.</p>
<p>The power of the high frequency range, of 100 to 200 Hz, elevated first in 9th and 10th channels and then in other channels (7th, 8th) positioned in the right temporal lobe. Sometimes it was found in other channels (as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1550059412451215">Figure 3</xref> shows). All results of the 6 seizures are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1550059412451215">Table 1</xref>. This table indicates the channel where the high-frequency oscillation first takes place.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1550059412451215" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Starting Channels of 6 Seizures’ Abnormal Signals.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1550059412451215" xlink:href="10.1177_1550059412451215-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Seizures</th>
<th>1st</th>
<th>2nd</th>
<th>3rd</th>
<th>4th</th>
<th>5th</th>
<th>6th</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Starting channels</td>
<td>Channel 10</td>
<td>Channel 9</td>
<td>Channel 9</td>
<td>Channel 9</td>
<td>Channel 10</td>
<td>Channel 9</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>MATLAB <italic>t</italic> test between every 2 signal sequences was performed to distinguish the abnormal sequence from all channels and to eliminate error. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1550059412451215">Table 2</xref> shows the <italic>P</italic> values of all pairs of 10 channels shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1550059412451215">Figure 3A</xref>. If the <italic>P</italic> value is less than .01, the possibility of error can be rejected. It can be seen that channel 10 has the smallest <italic>P</italic> value, which means the distinction between channel 10 and other channels was due to a pathological discharge, not errors or technical problems.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1550059412451215" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p><italic>P</italic> Values of All Combinational Pairs of 10 Channels.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1550059412451215" xlink:href="10.1177_1550059412451215-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>Ch 1</th>
<th>Ch 2</th>
<th>Ch 3</th>
<th>Ch 4</th>
<th>Ch 5</th>
<th>Ch 6</th>
<th>Ch 7</th>
<th>Ch 8</th>
<th>Ch 9</th>
<th>Ch 10</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Ch 1</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>.8335</td>
<td>.2890</td>
<td>.7446</td>
<td>.7388</td>
<td>.2146</td>
<td>.0527</td>
<td>.0129</td>
<td>.0646</td>
<td>3.35e-09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ch 2</td>
<td>.8335</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>.7360</td>
<td>.8755</td>
<td>.0031</td>
<td>.0077</td>
<td>.7073</td>
<td>.0178</td>
<td>.0311</td>
<td>1.22e-09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ch 3</td>
<td>.2890</td>
<td>.7360</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>.3249</td>
<td>.5331</td>
<td>.1722</td>
<td>.0181</td>
<td>.7757</td>
<td>7.24e-04</td>
<td>5.21e-07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ch 4</td>
<td>.7446</td>
<td>.8755</td>
<td>.3249</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>.9136</td>
<td>8.12e-04</td>
<td>.3238</td>
<td>.0156</td>
<td>.1098</td>
<td>5.71e-07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ch 5</td>
<td>.7388</td>
<td>.0031</td>
<td>.5331</td>
<td>.9136</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>7.93e-04</td>
<td>.3308</td>
<td>.0773</td>
<td>.3051</td>
<td>2.59e-09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ch 6</td>
<td>.2146</td>
<td>.0077</td>
<td>.1722</td>
<td>8.12e-04</td>
<td>7.93e-04</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>.5442</td>
<td>.4102</td>
<td>.0471</td>
<td>6.42e-06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ch 7</td>
<td>.8733</td>
<td>.7073</td>
<td>.0181</td>
<td>.3238</td>
<td>.3308</td>
<td>.5442</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>.4123</td>
<td>3.56e-9</td>
<td>3.56e-10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ch 8</td>
<td>.0527</td>
<td>.0178</td>
<td>.7757</td>
<td>.00156</td>
<td>.00773</td>
<td>.4012</td>
<td>.4123</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>.0901</td>
<td>7.29e-06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ch 9</td>
<td>.0646</td>
<td>.0311</td>
<td>7.24e-04</td>
<td>.1098</td>
<td>.3051</td>
<td>.0471</td>
<td>3.56e-9</td>
<td>.0901</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>1.59e-09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ch 10</td>
<td>3.35e-09</td>
<td>1.22e-09</td>
<td>5.21e-07</td>
<td>5.71e-07</td>
<td>2.59e-09</td>
<td>6.42e-06</td>
<td>3.56e-10</td>
<td>7.29e-06</td>
<td>1.59e-09</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1550059412451215">Table 1</xref> shows the starting position of the abnormal epileptic signals’ appearance in the right anterior temporal lobe, where the 9th and 10th channels are placed. Because those high-frequency signals of 100 to 200 Hz, also defined as the “ripple” by experts, are considered the special mark of the epileptic focus,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1550059412451215">3</xref></sup> our results suggest the focus is in the right anterior temporal lobe between positions of 9th and 10th channel, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1550059412451215">Figure 4</xref>. The entire right temporal is impacted when the epileptic seizure takes place.</p>
<fig id="fig4-1550059412451215" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>The epileptic signals take place at channel 9 and 10 (the most inferior electrodes in the temporal lobe). Thus, the corresponding area, right anterior temporal lobe, is determined to be the epileptic focus.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1550059412451215-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1550059412451215">Figure 3</xref> we found that the different ranges of frequency took place at a different time. A typical seizure is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1550059412451215">Table 3</xref>. The start time of the most intense elevation of those different frequency ranges is shown in the second row, while the amplitude range is in the third row.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1550059412451215" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>The Start Time of the Most Intense Elevation.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1550059412451215" xlink:href="10.1177_1550059412451215-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Frequency range</th>
<th>0-30 Hz</th>
<th>30-80 Hz</th>
<th>80-120 Hz</th>
<th>120-200 Hz</th>
<th>200-300 Hz</th>
<th>300-500 Hz</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Time of the most intense elevation</td>
<td>40-30 seconds before the seizure</td>
<td>10-0 seconds before the seizure</td>
<td>10-0 seconds before the seizure</td>
<td>0-10 seconds after the seizure</td>
<td>20-30 seconds after the seizure</td>
<td>30-40 seconds after the seizure</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Amplitude (dB)</td>
<td>40 to 10</td>
<td>15 to −10</td>
<td>−5 to −10</td>
<td>−5 to −20</td>
<td>−10 to −30</td>
<td>−15 to −30</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1550059412451215">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>All 3 patients’ epileptic foci are determined by our methods. The foci of 2 patients are right temporal, and 1 is right forehead. The results are verified by clinical examination and surgery. The clinical experts use the spike wave and sharp wave to determine approximately the area of the epileptic focus, and then they read the MRI to find the visual abnormality. Finally, they determined the epileptic focus to be near the hippocampus, exactly consistent with our results. Furthermore, the recovery of patients after the operation also strongly supported the conclusion.</p>
<p>The variations of frequency-domain signal have already been reported. Those variations contain the elevation of the frequency power, appearance of the ripple, even FR.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1550059412451215">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1550059412451215"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1550059412451215">12</xref></sup> However, the combination of the time–frequency analysis and clinical diagnosis is difficult because of complex ingredients of cortical EEG signals commonly used in hospitals. In this study, electro-myographic (EMG) and electro-oculographic (EOG) artifacts are avoided by use of an intracranial electrode. Software preprocessing, clearly refined the characteristics of the frequency domain.</p>
<p>Furthermore, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1550059412451215">Figure 3</xref> shows that the change in FR (250-500 Hz) is far from accurate enough to discriminate the epileptic focus, which is different from the conclusion reported in other earlier work.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1550059412451215">13</xref></sup></p>
<p>In this research, the value of high-frequency signals is verified. Although variation takes place in the whole range of frequency, the elevation of low-frequency power verified cannot be a special mark of the epilepsy. This is because the change of low-frequency-domain signals occasionally appears interictally, or in nonlesion areas. The spectra of different periods of 2 channels in nonlesion and lesion areas are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1550059412451215">Figure 5</xref>. The colors, in order of blue, green, shamrock, red, violet and yellow (See online color publication), represent 6 continuous time ranges.</p>
<fig id="fig5-1550059412451215" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>A, The spectrum of the signals from the normal area of cortex. B, The spectrum of the signals from the epileptic focus. The curves in different colors represent continuous time period in the order of blue, green, shamrock, red, violet, and yellow (See online color publication).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1550059412451215-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1550059412451215">Figure 5</xref>, it can be found that the elevation of the range 0 to 50 Hz in channels’ signals and curves in B shows no obvious difference compared with those in A.</p>
<p>The different ranges of frequency take place during the seizure at different times. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1550059412451215">Table 3</xref> lists the start time and the energy range of different frequency ranges. The order of the elevation of different frequency ranges is clearly detected. Basically, the energy rises in turn from low-frequency to high-frequency. The most intense elevation in 80 to 120 Hz and 120 to 200 Hz appears just at the seizure point. Elevations in those frequency domains are most sensitive to the seizure, and also, we can infer that the area where those elevations appear would be the epileptic focus. The result further confirms the specificity of those frequency ranges to the seizure. Those of  0 to 30 Hz and 30 to 80 Hz take place earlier than the seizure. However, the change of 0 to 30 Hz generally occurs in EEG signals. Therefore, the 30 to 80 Hz related with cyclical sharp wave might be used to forecast epileptic seizure in future research.</p>
<p>Nowadays, traditional methods used by clinical doctors combine many procedures including EEG and MRI. However, MRI is expensive and complicated to analyze. Furthermore, sometimes a great deviation exists between the conclusion derived from the MRI and EEG time domain. High-frequency oscillation detection depends on the time–frequency analyze introduced above and is only based on EEG signals, which significantly saves cost. However the accuracy is well guaranteed. Moreover, because of the concise algorithm, this method is beneficial to real-time monitoring.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1550059412451215">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>From the results and discussion, the high-frequency-domain signal is sensitive to the epileptic seizure. This provides evidence for the clinical approach to include the frequency domain of seizure identification. Compared with the traditional spike-dependent approach, this method focuses on frequency feature extraction and identification. It can be more easily designed into software diagnosis and then automatic diagnosis, especially in the determination of epileptic focus.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1550059412451215"><label>Authors’ Note</label>
<p>Xiaoying Tang, Li Xia, and Weifeng Liu contributed equally to this work.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn2-1550059412451215"><label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-1550059412451215"><label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>Reference</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1550059412451215">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>EEG in the diagnosis, classification, and management of patients with epilepsy</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>suppl 2</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1550059412451215">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pillai</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sperling</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Interictal EEG and the diagnosis of epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>47</volume>
<issue>(suppl.1)</issue>:<fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1550059412451215">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hjorth</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>EEG analysis based on time domain properties</article-title>. <source>Electroencephalogr Clin Neurophysiol</source>. <year>1970</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>306</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1550059412451215">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ko</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holmes</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>EEG and clinical predictor of medically intractable childhood epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Clin Neurophysiol</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1245</fpage>–<lpage>1251</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1550059412451215">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Webber</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lesser</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arroyo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Uematsu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>High-frequency EEG activity at the start of seizures</article-title>. <source>J Clin Neurophysiol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1550059412451215">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xian-zeng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wei-wei</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Study on relation between ripple oscillations and temporal lobe seizures of rats</article-title>. <source>Chin J Geriatr Heart Brain Vessel Dis</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>8</issue>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1550059412451215">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bragin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Engel</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fried</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Buzsaki</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>High-frequency oscillations In human brain</article-title>. <source>Hippocampus</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1550059412451215">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ochi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Otsubo</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Donner</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Dynamic changes of ictal high-frequency oscillations in neocortical epilepsy: using multiple band frequency analysis</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>286</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1550059412451215">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jirsch</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Urrestarazu</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>LeVan</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Olivier</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dubeau</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gotman</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>High-frequency oscillations during human focal seizure</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>pt 6</issue>):<fpage>1593</fpage>–<lpage>1608</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1550059412451215">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Staba</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frighetto</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Behnke</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Increased fast ripple to ripple ratios correlate with reduced hippocampal volumes and neuron loss in temporal lobe epilepsy patients</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2130</fpage>–<lpage>2138</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1550059412451215">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bragin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Engel</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Spatial stability over time of brain areas generating fast ripples in the epileptic rat</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1233</fpage>–<lpage>1237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1550059412451215">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Worrell</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Parish</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cranstoun</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jonas</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baltuch</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Litt</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>High-frequency oscillations and seizure generation in neocortical epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>127</volume>(<issue>pt 7</issue>):<fpage>1496</fpage>–<lpage>1506</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1550059412451215">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jacobs</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>LeVan</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chander</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hall</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dubeau</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gotman</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Interictal high-frequency oscillations (80-500Hz) are an indicator of seizure onset areas independent of spikes in the human epileptic brain</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1893</fpage>–<lpage>1907</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>