<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">LCH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">splch</journal-id>
<journal-title>Law, Culture and the Humanities</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1743-8721</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1743-9752</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1743872111406428</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1743872111406428</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Legality Against Orality</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>Bradley</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1743872111406428">Department of Political Science, University of Victoria, BC, Canada</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1743872111406428">Email: <email>bwb@uvic.ca</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>261</fpage>
<lpage>274</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Association for the Study of Law, Culture and the Humanities</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Recent work on political liberalism attempts to find ways to bring divergent cultural practices under a single rubric. This article examines one of the limits of the cultural commensurability of modern liberal legality. It argues that Western forms of evidentiary proof are not amenable to oral history testimony given by indigenous litigants. Current anthropological research on oral history and indigenous culture shows that oral history is not simply a “record” or “chronology” of events, but is a particular cultural practice that draws its members into the fold – and this is an event of its own. Western forms of evidence, however, traditionally treat testimony as “reporting” or as “creating a record” of a prior set of events in time. This article suggests that the distance between these two conceptions of “events” and “record” is significant enough to warrant rethinking the place of traditional trial practices in the treatment of oral history. It also suggests that the Western form of legality is grounded in an understanding of temporality that eschews any other way of thinking about events and their occurrence, a legality oriented against orality.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Oral history</kwd>
<kwd>evidence</kwd>
<kwd>legal record</kwd>
<kwd>testimony</kwd>
<kwd>legal theory</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1743872111406428" sec-type="intro">
<title>I. Introduction</title>
<p>The oral history of Aboriginal peoples presents a challenge to liberal society’s presumption of its own openness. The rules of evidence that permit oral evidence as testimony not only limit the strategies of Aboriginal peoples in court – they invite Aboriginal litigants to re-interpret their own storied past as nothing more than a series of represented, chronological events … a re-interpretation that harbors the possible destruction of their very culture and nationhood. In what follows I aim to show not only how any full account of oral history is at odds with Western evidentiary forms of legality, but also how such forms of legality are utterly corrosive of the cultural forms they seek to admit. In doing so, I draw on and refer to the work of many others both in the general area of indigenous oral history as a form of law, and of the place of oral history within Western settler legal traditions. In effect, we stand to learn how the very notion of truth and fact at the core of Western legal traditions instantiates an imperial stance. I should note that I have been very influenced by the work of John Borrows in this area, and that above all I admire his hopefulness for if not a rapprochement at least an evolution and inter-mingling of legal styles and traditions. Unfortunately I do not quite share that hopefulness, if only because of some nagging doubts about core ideas that animate Western law, that is, that both the events of the past and the law that governs them can be represented as having a chronological appearance in time, and in a way that governs and dictates the way we understand the facts of the present as a foundation for action. I will say more of this in what follows, but for now the key unsubstantiated proposition is that Western forms of legality as enshrined in the law of evidence create a relationship with the past and also posit a legal subject in relation to that past. The events of the past are interpreted as factual occurrences that can be recounted and retold in a way meant to mirror the original events. By requiring oral history to fit this mould, as it were, there is yet again unwitting colonization.</p>
<p>I begin with an account of the law of evidence governing the submission of oral history as evidence, and then with some basic and fundamental points about the foundations of evidence and of Western legality in general. This discussion of evidence will parlay into a discussion of what is at stake in the law of liberal societies, and why the rules of evidence exist and what they presume about events, the past, a record, and the role of authorities in settling such questions. Following this, we will alter our course and examine the notion of oral history in law, as well as the way oral history is thought of by historians and anthropologists. We will then be in a position to imagine (not prove or even show) what oral history might be for non-Western peoples, and hence to (only) imagine the conditions that support how other peoples understand themselves in relation to their histories.</p>
<p>Only once we have undertaken such an analysis could we be in a position to assess how difficult the question of oral history is for law. This question can be summed up in the simple observation made by indigenous litigants time and time again: oral history is not hearsay. And yet it behooves the non-Aboriginal to properly understand the force of this claim, since we understand history as the collection of events of the past – events that can be recounted and retold and verified in particular ways. Indeed, by seeing the limits of the law’s capacity to establish a verifiable record we witness the limit of a liberal society that attempts to resolve difference through law. Oral history exists at odds with legality; legality invites the speakers of oral history to unwittingly abandon their own possibilities as cultural agents by the very invitation that the court issues: “understand your testimony as a record of past events.” In this we witness the destruction of culture at the hands of law, something, as latecoming liberals, we would do better to think through to avoid. This article is, then, also a call to jurists and judges to think through the way we think of the kinds of evidence offered by indigenous litigants, and to take seriously the claim that oral history is not hearsay, and is indeed akin to the performance of nationhood it often claims to be.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1743872111406428">
<title>II. Oral History Evidence in Context: Canada’s “Exception to Hearsay” Rule</title>
<p>The original position, and some lawyers would say best position, that oral history can occupy as evidence within western legal traditions is as a form of hearsay admitted in exceptional cases. Oral history is offered in court as evidence of a prior practice, offered to vindicate the claim that a right or practice or title of ownership existed at some time prior to Western forms of historical record. The question about the extent and uses of oral history has been given considerable and unprecedented attention in Western Canada in the province of British Columbia where the historical extinguishment of indigenous land rights did not occur by cessation, treaty, or conquest. In this context, oral history is seen as a “last resort” in establishing proof of occupancy and use of territory.</p>
<p>In what has now become one of the most important cases on indigenous title rights, the court considered oral history in the case of <italic>Delgamuukw v. British Columbia</italic> – a case that saw many elder Aboriginal peoples travel from their historical homelands to give word to their storied presence on the land. Despite the original denial of oral history as evidence at the trial level in the now infamous decision of the late Alan McEachern CJ, the Supreme Court of Canada did go on to set guidelines for the admission of oral history testimonies as ways of indicating and proving various kinds of claims related to Aboriginal rights and title. The purpose of such evidence is often to establish that certain practices occurred at some significant point in the past, such that their past occurrence is warrant for the existence of present day rights – one of which is title. To the end of proving what has come to be called “Aboriginal title,” the court will consider the oral history given by elders as a way to corroborate the claim of a continuous occupation of the land in question, often for an extensive time prior to so-called contact by settlers. As an earlier edition of a classic evidentiary text in Canada makes clear, following the Supreme Court of Canada’s approach in <italic>Delgamuukw v. British Columbia</italic><sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1743872111406428">1</xref></sup> the oral history of Aboriginal peoples is to be treated as an exception to the general rule against hearsay evidence: “The use of oral histories as proof of historical facts should be placed on an equal footing with the types of documentary historical evidence that courts traditionally receive.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1743872111406428">2</xref></sup> The commentators note that the court makes this exception to hearsay because oral histories may be “the only record of their past.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1743872111406428">3</xref></sup> Here we have all the elements of a legal system that understands historical time in terms of a chronological record given representation by testimony coming up against the lifeblood of a people, grounded as that lifeblood is in the stories passed on from generation to generation such as to constitute their storied past and present. That is, here we have <italic>the legal focus on the record</italic> coming up against <italic>the oral focus on the event</italic>. Let us try to make this opposition clearer by noting that in the following testimony (by Delgam Uukw) given at the opening of the <italic>Delgamuukw</italic> case was, in large part, not any discrete oral history or story (or dance), but representations and descriptions of them.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>My power is carried in my House’s histories, songs, dances and crests. It is recreated at the Feast when the histories are told, the songs and dances performed, and the crests displayed. With the wealth that comes from the respectful use of the territory, the House feeds the name of the Chief in the Feast Hall. In this way, the law, the Chief, the territory, and the Feast become one. The unity of the Chief’s authority and his House’s ownership of its territory are witnessed and thus affirmed by the other Chiefs at the Feast. By following the law, the power flows from the land to the people through the Chief; by using the wealth of the territory, the House feasts its Chief so he can properly fulfill the law. This cycle has been repeated on my land for thousands of years.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1743872111406428">4</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This account has much of the Western trappings of “history” insofar as it purports to dislocate the power of narrative and other forms of oral history by requiring, instead, an account of the record of facts of occupation.</p>
<p>It is critical to note that when oral history is offered as an account of the stories that have been passed on, it can be introduced into evidence only as an exception to hearsay. According to the Western understanding of both orality and history, “oral history” can only ever be a verbal recounting of events that occurred in the past, and, in the case of oral history, thus can only ever be <italic>recounting events originally told by others.</italic> Court-tendered oral history is thus <italic>prima facie</italic> representational, and litigants cannot help but grasp their own stories in this manner. We can see that this way of tendering a story would be considered hearsay because the oral recounting of historical events passed on from generation to generation understandably contains statements (in this case oral, but they can be written) made by persons / beings “otherwise than in testimony at the proceeding in which it is offered.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1743872111406428">5</xref></sup> The rationale for this old and venerated rule is grounded in a concern for the accuracy of the record that such testimony establishes, the degree to which adversely affected parties have the ability to put the evidence to the test, and thus to control the way evidence is put before the trier of fact.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1743872111406428">6</xref></sup> Indeed, to be a “trier of fact” tells us much about what we expect from testimony and the establishment of a record of the events that surround the most ordinary of cases. With hearsay evidence it is very difficult if not impossible to test the veracity of what is offered precisely because the one offering the evidence is not present. Indeed, the latent trouble here makes manifest the distrust of the spoken as opposed to the written, for the former vanishes upon being spoken whereas the latter remains in the form in which it was communicated:<disp-quote>
<p>The law assumes that all oral testimony is unreliable, and has accordingly built in such safeguards as the requirement of an oath, the right of cross-examination and the creation of the crime of perjury. Special attention has been given to hearsay as being particularly fraught with untrustworthiness because its evidential value rests on the credibility of an out-of-court asserter who is not subject to the oath, cross-examination or a charge of perjury.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1743872111406428">7</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>So we have it all here now: oaths as the necessary condition for truthfulness, cross-examination as the mode of testing whether something that is said is true, and truthfulness, as the sincere representation of witnessed fact, as condition precedent to the establishment of the record. However, there remains some helpful ambiguity to “the record,” such that one can imagine the oral histories of indigenous peoples as being broadly construed to work within it.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1743872111406428">8</xref></sup> For example, we can see that the general construal of oral history as hearsay presumes certain things about the human subject as a member of community, as one who exists in a relation of memory to the times that precede one’s own time, and to what counts as an “experience” of an event. So even before we come to the notion of “the record,” we must at least concede that human subjectivity is implicated in how records operate to present the past <italic>as</italic> the set of cohesive events that precede and to a degree lead to the present. There is no necessary reason why we must assume that oral histories perform the same set of relations.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1743872111406428">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>There have been very helpful and corrective treatments of the Court’s ruling on the place of oral history as evidence as something possibly other than hearsay, or as hearsay that at the very least brings something beyond the usual concerns with reliability. John Borrows has convincingly shown the way oral history can indeed corroborate occupation despite being oral and not written.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1743872111406428">10</xref></sup> In his inimitable thoughtful way, Borrows invites the advocates of western law to embrace oral storytelling as one of its own forms of giving evidence, and that the point of stories and their deployment in court need not be treated within the strict confines of evidence in order to be valuable in establishing the record of practices required to sustain a claim of an Aboriginal right. Indeed, Borrows notes that the drive to grasp “what went on in the past” belongs to the path of justice, and is a noble goal of the trial. He asks, however, that courts listen to the words and sense of the story rather than seek verification of a factual record.</p>
<p>Val Napoleon has also shown ways that the guidelines restrict our understanding of oral history by questioning the rather narrow understanding of history that the court aims to recreate in its appropriation of indigenous storytelling as a means for establishing a depiction of the past.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1743872111406428">11</xref></sup> Both Napoleon and Borrows help us to see the way Western evidentiary standards too narrowly interpret indigenous oral history, not allowing it to stand on its own as a kind of proof of a former way of life that has come under the force of successive waves of colonization.</p>
<p>I wish to push their claim even further, and to do so by taking Western legality’s own notion of evidence, record, and history to task. For even though they both claim that oral history is indeed “history” that can corroborate the record of occupation in a definitive way, the orality of indigenous peoples is already understood as reporting and presenting some kind of account of past events <italic>rather than being the event itself</italic>. We fail to grasp the possible significance of oral history when we understand it solely as factual reproduction of events of the past instead of understanding it as the kind of formative and constitutive political event that the proclaiming of such stories may be – something also not foreign to Western understandings of constitutionalism.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-1743872111406428">12</xref></sup> It may be claimed that evidence generally is put forth for a variety of purposes; it is hard to deny that part of the force of oral history for claimants is its ability to claim that a certain way of life existed in the past. In inviting the indigenous litigant to interpret her history in this way, the temporal orientation of the colonizer takes hold of indigenous stories, and indeed of indigenous storytelling. Because the Western manner of adjudicating <italic>between</italic> narrative and what we might call “reality” hinges on an underlying view of history as chronological, Aboriginal oral history can only ever be taken as evidence <italic>of</italic> a tradition rather than in the manner or role in which its members might interpret and indeed inhabit it. But of course to the Western legal mind, the possibilities that lie latent within Aboriginal storytelling must remain possibilities interpreted anthropologically (i.e. as possibilities for a people’s self-understanding – this too requires the representation of a subject).</p>
<p>While it is not for me to say what indigenous storytelling is or has been, I can say that Western evidentiary rules invite litigants to see stories as <italic>reporting on events</italic> that occurred in the past necessarily in the mode of the representational legal subject, rather than to see their performance as an event in itself. As I will argue, Western legality is unable to see the statement of oral history in any other form. The Western legal mind can grasp the idea of storytelling veritably constituting something like a “worldview” for indigenous litigants, and can also recognize this as a possibility belonging to Aboriginal storytelling and oral history <italic>without</italic> getting into the anthropological or historical work of “fact-finding” about what these practices entail. That is to say, one can imagine the possibility of constitutive traditions without having to grasp the content of them. And yet, when Aboriginal storytelling is proffered in court <italic>as</italic> oral history, we have two very important moments of transformation folded into one: first, Aboriginal oral history, when described to the litigants themselves <italic>as</italic> representing and constituting the record of facts about the past, can be transformed for the litigants themselves into a Western practice, and thereby foreclose upon any other sense the story might have; and second one can only ever gesture at what Aboriginal storytelling <italic>could</italic> be, for it lies not in the non-Aboriginal ken to speak to whether it is “richer” or “deeper.” Thus, if we are honest with the limits of adjudication, we cannot be sure whether Aboriginal storytelling does allow for any kind of adjudication between what Westerners would refer to as the opposed relation of narrative and reality. For present purposes, let us note that the late-modern Westerner, such as we are, can grasp the possibility of such practices without commenting on what they make available to the members of their traditions, and in such imagining we have already understood storytelling as represented narrative.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1743872111406428">
<title>III. Legality’s Evidence: Event and Record</title>
<p>Many lawyers privately remark that “oral history” evidence is frustrating for lawyers who would like to cross-examine it because it is hearsay evidence. That is, it reports on stories of events that have been told and re-told. There is a recognition among lawyers and judges, in fact, that oral history cannot be cross-examined – and the sense is that to do so shows some kind of lack of respect to those who tender the evidence. However, my impression is that the reticence to cross-examine is due to the limited fruitfulness of cross-examining oral history – since the stories that comprise it do not lend themselves to easy interpretation of “what happened.” Insofar as we imagine oral history as proffering evidence of occupation, we run into trouble, we are told. As the judge who had presided at trial, McEachern CJ, later reported on his own assessment of oral history:<disp-quote>
<p>The first question of Delgamuukw was did [the Gitksan and Wet’suwet’en Nations] have the culture and society [that would entitle them to Aboriginal rights]. I decided on the basis of anthropological, geneological, archeological and historical evidence – hard evidence – that the answer was yes, they did. It was unnecessary to go further, because it was controversial … I said, ‘‘I don’t need that. I’ve decided that issue.’’ Now, the oral evidence has assumed a much larger role in this case than I thought it needed, because I decided on other evidence.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-1743872111406428">13</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Now, some lawyers find it strategic to offer oral history not for the truth of what it says but as evidence of a storytelling that goes back a number of generations. This, too, suffers the fate of hearsay simply because the best evidentiary value that the transmission of stories can offer is proof that one’s forebears were told the story by their forebears – also hearsay. It seems there is no way around understanding oral history as a form of hearsay. Hearsay is famously defined as evidence that reports what others have witnessed, and is often not admitted into evidence if it is possible to have primary witnesses available to give the evidence first-hand. Oral history was seen as a species of hearsay, and in being seen this way, highlights what the rules of evidence are: beyond governing the admissibility and presentation of testimony and artifacts into evidence, they are concerned with establishing a verifiable record, regardless of the weight given to the evidence. As Donald Casswell has very persuasively shown, rather than think of a strict exclusion of hearsay, we are best served by thinking of the admissibility in terms of a balancing of both the probative value that the evidence serves in illuminating an issue or fact in issue and the weight we might give it.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-1743872111406428">14</xref></sup> When oral history is tendered <italic>as evidence</italic>, the first concern (probative value) structures our understanding of what oral history actually is, i.e. we are invited to understand it as a form of reporting on a set of events of the past. When deemed admissible, the weight given to the evidence is balanced against its prejudicial effect, which is to say whether it can be effectively cross-examined or treated by the other party – in these cases usually the Crown. But even with this second purpose (the weight to be attached to oral history as testimony), the pre-understanding that Western forms of legality presume is that the testimony is offered as a kind of reporting on events that have already occurred. Indeed, it is hard to imagine how the legal process might be re-articulated or re-imagined to understand oral history in any other terms. Every lawyer knows that the key to effective trial practice surrounds the establishment of the record – for it makes no sense to put facts before the trier of fact if the facts themselves are not the issue. And in cases of Aboriginal rights and title, the issues are understood to be historical: were these practices consistent with those of the past, or was there sufficient evidence of prior use and occupation. Legality meets orality over the question of the past, and the question of the past is understood by Western legal traditions as ensuring that the court properly grasp what actually happened: the goal of the trial is to “try facts” and to find the “truth of the matter.” The rules of evidence only facilitate this but also (necessarily) presume what serves as truth, as fact, and hence as an event and as record.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-1743872111406428">15</xref></sup> The essence of evidence, and hence of the modern trial, is the establishment of a record of facts in order to pronounce judgment on “what happened.” There remain many questions to properly formulate concerning what occurs in judgment, and what political significance the act of judgment carried out by an official might have. Be that as it may, an essential aspect of the trial is to settle the record of facts. In this, witnesses are offered as vehicles that allow for the record and its veracity to be settled. It is difficult to imagine how else to view evidence except as a particularly legal variant of historical presentation.</p>
<p>The crucial point towards which we are moving is thus the following: it stands as an open question as to whether the use of oral history is appropriate to this evidentiary task not because of the worry about whether oral history is strong enough to corroborate such claims but because the persistence of legality as a mode of understanding the nature of legal subjects in relation to their own practices and pasts invites indigenous litigants to exchange what may be a different or even more robust involvement in their culture for one that sees time as the linear progression of events. In this way, the parlaying of oral history into testimony amounts to a form of de-culturation that perhaps we ought to find worrying. This is the heart of Western temporality as chronological history: history is understood as the record of events that follow each other and cause further events.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-1743872111406428">16</xref></sup> To understand oral history <italic>as history</italic> is already to understand the nature of the oral utterance as temporally bound, as projecting a future from out of past – and hence to re-affirm the particular political commitments of Western historiography. In <italic>The Limits of History</italic>, Constantin Fasolt articulates the way the “political” essence of history is <italic>not</italic> that it is biased towards this or that interpretation of the past, but rather that the articulation of temporality as historical is its political commitment:<disp-quote>
<p>History is linked to politics, some say, because politics is what history is <italic>about</italic>. From that perspective the link consists of the relation between a given method of examination (history) and a given subject matter to which that method is applied (politics). But that link is weak … History is linked to politics by the practice of history itself. There is no need for historians to focus their attention on politics in order to establish the connection. The connection is complete the moment they turn their attention to the past … They serve politics as soon as they begin to do research.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-1743872111406428">17</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>And as Fasolt goes on to say, there is nothing untoward about this except that historians presume that the essence of their practice is the only way to think the temporal relation of the existent human to its time. The difficulty we are confronted with is not soluble at the level of the trial or legality itself; the difficulty we are confronted with is what to do with the frank admission that the legality of the trial presents a vision of the temporality of the subject that is at odds in principle with those “subjects” (i.e. Aboriginal peoples’ and their oral traditions) it claims to treat.</p>
<p>Considered with respect to cases that seek to establish Aboriginal rights or title, a fundamental aspect of the admission of oral history as hearsay is to take account of the purpose for which it is offered, i.e. the establishment of a prior way of life that would substantiate the right in question. The fact that oral history has become linked to proprietary entitlement in the Western sense is not without significance, and it invites indigenous litigants to understand their own testimony in a straightforwardly utilitarian manner: the content of their own history is viewed as establishing not just a record of the facts of their way of life but a record of occupation of territory. Such an invitation not only alters the indigenous understanding of the relation of Aboriginal peoples to their lands<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-1743872111406428">18</xref></sup> – but also invites a re-conceptualizing of what “their own” history is. That is to say, the invitation to present oral history in the venue of the trial as evidence that can substantiate a record invites Aboriginal people to understand their oral traditions as records. Walter Ong puts the matter eloquently in <italic>Orality and Literacy</italic>, a fundamental shift in a people’s own orientation to language and thought occurs with the transformation of an oral culture into a literate one.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-1743872111406428">19</xref></sup> Despite a worry over what is lost, Ong embraced the “benefits” of writing – lamenting that there is no way we can properly grasp what was lost.</p>
<p>Let us not narrowly construe the robust nature of evidentiary proof or testimony. Historically, testimony has been of a varied nature, and the way testimony became legal fact that reported on a past event is itself an interesting story about how “law” has become “sociological legality,” as Marianne Constable has recounted.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20-1743872111406428">20</xref></sup> But as Constable also notes, the introduction of writing changes the nature of law by turning it into a seeming system of legal propositions that can be reproduced over and over again in general form during a trial. The development of legal rules of evidence goes hand in hand with both the invention and devaluation of a specific mode of speech: testimony that gives credence to a past event, that does not replicate the past event in speaking of it but can only be understood to report on it. Testimony’s frailties become doubled in the face of what the legal rule has become, i.e. a fact itself. Today, in contrast with trials prior to writing, testimony is essential to the trial because of the way it allows the “trier of fact” a certain kind of access to and control over the story of “what happened.” The key idea here is that some kind of event in the past stands behind law’s power to reproduce itself, an event that cannot itself be captured in the saying of law.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21-1743872111406428">21</xref></sup> But notice that the law’s power to reproduce itself in the pronouncement of a verdict upon the events it takes to have happened also rests upon yet a further story of the events of the past: the moment of contact and sovereignty. In the narrative of original contact between European and indigenous peoples, one also finds reference to stories that are no longer told – to doctrines of “empty land” or <italic>terra nullius</italic> that circulate to give credence to the “fact” of settlers coming to “settle” the land, to make tame and bring under control those elements <italic>ferae naturae</italic>. Testimony is meant to corroborate much older stories, ones that buttress the law’s claim to have a claim. In this way the story that is oral history is not simply recording or evidencing, it is, properly speaking, <italic>manifesting</italic> law. Oral history, then, must be understood as an event itself, a manifesting of what has hitherto remained hidden, and an acceptance of the invitation to understand itself not just as the corroboration of a set of events, but also of the event on which Western legality rests. In this way it can never corroborate a record without becoming something other than oral history, and if it is to remain oral history, it stands against legality.</p>
<p>We are not narrowly construing history when we acknowledge that the way the historical comes to us today does not admit of other ways of grasping how the individual might exist temporally. That is to say, to grasp time <italic>as</italic> history and hence events as facts that can be chronologically rendered also requires that we do not think of the event of politics as something on-going. For thinkers like Hobbes, Sovereignty was to be understood as an on-going event present in every single act and thought within the polity.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22-1743872111406428">22</xref></sup> The state of nature, as axiomatic and heuristic, is not an historical past but rather the principled basis at play in every one of our thoughts: our usage of roadways and acts of civility “evidence” our consent not because they report on its prior existence (there is not necessarily an actual consent) but because these activities demonstrate that we would rather participate than let our world slip into anarchy. For Hobbes, then, the event of politics is contained in every trial, and its legality can only ever showcase this event, right down to the presentation of the human as temporally bound in history. We can see that this manner of understanding is totalizing in the sense that it is difficult for the Western account of history to understand any other way of relating to the past. As Martin Heidegger puts it:<disp-quote>
<p>In the historical sciences, just as in the natural sciences, the methodology aims at representing what is fixed and stable and at making history an object. History can become an object only when it is past … And there is no other historiographical explanation so long as explaining means reduction to what is intelligible and so long as historiography remains research, i.e. an explaining. Because historiography as research projects and objectifies the past in the sense of an explicable and surveyable nexus of actions and consequences, it requires source criticism as its instrument of objectification. The standards of this criticism alter to the degree that historiography approaches journalism.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23-1743872111406428">23</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>There is no other way of grasping what is historical in oral history as long as we think of history as simply producing a record of what happens, which Heidegger perhaps unfairly refers to as journalism. Legality requires that history is the careful rendering of the historical as a chronological series of articulated events in evidence; to think otherwise is to move beyond what we ordinarily understand by legality.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1743872111406428">
<title>IV. Oral History: the Happening of an Event</title>
<p>The foregoing accounts of oral history and of the basis for treating oral history as an exception to hearsay are meant to focus our attention on the way we ordinarily think of history, and to encourage us to imagine what else oral history might be. For even though much anthropological research reports that “other cultures” comprehend the passage of time, and hence the identity of cultural members to their pasts, differently, simply trusting what anthropologists tell us about “other cultures” traffics in the same form of reporting on external occurrences we see with legality’s manner of establishing a record. That is to say, the mode of “reporting on fact” is a feature not just of legality but of a more general and widely held understanding of how “facts” occur “in” time, and consequently how we come across these facts. It is time to commit to memory the fact that “facts” are not the naturally occurring events we might imagine them to be, as has been shown elsewhere time and time again.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24-1743872111406428">24</xref></sup> To properly grasp oral history we do not need to show it as a kind of factual form of history that belongs to another people; rather, we need merely <italic>imagine the possibility of a history that is not simply reporting on events</italic>. That is, we need only grant the possibility of a way of life that is grounded in a completely other way of grasping the passage of time and the renewal of discrete possibilities, and to recognize its power to manifest. There is considerable excellent historiographical work that gives us the slow changing sense of how a particular trial is understood to capture the events of the past and pass judgment upon them – and the irony in drawing on these is all too apparent. Barbara Shapiro, for example, has shown convincingly that the very notion of a reasonable doubt, and the words that best express it, have at times been understood as “moral certainty” and at times demanding much less.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25-1743872111406428">25</xref></sup> Mary Poovey’s excellent historical work on the evolution of our very notion of factuality, placing it as she does in the history of bookkeeping as the first form of reckoning with the past in numbers, shows the way the notion of a past that can be recorded was not necessarily in existence prior to the early modern period.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26-1743872111406428">26</xref></sup> Again, we tread here ironically, for we find through our historiographical work that the very understanding of the past and its bearing on the present has changed within the Western tradition itself. Indeed we might remark, following Fasolt, that there may exist multiple histories, not just multiple chronologies, within what we call “the Western tradition.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27-1743872111406428">27</xref></sup></p>
<p>Let us imagine the way oral history might matter to a people who practice it, and let us do so without romanticizing that manner of existing. So far we have understood history as an amalgam of reports on events. What if history were something other than this, but rather a particular kind of practice that cultural members engage in and perform to constitute their lives and polities? What if history involves the opening of a world <italic>through</italic> the story that makes sense of events? Or, further, <italic>what if the story is the event itself</italic>? Such a question demands the utmost of our thinking – and it demands that we think through what we take an event and its establishment to be. It may be nothing short of the constitution of a way of life – one that we have generally thought of as “political.” And with that, perhaps, we can glean some sense from the strong suggestion put forth by the Supreme Court in <italic>Delgamuukw</italic>: that the questions articulated here are above all political.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1743872111406428" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>V. Conclusion: Can Legality Comprehend Oral History?</title>
<p>To answer the question directly: not unless legality is re-thought from the ground up – and re-thought not simply from the “outside” but in the very place in which we find it, namely, the trial. Further, we cannot simply change our minds or design our worldviews: that would be to presume that our “frames” are themselves part of the furniture of our world at our disposal. “Re-thought” means we have to think about what it means to stand before and with the law. Legality can only begin to comprehend oral history if it allows itself the challenge of turning away from “the fact” in its ordinary business, and allows something other to occur within its confines. This task of re-thinking oral history in the trial demands that we re-think the relationship between legality and politics, and to begin to ask the question of law and of politics once again, to let the not-so-obvious aspects of these words strike us. Even though there is ample research to suggest that much that occurs in trials has a “political” basis, in Canada we are no longer immune from de Tocqueville’s astute observation of the fate of politics: all profound political questions sooner or later become legal ones. But what does this properly say, and how can we think this anew? The trial needs to either be liberated from its narrow legality, and the politics of the times in which we live needs to be invigorated. And an escape from narrow legality means bringing into question the very idea of “doctrine,” of a “truth” that can be brought to bear independently of the circumstances that manifest it. It means understanding the storied foundations of the Western legal tradition, and what animates these over and against many others. Only by working towards a robust understanding of doctrine, one polyphonic, pragmatic, and self-conscious, might we even begin to imagine the performance of oral history as the continual re-instantiation of a people. Let us see if we are up to the challenge of imagining what would be required of legal liberalism to fully account for the otherness of oral history. This challenge goes to the heart of how we imagine politics and political liberalism – that is, who “we” take ourselves to be, we who would try to hear what the colonized would tell us, and we who recognize a continuing complicity.</p>
<p>It is not without significance that South Africa’s system of Apartheid was modeled on the British policy of creating reserves, and on the Canadian and American reserve systems.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28-1743872111406428">28</xref></sup> And while we can easily recognize the moral and political exigencies that required the abolition of Apartheid, we in Canada and the United States seem less able and certainly less willing to face the consequences of colonialism. One such consequence is the complicity of the very terms and methods of our legal and political life in the radical de-culturation of Aboriginal people – a de-culturation that continues through to this day. This complicity is one that exists at odds with our liberal sensibilities, since it is a legality that is, in its essence, <italic>against</italic> orality.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The author would like to thank Taiaiake Alfred, Mark Antaki, Benjamin Berger, John Borrows, Craig Cameron, Marianne Constable, Deborah Curran, Avigail Eisenberg, Rebecca Johnson, Johnny Mack, Val Napoleon, James Tully, and Jeremy Webber for comments and discussion on earlier versions of this article. The author is in no conflict of interest with respect to the research and writing of this article. This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1743872111406428">
<label>1.</label>
<p>[1997] 3 SCR 1010.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1743872111406428">
<label>2.</label>
<p>John Sopinka, Sidney Lederman, and Alan Bryant, <italic>The Law of Evidence in Canada</italic>, 2nd ed. (Toronto: LexisNexis Butterworths, 1999), p. 240.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1743872111406428">
<label>3.</label>
<p><italic>Op. cit.</italic>, p. 240.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1743872111406428">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Gisday Wa &amp; Delgam Uukw, <italic>The Spirit in the Land: The Opening Statement of the Gitksan and Wet’suwet’en Hereditary Chiefs in the Supreme Court of British Columbia May 11, 1987</italic> (Gabriola, BC: Reflections, 1992), specifically Delgam Uukw’s “testimony” at pp. 7–8.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1743872111406428">
<label>5.</label>
<p>Sopinka, Lederman, and Bryant, <italic>Law of Evidence in Canada</italic>, at p. 173.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1743872111406428">
<label>6.</label>
<p>Though there is dispute about the origins of the rule, and hence of the origins of the rationale for it, they seem to cohere in a desire to control the way the record is given form through proceedings: compare R.J. Deslisle, “Hearsay Evidence” [1984] <italic>L.S.U.C. Special Lectures</italic>, at pp. 59–64, and E.M. Morgan, “Hearsay Dangers and the Application of the Hearsay Concept” (1948), 62 <italic>Harvard Law Review</italic> 177, at pp. 177–84.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1743872111406428">
<label>7.</label>
<p>Sopinka, Lederman, and Bryant, <italic>The Law of Evidence in Canada</italic>, at p. 174.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1743872111406428">
<label>8.</label>
<p>Cf. John Borrows, “Listening for a Change: The Courts and Oral Tradition” (2001) 39 <italic>Osgoode Hall Law Journal</italic> 1.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1743872111406428">
<label>9.</label>
<p>See Walter Ong, <italic>Orality and Literacy: The Technologizing of the Word</italic> (London: Routledge, 1982), at pp. 12–15. I say “perform” because of the way the understanding of a human subject depends less on any particular theory or worldview of human subjectivity than it does on the way we glean that understanding from particular gestures and orientations one finds in the everyday average way that people direct themselves to each other. See Martin Heidegger, <italic>Being and Time</italic>, J. Macquarrie &amp; E. Robinson trans. (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1962), at ss. 26–27.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1743872111406428">
<label>10.</label>
<p>John Borrows, “Listening for a Change: The Courts and Oral Tradition” (2001) 39 <italic>Osgoode Hall Law Journal</italic> 1.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1743872111406428">
<label>11.</label>
<p>Val Napoleon, “<italic>Delgamuukw</italic>: A Legal Straightjacket for Oral Histories?” (2005) 20:2 <italic>Canadian Journal of Law &amp; Society</italic> 123.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-1743872111406428">
<label>12.</label>
<p>See and compare, for instance, Hannah Arendt’s insistence that the force of political, rather than legal, action is its constitutive role and form in Arendt, <italic>On Revolution</italic> (New York: Viking, 1963), at ch. 3, with Johnny Mack’s nuanced and important invitation to think not of “totems” as forms of law or constitutionalism but “constitutions as totems,” in Mack, <italic>Thickening Totems and Thinning Imperialism</italic>. Master’s Thesis, Faculty of Law, University of Victoria, 2007. Whenever we insist that certain cultural practices seem to look a lot like law we run the risk of saying something akin to “these mint leaves are a lot like toothpaste.” But this of course begs the question of which is prior. The ambiguity of priority should suggest the difficulty in the comparison, for, as Mack puts it (at p. 75): “Whether or not we are to become liberal citizens is not a live question – what is material is how we are to be ordered into the liberal state’s citizenry.”</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-1743872111406428">
<label>13.</label>
<p>Reported in <italic>The Ubyssey</italic>, Sept. 20, 2002, p. 3. Accessed at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ubcpubs.library.ubc.ca/?db=ubyssey#">http://ubcpubs.library.ubc.ca/?db=ubyssey#</ext-link> (Last accessed on September 9, 2010).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-1743872111406428">
<label>14.</label>
<p>Donald G. Casswell, “Through the Admissibility of Evidence Maze: An Attempt at a Purposive Structuring” (1991), 29 <italic>Alberta Law Review</italic> 584, at pp. 599–611.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-1743872111406428">
<label>15.</label>
<p>The classic articulation of this is C.A. Wright, “The Law of Evidence: Present and Future” (1942), 20 <italic>Canadian Bar Review</italic> 714, at p. 715.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-1743872111406428">
<label>16.</label>
<p>See Darien Shanske, <italic>Thucydides and the Philosophical Origins of History</italic> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009), at pp. 8–13, 148–55; Johannes Fabian, <italic>Time and the Other: How Anthropology Makes its Object</italic> (New York: Columbia University Press, 1983), at ch. 1; and more generally, Constantin Fasolt, <italic>The Limits of History</italic> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2004).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn17-1743872111406428">
<label>17.</label>
<p>Fasolt, <italic>Limits of History</italic>, at pp. xv–xvi.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn18-1743872111406428">
<label>18.</label>
<p>Bradley Bryan, “Property as Ontology: On English and Aboriginal Conceptions of Ownership” (2000) 13 <italic>Canadian Journal of Law and Jurisprudence</italic> 3. See also Hugh Brody, <italic>Maps and Dreams</italic> (Vancouver: McLelland &amp; Stewart, 1981).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn19-1743872111406428">
<label>19.</label>
<p>Walter Ong, <italic>Orality and Literacy: The Technologizing of the Word</italic> (London: Routledge, 1982).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn20-1743872111406428">
<label>20.</label>
<p>Cf. Marianne Constable, <italic>The Law of the Other: The Mixed Jury and Changing Conceptions of Citizenship, Law, and Knowledge</italic> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1994).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn21-1743872111406428">
<label>21.</label>
<p>Noted with perspicuity by Marianne Valverde’s account of the relation between the social scientific project of knowledge and law. See <italic>Law’s Dream of a Common Knowledge</italic> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2003), specifically at 10–11 and 225, but the book as a whole bears this point out.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn22-1743872111406428">
<label>22.</label>
<p>Most clearly articulated in the first part of <italic>The Leviathan</italic>. See Thomas Hobbes, <italic>The Leviathan</italic>, C.B. Macpherson, ed. (London: Penguin, 1982), at Bk I, ch. 10–13.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn23-1743872111406428">
<label>23.</label>
<p>Martin Heidegger, “The Age of the World Picture” in <italic>The Question Concerning Technology and Other Essays</italic>, W. Lovitt trans. (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1977), at p. 123.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn24-1743872111406428">
<label>24.</label>
<p>This observation is at least as old as Hume, and yet it seems that it is a foundational aspect of the way we think about the world and what happens in it: cf. Ian Hacking, <italic>Historical Ontology</italic> (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 2000), at ch. 1.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn25-1743872111406428">
<label>25.</label>
<p>Barbara Shapiro, “Fact and Proof of Fact in Anglo American Law” in Austin Sarat, ed. <italic>How the Law Knows</italic> (Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press, 2007).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn26-1743872111406428">
<label>26.</label>
<p>Mary Poovey, <italic>A History of the Modern Fact</italic> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1998).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn27-1743872111406428">
<label>27.</label>
<p>This is part of Fasolt’s main contention: <italic>Limits of History</italic>, at 221–32; see also Ian Hunter’s “Introduction,” <italic>Rival Enlightenments: Civil and Metaphysical Philosophy in Early Modern Germany</italic> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2001) for the contention that we deal as though there was a single sense to the past (i.e a single chronology) as well as a single way of gathering that past (i.e. a single historiography). It may be time for the legal manner for articulating history to catch up, as it were, to history’s study.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn28-1743872111406428">
<label>28.</label>
<p>That is, those in place following the Boer War, and institutionalized in “reserves” with the South African <italic>Native Land Act</italic> of 1913. See Graham Leach, <italic>South Africa: No Easy Path to Peace</italic> (London: Routledge, 1986), at pp. 68ff.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>