<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JER</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjer</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Journal of Engine Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1468-0874</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-3149</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1468087412445682</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1468087412445682</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Characterization of low- and high-temperature oxidation processes under non-premixed diesel-engine-like conditions</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Weclas</surname><given-names>Miroslaw</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Cypris</surname><given-names>Jochen</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1468087412445682">Faculty of Mechanical Engineering, Institute of Vehicle Technology (IFZN), Georg Simon Ohm University of Applied Sciences Nuremberg, Germany</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1468087412445682">M. Weclas, Faculty of Mechanical Engineering, Institute of Vehicle Technology (IFZN), Georg Simon Ohm University of Applied Sciences Nuremberg, Kesslerplatz 12, D-90489 Nürnberg, Germany. Email: <email>miroslaw.weclas@ohm-hochschule.de</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>628</fpage>
<lpage>638</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>22</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>24</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Low- and high-temperature oxidation processes, including thermal auto-ignition under diesel-engine-like conditions (non-premixed mixtures), have been investigated. A special combustion chamber, characterized by constant volume and adiabatic conditions, has been used as an engine simulator. The investigated processes are very complex in nature, and depend significantly on the temperature and pressure. There are five characteristic regions of the process characterized by different delay times, reaction rates and number of recognizable oxidation reactions: region 1 corresponds to processes occurring at low initial pressures over a wide range of initial temperatures; region 2 corresponds to low initial temperatures over a wide range of initial pressures; region 3 corresponds to middle pressures and higher temperatures; region 4 corresponds to middle temperatures and higher pressures; and region 5 corresponds to high initial pressures and high temperatures. by analogy to a negative temperature coefficient (as discussed in the literature), a positive pressure coefficient has been introduced here. This indicates that in the selected range of pressures, the delay time of low-temperature oxidation processes is the shortest, and the rate of these reactions is the highest. Further increases in the pressure behind the positive pressure coefficient range increase the delay time and decrease the reaction rate. The positive pressure coefficient has been observed at lower temperatures (mostly corresponding to cool-flame reactions and transitions to blue flames). Generally, the ignition delay time reduces with increasing chamber temperature and pressure.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Oxidation processes</kwd>
<kwd>thermal auto-ignition</kwd>
<kwd>diesel-engine-like conditions</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1468087412445682" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Fuel injection, mixture preparation and low- and high-temperature oxidation processes (including ignition) play a critical role in controlling engine combustion processes. The time between the beginning of fuel injection and the rapid pressure increase, corresponding to the high-temperature heat-release process, is defined as the ignition delay period. During this period of time, a number of complex chemical and physical processes occur. For example, chemical reactions (so-called pre-ignition or low-temperature oxidation processes) take place in order to establish correct conditions for thermal ignition (TI) (auto-ignition) processes, which are dependent on the temperature and pressure. The physics of the processes must consider a chain of processes such as fuel supply method (injection), spray distribution in space, spray atomization, fuel vaporization and mixing with air. These processes are highly complex in the case of diesel-engine-like conditions where the resulting mixture is highly non-homogeneous and is dependent on time and space. For future engines requiring clean combustion processes (homogeneous combustion processes), the chemistry of the pre-ignition processes, as well as controlled auto-ignition, are the key factors for process control under variable engine loads and rates. Low-temperature oxidation is usually treated as a two-stage process: cool and blue flames are followed by high-temperature oxidation (depending on the initial temperature and pressure, as well as on mixture composition). In real multi-stage oxidation and ignition processes, it is often difficult to select criteria for the occurrence of particular reactions, to recognize them and to formulate conditions of transition from one kind to another kind of reaction, including the thermal auto-ignition process. In addition to the physical processes, the chemistry of the reactions is very complex. The auto-ignition process of hydrocarbon fuels characterized by a large number of complex chemical reactions has been intensively investigated and reported in the literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1468087412445682">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1468087412445682"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1468087412445682"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1468087412445682">4</xref></sup> Hundreds of chemical species participate in thousands of reactions, the most important of which have been selected by Westbrook.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1468087412445682">4</xref></sup> These investigations clearly indicate that for hydrocarbon fuels, auto-ignition of the homogeneous charge and the ensuing combustion is a two-stage process in which low-temperature oxidation (cool- and blue-flame reactions) is followed by high-temperature reactions. As shown in the present paper, this process depends significantly on pressure and temperature. The ignition delay and corresponding low-temperature oxidation are key factors in understanding the process. Because of the time scale of the process (a few milliseconds and less), it is difficult to measure and analyse these processes under engine-like conditions. Cool flames are characteristic for low-temperature reactions, leading to two-stage ignition. At higher temperatures, single-stage ignition without the cool-flame process can be observed; however, as indicated in this paper, the effect of the gas pressure must also be considered. At lower temperatures (below the TI temperature), some mixtures react chemically (exothermally) with measurable heat release, including slow combustion and cool- and blue-flame reactions. These pre-ignition reactions have not yet developed to complete combustion via the thermal auto-ignition process; rather, the molecules break down and recombine to produce a variety of stable chemical compounds. These cool-flame and the following blue-flame reactions are very important in understanding the multi-stage ignition process.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1468087412445682">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1468087412445682"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1468087412445682"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1468087412445682"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1468087412445682"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1468087412445682"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1468087412445682">11</xref></sup> The heat-release rate of cool flames is fuel dependent and significantly influences the timing (delay) of TI. As indicated in this paper, the pre-ignition reactions control the auto-ignition process. Luck et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1468087412445682">12</xref></sup> concluded that the nature of the chemical steps involved in cool-flame oxidation plays an important role in the processes leading to auto-ignition in a motored engine. In their study, they indicated that these processes are independent of cylinder pressure. Results presented in the present paper, however, indicate significant influence of initial pressure on the pre-ignition (cool and blue flames) and thermal auto-ignition processes. Unlike in the present paper, in the literature, a low-temperature regime has been divided into three parts: slow combustion, cool flames and the negative temperature coefficient (NTC). By analogy to the NTC, which is a unique phenomenon characterized by decreasing reaction rate with increasing temperature, the present authors have introduced a positive pressure coefficient (PPC), indicating the pressure range of maximum reaction rate and minimum delay time mostly observed in the range of cool-flame reactions (see the concluding remarks).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1468087412445682">13</xref></sup> Both the NTC and PPC significantly influence the auto-ignition process. A complex of physical processes, such as fuel injection, spray formation and distribution in combustion chamber, atomization, simultaneous fuel vaporization and mixing with surrounding air, influence both the ignition delay and the combustion process itself. It must also be clearly noted that despite the very extensive experimental, numerical and theoretical investigations widely reported in the literature during the last two to three decades, the considered processes are still not fully understood. Significant progress made in modelling of the low- and high-temperature oxidation reactions, as well as ignition, requires extended support of very detailed experimental investigations, especially for complex real fuels. An intension of the present paper is to gain more insight into pre-ignition reactions, as well as ignition and combustion, for a real fuel under diesel-engine-like conditions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1468087412445682">
<title>Test conditions and model of investigated processes</title>
<sec id="section3-1468087412445682">
<title>Combustion chamber</title>
<p>For experimental investigation of complex chemical and physical processes of ignition and combustion under engine-like conditions, different types of simulators, such as rapid compression machines, have been applied.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1468087412445682">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1468087412445682"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1468087412445682"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1468087412445682"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1468087412445682"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1468087412445682">19</xref></sup> In order to perform detailed investigations on low- and high-temperature oxidation processes under engine-like conditions with a wide flexibility in setting the test conditions, a special high-pressure, high-temperature, constant volume and adiabatic combustion chamber has been built and equipped with a diesel common-rail (CR) injection system (commercially available diesel oil has been used), see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1468087412445682">Figure 1</xref>. A commercially available common-rail piezo-actuated seven-hole diesel injector has been used. The hole diameter was 143 µm and the spray angle was 158°.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Scheme of combustion chamber used in the present investigation: 1, diesel injector; 2, thermocouple; 3, pressure transducer; 4, high-pressure combustion chamber; 5, low-pressure isolation chamber; 6, heating element (wire); 7, electric contacts for electrical heating of the chamber; 8, inlet for air; 9, exhaust of burned gases. The combustion chamber diameter is 60 mm and the chamber height is 26 mm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The system simulates the thermodynamic conditions at the time instance of beginning of injection (corresponding to the nearly top dead centre (TDC) of compression in a real engine); however, the pressure and temperature can be chosen independently of one another.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1468087412445682">13</xref></sup></p>
<p>The following test conditions characterize the variability of the combustion chamber used in the present investigation:</p>
<list id="list1-1468087412445682" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>setting of the initial chamber temperature in the range T<sub>IB</sub>=293−1273 K;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>setting of the initial chamber pressure p<sub>IB</sub> in the range 1−20 bar (up to 50 bar possible);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>insulation of the thermal radiation of the chamber walls;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>different CR injectors can be used and variable injection parameters can be applied (injection pressure, duration, multiple injection, etc.);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>the CR injector is water cooled, preventing thermal overload in the chamber;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>application of a conventional spark plug for simulation of local ignition (if applied);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>control of the amount of supply air (or gas) for controlling the air excess ratio;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>varying the vertical location of the nozzle tip in the chamber;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>covering the combustion chamber with a thermally insulated external chamber;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>setting of the chamber temperature using an electrical heating system (electrical contacts using the electrodes of conventional spark plugs);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>equipping the combustion chamber with a high-resolution pressure transducer for measuring the pressure history;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>additionally equipping the combustion chamber with an endoscopic visualization system including charge-coupled devices or high-speed cameras.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>During the combustion process, the chamber is considered to be a closed system of constant volume. According to the first law of thermodynamics for a constant volume and an adiabatic system, the changes in the internal energy correspond directly to the heat-release rate in the chamber. Assuming that the combustion chamber during a short period of ignition and combustion is considered as an adiabatic system, any measured changes in the chamber pressure correspond directly to the released (or consumed) heat in the chamber. In this way, investigation of the pressure history (after the beginning of injection) allows analysis of corresponding heat-release and temperature changes in the chamber. By analogy, investigation of pressure gradient changes also allows the analysis of the heat-release rate. The experimental investigation presented in this paper uses a diesel-engine-like mixture formation and combustion conditions; however, no air motion in the form of swirl or squish have been applied for supporting the mixing process. The unpredictable air motion in the test chamber allows analysis of the pure effect of diesel sprays on the low- and high-temperature oxidation processes, as well as on the thermal auto-ignition process. In particular, the premixed part of the diesel-like combustion processes is analysed. Special attention is focussed on the analysis of process dynamics, especially on the heat-release rate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1468087412445682">
<title>Model of the heat-release process</title>
<p>It is well known in the literature that depending on the thermodynamic conditions (combustion chamber pressure and temperature), as well as on the chemical composition of the hydrocarbon fuel, there are two different mechanisms for ignition that may be selected:<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1468087412445682">2</xref></sup> a single-step and a multi-step process. For process analysis, a phenomenological model of multi-step oxidation (and ignition) has been constructed and used in the present analysis, as presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1468087412445682">Figure 2</xref>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1468087412445682">13</xref></sup></p>
<fig id="fig2-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Model of multi-step oxidation (and ignition) processes used for analysis of pressure history (top) and pressure gradient (bottom)</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>This figure indicates the characteristic points and investigated parameters that have been defined; however, the model does not include the range of ‘slow combustion’ that could be present in the very initial stage of the process. In this model, two measured parameters are investigated: pressure history and pressure gradient distribution, both as a function of time after injection begins. The whole process is analysed from time ‘zero’, defined as a trigger signal for the diesel injector (start of injection). At this point (point ‘IB’), the thermodynamic conditions in the combustion chamber are characterized by initial chamber pressure p<sub>IB</sub> and initial chamber temperature T<sub>IB</sub>. Additionally, a controlled mass of air is already trapped in the chamber. Starting from this point, the process is analysed in the form of chamber pressure (and corresponding pressure gradients) changes in time. Please note that in the investigated case of diesel-like test conditions, the mixture is not premixed and the chain of complex physical processes (e.g. fuel injection, spray formation and propagation, mixture formation, vaporization) occurs in addition to the investigated chemical processes (low-temperature oxidation, TI and high-temperature oxidation). Depending on the test conditions, it is often very difficult to select (recognize) individual processes and to formulate the criteria for transition from one to another process (e.g. transition from cool- to blue-flame reactions) is particularly complex. The authors hope that this paper will contribute to a better understanding of an overall heat-release process, especially through introducing new information and parameters, allowing very detailed analysis of individual processes, as well as formulating conditions for transition between them.</p>
<p>The following characteristic parameters are selected in this model.</p>
<list id="list2-1468087412445682" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>In general, the whole process consists of four characteristic phases: the initial phase concerning the start of injection and vaporization process until a minimum of the chamber pressure (period between points IB and A in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1468087412445682">Figure 2</xref>) is reached; the next phase describes cool-flame reactions (period between points A and C); the third phase relates to the blue-flame reactions (period between points C and TI); and the last phase correlates to the high-temperature oxidation (measured from the point of TI).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The duration (time window) of these phases is described by the characteristic duration time τ: τ<sub>v</sub> is the duration of the first phase (counted from the point of start of injection IB until the minimum pressure at point A is reached); τ<sub>CF</sub> is the duration of cool-flame reactions (counted from the point of minimum pressure A until transition to blue-flame reactions at point C). For further analysis, this period is divided into two time windows: τ<sub>1</sub> and τ<sub>2</sub>; τ<sub>BF</sub> is the duration of the blue-flame reactions (counted from point C until the point of TI); τ<sub>total</sub> is the total ignition delay consisting of both the chemical and physical parts (τ<sub>ch</sub>, τ<sub>phys</sub>); τ<sub>comb</sub> is the combustion duration defined by the duration of the heat-release process counted from the point of TI until complete release of the heat. In the present case, for the premixed part of diesel combustion, the maximum of the combustion pressure is taken into account (τ<sub>3</sub>).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The slope of the reaction curve corresponding to a particular kind of oxidation process represented by characteristic combustion regimes, e.g. cool flames, blue flames and high-temperature oxidation processes, is described by average pressure changes in bar/ms, characterizing the rate of the oxidation process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1468087412445682">Figure 3</xref>). sl<sub>CF</sub> is the slope of the cool-flame reactions; sl<sub>BF</sub> is the slope of the blue-flame reactions; and sl<sub>comb</sub> is the slope of high-temperature oxidation (heat release).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The angle α(slope, inclination) of the reaction curve corresponding to a particular oxidation process is described by characterizing the rate of the oxidation process; α represents the angle at which the mean slope of the reaction curve crosses the time axis.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The characteristic time t (delay time) of a particular phase of the process is counted from the zero-time point (injection begins at point IB). The characteristic time instances are measured by the location of points B, C and TI with respect to the zero-time line. t<sub>CF</sub> is the characteristic time of the cool-flame reactions (assuming the main part of the cool flames start from point B); t<sub>BF</sub> is the characteristic time of the blue-flame reactions; and t<sub>comb</sub> is the characteristic time of the high-temperature reactions.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Pressures changes (after fuel injection begins): Δp<sub>v</sub> is the negative pressure change in the chamber, characterized by the minimum pressure in the chamber resulting from the initial vaporization of the injected fuel being a difference between the minimum of the chamber pressure and the zero-pressure line. Δp<sub>CF</sub> is the pressure increase in the chamber resulting from the main part of the cool-flame oxidation reactions being a difference between the maximum of the chamber pressure during the cool-flame reactions and the zero-pressure line Δp<sub>BF</sub> is the pressure rise in the chamber resulting from the blue-flame oxidation reactions being a difference between the maximum of the chamber pressure during the blue-flame reactions and the end pressure of cool-flame reactions. Δp<sub>comb</sub> is the pressure increase in the chamber resulting from the high-temperature reactions (heat release) being a difference between the maximum of chamber pressure and the end pressure of the blue-flame reactions (point of TI).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The zero-pressure line corresponds to the initial chamber pressure p<sub>IB</sub> measured at the start of fuel injection (the following pressure changes are then measured in the chamber).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The zero-time point corresponds to the time instance at the start of fuel injection IB (the process is then measured in time after the beginning of injection).</p></list-item>
</list>
<fig id="fig3-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Definition of main slopes and indication of multi-step reactions.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Recognition of a particular process requires that during the process, enough heat is released, giving measurable pressure changes in the combustion chamber. Almost ‘no pressure change’ is interpreted as a ‘no heat release’ (no oxidation) process. This selection could be performed using recognizable changes in reaction rate in the pressure curve represented by a number of slopes.</p>
<p>The characteristic time describes the delay time after the beginning of injection of a given kind of reaction. Also important is consideration of the characteristic time ratio. In the following, this time ratio is defined as a dimensionless time ω. The transition from one reaction to another (e.g. from blue flames to high-temperature oxidation) requires temporal ‘synchronization’ of both reactions what requires close location of both delay times. Wide spacing of characteristic times for both kinds of reactions probably prevents this transition. The following criteria for transition from low-temperature to high-temperature oxidation processes have been selected: for a single-step ignition, ω∼1; for a multi-step ignition ω &gt; 1; for no thermal (auto) ignition ω &gt;&gt; 1.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1468087412445682">
<title>Measurement procedure and choice test conditions</title>
<p>The procedure for setting initial temperature T<sub>IB</sub> and initial pressure p<sub>IB</sub> in the combustion chamber is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1468087412445682">Figure 4</xref>. In a first step, a given mass of synthetic air at certain pressure p<sub>1</sub> is supplied to the chamber. After closing the intake system, the air inside the chamber is electrically heated to obtain the required temperature T<sub>IB</sub> and pressure p<sub>IB</sub>, defining (according to the above definition) the initial conditions for fuel injection. During the investigated heat-release process, the chamber can be considered to be adiabatic.</p>
<fig id="fig4-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Procedure of setting the initial temperature T<sub>IB</sub> and initial pressure p<sub>IB</sub> in combustion chamber.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>There are different test conditions used in the present investigation: constant initial temperature, constant initial pressure, constant air excess ratio and constant mass of injected fuel. The investigations have been performed in the range of initial temperatures T<sub>IB</sub> from 473 K to 973 K and initial pressures p<sub>IB</sub> from 1 bar to 20 bar. A constant injection pressure (600 bar) of a CR diesel injection system equipped with a six-hole nozzle has been used. The diesel injector, as well as the pressure transducer, is water cooled. The combination of these thermodynamic and injection conditions results in almost 80 selected measurement points used in the present investigation.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1468087412445682">
<title>Characteristics of low- and high-temperature oxidation processes</title>
<sec id="section7-1468087412445682">
<title>Overall description of the processes</title>
<p>As described above, it is clear that the combination of such variable test conditions results in different kinds of reactions after injection starts with different rates and delay times. Additionally, a number of reactions is represented by a number of slopes identified in pressure history of the investigated heat-release process. After analysing all investigated test conditions and selected parameters describing the process, it was possible to establish overall characteristics of a non-premixed diesel-like process, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1468087412445682">Figure 5</xref>. This diagram is presented in a qualitative form and, in a first approximation, the results are limited to the investigated pressures p<sub>IB</sub>, temperatures T<sub>IB</sub> and air excess ratios λ, as well as amounts of injected fuel. There are five characteristic regions of the process that have been selected.</p>
<fig id="fig5-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Overall characteristics of low- and high-temperature oxidation processes for non-premixed diesel-like conditions (description in text).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<list id="list3-1468087412445682" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Region 1</italic>. The process at low initial pressures p<sub>IB</sub> in a wide range of initial temperatures T<sub>IB</sub> is characterized by very long delay times (∼20 ms), very low reaction rates (&lt;1 bar/ms), and three slopes are recognizable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1468087412445682">Figure 6(a)</xref> shows an example measurement point).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Region 2.</italic> The process at low initial temperatures T<sub>IB</sub> in a wide range of initial pressures p<sub>IB</sub> is characterized by very long delay times ( &gt; 20 ms), very low reaction rates (&lt;1 bar/ms), and a single slope is recognizable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1468087412445682">Figure 6(b)</xref> shows an example measurement point).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Region 3.</italic> The process at middle initial pressures p<sub>IB</sub> and higher initial temperatures T<sub>IB</sub> is characterized by shorter delay times (&lt;10 ms), middle reaction rates (∼5 bar/ms), and three slopes are recognizable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1468087412445682">Figure 6(c)</xref> shows an example measurement point).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Region 4.</italic> The process at middle initial temperatures T<sub>IB</sub> and at higher initial pressures p<sub>IB</sub> is characterized by shorter delay times (&lt;10 ms), middle reaction rates (&lt;10 bar/ms), and two slopes are recognizable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1468087412445682">Figure 6(d)</xref> shows an example measurement point).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Region 5.</italic> The process at high initial pressures p<sub>IB</sub> and high initial temperatures T<sub>IB</sub> is characterized by short delay times (&lt;2 ms), high reaction rates ( &gt; 20 bar/ms), and two slopes are recognizable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1468087412445682">Figure 6(e)</xref> shows an example measurement point).</p></list-item>
</list>
<fig id="fig6-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Overall pressure history (left) and pressure history in initial phase of the process (right) of points located in the different regions of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1468087412445682">Figure 5</xref>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1468087412445682">Figure 5</xref> is presented in a qualitative form because the transition from one region to another cannot be exactly reconstructed. It is interesting is observe that by increasing the initial pressure p<sub>IB</sub> and initial temperature T<sub>IB</sub>, the heat-release process changes its character (single step and multi-step) and its dynamics. In addition, the delay time varies, and reduces with increasing initial thermodynamic conditions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1468087412445682">
<title>Process description at selected conditions</title>
<p>In order to observe the transition from one region to another, the process will be analysed under selected test conditions. At first, the process is analysed at a constant initial chamber temperature T<sub>IB</sub>=573 K and variable initial pressures p<sub>IB</sub>. The pressure increase in the chamber indicates an ‘irregular’ distribution of curves with respect to variations of the initial chamber pressure p<sub>IB</sub>. The higher the chamber pressure, the faster the reactions occur; however, this is not a rule at all pressures higher than 6 bar. Different process dynamics at different initial pressures p<sub>IB</sub> can be observed in a diagram plotted with a limited pressure axis (limited to 2 bar), as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1468087412445682">Figure 7</xref>. Three characteristic ranges can be selected: very low pressures characterized by very slow reactions (probably a slow combustion range); middle pressures characterized by two-step reactions; and high initial pressures characterized by single-step reactions. Analysis of the corresponding delay time distribution as a function of pressure p<sub>IB</sub> shows a very unique ‘U’-like type distribution, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1468087412445682">Figure 8</xref>. As indicated in this figure, in the selected range of pressures p<sub>IB</sub>, the delay time of the low-temperature oxidation process is the shortest, and the rate of these reactions is the highest. There are different characteristic ranges of the process to be selected at T<sub>IB</sub> = 573 K:</p>
<fig id="fig7-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Pressure history distributions plotted over a limited range of pressure changes for T<sub>IB</sub>=573 K and variable pressure at p<sub>IB</sub> (λ=1.5=const.).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig8-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of delay time for T<sub>IB</sub>=573 K as a function of initial pressure p<sub>IB</sub> (represents PPC) (λ=1.5=const.).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig8.tif"/>
</fig>
<list id="list4-1468087412445682" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>lowest pressure p<sub>IB</sub>=2.9 bar: the delay time is very long, of the order of 250 ms;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>slightly higher pressures p<sub>IB</sub> &lt; 5 bar: the delay time is reduced to approximately 50 ms, with increasing chamber pressure the delay time rapidly decrease;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>at pressure p<sub>IB</sub>=5 bar: the delay time is the shortest (∼40 ms);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>pressures in the range p<sub>IB</sub>=5 bar to 15 bar: the delay time is short, with a low-level plateaux;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>the highest pressures p<sub>IB</sub> &gt;  18 bar: delay time again increases ( &gt; 100 ms).</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Further increases of pressure p<sub>IB</sub> increase the delay time and decrease the reaction rate. By analogy to an NTC, the authors have defined this range of short delay time as a PPC. The PPC is not only temperature specific, and can be observed at various temperatures. More detailed investigation of the transition from one kind of reaction to another is necessary. At T<sub>IB</sub> higher than 623 K, this concave (U-type distribution) character of delay time distribution is not observed anymore, and a parabolic-like (not U-type) distribution of delay time is indicated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-1468087412445682">Figure 9</xref>). At the highest temperatures (T<sub>IB</sub>=923K and 973K), the delay time slightly (almost linearly) decreases with increasing the chamber pressure.</p>
<fig id="fig9-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 9.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of delay time t for variable temperature T<sub>IB</sub> as a function of initial pressure p<sub>IB</sub> (λ=1.5=const.).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig9.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Next, the process is investigated at a constant and high pressure, p<sub>IB</sub>=18 bar, over a wide range of initial temperatures T<sub>IB</sub>, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-1468087412445682">Figure 10</xref>. The heat-release process, depending on the temperature, crosses regions 2, 4 and 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1468087412445682">Figure 5</xref>). The following characteristic parts of the process have been selected:</p>
<fig id="fig10-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 10.</label>
<caption>
<p>Pressure history distributions at constant initial chamber pressure p<sub>IB</sub>=18 bar for variable temperature T<sub>IB</sub> and a constant amount of injected fuel m<sub>fuel</sub>=23.8 mg (λ varies from 2.5 at 573 K to 1.5 at 973 K).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig10.tif"/>
</fig>
<list id="list5-1468087412445682" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>T<sub>IB</sub>=573 K: the delay time is very long (∼60 ms) and the reaction rate is low (not included in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-1468087412445682">Figure 10</xref>);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>T<sub>IB</sub>=623 K: the delay time is shorter (∼20 ms) and the reaction rate is higher;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>T<sub>IB</sub>=673 K: the delay time is shorter (∼7 ms) and the reaction rate is slightly higher;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>T<sub>IB</sub>=723 K: the delay time is shorter (∼3 ms) and the reaction rate is slightly higher;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>723 K &lt; T<sub>IB</sub> &lt; 873 K: the delay time is of the order of 2 ms and the reaction rate only slightly changes;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>873 K ≤ T<sub>IB</sub> &lt; 973 K: the delay time is of the order of 1.5 ms and the reaction rate only slightly changes;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>T<sub>IB</sub> &gt;  973 K: the delay time is shortened to the level below 1.5 ms and the reaction rate practically does not change.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The delay time distribution at p<sub>IB</sub>=18 bar as a function of the initial chamber temperature T<sub>IB</sub> is plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-1468087412445682">Figure 11</xref>. Because of the very long delay time (∼66 ms) of the process at the lowest chamber temperature T<sub>IB</sub>=573 K, the lower temperature limit of this diagram has been set at T<sub>IB</sub>=623 K. The higher the chamber temperature, the shorter the delay time; however, there is a range of temperatures, T<sub>IB</sub> &lt; 773 K, where this time gradually (almost linearly) decreases with increasing initial chamber temperature. At higher temperatures, the delay time t<sub>comb</sub> is only weakly temperature dependent and reaches values around the 2 ms level. Similar behaviour is observed for the delay time t<sub>CF</sub>. As indicated in this figure, at high chamber pressure, the dimensionless time ω is almost constant at the level of ω∼1.2, indicating TI process. As marked in this figure, increasing the chamber temperature at constant pressure (p<sub>IB</sub>=18 bar) changes the localization of the process in the characteristic ranges (as defined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1468087412445682">Figure 5</xref>) from region 2 to region 5. There is a transition from a slow and highly delayed reaction (region 2) to a very fast and short delayed heat-release process (region 5). Analysis of reaction rates, represented by the reaction slope as a function of temperature T<sub>IB</sub>, supports this observation (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-1468087412445682">Figure 12</xref>). The slope increases with increasing temperature, reaching its maximum of 30 bar/ms at T<sub>IB</sub>=873 K. At even higher temperatures, the reaction rate is reduced to approximately 20 bar/ms. At the lowest investigated temperatures (∼573 K), the slope reduces to almost zero, indicating possible prevention from the TI process.</p>
<fig id="fig11-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 11.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of characteristic time after beginning of injection at constant chamber pressure p<sub>IB</sub>=18 bar for variable initial temperature T<sub>IB</sub>, for a constant amount of injected fuel m<sub>fuel</sub>=23.8 mg (λ varies from 2.5 at 573 K to 1.5 at 973 K).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig11.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig12-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 12.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of reaction rate after beginning of injection at constant chamber pressure p<sub>IB</sub>=18 bar for variable initial temperature T<sub>IB</sub> for a constant amount of injected fuel m<sub>fuel</sub>=23.8 mg (λ varies from 2.5 at 573 K to 1.5 at 973 K).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig12.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In the following, a process is investigated under test conditions characterized by a constant air excess ratio and constant amount of injected fuel at various temperatures T<sub>IB</sub> and variable pressures p<sub>IB</sub>, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-1468087412445682">Figure 13</xref>. This is especially important for understanding the influence of the amount of injected fuel on low- and high-temperature oxidation processes. According to the available test conditions, the pressure p<sub>IB</sub> and temperature T<sub>IB</sub> are not constant for constant λ and m<sub>fuel</sub>. Pressure distribution after beginning of injection shows different characteristic regimes. A range of low temperatures (T<sub>IB</sub>∼573 K) is characterized by very long delay times, much longer than 30ms. The process accelerates with increasing temperature and pressure. An initial part of the process (during τ<sub>v</sub>) is independent of the chamber pressure p<sub>IB</sub> and temperature T<sub>IB</sub>, and only duration of this process increases with reducing temperature and corresponding chamber pressure. In the middle range of temperatures, the pressure distribution indicates a possible multi-step oxidation process characterized by three slopes, and at high temperatures, two slopes can be recognized. The characteristic time t rapidly decreases with both increasing temperature T<sub>IB</sub> and increasing chamber pressure p<sub>IB</sub>, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-1468087412445682">Figure 14</xref>. The process crosses through different regimes with different characteristics. At temperatures of 673 K and 723 K, this delay time is reduced to approximately 4−5 ms. At temperatures 773 K and 823 K, this time is again reduced to approximately 2 ms. At high temperatures T<sub>IB</sub> &gt; 873 K, the delay time is very short (∼1 ms). The maximum of the pressure distribution is located at T<sub>IB</sub>=823 K. Analysis of the reaction rate shows that the reaction rate gradually increases with increasing chamber temperature T<sub>IB</sub>, and by transition from region 4 to region 3, a local plateaux at T<sub>IB</sub>=773−823 K is observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-1468087412445682">Figure 15</xref>). This transition can also be observed by analysis of the process at a constant initial chamber temperature T<sub>IB</sub>=923 K and variable initial pressure p<sub>IB</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig16-1468087412445682">Figure 16</xref>). This diagram presents three pressure chamber histories (top) and pressure gradient changes (bottom) in time after fuel injection begins. The higher the chamber pressure p<sub>IB</sub>, the shorter the delay time for heat release and the higher the increase of corresponding chamber pressure. The heat-release rate represented by the slope of the curves also increases with increasing p<sub>IB</sub>. At low chamber pressure (p<sub>IB</sub>=5 bar), the pressure gradient distribution is characterized by a single peak located late after fuel injection begins (6 ms after trigger signal). At chamber pressures of the order of 10 bar, a bi-modal pressure gradient distribution is observed, indicating a multi-step ignition process. At a high chamber pressure (19 bar), the first pressure gradient peak is significantly reduced (not fully ‘developed’) followed by a main maximum of the distribution. A peak that is not fully developed means that the ‘growing part’ of the distribution is clearly indicated, but the ‘falling’ part of the peak is not visible anymore; however, this local maximum of the distribution is still recognizable. In our opinion, this behaviour suggests transition from a multi-step to a single-step ignition process at high chamber pressures p<sub>IB</sub>, corresponding to the transition from region 3 to region 5.</p>
<fig id="fig13-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 13.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of pressure history after beginning of injection for variable initial temperature T<sub>IB</sub> and chamber pressure p<sub>IB</sub>, for a constant amount of injected fuel m<sub>fuel</sub>=26.4 mg and constant air excess ratio λ=1.5.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig13.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig14-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 14.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of delay time t after beginning of injection as a function of initial temperature T<sub>IB</sub>, for variable chamber pressure p<sub>IB</sub> and constant amount of injected fuel m<sub>fuel</sub>=26.4 mg (λ=1.5).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig14.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig15-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 15.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of reaction rate after beginning of injection as a function of initial temperature T<sub>IB</sub>, for variable chamber pressure p<sub>IB</sub> and constant amount of injected fuel m<sub>fuel</sub>=26.4 mg (λ=1.5).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig15.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig16-1468087412445682" position="float">
<label>Figure 16.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of pressure history (top) and pressure gradient (bottom) after beginning of injection at constant initial temperature T<sub>IB</sub>=923 K, for selected chamber pressures p<sub>IB</sub> at constant air excess ratio λ=1.5.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1468087412445682-fig16.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1468087412445682">
<title>Concluding remarks</title>
<p>Low- and high-temperature oxidation processes, including thermal auto-ignition under diesel-engine-like conditions (non-premixed mixture), have been investigated. Neither swirl nor squish have been used for promoting the mixing processes. The investigated processes are very complex in nature and depend on significantly temperature and pressure. A phenomenological model has been presented and used in the reported investigation, allowing the selection of individual processes under investigation. The processes have been investigated under different test conditions: at constant temperatures, at constant pressures, at constant air excess ratios, as well as for a constant mass of injected fuel. There are five characteristic regions of the process, characterized by different delay times, reaction rates and number of recognizable oxidation reactions. Region 1 corresponds to process occurring at low initial pressures p<sub>IB</sub> in a wide range of initial temperatures T<sub>IB</sub>, characterized by very long delay times, very low reaction rates, and with three recognizable oxidation reactions represented by three slopes in the pressure history curve. In region 2, corresponding to low initial temperatures T<sub>IB</sub> in a wide range of initial pressures p<sub>IB</sub>, the process is characterized by very long delay times, very low reaction rates, and a single-step reaction is recognizable. In region 3, corresponding to middle initial pressures p<sub>IB</sub> and higher initial temperatures T<sub>IB</sub>, the investigated process is characterized by shorter delay times, middle reaction rates, and a multi-step reaction represented by three slopes occurs. Processes occurring in region 4 located at middle initial temperatures T<sub>IB</sub> and at higher initial pressures p<sub>IB</sub>, are characterized by shorter delay times, middle reaction rates, and two slopes are recognizable. Region 5 corresponds to high initial pressures p<sub>IB</sub> and high initial temperatures T<sub>IB</sub>, and the investigated processes are characterized by short delay times, high reaction rates, and with two slopes in the pressure history. By analogy to an NTC (as given in the literature), the authors have introduced a PPC. The PPC indicates that in a selected range of pressures p<sub>IB</sub>, the delay time of the low-temperature oxidation processes is the shortest, and the rate of these reactions is the highest. Further increasing the pressure behind the PPC range increases the delay time and decreases the reaction rate. The PPC has been observed at lower temperatures (mostly corresponding to cool-flame reactions and transition to blue flames). Generally, the ignition delay time reduces with increasing chamber temperature and pressure. The effect of gas temperature depends significantly on the chamber pressure. Slow reactions are characterized by delay times of the order of many tens to even hundreds of milliseconds, down to less than 1 ms at high temperatures and high pressures. There is only a limited effect of the chamber pressure and temperature on the initial phase of the process, especially on the fuel vaporization rate and the resulting air–fuel mixture (no swirl or squish for promoting mixing with air).</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This work was supported by the German Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF) and the German Federation of Industrial Research Associations (AiF).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1468087412445682">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heywood</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Combustion engine fundamentals</source>. <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>, <year>1988</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1468087412445682">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldsborough</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Autoignition of lean iso-octane-air mixtures in an RCEM</article-title>. In: <conf-name>2007 Fall Meeting of the Western States of the Combustion Institute</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Sandia National Laboratories Livermore</conf-loc>, <conf-date>16–17 October</conf-date> <year>2007</year>, paper no. 07F-62.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1468087412445682">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirsch</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The autoignition of hydrocarbon fuels at high temperatures and pressures fitting of a mathematical model</article-title>. <source>Combust Flame</source> <year>1977</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1468087412445682">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Westbrook</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Chemical kinetics of hydrocarbon ignition in practical combustion systems</article-title>. <source>Proc Combust Inst</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1563</fpage>–<lpage>1577</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1468087412445682">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cullis</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The cool-flame oxidation of 3-methylpentane</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond A</source> <year>1972</year>; <volume>329</volume>: <fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1468087412445682">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Felton</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Low-temperature oxidation in a stirred flow reactor. I. Propane</article-title>. <source>Combust Flame</source> <year>1974</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1468087412445682">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Affens</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sheinson</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Autoignition: importance of the cool flame in the two-stage process</article-title>. <source>Loss Prev</source> <year>1980</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1468087412445682">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Caprio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Insola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lignola</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Isobutane cool flames in a CSTR: the behavior dependence on temperature and residence time</article-title>. <source>Combust Flame</source> <year>1981</year>; <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1468087412445682">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gaffuri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Faravelli</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ranzi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comprehensive kinetic model for the low-temperature oxidation of hydrocarbons</article-title>. <source>Am Inst Chem Engng J</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>1278</fpage>–<lpage>1286</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1468087412445682">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="thesis">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gitzinger</surname><given-names>H-P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Nutzung kalter flammen fuer die Gemischbildung zur Realisierung eines Strahlungsbrenners fuer flussige brennstoffe. Use of cool flames for the air/fuel mixture for the realization of a burner for liquid fuels</source>. PhD Thesis, <publisher-name>RWTH Aachen</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Germany</publisher-loc>, <year>1999</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1468087412445682">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pearlman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Low-temperature oxidation reactions and cool flames at earth and reduced gravity</article-title>. <source>Combust Flame</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>393</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1468087412445682">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luck</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Desty</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Study of the combustion of n-heptane in an engine using a novel high-speed sampling technique</article-title>. <source>Proc Combust Inst</source> <year>1973</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>512</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1468087412445682">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weclas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cypris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Combustion of diesel sprays under real-engine like conditions: analysis of low- and high-temperature oxidation processes</article-title>. In: <conf-name>ILASS – Europe 2010, 23rd Annual Conference on Liquid Atomization and Spray Systems</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Brno, Czech Republic</conf-loc>, <conf-date>September 2010</conf-date>, paper no. ID 39.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1468087412445682">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Halford-Maw</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Fundamental features of hydrocarbon autoignition in a rapid compression machine</article-title>. <source>Combust Flame</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1468087412445682">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Minetti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carlier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ribaucour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A rapid compression machine investigation of oxidation and auto-ignition of n-heptane: measurements and modelling</article-title>. <source>Combust Flame</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1468087412445682">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keck</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Ignition delays for iso-octane: measurement using a rapid compression machine and prediction using a reduced chemical kinetic model</article-title>. SAE paper 912553, <year>1991</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1468087412445682">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zigler</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Demonstration of a free-piston rapid compression facility for the study of high temperature combustion phenomena</article-title>. <source>Combust Flame</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>365</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1468087412445682">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wuermel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simmie</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Studying the chemistry of HCCI in rapid compression machines</article-title>. <source>Int J Veh Des</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1468087412445682">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mittal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A rapid compression machine for chemical kinetics studies at elevated pressures and temperatures</article-title>. <source>Combust Sci Technol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>179</volume>: <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>530</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>