<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">APA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spapa</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Am Psychoanal Assoc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0003-0651</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1941-2460</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0003065112465646</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0003065112465646</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: What Do Patients Want? Psychoanalytic Perspectives from the Couch</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>Janet M.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0003065112465646">Janet M. Mooney 160 North Craig Street, Suite 218 Pittsburgh, PA 15213 E-mail: <email>jmooneymsw@verizon.net</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>60</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>1329</fpage>
<lpage>1333</lpage>
<product><source>What Do Patients Want? Psychoanalytic Perspectives from the Couch</source>. By <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>Christine A. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Karnac Books</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>, <page-count count="xlii"/> + <page-count count="198"/> pp., <price>$37.95</price> paperback.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Psychoanalytic Association 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Psychoanalytic Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Beginning with the very title of her book, <italic>What Do Patients Want? Psychoanalytic Perspectives from the Couch</italic> (with its reference to Freud’s question, “What do women want?”), Christine Hill signals her intent to validate the perspective of the patient and to have us look at psychoanalysis through the eyes of the patient on the couch. Like the feminists who answered Freud’s question about women by first challenging the phallocentricity of classical psychoanalysis, Hill challenges the analyst-centered perspective of psychoanalysis and its process and outcome research. After reviewing the relevant research literature, as well as published accounts of personal and training analyses, she proceeds to describe the treatment experiences of eighteen former analysands whom she interviewed for her study. Alongside her very sensitive telling of those experiences, she thoughtfully juxtaposes the theoretical and technical issues raised by their reports, providing analysts a close-up view of themselves and their work.</p>
<p>Hill conducted her qualitative study in Australia, where she interviewed eleven men and seven women, thirteen of whom were psychotherapists relatively familiar with the workings of psychoanalysis. Her method was, in a sense, the method of psychoanalysis itself: listening. Her aim was to determine which factors facilitated or impeded psychoanalysis and which led to success or failure from the patient’s point of view. She organized their experiences around themes that emerged again and again in the interviews, much as a psychoanalyst organizes his data around repetitive themes. Hill’s training as a psychoanalytic psychotherapist helped her listen in this way, but she does so here with a focus—not on the patient, but on the patient’s experience of psychoanalysis.</p>
<p>In her introductory chapter, she reviews a number of concepts central to psychoanalysis (transference, countertransference, interpretation, neutrality) and nicely sets the foundation for her later chapters, especially for readers unfamiliar with analytic theory. This chapter offers a well-integrated review of basic concepts that will be of use to both psychoanalytic candidates and students of psychoanalytic psychotherapy. Here and throughout, Hill’s writing is straightforward, clear, and free of technical jargon; her style is refreshingly open.</p>
<p>Organizing her chapters chronologically, according to the progression of a psychoanalysis, gives Hill an organic way of taking the reader on a psychoanalytic journey, as she considers and reconsiders issues of importance to these eighteen patients. In her chapter on beginning the analysis, for example, we learn that the opening phase of analysis was not only of crucial importance in setting the tone of the analytic relationship but that the analyst’s handling of this phase was a major determinant of the success or failure of the analysis. Some patients felt liberated by the opportunity to free associate in the presence of an attuned and capable analyst, and these same patients ultimately found their treatments to be enormously enriching. By contrast, those who found the opening phase a bizarre and uncomfortable experience, with a silent analyst who explained little about the process, later considered the phase a prelude to what overall was an unsatisfactory analysis.</p>
<p>Referring to Akhtar’s work on turning points in psychotherapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0003065112465646">2009</xref>), Hill finds further validation for her participants’ conclusion that treatment failures often have their roots in the mishandling of the opening phase. Her findings give us good reason to reexamine our handling of this critical phase of treatment, as she and her participants underscore the importance of educating the patient about the process, listening to the patient’s expectations, and understanding how and why psychoanalysis (or a particular analyst) was chosen.</p>
<p>Two of Hill’s chapters are devoted to transference (the term was not necessarily used by the study participants, but the phenomenon was described by them in relating their experiences). According to Hill, these patients had a good understanding of the concept, recognizing that working transference issues through can bring about change, while failure to work them through can leave one trapped in endless repetitions. One patient described how her analyst’s attunement and flexibility lessened her terror over what was coming to life in the transference and thereby allowed her to recover memories she would not have otherwise. Another patient described his analyst’s “courage” and “sensitivity” (p. 42) in interpreting a homosexual fantasy about him, which initially felt too shocking to even try to understand. However, five of the eighteen patients found their analyst unable to successfully use the transference. One patient, for example, had two analyses but felt neither analyst was able to work with him in the transference. His first analyst was experienced as silent and withholding, while the second seemed to have become caught up in the transference, actually accusing the patient of being boring and causing him to fall asleep. Another patient found her analyst’s references to transference so predictable that they became devoid of meaning. Again and again, these patients detailed how the skilled handling of transference-countertransference facilitated a successful analysis, while its unskilled handling made for a mediocre or failed analysis.</p>
<p>In a special chapter on paternal transference, a theme that emerged often in the patient interviews, Hill reports that the success or failure to work through the father transference was related to the analyst’s capacity to be emotionally present. One patient felt that his analyst did better when he stepped outside of what appeared to be the rigidity of his theory. One of the many psychoanalytic ideas Hill refers to in this chapter is Herzog’s concept of father hunger (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0003065112465646">2001</xref>), a concept that seems to capture the needs and longings of those among the participants who were struggling to work through feelings related to their fathers. Patients concluded that it was the personal qualities of the analyst that facilitated the working through of their feelings. One patient in particular reported how helpful it was to have an analyst capable of withstanding his putdowns, rather than retaliating as his father had.</p>
<p>Hill’s chapter on engagement is especially alive with rich material, full of examples of patients’ experiences of engagement, or its lack, intertwined with discussions of the object relations concepts of containment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0003065112465646">Bion 1959</xref>) and the holding environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0003065112465646">Winnicott 1965</xref>). She also elaborates on two other concepts of particular relevance to these patients’ reports: psychological space as defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0003065112465646">Casement (2002)</xref> and physical space, a concept defined by Hill as akin to the concept of the frame but including the physical space of the office and its capacity to facilitate or impede the process. One patient explained her need to be engaged in such a way that she had to be “welded” to the analyst in order to “exist” (p. 62). Her analyst’s ability to connect with what she considered her infantile state seemed to facilitate her development so that eventually she felt she was being kept in mind even during separations. In contrast was the patient who felt that his analyst was chronically unable to receive the material he brought to session and that in response he tried to fit in with the analyst. Sadly, some patients felt no sense of connection, and they specifically linked this to the personality characteristics they believed their analysts had brought to the analytic situation.</p>
<p>Far from espousing the simplistic notion that modern analysts are supportive and therefore more helpful than traditional analysts, Hill demonstrates that patients want analysts who are able to handle disturbing material, including aggression. These analysands were highly satisfied when their hostilities were handled, their dreams, defenses, and transferences were interpreted, and their powerful past experiences were brought forward in an atmosphere of safety with an analyst who was reliably attuned, nonjudgmental, and present to the depth of the patient’s struggles. These patients did not want analysts they perceived as remote, disempowering, rigid, or promoting their own agenda. But they did not shy away from the intensity and struggle of the process, nor did they want a watered-down version of analysis. These analysands embraced basic psychoanalytic principles and were disappointed when their analysts failed to adhere to them.</p>
<p>While Hill and the study participants see the personality of the analyst as the major obstacle to the delivery of a good analysis, it seems to me that the concept of personality does not entirely cover the phenomenon they have encountered. I say this because it is difficult to fully separate the human qualities of the analyst from the analyst’s <italic>knowledge</italic>. Analytic knowledge is in the body, which makes it very different from intellectual knowing. The extent to which the analyst’s knowledge is internalized and integrated within himself determines his ability to understand and process patient material, sometimes very primitive material. To put it another way, analytic knowledge should change the analyst, just as analysis aims to change the patient. Additionally, analysts, regardless of personality, might have difficulty listening to certain kinds of transferences because of an actual lack in their training. Analysts trained to treat oedipal conflicts, for example, might not be fully prepared to handle more primitive preoedipal or narcissistic transferences, while those whose training emphasized earlier transferences might fall short when it comes to hearing oedipal material. To my reading, Hill’s participants want analysts who are prepared to handle the complexities of all these transferences, and they want analysts who are ready to make use of consultation when they encounter the inevitable gaps in their analytic knowledge.</p>
<p>In a paper addressing gaps in the analyst’s knowledge, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0003065112465646">Kantrowitz (1992)</xref> discusses how consultation helped her with a problematic counter- transference to a patient’s helplessness, a countertransference she thought was related to her personal style. What she discovered was that her countertransference stemmed from both an “educational deficit” and a “dynamic characterological source” (p. 191). Hill does a remarkable job of pointing us in the direction of identifying and remedying our gaps in knowledge, and in her later chapters reminds us of the potentially long-lasting negative consequences for the patient when we as analysts fail to do so.</p>
<p>Hill’s is a contemporary voice that values the viewpoint of the patient without attacking the core concepts of psychoanalytic theory. As she takes us on her journey of discovering the patient’s point of view, we are generously invited into the experiences of these former analysands, some of whom found analysis to be life-changing, others disappointing, and a few, damaging. Ultimately, Hill’s research validates psychoanalytic ideas and the high level of skill required for conducting psychoanalysis. It also demonstrates the need for better training methods, as well as for consultation throughout the analyst’s career. Hill’s book offers us a close-up view of the analyst from the perspective of the patient, a summary of the technical and theoretical issues involved at each stage of the analytic process, and a discussion of what it means to be fully engaged as an analyst.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0003065112465646">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Turning Points in Dynamic Psychotherapy: Initial Assessment, Boundaries, Money, Disruptions and Suicidal Crises</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Karnac Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0003065112465646">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bion</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1959</year>). <article-title>Attacks on linking</article-title>. In <source>Second Thoughts: Selected Papers on Psychoanalysis</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Karnac Books</publisher-name>, <year>1984</year>, pp. <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0003065112465646">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Casement</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Learning from Our Mistakes: Beyond Dogma in Psychoanalysis and Psychotherapy</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0003065112465646">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Father Hunger: Explorations with Adults and Children</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Analytic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0003065112465646">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kantrowitz</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>The analyst’s style and its impact on the analytic process: Overcoming a patient-analyst stalemate</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association</source> <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0003065112465646">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Winnicott</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1965</year>). <source>The Maturational Processes and the Facilitating Environment: Studies in the Theory of Emotional Development</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hogarth Press / Institute of Psychoanalysis</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>