<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EVI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spevi</journal-id>
<journal-title>Evaluation</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1356-3890</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7153</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1356389013493840</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1356389013493840</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Aid Effectiveness and Governance Reforms: Applying realist principles to a complex synthesis across varied cases</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Betts</surname><given-names>Julia</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1356389013493840">IOD PARC Ltd, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1356389013493840">Julia Betts, 16–26 Forth Street, Edinburgh EH1 3LH, UK. Email: <email>julia@iodparc.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: What can case studies do?</issue-title>
<fpage>249</fpage>
<lpage>268</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article describes an attempt to synthesize results from four major multi-partner evaluations applying a realist approach. The article argues that synthesizing the results of these four major evaluations proved possible applying (part of) a realistic approach, and also reveals some of the limitations of the realist model as experienced by a very complex synthesis exercise. The researchers identify the concepts and approaches of the realist model that provided a supportive framework for synthesizing a very broad and diverse range of evidence, and which helped convert the findings into accessible outputs to support policy decisions. Lessons learned are extracted in the hope of supporting others facing similar tasks.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>aid effectiveness</kwd>
<kwd>case study</kwd>
<kwd>complex synthesis</kwd>
<kwd>governance</kwd>
<kwd>realist</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1356389013493840" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Recent years have seen governance reforms move centre stage in aid effectiveness debates. The pace of change has been slow, however, and there has been widespread disagreement about the best ways for countries to manage reform.</p>
<p>To examine the evidence on progress in key areas of investment since 2009, donors and partner countries jointly commissioned four major international evaluations during 2010 and 2011. These reported on themes of: Public Sector Governance Reform; the Paris Declaration on Aid Effectiveness; the use of Budget Support; and Donor Support to Anti-Corruption. These were large-scale international studies; combined, they covered 26 aid-recipient countries.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1356389013493840">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>Subsequently, the OECD DAC’s Evaluation Network, with support from DANIDA, commissioned a synthesis exercise to extract the key areas of progress and learning to date. The synthesis was intended to inform discussions leading up to and arising at the High Level Forum on development effectiveness in Busan in November 2011 and to generate learning for use in policy discussions thereafter. Explicitly, its purpose was:
<disp-quote>
<p>to review and summarise findings and lessons from across the relevant studies into a series of topical Evaluation Insight Briefs and feed these in to policy discussions through a high-level international policy seminar and other channels.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1356389013493840">2</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>This article will describe a real-world experience of an approach to, and learning from, an attempt at complex synthesis of multi-country evaluation studies – here considered ‘cases’ – which themselves included synthesis reports. In doing so, it will explore the extent to which recent developments in the realist synthesis field were found to be relevant to an exercise that sought to balance a systematic and rigorous approach with a directive from commissioners to be ‘policy-relevant’.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1356389013493840">
<title>Approaches to synthesis</title>
<p>The past few years have witnessed growing interest in evidence syntheses as an information mechanism for policy reforms. In particular, demand has grown for syntheses that shed light on where, how, under what conditions, and with what results, social or economic interventions have worked (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1356389013493840">Greenhalgh et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1356389013493840">Lavis, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1356389013493840">Pawson et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>At the same time, the range of methods available for synthesizing across cases has grown considerably. Barnett-Page and Thomas for example summarize the profusion of approaches available, mainly deriving from the health field, which include meta-ethnography, approaches drawing on grounded theory, thematic synthesis, meta-study or meta-analysis, and critical interpretive synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1356389013493840">Barnett-Page and Thomas, 2009</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1356389013493840">Dixon-Woods et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>But the profusion of terms offers little insight into which method might be most appropriate for marshalling a broad range of evidence on aid effectiveness and governance reforms into a coherent synthesis, with the aim of influencing policy reform. In particular, little insight is available on how to tackle a synthesis exercise where the component ‘cases’ consist of evaluation reports addressing different objects within varied contexts. Yet, in the real world of development evaluation, the increasing trend is for larger-scale, cross-national studies of a particular object, often commissioned by multiple agencies jointly, and with an associated synthesis report as the overarching output – as the component studies for this exercise testify.</p>
<p>Clarifying a suitable approach is critical, therefore, if we are to be able to source and analyse evidence across cases from the sorts of increasingly complex initiatives that international aid and development presents. For this particular exercise, an approach was needed that would enable the synthesis of a wide range of evaluative evidence across four large areas of aid effectiveness and governance reforms – and in doing so, inform policymakers’ understandings of whether and how the many billions of dollars expended on aid effectiveness and governance reforms have created change, and with what results.</p>
<p>This article consequently describes a real-world attempt to find a path through the complex maze of methodological approaches, within the tight timeframe of the policymaking process, and under a strong driver to be ‘utilization-focused’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1356389013493840">Patton, 2012a</xref>). It does not present any sort of ‘model’ for such an exercise, since what worked on this occasion, and indeed what did not work, could not be guaranteed to function in a similar way under different conditions on another occasion. In describing the experience, however, and reflecting on the learning created, the article hopes to contribute to the debate on approaches to complex synthesis, particularly in the field of international development.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1356389013493840">
<title>Synthesis content</title>
<p>The material presented for synthesis by commissioners was complex and diverse. It involved a set of 22<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1356389013493840">3</xref></sup> country-level evaluation reports, here conceptualized as ‘cases’, conducted under a common framework, of four different objects: the aid modality of General Budget Support; Donor support to Anti-Corruption; Public Sector Governance Reforms; and finally the Paris Declaration policy compact. For each evaluation object, a synthesis report had been developed, though this was in the form of an initial note for the Budget Support evaluation. The component literature is provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1356389013493840">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1356389013493840" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Component evaluations.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1356389013493840" xlink:href="10.1177_1356389013493840-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Evaluation</th>
<th align="left">Evaluation questions</th>
<th align="left">Country evaluations</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>The Evaluation of the Paris Declaration</td>
<td>1. What are the factors that have shaped and limited the implementation of the Declaration reforms and their effects?<break/>2. What improvements have been made in aid effectiveness as targeted in the Declaration?<break/>3. What contributions have improvements in aid effectiveness made to sustainable development results?</td>
<td>Synthesis plus reports from: Bangladesh, Cambodia,<break/>Ghana, Indonesia, Malawi, Mali, Mozambique, Uganda, Vietnam, Zambia</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3"><hr/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Donor support to anti-corruption</td>
<td><italic>Relevance</italic><break/> – Are the approaches employed by the five donors to address corruption (including its negative effects on poor people and women in particular) appropriate to country circumstances, and how could they be made more relevant?<break/><italic>Effectiveness</italic><break/> – How effective have donor interventions been in addressing different types of corruption, including forms of corruption affecting poor people and women in particular?</td>
<td>Bangladesh, Viet Nam, Nicaragua, Tanzania, Zambia</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3"><hr/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Public sector governance reform</td>
<td>1. To what extent have investments made through PSGR programmes over the last ten years:<break/> i. Supported governments to be more capable, accountable and responsive in delivering services and maintaining the rights of citizens?<break/> ii. Helped create an enabling environment for economic growth?<break/> iii. Built state capability to manage and implement reforms?<break/>2. What lessons can be learnt, about both the conditions for success of PSGR activities and the ways in which challenges have been overcome, that will:<break/> i. Provide knowledge to further improve aid effectiveness?<break/> ii. Assist prioritization of activity?<break/> iii. Generate baseline information for future planning and implementation of PSGR including in the case study countries?<break/>Plus a number of secondary questions for country case studies</td>
<td>Cambodia, Indonesia, Mozambique, Uganda</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3"><hr/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Budget support</td>
<td>1. To what extent have budget support mechanisms been consistent with national strategic and policy frameworks and how well has the design been adapted to the specific political, economic and institutional context?<break/>2. To what extent has budget support contributed to an increased size and share of external funding subject to government’s budgetary process, the establishment of a framework of policy dialogue and to harmonization and alignment of external assistance?<break/>3. Did budget support have an impact on fiscal discipline and macro economic management, public finance management, public spending <bold>and revenue</bold>, governance and democratic accountability?</td>
<td>Initial synthesis note plus Zambia, Mali, Tunisia</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The research team had the advantage of involvement in three of the studies: in one case, the Paris Declaration Evaluation, as a member of the respective Evaluation Team; in three others, as part of the international governance structures.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1356389013493840">
<title>Realist synthesis</title>
<p>From the very start, it was clear that traditional approaches to systematic reviews, which often focus effort on identifying common patterns or trends and mapping results, were unsuited to very diverse evaluative material, which had applied different approaches and methodologies to the evaluation of different objects. While seeking to highlight results, this synthesis exercise was primarily aimed at generating a fuller understanding of the nature of aid effectiveness and governance reforms, how their implementation had worked in practice, and why changes had arisen as a result.</p>
<p>A methodology was therefore needed that:</p>
<list id="list1-1356389013493840" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>embraced complexity and placed context front and centre;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>sought explanations for what changes have taken place and why in different contexts; and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>could point to greater understandings of successes and failures (and all points in between) of the enormous investment in aid effectiveness and governance reforms by the international community.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>In working their way through the complex maze of potential methodological approaches, the research team encountered the field of realist synthesis. Realist review was originally developed for complex social interventions within the fields of health and criminal justice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1356389013493840">Pawson, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1356389013493840">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1356389013493840">Pawson and Tilley, 2001</xref>). It aimed to explore systematically how contextual factors influence the link between intervention and outcome. The realist research question is often summarized as ‘What works for whom under what circumstances, how and why?’</p>
<p>As Greenhalgh and colleagues recently put it:
<disp-quote>
<p>Many researchers are attracted to these approaches because they allow systematic exploration of how and why complex interventions work. Policymakers are attracted to them because they are potentially able to answer questions relevant to practical decisions (not merely ‘what is the impact of X?’ but ‘if we invest in X, to which particular sectors should we target it, how might implementation be improved and how might we maximize its impact?’). (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1356389013493840">Greenhalgh et al., 2012</xref>)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Realist reviews sit within ‘theory-based’ approaches to evaluation, whose relevance to international development have been widely recognized. Theory-based approaches begin by acknowledging that there are causal links in the chain, leading from starting to end point. Mapping out chains of causal mechanisms over time and into the future enables the tracking of progress, distance travelled and likely degree of future change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1356389013493840">Stern, 2008</xref>).They are, according to their proponents, particularly relevant to the challenge of evaluating ‘messy’ data collected in unpredictable contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1356389013493840">Stern, 2009</xref>). In aiming at ‘enlightenment’ of policy decisions, realist synthesis has much in common with utilization-focused approaches, which are focused on stimulating change through the provision and communication of policy-relevant evidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1356389013493840">Patton, 2012b</xref>).</p>
<p>Realist review is an interpretive process – that is, it is based on building plausible, evidenced explanations of observed outcomes, presented predominantly in narrative form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1356389013493840">Greenhalgh et al., 2012</xref>). As Leeman and colleagues point out, the end-product of the synthesis in the realist tradition is not a summary of the evidence in support of relationships (e.g. between an intervention and outcome), but rather a ‘beginning theory’ to explain ‘what works for whom in what circumstances and in what respects’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1356389013493840">Leeman et al., 2010</xref>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1356389013493840">Pawson, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>A group of realist researchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1356389013493840">Wong et al., 2013</xref>) have recently published the RAMESES (Realist and Meta-Narrative Evidence Synthesis) standards,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1356389013493840">4</xref></sup> which set out the basis of a realist approach to synthesis. In summary:</p>
<list id="list2-1356389013493840" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>A realist approach is based on a realist philosophy of science and considers the interaction between context, mechanism and outcome.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Realist synthesis is oriented around the central construct of programme theory, which sets out how and why an intervention is thought to ‘work’ to generate outcome(s) of interest.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>In a realist approach, an intervention (e.g. a governance reform introduced by policymakers with the aim of creating a defined outcome such as an increased share of the national budget allocated to poverty reduction) can alter surrounding context (e.g. by making new resources available), which then triggers a series of mechanism(s),<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1356389013493840">5</xref></sup> which produce both intended and unintended outcomes.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Researchers applying realist synthesis approaches try to understand the relationships between context, mechanism and outcomes (the CMO model, described below). In doing so, they try to explain examples of success, failure and occurrences between.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1356389013493840">
<title>Conditions for realist synthesis</title>
<p>Yet as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1356389013493840">Greenhalgh and colleagues (2012)</xref> have pointed out many published systematic reviews that claim to be ‘realist’ do not in fact satisfy the basic criteria of the approach – namely, being systematic, theory-driven and consistent with realist philosophy. The RAMESES project identified just 30 syntheses that satisfied realist synthesis criteria.</p>
<p>While these standards were not available at the time of this exercise, it was clear from an early stage that the synthesis exercise, in its approach and component evidence, could not satisfy some of the basic conditions for a true realist synthesis. As follows:</p>
<list id="list3-1356389013493840" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>the synthesis did not aim to collate evidence against a defined research question other than the headline question of the success or otherwise of aid effectiveness and governance reforms;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>the exercise was not oriented around a systematic literature search of primary studies that had a bearing on a single question. Rather, the component literature had been pre-selected, consisting of evaluation reports (cases) geared to four different evaluation objects, albeit within the common framework of aid effectiveness and governance;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>there was no single underlying programme theory for an ‘intervention’ under analysis – instead, each aid effectiveness reform has its own underlying theory of change that is captured in the reports to varying degrees, most explicitly in the Paris Declaration Evaluation.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>On the other hand, the research team were directed by commissioners partly to focus on results (what had worked) but also to focus on understanding – where had aid effectiveness and governance reforms succeeded most, why/why not, and how had reforms been shaped by, and affected, different contexts – in the hope of identifying possible replicable mechanisms that would translate to other contexts. These questions implied some common ground with the underlying philosophy and principles of a theory-driven synthesis, as follows:</p>
<list id="list4-1356389013493840" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>The primacy of context in shaping the nature and effects of aid effectiveness reforms was reflected in each component report. This was in tune with the realist school’s conviction that ‘social interventions, such as quality improvement initiatives, are complex, and that the way they bring about change is influenced by, dependent on and in turn influences their contexts’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1356389013493840">Mazzocato et al., 2010</xref>).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The realist approach that outcomes arise in a non-linear way thought multiple human interactions and decisions under the influence of a wide range of contextual factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1356389013493840">Wong et al., 2011</xref>), chimed with the researchers’ own professional experience.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The synthesis exercise did not seek absolute certainty for policy and programme decision making but rather to provide detailed insights into the complex workings of aid effectiveness and governance reforms. This is consistent with the realistic approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1356389013493840">Pawson et al., 2005</xref>).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The relationship between context and outcomes, core to the realist approach, was the central framework of all the component reports. Each report analysed – though to varying degrees, as described below – how the particular reforms were shaped by context; through which mechanisms change had occurred; and with what resulting outcomes</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>All the reforms evaluated had demonstrated the potential to influence the surrounding context. For example, the Public Sector Governance Reform studies identified changes in the national and decentralized governance environment occurring through policy shifts and structural or administrative process reforms. Again, this dynamic is central to realistic synthesis.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>All the component evaluations, plus the synthesis itself, sought some of the insights at the heart of realistic evaluation; namely, looking beyond the narrow and experimental, and into the reasons why and how change had happened, and the effects of context on results.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The realist model also offered some specific approaches that seemed relevant and appropriate, as follows.</p>
<list id="list5-1356389013493840" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1356389013493840">Jackson (2009)</xref> and others have signalled, the component evaluation reports both recognized the complexities of aid effectiveness reforms and rejected attempts to ignore contextual information in an attempt to determine the ‘magic bullet’ or the key causal agents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1356389013493840">Pawson, 2006</xref>).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Although no single overarching theory of change exists to encapsulate the full gamut of aid effectiveness and governance reforms, explicit theories of change were apparent in the Paris Declaration and Public Sector Governance Reform reports. Such a theory was an explicit output of the Budget Support report; and was obliquely available in the Donor Support to Anti-Corruption report. Moreover, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1356389013493840">Floyd and colleagues (2004)</xref> have pointed out, the ‘realistic’ approach to evaluation implies that theories of change can be sought from current knowledge; the literature on aid effectiveness and governance reforms is broad, and offered insight into the underlying theories of the reforms.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Many of the component evaluations, albeit to different degrees, sought out ‘analytic purchase’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1356389013493840">Greenhalgh et al., 2012</xref>) in the sense of being able to describe and understand the ‘contingencies that affect the likelihood of such interventions generating their intended outcomes’ (i.e. the factors that might influence whether change happens, or otherwise).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Realist evaluators also point out that the ways interventions generate change (or not) is highly mediated by context, through the triggering of specific mechanisms, through shifting actors’ perception of a problem or through the provision of resources or opportunities that can be taken up and applied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1356389013493840">McCormack et al., 2006</xref>). The component reports were clear (though to differing degrees) in their analyses that mechanisms through which change had been generated – albeit not explicitly framed as this technical concept – were mainly determined by context, and that constraining and enabling factors to results themselves commonly arose from the effects of context, as discussed below.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The researchers also wanted to focus on identifying constraints and barriers, limitations and difficulties within both the implementation of reforms and the results generated. This is consistent with the realistic perspective of ‘discover[ing] the typical weak points and major stumbling blocks in the implementation of the interventions under review’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1356389013493840">Pawson, 2006</xref>).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The realist approach emphasizes that the steps required to carry out a realist synthesis are often neither linear nor sequential: ‘Rather than reviewing a focused literature addressing a predetermined set of research questions, the review itself – generated by a beginning set of questions – leads to more questions and, therefore, a diverse range of categories for analysis’ (Leeman et al., 2006). Given the diversity of the cases included in the review, an iterative approach appeared sensible and realistic.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Overall, therefore, the research team found the philosophy, principles and approaches of a realist review design, if not the full realist synthesis approach, to suit this exercise because, briefly put, aid effectiveness reforms:</p>
<list id="list6-1356389013493840" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>are complex social interventions that are highly determined by context;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>are comprised of theories;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>consist of a chain of processes that interact and that are almost never linear;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>are implemented into, and embedded within, highly varied social systems; and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>frequently change during the implementation process – resulting in varied effects at different levels.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1356389013493840">
<title>Utility: Realist synthesis and policymaking</title>
<p>Systematic reviews of evidence have come centre stage in recent years, as the discourse of evidence-based policy and practice has taken hold. Policymaking has been defined as ‘whatever governments choose to do and not to do’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1356389013493840">Dye, 1984</xref>). As McMahon points out, however, the idea of linear policymaking stages, which operate in a logical process, has been largely displaced by recognition that policymaking is a more convoluted, diffuse and haphazard process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1356389013493840">McMahon, 2010</xref>). This view of policy recognizes its complex nature, where causality occurs through multiple sources, informed and generated by feedback loops that occur at irregular times.</p>
<p>The architect of realist evaluation, Ray Pawson, has argued for a realistic view of what evidence can contribute to the ‘doing’ (i.e. government-managed side of policy formulation) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1356389013493840">Pawson, 2006</xref>). Certainly, there is an often large gap between evidence generation and its feeding into policy reforms in aid effectiveness and governance – particularly when policy decisions are in reality formulated far in advance of evidence entering the process.</p>
<p>The idea that syntheses of evidence should include from the outset explicit consideration of how research will feed into the policy formulation process, thereby taking account of timeliness, audience and the current policy context, has also recently come to the fore (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1356389013493840">McMahon, 2010</xref>). In this case, due to their prior and ongoing involvement in the component evaluations, the research team had the advantage of up-to-date knowledge of the audience for the synthesis, and the surrounding policy development process. They were also mindful, given the wide range of evidence streams feeding into the High Level Forum and beyond, that the format of the output which would be produced, as the artefact of the synthesis, needed to be consistent with the needs of the audience.</p>
<p>The intended <italic>function</italic> of the synthesis in influencing policy was also considered by the researchers, who knew from their own experience within development agencies that evidence can be used to confirm and justify a position, to fine-tune draft policy positions, or alter course sometimes (though in reality, an evidence synthesis that contradicts an early-stage policy decision often results in another review being commissioned). Given that the component reports were already available as part of the evidence base, the output was not expected to significantly shape any of the high-level discussions, but to make the evidence base available in a compressed and digestible form.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1356389013493840">6</xref></sup></p>
<p>Finally, reviews that allow for a dialogue between the researcher and decision makers have been perceived as contributing to research transfer in other contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1356389013493840">McMahon, 2010</xref>). Here, the synthesis exercise was conceived as part of the policy dialogue process, partly through the research team’s connections with the dialogue process, and partly through formal events. For example, a Room Document was developed and presented an OECD DAC Working Party on Aid Effectiveness policy meeting in Paris, in the lead up to the High Level Forum.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1356389013493840">
<title>The synthesis process</title>
<p>An advantage for those new to realist synthesis is the provision of detailed procedural steps, set out in previous work by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1356389013493840">Pawson and colleagues (2004)</xref> and clarified in the RAMESES publication standards indicated above. These cover the stages of: clarifying the scope of the review, articulating the relevant underlying theoretical drivers, searching for evidence, and appraising and synthesizing the evidence.</p>
<p>However, for this exercise, as stated, the literature set was pre-determined. Moreover, since each of the four aid effectiveness and governance reforms has its own underlying theory of change, articulated to varying degrees in the component reports, there were multiple potential theoretical bases for the analysis. At aggregate level, no overarching theory or set of competing theories exists that adequately reflects the complex relationships between aid effectiveness reforms and the final intended result of poverty reduction.</p>
<p>Despite this, the component reports shared an interrelationship that facilitated (and indeed stimulated) their synthesis. The global Paris Declaration compact aimed at reforming aid relationships through the adoption and application of an agreed set of principles by donors and partner countries. Its evaluation therefore addressed this broad scope of reforms. The other three evaluations focused on partial reforms, but all of these were related to the principles and application of the Declaration. This inter-relationship meant that the results of the four studies could be synthesized a meaningful way.</p>
<p>All four studies were also careful to specify in their conceptual approach the limits of aid in the development process. There was considerable shared methodological ground, with three of the four studies applying contribution analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1356389013493840">Mayne, 2001</xref>). And in process terms, all had been subject to rigorous international quality assurance processes, involving high-level scrutiny by government and international agency representatives.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, as for the principles and approaches of the realist approach, many of the stages set out by Pawson and colleagues appeared useful and appropriate for this exercise. Consequently, the synthesis team applied an adapted model of synthesis which applied many of the steps of realist synthesis but which adapted some and omitted others. This is described below.</p>
<sec id="section8-1356389013493840">
<title>Stage 1: Defining the purpose and scope of the review</title>
<sec id="section9-1356389013493840">
<title>Scope of the review</title>
<p>The first stage in the realist synthesis model is to define the scope and purpose of the review. The overarching question for this exercise was formulated by commissioners prior to the synthesis process, and was initially very open: <italic>What have been the main lessons and policy implications from four international evaluations on aid effectiveness and governance?</italic></p>
<p>Based on initial review, this was broken down by the researchers into three more specific questions:</p>
<list id="list7-1356389013493840" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>What has been achieved over the decade from the combined effort to make states more effective and accountable?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What has been the contribution and quality of development cooperation partnerships?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What has been the quality and use of results measurement, monitoring and evaluation in strategy and programming decisions?</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1356389013493840">
<title>Purpose of the review</title>
<p>In terms of defining purpose, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1356389013493840">McCormack and colleagues (2006)</xref> list a range of possible options as follows:</p>
<list id="list8-1356389013493840" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Theory integrity</italic> – does the intervention work as predicted?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Theory adjudication</italic> – which theories about the intervention seem to fit best?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Comparison</italic> – how does the intervention work in different settings, for different groups?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Reality testing</italic> – how does the policy intent of the intervention translate into practice?</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The purpose of this exercise was a combination of three of the above:</p>
<list id="list9-1356389013493840" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>theory integrity</italic> – exploring at aggregate level whether the different theories of aid effectiveness and governance reforms had operated as anticipated (for instance, in crude terms, whether the use of the budget support aid modality had led to improvements in poverty reduction; or whether donor support to anti-corruption initiatives had resulted in reductions in corruption incidence);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>comparison</italic> – assessing how the different theories underlying each reform had worked in practice in varying contexts; and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>reality testing</italic> – reviewing the extent to which the policy <italic>intent</italic> of aid effectiveness and governance reforms had translated into reality, with the high end-game stakes of the lives of the poor.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1356389013493840">
<title>Extracting the programme theory</title>
<p>The next stage following the realist synthesis model is to locate and articulate the programme theory underlying the intervention. The Paris Declaration and Budget Support evaluations contained explicit theories of change; this was less clear in the Anti-Corruption study; and was present within the Governance reforms study as an analytical output, being part of the study remit.</p>
<p>As far as could be determined, the individual theories of change were not distinct but contained some areas of overlap – for example, in their intended end results (poverty reduction/the achievement of international development targets) along with some differences (reduced corruption incidence). The strategies to be applied also shared some common ground, orienting around institutional reforms/policy changes/improvements in accountability. But understandably, given the breadth and scope of the reforms under review, no single overarching theory of change exists for these, nor could one be constructed ex-ante without risking extreme overgeneralization. Even had its development been required or feasible, therefore, it would have required detailed work for which, under the timeline of the policy process, time was unavailable</p>
<p>With time pressing, and mindful of the driver for ‘policy relevance’, the team opted to focus less on refining a generic overarching theory of change as the main benchmark for analysis, and more on developing the analytical fields aligned to it as the main framework for interpretation. In an effort to draw as far as feasible from the theoretical basis for the reforms, these were taken mainly from the core text – the First Draft Busan Outcome document – with the addition of some articulated policy priorities (see below). This was extremely broad brush but provided a broad theoretical framework within which analysis could take place.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1356389013493840">
<title>Developing analytical fields</title>
<p>Pawson et al.’s approach of ‘concept mining’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1356389013493840">2004</xref>) describes the extraction of a theory from the existing literature, through the seeking out of themes that mutually verify and validate each other. The researchers applied this approach, within the framework of the broad brush theory of change, by turning to the key sources for the study:</p>
<list id="list10-1356389013493840" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The core document of the First Draft Busan Outcome Document, from which the main theoretical framework had been drawn;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>A set of priorities articulated by a policy structure within the OECD DAC, the Governance Network (GovNet);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The sub-theories of the four component objects.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>In specific terms, the process for developing the initial set of analytical fields was as follows:</p>
<list id="list11-1356389013493840" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Themes in the First Outcome Draft document were developed through simple discourse analysis (a list of 22 themes were developed);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Where feasible, these themes were consolidated and aggregated into higher level themes;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Themes were mapped against the GovNet identified priorities and consolidated where possible;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>As analysis progressed, other themes emerging from the component reports were mapped onto the consolidated set so far;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Tracking back took place to ensure that Outcome document themes remained constant as a reference point, given their relevance to the theoretical framework.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>A list of 20 fields finally arose from this process, presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1356389013493840">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1356389013493840" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Analytical fields.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1356389013493840" xlink:href="10.1177_1356389013493840-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Impact and results (where significant contribution made by intervention – include explanatory factors if available)</td>
<td>Use of country systems, public financial management reforms, alignment</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Accountability – mutual, the country or global compact</td>
<td>Capacity/institutional development</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Transparency/information systems/monitoring and reporting</td>
<td>Predictability</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Risk and risk management</td>
<td>Aid Effectiveness, e.g. reducing fragmentation, policy coherence, policy dialogue coordination, etc.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Measuring results i.e. indicators and targets, how to measure progress</td>
<td>Development by other means e.g. trade and private sector growth</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Managing for results/performance management (systems)</td>
<td>New partnerships for development/new types of aid flows e.g. climate change financing, aid for trade</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Domestic accountability – the citizen-state relationship</td>
<td>New challenges – climate change, the economic downturn, food and fuel price crises</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Country leadership and ownership/role of the State in development</td>
<td>Fragility</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Corruption</td>
<td>Political economy assessments and influence on programming</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Aid modalities and governance</td>
<td>Contextual drivers of reform</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1356389013493840">
<title>Developing the analytical framework</title>
<p>Finally, the analytical fields were plotted onto a spreadsheet which also contained the names of the component evaluations. Combined with a facility to identify connections and configurations between the different components of analysis, below, this tool comprised the main analytical framework for the study.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1356389013493840">
<title>Stage 2: Searching for and appraising the evidence</title>
<p>The realist model asks evaluators to assess the status of the evidence in terms of rigour and relevance. For this exercise, given that the composition of the evidence base was pre-determined, relevance had also been established <italic>ex ante</italic> – although individual findings still had to be assessed in terms of their relevance to the analytical fields. Rigour fell moreover outside the researchers’ remit: all the evaluation reports had been conducted under rigorous governance processes, at both international and national level, and had undergone their own independent quality assurance processes.</p>
<p>That said, the component evaluations were at different stages of completion at the time of the analysis; the analytical process therefore had to be explicit on the status of the dataset applied for analysis (whether component reports were at draft/final stage for example). The analysis therefore incorporated assessments of <italic>relevance</italic> and <italic>reliability</italic> (in terms of report status) within the analytical framework but not rigour. Reliability was emphatically not a quality assurance of the report but made explicit the status of the data on which the synthesis findings were based.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1356389013493840">
<title>Stage 3: Extracting and synthesizing the findings</title>
<sec id="section16-1356389013493840">
<title>Extracting the findings</title>
<p>Extraction of evidence concentrated on the findings and conclusions from the reports, rather than recommendations, since the synthesis focused on evidence rather than evaluative judgment. The OECD DAC definitions for these terms were applied.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1356389013493840">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Given the broad range of analytical fields developed, and the considerable time constraints, it would have been a swifter process to pre-prioritize a sub-set of fields against which evidence could have been extracted. However, the researchers opted to analyse each report across the full range of fields. This was more time-consuming, but its logic was as follows:</p>
<list id="list12-1356389013493840" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Any deleting of fields would be arbitrary;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The team did not wish to risk deleting analytical fields which might subsequently turn out to be important in the evidence base;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Analysis was approached as an emergent process; the team were aware that fields would prioritize themselves as the evidence was worked through.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Findings were plotted into a simple analytical spreadsheet against the analytical fields, which were themselves refined in an iterative process as data was extracted and overlap and duplication in the fields emerged. This resulted in a total of 18 final fields for analysis. The spreadsheets were them merged to create one composite evidence base.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1356389013493840">
<title>Synthesizing the findings: Consolidation and aggregation</title>
<p>To this point, the researchers were comfortable that both the development of the analytical fields and the extraction of the evidence analysis had been sufficiently systematic. If not fully meeting the conditions for, and applying the steps of, realist synthesis, the exercise had applied its principles and concepts as far as feasible, and found them useful.</p>
<p>The next stage in the realist process is described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1356389013493840">Pawson et al. (2004)</xref> as follows:</p>
<list id="list13-1356389013493840" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>‘Compare and contrast findings from different studies</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Use findings to address purpose</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Seek both confirmatory and contradictory findings</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Refine programme theories in the light of evidence’.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>For the four synthesis reports within the evidence base, this had presented little difficulty, given that their component country studies had applied similar approaches and methodologies to evaluate the same object. The number of realist studies identified by the RAMESES project – 30 as stated – also implies that, where the appropriate conditions exist, this is an entirely feasible process. Yet for a complex synthesis across varied objects, applying a very diverse evidence base – for which realist synthesis was not, of course, designed – it presented considerable problems.</p>
<p>Firstly, the nature of the evidence, whilst sharing the common framework of aid effectiveness and governance reforms, was present at different levels. It was not always simply comparable or contrastable. Some of the evidence did mutually confirm/contradict other evidence, but much also presented nuances or variations on a theme.</p>
<p>Secondly, the realist approach uses a Context-Mechanism-Outcome (CMO) model to respond to its core question of ‘what works for whom under what circumstances’ where context, mechanisms and outcomes are explored <italic>in configuration.</italic> Within the synthesis exercise, the extraction of mechanisms – the causal connections, generatively developed, which had led to the results cited – and their relationship to context and outcomes proved complex.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1356389013493840">8</xref></sup></p>
<p>None of the reports applied a formal CMO analysis, and none explicitly labeled their analytical elements according to the CMO model. With the exception of the Budget Support study, none generated, as an outcome of analysis, detailed sub-hypotheses or propositions, and then analysed these comprehensively in a configuration model, as a fully realist synthesis would require. While most did analyse contextual features and their relationships to change (outcomes), and to the ways that change had happened (broadly defined, mechanisms), the depth and scope of these analyses were highly variable.</p>
<p>To illustrate this, we present this example from the Bangladesh country case study within the Anti Corruption evaluation. Key contextual factors <italic>supporting</italic> anti-corruption reforms in the country were identified as: economic growth and new technologies; donor demand; the role of NGOs in service delivery; and an increasing demand for accountability from some sections of society. <italic>Constraining</italic> factors to reform were identified as: the limited influence of donors to improve laws and regulations; features of the national political economy such as the embedded patronage system; politicization within the Bangladesh civil service; a lack of political will to address corruption issues; and a lack of engagement by donors with MPs on the policy agenda. Beyond these contextually-grounded factors, the report also extracted, though to a more limited degree, the processes <italic>by which changes had occurred</italic>, though did not extrapolate these fully as mechanisms.</p>
<p>With some, though not all, individual features of the CMO configuration in place, therefore, and some degree of analysis of the interrelationships between them, but without a clear set of identified CMO configurations to apply, therefore, or an available set of sub-hypotheses underlying these (which would in any event have been unmanageably large), the synthesis team focused on best use of the analysis available. The key contextually-located ‘drivers for/barriers to’ change identified in the reports, were therefore firstly mapped on to a separate column in the analytical matrix as the first dimension of a realist-type analysis.</p>
<p>Secondly, within the individual evaluation reports, some individual <italic>mechanisms</italic> could be identified, since even if most of the reports had not labelled the causal connections as such, they had mapped out clearly the pathways of contribution which had led to the results. In most cases, these were also explored in their relation to the national or local context under study, namely particular aid architectures and relationships, political economies, governance and political structures and other factors in a country.</p>
<p>However, extracting these at synthesis level was no simple task. Initial attempts to map and aggregate them proved fruitless, merely creating an excessively broad set of mechanisms disconnected from context and results, with little common ground between them and with an unfeasibly large set of possible inter-connections. Moreover, the realist model’s proposition-building approach to the CMO model (i.e. the building of configurations through the identification and extraction of a full range of hypotheses from each component case) is a vast task even for a synthesis of similar programme-level interventions. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1356389013493840">Pawson and Manzano-Santaella (2012</xref>: 187) point out: ‘And so the hypotheses multiply until the researcher reaches exhaustion or the limits of funding.’ It approaches unfeasibility within a national evaluation of aid reforms which have taken place at decentralized as well as at national levels, and becomes completely impossible for 20+ such studies.</p>
<p>A simpler process was therefore undertaken by the researchers, namely the extraction of a set of identifiable <italic>mechanisms of change</italic> through analysis of the report narratives, which were linked to context and to outcomes and then categorized in broad groups. These were then verified through a process of checking traceability and ‘logical derivation’ from the evidence through repeated backtracking to the original evidence. Contradictions and tensions within the mechanisms of change which arose were included, rather than omitted, in the analysis.</p>
<p>The key narratives and categories for identified mechanisms of change are reflected in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1356389013493840">Table 3</xref>. Within these broad categories, specific mechanisms linked to context and outcomes, were then identified. An example is provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1356389013493840">Table 4</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1356389013493840" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Narratives and mechanism categories.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1356389013493840" xlink:href="10.1177_1356389013493840-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Narrative</th>
<th align="left">Mechanism category</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Improving the aid partnership</td>
<td>Stronger national ownership, improved public financial management, stronger country systems and greater use of these, improved predictability, better risk management and mitigation, stronger emphasis on mutual accountability, capacity improvements within individual ministries, stimulation of cross-government coordination</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Improving the citizen-state relationship</td>
<td>Changes in governance systems, working to develop domestic accountability and transparency, and greater emphasis on efforts to tackle corruption</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Improving results</td>
<td>Improving management for development results, and measuring and reporting (information systems and use) on results</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table4-1356389013493840" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Example mechanisms.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1356389013493840" xlink:href="10.1177_1356389013493840-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Narrative</th>
<th align="left">Mechanism category</th>
<th align="left">Mechanism of change (based on evidence)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Improving the aid partnership</td>
<td>Stronger national ownership</td>
<td>Ensuring national leadership over aid coordination at different levels (national and decentralized)<break/>Supporting the development of a national development strategy with relevant intended development results and linking it to a realistic financial framework<break/>Including civil society, local authorities and the private sector in developing the national development strategy<break/>Embedding international commitments on gender equality, human rights, disability and environmental sustainability into the national development strategy<break/>Monitoring the national development strategy through parliament</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>This stage of analysis involved reverting to a more traditional grounded theory model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1356389013493840">Strauss, 1987</xref>). As for the realist approach, grounded theory recognizes the primacy of context in analysis, and emphasizes the identification of patterns and trends. For the analytical process, it also meant confronting, rather than seeking to resolve, contradiction and diversity that arose from analysis; and acknowledging differences rather than seeking to suppress them.</p>
<p>In practical terms, this meant an aggregation process, drawing together the evidence on mechanisms, connecting these to contextually-grounded key barriers and drivers for reform, and linking them to the changes generated. Analysis resulted in a set of <italic>key narratives</italic>, which consolidated the evidence on contextual features, mechanisms and changes where patterns and trends were present; and retained differences and tensions where these existed. Variations were explored, and other possible theories considered for why particular changes might have occurred, where possible, assessed by returning to the base evidence, or to the wider literature. This process was then repeated several times, to maximize the consolidation process, and to ensure that sufficient effort had been made to identify and incorporate possible alternative explanations for change.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1356389013493840">
<title>Refining the programme theory</title>
<p>The penultimate step in the realist approach is to refine the programme theory. The task of the team was to synthesize the findings of the four component evaluations, and not to generate or refine a programme theory. Moreover, as stated, no overarching programme theory exists or would be practical to develop for the full gamut of aid effectiveness and governance reforms under analysis here.</p>
<p>The individual programme theory for aid effectiveness reform had already been extracted in the Paris Declaration Evaluation, with the sub-theories of change for particular governance and aid modality reforms attempted by the Governance and Budget Support Evaluations. With no explicit mandate to undertake it, and mindful of the directive for policy relevance, therefore, the research team focused on ensuring the robustness of the analytical fields and key narratives as the main theoretical output. Parallel to this, they sought to negotiate and agree the final text with commissioners and other stakeholders, and seek out opportunities for its insertion within the policy process.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1356389013493840">
<title>Stage 4: Validating the text and ensuring ‘policy relevance’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1356389013493840">9</xref></sup></title>
<p>The synthesis exercise was not a purely external one, given the research team’s involvement in the component studies, and within the policy discourse itself leading up to the Busan High Level Forum. The conducting of the synthesis exercise within a framework of policy discourse and substantive negotiation is well recognized by realist synthesizers: ‘[A] realist synthesis derives its focus from a negotiation between the study commissioners and the researchers’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1356389013493840">McCormack et al., 2006</xref>)</p>
<p>In keeping with the realist approach, the draft text was discussed with relevant stakeholders, partly for validation purposes and partly to check for policy relevance. Negotiation and validation took place as follows:</p>
<list id="list14-1356389013493840" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>with team leaders of the component evaluations, to check for validity;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>with commissioners, through feedback and comment;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>with other interested parties, who had not been involved in its commissioning but were part of the international evaluation community and played an active role in the pre-Busan dialogue;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>with an expert cohort, through presentation at an OECD DAC preparatory meeting for the High Level Forum.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The synthesis generated was therefore an explicit process of dialogue and negotiation: among the component studies themselves; between the component studies and the analytical fields: between the analytical process and the surrounding policy discourse; between the research team and the evaluation teams involved; between the research team and their commissioners. This raises the issue of bias, categorized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1356389013493840">White and Phillips (2012)</xref> as evaluator and respondent bias, and including such potential biases as courtesy and cognitive biases. By returning continually to the anchor point of evidence from the component studies; through the validation process with team leaders and other stakeholders; and through the dialogue process surrounding the final negotiation of the text – with participants who had mainly been involved in one or more of the studies, and who were familiar with both the evidence and its policy relevance – the researchers were confident that all efforts were made to acknowledge and tackle the various relevant forms of bias arising.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-1356389013493840">
<title>Final output</title>
<p>The synthesis process resulted in two final outputs:. first, a detailed ‘Room Document’ which was prepared for, and presented at, an OCED DAC preparatory meeting in the lead up to the Busan High Level Forum; and second, the Room Document was then itself developed into an Evaluation Insight, available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oecd.org/dac/evaluationofdevelopmentprogrammes/dcdndep/49247821.pdf">http://www.oecd.org/dac/evaluationofdevelopmentprogrammes/dcdndep/49247821.pdf</ext-link>, which was published as part of a series by the OECD DAC’s Evaluation Network (Evalnet).The resulting text entered the policy dialogue stream as intended, but much of its value eventually lay in the dialogue and negotiation surrounding its development.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-1356389013493840">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>Over and above its lack of adherence to the full standards for realist synthesis, a number of limitations to the synthesis process emerged. These, and how they were handled, are as follows.</p>
<list id="list15-1356389013493840" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Many of the reports were not in final/signed off version during the analysis – so the composite evidence base could not be considered as final. This was handled through the validation process, which allowed amendments to be made and changes in final approved reports tracked through into the final outputs.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The initial number of analytical themes was high, and some overlap emerged through the analysis e.g. between domestic accountability and transparency. This was handled by bringing these overlaps together at consolidation of mechanisms stage.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>There was a different level of depth between the reports, with the component reports from the Paris Declaration study significantly broader and more extensive in geographic coverage and thematic scope than all the others. This was handled though ongoing effort to stay true to the level of depth in the findings and to draw out the added value of the different scopes.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Some of the component evaluations had a focus on the effectiveness of aid/support rather than the country’s overall policy, systems and progress (this was arguably not the case with Paris Declaration or the Public Sector Governance Reform studies). This was handled by efforts to stay true to findings, through the validation processes described above, and to distinguish carefully between these two aspects in reporting.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>An important focus for the High Level Forum was expected to be on effective aid for state-building and peace in situations of fragility and conflict. The countries covered by the evaluations were not selected with this in mind, and coverage of this key issue for aid effectiveness was not sufficient to merit it being a key theme for the synthesis. This was handled through extracting the coverage of fragility issues where feasible, particularly within the Paris Declaration Evaluation component reports and some Public Sector Governance reports.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-1356389013493840">
<title>Extent to which a realist synthesis approach was adopted</title>
<p>As will be clear, the approach taken within this synthesis exercise to extracting context, mechanisms and outcomes, and to build a configuration model from these did not, in the final analysis, meet the standards of a fully realist model of synthesis. Applying the principles of the CMO model did however enable the use of the three concepts, and particularly that of mechanisms of change. These proved valuable in allowing for causality to be viewed from the vantage point of a meta-analysis across a wide range of evidence; and, if not fully established through a proposition-building approach, to be at least tentatively approached.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1356389013493840">Table 5</xref> sets out the synthesis team’s assessment of the extent to which the process for realist synthesis were adopted:</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-1356389013493840" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Application of realist principles.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1356389013493840" xlink:href="10.1177_1356389013493840-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Stage</th>
<th align="left">Steps</th>
<th align="left">Extent to which steps for realist synthesis followed</th>
<th align="left">Reasons/approach adopted</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3">1. Define the scope of the review</td>
<td>1.1 Identify the question</td>
<td>Followed in full</td>
<td>Key preliminary step. Headline question fixed but sub-questions and analytical fields developed/refined</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.2 Clarify the purpose of the review</td>
<td>Followed in full</td>
<td>Key preliminary step. Focused on policy reforms, and whether and how they had been implemented in practice, with what results</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.3 Find and articulate the programme<break/> theories</td>
<td>Only partially followed</td>
<td>More relevant to a synthesis where cases have high degrees of commonality e.g. similar programme interventions. For cases under synthesis here, were broad and very diverse. Sought out at individual case level, but too broad to fully articulate. Emphasized analytical fields rather than seeking to develop an aggregate level theory (also not part of study mandate)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">2. Search for and<break/> appraise the<break/> evidence</td>
<td>2.2 Search for the evidence</td>
<td>Not followed</td>
<td>Predetermined, so not a literature search per se</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2.3 Appraise the evidence</td>
<td>Not followed</td>
<td>Tests of relevance and rigour not appropriate since each case had already gone through a governance and quality assurance process</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3">3. Extract and synthesize findings</td>
<td>3.3 Extract the<break/> Results</td>
<td>Fully followed</td>
<td>Developed a data extraction template around the analytical fields<break/>Extracted data to populate the evaluative framework with evidence</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3.3 Synthesize<break/> findings</td>
<td>Partially followed, applied concepts of the CMO configuration approach but not the full model</td>
<td>Compared and contrasted findings from different studies; Applied findings from studies to address purposes of review; Sought out both confirmatory and contradictory findings; did not refine programme theories in the light of evidence but rather aggregated the evidence applying grounded theory and retained contradiction and diversity where this arose.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Consultation on<break/> and refinement<break/> of findings</td>
<td>New stage applied for this exercise</td>
<td>Validation with team leaders of the evaluations<break/>Consulted with expert cohort and networks (commissioners and presented in preparatory meetings for Busan)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4. Draw conclusions<break/> and make<break/> recommendations</td>
<td>Fully followed</td>
<td colspan="2">Involved commissioners/decision makers in review of findings<break/>Disseminated review with findings, conclusions though not recommendations</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1356389013493840">
<p>Adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1356389013493840">Pawson et al. (2004)</xref></p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section23-1356389013493840">
<title>Reflections on experience</title>
<p>The research team’s experience found that, for a complex synthesis involving a pre-established literature base, where the cases involved are diverse, and where an overarching programme theory is lacking and even unfeasible, the approaches and many of the steps involved in a realist model remain relevant. The evidence base did not meet the conditions for a full CMO configuration analysis, which proved unfeasible across such wide-ranging and varied cases and within tight time constraints. However, the application of realist principles and some of its concepts allowed for the identification and extraction of causal themes across even very diverse cases, and to place these within a policy-relevant framework for utilization.</p>
<p>The reversion to a more grounded theory model at the higher levels of analysis allowed for more emergent development of categories of mechanisms and identification of narrative themes, alongside a prioritization of the integrity of the original evidence as anchor. This proved valuable in supporting the development of the final narrative. Similarly, the dialogue surrounding the development of the final text also supported its validation. Together, these approaches helped ensure substantive validity, with findings firmly grounded in the evidence base, but which also allowed for ‘policy relevance’ to be seen as an enabling framework for interpretation, rather than an analytical straitjacket.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-1356389013493840">
<title>Lessons learned</title>
<p>This article does not present any sort of model for complex synthesis, but records some of the lessons arising from the experience, as follows.</p>
<list id="list16-1356389013493840" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>The principles and concepts of realist synthesis, if not the step by step approach described by Pawson and colleagues, can be relevant and useful for complex synthesis across a varied evidence base and particularly for starting to approach causality from an aggregate-level viewpoint.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>A common assumption, particularly of policymakers, is that by accumulating or aggregating specific case studies, general lessons can be learned. This is true to a limited extent, but the variation in mechanisms encountered here, being highly dependent on context, meant that the reasons why and how reforms had worked or otherwise are so many and varied as to be non-replicable. However, through a realist lens, their analysis did provide a framework for understanding across contexts.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Although it can be difficult to identify a core theoretical framework in an exercise of such breadth and scope, it is essential to at least recognize where this starts and ends, and to use it as the source for developing analytical fields. The task described would have been unfeasible had the component reports themselves not developed programme theories or intervention logics, even though these were varied in their depth and scope.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>A complex synthesis which is commissioned to inform international dialogue benefits from being explicitly situated within the surrounding policy process: both to substantively inform analysis; and to maximize utility. Ongoing dialogue, and a conceptualization of the synthesis as a process of internal and external negotiation, is a critical component of this.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Particularly where evidence is highly varied, moulding it to fit policy relevant categories can risk trade-offs in integrity. Continually returning to component case evidence can provide an anchor point; similarly, validating the evidence with its original generators ensures that integrity is retained.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Confronting, rather than attempting to resolve, tensions and contradiction within the original evidence provides valuable analytical insight in itself, while the dialogue process around them supports their resolution</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Complex synthesis is a dense and time-consuming process; it requires technical expertise, policy knowledge and engagement in surrounding dialogue. This should be borne in mind both by consultants and commissioners.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-1356389013493840" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The researchers’ hope is that this experience has shown how the principles, concepts and approaches of realist synthesis, if not the full set of steps including CMO configurations, can be applied to the complex synthesis across varied cases. It has helped deepen our understanding of the processes, opportunities and threats involved. During the experience it was possible to develop a coherent framework for analysis, applying realist concepts that, when populated and developed into accessible outputs, can support the decisions of policymakers. The process and framework presented here are far from definitive but the experience described may act as a starting point for others facing the growing demand for similar tasks.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1356389013493840">
<label>1</label>
<p>The component evaluations synthesized are available at the OECD DAC’s Evaluation Resource Centre (DEReC), at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oecd.org/derec/">http://www.oecd.org/derec/</ext-link>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1356389013493840">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Terms of Reference 2011.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1356389013493840">
<label>3.</label>
<p>In total, the country cases for the four evaluations totalled 36 in number, but to manage time and resource pressures, 22 were selected (applying criteria of a) preparedness of material – those studies in final version only were included and b) geographical concentration – ensuring that countries which had experienced multiple evaluations were included, to maximize the scope for validation and triangulation of themes).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1356389013493840">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/11/21">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/11/21</ext-link>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1356389013493840">
<label>5.</label>
<p>Under realism, mechanisms reflect ‘the many different ways in which the resources on offer may impinge on the stakeholders’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1356389013493840">Pawson and Tilley, 2001</xref>). ‘They do not reflect the multiple components of combined interventions, but penetrate to the layer beneath, attempting to explain how particular measures work’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1356389013493840">Pawson and Manzano-Santaella, 2012</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1356389013493840">
<label>6.</label>
<p>While the main strength of realist synthesis is often the level of specificity it can provide to decision-makers (particular mechanisms triggered within particular groups under specific conditions can be expected to lead to X or Y predefined results), the main purpose of this exercise was compression and accessibility of the evidence base for decision-makers.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1356389013493840">
<label>7.</label>
<p>As follows: <italic>Findings</italic>: A finding uses evidence from one or more evaluations to allow for a factual statement. <italic>Conclusions</italic>: Conclusions point out the factors of success and failure of the evaluated intervention, with special attention paid to the intended and unintended results and impacts, and more generally to any other strength or weakness. A conclusion draws on data collection and analyses undertaken, through a transparent chain of arguments. See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1356389013493840">OECD (2010)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1356389013493840">
<label>8.</label>
<p>The C + M = O ‘equation’ constitutes <italic>‘</italic>the hypothesis that the programme works (O) because of the action of some underlying mechanisms (M), which only comes into operation in particular contexts (C). If the right processes operate in the right conditions then the programme will prevail… The action of a particular mechanism in a particular context will generate a particular outcome pattern’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1356389013493840">Pawson and Manzano-Santaella, 2012</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1356389013493840">
<label>9.</label>
<p>This step appears in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1356389013493840">Pawson et al.’s (2004)</xref> model as ‘Stage 4. Draw conclusions and make recommendations’.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<p><bold>Julia Betts</bold>, D.Phil, is a consultant at IOD PARC Ltd. Formerly of the UK’s Department for International Development, she specializes in the evaluation of aid and development programmes and policies, and on gender, equity, and exclusion issues within development cooperation.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barnett-Page</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Methods for the synthesis of qualitative research: a critical review</article-title>. <source>BMC Medical Research Methodology</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dixon-Woods</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Synthesising qualitative and quantitative evidence: a review of possible methods</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Services Research and Policy</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <source>Understanding Public Policy</source>. <publisher-loc>New Jersey</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice-Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Floyd</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pilling</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Vocational rehabilitation: what works and in what circumstances</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Rehabilitation Research</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Greenhalgh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westhorp</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pawson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Protocol – realist and meta-narrative evidence synthesis: Evolving Standards (RAMESES)</article-title>. URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com">http://www.biomedcentral.com</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Langille</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winstanley</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Does moving from a high-poverty to lower-poverty neighbourhood improve mental health? A realist review of ‘Moving to Opportunity’</article-title>. <source>Health &amp; Place</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>961</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lavis</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>How can we support the use of systematic reviews in policymaking?</article-title> <source>PLoS Medicine</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>e1000141</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leeman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Voils</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crandell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sandelowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Implementation of antiretroviral therapy adherence interventions: a realist synthesis of evidence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advanced Nursing</source> <volume>66</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1915</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dewar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garbett</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ballantyne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>A Realist Synthesis of Evidence Relating to Practice Development</source>. Final Report To NHS Education for Scotland and NHS Quality Improvement Scotland. URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nhshealthquality.org/nhsqis/3134.html">http://www.nhshealthquality.org/nhsqis/3134.html</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A realist review of evidence to guide targeted approaches to HIV/AIDS prevention among immigrants living in high income countries. Flinders University</article-title>. URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://theses.flinders.edu.au/uploads/approved/adt-SFU20100707.104732/public/02Whole.pdf">http://theses.flinders.edu.au/uploads/approved/adt-SFU20100707.104732/public/02Whole.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mayne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Addressing attribution through contribution analysis: using performance measures sensibly</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Program Evaluation</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mazzocato</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brommels</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aronsson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Lean thinking in healthcare: a realist review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Quality and Safety in Healthcare</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>376</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>OECD</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Evaluating Development Co-operation: Key Norms and Standards</source>. URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oecd.org/development/evaluationofdevelopmentprogrammes/dcdndep/41612905.pdf">http://www.oecd.org/development/evaluationofdevelopmentprogrammes/dcdndep/41612905.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>MQ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012a</year>) <article-title>A utilization-focused approach to contribution analysis</article-title>. <source>Evaluation</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>364</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>MQ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012b</year>) <source>Utilisation-Focused Evaluation</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pawson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Evidence-based policy: the promise of ‘realist synthesis’</article-title>. <source>Evaluation</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pawson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Evidence-Based Policy. A Realist Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pawson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manzano-Santaella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A realist diagnostic workshop</article-title>. <source>Evaluation</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>176</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pawson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tilley</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Realistic evaluation bloodlines</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Evaluation</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pawson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenhalgh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walshe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Realist synthesis: an introduction: RMP Methods Paper 2/2004</source>. <publisher-name>Centre for Census and Survey Research, University of Manchester</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Manchester</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pawson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenhalgh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walshe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Realist review: a new method of systematic review designed for complex policy interventions</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Services Research and Policy</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, with contributions from: Laura Altinger, Osvaldo Feinstein, Marta Marañón, Nils-Sjard Schultz and Nicolai Steen Nielsen (<year>2008</year>) <source>Thematic Study on the Paris Declaration, Aid Effectiveness and Development Effectiveness</source>, <publisher-name>Danish Ministry of Foreign Affairs/OECD</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Paris Declaration Evaluation Phase 2: some sources and accompanying notes</article-title>. <source>Unpublished document produced for Paris Declaration Phase 2 researchers</source>, <month>September</month>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <source>Qualitative Analysis for Social Scientists</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Addressing attribution of cause and effect in small n impact evaluations: towards an integrated framework International Initiative for Impact Evaluation (3iE)</article-title>, Working paper 15, <month>June</month> <year>2012</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenhalgh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westhorp</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buckingham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pawson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>RAMESES publication standards: realist synthesis</article-title>. URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/11/21">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/11/21</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1356389013493840">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pawson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Policy guidance on threats to legislative interventions in public health: a realist synthesis</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>222</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>