<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HFS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphfs</journal-id>
<journal-title>Human Factors: The Journal of Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0018-7208</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1547-8181</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0018720811434513</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0018720811434513</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Psychological States and Neuroergonomics</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Play Experience Scale</article-title>
<subtitle>Development and Validation of a Measure of Play</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Pavlas</surname><given-names>Davin</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Jentsch</surname><given-names>Florian</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Salas</surname><given-names>Eduardo</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>Stephen M.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>Valerie</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0018720811434513">University of Central Florida, Orlando</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0018720811434513">Davin Pavlas, University of Central Florida, Department of Psychology, Institute for Simulation and Training, 3100 Technology Parkway, Orlando, FL 32826; e-mail: <email>davin@pavlas.com</email>.</corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-0018720811434513">
<p>Davin Pavlas is a graduate of the Applied Experimental and Human Factors Psychology doctoral program at the University of Central Florida. He obtained his PhD in 2010 through a dissertation that established a model of flow and play in games for learning. As a researcher at the Institute for Simulation and Training, he worked on a variety of projects that examine teams using simulations. To date, his research has examined the relationship between aesthetics and usability in user interfaces, the nature of flow state in games, the attributes of serious games that contribute to learning, and the role of play experience in learning.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio2-0018720811434513">
<p>Florian Jentsch is director of the Team Performance Laboratory and an associate professor of psychology at the University of Central Florida, with a joint appointment in the Department of Psychology and at the Institute for Simulation and Training. He received his PhD in human factors psychology at the University of Central Florida in 1997. He also holds master’s degrees in aeronautical engineering from the Technical University of Berlin and in aeronautical science from Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University. His dissertation for junior flight crewmembers won the American Psychological Association 1998 George E. Briggs Award for the best dissertation in applied or experimental psychology. He also won the American Psychological Association Earl Allusi Award in 2002 for early career achievement. He has coauthored more than 150 publications, presentations, and technical reports, with research ranging from pilot training and aviation research to transportation security X-ray baggage screening and human robot teaming.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio3-0018720811434513">
<p>Eduardo Salas is the trustee chair and a professor of psychology at the University of Central Florida, where he also holds an appointment as program director for the Human Systems Integration Research Department at the Institute for Simulation and Training. Previously, he was the director of the University of Central Florida’s Applied Experimental and Human Factors PhD Program. Before joining the Institute for Simulation and Training, he was a senior research psychologist and head of the Training Technology Development Branch of the Naval Air Warfare Center Training Systems Division for 15 years. He has coauthored more than 300 journal articles and book chapters and has coedited 19 books. His expertise includes assisting organizations in how to foster teamwork, design and implement team training strategies, facilitate training effectiveness, manage decision making under stress, and develop performance measurement tools. He received his PhD in industrial and organizational psychology at Old Dominion University in 1984.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio4-0018720811434513">
<p>Stephen M. Fiore is on the faculty of the University of Central Florida’s Cognitive Sciences Program in the Department of Philosophy and is the director of the Cognitive Sciences Laboratory at the University of Central Florida’s Institute for Simulation and Training. He earned his PhD degree (2000) in cognitive psychology from the University of Pittsburgh, Learning Research and Development Center.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio5-0018720811434513">
<p>Valerie Sims is the director of the Applied Cognition and Technology Laboratory and an associate professor of psychology at the University of Central Florida. Her research centers primarily on individual differences in spatial ability and human-robot interaction. She received her PhD in applied cognitive psychology from the University of California, Santa Barbara, in 1996.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>54</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>214</fpage>
<lpage>225</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>18</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>11</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><bold>Objective</bold>: A measure of play experience in video games was developed through literature review and two empirical validation studies.</p>
<p><bold>Background</bold>: Despite the considerable attention given to games in the behavioral sciences, play experience remains empirically underexamined. One reason for this gap is the absence of a scale that measures play experience.</p>
<p><bold>Method</bold>: In Study 1, the initial Play Experience Scale (PES) was tested through an online validation that featured three different games (<italic>N</italic> = 203). In Study 2, a revised PES was assessed with a serious game in the laboratory (<italic>N</italic> = 77).</p>
<p><bold>Results</bold>: Through principal component analysis of the Study 1 data, the initial 20-item PES was revised, resulting in the 16-item PES-16. Study 2 showed the PES-16 to be a robust instrument with the same patterns of correlations as in Study 1 via (a) internal consistency estimates, (b) correlations with established scales of motivation, (c) distributions of PES-16 scores in different game conditions, and (d) examination of the average variance extracted of the PES and the Intrinsic Motivation Scale.</p>
<p><bold>Conclusion</bold>: We suggest that the PES is appropriate for use in further validation studies. Additional examinations of the scale are required to determine its applicability to other contexts and its relationship with other constructs.</p>
<p><bold>Application</bold>: The PES is potentially relevant to human factors undertakings involving video games, including basic research into play, games, and learning; prototype testing; and exploratory learning studies.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>serious games</kwd>
<kwd>play</kwd>
<kwd>measure</kwd>
<kwd>motivation</kwd>
<kwd>game</kwd>
<kwd>PES</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0018720811434513" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Play is an essential component of the human experience. Humans seek play not only as children but also as adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0018720811434513">Anderson, 1998</xref>). Play can even be found outside of the human species, as animals have been shown to engage in spontaneous play (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0018720811434513">Van Leeuwen &amp; Westwood, 2008</xref>). Despite the pervasiveness of play activities, there is a surprising paucity of play assessment instruments in the literature. Although there are measures of playfulness (i.e., the propensity of an individual to engage in play; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0018720811434513">Webster &amp; Martocchio, 1992</xref>), and observational ratings scales for child play exist throughout the developmental literature (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0018720811434513">Knox, 1997</xref>), a self-report scale of play behavior is markedly absent. This gap is even more surprising given the recent surge in investigations into the science of games (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0018720811434513">Chertoff, Jerome, Martin, &amp; Knerr, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0018720811434513">Cotton, Mayes, Jentsch, &amp; Sims, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0018720811434513">Pavlas, Heyne, Bedwell, Lazzara, &amp; Salas, 2010</xref>). Although the human factors community has embraced games for training (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0018720811434513">Gopher, Weil, &amp; Bareket, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0018720811434513">Lampton, Bliss, Orvis, Kring, &amp; Glenn, 2009</xref>) and examined the basic science of games, the field has not more closely examined the psychological correlates of game play.</p>
<p>The present research expands on these recent undertakings through the development and initial validation of the Play Experience Scale (PES). First, a brief description of the construct of play is provided. Then, the contents of the initial prototype are described, as are two empirical studies to test its validity and establish its psychometric properties. Finally, results and implications for future research are presented.</p>
<sec id="section2-0018720811434513">
<title>Play</title>
<p>Intuitively, play is simple to recognize. Defining play in a scientifically useful manner is more difficult. On the most basic level, play is an intrinsically motivated (autotelic) activity free of extrinsic goals or consequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0018720811434513">O’Connor &amp; LaPoint, 1980</xref>), even though extrinsic motivators are often present in sports, games for learning, and performances, that is, in activities that also include play as a component. These activities can further be characterized on the basis of the player’s degree of attention, that is, whether it is focused on his or her play behavior rather than external needs or goals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0018720811434513">Calleja, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0018720811434513">Cowley, Charles, Black, &amp; Hickey, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Beyond attention and motivation, the notion of freedom within rule frames is key to understanding play (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0018720811434513">Gordon, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0018720811434513">Salen &amp; Zimmerman, 2004</xref>). Zimmerman describes play as “the free space of movement within a more rigid structure,” noting that “play exists because of and also despite the more rigid structures of a system” (Zimmerman, as cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0018720811434513">Esposito, 2005</xref>, p. 3). Finally, play may be construed as a modifier for other behaviors rather than as its own behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0018720811434513">Millar, 1968</xref>). This distinction is important, as it establishes that play is not a behavior unto itself but rather something that can contain a wide range of behaviors. Even work activities can be play; given, however, that work is often considered the opposite of play (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0018720811434513">Gitlin-Weiner, 1998</xref>), it is reasonable to assume that work-play is “less” playlike because of its explicit external contingencies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0018720811434513">
<title>Scale Constructs and Content</title>
<p>On the basis of the play literature described in the preceding section, we defined play as behaviors that (a) are predominantly intrinsically motivated, (b) are performed freely by the player, (c) require and capture the player’s attention, and (d) are not contingent by external rewards or consequences. Using these four definitional elements (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0018720811434513">Table 1</xref>), we developed a candidate PES. Responses to the 20 items of the PES-20 were indicated via a 6-point Likert-type scale ranging from <italic>strongly disagree</italic> (1) to <italic>strongly agree</italic> (6). Although the items were created for the context of video games, care was taken to ensure that the wordings could be changed to refer to other play contexts. In the following sections, the theoretical underpinnings of these categories are discussed.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0018720811434513" position="float">
<label>Table 1:</label>
<caption>
<p>Initial Play Experience Scale</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0018720811434513" xlink:href="10.1177_0018720811434513-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Item Number</th>
<th align="center">Item Text</th>
<th align="center">Dimension/Coding</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>I felt that I was free to use whatever strategy I wanted to while I was using the game</td>
<td>Freedom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>I was able to make the game do what I wanted it to</td>
<td>Freedom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>The game gave me the freedom to act how I wanted to</td>
<td>Freedom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>The game made it difficult to do what I wanted to do</td>
<td>Freedom (R)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>I was not worried about someone judging how I performed in the game</td>
<td>No extrinsic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>Regardless of how I performed in the game, I knew there wouldn’t be a real-world consequence</td>
<td>No extrinsic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>My performance in the game was not going to matter outside of the game</td>
<td>No extrinsic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>I felt like I had to do well, or the experimenter would judge me</td>
<td>No extrinsic (R)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>When I was using the game, it felt like I was playing rather than working</td>
<td>Play-direct</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>I would characterize my experience with the game as “playing”</td>
<td>Play-direct</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>I was playing a game rather than working</td>
<td>Play-direct</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>Using the game felt like work</td>
<td>Play-direct (R)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13</td>
<td>When I was using the game, I didn’t worry about anything in the real world</td>
<td>Focus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14</td>
<td>I was able to concentrate on the game without thinking about other things</td>
<td>Focus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>When I was using the game, I was focused on the task at hand</td>
<td>Focus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td>I had a hard time concentrating on the game</td>
<td>Focus (R)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>17</td>
<td>I wanted to do well in the game, “just because”</td>
<td>Autotelic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18</td>
<td>When I was using the game, I wanted to do as well as possible</td>
<td>Autotelic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>19</td>
<td>I tried to succeed in the game because I felt like it</td>
<td>Autotelic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td>During the game, my performance didn’t matter to me</td>
<td>Autotelic (R)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0018720811434513">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. Reverse-coded items are denoted with an (R).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section4-0018720811434513">
<title>Autotelic experience</title>
<p>The first set of items in the PES-20 assessed intrinsic motivation through the lens of autotelic experience. When an experience is autotelic, an individual engages in it solely for its own rewards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0018720811434513">Cowley et al., 2008</xref>). In other words, the experience is intrinsically motivating (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0018720811434513">Malone, 1981</xref>). Consequently, the wording of the items in this category reflected an internal source of drive (e.g., “I wanted to” and “I felt like”).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0018720811434513">
<title>Freedom</title>
<p>The second set of items targeted freedom. When an individual is free in a play context, he or she is able to perform the actions he or she wishes to perform. The notion of self-determination within the artificial rule set of a play experience is inherent to modern definitions of play (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0018720811434513">Salen &amp; Zimmerman, 2004</xref>) and thus motivated items assessing freedom as a concept. Items in this category reflected this direction, referring to the “wants” of the individual within play as well as his or her ability to act on those wants (e.g., self-determination in leisure motivation; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0018720811434513">Weissinger &amp; Bandalos, 1995</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0018720811434513">
<title>Focus</title>
<p>The focus category targeted the states of immersion, concentration, and attentional narrowing in definitions of play. Immersion is a popular topic in the games literature, describing a state of intense concentration that is related to engagement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0018720811434513">McMahan, 2003</xref>) and flow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0018720811434513">Csikszentmihalyi, 1990</xref>). When an individual is immersed in his or her play experience, the salience of nonplay concerns diminishes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0018720811434513">Cowley et al., 2008</xref>). In other words, individuals who are immersed are focused on the task at hand; their attention and concentration are allocated to the play task. Items in this category reflected this loss of concern and focused concentration.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0018720811434513">
<title>Absence of extrinsic motivation</title>
<p>The fourth set of items was based on the construct of extrinsic motivation. Unlike intrinsic motivation, which emerges from the individual, extrinsic motivation is created through external impositions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0018720811434513">Ryan &amp; Deci, 2000</xref>). Most commonly, these impositions take the form of rewards or punishments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0018720811434513">Benabou &amp; Tirole, 2003</xref>). Items in this category addressed whether the respondents felt there were consequences to their play, whether via evaluative judgment by another entity or through real-world consequences for task performance.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0018720811434513">
<title>Direct play assessment</title>
<p>The last set of questions in the draft PES assessed whether the individual believed he or she engaged in play. Unlike the others, this category did not target any particular aspect of play but simply play itself. Because of the relative scarcity of play research, there was little to guide the creation of these questions other than the inherent opposition between work and play (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0018720811434513">O’Connor &amp; LaPoint, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0018720811434513">Yee, 2005</xref>). Additionally, these items directly referenced play, whereas the other four categories did not directly employ the word <italic>play</italic>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0018720811434513">
<title>Study 1</title>
<p>The 20-item PES-20 was tested via a game-based experiment to establish its psychometric properties and theoretical alignment.</p>
<sec id="section10-0018720811434513">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section11-0018720811434513">
<title>Participant</title>
<p>For Study 1, 226 undergraduates (80 male, 146 female) enrolled at the University of Central Florida participated for course credit. Participants’ ages ranged from 18 to 58 years, with a mean age of 21.02 years (<italic>SD</italic> = 4.95).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0018720811434513">
<title>Materials</title>
<p>We used three games as the conditions for the study: (a) a Flash version of the classic computer game <italic>Tetris</italic>, (b) the adaptive game <italic>flOw</italic>, and (c) a custom-designed letter search task. The search task was purposely designed to be “boring,” comprising only the minimum elements required to make the task a game (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0018720811434513">Garris, Ahlers, &amp; Driskell, 2002</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0018720811434513">
<title>Measures</title>
<p>To determine the psychometric properties and theoretical alignment of the PES, the PES-20 was joined by measures assessing playfulness, intrinsic motivation, and extrinsic motivation.</p>
<list id="list1-0018720811434513" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><italic>Computer Playfulness Scale (CPS)</italic>. As a measure of trait playfulness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0018720811434513">Webster &amp; Martocchio, 1992</xref>), the CPS served as a potential indicator of the PES’s suitability. The seven-item Likert-type scale was anchored from <italic>strongly disagree</italic> (1) to <italic>strongly agree</italic> (7).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Intrinsic Motivation Scale (IMS).</italic> Given the importance of intrinsic motivation to the definition of play, a measure thereof was key to establishing the PES’s validity. An outcome IMS measuring respondent reaction to items assessing interest, tension, effort, and competence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0018720811434513">McAuley, Duncan, &amp; Tammen, 1989</xref>) was used. The 18-item scale had six Likert-type anchors ranging from <italic>strongly disagree</italic> to <italic>strongly agree</italic>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Situational Motivation Scale (SIMS).</italic> The external regulation and amotivation components of the SIMS served as the study’s measure of extrinsic motivation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0018720811434513">Guay, Vallerand, &amp; Blanchard, 2000</xref>). The 16-item scale had six Likert-type anchors ranging from <italic>strongly disagree</italic> to <italic>strongly agree</italic>.</p></list-item></list>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0018720811434513">
<title>Design</title>
<p>The experiment used a 3 × 2 mixed-model design. The between-subjects variable was game type with three levels (i.e., <italic>Tetris</italic> vs. <italic>flOw</italic> vs. letter search task). The two-level within-subjects variable was trial block (first vs. second).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0018720811434513">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>Participants were assigned to one of the three game conditions. After providing answers to demographics and the CPS, participants were tasked with playing their assigned game for 5 min and completing three measures: the PES-20, IMS, and SIMS. Participants then played a second 5-min round and again completed the PES-20, IMS, and SIMS.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0018720811434513">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Of the 226 participants, 203 provided complete data sets (i.e., completed both game rounds and surveys). There were no significant differences between participants who completed and those who dropped from the experiment in terms of age, gender, or condition. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0018720811434513">Table 2</xref> shows the means, standard deviations, and correlations among the primary study variables. For the following analyses, the second-round responses were used (unless otherwise noted).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0018720811434513" position="float">
<label>Table 2:</label>
<caption>
<p>Study 1 Means, Standard Deviations, and Correlations</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0018720811434513" xlink:href="10.1177_0018720811434513-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center">Age</th>
<th align="center">Gender<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0018720811434513">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Gamer</th>
<th align="center">Playful</th>
<th align="center">PES R1</th>
<th align="center">PES R2</th>
<th align="center">Motiv R1</th>
<th align="center">Motiv R2</th>
<th align="center">Ext R1</th>
<th align="center">Ext R2</th>
<th align="center">Amot R1</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>21.01</td>
<td>4.95</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gender<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0018720811434513">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>−.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gamer</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td>.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">*</xref></td>
<td>−.48<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Playful</td>
<td>5.59</td>
<td>0.78</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PES R1</td>
<td>4.36</td>
<td>0.78</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PES R2</td>
<td>4.22</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">**</xref></td>
<td>.73<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Motiv R1</td>
<td>3.82</td>
<td>0.76</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.67<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>.61<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Motiv R2</td>
<td>3.76</td>
<td>0.84</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">*</xref></td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>.64<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>.79<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>.80<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ext R1</td>
<td>3.55</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>−.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">**</xref></td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>−.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">*</xref></td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>−.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>−.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>−.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>−.37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ext R2</td>
<td>3.51</td>
<td>1.15</td>
<td>−.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>−.10</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>−.11</td>
<td>−.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">**</xref></td>
<td>−.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">**</xref></td>
<td>−.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>.76<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Amot R1</td>
<td>3.29</td>
<td>1.03</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>−.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>−.41<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>−.43<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>−.46<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>.60<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>.48<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Amot R2</td>
<td>3.36</td>
<td>1.08</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>−.10</td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>−.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>−.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>−.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>−.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>.52<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>.58<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>.72<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0018720811434513">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. R1 = Round 1; R2 = Round 2; Playful = Computer Playfulness Scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0018720811434513">Webster &amp; Martocchio, 1992</xref>); Gamer = self-reported gamer status from demographics; PES = Play Experience Scale; Motiv = intrinsic motivation; Ext = Situational Motivation Scale (SIMS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0018720811434513">Guay, Vallerand, &amp; Blanchard, 2000</xref>) External Regulation; Amot = SIMS Amotivation.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0018720811434513">
<label>a</label>
<p>Gender shows correlations for female participants (0 = male, 1 = female).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0018720811434513">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section17-0018720811434513">
<title>Data screening</title>
<p>First, the data were assessed for their suitability for factor analyses. Of the 20 items, 19 were significantly correlated (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05) at least <italic>r</italic>(201) = .25 with another item, suggesting their suitability for factor analysis. Similarly, the Kaiser-Meyer-Olkin measure of sampling adequacy was .88, which was well above the recommended value of .60. Finally, Bartlett’s test of sphericity was significant, χ<sup>2</sup>(190) = 2256.83, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. On the basis of these statistics, we deemed factor analysis appropriate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0018720811434513">
<title>Candidate scale structure and pruning</title>
<p>The underlying structure of the scale was examined to determine whether it reflected the previously defined dimensions. A principal component analysis (PCA) extraction with manual five-component truncation was followed by oblique rotation via Promax (because of expected intercorrelations). Results suggested that the original five-factor theory was not represented in the data. Instead, the first component consisted of a merging of the Focus and Autotelic Experience subscales. The fifth component of the scale consisted of the reverse-coded items of the scale.</p>
<p>Next, we pruned the scale to remove four flawed or ineffective items: Item 16 failed to load onto any of the components and was dropped alongside Component 1’s three lowest-loading items. These changes resulted in a symmetrical 16-item scale (PES-16), which was examined once more using PCA with Promax rotation. In this iteration, only the components with eigenvalue &gt; 1 were retained, which removed Item 4 from the scale because of its ambiguous loading pattern. A test of the diagnosticity of each element of the scale for the game condition variable via multiple linear regression (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0018720811434513">Table 3</xref>) further removed Item 1.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0018720811434513" position="float">
<label>Table 3:</label>
<caption>
<p>Play Experience Scale Individual Item–Game Condition Regression</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0018720811434513" xlink:href="10.1177_0018720811434513-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Item Number</th>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>0.29</td>
<td>.77</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>.15</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>6.64</td>
<td>.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.27</td>
<td>3.99</td>
<td>.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.17</td>
<td>2.47</td>
<td>.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0018720811434513">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>.32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>.61</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>1.84</td>
<td>.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>.17</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>.17</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.36</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>17</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>19</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-0018720811434513">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. All regressions run individually to determine univariate impact. For all cases, <italic>df</italic> = 1201.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0018720811434513">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>We then conducted a final PCA using Promax to examine the properties of the resultant 14-item scale (PES-14). Although the scale was not symmetrical (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0018720811434513">Table 4</xref>), its items loaded cleanly onto theory-consistent components. A confirmatory factor analysis of the four-factor model suggested the PES-14 showed good fit, χ<sup>2</sup>(71) = 158, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 (goodness-of-fit index = 90; standardized root mean residual = .06). This version of the scale was also significantly and positively correlated with playfulness, <italic>r</italic>(201) = .20, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. Given these indicators, the PES-14 was used for further analysis.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0018720811434513" position="float">
<label>Table 4:</label>
<caption>
<p>Principal Component Analysis: 14-Item Play Experience Scale</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0018720811434513" xlink:href="10.1177_0018720811434513-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Item Number</th>
<th align="center">C1</th>
<th align="center">C2</th>
<th align="center">C3</th>
<th align="center">C4</th>
<th align="center">Communality</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>.87</td>
<td>.81</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>−.10</td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.94</td>
<td>.80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>.76</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>.67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>.67</td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>.43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>.36</td>
<td>−.36</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td>.15</td>
<td>.55</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>−.30</td>
<td>.27</td>
<td>.79</td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>.67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>.79</td>
<td>−.02</td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>.81</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>.17</td>
<td>.76</td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>.82</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>.75</td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.82</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>.90</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>.73</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>.72</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>.71</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>17</td>
<td>.83</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>.74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18</td>
<td>.91</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>.81</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>19</td>
<td>.90</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>−.14</td>
<td>.76</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn7-0018720811434513">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. Factor loadings &gt;.40 shaded. Oblique rotation conducted with use of the Promax function. The four components accounted for 72.41% of the total variance in the 14 items. C1 = Component 1; C2 = Component 2; C3 = Component 3; C4 = Component 4.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0018720811434513">
<title>Reliability</title>
<p>Responses to the scale were very slightly skewed (skew = −0.05) and mildly platykurtic (kurtosis = −0.57). Cronbach’s alpha was calculated for both administrations of the PES-14. The reliability estimates for the both administrations of the PES-14 were high: Alpha equaled .83 in the first and .86 in the second administration of the PES-14. Test-retest reliability was established by examining correlations between the first and second administrations of the PES-14, <italic>r</italic>(201) = .73, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0018720811434513">
<title>Convergent validity</title>
<p>As the construct of play is conceptually similar to that of state-based intrinsic motivation, correlations between the PES and the IMS were calculated (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0018720811434513">Table 5</xref>). The correlation between the scales was high, <italic>r</italic>(201) = .79, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, supporting the convergent validity of the scale. In addition, the PES-14 and the state-based Amotivation subscale of the SIMS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0018720811434513">Guay et al., 2000</xref>) were negatively correlated, <italic>r</italic>(201) = –.35, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. Finally, the PES-14’s relationship to the state-based External Regulation (e.g., extrinsic motivation) subscale of the SIMS was negative, <italic>r</italic>(201) = –.20, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. Since theory suggests that play is positively related to intrinsic motivation but negatively to external regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0018720811434513">O’Connor &amp; LaPoint, 1980</xref>), convergent validity was supported.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-0018720811434513" position="float">
<label>Table 5:</label>
<caption>
<p>Scale Correlations, Round 2</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0018720811434513" xlink:href="10.1177_0018720811434513-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">PES-14</th>
<th align="center">PES-4</th>
<th align="center">Playfulness</th>
<th align="center">IMS</th>
<th align="center">SIMS External</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>PES-14</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PES-4</td>
<td>.76<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Playfulness</td>
<td>.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0018720811434513">**</xref></td>
<td>.12</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IMS</td>
<td>.79<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>.63<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>.10</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SIMS External</td>
<td>−.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0018720811434513">**</xref></td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>−.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SIMS Amotivation</td>
<td>−.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>−.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>−.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
<td>.58<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0018720811434513">***</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn8-0018720811434513">
<p><italic>Note. N</italic> = 203. Two-tailed significance values reported. PES-14 = 14-item Play Experience Scale; PES-4 = 4-item Play Experience Scale; IMS = Intrinsic Motivation Scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0018720811434513">McAuley, Duncan, &amp; Tammen, 1989</xref>); SIMS = Situational Motivation Scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0018720811434513">Guay, Vallerand, &amp; Blanchard, 2000</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn9-0018720811434513">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0018720811434513">
<title>Discriminant validity</title>
<p>We assessed the discriminant validity of the PES-14 by comparing the average variance extracted (AVE; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0018720811434513">Farrell, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0018720811434513">Fornell &amp; Larcker, 1981</xref>) with the squared correlation of the PES-14 and the IMS. We calculated AVE values using Construct Validity Calculator 2.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0018720811434513">Md-Basir et al., 2010</xref>). The 14-item PES had an AVE of 0.68; the IMS’s AVE was 0.77 (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0018720811434513">Table 5</xref> for scale correlations). Both of these were higher than the squared correlation between PES and IMS, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = .62. Thus, although the two scales were highly correlated, the PES and IMS showed discriminant validity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0018720811434513">
<title>Construct validity</title>
<p>Because another measure of play, as such, did not exist, we assessed construct validity by comparing PES aggregated means in the two game conditions (designed to involve play) with the search task condition (as “play-free” as possible) via ANOVA. Mean scores for the combined game conditions (<italic>M</italic>
<sub>Games</sub> = 4.56, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.73) were significantly higher than for the search task condition (<italic>M</italic>
<sub>Search Task</sub> = 3.57, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.57), <italic>F</italic>(1, 201) = 96.94, η<sup>2</sup> = .32, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. Construct validity was also assessed by the correlation between playfulness as measured by the CPS and the PES-14, <italic>r</italic>(201) = .20, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0018720811434513">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The purpose of Study 1 was to examine the psychometric properties of the initial, theoretically derived PES. After it was pruned to 14 items, the scale showed high reliability and correlated with existing measures of theoretically related constructs. Furthermore, Study 1 provided evidence of good discriminant, convergent, and predictive validity from the relationships of the PES-14 with established scales of motivation and playfulness and the study manipulation. As expected, the PES-14 was positively correlated with intrinsic motivation (IMS) and playfulness (CPS) but negatively correlated with the amotivation and external regulation components of the SIMS. These results align with theory.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0018720811434513">
<title>Study 2</title>
<p>Study 1 suggested that the 14-item version of the PES could serve as an adequate and meaningful measure of play experience in video games. However, because the PES-14 was nonsymmetrical, the impact of the freedom dimension (with only 2 items) might be underestimated in overall PES-14 scores unless practitioners averaged within each scale first. Consequently, we developed a symmetrical, 16-item version (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-0018720811434513">Table 6</xref>) of the scale by adding 2 items to the freedom dimension. To avoid introducing new concepts to the scale, the items added were similar to the two freedom items already present in the scale (i.e., focused on the player being able to make the game do what he or she wanted to do). In Study 2, we tested whether adding the items had resulted in any change to the scale’s reliability or validity. We also increased the generalizability of the Study 2 findings by using a previously developed serious game, <italic>InnerCell</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0018720811434513">Pavlas et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table6-0018720811434513" position="float">
<label>Table 6:</label>
<caption>
<p>Play Experience Scale 16-Item Version</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-0018720811434513" xlink:href="10.1177_0018720811434513-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Item Number</th>
<th align="center">Item Text</th>
<th align="center">Dimension/Coding</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>If I wanted to do something in the game, I was able to do it</td>
<td>Freedom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>I was able to make the game do what I wanted it to</td>
<td>Freedom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>The game gave me the freedom to act how I wanted to</td>
<td>Freedom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>The game made it difficult to perform the actions that I wanted to</td>
<td>Freedom (R)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>I was not worried about someone judging how I performed in the game</td>
<td>No extrinsic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>Regardless of how I performed in the game, I knew there wouldn’t be a real-world consequence</td>
<td>No extrinsic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>My performance in the game was not going to matter outside of the game</td>
<td>No extrinsic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>I felt like I had to do well, or the experimenter would judge me</td>
<td>No extrinsic (R)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>When I was using the game, it felt like I was playing rather than working</td>
<td>Play-direct</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>I would characterize my experience with the game as playing</td>
<td>Play-direct</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>I was playing a game rather than working</td>
<td>Play-direct</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>Using the game felt like work</td>
<td>Play-direct (R)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13</td>
<td>When I was using the game, I was focused on the task at hand</td>
<td>Autotelic–Focus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14</td>
<td>I wanted to do well in the game, “just because”</td>
<td>Autotelic–Focus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>When I was using the game, I wanted to do as well as possible</td>
<td>Autotelic–Focus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td>I tried to succeed in the game because I felt like it</td>
<td>Autotelic–Focus</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn10-0018720811434513">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. Item numbers do not correspond to original item numbers because of removal of original items. R indicates item was reverse-coded.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section25-0018720811434513">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section26-0018720811434513">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>A sample of 77 undergraduate volunteers (36 male, 41 female) enrolled at the University of Central Florida participated in Study 2 for course credit. They ranged in age from 18 to 27 years (<italic>M</italic> = 18.84 yrs, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.71).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-0018720811434513">
<title>Materials</title>
<p><italic>InnerCell</italic> is a strategy game that requires players to learn about the immune system while defending a patient’s body from infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0018720811434513">Pavlas et al., 2010</xref>). Players direct the body’s immune cells to defeat pathogens, with each pathogen being vulnerable to a particular combination of cells and treatments. Each successive round of game play increases in difficulty and complexity, providing new pathogens and options.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section28-0018720811434513">
<title>Measures</title>
<p>As Study 2 was not only a validation effort for the PES but also an investigation of a theoretical model of learning and behavior in serious games, several additional measures were employed. However, for the purposes of this second validation effort, we report only on those measures meaningful to the validation. These were the 16-item revision of the PES (PES-16), the CPS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0018720811434513">Webster &amp; Martocchio, 1992</xref>), and the IMS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0018720811434513">McAuley et al., 1989</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-0018720811434513">
<title>Design</title>
<p>This validation effort was part of a nonexperimental study examining participant behaviors and states across a variety of dimensions (e.g., play, motivation, emotion, performance) within the <italic>InnerCell</italic> serious game. Given this design, there was no manipulated independent variable. Participants engaged in game play across three rounds, with a variety of measures, including the PES, collected after each round.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section30-0018720811434513">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>Participants completed a short set of demographic and other premeasures and viewed a simple training video explaining the <italic>InnerCell</italic> game. They then played the game for three full rounds. Between each round, participants responded to the PES. Finally, participants completed the intrinsic motivation measure and learning assessments.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section31-0018720811434513">
<title>Results</title>
<p>As previously noted, two items had been added to the PES-14 to make it symmetrical. The revised 16-item PES-16 (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-0018720811434513">Table 6</xref>) was very highly correlated with the PES-14, <italic>r</italic> = .99, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. Furthermore, mean scores of the PES-16 (<italic>M</italic> = 4.61, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.69) were significantly and positively correlated with intrinsic motivation (IMS; <italic>M</italic> = 4.07, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.76), <italic>r</italic> = .66, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. On the basis of item-total correlation, the two new items (Items 1 and 4) were meaningful contributors to the overall scale: Item 1, <italic>r</italic>(74) = .74, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001; Item 2, <italic>r</italic>(74) = .53, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. Given the correlation between the 14-item and the 16-item versions of the scale and the item-total correlations, it was reasonable to suggest that the 16-item version of the scale did not reduce the validity of the PES.</p>
<p>Cronbach’s alphas for each of the three administrations of the 16-item version of the scale were calculated, ranging from .86 to .90 (Round 1, α = .90; Round 2, α = .89; Round 3, α = .86). For comparison, alphas for the 14-item version of the scale were also calculated (Round 1, α = .89; Round 2, α = .88; Round 3, α = .86). These scores also indicated good reliability.</p>
<p>The utility of the extrinsic motivation items of the PES was also examined. These items were identical in both the PES-14 and the PES-16. In Study 1, the extrinsic motivation items were not strongly related to the PES. Consequently, in Study 2, item-total correlations for the scale were examined to ascertain whether the change in game context resulted in greater meaning for these items. Items 5 through 8 showed more reasonable item-total correlations (ranging from .38 to .60) in this outcome-oriented context, suggesting they be retained in the final version of the scale.</p>
<p>Finally, the link between playfulness and play was examined. The correlation between mean scores on the CPS and the PES-16 was the same as in Study 1, <italic>r</italic> = .20, but not statistically significant in Study 2, <italic>r</italic>(72) =.20, <italic>p</italic> = .09, because of its smaller sample size (<italic>df</italic><sub>Study1</sub> = 201 vs. <italic>df</italic><sub>Study2</sub> = 72).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section32-0018720811434513">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Study 2 served to provide additional validation of the PES. Although factor analysis was not possible because of sample size restrictions, evidence based on correlations suggested that the two items added to the scale did not alter its meaning or psychometric properties.</p>
<p>Study 2 also added a learning evaluation that provided participants with a degree of external motivation and addressed concerns about Study 1’s lack of context for the external motivation items. This evaluation also increased the generalizability of the results from Study 2 to other game contexts.</p>
<p>The lack of a significant correlation between playfulness and play in Study 2 appeared to present a problematic result at first. The actual correlations between play and playfulness, however, were approximately the same in both Study 1 and Study 2 (<italic>r</italic> = .20); only the probability values were different because of different sample sizes. Indeed, a sample size of at least 150 is required to detect a significant correlation of .20 at alpha = .05 and beta = .20. Although this finding was encouraging, correlations of .20 explain only 4% of the variance in play by playfulness. This rather low value may be attributable to several reasons: First, the link between actual behavior and an individual’s traits or attitudes can be weak (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0018720811434513">Ajzen &amp; Fishbein, 1977</xref>) or complicated by external factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0018720811434513">Kraus, 1995</xref>). Second, the low correlations may suggest limited construct validity of the CPS, a concern previously mentioned in the literature (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0018720811434513">Kruger, 1995</xref>). Further research will be required to delve into the relationship between playfulness and play.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section33-0018720811434513" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Overall Discussion</title>
<p>The research reported here was conducted to fill a particular need: Until now, no scale measuring the subjective experience of play existed. Although it was possible to measure playfulness (i.e., propensity to play), no measure was available to assess an individual’s manifested play behavior. The PES was created on the basis of a number of definitions of play, with an emphasis placed on using concepts that were tied to established psychological theory.</p>
<p>In two validation studies, the PES’s relationships to existing measures of intrinsic motivation, external regulation, and amotivation emerged as expected. As suggested by theory, play behavior was positively correlated with intrinsic motivation, negatively correlated with external regulation, and negatively correlated with amotivation. The scale was also sensitive to variations in task characteristics in that the restricted, tedious, and decidedly “nonplay” word search task in Study 1 was associated with lower PES scores.</p>
<sec id="section34-0018720811434513">
<title>Limitations and Future Research</title>
<p>Although the validation efforts reported in this article were fruitful, additional investigations into the PES are warranted. First, even though the scale was validated in four video game contexts, it is still in need of validation in other settings. In particular, this effort examined the utility of the PES only within the context of video games. However, play is observed across the full range of human experience. Future research efforts should examine the PES in other contexts (e.g., music, performance, sport, work).</p>
<p>Second, the scale was examined with a relatively limited population (i.e., young college students). The scale may have different psychometric properties when employed with different populations. Future research should investigate how the PES functions for different kinds of respondents.</p>
<p>Third, play as measured by the PES and the propensity for “playfulness” (here measured by the CPS) showed only relatively small correlations between the two measures (<italic>r</italic> ≈ .20) in both studies. Further research is required to determine whether this finding reflects the actual magnitude of the relationship between the two constructs, is attributable to external factors influencing trait-behavior correlations, or is a sign of validity issues for the CPS (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0018720811434513">Kruger, 1995</xref>) or the PES-16.</p>
<p>Finally, although the PES-16 consists of four subscales, we do not suggest that these subscales be used diagnostically, as they were not validated for such use. Validation against nonsubjective measures of emotional experience may provide further evidence to determine the overall appropriateness of the PES. For example, modeling emotional experience through physiological indicators, such as galvanic skin response, electromyography, and heart rate, can provide additional insight into how individuals respond to play experiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0018720811434513">Mandryk &amp; Atkins, 2007</xref>). Tying these objective measures of experience to the newly developed subjective measure of play would provide an excellent addition to the present validation efforts.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section35-0018720811434513" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The PES fills a conspicuous gap in the game literature. Because play is one of the defining characteristics of games (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0018720811434513">Ang, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0018720811434513">Baranauskas, Neto, &amp; Borges, 1999</xref>), the tool set available to researchers investigating game-based learning is incomplete without a method by which to investigate play. With the creation and validation of this new scale, it is now possible for researchers to directly examine play experiences in games using a simple posttask measure. Furthermore, the general lack of play studies is indicative of a large theoretical gap in the literature. The introduction of a scale that assesses play experience will hopefully spark a surge of interest into investigating how play influences a wide range of behaviors, states, and experiences.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section36-0018720811434513">
<title>Key Points</title>
<list id="list2-0018720811434513" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Although games are a subject of growing interest to the field, the study of games is constrained by the lack of a measure of play as a subjective experience.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The 16-item version of the Play Experience Scale (PES-16) is a short yet valid and reliable measure of play in conventional video games.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The Computer Playfulness Scale may require further examination, as extant concerns about its validity were corroborated by this study.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Further validation and modification of the PES is required for use in contexts other than video games.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>The <italic>InnerCell</italic> game used in this study was created as a result of earlier research that was partially supported by Subcontract No. 0450-1382 from Aptima under prime contract from the Naval Air Warfare Center, Contract No. N68335-07-C-0444. All opinions expressed in this article are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the official position of the University of Central Florida, Aptima, or the Department of Defense.</p></ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The meaning of play as a human experience</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fromberg</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bergen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Play from birth to twelve and beyond: Contexts, perspectives, and meanings</source> (pp. <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Garland</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ang</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Rules, gameplay, and narratives in video games</article-title>. <source>Simulation &amp; Gaming</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>306</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>. doi:10.1177/1046878105285604<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1046878105285604</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Azjen</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fishbein</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <article-title>Attitude-behavior relations: A theoretical analysis and review of empirical research</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>888</fpage>–<lpage>918</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baranauskas</surname><given-names>M. C. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>N. G. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>M. A. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Learning at work through a multi-user synchronous simulation game</article-title>. In <conf-name>Proceedings of the PEG 99 Conference</conf-name> (pp. <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Exeter, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Exeter</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benabou</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tirole</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Intrinsic and extrinsic motivation</article-title>. <source>Review of Economic Studies</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>489</fpage>–<lpage>520</lpage>. doi:10.1111/1467-937X.00253<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1467-937X.00253</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Calleja</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Revising immersion: A conceptual model for the analysis of digital game involvement</article-title>. In <conf-name>Proceedings of the DiGRA 2007 Conference</conf-name> (pp. <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The University of Tokyo</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chertoff</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jerome</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Knerr</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>GamePAB: A game-based performance assessment battery application</article-title>. In <conf-name>Proceedings of the Human Factors and Ergonomics Society 52 nd Annual Meeting</conf-name> (pp. <fpage>1570</fpage>–<lpage>1573</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Santa Monica, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cotton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mayes</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jentsch</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The relationship between video game characteristics and player ability</article-title>. In <conf-name>Proceedings of the Human Factors and Ergonomics Society 47th Annual Meeting</conf-name> (pp. <fpage>945</fpage>–<lpage>947</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Santa Monica, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cowley</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Toward an understanding of flow in video games</article-title>. <source>Computers in Entertainment</source>, <volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <comment>Article 20</comment>. doi:10.1145/1371216.1371223<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/1371216.1371223</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Csikszentmihalyi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>Flow: The psychology of optimal experience</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harper Perennial</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A short and simple definition of what a videogame is</article-title>. In <source>Proceedings of the DiGRA 2005 Conference: Changing Views—Worlds at Play</source>. <publisher-loc>Vancouver</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Vancouver</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.digra.org/dl/order_by_author?publication=Changing%20Views:%20Worlds%20in%20Play">http://www.digra.org/dl/order_by_author?publication=Changing%20Views:%20Worlds%20in%20Play</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Insufficient discriminant validity: A comment on Bove, Pervan, Beatty, and Shiu (2009)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business Research</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>324</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage>. doi:10.1016/j.jbusres.2009.05.003<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbusres.2009.05.003</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fornell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larcker</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>Evaluating structural equation models with unobservable variables and measurement error</article-title>. <source>Journal of Market Research</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>. doi:10.2307/3151312<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3151312</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Garris</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahlers</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Driskell</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Games, motivation, and learning: A research and practice model</article-title>. <source>Simulation &amp; Gaming</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>467</lpage>. doi:10.1177/1046878102238607<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1046878102238607</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gitlin-Weiner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Clinical perspectives on play</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fromberg</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bergen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Play from birth to twelve and beyond: Contexts, perspectives, and meanings</source> (pp. <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Garland</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gopher</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weil</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bareket</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Transfer of skill from a computer game trainer to flight</article-title>. <source>Human Factors</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>405</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>What is play? In search of a universal definition</article-title>. <source>Play and Culture Studies</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guay</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vallerand</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>On the assessment of situational intrinsic and extrinsic motivation: The situational motivation scale (SIMS)</article-title>. <source>Motivation and Emotion</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Development and current use of the Knox Preschool Play Scale</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Parham</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fazio</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Play in occupational therapy for children</source> (pp. <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>). <publisher-loc>St. Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mosby</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Attitudes and the prediction of behavior: A meta-analysis of the empirical literature</article-title>. <source>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>58</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>. doi:10.1177/0146167295211007<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0146167295211007</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kruger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The Adult Playfulness Scale: A review</article-title>. <source>Psychology: A Journal of Human Behavior</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lampton</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bliss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orvis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kring</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>A distributed game-based simulation training research testbed</article-title>. In <source>Proceedings of the Human Factors and Ergonomics Society 53rd Annual Meeting</source> (pp. <fpage>1989</fpage>–<lpage>1993</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Santa Monica, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>Toward a theory of intrinsically motivating instruction</article-title>. <source>Cognitive Science: A Multidisciplinary Journal</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>. doi:10.1016/S0364-0213(81)80017-1<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0364-0213(81)80017-1</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mandryk</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>A fuzzy physiological approach for continuously modeling emotion during interaction with play technologies</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Human-Computer Studies</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>347</lpage>. doi:10.1016/j.ijhcs.2006.11.011<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijhcs.2006.11.011</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tammen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Causal attributions and affective reactions to disconfirming outcomes in motor performance</article-title>. <source>Journal of Sport and Exercise Psychology</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McMahan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Immersion, engagement and presence: A new method for analyzing 3-D video games</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>M. J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perron</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.) <source>The video game theory reader</source> (pp. <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Md-Basir</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mahzan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mokhtar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abdl-Aziz</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daud</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>The online construct validity calculator Version 2.0</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hishammb.net/cvc2/index.asp">http://www.hishammb.net/cvc2/index.asp</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1968</year>). <source>The psychology of play</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>LaPoint</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>The phenomenon of play: A multi-dimensional definition</article-title>. <source>Recreation Sports Journal</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pavlas</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heyne</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bedwell</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lazzara</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salas</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Game-based learning: The impact of flow state and videogame self-efficacy</article-title>. In <source>Proceedings of the Human Factors and Ergonomics Society 54th Annual Meeting</source> (pp. <fpage>2398</fpage>–<lpage>2402</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Santa Monica, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Intrinsic and extrinsic motivations: Classic definitions and new directions</article-title>. <source>Contemporary Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>. doi:10.1006/ceps.1999.1020<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/ceps.1999.1020</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Rules of play: Game design fundamentals</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westwood</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Adult play, psychology, and design</article-title>. <source>Digital Creativity</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martocchio</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Microcomputer playfulness: Development of a measure with workplace implications</article-title>. <source>MIS Quarterly</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>. doi:10.2307/249576<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/249576</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weissinger</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bandalos</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Development, reliability and validity of a scale to measure intrinsic motivation in leisure</article-title>. <source>Journal of Leisure Research</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0018720811434513">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The labor of fun: How video games blur the boundaries of work and play</article-title>. <source>Games and Culture</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>