<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PPS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppps</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Perspect Psychol Sci</journal-id>
<journal-title>Perspectives on Psychological Science</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1745-6916</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1745-6924</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1745691612474318</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1745691612474318</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Intelligence of Nations</article-title>
<subtitle>A Productive Research Paradigm—Comment on Hunt (2012)</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Rindermann</surname><given-names>Heiner</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1745691612474318">Department of Psychology, Chemnitz University of Technology</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1745691612474318">Heiner Rindermann, Department of Psychology, Chemnitz University of Technology, Wilhelm-Raabe-Str. 43, D-09107 Chemnitz, Germany E-mail: <email>heiner.rindermann@psychologie.tu-chemnitz.de</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>190</fpage>
<lpage>192</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Association for Psychological Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In an article based on his APS award address, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1745691612474318">Earl Hunt (2012)</xref> described the current state of research about the intelligence of nations. The article gives a broad and balanced overview and is a well done introduction for all who are until now not acquainted with this rather new research paradigm. I want to deal with the seven most important questions raised in Hunt’s article.</p>
<p>First, what is “<italic>intelligence of nations</italic>”? Initially, it is the average result of mostly student samples in psychometric IQ (e.g., from the Raven’s test family or the CFT) or student assessment tests (PISA, TIMSS and PIRLS). These results are directly, or after corrections, generalized to the entire youth (“the coming workforce”; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1745691612474318">Hunt, 1995</xref>) and to entire country populations. There are many problems with small, old, and nonrepresentative samples and, like in all beginnings, with some errors in study selection (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1745691612474318">Hunt, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1745691612474318">Wicherts, Dolan, &amp; van der Mass, 2010</xref>), but these teething troubles seemed to have been overcome with newer research (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1745691612474318">Lynn &amp; Vanhanen, 2012</xref>), especially by integrating the results of student assessment studies.</p>
<p>Second, what is the meaning of these average test results? Hunt offers a modest interpretation: the ability to use cognitive artifacts in a modern society with its many technological and abstract challenges. I would go further and plead that intelligence covers the <italic>ability to think</italic>. This includes the use of cognitive artifacts, but also the ability to solve problems in a cognitive way, to think abstractly, to reason, to infer, to comprehend and to learn. There is an overlap of intelligence and knowledge and its competent use (the three together covered by the terms <italic>cognitive ability</italic> or <italic>cognitive competence</italic>). All intelligence and student assessment tests measure only parts of this construct, but not only do they highly correlate at the individual level, as is well known, but they also very highly correlate at the level of countries. Whether they are good measures of intelligence is less an empirical question and more a question of content-based validity. However, the empirical base should be widened to include results of Piagetian measures of cognitive development, sediments of cognitive activity (as the development of important cultural or technological improvements—e.g., the invention of scripture, patents), and such indicators in everyday life as rationality or effectiveness in obtaining well-justified aims. Hunt mentioned some examples that could be used as indicators of a nation’s intelligence (e.g., having well-organized schools or a testing system).</p>
<p>Third, why is intelligence of nations relevant? There is an empirical and a theoretical answer. To begin with the empirical, there are high correlations of a nation’s intelligence and mean knowledge level with wealth and its growth, with democracy and rule of law, and with health and human development. And there is a well-founded and empirically supported theory that cognitive ability facilitates individuals and nations to achieve such positively valued conditions (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1745691612474318">Gottfredson, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1745691612474318">Rindermann, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1745691612474318">Rindermann &amp; Meisenberg, 2009</xref>). But intelligence is more than a useful, utilitarian tool to cope with everyday demands. It helps us to comprehend life, world, and being.</p>
<p>Human capital, in an economic perspective, is everything that enables individuals to be productive workers, from ability to personality, usually measured and defined by formal education (its duration or the highest acquired degree). The economists Jacob Mincer, Theodore W. Schultz, and Gary Becker started that research in the 1950s. But economists failed to establish a precise and psychologically well thought-out construct. Human capital and education are misleading: Within broad and diffuse human capital (think of using “cheetah capital” for the ability to run fast), intelligence and the intelligent use of knowledge are crucial. And education itself is no positive factor—students do not produce anything and education consumes time and resources. Only the consequences of education as cognitive ability and personality attributes could become positively relevant for economics. Nobody recommends endowing every newborn with a master’s degree. The working mechanism is not knowledge itself, which frequently remains inert, but its intelligent, adapted, efficient use.</p>
<p>The intelligence paradigm starts to be recognized also in economics (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1745691612474318">Jones, 2011</xref>). In a modern “cognitive society,” the relevance of cognitive competences is growing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1745691612474318">Hunt &amp; Madhyastha, 2012</xref>), decreasing the impact of geographic or historical factors, working through innovation and institutions and through economic and social conditions with positive impact on economic and political development (e.g., the rule of law, economic freedom, low corruption, government effectiveness; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1745691612474318">Rindermann &amp; Thompson, 2011</xref>)—what was termed as <italic>cognitive capitalism</italic>.</p>
<p>Fourth, what are the causes of international intelligence differences? Some shy away from international intelligence research, because seeing differences in mean intelligence between nations is connoted with disparaging others. Some might think it is better to courteously overlook bare facts and the crude people uncovering them. However, if empiricism is tolerated, facts could be made bearable by attributing them to external factors that are the responsibility of others or those that could be easily changed. Of course, there are important environmental factors, from nutrition and health care to education and culture, which are responsible for past and present within-country differences and for current cross-country differences. Amount and quality of education are crucial (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1745691612474318">Rindermann &amp; Ceci, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>But Earl Hunt not only pushes this research paradigm to the center of the scientific community through his unbiased, respectful, and humorous way of dealing with it, but also by directly tackling the genetic hypothesis in cross-country differences. For the initiators of IQ comparisons, Richard Lynn and Tatu Vanhanen, the genetic hypothesis, founded in evolutionary theory, is the main (but not the only) explanatory approach: According to their theory, genes explain around 50% to 70% of international differences based on ethnic and racial differences (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1745691612474318">Rushton &amp; Rushton, 2004</xref>). Hunt takes an agnostic position and does not exclude the possibility of genetic effects on international differences. Because we do not know the genes, we cannot convincingly prove genetic effects on cross-country differences. Nevertheless, there is some indirect evidence, as shown by stability across time and countries, associations with haplogroups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1745691612474318">Rindermann, Woodley, &amp; Stratford, 2012</xref>), and high <italic>g</italic> loadings of group differences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1745691612474318">te Nijenhuis, 2012</xref>). But even if there is a strong genetic component, it would not exclude the possibility of effective interventions as for myopia through the simple use of eyeglasses.</p>
<p>Fifth, what is a probable future development of the intelligence of nations? Hunt takes an optimistic position that through “the cognitive artifacts that we are developing today … this process will continue in the future” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1745691612474318">Hunt, 2012</xref>, p. 287). Further improvements in nutrition and health care, education and training, and maybe the development of effective neuroenhancers and or even futurist technological implants can back up this development. But there is also some counter development, especially in “high-ability” countries reaching their possible thresholds, (e.g., Norway, Denmark, and Great Britain). Persons as well as nations with higher education and intelligence have fewer children and have them later in life. But parents transmit their abilities to children via nature and nurture (correlations around <italic>r</italic> = .50). <italic>Ceteris paribus</italic> (if the environment is not continuously improved), this must to lead to a declining effect (see projections of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1745691612474318">Lynn, 2011</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1745691612474318">Meisenberg, 2009</xref>). In addition, there are selective effects of immigration and emigration, which can lead to brain gain, brain drain, or low-brain gain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1745691612474318">Kapur &amp; McHale, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1745691612474318">Nyborg, 2012</xref>). The large gains in past decades in emerging countries (e.g., Argentina; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1745691612474318">Flynn &amp; Rossi-Casé, 2012</xref>) and the still suboptimal environmental conditions in many countries give hope for further increases.</p>
<p>Sixth, what can be done to raise the intelligence of nations? Improve all the conditions relevant for healthy biological development and support via environmental stimulation and instruction in the acquisition of knowledge, the development of cognitive strategies, and the practice of thinking! For educational policy, this includes widespread, long, and high-quality kindergarten education; central, objective, and demanding exams measuring knowledge, understanding, and problem solving; the use of tests and central exams for the improvement of education and for student admission and streaming decisions; school autonomy; discipline education (increases time on cognitive tasks); selection of well-educated teachers and their training; maximum class sizes of 15 to 35 students, depending on students’ ability and discipline; and longer formal education leading to better qualifications for a higher share of youth and adults (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1745691612474318">Rindermann &amp; Ceci, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Finally, how does research proceed in this field? <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1745691612474318">Hunt and Carlson (2007)</xref> have described some concerns about research on group differences (as national intelligence differences) and recommended guidelines to improve research and its outcomes. I think the 1970s are gone; there is a new and calmer willingness to deal with “controversial” issues. Simply put, fundamental principles of scientific thinking should be applied in all areas of research: Their core is epistemic rationality based on logic, empirical observations, and reasonable arguments. Scientists write for an abstract, rational reader who can be convinced (this is both an ability and a willingness) through argumentation using logic, empirical facts, and systematic reasoning. These orientations coupled with freedom of research and respect for others in their epistemic endeavor will help the entire scientific community to progress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1745691612474318">Ceci &amp; Williams, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1745691612474318">Flynn, 2007</xref>) here as well as in all other fields of research.</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author declared no conflicts of interest with respect to the authorship or the publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ceci</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Should scientists study race and IQ? Yes: The scientific truth must be pursued</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>457</volume>, <fpage>788</fpage>–<lpage>789</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>, <month>November</month>). <article-title>Arthur Jensen and John Stuart Mill</article-title>. <source>Cato Unbound</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cato-unbound.org/2007/11/23/james-r-flynn/arthur-jensen-and-john-stuart-mill">http://www.cato-unbound.org/2007/11/23/james-r-flynn/arthur-jensen-and-john-stuart-mill</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rossi-Casé</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>IQ gains in Argentina between 1964 and 1998</article-title>. <source>Intelligence</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gottfredson</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>g, jobs and life</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Nyborg</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The scientific study of general intelligence: Tribute to Arthur R. Jensen</source> (pp. <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>342</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Oxford, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pergamon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>Will we be smart enough? A cognitive analysis of the coming workforce</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Russell Sage Foundation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Human intelligence</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>What makes nations intelligent?</article-title> <source>Perspectives on Psychological Science</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>284</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Considerations relating to the study of group differences in intelligence</article-title>. <source>Perspectives on Psychological Science</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>194</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Madhyastha</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Cognitive demands of the workplace</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroscience, Psychology, and Economics</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>National IQ and national productivity: The hive mind across Asia</article-title>. <source>Asian Development Review</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kapur</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McHale</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Give us your best and brightest: The global hunt for talent and its impact on the developing world</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Center for Global Development</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Dysgenics: Genetic deterioration in modern populations</source>. <publisher-loc>Coleraine, Ireland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ulster Institute for Social Research</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vanhanen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <source>Intelligence: A unifying construct for the social sciences</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ulster Institute for Social Research</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Meisenberg</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Wealth, intelligence, politics and global fertility differentials</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biosocial Science</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>535</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nyborg</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The decay of western civilization</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rindermann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Intellectual classes, technological progress and economic development: The rise of cognitive capitalism</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>108</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rindermann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ceci</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Educational policy and country outcomes in international cognitive competence studies</article-title>. <source>Perspectives on Psychological Science</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>577</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rindermann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meisenberg</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Relevance of education and intelligence at the national level for health: The case of HIV and AIDS</article-title>. <source>Intelligence</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>395</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rindermann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Cognitive capitalism: The effect of cognitive ability on wealth, as mediated through scientific achievement and economic freedom</article-title>. <source>Psychological Science</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>754</fpage>–<lpage>763</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rindermann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woodley</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stratford</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Haplogroups as evolutionary markers of cognitive ability</article-title>. <source>Intelligence</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>362</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rushton</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rushton</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Progressive changes in brain size and musculo-skeletal traits in seven hominoid populations</article-title>. <source>Human Evolution</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>te Nijenhuis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The Flynn effect, group differences, and g loadings</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>. Advance online publication. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.paid.2011.12.023</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1745691612474318">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wicherts</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Mass</surname><given-names>H. L. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A systematic literature review of the average IQ of sub-Saharan Africans</article-title>. <source>Intelligence</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>