<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CPJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcpj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Pediatr (Phila)</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical Pediatrics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0009-9228</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-2707</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0009922813483874</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0009922813483874</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Depression Screening and Management Among Adolescents in Primary Care</article-title>
<subtitle>Factors Associated With Best Practice</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Taliaferro</surname><given-names>Lindsay A.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MPH, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922813483874">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hetler</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD, LP</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0009922813483874">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwall</surname><given-names>Glenace</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD, PsyD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0009922813483874">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>Catherine</given-names></name>
<degrees>MS, LPCC</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0009922813483874">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>Anne R.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0009922813483874">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Borowsky</surname><given-names>Iris W.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0009922813483874">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0009922813483874"><label>1</label>University of Missouri, Columbia, MO, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0009922813483874"><label>2</label>University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0009922813483874"><label>3</label>Minnesota Department of Human Services, St Paul, MN, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0009922813483874"><label>4</label>Park Nicollet Clinic, St Louis Park, MN, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0009922813483874">Lindsay A. Taliaferro, Department of Health Sciences, School of Health Professions, University of Missouri, 505 Clark Hall, Columbia, MO 65211, USA. Email: <email>taliaferrol@health.missouri.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>52</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>557</fpage>
<lpage>567</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><italic>Objective.</italic> To compare depression identification and management perceptions and practices between professions and disciplines in primary care and examine factors that increase the likelihood of administering a standardized depression screening instrument, asking about patients’ depressive symptoms, and using best practice when managing depressed adolescents. <italic>Methods.</italic> Data came from an online survey of clinicians in Minnesota (20% response rate). Analyses involved bivariate tests and linear regressions. <italic>Results.</italic> The analytic sample comprised 260 family medicine physicians, 127 pediatricians, 96 family nurse practitioners, and 54 pediatric nurse practitioners. Overall, few differences emerged between physicians and nurse practitioners or family and pediatric clinicians regarding addressing depression among adolescents. Two factors associated with administering a standardized instrument included having clear protocols for follow-up after depression screening and feeling better prepared to address depression among adolescents. <italic>Conclusions.</italic> Enhancing clinicians’ competence to address depression and developing postscreening protocols could help providers implement universal screening in primary care.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>adolescent</kwd>
<kwd>depression</kwd>
<kwd>primary health care</kwd>
<kwd>screening</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0009922813483874" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Depression among adolescents represents a concern for primary care providers (PCPs). At any time, 5% to 6% of adolescents experience significant depressive symptoms,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922813483874">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0009922813483874">2</xref></sup> whereas 30% to 35% experience elevated symptoms that may not reach criteria for diagnosis of major depressive disorder.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0009922813483874">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0009922813483874">4</xref></sup> Lifetime rates of major depressive disorder among youth may reach up to 20%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0009922813483874">5</xref></sup> Prevalence of depression among adolescents seen in primary care ranges from 9% to 20%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0009922813483874">6</xref></sup> Depression during adolescence is associated with the co-occurrence of substance use,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0009922813483874">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0009922813483874">7</xref></sup> nonsuicidal self-injury,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0009922813483874">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0009922813483874">9</xref></sup> and suicide ideation or behavior<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0009922813483874">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0009922813483874"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0009922813483874">12</xref></sup> as well as with depression, suicidality, and impaired functioning later in life.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0009922813483874">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0009922813483874"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0009922813483874"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0009922813483874">16</xref></sup></p>
<p>Still, many PCPs do not identify young people experiencing depression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0009922813483874">17</xref></sup> Ozer et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0009922813483874">18</xref></sup> found that almost 70% of youth experiencing depressive symptoms had not discussed their mood with their providers. PCPs frequently rely on presenting complaints and family concerns to identify depressed youth,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0009922813483874">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0009922813483874">20</xref></sup> yet many adolescents in distress present with medical problems rather than psychological symptoms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0009922813483874">21</xref></sup> Adolescents also may not verbalize their feelings or disclose their psychosocial problems without prompting from clinicians.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0009922813483874">22</xref></sup> Limited screening for depression by PCPs suggests that contacts with primary care represent critical missed opportunities to identify distressed adolescents and facilitate connections to mental health services early in the course of a problem.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0009922813483874">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0009922813483874">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0009922813483874">23</xref></sup></p>
<p>The American Academy of Pediatrics identified routine screening as an opportunity to address many unmet mental health needs among adolescents.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0009922813483874">24</xref></sup> In 2009, the US Preventive Services Task Force (USPSTF) recommended screening adolescents aged 12 to 18 for depression in primary care when systems are in place to ensure accurate diagnosis, psychotherapy, and follow-up.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0009922813483874">5</xref></sup> Administering a standardized depression screening instrument may increase the likelihood of identifying adolescents in distress by opening lines of communication or providing cutoff scores that signal the need for further assessment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0009922813483874">25</xref></sup> and may lead to increases in the care delivered such as physician counseling and referrals.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0009922813483874">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0009922813483874">21</xref></sup> PCPs report satisfaction with screening processes and little resistance among patients and parents.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0009922813483874">25</xref></sup> Still, individual and systemwide barriers likely preclude many PCPs from addressing mental health issues, including lack of time and/or confidence to treat mental health problems, long waiting times to see mental health specialists, lack of training, and lack of specialists to whom to refer depressed youth.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0009922813483874">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0009922813483874">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0009922813483874">26</xref></sup></p>
<p>Gaps in the literature exist regarding depression identification and management practices, barriers, and perceptions of PCPs. In particular, researchers have not assessed these practices since publication of the 2009 USPSTF recommendations. In addition, limited research has examined differences in perceptions and practices between physicians and nurse practitioners or family and pediatric clinicians. Data from clinicians across professional groups can help identify areas of shared strength and weakness. Findings from this line of research may inform education and training programs as well as practice policies and procedures.</p>
<p>The current study sought to address these gaps by surveying a statewide sample of PCPs in Minnesota. We pursued 4 research questions: (1) What similarities and differences exist across professions and disciplines related to factors associated with screening and managing adolescents experiencing depression? (2) What factors increase the likelihood of administering a standardized, written depression screening instrument to adolescents? (3) What factors increase the likelihood of asking about depressive symptoms when providing health supervision? and (4) What factors increase the likelihood of using best practices when managing adolescents experiencing depression?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0009922813483874" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section3-0009922813483874">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>We identified PCPs who likely met the inclusion criteria (ie, currently provide direct ambulatory, primary care services to adolescents 12 to 18 years of age) from lists obtained from the Minnesota Board of Nursing and Board of Medical Practice. Potential participants were included if their area of specialty matched the inclusion criteria (eg, physicians or nurse practitioners with a specialty of pediatrics or family medicine) or if they had a certificate or second specialty consistent with the inclusion criteria (eg, family medicine physicians with a specialty in sports medicine, not family medicine physicians with a certificate in geriatric medicine). We e-mailed invitation letters with a link to the survey to 3337 pediatricians, family medicine physicians, pediatric nurse practitioners, and family nurse practitioners. A total of 67 clinicians followed a link to opt out embedded within the letter; 115 e-mail addresses bounced back; 222 PCPs were ineligible (self-identified and researcher identified from descriptions of professions: eg, psychiatrists and emergency room physicians); and 114 notified the first author that they were ineligible, uninterested in participating, or could not access the survey because of technical difficulties.</p>
<p>A sample of 552 eligible PCPs completed a confidential survey created within SurveyMonkey. The overall response rate was 20%, similar to rates obtained in previous studies that administered online surveys to clinicians.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0009922813483874">27</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0009922813483874"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0009922813483874"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0009922813483874"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0009922813483874">31</xref></sup> Respondents were significantly more likely than nonrespondents to identify as female (65% vs 53%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). They did not differ in age, profession, or time since licensure. In all, 15 PCPs did not answer questions beyond items related to their background and clinical setting. Therefore, we eliminated these clinicians and analyzed data obtained from 537 PCPs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0009922813483874">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0009922813483874" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sample.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0009922813483874-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0009922813483874">
<title>Survey Instrument and Administration</title>
<p>We developed the survey based on the research literature and similar surveys of PCPs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0009922813483874">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0009922813483874">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0009922813483874">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0009922813483874">32</xref></sup> An expert review of the survey was completed with 2 developmental-behavioral pediatricians, 2 general pediatricians, and 1 child and adolescent psychiatrist. We pilot tested the survey with 2 clinicians from each of the 4 provider groups and revised the instrument after each round of review. The survey consisted of 28 general question categories and 92 potential response options. The instrument included yes or no, multiple-choice, and mark-all-that-apply questions, and 5-point Likert scales of agreement (<italic>strongly agree</italic> to <italic>strongly disagree</italic>), level of preparation (<italic>not at all prepared</italic> to <italic>extremely well prepared</italic>), and frequency of engaging in a behavior (<italic>never</italic> to <italic>almost always</italic>). The instrument took about 10 minutes to complete. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0009922813483874">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0009922813483874">2</xref> present most of the items.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0009922813483874" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sample Characteristics.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0009922813483874" xlink:href="10.1177_0009922813483874-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="bottom">Items</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Profession (%)<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Discipline (%)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center">Physician (n = 387)</th>
<th align="center">Nurse Practitioner (n = 150)</th>
<th align="center">χ<sup>2</sup></th>
<th align="center">Family Practice (n = 356)</th>
<th align="center">Pediatrics (n = 181)</th>
<th align="center">χ<sup>2</sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Sex</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>99.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>5.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922813483874">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>38</td>
<td>28</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>99</td>
<td/>
<td>62</td>
<td>72</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Practice setting</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>21.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>29.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Suburban</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>31</td>
<td/>
<td>42</td>
<td>52</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Urban</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>41</td>
<td/>
<td>25</td>
<td>36</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rural</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>29</td>
<td/>
<td>33</td>
<td>12</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Onsite mental health</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>6.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922813483874">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>5.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922813483874">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>51</td>
<td/>
<td>39</td>
<td>50</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>49</td>
<td/>
<td>61</td>
<td>50</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient insurance</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>58.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mostly private</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>26</td>
<td/>
<td>42</td>
<td>48</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Equal public and private</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>34</td>
<td/>
<td>37</td>
<td>30</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mostly public</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>32</td>
<td/>
<td>16</td>
<td>20</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mostly uninsured</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>9</td>
<td/>
<td>4</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Mean</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic> Test</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Mean</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic> Test</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Years in practice</td>
<td>19.4</td>
<td>11.7</td>
<td>8.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td>16.3</td>
<td>19.1</td>
<td>3.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average number of patients seen per half day</td>
<td>10.9</td>
<td>9.2</td>
<td>2.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td>10.1</td>
<td>11.2</td>
<td>2.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922813483874">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average number of adolescents seen each week</td>
<td>13.4</td>
<td>16.8</td>
<td>2.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922813483874">*</xref></td>
<td>11.5</td>
<td>20.0</td>
<td>6.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0009922813483874">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>P</italic> &lt; .05; **<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-0009922813483874" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Depression Screening and Management Perceptions and Practices Among Primary Care Providers (PCPs).</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0009922813483874" xlink:href="10.1177_0009922813483874-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="bottom">Items</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Profession (%)<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Discipline (%)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center">Physician (n = 387)</th>
<th align="center">Nurse Practitioner (n = 150)</th>
<th align="center">χ<sup>2</sup></th>
<th align="center">Family Practice (n = 356)</th>
<th align="center">Pediatrics (n = 181)</th>
<th align="center">χ<sup>2</sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Preparation (not at all prepared or less than adequately prepared)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Feel prepared to screen adolescents for depression</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Feel prepared to diagnose adolescent depression</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>5.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">*</xref></td>
<td>18</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Feel prepared to treat depressed adolescents with medications</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>27.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td>31</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Know when to refer depressed adolescents for mental health services</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Feel prepared to address nonsuicidal self-injury</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Feel prepared to assess adolescents for suicide risk</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Feel prepared to respond to adolescents with suicidal thoughts</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Perceptions (agree or strongly agree)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PCPs should be responsible for identifying adolescents experiencing depression</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PCPs should be responsible for managing adolescents experiencing depression</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>17.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td>41</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PCPs should be responsible for comanaging adolescents experiencing depression with a mental health provider</td>
<td>86</td>
<td>91</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>87</td>
<td>89</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PCPs should be responsible for initiating specialty referrals</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> I am familiar with official recommendations regarding screening for depression among adolescents in primary care</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>5.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> I can effectively identify adolescents experiencing depression in my practice setting</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> I can effectively manage adolescents experiencing depression in my practice setting</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>13.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td>46</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Identification practices (usually or almost always)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Use a standardized, written depression screening instrument</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Use a depression screening item within a comprehensive behavioral screening instrument (eg, PHQ-A, PSC, GAPS)</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Use a psychosocial interview (eg, HEADSS assessment)</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>32.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Use clinical observation/overall impression</td>
<td>80</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>78</td>
<td>86</td>
<td>4.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Management practices (usually or almost always)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Use watchful waiting only</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Recommend lifestyle changes (eg, exercise)</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>77</td>
<td>7.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td>68</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Brief counseling (eg, helping identify support systems)</td>
<td>73</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>74</td>
<td>77</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Provide educational materials to patients and families</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>14.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td>44</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Use a care coordinator</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>7.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td>19</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Schedule follow-up</td>
<td>87</td>
<td>88</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>6.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Use antidepressant medications</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Provide self-help or support group referral</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>16.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td>20</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Provide psychiatry referral</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>6.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">*</xref></td>
<td>22</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Provide mental health referral</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>73</td>
<td>12.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Consult (by phone) with a mental health professional</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Policies and procedures (yes, and widely used or yes, and used to some extent)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Practice has clear protocols for follow-up after depression screening</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Practice has a formal, written policy for assessing and managing adolescents who report thinking about suicide</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7"> Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Have collaboration agreements with specialty mental health providers</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>4.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">*</xref></td>
<td>36</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Barriers to identifying or managing adolescents experiencing depression (sometimes, usually, or almost always)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Parent and/or patient concerns about stigma</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>79</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lack of available resources to assist when suicidality is uncovered</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Discomfort assessing and managing suicidality among youth</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Low literacy rate in my patient population</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>10.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td>24</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Language and cultural issues</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>10.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td>36</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lack of clarity about limits of confidentiality</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>13.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lack of comfort talking about mental health problems</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>12.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lack of confidence in my ability to diagnose adolescents with depression</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>9.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td>34</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lack of confidence about the accuracy of screening for depression</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lack of professional training</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>5.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">*</xref></td>
<td>41</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>11.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lack of appropriate reimbursement</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lack of adequate time to screen, discuss screening results, or treat depression</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>8.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0009922813483874">**</xref></td>
<td>69</td>
<td>74</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Patients’ insurance coverage limits treatment options</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lack of support systems within my clinic</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lack of defined clinical practice guidelines</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Medical problems more pressing</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other psychosocial problems more pressing</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Not familiar with conveniently located competent/qualified providers to whom to refer adolescents</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lack of collaborative care</td>
<td>69</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lack of educational materials that help engage patients and parents in a dialogue about depression</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Long waiting times for referrals to mental health providers</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>88</td>
<td>NS</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>89</td>
<td>NS</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0009922813483874">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>P</italic> &lt; .05; **<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01. Abbreviations: PHQ-A, patient Health questionnaire for adolescents; PSC, pediatric symptom checklist; GAPS, guidelines for adolescent preventive services; HEADSS, home, education, activities, drugs, sexuality, and suicide/ depression.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>A link to the survey was initially sent within a letter from the first author, cosigned by the president of the Minnesota Chapter of the National Association of Pediatric Nurse Practitioners, president of the Minnesota Academy of Family Physicians, and recent past president of the Minnesota Chapter of the American Academy of Pediatrics. Several follow-up letters were signed by other authors (IWB, JH). We collected data from June 2011 through January 2012. Participants were offered a chance to win 1 of 25 Target gift cards worth $25. The institutional review board at the University of Minnesota approved this study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0009922813483874">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>Descriptive statistics and bivariate tests examined similarities and differences between professions (physicians vs nurse practitioners) and disciplines (family practice vs pediatrics) on survey items. Linear regression analyses determined factors that increased the likelihood of administering a standardized, written depression screening instrument; asking about patients’ depressive symptoms when providing health supervision; and using best practice when managing adolescents experiencing depression (ie, working with a care coordinator, prescribing antidepressant medication, providing a psychiatry referral, providing a mental health referral, or consulting a mental health professional via telephone<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0009922813483874">33</xref></sup>).</p>
<p>Independent variables entered simultaneously into regression models were selected based on their theoretical importance or potential to impact training, practice, or policy. Variables are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0009922813483874">Tables 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0009922813483874">4</xref>. We created 4 scaled variables: perceived level of preparation to address depression among adolescents (screen for depression, diagnose depression, treat depression with medications, and know when to refer depressed adolescents for mental health services; α = .89), perceived level of preparation to address self-injury and suicidality (address nonsuicidal self-injury, assess for suicide risk, and respond to adolescents with suicidal thoughts; α = .86), perceptions regarding responsibilities for addressing depression among adolescents (feel responsible for identifying, managing, and comanaging depressed adolescents as well as initiating specialty referrals for depressed adolescents; α = .72), and perceptions regarding ability to identify and manage depression among adolescents in one’s practice setting (α = .74).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0009922813483874" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Factors Associated With Administering a Standardized Depression Screening Instrument and Asking About Depressive Symptoms When Providing Health Supervision to Adolescents.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0009922813483874">a</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0009922813483874" xlink:href="10.1177_0009922813483874-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="bottom">Variable</th>
<th align="center">Administer a Standardized, Written Depression Screening Instrument<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Ask About Depressive Symptoms When Providing Health Supervision to Adolescents<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Estimate (<italic>P</italic> Value)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Female versus male</td>
<td>0.55 (.001)</td>
<td>0.19 (.068)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Physicians versus nurse practitioners</td>
<td>0.06 (.735)</td>
<td>−0.02 (.854)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pediatric versus family clinicians</td>
<td>−0.37 (.016)</td>
<td>0.11 (.256)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Practice setting</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Urban versus suburban</td>
<td>−0.11 (.531)</td>
<td>−0.02 (.841)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rural versus suburban</td>
<td>0.12 (.508)</td>
<td>−0.11 (.355)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Onsite mental health (yes vs no)</td>
<td>−0.06 (.660)</td>
<td>0.03 (.705)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">Insurance</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Equal public and private versus mostly private</td>
<td>0.10 (.534)</td>
<td>0.18 (.076)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mostly public or uninsured versus mostly private</td>
<td>−0.02 (.941)</td>
<td>0.09 (.471)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average years in practice</td>
<td>0.00 (.694)</td>
<td>−0.01 (.174)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average number of patients seen per half day</td>
<td>0.00 (.950)</td>
<td>0.00 (.849)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average number of adolescents seen per week</td>
<td>−0.00 (.462)</td>
<td>0.01 (.119)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Have protocols for follow-up after depression screening that is used at least some extent (yes vs no)</td>
<td>0.43 (.004)</td>
<td>−0.01 (.900)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Have a formal, written policy for assessing and managing adolescents thinking about suicide that is used at least some extent (yes vs no)</td>
<td>−0.03 (.875)</td>
<td>0.12 (.348)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Have collaboration agreements with mental health providers (yes vs no)</td>
<td>0.06 (.680)</td>
<td>−0.08 (.398)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Feel prepared to address depression among adolescents</td>
<td>0.44 (.004)</td>
<td>0.15 (.113)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Feel prepared to address self-injury and suicidality among adolescents</td>
<td>−0.21 (.112)</td>
<td>0.02 (.775)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Believe PCPs should be responsible for addressing depression among adolescents</td>
<td>0.12 (.422)</td>
<td>0.27 (.004)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Believe can address depression among adolescents in one’s practice setting</td>
<td>−0.01 (.907)</td>
<td>0.15 (.062)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Familiar with official recommendations regarding screening for depression</td>
<td>0.11 (.124)</td>
<td>0.11 (.026)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0009922813483874">
<p>Abbreviation: PCP, primary care provider.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0009922813483874">
<label>a</label>
<p>All variables were entered simultaneously within separate linear regression models for each dependent variable.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table4-0009922813483874" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Factors Associated With Different Practices Used by PCPs to Manage Adolescents Experiencing Depression.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0009922813483874">a</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0009922813483874" xlink:href="10.1177_0009922813483874-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="bottom">Variable</th>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Estimate (P Value)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center">Antidepressant Medication</th>
<th align="center">Care Coordinator</th>
<th align="center">Psychiatry Referral</th>
<th align="center">Mental Health Referral</th>
<th align="center">Phone Consult</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Female versus male</td>
<td>0.06 (.436)</td>
<td>−0.10 (.522)</td>
<td>−0.05 (.592)</td>
<td>0.27 (.010)</td>
<td>0.06 (.538)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Physicians versus nurse practitioners</td>
<td>0.05 (.627)</td>
<td>−0.22 (.193)</td>
<td>−0.10 (.382)</td>
<td>−0.10 (.372)</td>
<td>0.02 (.853)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pediatric clinicians versus family practice</td>
<td>−0.19 (.023)</td>
<td>−0.10 (.532)</td>
<td>−0.16 (.100)</td>
<td>0.17 (.100)</td>
<td>0.09 (.390)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Practice setting</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Urban versus suburban</td>
<td>−0.16 (.100)</td>
<td>0.04 (.824)</td>
<td>0.10 (.376)</td>
<td>0.13 (.263)</td>
<td>0.13 (.279)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rural versus suburban</td>
<td>0.00 (.973)</td>
<td>−0.23 (.191)</td>
<td>−0.04 (.725)</td>
<td>−0.18 (.121)</td>
<td>0.13 (.237)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>On-site mental health (yes vs no)</td>
<td>−0.13 (.069)</td>
<td>0.26 (.063)</td>
<td>0.02 (.846)</td>
<td>0.04 (.666)</td>
<td>0.21 (.023)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Insurance</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Equal public and private versus mostly private</td>
<td>0.03 (.756)</td>
<td>0.19 (.227)</td>
<td>0.10 (.301)</td>
<td>0.10 (.321)</td>
<td>0.02 (.882)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mostly public or uninsured versus mostly private</td>
<td>−0.10 (.353)</td>
<td>0.24 (.234)</td>
<td>0.10 (.443)</td>
<td>−0.01 (.969)</td>
<td>0.03 (.822)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average years in practice</td>
<td>0.00 (.267)</td>
<td>−0.00 (.554)</td>
<td>−0.01 (.097)</td>
<td>0.00 (.394)</td>
<td>0.01 (.086)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average number of patients seen per half day</td>
<td>0.01 (.117)</td>
<td>0.00 (.807)</td>
<td>0.00 (.680)</td>
<td>0.01 (.385)</td>
<td>−0.02 (.060)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average number of adolescents seen per week</td>
<td>0.00 (.634)</td>
<td>−0.01 (.394)</td>
<td>−0.00 (.884)</td>
<td>0.01 (.061)</td>
<td>0.00 (.994)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Have protocols for follow-up after depression screening that is used at least some extent (yes vs no)</td>
<td>−0.04 (.657)</td>
<td>0.16 (.279)</td>
<td>0.08 (.379)</td>
<td>0.10 (.308)</td>
<td>−0.22 (.025)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Have a formal, written policy for assessing and managing adolescents thinking about suicide that is used at least some extent (yes vs no)</td>
<td>−0.12 (.229)</td>
<td>0.65 (.001)</td>
<td>−0.02 (.884)</td>
<td>−0.07 (.579)</td>
<td>0.28 (.021)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Have collaboration agreements with mental health providers (yes vs no)</td>
<td>−0.02 (.775)</td>
<td>0.01 (.932)</td>
<td>0.06 (.495)</td>
<td>0.05 (.623)</td>
<td>0.33 (.001)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Feel prepared to address depression among adolescents</td>
<td>0.22 (.006)</td>
<td>−0.15 (.307)</td>
<td>−0.14 (.148)</td>
<td>−0.04 (.655)</td>
<td>−0.18 (.069)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Feel prepared to address self-injury and suicidality among adolescents</td>
<td>−0.17 (.020)</td>
<td>−0.01 (.963)</td>
<td>−0.03 (.735)</td>
<td>0.07 (.424)</td>
<td>0.10 (.268)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Believe PCPs should be responsible for addressing depression among adolescents</td>
<td>0.28 (.000)</td>
<td>0.16 (.264)</td>
<td>−0.10 (.290)</td>
<td>0.01 (.952)</td>
<td>0.25 (.008)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Believe can address depression among adolescents in one’s practice setting</td>
<td>0.25 (.000)</td>
<td>0.08 (.521)</td>
<td>−0.12 (.136)</td>
<td>−0.10 (.216)</td>
<td>−0.09 (.253)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Familiar with official recommendations regarding screening for depression</td>
<td>−0.06 (.123)</td>
<td>0.13 (.065)</td>
<td>0.04 (.361)</td>
<td>−0.03 (.513)</td>
<td>0.04 (.450)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-0009922813483874">
<p>Abbreviation: PCP, primary care provider.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0009922813483874">
<label>a</label>
<p>All variables were entered simultaneously within separate linear regression models for each dependent variable.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0009922813483874" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The analytic sample included 260 family medicine physicians (48%), 127 pediatricians (24%), 96 family nurse practitioners (18%), and 54 pediatric nurse practitioners (10%). On average, PCPs had 17 years (standard deviation = 9.9) of licensure. Most participants reported practicing in a suburban setting (45%) rather than urban (29%) or rural (26%) settings. We found significant differences between professions and disciplines on most background variables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0009922813483874">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0009922813483874">Table 2</xref>, we present similarities and differences across professions and disciplines in depression identification and management perceptions and practices. The groups did not differ in their perceptions of feeling prepared to address most of the assessed concepts, except for the fact that nurse practitioners felt significantly less prepared than physicians to diagnose and treat adolescents with depression. Overall, PCPs felt least prepared to address nonsuicidal self-injury and most prepared for knowing when to refer depressed adolescents for mental health services. Clinicians felt strongly that PCPs should be responsible for identifying, comanaging, and initiating specialty referrals for adolescents experiencing depression. Compared with physicians, nurse practitioners were significantly less likely to strongly believe that they are responsible for managing depressed adolescents (46% vs 26%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01), and they felt less sure that they could effectively manage these youth in their practice settings (50% vs 32%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01).</p>
<p>Pediatric clinicians were significantly more likely than family providers to report greater familiarity with official recommendations regarding depression screening (54% vs 43%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05), yet they were less likely to routinely administer a standardized, written depression screening instrument (44% vs 53%; <italic>P</italic> = .06). More than three-fourths of participants indicated they ever administer a standardized depression instrument to adolescents. However, most screen only high-risk patients, after identifying warning signs (79%) and screen in response to specific patient complaints (62%). We found no significant differences in rates on these variables by profession or discipline (data not shown). Overall, 69% of PCPs reported usually/almost always asking about adolescents’ depressive symptoms when providing health supervision. A significantly greater percentage of pediatric than family clinicians indicated that they frequently ask about depressive symptoms (75% vs 66%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) and routinely perform psychosocial interviews (36% vs 14%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). In general, PCPs more frequently use their clinical observation/overall impression to identify adolescents experiencing depression than other methods.</p>
<p>Regarding management practices, PCPs most often reported scheduling a follow-up, providing brief counseling, recommending lifestyle changes, and/or providing mental health referrals. Few reported using watchful waiting only or consulting a mental health professional via telephone. Compared with pediatric clinicians, a greater percentage of family clinicians reported scheduling a follow-up (82% vs 90%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01) and a smaller percentage reported providing a mental health referral (73% vs 57%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). Few PCPs reported having a formal, written policy for assessing and managing adolescents thinking about suicide (sample range: 13%-19%). About 40% reported having clear protocols for follow-up after depression screening, and a similar percentage have collaboration agreements with mental health providers.</p>
<p>The most frequently endorsed barrier to identifying or managing adolescents experiencing depression was long waiting times for referrals to mental health providers (sample range: 86%-90%). Other consistent barriers included parent and/or patient concerns about stigma; lack of adequate time to screen, discuss screening results, or treat depression; lack of collaborative care; lack of available resources to assist when suicidality is uncovered; and lack of educational materials that help engage patients and parents in a dialogue about depression. Pediatric clinicians were significantly less likely than family providers to identify lack of comfort talking about mental health problems as a barrier (12% vs 26%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). However, they were more likely to identify lack of professional training as a barrier (57% vs 41%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01), as were nurse practitioners compared with physicians (55% vs 43%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05).</p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0009922813483874">Table 3</xref>, we present results from analyses that determined factors associated with more frequently administering a standardized depression screening instrument and asking about depressive symptoms when providing health supervision. Factors associated with increased likelihood of administering a standardized depression instrument included female gender, being a family clinician, having clear protocols for follow-up after depression screening, and feeling better prepared to address depression among adolescents. Factors that increased the likelihood of asking about depressive symptoms included believing more strongly that PCPs should be responsible for addressing depression among adolescents and being more familiar with official recommendations regarding screening for depression.</p>
<p>A variety of factors were associated with the frequency with which PCPs reported using various best practices for managing adolescents experiencing depression (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0009922813483874">Table 4</xref>). Factors associated with prescribing antidepressant medication included being a family practice clinician, feeling better prepared to address depression, feeling less prepared to address self-injury and suicidality, feeling more strongly that PCPs should be responsible for addressing depression among adolescents, and believing more strongly that one can address depression in his or her practice setting. The only factor associated with using a care coordinator was having and using a policy for assessing and managing adolescents considering suicide. None of the factors included in the regression models were associated with providing a psychiatry referral, and only female gender was associated with providing a mental health referral. In all, 5 factors were associated with consulting a mental health professional via telephone: having on-site mental health services, not having or using protocols for follow-up after depression screening, having and using a policy for assessing and managing adolescents thinking about suicide, having a collaboration agreement with specialty mental health providers, and feeling more strongly that PCPs should be responsible for addressing depression among adolescents.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0009922813483874" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The present study examined preparation, perceptions, practices, policies, and barriers associated with identifying and managing adolescents experiencing depression in primary care. Overall, 69% of PCPs reported that they routinely ask about depressive symptoms during health supervision with adolescents. About 75% ever administer a standardized, written depression screening instrument, and half the sample reported routinely administering an instrument. Among the former, most PCPs usually administer a standardized instrument in response to specific patient complaints or only to high-risk youth, after identifying warning signs. Consistent with previous research,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0009922813483874">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0009922813483874">20</xref></sup> most often, PCPs use their clinical observation/overall impression to identify depressed youth. Findings regarding the predominant use of clinical observation to identify youth experiencing depression and screening only high-risk youth suggest that official recommendations regarding routine screening have yet to have an impact on clinician behavior.</p>
<p>Overall, we found few differences between physicians and nurse practitioners or family and pediatric clinicians regarding addressing depression among adolescents. Most PCPs felt well prepared to refer adolescents for mental health services, screen for depression, diagnose depression, and assess for suicide risk. Fewer clinicians felt prepared to treat depressed adolescents with medications, particularly nurse practitioners; address nonsuicidal self-injury; or respond to adolescents with suicidal thoughts. The majority of PCPs felt responsible for identifying adolescents experiencing depression and thought that they could identify depressed youth in their practice settings. However, far fewer felt that they were responsible for managing adolescents experiencing depression, especially nurse practitioners. These findings support research by Stein et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0009922813483874">34</xref></sup> who found that 88% of pediatricians thought that they were responsible for identifying child/adolescent depression, and 86% thought that they were responsible for referring depressed youth, yet just 25% indicated that they were responsible for treating or managing depressed youth.</p>
<p>The strong feelings of responsibility to identify youth experiencing depression in the present study did not translate into routine screening for depression among all youth using a standardized instrument or formal psychosocial interview. The Guidelines for Adolescent Depression in Primary Care (GLAD-PC) indicate that optimal identification should include administering depression-specific screening tools, followed by clinical interviews.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0009922813483874">17</xref></sup> Our data suggest that PCPs who feel better prepared to address depression among adolescents show increased likelihood of using standardized screening instruments. Similar to previous research,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0009922813483874">20</xref></sup> the management practices most commonly used among PCPs in this study included scheduling a follow-up, recommending lifestyle changes, providing brief counseling, and providing a mental health referral. According to GLAD-PC, clinicians should manage adolescents experiencing moderate to severe depression by consulting with a mental health professional, providing evidence-based psychotherapy and/or pharmacotherapy, and/or referring the person for mental health services.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0009922813483874">33</xref></sup></p>
<p>Overall, PCPs across professions and disciplines reported similar barriers to identifying or managing adolescents experiencing depression. Long waiting times for referrals to mental health providers represented the most strongly endorsed barrier. Other significant barriers included concerns about stigma and lack of time, available resources when suicidality is uncovered, collaborative care, and educational materials. Most of these barriers were cited by clinicians in previous studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0009922813483874">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0009922813483874">26</xref></sup> A distinct barrier examined in this study related to possessing sufficient resources to address suicidality. PCPs may perceive this issue as a barrier because their practice settings lack policies for assessing and managing adolescents thinking about suicide. Furthermore, many PCPs reported feeling unprepared to respond to youth with suicidal thoughts, and having a policy for addressing suicidality among youth represented a significant factor associated with consulting a mental health professional via telephone when managing depressed youth. These findings suggest that implementing written policies that assist clinicians when they encounter patients considering suicide may improve self-efficacy and reduce a significant barrier to identifying or managing adolescents experiencing depression.</p>
<p>The USPSTF acknowledges that researchers have not examined health outcomes among youth screened for depression or the impact of screening on the rate of youth identified as experiencing depression or receiving treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0009922813483874">6</xref></sup> Future research must address these gaps in the literature. Researchers also should confirm findings from the present investigation through replication studies with national samples. In addition, they should test individual and system-level interventions that address factors associated with increased likelihood of administering a standardized depression screening instrument, such as professional training and protocol implementation. Investigators have demonstrated positive effects of training programs on clinicians’ ability to recognize adolescents in distress,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0009922813483874">35</xref></sup> yet multifaceted approaches are likely required to substantially change professional practice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0009922813483874">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0009922813483874">37</xref></sup></p>
<p>Limitations of this study warrant consideration. The low response rate among only clinicians practicing in Minnesota may reflect a biased sample comprising PCPs interested in this topic. Their responses may not be representative of the population of PCPs in Minnesota or nationwide. In addition, this study relied on self-report. Objective measures of clinician behavior, such as daily logs or notes documented in medical charts, may provide more accurate information or substantiate clinicians’ reports of their behavior.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0009922813483874" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>This study adds to the literature on depression screening and management in primary care by examining perceptions and behaviors between professions and disciplines. Similarities across the groups suggest that other than efforts to enhance nurse practitioners’ self-efficacy to diagnose and manage adolescents experiencing depression, efforts to improve practices do not require much tailoring to specific professions or disciplines. Instead, training interventions, policy and protocol development, and system-level changes to address significant barriers should produce improvements within diverse segments of primary care that augment services provided to adolescents. Addressing facilitators and barriers to screening for and effectively managing depression will help ensure that contacts with primary care no longer represent missed opportunities to help distressed youth.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank Jessica Barnes from the Children, Youth, and Family Consortium, University of Minnesota Extension, for her help with administering the survey and managing responses.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<label>Authors’ Note</label>
<p>The findings and conclusions in the article are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the official position of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared the following potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: Dr Glenace Edwall and Ms Catherine Wright work at the state agency that funded this project. The other authors have no conflicts of interest relevant to this article to disclose.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This study was funded in part through contracts from the Minnesota Department of Human Services. The first author’s time was partially supported through funds from the Healthy Youth Development—Prevention Research Center, University of Minnesota, Cooperative Agreement Number 5U48DP001939 from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (PI: Resnick).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0009922813483874">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erkanli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Angold</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Is there an epidemic of child or adolescent depression?</article-title> <source>J Child Adolesc Psychiatr</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>1263</fpage>-<lpage>1271</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0009922813483874">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brent</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birmaher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Adolescent depression</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>347</volume>:<fpage>667</fpage>-<lpage>671</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0009922813483874">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kubik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lytle</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birnbaum</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and correlates of depressive symptoms in young adolescents</article-title>. <source>Am J Health Behav</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>546</fpage>-<lpage>553</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0009922813483874">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rushton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forcier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schectman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Epidemiology of depressive symptoms in the National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent Health</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>199</fpage>-<lpage>205</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0009922813483874">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Calonge</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tetitti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeWitt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Screening and treatment for major depressive disorder in children and adolescents: U.S. Preventive Services Task Force Recommendation Statement</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>123</volume>:<fpage>1223</fpage>-<lpage>1228</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0009922813483874">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whitlock</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Screening for child and adolescent depression in primary care settings: a systematic evidence review for the US Preventive Services Task Force</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>123</volume>:<fpage>e716</fpage>-<lpage>e735</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0009922813483874">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Saluja</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iachan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scheidt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Overpeck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Giedd</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Prevalence of and risk factors for depressive symptoms among young adolescents</article-title>. <source>Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>158</volume>:<fpage>760</fpage>-<lpage>765</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0009922813483874">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cloutier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muehlenkamp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Characteristics and co-occurrence of adolescent non-suicidal self-injury and suicidal behaviours in pediatric emergency crisis services</article-title>. <source>J Youth Adolesc</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>-<lpage>269</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0009922813483874">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muehlenkamp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Risk for suicide attempts among adolescents who engage in non-suicidal self-injury</article-title>. <source>Arch Suicide Res</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0009922813483874">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glied</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pine</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Consequences and correlates of adolescent depression</article-title>. <source>Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>156</volume>:<fpage>1009</fpage>-<lpage>1014</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0009922813483874">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spirito</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Esposito-Smythers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Attempted and completed suicide in adolescence</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Clin Psychol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>266</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0009922813483874">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beautrais</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Risk factors for suicide and attempted suicide among young people</article-title>. <source>Aust N Z J Psychiatry</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>420</fpage>-<lpage>436</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0009922813483874">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fergusson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Mental health, educational, and social role outcomes of adolescents with depression</article-title>. <source>Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage>-<lpage>231</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0009922813483874">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fergusson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horwood</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Risk factors and life processes associated with the onset of suicidal behaviour during adolescence and early childhood</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0009922813483874">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Psychiatric diagnosis in child and adolescent suicide</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>339</fpage>-<lpage>348</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0009922813483874">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Depressed adolescents grown up</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>281</volume>:<fpage>1707</fpage>-<lpage>1713</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0009922813483874">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zuckerbrot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laraque</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>; and <collab>the GLAD-PC Steering Group</collab>. <article-title>Guidelines for Adolescent Depression in Primary Care (GLAD-PC): I. Identification, assessment, and initial management</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>120</volume>:<fpage>e1299</fpage>-<lpage>e1312</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0009922813483874">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ozer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zahnd</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Are adolescents being screened for emotional distress in primary care?</article-title> <source>J Adolesc Health</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>520</fpage>-<lpage>527</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0009922813483874">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Habis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tall</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guenther</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Pediatric emergency medicine physicians’ current practices and believes regarding mental health screening</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Emerg Care</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>387</fpage>-<lpage>393</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0009922813483874">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kemper</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zuckerman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Primary care pediatricians’ roles and perceived responsibilities in the identification and management of depression in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Ambul Pediatr</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0009922813483874">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zuckerbrot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Improving recognition of adolescent depression in primary care</article-title>. <source>Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>694</fpage>-<lpage>704</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0009922813483874">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gerralds</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Psychiatric disorders in adolescents in primary care</article-title>. <source>Br J Psychiatry</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>173</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>-<lpage>309</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0009922813483874">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pajer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Primary care clinicians’ use of standardized tools to assess child psychosocial problems</article-title>. <source>Ambul Pediatr</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>-<lpage>195</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0009922813483874">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laraque</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>; <collab>for the American Academy of Pediatrics Task Force on Mental Health</collab>. <article-title>Enhancing pediatric mental health care: strategies for preparing a primary care practice</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>S87</fpage>-<lpage>S108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0009922813483874">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zuckerbrot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maxon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pagar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Adolescent depression screening in primary care: feasibility and acceptability</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0009922813483874">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Horowitz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Barriers to health care research for children and youth with psychosocial problems</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>288</volume>:<fpage>1508</fpage>-<lpage>1512</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0009922813483874">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Danhauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>David</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Survey of pediatricians and early hearing detection and identificationprograms at a precise local level: an academic medical center</article-title>. <source>Semin Hear</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>-<lpage>183</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0009922813483874">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Primary care providers’ views regarding assessing and treating suicidal patients</article-title>. <source>Suicide Life Threat Behav</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>614</fpage>-<lpage>623</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0009922813483874">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danhauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Celani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Hearing and balance screening and referrals for medicare patients: a national survey of primary care physicians</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Audiol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>-<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0009922813483874">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Karpel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szema</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Differences in physicians’ self-reported knowledge of, attitudes toward, and responses to the black box warning on long-acting β-agonists</article-title>. <source>Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>304</fpage>-<lpage>310</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0009922813483874">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leece</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhandari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sprague</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Internet versus mailed questionnaires: a controlled comparison</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e39</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0009922813483874">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Borowsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ireland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>National survey of pediatricians’ violence prevention counseling</article-title>. <source>Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>1170</fpage>-<lpage>1176</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0009922813483874">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zuckerbrot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghalib</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laraque</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Guidelines for Adolescent Depression in Primary Care (GLAD-PC): II. Treatment and ongoing management</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>120</volume>:<fpage>e1313</fpage>-<lpage>e1326</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0009922813483874">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horowitz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Storfer-Isser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heneghan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoagwood</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Do pediatricians think they are responsible for indentification and management of child mental health problems? results of the AAP Pediatric Survey</article-title>. <source>Ambul Pediatr</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0009922813483874">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pfaff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Acres</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McKelvey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Training general practitioners to recognise and respond to psychological distress and suicidal ideation in young people</article-title>. <source>Med J Aust</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>174</volume>:<fpage>222</fpage>-<lpage>226</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0009922813483874">
<label>36.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gilbody</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whitty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grimshaw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>.<article-title>Educational and organizational interventions to improve the management of depression in primary care: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>289</volume>:<fpage>3145</fpage>-<lpage>3151</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0009922813483874">
<label>37.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Asarnow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jaycox</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of quality improvement intervention for adolescent depression in primary care clinics: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>293</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>-<lpage>319</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>