<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JEN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjen</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Building Physics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1744-2591</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1744-2583</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1744259112440518</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1744259112440518</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Editorial</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bomberg</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>35</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>305</fpage>
<lpage>308</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The wisdom from the Far East explains that a temporary absence of a good manager makes no difference because the enterprise functions as if he or she was there. My recent experience of working in China, where Google does not work, and working with another internet-based, big American e-mail system, added another piece of wisdom to my vocabulary, namely, “good intentions but inadequate tools make the results very poor.” So, with this in mind, I decided that it is the time to balance the editorial board of the journal between those who are close to the retirement and those who are young but received good training in building physics. All members of the editorial board are recognized as experts but some are “experts below 40.”</p>
<p>You may have noticed recent appointments to the editorial board of Dr Hamed Saber from National Research Council of Canada and Dr Manfred Kehrer from Oak Ridge National Laboratory, USA. This time we welcome Dr Thomas Thorsell from Royal Institute of Technology, Stockholm, and Dr Marcin Pazera from Centria Corporation in Pittsburg, Pennsylvania, USA.</p>
<graphic id="img1-1744259112440518" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1744259112440518-img1.tif"/>
<p>Marcin Pazera, PhD, is a Senior Research and Development Associate with CENTRIA in Moon Township, Pennsylvania. He holds a Bachelor’s degree in Architectural Technology (BTech) with building science specialization from Ryerson University in Toronto, Canada; Master’s degree in Applied Science in Building Engineering (MASc) from Concordia University in Montreal, Canada; and Doctor of Philosophy degree in Mechanical Engineering from Syracuse University in Syracuse, New York, USA.</p>
<p>He has worked as a researcher and a consultant on building science issues related to building enclosure design, performance, and durability. His research has been focused on moisture transport and effects on materials, development of hygrothermal test methods for laboratory, and field performance of building enclosure materials/systems. Between 2000 and 2008, Dr Pazera was a leading member in the team responsible for the development of hygrothermal laboratories for evaluation of hygrothermal properties of materials, first at Concordia University (Montreal) and later at Syracuse University. In this time, he also worked with heat, air, and moisture transfer; computational fluid dynamics; and indoor air quality. More notable projects included development of laboratory performance evaluation of Water Resistive Barriers (WRB); evaluation of moisture drainage, retention, and drying capability of various External Insulation and Finish System (EIFS); and Moisture and Airflow Characterization of Siding Materials and Evaluation of Drying Performance of Wet Applied Cellulose Insulation to improve industry practices for product installation in cold climate.</p>
<p>Between 2008 and 2011, working in a leading consultation company he was investigating moisture- and thermal-related problems in building enclosures applying advanced computer simulation tools for the design and repair of building enclosures. Currently, he works in design and evaluation of panelized buildings.</p>
<p>Dr Pazera is a voting member on ASTM International including the C16 Thermal Insulation, E06 Performance of Buildings, E06.41 Air Leakage and Ventilation Performance, E06.55 Exterior Building Wall Systems, E06.58 Exterior Insulation and Finish Systems (EIFS), E60 Sustainability, and E60.01 Buildings and Construction. He is a member of American Society of Heating, Refrigerating, and Air-Conditioning Engineers (ASHRAE) and committee of National Institute of Building Sciences (NIBS). He is a former co-Chair of Building Enclosure Council (BEC), Washington (DC), and a current co-chair of the Western Pennsylvania BEC Chapter. He published 12 referred journal papers and a number of conference presentations.</p>
<graphic id="img2-1744259112440518" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1744259112440518-img2.tif"/>
<p>On 16 March 2012, Mr Thomas Thorsell will defend his PhD thesis. Yet, this editorial is written before 16 March, so we have to call him mister, even though a few years ago he defended his technical licentiate.</p>
<p>During his high school years, in 1986, Mr Thomas Thorsell started to work as a part-time manual draftsman. In 1992, he received Master of Science in Civil Engineering at the School of Architecture and the Built Environment, Division of Building Technology, Royal Institute of Technology (supervisor: Gudni A. Jóhannesson, Director General, The Icelandic National Energy Authority/Affiliated professor at KTH Sweden).</p>
<p>He continued work first as junior designer and in years 1994–2007 as a building engineer. This job included building design, consulting, and quality control. During this time, he was working with building design supervision, energy performance, and construction quality control. In the last 2 years of this period, the work was mainly focused on consulting.</p>
<p>Parallel to working in the consulting company Mr Thorsell performed research and studied at the Royal Institute of Technology (KTH, Stockholm). The most important projects were as follows:</p>
<list id="list1-1744259112440518" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>European research project EC-SAVE project KOPRACTICE (bringing KOBRA and EUROKOBRA to the building PRACTICE).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>European research project ENPER (European collaboration in relation to Energy Performance Regulation for buildings and model code development).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Annex 39, HiPTI (High Performance Thermal Insulation) dealing with use of vacuum insulation panels in buildings.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Working with the latter project, Mr Thorsell prepared thesis on “Vacuum insulation in buildings—Means to prolong service life” and in 2006 defended the licentiate degree in Building Technology at the School of Architecture and the Built Environment, Division of Building Technology, Royal Institute of Technology (supervisor: Prof. Gudni A. Jóhannesson)</p>
<p>In 2007, Mr Thorsell accepted position of a teaching assistant at Department of Mechanical Engineering of the Syracuse University, and for the next 2 years, he was working as a key researcher in Syracuse University, Industrial Consortium on Assembly for Built Environmental Systems. His work was focused on development of test methodology for heat and air performance of building enclosures. In addition to the published research, one should mention the Research Internship (summer 2008) on a novel desiccant air conditioning system where Mr Thorsell led the data acquisition and the data analysis.</p>
<p>During years 2007–2011, he worked at LC Smith College of Engineering and Computer Science, Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, Syracuse University, Syracuse, New York, USA, on Development of an Integrated Testing and Modeling Method for Determining the Thermal Performance under Simultaneous Heat and Air Flow Conditions with cosupervisors Mark Bomberg, Research Prof., and Jianshun Zhang, Prof. and director BEESL at Syracuse University. This research can be seen in the published papers.</p>
<p>Mr Thorsell wrote six referred journal papers in English and two papers in Swedish and six referred conference papers. Since 2008, Mr Thorsell is a member of ASHRAE and since 2009 also of the International Society of Indoor Air Quality and Climate (ISIAQ).</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>Mark Bomberg</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>