<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MIS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmis</journal-id>
<journal-title>Missiology: An International Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0091-8296</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2051-3623</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0091829612475170c</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0091829612475170c</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: <italic>Pedagogy for religion: missionary education and the fashioning of Hindus and Muslims in Bengal</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Priest</surname><given-names>Robert J.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hedlund</surname><given-names>Roger E.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<issue-title>Special issue: Anthropology and Sociology of Short-Term Missions</issue-title>
<fpage>228</fpage>
<lpage>230</lpage>
<product>
<source>Pedagogy for religion: missionary education and the fashioning of Hindus and Muslims in Bengal</source> <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>Parna</given-names></name>
</person-group> <publisher-loc>Berkeley, Los Angeles, London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>. <page-count count="X"/> + <page-count count="211"/> pp. <price>$29.95</price>, paper.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">American Society of Missiology</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In this fascinating study of Bengal’s colonial history, Parna Sengupta finds that the Evangelical missionary educational project had unintended consequences in the Hindu and Muslim communities in Bengal and for the future development of Independent India. Contrary to the popular secularization “myth” which assumes that Western colonial schooling and rule demystified and secularized South Asian society, Sengupta demonstrates how modern education actually intensified religious commitment and identity. Upper caste Hindus, for instance, utilized the English language and English schools for retaining dominance. Simultaneously, caste prejudice deemed the lowest castes unfit for schooling, consigning them thus to perpetual servitude—despite the protests of CMS missionary James Long and Bengali pastor Lal Behari De and other reformers. Sengupta’s exposition of the outcome of the “Permanent Settlement” (pp. 36–39) is one of the highlights of the book.</p>
<p>Another important facet of this study concerns the identity of Bengali Muslims. Is the Bengali Muslim a peasant basically the same as a Bengali Hindu peasant? Or is the Bengali Muslim primarily a Muslim and only incidentally a Bengali? “Religious reformers targeted the continued use by Bengali Muslims of devotional traditions and charms, astrological beliefs, and stories of their Hindu neighbors” (p. 142). The tension and ambiguity are never fully resolved but would resurface in two Bengali nationalist movements in 1947 and 1971 (p. 131). At issue is the religious character of village schools in nineteenth-century Bengal, a discussion with particular insight into political developments in the twentieth century.</p>
<p>One or two flaws may be pointed out. Sengupta’s reconstruction carries a major supposition: she assumes that the missionary purpose was to serve the interests of the British colonial rule and hence that the intended purpose of mission schools and colleges was the production of Christian subjects loyal to the British Raj (pp. 7, 9). To identify the work of the missions with colonialism is a common error which, however, distorts the facts. In actuality, the missions were barely tolerated. A striking case was the opposition of the East India Company to the presence of William Carey and the early Baptist missionaries who sought refuge at Serampore to avoid arrest and deportation from Calcutta.</p>
<p>The connection between the Evangelical development of Sunday Schools in London and the establishment of vernacular rural education in Bengal (pp. 29, 44) is not clear. (The Sunday School was originally begun by Evangelicals in order to provide opportunity for London’s poor to learn to read. After a national education system provided mass education for all, the Sunday School switched to Christian religious education in the churches.) These minor blemishes need not detract from the findings of an important study.</p>
<p>Sengupta’s ground-breaking work will be of particular interest to scholars of modern Bengali and South Asian religious history as well as to researchers into various aspects of colonial and missionary history. Distinct entities they may be, yet at several points the colonial and missionary do both intersect and interact. Parna Sengupta, author of this seminal study, has a PhD in History from the University of Michigan, and at present serves as Associate Director of Stanford Introductory Studies at Stanford University in the San Francisco Bay area, USA.</p>
<p>Roger E. Hedlund, PhD (University of Madras) lived for 32 years in India serving in several capacities, including Professor of Mission Research at Serampore College near Kolkata. He is chief editor of the <italic>Oxford Encyclopedia of South Asian Christianity</italic> (New Delhi, 2012).</p>
</body>
</article>