<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SJP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsjp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Scand J Public Health</journal-id>
<journal-title>Scandinavian Journal of Public Health</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1403-4948</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1651-1905</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1403494812449078</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1403494812449078</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Trends in out-of-hospital ischaemic heart disease deaths 1992 to 2003 in southern Sweden</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Gerward</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1403494812449078">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1403494812449078">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1403494812449078">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Midlöv</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1403494812449078">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ekesbo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1403494812449078">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Gullberg</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1403494812449078">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hedblad</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1403494812449078">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1403494812449078"><label>1</label>Department of Clinical Sciences in Malmö, Cardiovascular Epidemiology, Lund University, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1403494812449078"><label>2</label>Department of Cardiology</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1403494812449078"><label>3</label>Department of Clinical Sciences in Malmö, General Practice/Family Medicine, Sweden</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1403494812449078">Sofia Gerward, Department of Clinical Sciences in Malmö, Cardiovascular Epidemiology, CRC, Entrance 60 floor 13, Skåne University Hospital, S-205 02 MALMÖ, Sweden. E-mail: <email>sofia.gerward@med.lu.se</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>340</fpage>
<lpage>347</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>29</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 the Nordic Societies of Public Health</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Associations of Public Health in the Nordic Countries Regions</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-1403494812449078">
<title>Aims:</title>
<p>In western countries out-of-hospital ischaemic heart disease (IHD) deaths account for approximately 50–70% of all IHD deaths. The objective was to examine the trends in out-of-hospital IHD deaths in the Region of Skåne in southern Sweden, in different sex- and age-groups.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1403494812449078">
<title>Methods:</title>
<p>All 14,347 persons (range 24–110 years) in Skåne who died out-of-hospital between 1992 and 2003 from IHD (I410–I414; I20–I25) as the underlying cause of death. Subjects with previous admission for IHD since 1970 were excluded. Data were retrieved from the Swedish National Cause of Death and Patient Register. Age-standardized IHD mortality rates and trends were calculated using Poisson regression analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1403494812449078">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>Age-standardized annual out-of-hospital IHD mortality rates from 1992–2003 decreased in men from 177±13 to 103±9/100,000 inhabitants (−4.7%; <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001) and in women from 142±11 to 96±9/100,000 (−2.7%; <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001). In men, the annual change in age-standardized IHD mortality rates were −5.3 % (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001), −4.0 % (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001) and −4.7 % (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001), respectively, in the age groups 20–64 years, 65–74 years and ≥75 years. Corresponding figures in women were −4.4 % (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001), −2.4 % (<italic>p</italic>=0.003) and −2.5 % (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001). The proportion of IHD deaths occurring out-of-hospital was in these age groups 50%, 40% and 35% respectively.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1403494812449078">
<title>Conclusions:</title>
<p><bold>In Skåne, out-of-hospital mortality in IHD deaths decreased significantly between 1992 and 2003. The decrease is more pronounced in men than women, and at the end of the study period in 2003, rates were almost equal. The proportion of IHD deaths occurring outside hospital was higher in younger people than in older people</bold>.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Coronary disease</kwd>
<kwd>epidemiology</kwd>
<kwd>mortality</kwd>
<kwd>trends</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section5-1403494812449078">
<title>Background</title>
<p>In 2006, ischaemic heart disease (IHD) accounted for 18% in women and 21% in men of all deaths in Sweden [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1403494812449078">1</xref>]. In both sexes, the mortality in IHD decreased by about 50% in Sweden between 1987 and 2006 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1403494812449078">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1403494812449078">2</xref>]. This decrease is due to both decreased incidence as well as case-fatality rates and is similar to mortality trends in other western countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1403494812449078">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1403494812449078">4</xref>]. However, although the trends are declining in Sweden, the immediate deaths after myocardial infarction (MI), are not as favourable as for 28-day case fatality rates among hospitalized patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1403494812449078">2</xref>]. Out-of-hospital IHD deaths constitute between 50–70% of all IHD deaths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1403494812449078">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1403494812449078"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1403494812449078">7</xref>]. Out-of-hospital IHD deaths are thus considered an important target for efforts aiming at further reducing the IHD mortality.</p>
<p>There are few studies reporting trends in out-of-hospital IHD deaths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1403494812449078">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1403494812449078"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1403494812449078"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1403494812449078"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1403494812449078">12</xref>]. One reason may be a lack of a national registry of these deaths. In some of these studies important sex and age differences, with smaller decreases in elderly people and in women, have been demonstrated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1403494812449078">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1403494812449078"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1403494812449078">10</xref>]. In addition, studies have shown substantial regional variations in mortality in IHD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1403494812449078">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1403494812449078">13</xref>], thus regional studies are warranted to allocate resources on both regional and national levels.</p>
<p>We therefore explored trends in IHD out-of-hospital mortality between 1992 and 2003 in southern Sweden, a region with the same climate, geography and provider of medical care and with special emphasis on sex and age differences in trends.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1403494812449078" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Material and methods</title>
<sec id="section7-1403494812449078">
<title>Demographic setting</title>
<p>This study is based on data from the Region of Skåne situated in southern Sweden, with 822,441 inhabitants aged 20 and over (397,198 men and 425,243 women) in 1992, and 879,624 inhabitants aged 20 and over (427,057 men and 452,567 women) in 2003. Of these, about 53% lived in 13 cities and 17% in 25 smaller villages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.regionfakta.com">www.regionfakta.com</ext-link>). The total area of the region is about 11,000 square kilometres and the agricultural land covers about 48% and forested land covers 35%, compared to 8% and 53%, respectively, in Sweden as a whole. The climate is characterized by relatively warm summers and mild winters. During the study period a large change in the organization of the healthcare system in Skåne in southern Sweden was enacted by 1 January 1999. Three counties (the city of Malmö, Malmöhus county and Kristianstad county) with their own responsibility for health care were united into the Region of Skåne. The Region of Skåne is a politically run organization, which has elections every fourth year and organizes the medical care in this region. In addition, there were 10 hospitals providing 24-hour emergency care. During the study period no new hospitals were opened or closed. Among these, there were two university hospitals (Malmö and Lund), two medium-care hospitals (Helsingborg and Kristianstad) and six smaller hospitals (Ängelholm, Hässleholm, Landskrona, Trelleborg, Ystad and Simrishamn), as well as about 120 primary healthcare centres. There were four percutaneous intervention centres (Malmö, Lund, Helsingborg and Kristianstad). In rural areas the longest driving time to hospital was 60 minutes, and a primary care centre could be reached within 30 minutes. However, in the urban areas of the region, these figures are much lower (i.e. within a maximum of 10–15 minutes).</p>
<p>In 1999, mobile electrocardiograms (ECG) for the ambulances in Skåne were introduced to enable pre-hospital thrombolysis. Gradually from around 2002 to 2003 the recommended method was changed to direct percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) in ST-elevation infarction and transport direct from home to the nearest PCI centre using mobile ECG. In 1999 the first pre-hospital heart care programme in Skåne (PHAVIS) was created to coordinate effective patient transports between ambulance, primary care, emergency room and heart intensive care units. The ambulance resource is spread over Skåne in relation to the number of inhabitants in different cities/communities and has gradually increased during the study period 1992–2003.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1403494812449078">
<title>Case retrieval</title>
<p>Data were collected from the National Cause of Death Register [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1403494812449078">1</xref>] and the National Patient Register [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1403494812449078">14</xref>], which includes data from 1970 and onwards in this region. Both these registers are provided by the National Board of Health, Centre of Epidemiology (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.socialstyrelsen.se">http://www.socialstyrelsen.se</ext-link>). Of all deaths in Sweden, information on cause of death was missing in 0.7%, and in another 0.3% data were missing due to technical reasons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1403494812449078">15</xref>]. In the Patient Registry a hospital discharge diagnosis is missing in less than 1% in this region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1403494812449078">15</xref>].</p>
<p>A database was created comprising all incident cases of IHD who died out-of-hospital during the period 1992 to 2003. A case was defined as a death certificate diagnosis of ICD-9: I410 and ICD-10: I21 as an underlying or a contributing cause of death or ICD-9: I411-I414 and ICD-10: I20, I22-I25 as the underlying cause of death. Patients with symptomatic IHD are high risk individuals for out-of-hospital cardiac deaths. To ensure that participants did not have a previous hospital admission with IHD we excluded those with previous admission for ICD-9: I410-I414 and ICD-10: I20-I25 according to principal or secondary diagnosis from 1970 onwards. Cases who died in the emergency room are considered as out-of-hospital deaths according to national classification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1403494812449078">1</xref>]. We chose to start the study in 1992 because of important changes in the reporting system of deaths, which were established on 1 July 1991 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1403494812449078">15</xref>]. After this date, the death certificate was divided into two forms: 1) a death certificate to be sent the first working day after the death to the Swedish Tax Agency, and 2) a cause of death certificate to be sent within three weeks to the National Board of Health and Welfare for registration. After this change in the reporting system, it became customary for the doctor on-call to complete the first form (i.e. the death certificate) and the ordinary doctor specifies the cause of death for most deaths occurring out-of-hospital. Following these changes in the reporting system, the autopsy rate decreased significantly from 52% in 1991 to 35% in 1992, especially for those aged ≥75 years, but after 1992 the autopsy rate has been rather stable. In southern Sweden the 10th International Classification of Diseases (ICD) was implemented in 1998. However, the changeover in the ICD has been shown to have only a minimal effect on the coding of cardiac deaths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1403494812449078">15</xref>]. In 2001, new diagnostic criteria for MI were introduced. The introduction of new criteria for MI with more focus on cardiac biomarkers should mainly affect incidence, however, and affects the out-of-hospital IHD deaths to a lesser extent.</p>
<p>For each case, information on date of birth, sex, date of death, cause of death and autopsy was available. Population figures and the total mortality in IHD for 1992–2003 were retrieved from the National Board of Health and Welfare.</p>
<p>The study was approved by the Regional Ethical Committee at Lund University, Sweden (Dnr131/2006).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1403494812449078">
<title>Statistical methods</title>
<p>Out-of-hospital mortality rates were age-standardized with the direct method using five-year age groups and weighted for the population in each age group. The sex-specific mean population in Skåne between the years 1992 and 2003 was used as a standard population. Trends were then calculated using Poisson regression and presented as percent decrease per year. Autopsy rates for different age groups and separately for men and women were calculated. In the statistical analysis SPSS 12.0.1 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) and STATA 10.0 software were used. A <italic>p</italic>-value &lt;0.05 was considered to be statistically significant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1403494812449078" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Between 1 January 1992 and 31 December 2003 a total of 14,347 people died out-of-hospital from IHD. Of these, 51.2% were men and 48.8% were women, and the average age at the time of death was 74.6±12.3 years for men and 83.4±9.8 years for women. In 1992, the mean age was 74.1±11.8 years for men and 81.9±10.2 years for women, increasing to 75.1±12.5 years for men and to 85.7±9.8 years for women in 2003.</p>
<sec id="section11-1403494812449078">
<title>Out-of-hospital IHD mortality rates</title>
<p>The age-standardized out-of-hospital IHD mortality during 1992–2003 decreased in men from 177±13 to 103±9/100,000 inhabitants (−4.7%; <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001) and in women from 142±11 to 96±9/100,000 (−2.7%; <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1403494812449078">Figure 1</xref>). In men, the annual change in age-standardized mortality rates were −5.3 % (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001), −4.0 % (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001) and −4.7 % (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001), respectively, in the age groups 20–64 years, 65–74 years and ≥75 years (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1403494812449078">Table I</xref>). Corresponding figures in women were −4.4 % (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001), −2.4 % (<italic>p</italic>=0.003) and −2.5 % (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001), respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1403494812449078">Table I</xref>). A significant decrease in out-of-hospital IHD mortality rates was observed in both sexes and in all age groups, but these were more pronounced in men than in women. At the end of the study period in 2003, mortality rates in out-of-hospital IHD deaths in men and women were almost at the same level. In 2003, men &lt;75 years compared to women, had two to three times higher rates of out-of-hospital IHD deaths.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1403494812449078" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Age-standardized mortality in out-of-hospital ischaemic heart disease deaths in the Region of Skåne during 1992 to 2003. The figures are presented as annual age-standardized mortality per 100,000 inhabitants with 95% confidence intervals (CI).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1403494812449078-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-1403494812449078" position="float">
<label>Table I.</label>
<caption><p>Age-standardized mortality in out-of-hospital coronary heart disease deaths in Skåne during 1992 to 2003.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1403494812449078" xlink:href="10.1177_1403494812449078-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Year</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">All ages (over 20 years)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">20–64 years<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">65–74 years<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">75 years and above<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Men</th>
<th align="left">Women</th>
<th align="left">Men</th>
<th align="left">Women</th>
<th align="left">Men</th>
<th align="left">Women</th>
<th align="left">Men</th>
<th align="left">Women</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1992</td>
<td>177±13</td>
<td>142±11</td>
<td>49±8</td>
<td>13±4</td>
<td>368±54</td>
<td>127±29</td>
<td>1074±110</td>
<td>829±74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1993</td>
<td>171±13</td>
<td>144±11</td>
<td>51±8</td>
<td>9±3</td>
<td>363±53</td>
<td>134±30</td>
<td>990±105</td>
<td>859±75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1994</td>
<td>172±13</td>
<td>142±11</td>
<td>46±8</td>
<td>10±4</td>
<td>328±51</td>
<td>116±28</td>
<td>1102±109</td>
<td>855±74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1995</td>
<td>174±13</td>
<td>149±11</td>
<td>46±8</td>
<td>8±3</td>
<td>394±56</td>
<td>117±28</td>
<td>1028±104</td>
<td>915±75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1996</td>
<td>169±13</td>
<td>140±11</td>
<td>44±7</td>
<td>9±3</td>
<td>344±53</td>
<td>132±30</td>
<td>1058±104</td>
<td>833±71</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1997</td>
<td>164±12</td>
<td>145±11</td>
<td>40±7</td>
<td>8±3</td>
<td>363±55</td>
<td>136±31</td>
<td>1013±101</td>
<td>872±72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1998</td>
<td>137±11</td>
<td>138±11</td>
<td>32±6</td>
<td>6±3</td>
<td>318±52</td>
<td>141±32</td>
<td>833±91</td>
<td>819±69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1999</td>
<td>140±11</td>
<td>132±10</td>
<td>36±6</td>
<td>8±3</td>
<td>268±46</td>
<td>122±30</td>
<td>900±94</td>
<td>791±67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2000</td>
<td>133±11</td>
<td>113±10</td>
<td>35±6</td>
<td>8±3</td>
<td>304±51</td>
<td>109±28</td>
<td>792±87</td>
<td>666±61</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2001</td>
<td>108±10</td>
<td>109±9</td>
<td>32±6</td>
<td>9±3</td>
<td>216±43</td>
<td>98±27</td>
<td>649±78</td>
<td>640±60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2002</td>
<td>126±10</td>
<td>107±9</td>
<td>31±6</td>
<td>9±3</td>
<td>303±51</td>
<td>107±28</td>
<td>742±83</td>
<td>615±58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2003</td>
<td>103±9</td>
<td>96±9</td>
<td>27±5</td>
<td>6±2</td>
<td>217±43</td>
<td>99±27</td>
<td>637±76</td>
<td>564±56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Annual change (95% CI)</td>
<td>−4.7%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1403494812449078">*</xref> (−5.3 to −4.1)</td>
<td>−2.7%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1403494812449078">*</xref> (−3.5 to −1.9)</td>
<td>−5.3%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1403494812449078">*</xref> (−6.6 to −3.8)</td>
<td>−4.4%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1403494812449078">*</xref> (−6.8 to −1.9)</td>
<td>4.0%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1403494812449078">*</xref> (−5.3 to −2.7)</td>
<td>−2.4%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1403494812449078">**</xref> (−4.0 to −0.8)</td>
<td>−4.7%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1403494812449078">*</xref> (−5.6 to −3.9)</td>
<td>−2.5%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1403494812449078">*</xref> (−3.5 to −1.5)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1403494812449078"><p>Figures are presented as annual age-standardized mortality per 100,000 inhabitant’s ± 2 standard deviation (SD). The annual change (95% CI) is calculated using Poisson regression.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-1403494812449078">
<label>*</label>
<p>=<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001, **= <italic>p</italic>=0.003</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1403494812449078">
<title>Proportion who died out-of-hospital</title>
<p>The proportion of out-of-hospital IHD deaths compared to the total number of IHD deaths from 1992 to 2003 varied between 33% and 40% among men and 36% and 45% among women (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1403494812449078">Figure 2</xref>). In the age groups 20–64, 65–74 and ≥75 years the proportion range was 52–63%, 33−46% and 29−35% in men, and 36–60%, 34−48%, 36−45% in women, respectively. Overall, the proportion of out-of-hospital IHD deaths decreased with increasing age. For victims aged 20–64 years, more men than women died out of hospital, however, in the age group ≥75 the findings were the opposite.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1403494812449078" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Proportion of out-of-hospital ischaemic heart disease (IHD) deaths (without previous IHD) compared with the total number of IHD deaths in southern Sweden during the years 1992 to 2003. The figures are presented as all ages above 20 years old, and divided into age groups (20–64 years, 65–74 years and ≥ 75 years).</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1403494812449078-fig2.tif"/></fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1403494812449078">
<title>Autopsy rate</title>
<p>During the study period 1992–2003, eight out of 10 victims aged 20–64 years dying outside hospital due to IHD were autopsied. The corresponding figures for victims aged 65–74 years and ≥75 years was 50–60% and 15–25%, respectively. Thus, autopsy rates were much higher in the younger victims. No statistically significant difference in the autopsy rate between men and women in the age group 20–64 years was observed (data not shown). The age-adjusted autopsy rate among female victims ≥65 years were significantly lower compared to men. No statistically significant decreasing trend in the age-adjusted autopsy rate was seen during the studied time period.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1403494812449078" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In Skåne in southern Sweden, during the period 1992 to 2003, mortality in out-of-hospital IHD in people without a history of IHD has decreased significantly in men and women. The declining trend is approximately two times greater in men than in women. However, in 2003 the mortality rates were almost comparable in both groups. Notably, rates of out-of-hospital IHD deaths in 2003 among men aged &lt;75 years, were two to three times higher than the corresponding age group in women.</p>
<p>A recent Swedish nationwide study showed that out-of-hospital deaths as proportions of all major coronary events (including those hospitalized for acute MI) has decreased annually by 2.2% between 1991 to 2006 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1403494812449078">6</xref>]. In contrast, no changes in the immediate case fatality rate following an MI attack were observed during a 10-year follow-up between 1987 and 1995 in another nationwide Swedish study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1403494812449078">16</xref>]. However, national trends are not necessarily equal to regional trends. Studies have shown that regional variations in trends in mortality within [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1403494812449078">13</xref>] and between countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1403494812449078">5</xref>] are significant, making studies within a single region of great interest. Compared to other Swedish regional studies covering the years 1975 to 1999 our results are largely in line [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1403494812449078">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1403494812449078">12</xref>]. However, in these studies only people below 65 years old were included. Furthermore, in the MONICA study from northern Sweden [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1403494812449078">10</xref>], there was no obvious decrease in sudden cardiac mortality among women. This is in contrast to a study of middle-aged subjects in Finland, where a yearly decrease in out-of-hospital death from IHD of about 6–7% in both genders was presented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1403494812449078">11</xref>]. This result is in accordance with a study from Scotland [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1403494812449078">8</xref>]. In that study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1403494812449078">8</xref>] and in a study from United States [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1403494812449078">9</xref>] older participants were included, showing lesser decreases in elderly people and in women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1403494812449078">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1403494812449078">9</xref>]. In accordance with these studies, the present study showed that the percentage in annual reduction in the mortality rates was higher in men than in women across all age groups. Furthermore, elderly women showed lower reductions in death rates compared to the youngest age group. However, in absolute numbers the out-of-hospital IHD mortality was highest in the oldest age group, which simply reflects that age is a major risk factor for out-of- hospital cardiovascular mortality.</p>
<p>In the present study the IHD deaths out of hospital among subjects aged 20 years and over constituted about 30–40% of the total number of IHD deaths. The proportions were, however, higher in those younger than 65 years, i.e. 40–60%. However, in that age group the number of IHD deaths is rather low, especially among women, which makes it difficult to compare proportion figures between age groups. In addition, a higher autopsy rate in subjects aged &lt;65 years can also influence the observed differences in proportions between the age groups. Another possible explanation is that younger individuals are more prone to ST-elevation infarctions, a condition associated with higher acute cardiac mortality. The IHD deaths out of hospital of the total number of IHD deaths in people aged 20–65 and &gt;65 years, respectively, in our study are somewhat lower compared to national and international studies, which in the present study could be explained by the fact that the study group consisted of people without previous hospital admission for IHD diagnosis since 1970. Importantly, we excluded patients with prior hospital registration for IHD. It is well-known that out-of-hospital IHD deaths today constitute the larger part of the total number of IHD deaths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1403494812449078">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1403494812449078"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1403494812449078">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1403494812449078">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1403494812449078">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1403494812449078">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1403494812449078">17</xref>]. Out-of hospital fatality from acute IHD is also inversely related to age and is common in people without a history of IHD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1403494812449078">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1403494812449078">7</xref>]. Thus, effective primary prevention, traditionally associated with out-of-hospital IHD deaths, is increasingly important in reducing the total mortality. The American Heart Association Council on Clinical Cardiology Committee recently stated that we still lack the tools to identify and treat people at risk for sudden cardiac death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1403494812449078">18</xref>]. Despite this difficult task, the improved primary prevention both on the individual level and on the population level, during the last decades, may very well be associated with the decreasing trend seen in out-of-hospital IHD mortality in the present study.</p>
<p>The INTERHEART study, a worldwide case-control study in 52 countries, showed that nine modifiable risk factors (hyperlipidaemia, smoking, hypertension, diabetes, abdominal obesity, psychosocial factors, consumption of fruits and vegetables, alcohol and physical activity) explained about 90% of the risk of MI worldwide in both sexes, in all ages, and in all regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1403494812449078">19</xref>]. One recent study from Sweden has showed that more than 50% of the substantial IHD mortality decrease among people aged 25–84 years in Sweden, between 1986 and 2002, was attributable to reductions in major risk factors, mainly a large decrease in total serum cholesterol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1403494812449078">20</xref>]. In that study medical and surgical treatments explained 1/3 of the mortality reduction, however relatively small reductions (&lt;4%) were a result of coronary revascularization for chronic angina or in connection with acute MI or unstable angina. As the observation period in that study is rather similar to our study it is reasonable to believe that these results are also valid for the Region of Skåne. Comparative health conditions surveys of risk factors were performed among inhabitants in the Region of Skåne in the year 2000, 2004 and 2008 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1403494812449078">21</xref>]. These results have been used to target health preventive measures in the region and to make changes to the healthcare system aiming at a healthier Skåne population. In the report from 2008 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1403494812449078">21</xref>], when comparing prevalence rates with the year 2000, smoking had slightly decreased. In addition, a small improvement in leisuretime physical activity was found among women; however, the proportion of overweight/obesity in both sexes had increased substantially. These surveys did not retrieve any data on blood lipids, blood pressure, presence or treatment for hypertension or diabetes.</p>
<p>The reorganization of the three county councils in 1999 into the Region of Skåne has increased the communication and collaboration between hospitals and primary care units in Skåne. It remains to be evaluated whether this profound change in the organization of the healthcare system in the Region of Skåne is related to the declining trend in out-of-hospital deaths in IHD in the present study. In addition, since 1999 there have been pharmaceutical therapy groups in the Region of Skåne. These groups publish annual drug recommendations for physicians to be used when treating certain conditions aiming at improving the choice of appropriate medical drugs in the Region of Skåne. This may help the health providers to adhere to medical guidelines.</p>
<p>The decreased incidence of ST-elevation myocardial infarctions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1403494812449078">22</xref>], traditionally more common in younger men, could also be a contributor to the decreased out-of-hospital cardiac deaths observed in the present study.</p>
<p>Women aged 20 to 64 years, when compared to men, generally had lower rates and lesser decreases during the 10-year study period in out-of-hospital IHD mortality. One explanation might be that sudden cardiac death incidence in women lags behind men by more than 10 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1403494812449078">23</xref>], and thus a larger part of out-of-hospital IHD deaths among women occur in elderly people. Furthermore, smoking rates have been almost unchanged during recent decades among women, whereas in men smoking has decreased in all age groups. Lung cancer incidence is now more common among women up to 65 years of age than in men [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1403494812449078">24</xref>].</p>
<p>Differences in access to medical care and medical seeking patterns could perhaps influence the out-of-hospital cardiac deaths. In Sweden, all inhabitants are insured through a public healthcare system where ambulance transport is free of charge and in- and out-of-hospital care is provided at a very low cost. In a previous study from the city of Malmö in southern Sweden, two thirds of the patients who died out of hospital of MI had been in contact with the medical services within the last three months prior to their death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1403494812449078">25</xref>]. However, many had visited clinics that normally do not treat coronary symptoms. In that study no significant differences between men and women and different age-groups were observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1403494812449078">25</xref>]. Furthermore, there are multiple factors such as older age, female sex, low social support, that affect pre-hospital delay in patients with acute coronary syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1403494812449078">26</xref>]. In addition, differences in socioeconomic circumstances have been shown to influence the out-of-hospital MI mortality rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1403494812449078">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1403494812449078">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1403494812449078">27</xref>]. Compared with the lowest income group, the highest income group had a 50–70% lower risk of pre-hospital death in MI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1403494812449078">25</xref>].</p>
<p>This study has some strengths but also some limitations. The strength of the present study is that elderly people and both sexes were included, living in a region with the same climate, geography and provider of medical care. Swedish registries provide unique possibilities to study trends in IHD, including registered cases of all ages. In southern Sweden the Patient Registry started in 1970 giving us the ability to create a study population without previous hospital admission for IHD up to 22–34 years before the incident out-of-hospital IHD death. A validation study from the National Board of Health and Welfare in Sweden has shown that the diagnosis of MI and IHD is valid in 95% of the cases in the Patient Register [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1403494812449078">28</xref>]. The Cause of Death Registry has limitations, the most important being the assumed cause of death as reported by a physician, which is based, among non-autopsied cases, on previous clinical history and medical findings during examination. In the present study the autopsy rate was around 80% in the age group 20–64 years during the study period. In older patients, the cause of death may be less reliable due to greater comorbidity and a lower autopsy rate than in younger people. According to Swedish law, an autopsy is required when the cause of death cannot be established. A validation of certificates of out-of-hospital IHD deaths in the United States has shown an agreement in about 80% of the cases after physician review of medical records and had a high sensitivity and a positive predictive value of 91% and 96%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1403494812449078">29</xref>]. No similar validation study of out-of-hospital deaths has been performed during the study period 1992–2003 in Sweden. Although the underlying cause of death in the present study population was ischaemic heart disease, an unknown proportion of rare diseases such as hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, primary arrhythmia and other hereditary cardiac diseases, especially among younger people, could be misdiagnosed. Due to study design, and because our cases died out-of-hospital, we lack individual information about conventional and modern risk factors, circumstances affecting pre-hospital delay and socioeconomic circumstances, any or all of which could possibly influence the results.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1403494812449078" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In Skåne in southern Sweden the out-of-hospital IHD mortality decreased significantly between the years 1992 and 2003. The decrease is more pronounced in men than in women, and at the end of the study period in 2003, rates were almost equal. However men aged &lt;75 years, in 2003 still had a two to three times higher rate of out-of-hospital IHD deaths than women. The proportion of IHD deaths occurring outside hospital was higher in younger than older victims. Further studies are warranted to explain these differences and to improve the identification of individuals at risk.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This work was supported by the Swedish Heart and Lung Foundation, Swedish Research Council, The Region of Skane (ALF-grants), Malmo University Hospital.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interests</label>
<p>None declared.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1403494812449078">
<label>[1]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Board of Health and Welfare</collab>. <comment>Center of Epidemiology</comment>. <article-title>Causes of death 2004 and 2006</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm, Sweden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NBHW</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1403494812449078">
<label>[2]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Board of Health and Welfare</collab>. <comment>Centre of Epidemiology</comment>. <article-title>Myocardial infarctions in Sweden 1987-2006</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm, Sweden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NBHW</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1403494812449078">
<label>[3]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kannel</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Temporal trends in coronary heart disease mortality and sudden cardiac death from 1950 to 1999: the Framingham Heart Study</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2004</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>522</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1403494812449078">
<label>[4]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tunstall-Pedoe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuulasmaa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mahonen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tolonen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruokokoski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amouyel</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Contribution of trends in survival and coronary-event rates to changes in coronary heart disease mortality: 10-year results from 37 WHO MONICA project populations. Monitoring trends and determinants in cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>1999</year>;<volume>353</volume>(<issue>9164</issue>):<fpage>1547</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1403494812449078">
<label>[5]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chambless</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keil</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dobson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mahonen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuulasmaa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rajakangas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Population versus clinical view of case fatality from acute coronary heart disease: results from the WHO MONICA Project 1985-1990. Multinational MONItoring of Trends and Determinants in CArdiovascular Disease</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3849</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1403494812449078">
<label>[6]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dudas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lappas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosengren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Trends in out-of-hospital deaths due to coronary heart disease in Sweden (1991 to 2006)</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2011</year>;<volume>123</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1403494812449078">
<label>[7]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>RM.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Fatality outside hospital from acute coronary events in three British health districts, 1994-5. United Kingdom Heart Attack Study Collaborative Group</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>1998</year>;<volume>316</volume>(<issue>7137</issue>):<fpage>1065</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref> <ref id="bibr8-1403494812449078">
<label>[8]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Capewell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacIntyre</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chalmers</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Finlayson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Age, sex, and social trends in out-of-hospital cardiac deaths in Scotland 1986-95: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2001</year>;<volume>358</volume>(<issue>9289</issue>):<fpage>1213</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1403494812449078">
<label>[9]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weston</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Killian</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>VL.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Secular trends in deaths from cardiovascular diseases: a 25-year community study</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>2285</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1403494812449078">
<label>[10]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Messner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lundberg</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Trends in sudden cardiac death in the northern Sweden MONICA area 1985-99</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source> <year>2003</year>;<volume>253</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>320</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1403494812449078">
<label>[11]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salomaa</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ketonen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koukkunen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Immonen-Raiha</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jerkkola</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karja-Koskenkari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Decline in out-of-hospital coronary heart disease deaths has contributed the main part to the overall decline in coronary heart disease mortality rates among persons 35 to 64 years of age in Finland: the FINAMI study</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2003</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>691</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1403494812449078">
<label>[12]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilhelmsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosengren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lappas</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Coronary heart disease attack rate, incidence and mortality 1975-1994 in Goteborg, Sweden</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>572</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1403494812449078">
<label>[13]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nichol</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aufderheide</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Regional variation in out-of-hospital cardiac arrest incidence and outcome</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <year>2008</year>;<volume>300</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1423</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1403494812449078">
<label>[14]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Board of Health and Welfare</collab>. <comment>Center of Epidemiology</comment>. <article-title>Patientregistret. Utskrivningar från sluten vård 1964-2006. Kvalitet och innehåll</article-title>. [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Patient Registry. Discharges from in-patient care 1964-2006. Quality and content.</trans-title>]. <source>Stockholm</source>, <publisher-loc>Sweden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NBHW</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1403494812449078">
<label>[15]</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>National Board of Health and Welfare</collab>. <article-title>Cause of death register and patient register – quality and missing cases (in Swedish)</article-title>.<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.socialstyrelsen.se/register/dodsorsaksregistret/bortfallochkvalitet">http://www.socialstyrelsen.se/register/dodsorsaksregistret/bortfallochkvalitet</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.socialstyrelsen.se/register/dodsorsaksregistret/historik">http://www.socialstyrelsen.se/register/dodsorsaksregistret/historik</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.socialstyrelsen.se/register/halsodataregister/patientregistret/bortfallochkvalitet">http://www.socialstyrelsen.se/register/halsodataregister/patientregistret/bortfallochkvalitet</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 18 May 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1403494812449078">
<label>[16]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alfredsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hammar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kahan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spetz</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ysberg</surname><given-names>AS.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Attack rate, mortality and case fatality for acute myocardial infarction in Sweden during 1987-95. Results from the national AMI register in Sweden</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source> <year>2000</year>;<volume>248</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1403494812449078">
<label>[17]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goraya</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kottke</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weston</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>VL.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Coronary heart disease death and sudden cardiac death: a 20-year population-based study</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <year>2003</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>763</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1403494812449078">
<label>[18]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldberger</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hohnloser</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kadish</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lauer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>American Heart Association/American College of Cardiology Foundation/Heart Rhythm Society Scientific Statement on Noninvasive Risk Stratification Techniques for Identifying Patients at Risk for Sudden Cardiac Death. A scientific statement from the American Heart Association Council on Clinical Cardiology Committee on Electrocardiography and Arrhythmias and Council on Epidemiology and Prevention</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source> <year>2008</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1179</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1403494812449078">
<label>[19]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yusuf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hawken</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ounpuu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dans</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Avezum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lanas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of potentially modifiable risk factors associated with myocardial infarction in 52 countries (the INTERHEART study): case-control study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2004</year>;<volume>364</volume>(<issue>9438</issue>):<fpage>937</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1403494812449078">
<label>[20]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Björck</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosengren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lappas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Capewell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Modelling the decreasing coronary heart disease mortality in Sweden between 1986 and 2002</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1046</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1403494812449078">
<label>[21]</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosvall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grahn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Modén</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Merlo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Health Situation i Skåne (in Swedish)</article-title>. [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Hälsoförhållanden i Skåne. Folkhälsoenkät Skåne 2008</trans-title>]. <comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.skane.se/upload/Webbplatser/folkhalsa/102923_fh-08_INL.pdf">http://www.skane.se/upload/Webbplatser/folkhalsa/102923_fh-08_INL.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 18 May 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1403494812449078">
<label>[22]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Movahed</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramaraj</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hashemzadeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jamal</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rate of acute ST-elevation myocardial infarction in the United States from 1988 to 2004 (from the Nationwide Inpatient Sample)</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source> <year>2009</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1403494812449078">
<label>[23]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kannel</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>D’Agostino</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Sudden coronary death in women</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source> <year>1998</year>;<volume>136</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1403494812449078">
<label>[24]</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>National Board of Health and Welfare</collab>. <article-title>National Health Report 2009 (in Swedish)</article-title>. [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Folkhälsorapport 2009</trans-title>]. <source>Stockholm</source>, <publisher-loc>Sweden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NBHW</publisher-name>;<year>2009</year>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.socialstyrelsen.se/Lists/Artikelkatalog/Attachments/8495/2009-126-71_200912671.pdf">http://www.socialstyrelsen.se/Lists/Artikelkatalog/Attachments/8495/2009-126-71_200912671.pdf</ext-link></comment>. [ISBN <isbn>978-91-978065-8-9</isbn>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1403494812449078">
<label>[25]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosvall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gerward</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Engstrom</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hedblad</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Income and short-term case fatality after myocardial infarction in the whole middle-aged population of Malmo, Sweden</article-title>. <source>Eur J Public Health</source> <year>2008</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>533</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1403494812449078">
<label>[26]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kimble</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alberts</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alonzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dracup</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reducing delay in seeking treatment by patients with acute coronary syndrome and stroke: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association Council on cardiovascular nursing and stroke council</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1403494812449078">
<label>[27]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gerward</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tyden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Engstrom</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hedblad</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Marital status and occupation in relation to short-term case fatality after a first coronary event – a population based cohort</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source> <year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1403494812449078">
<label>[28]</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Board of Health and Welfare</collab>, <comment>Center of Epidemiology</comment>, <article-title>Värdering av diagnoskvaliteten för akut hjärtinfarkt i patientregistret 1987 and 1995</article-title> [<trans-title xml:lang="en">The validity of the diagnosis of acute myocardial infarction in the patient registry 1987 and 1995</trans-title>]. <source>Stockholm</source>, <publisher-loc>Sweden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NBHW</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1403494812449078">
<label>[29]</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goraya</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Belau</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weston</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kottke</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>VL.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Validation of death certificate diagnosis of out-of-hospital coronary heart disease deaths in Olmsted County, Minnesota</article-title>. <source>Mayo Clinic Proceedings</source> <year>2000</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>681</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>