<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CPJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcpj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Pediatr (Phila)</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical Pediatrics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0009-9228</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-2707</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0009922812436550</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0009922812436550</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Compliance on the American Board of Pediatrics Certifying Examination and the Importance of Location and Size on Pass Rates</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Falcone</surname><given-names>John L.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, MS</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812436550">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0009922812436550">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0009922812436550"><label>1</label>University of Pittsburgh Medical Center, Pittsburgh, PA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0009922812436550"><label>2</label>Children’s Hospital of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0009922812436550">John L. Falcone, University of Pittsburgh Medical Center, Presbyterian University Hospital, F-675, 200 Lothrop Street, Pittsburgh, PA 15213, USA Email: <email>falconej@upmc.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>51</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>483</fpage>
<lpage>489</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><italic>Objective</italic>. To describe residency program compliance to a 60% pass rate and 80% eligibility standard outlined by the Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education (ACGME) on the American Board of Pediatrics Certifying Examination. The hypothesis is that larger programs will have higher pass rates. <italic>Methods</italic>. Pediatric residency programs were retrospectively evaluated from 2008 to 2010 regarding the ACGME standards. Simple linear regression was performed to see if program pass rates were dependent on program size. <italic>Results</italic>. A total of 162/163 (83.4%) programs had first-time examinee pass rates of 60%. A total of 179/193 (92.7%) programs satisfied the 80% eligibility standard. The Northeast performed lower than Midwest, Southern, and Western states (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). The West performed higher than the Northeast, Midwest, and Southern states (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Simple linear regression showed that performance depends on program size (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). <italic>Conclusions</italic>. A majority of programs satisfy the minimum ACGME standards. Program performance is associated with program size and location. These findings may alter application patterns to pediatric residency programs.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Certification</kwd>
<kwd>educational measurement</kwd>
<kwd>geographic factors</kwd>
<kwd>pediatrics</kwd>
<kwd>specialty boards</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0009922812436550" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Physicians can become board-certified general pediatricians by passing the American Board of Pediatrics (ABP) General Pediatrics Certifying Examination. The ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination is a multiple choice computer-based examination lasting approximately 9 hours.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922812436550">1</xref></sup> It is an expectation of the Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education (ACGME) that residency training programs achieve a minimum 5-year-program first-time examinee pass rate of 60% on the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination. It is also an expectation of the ACGME that 80% of residents completing the program take the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0009922812436550">2</xref></sup> The ABP publishes the performance of every residency program in the United States and Puerto Rico on its website.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0009922812436550">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>For individual examinees, there is a definite correlation between performance on a board examination and performance on the in-training examination in pediatrics and internal medicine.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0009922812436550">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0009922812436550">5</xref></sup> Additionally, performance on the United States Medical Licensing Examination Step 1 is directly associated with higher pass rates on the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0009922812436550">6</xref></sup> As a corollary, self-directed learning in the form of participation in an electronic board review program is positively correlated with board certification in pediatrics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0009922812436550">7</xref></sup> It has also been shown that conference attendance and self-directed reading of electronic content had statistically and educationally significant independent associations with knowledge acquisition in medicine.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0009922812436550">8</xref></sup> These findings suggest that there are individual predictors of performance and educational content and that curricula offered by programs also affect performance.</p>
<p>However, at the residency training program level, there is a relative paucity of predictors of board examination success. For the American Board of Internal Medicine (ABIM) Certifying Examination, there is a positive correlation between how many residents per program take the ABIM Certifying Examination and the composite examination scores (Pearson correlation coefficient = 0.24). The number of teaching beds per resident is inversely related to ABIM Certifying Examination performance. Furthermore, program characteristics have an impact on the cognitive skills of residents over and above what would be predicted by test scores at the end of medical school. Programs with better examination performance tend to provide residents an extensive, well-supervised educational experience.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0009922812436550">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>The aims of this study are twofold. The first aim is to evaluate the pediatric residency training programs in the United States and Puerto Rico with regards to the ACGME standard of a 60% pass rate on the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination and the ACGME 80% eligibility standard. The second aim of this study is to determine if the demographic characteristics of residency program location and size have an impact regarding outcomes on the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination. The hypothesis is that larger residency programs will have more resources leading to robust educational programs and curricula, subsequently leading to higher pass rates on the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0009922812436550" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>In this retrospective cohort study from 2008 to 2010, the publicly available electronic data set for residency program performance on the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination was obtained from the ABP Web site for training programs in the United States and Puerto Rico.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0009922812436550">3</xref></sup> Permission to cite and use this published electronic data for research purposes was confirmed by a personal communication with a psychometrician for the ABP.</p>
<p>Programs were included if at least 1 resident had attempted to take the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination from 2008 to 2010. The program-specific first-time examinee pass rates for the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination were extrapolated from the data set. The number of residents eligible to take the examination and the number of residents that took the examination were also obtained. Independent double data entry was performed to ensure the accuracy of the extrapolated entries.</p>
<p>A scatter plot showing residency program percentage of pass rates and percentage of eligible first-time examinees was performed to visualize program performance based on the ACGME minimum requirements. To show regional differences in examination performance, pediatric residency programs were grouped together by state, and statewide pass rates were determined and mapped. Pass rates were also determined for the 4 regions of the United States as recognized by the United States Census Bureau: Northeast, Midwest, South, and West.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0009922812436550">10</xref></sup> Differences in first-time examinees that passed and failed the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination were determined using χ<sup>2</sup> tests.</p>
<p>To show if pediatric residency program pass rates were dependent on residency size, simple linear regression was performed using the 3-year program pass rate on the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination as the dependent variable and the number of eligible residents from 2008 to 2010 as an indicator of residency size. A Pearson correlation coefficient was found between these continuous variables. Statistics were performed using Stata 11.1 statistical software (StataCorp, College Station, TX), using an α = .05.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0009922812436550" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Of the 194 pediatric residency programs in the United States and Puerto Rico, 193 (99.5%) programs satisfied the inclusion criteria of the study. One (0.5%) program did not have any examinees take the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination from 2008 to 2010. The overall first-time examinee pass rate on the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination was 79.3% (6311/8341). The median residency program pass rate was 77% (interquartile range [IQR] = 65% to 88%). The median number of first-time examinees per residency program was 37 (IQR = 24 to 58). The overall percentage of eligible first-time examinees that attempted the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination was 93.0% (8341/8969). The median percentage of eligible residents per program that took the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination was 94% (IQR = 89% to 97%). The median number of eligible first-time examinees per residency program was 39 (IQR = 28 to 62).</p>
<p>A scatter plot of the percentage of pass rates and percentage of eligible examinees that took the ABP Certifying Examination from 2008 to 2010 for 193 residency programs is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0009922812436550">Figure 1</xref>. There were 162/193 (83.4%) of pediatric residency programs that had a first-time examinee pass rate ≥60%. There were 31/193 (16.6%) of pediatric residency programs that were “at risk” for failing to meet the minimum 60% first-time examinee pass rate as outlined by the ACGME. There were 179/193 (92.7%) of pediatric residency programs that had at least 80% of eligible examinees take the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination from 2008 to 2010. There were 14/193 (7.3%) of pediatric residency programs that were “at risk” for failing to meet the minimum 80% eligibility criteria outlined by the ACGME. There were 157/193 (81.3%) pediatric residency programs that met both ACGME standards. There were 27/193 (14.0%) pediatric residency programs that are “at risk” for failing to meet 1 of the 2 ACGME standards. There were 9/193 (4.7%) of pediatric residency programs that are “at risk” for failing to meet both ACGME standards.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0009922812436550" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Scatter plot showing compliance of 193 pediatric residency programs in the United States and Puerto Rico with the ACGME standards of a 60% program pass rate and with 80% of eligible residents taking the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination</p>
<p>Abbreviations: ABP, American Board of Pediatrics; ACGME, Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812436550-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The statewide and regional pass rates on the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0009922812436550">Table 1</xref>. The median number of residents per state or region was 111 (IQR = 55 to 203). The median pass rate per state or region was 81.9% (IQR = 76.2% to 85.9%). Three of the highest 7 performing states were in New England (Vermont, Maine, Rhode Island) with a combined pass rate of 88.4% (84/95). Four of the lowest 10 performing states were in the South (Florida, Mississippi, Louisiana, Georgia), with a combined pass rate of 73.4% (438/597). A χ<sup>2</sup> test showed that the New England state cluster performed higher than the Southern state cluster (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). A coded map of the Continental United States showing statewide differences in performance is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0009922812436550">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0009922812436550" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Passing Percentage for First-Time Examinees on the American Board of Pediatrics General Pediatric Certifying Examination in the United States and Puerto Rico From 2008 to 2010</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0009922812436550" xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812436550-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">State or Region</th>
<th align="center">Total Residents</th>
<th align="center">Passing Residents</th>
<th align="center">Passing Percentage</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Oregon</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>100.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Colorado</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>97.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Delaware</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>91.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Vermont</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>88.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Alabama</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>79</td>
<td>87.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Maine</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>88.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>North Carolina</td>
<td>223</td>
<td>197</td>
<td>88.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rhode Island</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>88.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>South Carolina</td>
<td>106</td>
<td>93</td>
<td>87.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Utah</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>88.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>California</td>
<td>802</td>
<td>694</td>
<td>86.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Massachusetts</td>
<td>281</td>
<td>241</td>
<td>85.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Missouri</td>
<td>206</td>
<td>177</td>
<td>85.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indiana</td>
<td>118</td>
<td>99</td>
<td>83.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ohio</td>
<td>478</td>
<td>403</td>
<td>84.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Washington</td>
<td>102</td>
<td>86</td>
<td>84.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Washington DC</td>
<td>150</td>
<td>126</td>
<td>84.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Arkansas</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>82.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kentucky</td>
<td>103</td>
<td>86</td>
<td>83.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Minnesota</td>
<td>120</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>83.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New Hampshire</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>83.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pennsylvania</td>
<td>411</td>
<td>341</td>
<td>83.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Illinois</td>
<td>450</td>
<td>370</td>
<td>82.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tennessee</td>
<td>168</td>
<td>137</td>
<td>81.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Connecticut</td>
<td>119</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>79.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Texas</td>
<td>549</td>
<td>438</td>
<td>79.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>193</td>
<td>154</td>
<td>79.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Maryland</td>
<td>146</td>
<td>116</td>
<td>79.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nebraska</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>79.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New Mexico</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>78.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Oklahoma</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>78.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wisconsin</td>
<td>119</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>79.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Iowa</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>77.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Michigan</td>
<td>311</td>
<td>241</td>
<td>77.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Arizona</td>
<td>140</td>
<td>106</td>
<td>75.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Florida</td>
<td>314</td>
<td>238</td>
<td>75.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mississippi</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>75.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hawaii</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>74.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Louisiana</td>
<td>116</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>71.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New York</td>
<td>1252</td>
<td>868</td>
<td>69.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Georgia</td>
<td>130</td>
<td>89</td>
<td>68.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>West Virginia</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>66.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kansas</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>61.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nevada</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>58.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New Jersey</td>
<td>252</td>
<td>148</td>
<td>58.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Puerto Rico</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>54.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Overall</td>
<td>8341</td>
<td>6611</td>
<td>79.3</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig2-0009922812436550" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>First-time examinee pass rates on the American Board of Pediatrics General Pediatrics Certifying Examination from 2008 to 2010 for the Continental United States</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812436550-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>First-time examinee performance according to the US Census Bureau Regions is given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0009922812436550">Table 2</xref>. Chi-square tests showed that the Northeast performed lower than each of the other 3 United States Census Bureau Regions (all <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). There were no differences in performance between states in the Midwest and the South (p = 0.20). The states in the West performed higher than each of the other 3 United States Census Bureau Regions (all <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0009922812436550" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>First-Time Examinee Performance on the American Board of Pediatrics General Pediatrics Certifying Examination from 2008 to 2010 for the Four United States Census Bureau Regions</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0009922812436550" xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812436550-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Region</th>
<th align="center">Passing Examinees</th>
<th align="center">Failing Examinees</th>
<th align="center">Total Examinees</th>
<th align="center">Pass Rate (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Northeast</td>
<td>1792</td>
<td>636</td>
<td>2428</td>
<td>73.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Midwest</td>
<td>1581</td>
<td>353</td>
<td>1934</td>
<td>81.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>South</td>
<td>2069</td>
<td>510</td>
<td>2579</td>
<td>80.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>West</td>
<td>1136</td>
<td>203</td>
<td>1339</td>
<td>84.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>6578</td>
<td>1702</td>
<td>8280</td>
<td>79.4</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The simple linear regression analysis using the number of eligible residents from 2008 to 2010 per program as a predictor of ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination pass rate from 2008 to 2010 is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0009922812436550">Figure 3</xref>. The Pearson correlation coefficient between these 2 variables was 0.43. The slope of the best-fit line was 0.28 (95% confidence interval = 0.19-0.36). The slope of the best-fit line was greater than 0 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001).</p>
<fig id="fig3-0009922812436550" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Simple linear regression showing a dependence of ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination pass rates on residency program size from 2008 to 2010 for 193 residency programs in the United States and Puerto Rico</p>
<p>Abbreviations: ABP, American Board of Pediatrics; ACGME, Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812436550-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0009922812436550" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In the analyses, residency programs demonstrate a high adherence to the ACGME minimum standards. In the United States and Puerto Rico, 83.4% of pediatric residency programs maintain a first-time examinee pass rate on the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination of at least 60% over the study period. In parallel, 92.7% of residency programs have at least 80% of eligible residents take the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination. Overall, 81.3% of pediatric residency programs meet both ACGME standards. This high apparent compliance of residency program compliance is important to recognize, and this is the first known article to describe the current state of performance for pediatric residency training programs in the United States and Puerto Rico. Conversely, a minority of programs (18.7%) are “at risk” for possible failure to meet one or both of the ACGME minimum standards. However, this analysis spans a 3-year time frame whereas the ACGME minimum standards are over a 5-year time frame. So, some of the “at risk” programs may be able to improve performance and change their compliance status. On a similar note, some programs that are in current compliance could possibly fall below these standards with poorer performance and eligibility compliance. It is important to know which programs are on the border of these important educational benchmarks.</p>
<p>It is also evident that there are differences in statewide and regional performance. This is the first known study in pediatrics looking at written board examination performance in this manner. There is evidence that a New England state cluster performs much higher than a Southern state cluster. But, pass rates on the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination are significantly lower overall in the Northeast compared with the Midwest, South, and West. The lower performance in the Northeast is likely dependent most on New York State, as this is the state with the highest number of first-time examinees from 2008 to 2010. This heavily populated state weighs down the overall Northeast performance, making it interesting that the New England state cluster has some of the higher performing states amid the lowest performing United States Census Bureau Regions.</p>
<p>Moreover, it is clear that larger pediatric residency programs outperform smaller programs on the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination. This is consistent with our hypothesis. Although there is a moderately positive Pearson correlation coefficient, the best-fit line has a slope greater than 0. This finding is consistent with the weakly positive correlation of 0.24 between the number of residents taking the ABIM Certifying Examination per residency program and the ABIM Certifying Examination composite score in 1978.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0009922812436550">9</xref></sup> The correlation coefficient is higher in this study, implying an even more linear association in the independent and dependent variables.</p>
<p>There are important implications to these demographic findings. Pediatric residency program applicants may be more inclined to apply to larger residency programs, or apply in states with a recent history of higher examination performance. These results have the potential to change national application patterns from the resident applicant standpoint.</p>
<p>However, it is ultimately unclear why there are significant differences in state and regional performance. Even within states, individual program performance and eligible resident percentages vary a great deal. It is also unclear why there is such variability in individual residency performance. Residency program performance is extremely complex, and depends on multiple factors, such as resident selection, curriculum structure, faculty recruitment, incentives, and other variables that simply cannot be evaluated in this study. Another weakness to this study is that its retrospective nature makes it impossible to establish cause and effect. There are clear associations demonstrated in this data set, but causation cannot be established. There are likely confounding variables that are associated with program size that account for these differences in educational outcomes. Additionally, evaluating program pass rates does not evaluate any clinical skills or patient-based outcomes. Further study into the nature of some of these institution-specific educational parameters is needed.</p>
<p>There are numerous strengths to this study. First, the population of first-time examinees over 3 years in the United States and Puerto Rico is evaluated, as opposed to a local or regional sample of examinees. The 3-year evaluation gives longitudinal validity to the study as opposed to performance during a single year. Because the data are published electronically, this study could easily be repeated. This is the first known study to evaluate the current state of pediatric residency training program performance, to show which programs are “at risk” of not meeting ACGME standards, to show statewide and regional differences in performance, and the dependence of pass rate on program size. The findings in this study can potentially alter application behaviors.</p>
<p>Overall, this study shows that a majority of pediatric residency programs satisfy the minimum ACGME standards regarding performance on the ABP General Pediatrics Certifying Examination. Also, there are some demographic patterns that demonstrate that residency program performance is associated with program location and program size. These findings may alter application patterns for pediatric residency programs.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0009922812436550">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>American Board of Pediatrics</collab>. <article-title>Exam day: what to expect</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.abp.org/ABPWebStatic/?anticache=0.925842756723639#murl%3D%2FABPWebStatic%2Ftakeexamgp.html%26surl%3D%2Fabpwebsite%2Fprometric%2Fwhattoexpect.htm">https://www.abp.org/ABPWebStatic/?anticache=0.925842756723639#murl%3D%2FABPWebStatic%2Ftakeexamgp.html%26surl%3D%2Fabpwebsite%2Fprometric%2Fwhattoexpect.htm</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed November 11, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0009922812436550">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education</collab>. <article-title>Specialty-specific references for dios: board certification requirements and pass rate information</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.acgme.org/acWebsite/irc/DIO_Board_Pass_Rate.pdf">http://www.acgme.org/acWebsite/irc/DIO_Board_Pass_Rate.pdf</ext-link>. Published June 2011</comment>. <access-date>Accessed November 11, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0009922812436550">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>American Board of Pediatrics</collab>. <article-title>Pediatric training program pass rates</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.abp.org/ABPWebStatic/?anticache=0.5994684103279906#murl%3D%2FABPWebStatic%2Fbecomecerttrain.html%26surl%3D%2Fabpwebsite%2Fbecomecert%2Ftrainingprograms%2Faboutgeneralpediatrics%2Fpassrateschart.htm">https://www.abp.org/ABPWebStatic/?anticache=0.5994684103279906#murl%3D%2FABPWebStatic%2Fbecomecerttrain.html%26surl%3D%2Fabpwebsite%2Fbecomecert%2Ftrainingprograms%2Faboutgeneralpediatrics%2Fpassrateschart.htm</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed November 11, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0009922812436550">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Althouse</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGuinness</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The in-training examination: an analysis of its predictive value on performance on the general pediatrics certification examination</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>425</fpage>-<lpage>428</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0009922812436550">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rollins</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martindale</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edmond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manser</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scheld</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Predicting pass rates on the American Board of Internal Medicine certifying examination</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>414</fpage>-<lpage>416</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0009922812436550">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCaskill</surname><given-names>QE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barata</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wludyka</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zenni</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>USMLE step 1 scores as a significant predictor of future board passage in pediatrics</article-title>. <source>Ambul Pediatr</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>192</fpage>-<lpage>195</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0009922812436550">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Langenau</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fogel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Correlation between an email based board review program and American Board of Pediatrics General Pediatrics Certifying Examination scores</article-title>. <source>Med Educ Online</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0009922812436550">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zeger</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kolars</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Factors associated with medical knowledge acquisition during internal medicine residency</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>962</fpage>-<lpage>968</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0009922812436550">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Norcini</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grosso</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The relationship between features of residency training and ABIM certifying examination performance</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>330</fpage>-<lpage>336</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0009922812436550">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>US Census Bureau</collab>. <article-title>Census regions and divisions of the United States. Geography Division</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.census.gov/geo/www/us_regdiv.pdf">http://www.census.gov/geo/www/us_regdiv.pdf</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed November 11, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>