<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GMT</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spgmt</journal-id>
<journal-title>General Music Today</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1048-3713</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1931-3756</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1048371313476296</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1048371313476296</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Resources, Reviews, and Research</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Quite a Lot on Some Problems With—and Just a Little on the Hopes for—Secondary General Music With Regards to Culturally Responsive and Respectful Music Education</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Thibeault</surname><given-names>Matthew D.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1048371313476296">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1048371313476296"><label>1</label>University of Illinois, Urbana, IL, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1048371313476296">Matthew Thibeault, University of Illinois, 1114 West Nevada Street, Urbana, IL 61801, USA. Email: <email>mdthib@illinois.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>26</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>35</fpage>
<lpage>38</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 National Association for Music Education</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">MENC: The National Association for Music Education</copyright-holder>
</permissions></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This issue’s theme is culturally responsive and respectful teaching. To be honest, this too often has been the opposite of what one found in secondary general music classes.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1048371313476296">1</xref></sup> Many of these classes hold a deservedly poor reputation in fiction, on the political trail, and perhaps even within our personal memories.</p>
<p>This column “comes clean” about secondary general music, admitting some common wrongs, looking briefly into some reasons for the current state of affairs, and finally moving onto a redefinition of secondary general—a redefinition that perhaps may be the best hope for responsive and respectful music education.</p>
<sec id="section1-1048371313476296">
<title>Coming Clean: Some Wrongs of Secondary General Music</title>
<p>Examples of secondary general music education that lack cultural responsiveness and respect are not hard to find. In the novel <italic>The Good Times Are Killing Me</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1048371313476296">Barry, 2002</xref>), Edna Arkins—protagonist and music lover—describes her view as a student in a secondary general music appreciation class:
<disp-quote>
<p>Well one thing that they never tell you in the grade school is to enjoy singing while you can because eventually you are going to be divided up by who can sing and who can’t sing, and the people who can sing will go to Choir, and the ones who can’t sing, won’t sing, and may never sing again, and go to the class called “Music Appreciation” where a teacher will give you a piece of cardboard printed with the life-size keys of a piano and then teach you how to play “Go Tell Aunt Rhody” on it to a record. (p. 83)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>It is hard to imagine a student enjoying a class where all are stigmatized as unable to sing, and it is impossible enjoy a cardboard keyboard under any circumstances.</p>
<p>While on the campaign trail in 2008, Barack Obama went off-script during a speech about the importance of the arts to make a brief aside about his experiences in the music classroom:
<disp-quote>
<p>I mean, you always had an art teacher, and a music teacher. You could be in the poorest school district in the world. Now, I’m not saying music was always exciting . . . Right? I mean, sometimes, you know, the teacher would be making you sing songs that, from like, the old show tunes, you know? I had one music teacher who made me, [sings] “Oklahoma where the . . .” And I was more into Stevie Wonder, so . . . (Barack Obama in Wallingford, Pennsylvania, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1048371313476296">2008</xref>)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Obama’s description is similar to my own experiences in middle school general music during the 1980s, where my strongest memories are of watching film strips about the history of music and singing a few completely unmemorable songs. The specifics might have been different, but like Obama, my middle school music class was not always—in fact, hardly ever—exciting.</p>
<p>Part of the problem with these classes is definitional, a problem inherent in the very phrase <italic>general music</italic>. The online Oxford Dictionary (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://english.oxforddictionaries.com">http://english.oxforddictionaries.com</ext-link>) defines <italic>general</italic> first as “affecting or concerning all or most people or things; widespread.” Things that are general are also defined as “not specialized or limited in range of subject, application, activity, etc.” Those of us in general music seem condemned, by definition, to live fluid lives as teachers, adrift on vast oceans of musical culture through eons of musical history. We seem to be <italic>required</italic> to avoid specialization—with the pleasures of dry land and clear boundaries left for band, orchestra, and choir—while we <italic>generalists</italic> float on by.</p>
<p>Perhaps the only solace for elementary general music educators is this: At least they do not teach <italic>secondary</italic> general music. My dictionary’s first definition of secondary is, “coming after, less important than, or resulting from someone or something else that is primary.” This certainly describes the place of secondary general music in the music education curricula of most colleges, including my own. Elementary general students complete 18 to 20 credit hours of coursework in general music at the University of Illinois, but of the 22 course hours instrumental music education students take (conducting classes, secondary instruments, and instrumental methods courses), only 2 of those 22 credits are in general music.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1048371313476296">2</xref></sup> Instrumental string students have no general music requirement, but, rather, they complete a course on teaching strings in group settings. <italic>Secondary</italic> is a generous term for the value and importance placed on these general music courses at my institution.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1048371313476296">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>Given the problems that define secondary general music, it is difficult to see how these courses can ever be substantial. It is a challenge to rally around the amorphous blob that is secondary general music, particularly when virtually no professional preparation exists in a college degree. It remains easy to see how secondary general can seem an afterthought, a way to fill in the schedule of a music teacher whose specialties lie elsewhere.</p>
<p>The challenges associated with secondary general music have been acknowledged for nearly 50 years. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1048371313476296">Bennett Reimer (1965)</xref>, writing in favor of a new approach to secondary general music, found,
<disp-quote>
<p>Instead there is an almost universal clinging to the concept of junior high school music as a continuation of elementary music . . . The problem, then, is to rethink and redefine the nature of the experiences with music offered to junior and senior high school students who are not and most likely will not be performers or composers, but who should be intelligent consumers of the art of music. The general music class is the logical—indeed the only—place where preparation of this nature can be given to all secondary school students. (pp. 13-14)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1048371313476296">
<title>Moving Forward: Redefining Secondary General Music</title>
<p>Forty-eight years after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1048371313476296">Reimer’s (1965)</xref> call, we still need to redefine secondary general music in terms of positive possibilities and interesting opportunities. Fortunately, the lack of compelling traditions allows us to move quickly in new directions. The very openness that surrounds secondary general music affords the possibility to quickly adjust offerings and take advantage of interesting cultural opportunities. In other words, secondary general music <italic>can</italic> be culturally responsive and respectful. To assert the claim more boldly, secondary general music is uniquely positioned to be exceptionally responsive and respectful of our students’ musical cultures, cultures that can be fickle, saturated with media and new technologies, and distant from the culture of large ensembles. But on what grounds can we forge a consensus for moving ahead and creating a vibrant secondary general music classroom that is both culturally responsive and respectful?</p>
<p>Thankfully, a host of new resources point the way forward for secondary general music, with NAfME active on a number of fronts. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1048371313476296">Ann Clements (2010)</xref> edited an invaluable collection of case studies depicting alternative approaches to music education, responding to and respecting many diverse aspects of today’s musical cultures. Some of these are designed to fit into band, orchestra, and choir, but many easily find a home in flexible, secondary general music offerings. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1048371313476296">Lucy Green’s (2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1048371313476296">2008</xref>) work, highly responsive to student musical cultures through informal pedagogy, is well established in the literature but still adapting to classrooms in the United States.</p>
<p>Scott Shuler, immediate Past President of NAfME, has called repeatedly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1048371313476296">Shuler, 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1048371313476296">2011b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1048371313476296">2012</xref>) for courses that reach a broader swath of students, and suggests, “The music curriculum design answer is clear: in addition to high-quality ensemble classes, music programs must offer alternatives that attract and engage other students” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1048371313476296">2011a</xref>, p. 9). In pursuit of these goals, Shuler created new NAfME “Councils for Composition, Guitar, and IN-ovations, the last being our ‘greenhouse’ for testing and promoting innovative alternative courses” (p. 12).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1048371313476296">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>Some emerging resources are specifically and entirely devoted to secondary general music. A recent edited volume (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1048371313476296">Burton, 2012</xref>) devoted to general music in middle school serves as a wonderful resource for those looking for interesting ideas and innovative practices. The chapters, contributed by many luminaries in our field, address areas as diverse as learners with special needs, middle school keyboard and guitar classes, interdisciplinary work, and approaches to working with and through technology. The authors provide clear examples and suggestions while connecting with theoretical concepts.</p>
<p>New ideas for secondary general music abound in these resources and, of course, in the pages of <italic>General Music Today</italic>. To pursue these ideas and meet the challenges, we need to support the development of confident, competent teachers for whom general music is not often why they pursued certification. Even then, we should be on guard against superficial treatments. Responding to President <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1048371313476296">Shuler’s (2011b)</xref> “Five Guiding Principles” article, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1048371313476296">Reimer (2011)</xref> warns about offering the kinds of electives that attract students outside of ensembles without adequate sequential and rigorous preparation:
<disp-quote>
<p>But we must recognize that each specialized area of study in music is as complex and demanding as being a successful band, chorus, or orchestra director. I doubt that any music educator would claim that “some exploring via workshops, summer institutes, or courses,” as Shuler recommends, would a well-prepared ensemble director make. (p. 28)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Perhaps ironically, the very problems of secondary general music position the class to be a leader in the field. Compelling courses that reach nonensemble students stand to increase participation and the profile of music in secondary schools during this critical time. We need more teachers for whom secondary general music is a primary consideration, and more support from universities, as well as through professional development options and publications. But for those young musicians preparing to teach music, there may be no area with more flexibility, more agility, and more openness for new ideas as in the secondary general music arena. May we all work together to redefine secondary general music to be just that kind of responsive and respectful classroom that all students can love.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<label>Author’s Note</label>
<p>The title of this article, along with the generally casual tone of this article (and the endnotes, also), is a humble attempt to write in the style of David Foster Wallace. Wallace, despite his death, continues to inspire me, and I think about him nearly every day on my way to work as I bicycle past the street where he grew up in Urbana, Illinois. It was hard to resist using his favored abbreviation of “with regards to” (w/r/t), and his fans, self-described “howling fantods,” should be aware it was present in an early draft of this column.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1048371313476296">
<label>1.</label>
<p>I write <italic>classes</italic> instead of <italic>classrooms</italic> deliberately, as I rarely if ever have seen a secondary general music class take place anywhere other than a room with another purpose (choir room, band room, etc.), just another dimension of the “secondary” nature of general music after elementary school.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1048371313476296">
<label>2.</label>
<p>This isn’t to deny that perhaps aspects and issues pertaining to general music don’t permeate the borders of classes, or that future curricular revisions might redress this wrong, but I continually encounter our graduates who routinely gripe that the program fails to prepare them for the inevitable assignment of teaching secondary general music. The curricular requirements I write about were retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://provost.illinois.edu/ProgramsOfStudy/2012/fall/programs/undergrad/faa/music_ed.html">http://provost.illinois.edu/ProgramsOfStudy/2012/fall/programs/undergrad/faa/music_ed.html</ext-link></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1048371313476296">
<label>3.</label>
<p>It is also worth noting that the Wild West nature of secondary general music seems to extend to those who teach these courses with regards to qualifications. It is unimaginable that we would allow someone to teach a course in instrumental methods whose background was not thorough, but what can we even claim would constitute a thorough background in secondary general music? I enjoy serving as the columnist for “Secondary Scene” but happily admit that my background teaching general music is primarily at the elementary level. With secondary work limited to some summer camps and 2 years’ adjunct teaching a general music class at the San Francisco School of the Arts, I freely admit that I may be the least qualified columnist in our profession.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1048371313476296">
<label>4.</label>
<p>These NAfME Councils, and others, can best be explored through the NAfME website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://musiced.nafme.org/about/societies-and-councils/">https://musiced.nafme.org/about/societies-and-councils/</ext-link>). In many instances, there are many opportunities for further contributions from members with passion and projects to share.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author Biography</title>
<p><bold>Matthew D. Thibeault</bold> is assistant professor at the University of Illinois, where he teaches courses in general music, music education technology, and research methods. He was the 2013 recipient of the Outstanding Emerging Researcher Award issued by the Center for Music Education Research at the University of South Florida. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.matthewthibeault.com">www.matthewthibeault.com</ext-link></p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1048371313476296">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>The good times are killing me</source>. <publisher-loc>Seattle, WA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sasquatch Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1048371313476296">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Barackobamadotcom</collab> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Barack Obama in Wallingford, PA [Video file]</article-title>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yN2Zy_68RcY">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yN2Zy_68RcY</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1048371313476296">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.). (<year>2012</year>). <source>Engaging musical practices: A sourcebook for middle school general music</source>. <publisher-loc>Lanham, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Association for Music Education/R&amp;L Education</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1048371313476296">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Alternative approaches in music education: Case studies from the field</source>. <publisher-loc>Lanham, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MENC/Rowman &amp; Littlefield Education</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1048371313476296">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>How popular musicians learn: A way ahead for music education</source>. <publisher-loc>Aldershot, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1048371313476296">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Music, informal learning and the school: A new classroom pedagogy</source>. <publisher-loc>Aldershot, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1048371313476296">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1965</year>). <article-title>A new curriculum for secondary general music</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of the Council for Research in Music Education</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/40375258</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1048371313476296">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Professional notes President Shuler’s guiding principles—Big steps in the right direction</article-title>. <source>Music Educators Journal</source>, <volume>97</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0027432111409855</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1048371313476296">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shuler</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011a</year>). <article-title>Music education for life: Building inclusive, effective twenty-first-century music programs</article-title>. <source>Music Educators Journal</source>, <volume>98</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0027432111418748</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1048371313476296">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shuler</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011b</year>). <article-title>Music education for life: Five guiding principles for music education</article-title>. <source>Music Educators Journal</source>, <volume>97</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0027432110395080</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1048371313476296">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shuler</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Music education for life: core music education: Students’ civil right</article-title>. <source>Music Educators Journal</source>, <volume>98</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0027432112446912</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>