<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="news">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">amjsports</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Sports Med</journal-id>
<journal-title>The American Journal of Sports Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0363-5465</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3365</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0363546511434705</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0363546511434705</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Society News and Announcements</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Society News and Announcements</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>232</fpage>
<lpage>234</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 American Orthopaedic Society for Sports Medicine</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Orthopaedic Society for Sports Medicine</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0363546511434705">
<title>Claim your CME Credits for the AOSSM 2012 Specialty Day and AOSSM/POSNA Joint Session</title>
<p>AOSSM staff will e-mail all AOSSM 2012 Specialty Day registrants the transcript/certificate information within a few weeks of the meeting, including the AOSSM/POSNA Joint Session. The AAOS kiosk will not have continuing education transcripts for registrants of AOSSM 2012 Specialty Day. If you need any additional information or assistance, please contact Pat Kovach at <email>pat@aossm.org</email>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0363546511434705">
<title>Join an AOSSM Committee</title>
<p>Are you looking for a great way to get involved with AOSSM? Volunteer for a committee. Check out the vacancies on the AOSSM Web site’s home page and submit your application by February 1, 2012, to Camille Petrick at <email>camille@aossm.org</email>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0363546511434705">
<title>Order a Personalized Version of <italic>In Motion</italic> for Your Waiting Room</title>
<p><italic>In Motion</italic> is now available to be personalized with your practice name and logo. For just $300, you will receive four personalized issues (Spring, Summer, Fall, Winter) and the high- and low-resolution PDFs to send to patients’ inboxes, put on your Web site, or print out and place in your waiting room. For more information contact Lisa Weisenberger, Director of Communications, at <email>lisa@aossm.org</email>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0363546511434705">
<title>New Opportunity to Participate in AOSSM Young Pitchers Studies</title>
<p>As you may be aware, AOSSM members are collaborating in a national multicenter project involving youth baseball pitchers between the ages of 9 and 18 years. Already, more than 800 young pitchers have been assessed, with a goal of enrolling 2000 subjects. The studies recently received approval through a private, central Institutional Review Board (Western IRB) that will provide IRB review for anyone who does not have their own review board. You can now rapidly join the group without administrative hassle. More information about the project is at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sportsmed.org/Youth-Baseball-Studies">www.sportsmed.org/Youth-Baseball-Studies</ext-link>. Please contact Director of Research, Bart Mann (<email>bart@aossm.org</email>) if you would like to get involved or if you have any questions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0363546511434705">
<title>New AOSSM/MTF Meniscal Allograft Transplantation Grant Available</title>
<p>The purpose of the new AOSSM/MTF Meniscal Allograft Transplantation grant is to foster research for clinically relevant biomechanical studies, basic science studies, and preclinical or clinical studies related to meniscal transplantation. A list of potential research priorities related to this field and identified by leaders in this field is listed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sportsmed.org/researchgrants">www.sportsmed.org/researchgrants</ext-link>. Proposed studies need to relate specifically to meniscal transplantation. Projects related solely to meniscus repair or preservation, meniscus regeneration, collagen implants, and other such topics will not be considered for this grant. Applications will be reviewed for the potential impact on the field of meniscal transplantation, but the quality of the study approach and the ability of the investigator(s) and site(s) to conduct and complete the proposed research within the time frame noted will be strictly assessed.</p>
<p>This grant is specifically designed to give a one-time grant of $300,000. Any investigative team pursuing this grant must include at least one member of AOSSM in good standing. No AOSSM board officer (president, vice president, treasurer, etc) may be a named investigator on the application.</p>
<p>Deadline for applications is April 1, 2012. For more information and to apply, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sportsmed.org/researchgrants">www.sportsmed.org/researchgrants</ext-link> or contact Bart Mann, Director of Research, at <email>bart@aossm.org</email>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0363546511434705">
<title>Innovative Outcomes Assessment Grant</title>
<p>AOSSM is pleased to announce a new grant sponsored by Smith &amp; Nephew to support development of innovative approaches to measuring the effects of surgical procedures in orthopaedic sports medicine. This $25,000 grant is meant to advance the evaluation of clinical outcomes related to surgery by encouraging development of novel approaches, techniques, and/or methodology that will facilitate and enhance clinical research. Examples might include new Web-based instruments to allow interinstitutional collaborative efforts, tools to quantify joint laxity, or innovative methods to measure the results of arthroscopic procedures about the hip. The intent of this award is to provide start-up funding for the development of tools and/or technology that can be leveraged and used for future, larger-scale clinical research studies.</p>
<p>Applications for this grant will be judged on 3 criteria:</p>
<list id="list1-0363546511434705" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Innovation</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Feasibility</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Clinical Significance</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The proposal should define the limitations with currently available assessments, clearly describe the proposed innovative approach, state how the new assessment will be tested, and discuss the clinical significance of this novel method to the field if successful. Because this grant is intended to foster new ideas and creativity, prior data related to the innovation are not required but can be presented to establish feasibility. Deadline for applications is April 17, 2012. The principal investigator or a co-investigator must be an AOSSM member in good standing.</p>
<p>To begin the application process, please review the guidelines specific to this grant and complete all information as described online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sportsmed.org/researchgrants">www.sportsmed.org/researchgrants</ext-link>. All information should be submitted in a single PDF document to Bart Mann, AOSSM Director of Research, at <email>bart@aossm.org</email>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0363546511434705">
<title>Current Concepts + CME = Optimal Care for Every Patient</title>
<p>Most practitioners are so deeply enmeshed in patient care that finding the time to keep up with the tidal wave of information about new theories and techniques is very difficult. Every busy practitioner knows those new theories and techniques are the pathways to providing optimal care to each patient. <italic>AJSM</italic> Current Concepts has a solution to this problem.</p>
<p>Current Concepts presents a different topic each month. These broad, systematic reviews of medical research are among the most widely read articles in <italic>AJSM</italic>. Studies on physician CME emphasize the relationship between review or overview articles and the likelihood of producing a commitment to change a physician’s practice routine. You can earn 1 <italic>AMA PRA Category 1 Credit</italic>™ each time you read a Current Concepts article and complete the quiz.</p>
<p>If you haven’t tried this CME activity, your <italic>AJSM</italic> subscription includes 2 complimentary journal CME opportunities. Check out the table of contents in this month’s issue of <italic>AJSM</italic> and look for the Current Concepts article. It takes just a few minutes to complete the online quiz and evaluation. Claim CME and stay current as you pursue the goal of providing optimal care to every patient with <italic>AJSM</italic> Current Concepts.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0363546511434705">
<title>Get Involved—Join the Stop Sports Injuries Campaign</title>
<p>You can easily get involved in the campaign by becoming an official supporter. Simply fill out the form online under the <italic>Join Our Team</italic> tab and submit your sporting organization, hospital/institution, or practice, bio and logo, to campaign director, Michael Konstant at <email>michael@stopsportsinjury.org</email>. We will then add your information to the site and you will have access to a specialized logo to place on your Web site and utilize in presentations, events, or other materials. Visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.STOPSportsInjuries.org">www.STOPSportsInjuries.org</ext-link> to download the agreement and get involved today!</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0363546511434705">
<title>Got News We Could Use? <italic>Sports Medicine Update</italic> Wants to Hear From You!</title>
<p>Have you received a prestigious award recently? A new academic appointment? Been named a team physician? AOSSM wants to hear from you! <italic>Sports Medicine Update</italic> welcomes all members’ news items. Please send information to Lisa Weisenberger, AOSSM Director of Communications, at <email>lisa@aossm.org</email>, fax to 847-292-4905, or contact the Society office at 847-292-4900. High-resolution (300 dpi) photos are always welcome.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0363546511434705">
<title>Upcoming Meetings</title>
<list id="list2-0363546511434705" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><bold>Specialty Day</bold></p>
<p>San Francisco, CA</p>
<p>February 11, 2012</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>AOSSM Annual Meeting 2012</bold></p>
<p>Baltimore, MD</p>
<p>July 12-15, 2012</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>AOSSM/AAOS Board Review Course for Subspecialty Certification in Orthopaedic Sports Medicine</bold></p>
<p>Chicago, IL</p>
<p>August 10-12, 2012</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Keep Your Edge: Hockey Sports Medicine in 2012</bold></p>
<p>Toronto, Canada</p>
<p>August 24-26, 2012</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0363546511434705">
<title>Upcoming Deadlines</title>
<list id="list3-0363546511434705" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><bold>Meniscal Allograft Transplantation Grant</bold></p>
<p>April 1, 2012</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Innovative Outcomes Assessment Grant</bold></p>
<p>April 17, 2012</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0363546511434705">
<title>Announcements</title>
<p>The 2nd INTERNATIONAL KNEE UPDATE will be held March 8 to 10, 2012, at the Morosani Hotel, Davos, Switzerland. For more information, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gelenkzentrum.com">www.gelenkzentrum.com</ext-link>. Online registration is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.intercongress.de">www.intercongress.de</ext-link>.</p>
<p>The INTERNATIONAL CONGRESS ON CARTILAGE REPAIR OF THE ANKLE will be held at Clontarf Castle, Dublin Ireland, March 9 to 10, 2012. The first day of the Congress will consist of lectures and discussion on specific topics within cartilage repair surgery of the ankle, as well as interesting and related topics from special guest speakers. These lectures will serve as the basis for discussion on the second day. The second day of the Congress will begin with a closed meeting of all faculty members to debate and discuss the controversies highlighted in the previous day. An open meeting with all participants will then follow with interesting case discussion and presentation of the current concepts and treatment guidelines. For registration and more information, visit the Web site at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esska-afas.org/dublin2012">www.esska-afas.org/dublin2012</ext-link>.</p>
<p>The XII INTERNATIONAL CONGRESS OF THE ARTHROSCOPY ASSOCIATION OF ARGENTINA (AAA) combined meeting with the Arthroscopy Association of North America (AANA) Argentina will be held April 18 to 21, 2012, at the Buenos Aires Hilton Hotel. For more information go to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.artroscopia.com.ar">www.artroscopia.com.ar</ext-link>.</p>
<p>The XXI INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON SPORTS REHABILITATION AND TRAUMATOLOGY, Football Medicine Strategies for Knee Injuries, will be held at Stamford Bridge Stadium, London, United Kingdom, on April 21 and 22, 2012. Injuries to the knee are among the most common sports-related injuries, with prevalence in football particularly high. These injuries can result in a prolonged absence from competition, in some cases ending careers. This illustrates the continuing need to develop successful football medicine strategies, shared for the benefit of all athletes. This conference has been designed based upon the common challenges presented to football players and their support teams. Management strategies will be defined for each stage of the injury continuum; from injury prevention to surgery and rehabilitation. Key components within the knee have been identified, and these will be explored by leading speakers within their areas of expertise. Updated information is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.isokinetic.com">www.isokinetic.com</ext-link> or by contacting François Westcombe at <email>f.westcombe@isokinetic.com</email> or Cristina Zanetti at <email>congressi@isokinetic.com</email>.</p>
<p>ICRS 2012 - 10th WORLD CONGRESS OF THE INTERNATIONAL CARTILAGE REPAIR SOCIETY will be held May 12 to 15, 2012, in Montreal, Canada. Visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cartilage.org">www.cartilage.org</ext-link> for full details.</p>
<p>The 27th Annual ADVANCES ON THE KNEE AND SHOULDER CONFERENCE will be held May 27 through 30, 2012, at the Westin Resort on Hilton Head Island, South Carolina. The conference is cosponsored by the University of Cincinnati’s Office of Continuing Medical Education and Cincinnati SportsMedicine Research and Education Foundation and provides 30 AMA PRA Category 1 credits™. This conference is one of a few comprehensive continuing education courses that includes clinical, surgical, and rehabilitative management of knee and shoulder pathology. Our internationally recognized, multidisciplinary faculty will share their experiences, research, and outcomes to stimulate you to rethink your approach to many musculoskeletal challenges. For more information and to view the conference program, please visit our Web site at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cincinnatisportsmed.com">www.cincinnatisportsmed.com</ext-link>. You may also contact Debbie Hartwig at 513-794-8461 or via e-mail at <email>dlhartwig@csmoc.com</email>.</p>
<p>PRINCIPLES OF DANCE MEDICINE: Clinical Management of the Dancer Patient Continuing Medical Education Course, will be held July 12 to 15, 2012 at the NYU Langone Medical Center, Farkas Auditorium, New York, New York. This course is sponsored by the NYU Post-Graduate Medical School and hosted by Harkness Center for Dance Injuries of the NYU Hospital for Joint Diseases. For more information visit the Web site at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.danceinjury.org">www.danceinjury.org</ext-link> or contact Harkness Center for Dance Injuries, NYU Hospital for Joint Diseases, 301 East 17th Street, New York, NY 10003. TEL: +1-212-598-6022; FAX: +1-212-598-7613; e-mail: <email>harkness@nyumc.org</email>.</p>
<boxed-text id="boxed-text1-0363546511434705">
<p>DEADLINES FOR ANNOUNCEMENTS: We are happy to print notices of noncommercial seminars, courses, continuing education courses, and the like. The sooner you get your information to us, the more often we will print it. Please send course announcements to Donna Tilton at <email>dtilton@ajsm.org</email>. Remember that we need your information as early as possible because of our printer deadlines. Here are the next three deadlines: April, February 15; May, March 15; June, April 15.</p>
</boxed-text>
</sec>
</body>
</article>