<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OPP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spopp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Oncol Pharm Pract</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Oncology Pharmacy Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1078-1552</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-092X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1078155212438453</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1078155212438453</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Pemetrexed-induced cellulitis: A rare toxicity in non-small cell lung cancer treatment</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Katsenos</surname><given-names>Stamatis</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1078155212438453"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1078155212438453">Department of Pneumonology, Army General Hospital of Athens, Athens, Greece</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Psara</surname><given-names>Anthoula</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-1078155212438453">Department of Pneumonology, Army General Hospital of Athens, Athens, Greece</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Panagou</surname><given-names>Chara</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff3-1078155212438453">Department of Pneumonology, Army General Hospital of Athens, Athens, Greece</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1078155212438453">Stamatis Katsenos, Department of Pneumonology, Army General Hospital of Athens, 158 Mesogion&amp;Katehaki Avenue, 115 25 Athens, Greece. Email: <email>skatsenos@yahoo.gr</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>93</fpage>
<lpage>94</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Pemetrexed is indicated for locally advanced or metastatic non-squamous non-small-cell lung cancer as an initial treatment in combination with cisplatin or after prior chemotherapy as a single agent. It is generally a well-tolerated drug. The most common adverse reactions (incidence ≥20%) with single-agent use are fatigue, nausea, and anorexia. Additional common side effects when used in combination with cisplatin include vomiting, neutropenia, leukopenia, anemia, stomatitis/pharyngitis, thrombocytopenia, and constipation. Peripheral edema with associated erythema has rarely been described as an adverse effect. Herein, we report a patient with advanced non-small-cell lung cancer who experienced bilateral peripheral edema after pemetrexed administration. Discontinuation of pemetrexed and corticosteroids use completely resolved peripheral edema.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Non-small-cell lung cancer</kwd>
<kwd>pemetrexed</kwd>
<kwd>cellulitis</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1078155212438453" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Pemetrexed is a folate analog metabolic inhibitor used to treat locally advanced or metastatic non-squamous non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC) either as initial treatment in combination with cisplatin or as a single agent after prior chemotherapy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1078155212438453">1</xref></sup> It is generally a well-tolerated drug. Peripheral edema has rarely been described as an adverse effect. Herein, we report a case of pemetrexed-associated cellulitis in a patient with advanced lung adenocarcinoma.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1078155212438453" sec-type="cases"><title>Case report</title>
<p>A 70-year-old female was admitted for evaluation of a right lung mass and ipsilateral pleural effusion. Fiberoptic bronchoscopy was negative but medical thoracoscopy showed a diffusely red thickened chest wall pleura with associated foci of anthracotic pigments and a whitish nodule on the upper lung surface. Biopsies obtained from both lung and parietal pleura lesions were positive for primary lung adenocarcinoma. It was classified as stage IV and the patient was treated with cisplatin (100 mg/m<sup>2</sup>) every 4 weeks and vinorelbine (25 mg/m<sup>2</sup> per week) for a total of six cycles. However, this regimen did not provide any benefit and pemetrexed (500 mg/m<sup>2</sup>) was started as a single chemotherapeutic agent every 3 weeks.</p>
<p>While being treated with pemetrexed, she experienced bilateral swelling of lower extremities with associated tenderness, erythema, and numbness after 3 months of therapy. On examination, the skin was hot, red, and edematous, with surface appearance resembling the skin of an orange (peau d’orange) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1078155212438453">Figure 1 (a)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1078155212438453">b</xref>)). Cutaneous lesions’ borders were generally indistinct. Symmetric distal lower limb sensory deficit was noted with relative sparing of motor power, balance, and tendon jerks. A diagnosis of cellulitis and peripheral neuropathy was made. A drug-associated origin was the most likely explanation after ruling out other possible causes including heart, kidney, or liver failure and deep vein thrombosis (DVT). The temporal association between pemetrexed administration and cellulitis development substantiated its causative role. Cutaneous lesions were gradually regressed after discontinuing pemetrexed and instituting corticosteroids. Neuropathic pain was also relieved by gabapentin. Pemetrexed was reinstituted at 75% of the previous dose because of its effectiveness in our patient with all due care for skin toxicity reappearance.
<fig id="fig1-1078155212438453" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Erythematous and edematous lower limb with ‘peau d’orange’ skin surface.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1078155212438453-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1078155212438453" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>Pemetrexed is a novel antifolate agent approved in combination with cisplatin for the treatment of patients with malignant pleural mesothelioma who have unresectable disease and for the therapy of previously treated patients with locally advanced or metastatic NSCLC as a single agent or in association with cisplatin as a first-line treatment in patients with non-squamous histology.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1078155212438453">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1078155212438453">2</xref></sup> Although it has favorable effects in patients with NSCLC, toxicity profile is not negligible. The most frequently observed adverse effects include myelosuppression, fatigue, and mucositis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1078155212438453">3</xref></sup> Cellulitis of lower limbs has rarely been reported as an untoward reaction of pemetrexed use.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1078155212438453">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>There are no established criteria for the diagnosis of drug-induced cellulitis. However, the diagnosis is possible by exclusion of other conditions that cause peripheral edema with associated erythema including renal and liver insufficiency, congestive heart failure, and DVT. Furthermore, it is supported by the time course of drug infusion and cutaneous lesion appearance as well as its remission following the withdrawal of the culprit agent. In the present case, any possible cause of cellulitis was ruled out. Pemetrexed cessation and timely initiation of corticosteroids resulted in edema regression.</p>
<p>Data addressing pemetrexed-induced cellulitis are very limited. However, two recent studies investigated the incidence and risk factors for its development. In the former study, 14 patients developed cellulitis out of 489 who were treated with pemetrexed. In all cases, symptoms resolved with discontinuation or dose reduction of the drug. Patients who received corticosteroids showed improvement in their symptoms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1078155212438453">4</xref></sup> The latter one evaluated pemetrexed-induced cutaneous adverse events (CAE) such as conjunctivitis, periorbital, and limb edema and found that female gender is an independent factor for the appearance of skin lesions. Patients with CAE had more cycles of pemetrexed than those without experiencing these events (7 versus 5.5; <italic>p</italic> = 0.028).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1078155212438453">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>In conclusion, physicians should be aware of this rare but serious complication since pemetrexed is increasingly prescribed for advanced NSCLC. Moreover, patients should be urged to promptly report the relevant symptoms so that comorbid conditions can be excluded and appropriate treatment initiated.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec4-1078155212438453"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This work received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1078155212438453"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>FDA drug approval summary: pemetrexed for injection (Alimta) for the treatment of non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Oncologist</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>368</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1078155212438453"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>European Medicines Agency: EPARs for authorized medicinal products for human use: Alimta. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.emea.europa.eu">www.emea.europa.eu</ext-link> (accessed 1 May 2008)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1078155212438453"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and toxicity of pemetrexed as a third-line treatment for non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Jpn J Clin Oncol</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1078155212438453"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D’Angelo</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kris</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietanza</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A case series of dose-limiting peripheral edema observed in patients treated with pemetrexed</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Oncol</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>624</fpage>–<lpage>626</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1078155212438453"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Equia</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruppert</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fillon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Skin toxicities compromise prolonged pemetrexed treatment</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Oncol</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>2083</fpage>–<lpage>2089</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>