<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">LDX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spldx</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Learn Disabil</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Learning Disabilities</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0022-2194</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1538-4780</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022219411423423</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0022219411423423</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Early Writing Deficits in Preschoolers With Oral Language Difficulties</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Puranik</surname><given-names>Cynthia S.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0022219411423423">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lonigan</surname><given-names>Christopher J.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0022219411423423">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0022219411423423"><label>1</label>University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0022219411423423"><label>2</label>Florida State University, Tallahassee, FL, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0022219411423423">Cynthia S. Puranik, Department of Communication Science &amp; Disorders, University of Pittsburgh, 4033 Forbes Tower, Pittsburgh, PA 15260 Email: <email>cpuranik@pitt.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-0022219411423423">
<p>Cynthia S. Puranik, PhD, CCC/SLP, is an assistant professor in the department of Communication Science &amp; Disorders at the University of Pittsburgh. Her primary area of research involves understanding the development of early writing and the assessment of preschool children’s emergent writing skills. Other areas of research interest include assessment of writing in elementary school children and language-based reading difficulties.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio2-0022219411423423">
<p>Christopher J. Lonigan, PhD, is a Distinguished Research Professor of Psychology and an associate director of the Florida Center for Reading Research at Florida State University. His current research interests include the development, assessment, and promotion of preschool early literacy skills and self-regulation, early identification of reading disability, and the development and evaluation of preschool interventions and curricula for children at-risk of academic difficulties.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>45</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>179</fpage>
<lpage>190</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Hammill Institute on Disabilities 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Hammill Institute on Disabilities</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The purpose of this study was to investigate whether preschool children with language impairments (LI), a group with documented reading difficulties, also experience writing difficulties. In addition, a purpose was to examine if the writing outcomes differed when children had concomitant cognitive deficits in addition to oral language problems. A group of 293 preschool children were administered an assessment battery that included measures to examine oral language, nonverbal cognition, emergent reading, and writing. Children were divided into four groups based on their language and cognitive performance. The findings from this study show that as early as preschool, children with weaker oral language skills lag behind their peers with stronger oral language skills in terms of their writing-related skills. Children with oral language and cognitive deficits performed more poorly than children whose deficits were confined to oral language. A child’s cognitive ability also has an impact on emergent writing skills, but it appears to be moderated by oral language skills. These results are consistent with research documenting links between preschool language and emergent reading in children with a history of LI.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>emergent writing</kwd>
<kwd>emergent literacy</kwd>
<kwd>language impairment</kwd>
<kwd>preschool</kwd>
<kwd>writing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>March/April 2012</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A substantial body of research has examined the relationship between oral language skills and reading (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022219411423423">Aram &amp; Nation, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0022219411423423">Bishop &amp; Adams, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0022219411423423">Bishop &amp; Edmundson, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022219411423423">Catts, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022219411423423">Catts, Fey, Tomblin, &amp; Zhang, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0022219411423423">Naucler &amp; Magnusson, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0022219411423423">Roth, Speece, &amp; Cooper, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0022219411423423">Scarborough &amp; Dobrich, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0022219411423423">Silva, Williams, &amp; McGee, 1987</xref>). Results of these investigations have established that there are short-term and long-term negative consequences of poor oral language skills on beginning and subsequent reading achievement. Those identified with reading difficulties in the early grades continue to read poorly throughout their school years (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0022219411423423">Badian, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0022219411423423">Juel, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0022219411423423">Scarborough, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0022219411423423">Stothard, Snowling, Bishop, Chipchase, &amp; Kaplan, 1998</xref>). Children who enter school with limited reading-related skills are at high risk for later academic underachievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022219411423423">Aram &amp; Nation, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0022219411423423">Scarborough, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0022219411423423">Snowling, Adams, Bishop, &amp; Stothard, 2001</xref>). Consequently, these children are more likely to be referred for special education services and present with concomitant social, behavioral, and mental health problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0022219411423423">Johnson et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0022219411423423">Law, Rush, Schoon, &amp; Parsons, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0022219411423423">Nelson, Benner, Stern, &amp; Stage, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0022219411423423">Snowling, Bishop, Stothard, Chipchase, &amp; Kaplan, 2006</xref>). Over the long term, these early language and associated reading difficulties have negative consequences for employment opportunities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0022219411423423">Felsenfeld, Broen, &amp; McGue, 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0022219411423423">1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0022219411423423">Howlin, Mawhood, &amp; Rutter, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0022219411423423">Law et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The relationship between oral language and reading does not surface in grade school but begins early. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022219411423423">Boudreau and Hedberg (1999)</xref> compared differences in early emergent reading-related skills in 18 children with language impairments (LI) and their typically developing (TD) peers. They found that children with LI performed more poorly on letter names, rhyme awareness, and print concepts compared to their TD peers. Findings have been similar when preschoolers with LI have been followed longitudinally. Among the earliest investigations included a longitudinal study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022219411423423">Aram and Nation (1980)</xref>. A total of 63 children with LI were evaluated in preschool and then followed up 4 to 5 years later. At the time of the second evaluation, the majority of these children exhibited below-normal achievement in reading, spelling, and mathematics in addition to speech-language problems. Likewise, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022219411423423">Catts (1993)</xref> compared 56 children with a preschool history of speech-language impairments to 30 TD children. In kindergarten, children were administered tests of receptive and expressive language, articulation, nonverbal abilities, phonological awareness, and rapid naming. In first and second grades, reading achievement was measured with word identification, word recognition, and reading comprehension tests. Findings indicated that children with speech-language impairments were at an increased risk for reading disabilities.</p>
<p>Research also has documented links between oral language and emergent literacy in children with weak oral language skills but without a history of preschool LI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0022219411423423">Lonigan, Burgess, &amp; Anthony, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0022219411423423">Spira, Bracken, &amp; Fishel, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0022219411423423">Storch &amp; Whitehurst, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0022219411423423">Whitehurst &amp; Lonigan, 1998</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0022219411423423">Spira et al. (2005)</xref>, who followed children longitudinally from kindergarten through fourth grade, found that children’s reading development was strongly related to individual linguistic abilities. Children who had better oral language, print knowledge, and phonological awareness skills were more likely to show increased reading skills as they progressed through elementary school. Thus, in comparison to children with stronger oral language skills, children with weaker oral language skills perform less well on emergent literacy tasks.</p>
<p>Given the consequences of poor oral language skills on emergent literacy skills and their subsequent effects on reading achievement, academic progress, and social and behavioral problems, it is surprising that the effect of oral language skills on early writing skills has not been examined. The studies mentioned above have focused on early reading outcomes. However, it is likely that in addition to their reading difficulties, children with oral language difficulties also have difficulties with writing. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0022219411423423">Scarborough (2001)</xref> argued that difficulties with oral and written language might be causally related to and a reflection of an underlying core weakness in language, such that they affect both oral and written (reading and writing) language.</p>
<p>Although the evidence for the relationship between oral LI and reading impairments is well established, evidence for the relationship between oral LI and writing impairments has been steadily mounting. A growing body of research indicates that children with LI have difficulty with writing or have writing impairments. Findings indicate that children with LI have difficulty producing both narrative and expository texts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0022219411423423">Dockrell, Lindsay, Connelly, &amp; Mackie, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0022219411423423">Fey, Catts, Proctor-Williams, Tomblin, &amp; Zhang, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0022219411423423">Gillam &amp; Johnston, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0022219411423423">Gillam, McFadden, &amp; van Kleeck, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0022219411423423">Liles, Duffy, Merritt, &amp; Purcell, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0022219411423423">Mackie &amp; Dockrell, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0022219411423423">Puranik, Lombardino, &amp; Altmann, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0022219411423423">Scott &amp; Windsor, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0022219411423423">Strong &amp; Shaver, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0022219411423423">Windsor, Scott, &amp; Street, 2000</xref>). Children with LI write fewer words and produce shorter texts compared to their TD peers. Furthermore, they express fewer ideas, make more grammatical errors, and demonstrate reduced lexical complexity in their writing when compared to their TD peers. However, these studies examining writing have been conducted with older children in elementary school and beyond.</p>
<p>Children do not begin writing in grade school. They begin writing as early as 2 years of age by scribbling, drawing, and making marks on paper to express meaning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0022219411423423">Baghban, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0022219411423423">Schickedanz, 1990</xref>). They advance from writing letter-like forms, writing random letters, and writing their names to using invented spelling to spell words before writing conventionally. These early forms of written expression have been referred to as emergent writing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0022219411423423">Clay, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0022219411423423">Ferreiro &amp; Teberosky, 1982</xref>). Given that emergent reading weaknesses are apparent prior to formal reading instruction (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022219411423423">Boudreau &amp; Hedberg, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0022219411423423">Gillam &amp; Johnston, 1985</xref>), it is likely that weaknesses in emergent writing are also apparent prior to formal writing instruction. In fact, there is preliminary evidence to suggest that differences in writing appear early. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0022219411423423">Cabell, Justice, Zucker, and McGinty (2009)</xref> found significant differences in the name-writing abilities of preschool children with LI compared to TD peers. Apart from this single study of name writing in preschoolers, however, we were unable to find other studies examining the early writing abilities of children with LI.</p>
<p>Because little is known about the early writing skills of this group of children, the purpose of this study was to address some of these knowledge gaps by examining the early writing skills of children with LI. Examining whether differences in writing or writing difficulties surface early is important for several reasons. First, literacy learning begins prior to formal schooling and before children exhibit conventional ways of reading and writing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0022219411423423">Clay, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0022219411423423">Mason &amp; Stewart, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0022219411423423">Sulzby, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0022219411423423">Sulzby &amp; Teale, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0022219411423423">Whitehurst &amp; Lonigan, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0022219411423423">2001</xref>). Second, the developmental trajectory for literacy success or literacy failure begins early. Children who are poor writers in first grade are highly likely to remain poor writers at the end of fourth grade (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0022219411423423">Juel, 1988</xref>). Third, reading deficits appear to become stable over time (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0022219411423423">Puranik, Petscher, Al Otaiba, Catts, &amp; Lonigan, 2008</xref>), and they are increasingly difficult to remediate as children get older (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0022219411423423">Torgesen, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0022219411423423">Vaughn, Linan-Thompson, &amp; Hickman, 2003</xref>). The same might be true for writing. Hence, the purpose of this study was to investigate whether preschool children with LI—a group with documented reading difficulties—also experience writing difficulties.</p>
<p>In examining the relationship between LI and writing difficulties, we took into account children’s cognitive status. Recent studies examining social and educational outcomes in children with LI have made a distinction between children with specific LI and those with more general LI. The former include children with a discrepancy between language and nonverbal performance, whereas the latter include children with deficits in both language and nonverbal cognition and are referred to as children with nonspecific LI (NS-LI). Cognitive skills appear to affect reading achievement (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0022219411423423">Bishop &amp; Adams, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022219411423423">Catts et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0022219411423423">Snowling, Bishop, &amp; Stothard, 2000</xref>); therefore, studies examining literacy and subsequent related outcomes (e.g., mental health and employment) of children with a history of LI have also found it useful to differentiate between children with LI and children with NS-LI (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022219411423423">Catts et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0022219411423423">Law et al., 2009</xref>) because outcomes have differed based on the presence or absence of nonverbal impairments. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022219411423423">Catts et al. (2002)</xref>, who followed children with LI from kindergarten through fourth grade, found that children with LI were at high risk for reading disabilities in fourth grade; however, the risk was higher for children with NS-LI (i.e., children with nonverbal and oral language deficits). Similar results were found by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0022219411423423">Bishop and Adams (1990)</xref>, who followed children with LI from 4 years to 8.5 years and then later at 15 years of age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0022219411423423">Snowling et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0022219411423423">Stothard et al., 1998</xref>). Thus, it appears that children with LI are at risk for literacy difficulties; however, these difficulties are more pronounced when they occur in conjunction with cognitive deficits. In addition to affecting reading outcomes, cognitive skills affect the ability to produce written language (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0022219411423423">Hayes, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0022219411423423">Stanovich, Cunningham, &amp; Freeman, 1984</xref>) and are therefore consistently used as a control variable in studies examining writing (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0022219411423423">Abbott, Berninger, &amp; Fayol, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0022219411423423">Berninger &amp; Swanson, 1994</xref>). Hence, an additional goal of this study was to examine if the writing outcomes of children with NS-LI differed from the writing outcomes of children with LI.</p>
<sec id="section1-0022219411423423">
<title>Research Questions</title>
<list id="list1-0022219411423423" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Do preschool children with LI have poorer writing outcomes compared to their TD peers before beginning formal literacy instruction? In line with studies examining reading outcomes in preschool children, we hypothesized that there would be an association between oral language difficulties and writing. Differences in writing between preschool children with and without LI would be evident early.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Do writing outcomes vary for children with NS-LI versus children with LI? In line with previous studies on reading, we hypothesized that although both children with NS-LI and children with LI would have difficulties with writing compared to their TD peers, children with NS-LI would have poorer outcomes compared to their peers with LI.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0022219411423423" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section3-0022219411423423">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>Participants for this study were 359 preschool children who were part of a larger longitudinal study that was a randomized control trial examining the effects of literacy intervention. These children were enrolled in various public and private preschools and child care centers that served children from families from a diverse range of socioeconomic status in a moderate-sized city in northern Florida. Informed consent forms were distributed to parents of all children in the participating centers through their classroom teachers. Only children whose parents or guardians returned signed consent forms participated in this study. Of this larger group, 293 children had complete data on the oral language, cognitive, and emergent literacy measures used in this study. Demographic information for the participants is provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0022219411423423">Table 1</xref>. Parental education was normally distributed and ranged from did not complete high school to postdoctoral degree (median education reported ranged from completed some college to completed AA degree). Only 10% of the sample reported completing a BA or above, and less than 10% reported less than a high school diploma or GED. Median reported income was in the $31,000 to $40,000 range.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0022219411423423" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Demographic Information for NS-LI, LI, TD, and LNIQ Groups</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0022219411423423" xlink:href="10.1177_0022219411423423-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">NS-LI (<italic>n</italic> = 92)</th>
<th align="center">LI (<italic>n</italic> = 28)</th>
<th align="center">TD (<italic>n</italic> = 89)</th>
<th align="center">LNIQ (<italic>n</italic> = 84)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age (months; <italic>M</italic>, <italic>SD</italic>)</td>
<td>58.49, 3.46</td>
<td>58.0, 3.24</td>
<td>58.2, 3.65</td>
<td>59.93, 3.58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Gender</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male</td>
<td>66.7</td>
<td>57.1</td>
<td>57.3</td>
<td>57.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td>33.3</td>
<td>42.9</td>
<td>42.7</td>
<td>42.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Ethnicity</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Asian</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>2.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black or African American</td>
<td>45.7</td>
<td>32.1</td>
<td>40.4</td>
<td>44.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>7.1</td>
<td>4.5</td>
<td>2.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> White</td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td>53.6</td>
<td>47.2</td>
<td>45.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>5.6</td>
<td>6.0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0022219411423423">
<p>Note: NS-LI = nonspecific LI; LI = language impairment; TD = typically developing controls; LNIQ = low nonverbal IQ.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0022219411423423">
<title>Procedures and Materials</title>
<p>All children were tested individually by trained research assistants at their child care centers or preschools. All assessments were completed in the spring of the school year prior to the literacy intervention for the larger study. The assessments were conducted in a quiet room in two to three sessions that lasted approximately 20 to 30 minutes each depending on the child’s tolerance level and ability to attend to the task.</p>
<sec id="section5-0022219411423423">
<title>Oral language</title>
<p>The Clinical Evaluation of Language Fundamentals–Preschool (CELF-P; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0022219411423423">Semel, Wiig, &amp; Secord, 1992</xref>) was used to assess oral language. The CELF-P is a widely used, psychometrically sound measure of preschool oral language skills. Scores on the CELF-P subtests are combined to yield an expressive language standard score (Formulating Labels, Word Structure, and Recalling Sentences subtests), a receptive language standard score (Basic Concepts, Linguistic Concepts, and Sentence Structure subtests), and a total language standard score. Internal consistency reliabilities across all subtests for children 3 to 6 years of age range from .74 to .85. The test has good concurrent validity with the Differential Ability Scales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0022219411423423">Elliott, 1990</xref>) and the Preschool Language Scales–3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0022219411423423">Zimmerman, Steiner, &amp; Pond, 1992</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0022219411423423">
<title>Nonverbal cognitive abilities</title>
<p>The Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence–Revised (WPPSI-R; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0022219411423423">Wechsler, 1989</xref>) measures intellectual abilities in young children ages 2.6 to 7.3 years. In this study, children completed the Block Design and Matrix Reasoning subtests. On the Block Design subtest, the child is required to re-create a design using blocks while viewing a constructed model or a picture in a stimulus book within a specified time limit. On the Matrix Reasoning subtest, the child is shown an incomplete matrix and is required to select the missing portion from four or five response options. These subtests have strong reliability and have significant correlations with both the Performance IQ and the Full Scale IQ scores derived from the WPPSI-III. Criterion validity for the WPPSI-R is supported by high correlations with other instruments measuring cognitive abilities. These subtests have been used in previous studies and are particularly useful in measuring nonverbal cognitive abilities in children with LI (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0022219411423423">Stothard et al., 1998</xref>) because they do not require a verbal response.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0022219411423423">
<title>Emergent writing measures</title>
<p>Three measures were used to assess children’s emergent writing skills. On the Write Letters task, children were asked to write each of 10 letters named by the examiner (B, D, S, T, O, A, H, K, M, and C). These letters were chosen based on previous recommendations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0022219411423423">Mason &amp; Stewart, 1990</xref>) and research documenting the letters known most frequently by preschool children (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0022219411423423">Justice, Pence, Bowles, &amp; Wiggins, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0022219411423423">Phillips, Lonigan, &amp; Graham, 2006</xref>). The examiner said a letter in the same random order, and the children were asked to write the letter. Children were not given any directions regarding writing in uppercase or lowercase and were given points irrespective of the case used; however, the majority of children wrote letters in uppercase. The Write Letters task was scored on a 0 through 2 scale depending on if, and how well or poorly, the letters were formed. Children obtained a score of 0 if they did not respond or wrote an unrecognizable letter, a score of 1 if the letter was reversed or was poorly formed and recognized only in context, and a score of 2 if the letter was written accurately and could be recognized out of context. Internal consistency estimates obtained for the Write Letters task were high (α = .93).</p>
<p>For the Write Name task, the examiner gave the child paper and a pencil and asked the child to write his or her name. Children’s name writing was scored on a 9-point scale using a modified version of the rubric used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0022219411423423">Levin, Both-de Vries, Aram, and Bus (2005)</xref>. On this scale, children are given progressively higher scores based on the number of the elements included in their writing. This scoring is in line with other studies examining name writing (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0022219411423423">Ferreiro &amp; Teberosky, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0022219411423423">Hildreth, 1936</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0022219411423423">Levin &amp; Bus, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0022219411423423">Levin et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0022219411423423">Lieberman, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0022219411423423">Puranik &amp; Lonigan, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0022219411423423">Puranik, Lonigan, &amp; Kim, in press</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0022219411423423">Saracho, 1990</xref>). Scoring was based on the following: no response or a scribble produced by scratching generally distributed over the page = 0 points; a scribble that is linear—organized in a horizontal or vertical line = 1 point; writing containing distinguishable or separate units—circles, dots, or lines that are separated = 2 points (child needed to have at least 2 to receive credit, with the exception of a cursive line that goes up and down repeatedly); writing contains simple characters—units are simple forms including dots, circles, square- and triangle-like forms, short lines and symbols—that are separated = 3 points; writing contains simple characters and is written demonstrating left-to-right orientation = 4 points; writing contains first letter of name and other letters may be represented by simple characters = 5 points; writing contains first letter of name and other letters may be represented by complex characters—the units are not simple but include pseudo and real letters = 6 points; writes name using correct first letter and represents other sounds in name with random letters = 7 points; writes more than half of the letters contained in the first name = 8 points; and correctly spells first name using conventional spelling = 9 points.</p>
<p>The Spelling task included six items that required children to write common CVC words (i.e., mat, bed, duck, cat, fell, hen). The Spelling task was scored on a 7-point scale using a modified version of the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0022219411423423">Tangel and Blachman (1992)</xref> spelling rubric. According to this scale, children receive points for the number of phonemes they represent in writing. Children were given a score of 0 if they did not respond, 1 if they responded verbally with random letters, 2 if they produced a scribble, 3 if they used random letters to spell a word (e.g., “toh” for “bed,” “ka for “fell”), 4 if they wrote the correct initial or last letter (e.g., “mob” for “mat,” “tad” for “bed”), 5 if their spelling contained the correct initial and last letter (e.g., “fl” for “fell,” “hn” for “hen”), 6 if they had the first and last letter but the incorrect vowel (e.g., “hin” for “hen,” “bad” for “bed”) or used invented spelling (e.g., “duc” for “duck,” “fel” for “fell”), and 7 if they had the correct spelling. Excellent internal consistency was obtained (α = .96).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0022219411423423">
<title>Emergent reading measures</title>
<p>Four measures were used to assess children’s emergent reading skills. A researcher-developed Print-Related Knowledge task, which included 24 items to assess children’s knowledge about print and print conventions, was administered. The measure included questions to assess children’s knowledge regarding general principles of print (e.g., “Which one is a word?”), environmental print (e.g., “Which one says Wal-Mart™?”), and functions of print (e.g., “Show me a newspaper? What do people do with a newspaper?”). Children were shown a set of four pictures and had to point to the correct picture for all the subtests except for portions of the Functions of Print subtest, in which they had to also answer specific questions (e.g., “What do people do with a newspaper?”). Internal consistency estimate obtained for the print knowledge task was high (α = .84). Concurrent validity for the Print-Related Knowledge task was established by examining correlations with subtests of the Preschool Comprehensive Test of Phonological and Print Processing (Pre-CTOPPP; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0022219411423423">Lonigan, Wagner, Torgesen, &amp; Rashotte, 2002</xref>). The Pre-CTOPPP was the development version of the Test of Preschool Early Literacy (TOPEL; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0022219411423423">Lonigan, Wagner, Torgesen, &amp; Rashotte, 2007</xref>) and was designed as a downward extension of the Comprehensive Test of Phonological Processing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0022219411423423">Wagner, Torgesen, &amp; Rashotte, 1999</xref>). Correlations between the Print-Related Knowledge task and the Print Knowledge and the Expressive Vocabulary subtests of the TOPEL were .69 and .66, respectively.</p>
<p>On a Letter-Naming task, children were shown uppercase letters printed on cards and were asked to name the letter. The letters were presented to children in a fixed random order. The letters were the same as used in the Write Letters task. This task was untimed, and responses were scored dichotomously. The internal consistency estimate obtained for the Letter-Naming task was .94.</p>
<p>Two phonological awareness subtests from the Pre-CTOPPP were administered. The phonological awareness subtests include an 18-item Elision subtest that assesses analysis skills and a 21-item Blending subtest that assesses synthesis skills across the developmental continuum of phonological awareness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0022219411423423">Anthony et al., 2002</xref>). For the Elision subtest, children had to respond to questions such as “Look at these pictures. My word is (sunflower). Say (sunflower). Now point to sunflower without flower.” The child is expected to point to the picture of (sun) from an array of four pictures. For the Blending subtest, children had to respond to questions such as, “What words do these make: hot-dog, air-plane.” Reliabilities for the phonological awareness subtests of the Pre-CTOPPP for 3-, 4-, and 5-year-old children are reported to be high (α = .86 to .88).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0022219411423423">
<title>Interrater Reliability</title>
<p>After practice and establishing coding guidelines, two research assistants and the first author coded the Write Name, Write Letters, and the Spelling tasks. Approximately 25% of the written samples were randomly chosen to calculate interrater reliability. Interrater reliability was 94% for the Write Letters task, 95% for the Write Name task, and 91% for the Spelling task. All scoring differences were settled by consensus following discussion. The final score entered was the one agreed on by both raters.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0022219411423423" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section11-0022219411423423">
<title>Operationalizing the Language Groups</title>
<p>The participants were divided into four groups following the criteria used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022219411423423">Catts et al. (2002)</xref>. The four groups were LI, NS-LI, TD, and low nonverbal IQ (LNIQ) based on a diagnostic test battery of language and nonverbal abilities. Participants were defined as having LI if their performance was 1.25 SD or more below their chronological age-expected scores on at least two of the three oral language composite measures. Participants who scored within 1 SD of the mean on all oral language measures formed the TD group.</p>
<p>Children with LI were further divided based on their nonverbal skills. The LI group included children who scored within 1 SD of the mean on the Matrix Reasoning subtest of the WPPSI-R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0022219411423423">Wechsler, 1989</xref>), and the NS-LI group included children who scored more than 1 SD below the mean on the subtest.</p>
<p>Similar to the LI groups, the TD group was also divided into those with and without nonverbal cognitive deficits. Those without nonverbal cognitive deficits, that is, those who scored within 1 SD of the mean on the Matrix Reasoning subtest of the WPPSI-R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0022219411423423">Wechsler, 1989</xref>), formed the TD group. Participants who scored 1 SD below the mean on the Matrix Reasoning subtest met the criterion for a nonverbal deficit and composed the LNIQ group. Just as in studies of reading (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022219411423423">Catts et al., 2002</xref>), this group served as a useful comparison group when considering the relationship between nonverbal IQ and writing achievement. Demographic information for participants in all four groups is provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0022219411423423">Table 1</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0022219411423423">
<title>Descriptive Statistics</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0022219411423423">Table 2</xref> contains the scores for oral language and nonverbal cognitive skills for each of the four groups. There were no significant differences in the mean chronological age for the groups. By definition, the LI children scored below the mean on oral language measures but scored in the average range on the nonverbal IQ test. Children in the NS-LI group scored below the mean on tests of oral language and the WPPSI subtests. The TD group scored in the average range for oral language tests and the WPPSI subtests. Finally, the LNIQ group scored within the mean for the test on the oral language measures, but their scores on the WPPSI subtests were mixed. Scores on the Block Design subtest were below the mean for the test, whereas scores on the Matrix Reasoning subtest were in the average range.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0022219411423423" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Means and Standard Deviations for Oral Language and Nonverbal IQ Scores by Group</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0022219411423423" xlink:href="10.1177_0022219411423423-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="8">Language Impairment Group</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">NS-LI (<italic>n</italic> = 92)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">LI (<italic>n</italic> = 28)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">TD (<italic>n</italic> = 89)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">LNIQ (<italic>n</italic> = 84)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Measure</th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>CELF-P Expressive</td>
<td>78.11</td>
<td>13.91</td>
<td>78.43</td>
<td>14.21</td>
<td>104.01</td>
<td>12.03</td>
<td>102.86</td>
<td>10.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Formulating Labels</td>
<td>7.18</td>
<td>2.61</td>
<td>7.64</td>
<td>2.25</td>
<td>11.36</td>
<td>3.24</td>
<td>11.08</td>
<td>2.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Word Structure</td>
<td>5.32</td>
<td>2.15</td>
<td>5.25</td>
<td>2.34</td>
<td>9.98</td>
<td>2.34</td>
<td>9.70</td>
<td>2.14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Recalling Sentences</td>
<td>6.44</td>
<td>2.05</td>
<td>6.64</td>
<td>1.95</td>
<td>10.83</td>
<td>2.01</td>
<td>10.61</td>
<td>1.72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CELF-P Receptive</td>
<td>74.56</td>
<td>14.59</td>
<td>78.21</td>
<td>11.17</td>
<td>106.69</td>
<td>10.21</td>
<td>103.02</td>
<td>9.97</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Basic Concepts</td>
<td>6.25</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>6.75</td>
<td>2.44</td>
<td>11.8</td>
<td>2.21</td>
<td>11.11</td>
<td>2.38</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Linguistic Concepts</td>
<td>5.21</td>
<td>2.66</td>
<td>5.57</td>
<td>2.22</td>
<td>11.43</td>
<td>2.43</td>
<td>10.68</td>
<td>2.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sentence Structure</td>
<td>5.41</td>
<td>2.12</td>
<td>5.68</td>
<td>1.94</td>
<td>9.88</td>
<td>2.68</td>
<td>9.25</td>
<td>2.48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CELF-P Composite</td>
<td>75.63</td>
<td>12.6</td>
<td>78.46</td>
<td>10.78</td>
<td>105.59</td>
<td>9.88</td>
<td>102.94</td>
<td>9.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WPSSI-R Block Design</td>
<td>6.51</td>
<td>1.77</td>
<td>11.64</td>
<td>2.13</td>
<td>12.27</td>
<td>2.27</td>
<td>7.63</td>
<td>1.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WPSSI-R Matrix Reasoning</td>
<td>7.07</td>
<td>3.38</td>
<td>8.43</td>
<td>3.94</td>
<td>10.18</td>
<td>3.65</td>
<td>8.99</td>
<td>3.01</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0022219411423423">
<p>Note: Values for CELF-P expressive, receptive, and composite scores are reported in standard scores with a mean of 100 and an SD of 15; values for CELF-P subtests are reported in standard scores with a mean of 10 and an SD of 3; WPSSI-R scores are reported in standard scores with a mean of 10 and an SD of 3. NS-LI = nonspecific LI; LI = language impairment; TD = typically developing controls; LNIQ = low nonverbal IQ; CELF-P = <italic>Clinical Evaluation of Language Fundamentals–Preschool</italic>; WPSSI-R = <italic>Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence–Revised</italic>.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Bivariate correlations among the oral language, cognitive, emergent writing, and emergent reading measures are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0022219411423423">Table 3</xref>. As expected, strong correlations were noted between the oral language measures and emergent literacy measures. Correlations between oral language measures and emergent writing measures were in the moderate range (rs = .40 to .49), whereas the correlations between oral language measures and emergent reading measures were strong (rs = .51 to .69). Correlations between nonverbal cognitive measures and emergent reading and emergent writing measures were similar and in the moderate range (rs = .29 to .40). The correlations between emergent reading and emergent writing measures were moderate to strong (rs = .42 to .62).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0022219411423423" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Correlations Among Oral Language, IQ, and Emergent Reading and Writing Measures</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0022219411423423" xlink:href="10.1177_0022219411423423-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">1</th>
<th align="center">2</th>
<th align="center">3</th>
<th align="center">4</th>
<th align="center">5</th>
<th align="center">6</th>
<th align="center">7</th>
<th align="center">8</th>
<th align="center">9</th>
<th align="center">10</th>
<th align="center">11</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1.CELF-P Receptive</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2.CELF-P Expressive</td>
<td>.79</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3.CELF-P Total</td>
<td>.95</td>
<td>.94</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4.WPSSI-R Block Design</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.27</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5.WPSSI-R Matrix Reasoning</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6.Write Letters</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7.Write Name</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.50</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.62</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8.Spelling</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>.65</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9.Print-Related Knowledge</td>
<td>.69</td>
<td>.61</td>
<td>.69</td>
<td>.39</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.62</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10.Pre-CTOPPP Blending</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>.56</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11.Pre-CTOPPP Elision</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>.51</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.35</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0022219411423423">
<p>Note: All correlations significant at p &lt; .001. CELF-P = <italic>Clinical Evaluation of Language Fundamentals–Preschool</italic>; WPSSI-R = Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence-Revised; Pre-CTOPPP = <italic>Preschool Comprehensive Test of Phonological and Print Processing</italic>.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0022219411423423">
<title>Early Writing and Oral language</title>
<p>Our first question concerned the nature of the writing outcomes for children with LI. Given that the sample sizes for the four groups were different, a primary concern was violation of the homogeneity of variance assumption for ANOVA analyses. Therefore, Levene’s test was conducted for each outcome measure and Welch’s ANOVA was used to protect against Type I error. Group differences on the reading- and writing-related measures are displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0022219411423423">Table 4</xref>. Children with LI had lower scores, compared to their TD peers, on all emergent writing and emergent reading measures, Fs(3, 289) ≥ 17.73, ps ≤ .001. Both groups of children with LI (LI and NS-LI) named and wrote fewer letters than the group without LI (TD and NLIQ). They were also less proficient in their name writing than the TD and NLIQ groups. Only 32% and 50% of children in the NS-LI and LI groups, respectively, could write their first names accurately, compared to 79% and 68%, respectively, of children from the TD and NLIQ groups. The LI and NS-LI groups had poorer spelling abilities and lower scores on the print knowledge and phonological awareness tasks compared to the TD and LNIQ groups.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0022219411423423" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Means and Standard Deviations on Emergent Reading and Writing Measures by Group</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0022219411423423" xlink:href="10.1177_0022219411423423-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="8">Language Impairment Group</th>
<th/>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">NS-LI (<italic>n</italic> = 92)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">LI (<italic>n</italic> = 28)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">TD (<italic>n</italic> = 89)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">LNIQ (<italic>n</italic> = 84)</th>
<th/>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Measures</th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>F</italic> for Overall Age-Group Contrast, With F(3, 289)</th>
<th align="center">Four-Group Contrasts</th>
<th/>
<th/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="11">Emergent Writing</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Write Letters</td>
<td>5.89</td>
<td>6.12</td>
<td>10.54</td>
<td>6.79</td>
<td>14.27</td>
<td>5.57</td>
<td>12.08</td>
<td>6.14</td>
<td>31.37, p &lt; .001</td>
<td>1 &lt; 2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">**</xref>; 1 &lt; 3,4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">***</xref>; 2 &lt; 3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Write Name</td>
<td>6.05</td>
<td>2.56</td>
<td>7.54</td>
<td>2.38</td>
<td>8.65</td>
<td>2.03</td>
<td>8.04</td>
<td>2.03</td>
<td>24.54, p &lt; .001</td>
<td>1 &lt; 2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">*</xref>; 1 &lt; 3,4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">**</xref>; 2 &lt; 3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Spelling</td>
<td>11.89</td>
<td>1.01</td>
<td>14.50</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>21.66</td>
<td>1.02</td>
<td>19.45</td>
<td>9.94</td>
<td>17.73, p &lt; .001</td>
<td>1 &lt; 3,4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">**</xref>; 2 &lt; 3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="11">Emergent Reading</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Print-Related Knowledge</td>
<td>9.59</td>
<td>4.03</td>
<td>12.00</td>
<td>4.09</td>
<td>16.96</td>
<td>3.71</td>
<td>16.02</td>
<td>4.52</td>
<td>60.42, p &lt; .001</td>
<td>1 &lt; 2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">*</xref>; 1 &lt; 3,4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">**</xref>; 2 &lt; 3,4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Letter naming</td>
<td>5.08</td>
<td>3.73</td>
<td>6.79</td>
<td>3.56</td>
<td>8.49</td>
<td>2.34</td>
<td>7.82</td>
<td>2.86</td>
<td>20.74, p &lt; .001</td>
<td>1 &lt; 2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">*</xref>; 1 &lt; 3,4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Pre-CTOPPP Blending</td>
<td>12.35</td>
<td>4.62</td>
<td>13.07</td>
<td>4.10</td>
<td>16.67</td>
<td>3.63</td>
<td>16.21</td>
<td>3.64</td>
<td>23.98, p &lt; .001</td>
<td>1 &lt; 3,4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">***</xref>; 2 &lt; 3,4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Pre-CTOPPP Elision</td>
<td>7.79</td>
<td>3.83</td>
<td>8.61</td>
<td>4.06</td>
<td>12.92</td>
<td>3.82</td>
<td>11.79</td>
<td>3.62</td>
<td>33.13, p &lt; .001</td>
<td>1 &lt; 3,4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">***</xref>; 2 &lt; 3,4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0022219411423423">**</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0022219411423423">
<p>Note: NS-LI = nonspecific LI; LI = language impairment; TD = typically developing controls; LNIQ = low nonverbal IQ; Pre-CTOPPP = <italic>Preschool Comprehensive Test of Phonological and Print Processing</italic>.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0022219411423423">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0022219411423423">
<title>Early Writing and Cognitive Abilities</title>
<p>For our second question, we examined whether IQ played a role in determining early writing outcomes. Hence, we examined whether children with LI and children with NS-LI had different writing outcomes and whether children with LNIQ and the TD children had different writing outcomes. Results of the ANOVA indicated that children with NS-LI performed less well on all of the reading- and writing-related outcomes compared to children with LI. Differences between the LI and NS-LI groups were statistically significant for Write Letters (p &lt; .01), Write Name (p &lt; .05), Print-Related Knowledge (p &lt; .05), and the Letter-Naming task (p &lt; .05). Although the means for the NS-LI groups were lower than the means for the LI group for the Blending, Elision, and Spelling tasks, the differences were not statistically significant. Comparison of the performance on literacy-related measures for the TD and LNIQ groups yielded a different pattern. Although the means for the LNIQ group were lower than the means for the TD group for all reading and writing measures, none of those differences were statistically significant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0022219411423423" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this study, we compared the performance of preschool children with and without LI on emergent writing measures. Furthermore, we examined the impact of nonverbal IQ on performance on early writing measures. The findings from this study show that as early as preschool, children with significant delays in oral language skills lag behind their peers with TD oral language skills in terms of their writing-related skills. Children with oral language and cognitive deficits performed more poorly than children whose deficits were confined to oral language. Previous research has shown that children with weaker oral language skills and children with LI have weaker emergent reading skills as compared to their peers with higher oral language skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022219411423423">Aram &amp; Nation, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022219411423423">Boudreau &amp; Hedberg, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022219411423423">Catts, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0022219411423423">Gillam &amp; Johnston, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0022219411423423">Spira et al., 2005</xref>). The findings of this study showing differences in writing-related outcomes between children with LI and those with NS-LI extend previous research by demonstrating that for children with oral LI, difficulties with written language are not confined to reading but also extend to difficulties with writing.</p>
<sec id="section16-0022219411423423">
<title>Effect of Oral LI on Writing</title>
<p>The findings of this study showing differences in writing-related outcomes between children with LI and those with NS-LI demonstrate that writing difficulties do not surface in elementary school and later but begin as early as preschool, prior to the start of formal education. Our results are in line with the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0022219411423423">Cabell et al. (2009)</xref>, who reported that children with LI showed poorer name-writing skills compared to their TD peers. However, our results extend their findings by showing that children with LI performed more poorly not only on the Write Name task but also on other writing tasks such as writing letters and spelling words.</p>
<p>Although the performance of the NS-LI and LI groups was poor in comparison to their peers without oral language difficulties on all three writing tasks included in this study, our results indicate that 32% and 50% of the children, respectively, could write their first names accurately. These percentages are higher than those reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0022219411423423">Cabell et al. (2009)</xref>. They reported that only one child (4%) of the LI children compared to 65% of their TD peers in their study wrote their names accurately. Differences in the findings could be the result of at least two partially related reasons—the time and the age of the children when these tasks were administered. Measures for this study were administered in early spring—closer to the end of the preschool year, when a majority of children are able to write their names. No information about timing of assessment was provided by Cabell et al. Given that proficiency in name writing is acquired over a relatively short time span, difference in timing of the assessment during the preschool year between studies might explain the differences in findings. In addition, the children in this study were on average 4 months older than those in the Cabell et al. study (58 months vs. 54 months), which is likely associated with the time during preschool when measures were administered.</p>
<p>Our results concerning group differences support the notion that oral language skills play an important role in the development of writing starting in preschool. Additional evidence for this conclusion comes from the moderate correlations noted between oral language measures and writing outcomes. Further substantiation comes from examining differences between subgroups. Statistically significant differences were obtained between children with LI (NS-LI and LI groups) and their peers without LI (TD and NLIQ group), who had higher language scores than the two groups with LI. The finding that the children with LI and the NS-LI group performed more poorly on writing measures is consistent with the results of other studies examining differences in reading and other long-term outcomes between these two groups. Although this was not the focus of this study, our results also showed that children with LI and NS-LI performed more poorly than the TD and LNIQ groups on emergent reading tasks, including naming letters, print-related knowledge, and phonological awareness skills, consistent with the findings of previous studies of young children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022219411423423">Aram &amp; Nation, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022219411423423">Boudreau &amp; Hedberg, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022219411423423">Catts, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0022219411423423">Gillam &amp; Johnston, 1985</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0022219411423423">
<title>Effects of Cognitive Abilities on Writing</title>
<p>Another important aim of this investigation was to identify if IQ was related to writing outcomes in children with LI, and our results confirmed our hypothesis. Correlations between nonverbal IQ and writing tasks were significant and in the moderate range. This relation was further validated by examining the performance differences between the TD group and the LNIQ group and the performance differences between the LI and NS-LI groups. In both cases, the group with stronger nonverbal cognitive skills outperformed its respective comparison group. The differences between the NS-LI and LI were significant for two out of the three writing variables. Although the mean of the NS-LI group was lower than the mean for the LI group for the Spelling task, the difference was not statistically significant. Most likely this may have been because spelling compared to name writing and letter writing is a more complex task such that both groups struggled with the task. Although differences between the NS-LI and LI were significant for most of the writing variables, the differences between the TD and LNIQ groups were not statistically significant. The former results indicate that nonverbal cognitive abilities matter, whereas the latter results indicate that although nonverbal cognitive abilities matter, oral language skills have a moderating effect. Thus, nonverbal cognitive abilities are related to writing, but this relationship is affected by oral language competency.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0022219411423423">
<title>Limitations and Future Research</title>
<p>Despite evidence for associations between emergent literacy skills and oral language, there have been relatively few studies examining the relationship specifically between emergent writing and oral language. The findings of this study thus extend previous work examining the relationship between oral language and emergent literacy skills. However, as with most studies, some limitations of the current study must be noted. The results of this study should be considered preliminary because it was cross-sectional and correlational and no unambiguous causal inferences can be drawn from our data. Future studies replicating these findings are needed, as are longitudinal examinations before drawing conclusions. This is even more important because in his investigation of preschool children, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022219411423423">Catts (1993)</xref> found significant differences between the children with LI and their TD peers; however, only one half of those children continued to demonstrate reading difficulties when assessed in first and second grades. These results must also be tempered with caution because children’s reading performance has been shown to change over time; performance in the early grades is not an absolute predictor of long-term reading achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0022219411423423">Cunningham &amp; Stanovich, 1997</xref>). This could likely be the case for writing performance, which may change over time with maturation, with instruction, or as oral language deficits resolve.</p>
<p>Another limitation of this study is that we did not systematically observe the literacy instruction taking place in the classrooms, which may have had some effect on student performance. Informal observations indicated that the procedures and routines at the participating preschools were comparable and included a variety of activities seen in typical preschool classrooms. These included painting, drawing, puzzles, toys, dress-up clothes, books, music, and activity centers. All preschools reported activities involving identifying children’s names and learning the letters of the alphabet. Finally, our writing tasks were limited to word-level tasks, namely name writing, letter writing, and spelling, and we did not examine children’s ability to compose sentences. It is more than likely that children with weaker oral language skills who struggled with the writing tasks included in this study would have had a particularly difficult time with more complex writing tasks such as sentence writing and writing notes. However, this remains a study for the future.</p>
<p>One of the strengths of this study was that we did not use clinical referral to obtain participants; instead, the children with LI in this study were chosen from the educational setting. Results from participants referred clinically may be biased because of an overrepresentation of the more severe cases in the population (Berkson, 1946, as cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022219411423423">Catts et al., 2002</xref>). Often these more extreme clinical cases also present with other problems in addition to their language difficulties, making it difficult to examine the relationship between oral LI and writing. An additional strength of this study was that the comparison groups included children from the same classrooms receiving similar instruction. Past research has indicated less than optimal congruence between groups identified through research and clinically referred population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0022219411423423">Aram, Morris, &amp; Hall, 1993</xref>). How the findings of this study generalize to the clinical population remains a topic for a future study. Replicating these findings with a clinical population could be an avenue for future research.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0022219411423423">
<title>Implications for Research</title>
<p>Our finding that children with LI exhibit differences in writing as early as preschool has important implications for early identification and intervention. Research on literacy has clearly shown substantial developmental continuity in reading skills from the preschool period into the elementary grades. Children who have success with reading continue to read more and maintain that success; in contrast, children who fall behind early are less motivated to read, continue to struggle, and have later reading problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0022219411423423">Scarborough, 1998</xref>). It is for this reason that early identification and remediation of reading difficulties have been a big educational emphasis. Although preliminary, the findings of this study raise questions about the need for early screening and assessment of emergent writing skills especially for children with weaker oral language skills. Classroom teachers and educators could take steps to extend their prevention efforts to include writing. At the very least, the findings of this study suggest the need to incorporate or encourage writing activities to foster written language development especially because teaching writing has been shown to have facilitative effects that promote children’s language and literacy skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0022219411423423">Kaderavek, Justice, Hunt, &amp; Cabel, 2007</xref>; also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0022219411423423">Graham &amp; Hebert, 2010</xref>). This might be particularly beneficial for children with weaker oral language skills.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>Support for carrying out this research was provided in part by grant P50 HD052120 from the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, by a Postdoctoral Training Grant R305B050032 and grant R305A080488 from the Institute of Education Sciences. The views expressed herein are those of the authors and have not been reviewed or approved by the granting agencies.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berninger</surname><given-names>V. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fayol</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Longitudinal relationships of levels of language in writing and between writing and reading in Grades 1 to 7</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>102</volume>, <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lonigan</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bloomfield</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Structure of preschool phonological sensitivity: Overlapping sensitivity to rhyme, words, syllables, and phonemes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Child Psychology</source>, <volume>82</volume>, <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aram</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Clinical and research congruence in identifying children with specific language impairment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>580</fpage>–<lpage>591</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aram</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nation</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Preschool language disorders and subsequent language and academic difficulties</article-title>. <source>Journal of Communication Disorders</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Badian</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Predicting dyslexia in a preschool population</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Masland</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Masland</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Preschool prevention of reading failure</source> (pp. <fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Parkton, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>York Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baghban</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <source>Our daughter learns to read and write</source>. <publisher-loc>Newark, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Reading Association</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berninger</surname><given-names>V. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Modifying Hayes &amp; Flower’s model of skilled writing to explain beginning and developing writing</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Butterfield</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Children’s writing: Toward a process theory of development of skilled writing</source> (pp. <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Greenwich, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>JAI</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>D. V. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>A prospective study of the relationship between specific language impairment, phonological disorders and reading retardation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>1027</fpage>–<lpage>1050</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>D. V. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edmundson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Language-impaired 4-year-olds: Distinguishing transient from persistent impairment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech and Hearing Disorders</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boudreau</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hedberg</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>A comparison of early literacy skills in children with specific language impairment and their typically developing peers</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Speech-Language Pathology</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>260</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cabell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Justice</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zucker</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGinty</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Emergent name-writing abilities of preschool-age children with language impairment</article-title>. <source>Language, Speech, and Hearing Services in Schools</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Catts</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>The relationship between speech-language impairments and reading disabilities</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>948</fpage>–<lpage>958</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Catts</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fey</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tomblin</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>A longitudinal investigation of reading outcomes in children with language impairments</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>1142</fpage>–<lpage>1157</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <source>What did I write?</source> <publisher-loc>Portsmouth, NH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Heinemann</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.). (<year>1985</year>). <source>Early detection of reading difficulties</source> (<edition>3rd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Portsmouth, NH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Heinemann</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stanovich</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Early reading acquisition and its relation to reading experience and ability 10 years later</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>934</fpage>–<lpage>945</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dockrell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mackie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Constraints in the production of written texts of children with specific language impairments</article-title>. <source>Exceptional Children</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>Differential Ability Scales</source>. <publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Felsenfeld</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Broen</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGue</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>A 28-year follow-up of adults with a history of moderate phonological disorder: Linguistic and personality results</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>1114</fpage>–<lpage>1125</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Felsenfeld</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Broen</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGue</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>A 28-year follow-up of adults with a history of moderate phonological disorder: Educational and occupational results</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>1341</fpage>–<lpage>1353</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ferreiro</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Teberosky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>1982</year>). <source>Literacy before schooling</source>. <publisher-loc>Exeter, NH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Heinemann</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Catts</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Proctor-Williams</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tomblin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Oral and written story composition skills of children with language impairment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>1301</fpage>–<lpage>1318</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gillam</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Development of print awareness in language-disordered preschoolers</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>526</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gillam</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Spoken and written language relationships in language/learning-impaired and normally achieving school-age children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>1303</fpage>–<lpage>1315</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gillam</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McFadden</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Kleeck</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Improving narrative abilities: Whole language and language skills approaches</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fey</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Windsor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Language intervention: Preschool through the elementary years</source> (pp. <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brookes</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Writing to read: Evidence for how writing can improve reading. A Carnegie Corporation time to act report</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Alliance for Excellent Education</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>A new framework for understanding cognition and affect in writing</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ransdell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The science of writing: Theories, methods, individual differences, and applications</source> (pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hildreth</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1936</year>). <article-title>Developmental sequences in name writing</article-title>. <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Howlin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mawhood</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Autism and developmental receptive language disorder—A follow-up comparison in early adult life. II: Social, behavioural, and psychiatric outcomes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>578</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beitchman</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Fourteen-year follow-up of children with and without speech/language impairments: Speech/language stability and outcomes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>744</fpage>–<lpage>761</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Juel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Learning to read and write: A longitudinal study of 54 children from first through fourth grades</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Justice</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pence</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bowles</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wiggins</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>An investigation of four hypotheses concerning the order by which 4-year-old children learn the alphabet letters</article-title>. <source>Early Childhood Research Quarterly</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>374</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaderavek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Justice</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cabel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>, <month>November</month>). <source>Moving on: Adding emergent writing to early literacy programs</source>. <conf-name>Seminar presented at the meeting of the American, Speech, Language, and Hearing Association</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Boston, MA</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rush</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schoon</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Modeling developmental language difficulties from school entry into adulthood: Literacy, mental health, and employment outcomes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language, &amp; Hearing Research</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>1404</fpage>–<lpage>1416</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Both-de Vries</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aram</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bus</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Writing starts with own name writing: From scribbling to conventional spelling in Israeli and Dutch children</article-title>. <source>Applied Psycholinguistics</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>477</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bus</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>How is emergent writing based on drawing? Analyses of children’s products and their sorting by children and mothers</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>891</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <source>Name writing and the preschool child</source>. <publisher-loc>Phoenix, AZ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Phoenix College, Early Childhood Center</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from ERIC database. (ED269759)</comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liles</surname><given-names>B. Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Measurement of narrative discourse abilities in children with language disorders</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lonigan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Development of emergent literacy and early reading skills in preschool children: From a latent-variable longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>596</fpage>–<lpage>613</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lonigan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torgesen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rashotte</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Preschool Comprehensive Test of Phonological and Print Processing (Pre-CTOPP)</source>. <publisher-loc>Tallahassee</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Florida State University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lonigan</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torgesen</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rashotte</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>TOPEL: Test of Preschool Early Literacy</source>. <publisher-loc>Austin, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PRO-ED</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mackie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dockrell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The nature of written language deficits in children with SLI</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>1469</fpage>–<lpage>1483</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Emergent literacy assessment for instructional use in kindergarten</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Assessment for instruction in early literacy</source> (pp. <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Naucler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Reading and writing development: Reports from an ongoing longitudinal study of language-disordered and normal groups from pre-school to adolescence</article-title>. <source>Folia Phoniatrica et Logopaedica</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benner</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stage</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Interrelationships among language skills, externalizing behavior, and academic fluency and their impact on the academic skills of students with ED</article-title>. <source>Journal of Emotional and Behavioral Disorders</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lonigan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>, <month>July</month>). <source>Now I know my ABC’s: Alphabetic order and first name predict letter knowledge development in young children</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the 13th annual meeting of the Society of the Scientific Study of Reading</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Vancouver, Canada</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Puranik</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lombardino</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Writing through retellings: An exploratory study of language impaired and dyslexic populations</article-title>. <source>Reading and Writing: An Interdisciplinary Journal</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Puranik</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lonigan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>From scribbles to scrabble: Preschool children’s developing knowledge of written language</article-title>. <source>Reading and Writing: An Interdisciplinary Journal</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>567</fpage>–<lpage>589</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Puranik</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lonigan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<comment>in press</comment>). <article-title>Contributions of emergent literacy skills to name writing, letter writing, and spelling in preschool children</article-title>. <source>Early Childhood Research Quarterly</source>. doi:10.1016/j.ecresq.2011.03.002<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecresq.2011.03.002</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Puranik</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petscher</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al Otaiba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Catts</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lonigan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Development of oral reading fluency in children with speech or language impairments: A growth curve analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Learning Disabilities</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>F. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Speece</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>A longitudinal analysis of the connection between oral language and early reading</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Research</source>, <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Saracho</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Developing sequences in three-year-old children’s writing</article-title>. <source>Early Child Development and Care</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scarborough</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Early identification of children at risk for reading disabilities</source>. <publisher-loc>Timonium, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>York Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scarborough</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Connecting early language and literacy to later reading (dis)abilities: Evidence, theory, and practice</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of early literacy research</source> (pp. <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>1100</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scarborough</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dobrich</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Development of children with early language delay</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schickedanz</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>Much more than the ABCs: The early stages of reading and writing</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Association for the Education of Young Children</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Windsor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>General language performance measures in spoken and written discourse produced by school-age children with and without language learning disabilities</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>324</fpage>–<lpage>339</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Semel</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wiig</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Secord</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <source>The Clinical Evaluation of Language Fundamentals–Preschool</source>. <publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>A longitudinal study of children with developmental language delay at age three: Later intelligence, reading, and behaviour problems</article-title>. <source>Developmental Medicine and Child Neurology</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>630</fpage>–<lpage>640</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Snowling</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>D. V. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Educational attainments of school leavers with a preschool history of speech-language impairments</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Language and Communication Disorders</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Snowling</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>D. V. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Is preschool language impairment a risk factor for dyslexia in adolescence?</article-title> <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>600</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Snowling</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>D. V. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chipchase</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Psycho-social outcomes at 15 years of children with a pre-school history of speech-language impairment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>759</fpage>–<lpage>765</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spira</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bracken</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fishel</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Predicting improvement after first-grade reading difficulties: The effects of oral language, emergent literacy, and behavior skills</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stanovich</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Intelligence, cognitive skills, and early reading progress</article-title>. <source>Reading Research Quarterly</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Storch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whitehurst</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Oral language and code-related precursors to reading: Evidence from a longitudinal structural model</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>934</fpage>–<lpage>947</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snowling</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chipchase</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Language-impaired preschoolers: A follow-up into adolescence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaver</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Stability of cohesion in the spoken narratives of language-impaired and normally developing school-aged children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sulzby</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Assessment of writing and of children’s language while writing</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The role of assessment and measurement in early literacy instruction</source> (pp. <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sulzby</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Teale</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Emergent literacy</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kamil</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mosenthal</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of reading research</source> (<volume>Vol. 2</volume>, pp. <fpage>727</fpage>–<lpage>758</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Longman</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tangel</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blachman</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Effect of phoneme awareness instruction on kindergarten children’s invented spelling</article-title>. <source>Journal of Reading Behavior</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Torgesen</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Individual differences in response to early interventions in reading: The lingering problem of treatment resisters</article-title>. <source>Learning Disabilities Research and Practice</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Linan-Thompson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Response to intervention as a means of identifying students with reading/learning disabilities</article-title>. <source>Exceptional Children</source>, <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>409</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torgesen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rashotte</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Comprehensive Test of Phonological Processing</source>. <publisher-loc>Austin, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PRO-ED</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <source>Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence–Revised</source>. <publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whitehurst</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lonigan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Child development and emergent literacy</article-title>. <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>848</fpage>–<lpage>872</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Whitehurst</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lonigan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Emergent literacy: Development from prereaders to readers</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of early literacy research</source> (pp. <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Windsor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Street</surname><given-names>C. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Verb and noun morphology in the spoken and written language of children with language learning disabilities</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>1322</fpage>–<lpage>1336</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-0022219411423423">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>I. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>V. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pond</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <source>Preschool Language Scale–3</source>. <publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>