<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIV</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjiv</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Interpers Violence</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0886-2605</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6518</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0886260511416476</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0886260511416476</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Sexual Assault Nurse Examiners’ Perceptions of the Revictimization of Rape Victims</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>Shana L.</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0886260511416476">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0886260511416476"><label>1</label>Widener University, Chester, PA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0886260511416476">Shana L. Maier, Associate Professor, Department of Criminal Justice, Widener University, One University Place, Chester, PA 19013, USA Email: <email>slmaier@mail.widener.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-0886260511416476">
<p>Shana L. Maier, PhD, is an associate professor in the Department of Criminal Justice at Widener University, Chester, Pennsylvania. Her research interests include violence against women, the treatment of rape victims by the criminal justice and legal systems, the transformation of rape crisis centers, and the experiences and struggles of rape victim advocates and Sexual Assault Nurse Examiners. She is the author of articles in <italic>Journal of Ethnicity in Criminal Justice</italic>, <italic>Feminist Criminology</italic>, <italic>Violence Against Women</italic>, and <italic>Women &amp; Criminal Justice</italic> and the coauthor of articles appearing in <italic>Deviant Behavior</italic>, <italic>Journal of Women</italic>, <italic>Politics &amp; Policy</italic>, <italic>International Review of Victimology</italic>, and <italic>Women’s Health and Urban Life</italic>.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>287</fpage>
<lpage>315</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>While Sexual Assault Nurse Examiner programs have improved the treatment of rape victims by offering more compassionate and thorough treatment, SANEs believe victims continue to face revictimization by the medical, criminal justice and legal systems. The purpose of this research is to explore SANEs’ perceptions of the revictimization of rape victims by the police, legal system and medical system. Data from interviews with 39 Sexual Assault Nurse Examiners from four East Coast states reveal that most SANEs believe that the medical, criminal justice, and legal systems wield the power to revictimize rape victims. SANEs were more likely to cite the criminal justice system as a source of revictimization, followed by the medical system and legal system. According to SANEs, police contribute to victims’ distress through failure to ask questions in a sensitive manner, failure to proceed with investigations, and by asking victim-blaming questions. Revictimization by the legal system results when charges are never filed, cases are postponed or dropped, plea bargains are unsatisfactory, and victims’ character and credibility are questioned. Revictimization by the medical system is marked by long waits for medical attention.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>revictimization</kwd>
<kwd>sexual assault</kwd>
<kwd>intervention</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In response to the negative and inefficient treatment of rape victims by emergency room personnel, the first Sexual Assault Nurse Examiner (SANE) programs began in the mid- to late 1970s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0886260511416476">Antognoli-Toland, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0886260511416476">Ledray, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0886260511416476">Speck &amp; Aiken, 1995</xref>). SANEs are specially trained forensic nurses who provide rape victims with emotional support, medical care, and quality, timely collection of forensic evidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0886260511416476">Brown, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0886260511416476">Campbell, Townsend, et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0886260511416476">Ciancone, Wilson, Collette, &amp; Gerson, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0886260511416476">Emergency Nurses Association, 2007</xref>). Recent estimates indicate there are more than 600 SANE programs nationwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0886260511416476">International Association of Forensic Nursing, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0886260511416476">Ledray, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0886260511416476">SANE, Sexual Assault Response Team, 2010</xref>). Most are run by hospital emergency rooms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0886260511416476">Campbell, 2004</xref>). SANE programs are essential, given that the number of rape victims seeking medical attention in emergency rooms has increased (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0886260511416476">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0886260511416476">Magid et al., 2004</xref>) and sexual assaults represented 8% of all nonfatal violence-related injury visits to emergency departments for females in 2008 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0886260511416476">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Although previous research has explored rape victim advocates’ perceptions of victims’ treatment in emergency rooms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0886260511416476">Campbell &amp; Bybee, 1997</xref>), rape victim advocates’ perceptions of victims’ treatment by the criminal justice and medical systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0886260511416476">Maier, 2008</xref>), and rape victims’ experiences with the medical system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0886260511416476">Campbell, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0886260511416476">Campbell, Wasco, Ahrens, Sefl, &amp; Barnes, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0886260511416476">DuMont, White, &amp; McGregor, 2009</xref>), there is a gap in the research that details the views of SANEs. The purpose of this research is to explore SANEs’ <italic>perceptions</italic> of the revictimization of rape victims by the police, legal system, and medical system. More specifically, SANEs’ perceptions include their views on who is responsible for the revictimization of rape victims, how such people or systems revictimize rape victims, and if and how SANEs believe they are personally able to reduce revictimization and improve victims’ treatment.</p>
<p>While other research examines the direct experiences of rape victims, SANEs are in a unique position to witness the possible revictimization of rape victims not only because they are present when emergency department doctors treat victims and when police officers interview victims but also because oftentimes SANEs witness how victims are treated during pretrial and trial proceedings. SANEs hold a wealth of knowledge about victims’ experiences with revictimization not only because they witness the treatment of victims by multiple systems but also because they are able to reflect on experiences working with multiple victims. As treatment of victims by doctors, police, and attorneys varies from one community to another, with some communities treating victims better than others (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0886260511416476">Martin, 2005</xref>), it is important to consider the perceptions of SANEs working in various areas. Accordingly, the present research explores perceptions of SANEs working in four states. Moreover, while victims’ own accounts of their experiences cannot be discredited and have been included in other research (see, for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0886260511416476">Campbell, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0886260511416476">Campbell et al., 2001</xref>), SANEs may hold more objective perceptions than victims who most likely are experiencing emotional trauma when interacting with medical professionals and police immediately after their rape.</p>
<sec id="section1-0886260511416476">
<title>Review of Literature</title>
<p>Revictimization refers to the blame and stigmatizing responses to victims by the criminal justice, legal, and medical systems, as well as friends and family. It also refers to the trauma, distress, and alienation that victims may experience after the assault as a result of the responses of the criminal justice, legal, and medical systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0886260511416476">Madigan &amp; Gamble, 1991</xref>). There is ample research indicating that rape victims are revictimized or face a second assault at the hands of the medical, criminal justice, and legal systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0886260511416476">Campbell, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0886260511416476">Crandall &amp; Helitzer, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0886260511416476">Girardin, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0886260511416476">Konradi, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0886260511416476">Littel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0886260511416476">Stermac &amp; Stirpe, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0886260511416476">Taylor, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-0886260511416476">Ullman, 1996</xref>). Research also indicates that rape victims report not seeking help from formal social systems because they fear such systems will cause them future trauma by blaming them or not believing them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0886260511416476">Patterson, Greeson, &amp; Campbell, 2009</xref>). Three key sources of revictimization have been identified in previous research: medical practitioners, police, and legal professionals.</p>
<p>First, rape victims seeking medical attention in hospitals <italic>without</italic> SANE programs face problems such as long wait times and longer exam times (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0886260511416476">Crandall &amp; Helitzer, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0886260511416476">DiNitto, Martin, Norton, &amp; Maxwell, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0886260511416476">Girardin, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0886260511416476">Littel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0886260511416476">Martin &amp; DiNitto, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0886260511416476">Stermac &amp; Stirpe, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0886260511416476">Taylor, 2002</xref>). They also face doctors and nurses who are not adequately trained on treating rape victims or collecting forensic evidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0886260511416476">Campbell et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0886260511416476">Campbell, Patterson, &amp; Lichty, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0886260511416476">Littel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0886260511416476">Plichta, Clements, &amp; Houseman, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0886260511416476">Taylor, 2002</xref>), who do not want to or are unable to take the time to properly treat rape victims or testify in court (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0886260511416476">Girardin, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0886260511416476">Ledray &amp; Barry, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0886260511416476">Littel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0886260511416476">Martin &amp; DiNitto, 1987</xref>), and who feel the rape exam is not a procedure that requires their medical expertise (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0886260511416476">Martin, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Furthermore, victims do not always receive proper information or prophylactic treatment for pregnancy, HIV or STDs when treated by doctors and nurses in standard emergency rooms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0886260511416476">Amey &amp; Bishai, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0886260511416476">Bechtel, Ryan, &amp; Gallagher, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0886260511416476">Campbell &amp; Bybee, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0886260511416476">Campbell et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0886260511416476">Monroe et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0886260511416476">Plichta et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0886260511416476">Rovi &amp; Shimoni, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0886260511416476">Stermac, Dunlap, &amp; Bainbridge, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0886260511416476">Woodell, Bowling, Moracco, &amp; Reed, 2007</xref>). In addition to victims’ medical needs not being met, their emotional needs may not be met either, and they may face victim-blaming questions by emergency room doctors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0886260511416476">Girardin, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0886260511416476">Littel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0886260511416476">Taylor, 2002</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0886260511416476">Campbell (2006)</xref> interviewed 81 victims seeking services at two hospitals and found that most (69%) victims from one hospital and 36% from the other hospital said they were treated “impersonally” or “coldly” by emergency room doctors or nurses during the examination (p. 38). In a study that explores reactions of support providers, victims who disclosed the rape to doctors were more likely to report being revictimized compared with victims who disclosed the rape to friends, relatives, or mental health professionals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-0886260511416476">Ullman, 1996</xref>). Clearly, the experience in the emergency room can seem like a second assault (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0886260511416476">Campbell, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0886260511416476">Campbell et al., 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0886260511416476">2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0886260511416476">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0886260511416476">DuMont &amp; Parnis, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0886260511416476">Gregory &amp; Lees, 1994</xref>). Whereas victims may face revictimization by emergency room doctors and nurses, treatment by SANEs can be beneficial to victims for various reasons, which will be discussed later.</p>
<p>In addition to being revictimized by hospital staff, victims may not always have positive interactions with police. Victims report that police discouraged them from filing a formal report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0886260511416476">Campbell, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0886260511416476">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0886260511416476">Campbell &amp; Raja, 2005</xref>). In addition, police who often accept stereotypical images of “real” rape victims determine whether to initiate an investigation or an arrest based on the perception of the alleged victim as someone truly harmed and blameless (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0886260511416476">Edward &amp; Macleod, 1999</xref>). For example, if a weapon was not used during the rape, a victim failed to quickly report the rape, or was raped by an acquaintance, then the police may view her as less credible and not a “real” victim (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0886260511416476">Archambault &amp; Lindsay, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0886260511416476">Estrich, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0886260511416476">LaFree, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0886260511416476">Madigan &amp; Gamble, 1991</xref>). Victims whose experience did not reflect the stereotypical rape (raped by stranger with weapon and sustained injury) are less likely to report or seek help from formal social systems compared with other victims (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0886260511416476">Campbell et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0886260511416476">Patterson et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0886260511416476">Starzynski, Ullman, Filipas, &amp; Townsend, 2005</xref>). This is especially problematic given that most victims know their rapist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0886260511416476">Kilpatrick, Resnick, Ruggiero, Conoscenti, &amp; McCauley, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0886260511416476">Logan, Cole, &amp; Capillo, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Police may cause revictimization of victims of both stranger and acquaintance rape by posing victim-blaming questions. These include but are not limited to questions pertaining to a victim’s attire, the use of alcohol or drugs, degree of resistance, prior sexual encounters with the alleged assailant, and whether she “led on” the alleged assailant. Police may engage in aggressive questioning of the victim because of the demand that probable cause be established before an arrest is made. Victims are also questioned multiple times to make sure their details of the event remain consistent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0886260511416476">Halligan, Michael, Clark, &amp; Ehlers, 2003</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0886260511416476">Martin (2005)</xref> explains that police are required to build a good case, and in doing so they treat the victim as a witness to a crime. Martin states, “Prosecutors pressure law enforcement to be aggressive in obtaining physical evidence and conducting ‘good’ interviews with victims, in short to ‘build a good case,’ and these pressures regularly override concerns with victims’ welfare” (p. 54). Therefore, police officers’ mission to establish a good case may interfere with their ability to treat victims with sensitivity. Police officers may view their behaviors to be “normal” and part of their jobs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0886260511416476">Campbell, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Many victims report to police hoping for justice (identifying and convicting rapist; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0886260511416476">DuMont et al., 2009</xref>). One study conducted in Maryland found that 69% of 125 victims who were interviewed indicated that they would not file charges with the police, and almost half (46%) of those who did file charges expressed dissatisfaction with the police interview (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0886260511416476">Monroe et al., 2005</xref>). Victims’ negative experiences with police result from feeling judged, blamed, or believing that police did not follow-up on leads or evidence to charge assailants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0886260511416476">Ericksen et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-0886260511416476">Ullman, 1996</xref>). Furthermore, victims whose cases are not prosecuted are more likely than victims whose cases are prosecuted to report they experienced revictimization by detectives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0886260511416476">Patterson, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Rape victims often have negative and traumatizing experiences with the legal system as well (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0886260511416476">Frazier &amp; Haney, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0886260511416476">Frohmann, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0886260511416476">Konradi, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0886260511416476">Larcombe, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0886260511416476">Martin &amp; Powell, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0886260511416476">Matoesian, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0886260511416476">Taslitz, 1999</xref>). More specifically, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0886260511416476">Konradi and Burger (2000)</xref> found that more than half (52%) of victims expressed concern about achieving justice through the system, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0886260511416476">Campbell et al. (2001)</xref> found that contact with the legal system was viewed as hurtful by more than half (52%) of rape victims. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0886260511416476">Konradi (2007)</xref> found that some victims delayed reporting to the police because they were afraid of how prosecutors would treat them and how they would handle cross-examination.</p>
<p>Legal practitioners may be responsible for the revictimization of rape victims when they do not file legal charges against assailants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0886260511416476">Campbell et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0886260511416476">Frazier &amp; Haney, 1996</xref>), grant defendants continuances, or reduce charges or sentences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0886260511416476">Konradi, 2007</xref>). Although most rape cases do not make it all the way through the criminal justice system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0886260511416476">Bouffard, 2000</xref>), if a case goes to trial, victims must repeat and relive the rape and defend their character and credibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0886260511416476">Konradi, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0886260511416476">Koss &amp; Achilles, 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0886260511416476">Konradi (2007)</xref> found that victims who were not satisfied with plea agreements felt angry and revictimized. Preparation for the case may also be traumatic. Victims are forced to read police reports multiple times, practice recounting the details of the rape, and be coached on how to dress and act while testifying (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0886260511416476">Konradi, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>While victims may face revictimization by the medical, criminal justice, and legal systems, treatment by SANEs can be emotionally beneficial to victims as they have more time to spend with each victim than do emergency room doctors or nurses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0886260511416476">Girardin, 2005</xref>). Rape victims who receive specialized sexual assault services report feeling more respected, more in control, and more informed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0886260511416476">Ericksen et al., 2002</xref>), receive more sensitive and thorough care (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0886260511416476">Campbell et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0886260511416476">Campbell, Patterson, et al., 2005</xref>), and report that they were permitted to stop or pause the exam if requested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0886260511416476">Campbell, Patterson, Adams, Diegel, &amp; Coats, 2008</xref>). Also, victims who are treated by SANEs face shorter wait times (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0886260511416476">Crandall &amp; Helitzer, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0886260511416476">DiNitto et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0886260511416476">Girardin, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0886260511416476">Littel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0886260511416476">Martin &amp; DiNitto, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0886260511416476">Stermac &amp; Stirpe, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0886260511416476">Taylor, 2002</xref>). While the literature notes how SANE programs benefit victims, the extent to which victims treated in hospitals with SANE programs still interact with emergency department doctors and nurses varies.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0886260511416476">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>SANE programs are not only beneficial to victims but also beneficial to emergency department doctors, police, and prosecutors. SANEs take responsibility off busy emergency department doctors to conduct lengthy rape examinations (Townsend &amp; Campbell, 2009). Police officers and prosecutors benefit from SANE programs because better evidence is collected by SANEs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0886260511416476">Campbell, Patterson, Bybee, &amp; Dworkin, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0886260511416476">Ledray &amp; Simmelink, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0886260511416476">Littel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0886260511416476">Pennington, Zwemer, &amp; Krebs, 2010</xref>), which assists in investigation and prosecution. Specifically, evidence collection kits collected by SANEs rather than non-SANE nurses and doctors are more accurate, complete, and detailed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0886260511416476">Ledray &amp; Simmelink, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0886260511416476">Sievers, Murphy, &amp; Miller, 2003</xref>). Therefore, charges are more likely to be filed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0886260511416476">Nugent-Borakove et al., 2006</xref>), defendants are more likely to plea bargain once they realize the detail of the forensic evidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0886260511416476">Littel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0886260511416476">Speck &amp; Aiken, 1995</xref>), and convictions are more likely due to evidence collected by SANEs and expert testimony provided by them during trial (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0886260511416476">McGregor, DuMont, &amp; Myhr, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0886260511416476">Nugent-Borakove et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0886260511416476">O’Brien, 1996</xref> as cited by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0886260511416476">Ledray, 1999</xref>). For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0886260511416476">Crandall and Helitzer (2003)</xref> compared prosecutorial outcomes of rape cases before and after a SANE program was implemented in New Mexico. Their findings indicate that after the SANE program began, more victims reported rape and sexual assault to police, more victims had forensic evidence collected, more charges were filed against alleged rapists, and more rapists were convicted. Successful investigations and prosecutions clearly benefit victims; their rapists are punished and victims may feel justice has been served.</p>
<p>Despite research on the revictimization of rape victims by the medical, criminal justice, and legal systems, the benefits of SANE programs to victims, doctors, police, and prosecutors, and the unique position that SANEs are in to witness victims’ treatment by emergency department doctors, police officers, <italic>and</italic> prosecutors, to the author’s knowledge there is no research on SANEs’ <italic>perceptions</italic> of the revictimization of rape victims. This article is an attempt to fill this gap in the literature. Accordingly, the present study explores perceptions of 40 SANEs working in four states.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0886260511416476" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section3-0886260511416476">
<title>Recruitment of Participants</title>
<p>From October 2006 to February 2007, 76 letters or e-mails of inquiry were sent to directors/coordinators of SANE programs in four east coast states, which will remain confidential and referred to as States A, B, C, and D. The letters of inquiry explained the purpose of the research and requested access to interview SANEs affiliated with the program. SANE programs were selected after review of the programs listed in the database of the Sexual Assault Resource Service, funded by the U.S. Department of Justice’s Office for Victims of Crime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-0886260511416476">U.S. Department of Justice, Office for Victims of Crime, 2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-0886260511416476">2004b</xref>) and the U.S. Department of Commerce’s National Telecommunications and Information Administration (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sane-sart.com">www.sane-sart.com</ext-link>). The four states were selected because in 2003 and 2004, the author interviewed rape victim advocates from the four states.</p>
<p>All directors who responded to the e-mail stated that they forwarded the letter or e-mail to other SANEs, announced the research and provided the researcher’s contact information at staff meetings or trainings, or passed along the information through word of mouth. Because of the method of recruitment used, the author is unable to determine a response rate. However, only one SANE initially agreed to the interview but later said she was unable to participate because her employer (county prosecutor) would “not allow” her to participate. In addition, one other SANE could not be reached after agreeing to participate.</p>
<p>All SANEs who were interviewed were required to have experience treating victims in the hospital setting so that data on their perceptions of the treatment of rape victims by police, hospital staff, and rape victim advocates could be gathered. Interviews were conducted with SANEs working for hospitals, government agencies, or for prosecutors’ offices in four states on the East Coast. These states had between three and 45 SANE programs. In States A and D, all programs were hospital-based, in State C SANE programs were run out of the Prosecutor’s office, and in State B programs were run out of a state agency.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0886260511416476">
<title>Description of Sample</title>
<p>Of the 40 SANEs, 17 also currently served as directors of the programs and one had served as the director but resigned from the position prior to the interview. Four directors were from State A, two were from State B, five were from State C, and six were from State D. The one director who resigned from State D continued to work as a SANE in the state. Of the total sample of 40 SANEs, five worked in State A, seven in State B, 15 in State C, and 13 in State D. Refer to <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0886260511416476">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0886260511416476" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Description of Sample</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0886260511416476" xlink:href="10.1177_0886260511416476-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">State A</th>
<th align="center">State B</th>
<th align="center">State C</th>
<th align="center">State D</th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Hospital-Based</th>
<th align="center">Programs Run by State Agency</th>
<th align="center">Programs Run by Prosecutor’s Office</th>
<th align="center">Hospital-Based</th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Directors</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>2</td>
<td> 5</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SANEs not in director positions</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The 40 SANEs interviewed were between the ages of 21 and 62 (mean 45 years old, median 46.5 years old). All were women. Five percent of respondents were in their 20s at the time of the interview, 22.5% were in their 30s, 37.5% were in their 40s, 32.5% were in their 50s, and 2.5% were in their 60s. Thirty-eight (95%) of the SANEs interviewed were White, and 2 (5%) were African American.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0886260511416476">2</xref></sup> Thirty-two (80%) of the SANEs interviewed were registered nurses (RN), 1 (2.5%) was a nurse practitioner, and 7 (17.5%) were not RNs because they had a bachelor’s degree in nursing (BSN). Twenty-four SANEs (60%) were employed part-time for the SANE program, and 16 (40%) were employed full-time. SANEs included in this sample received their nursing degrees between 1971 and 2005. Almost one quarter (22.5%) completed their nursing degrees in the 1970s, 32.5% completed their nursing degrees in the 1980s, 37.5% completed their nursing degrees in the 1990s, and 7.5% completed their nursing degrees between 2000 and 2005.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0886260511416476">
<title>Observation of Training and Interviews</title>
<p>In addition to conducting interviews, the author observed 30 of 40 hr of training for SANEs. The training was held in one of the states where interviews were conducted and was facilitated by one of the directors of a SANE program included in this research. These observations allowed the author to gain firsthand knowledge of the topics covered during training. This experience was quite beneficial as the author does not have a degree in nursing or nursing experience. The training took place between April 10, 2007 and May 2, 2007. Topics included the history of forensic nursing, the importance of the Sexual Assault Response Team model, the role of the advocate, the components of the evidence-collection kit, DNA, legal issues of rape and sexual assault, how to best question victims, rape myths, victims with special needs, diversity, how the police investigate the crime and collect evidence, anatomy, and forensic photography. In addition to the primary trainer who was a SANE, guest speakers were brought in from a rape crisis center, the special victims’ unit of a police department, and the prosecutor’s office. The author attended five of the eight sessions including a tour of the city crime lab; three of the sessions were not relevant to the purposes of her research (explanation of anatomy, how to use a colposcope, how to take digital photographs, tour of emergency room, review session for certification exam). While this training was also relevant to the larger study, the coverage of rape myths, how to best question victims, and how the police investigate the crime were helpful topics since they can all be sources of revictimization. In addition, since SANEs included in this sample later revealed how police and prosecutors can be sources of revictimization, it was helpful to have observed during the training sessions when representatives from the special victims’ unit of a police department and the prosecutor’s office spoke because this gave the author a better understanding of their roles and objectives.</p>
<p>Interviews were conducted between October 13, 2006 and April 20, 2007. Interviews ranged from 45 min to 1 hr and 45 min. The average interview lasted 1 hr and 15 min. All interviews were conducted over the phone for convenience—either to accommodate the SANEs’ preference or due to distance. All participants were required to sign a consent form prior to the interview. Most interviews were tape-recorded on the participant’s consent. Only one respondent declined to be tape-recorded so extensive notes were taken during the interview. Participants were compensated with gift cards to an establishment local to them (i.e., Starbucks, Panera). All SANEs were given US$10 gift cards as a token of appreciation for their time, and SANEs who were also serving as directors of programs were given US$15 gift cards because they were asked additional questions about the organization and funding of programs.</p>
<p>While 40 SANEs were interviewed, results in this article will be based on the responses of 39 SANEs because one micro cassette broke during the transcription of the interview. Although the participant’s responses for most questions were transcribed, questions pertaining to revictimization were not. This participant worked as a SANE in State C and had resigned as a director of a program in that state 4 months prior to the interview.</p>
<p>Although this article will focus on SANEs’ perceptions of the revictimization of rape victims by the police, legal system, and medical system, the interview consisted of approximately 70 open-ended questions.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0886260511416476">3</xref></sup> The key questions about SANEs’ perceptions of the revictimization of rape victims were: When I use the term <italic>secondary victimization</italic> or <italic>revictimization</italic>, what do you think of? What/who is most responsible for revictimizing rape victims? Are you ever able to minimize the impact of revictimization of rape victims? If so, how? How have SANE programs improved treatment of rape victims?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0886260511416476">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>Because of the nature of the research, a qualitative methodology is necessary to fully assess the perceptions and experiences of study participants and explore their perceptions and experiences in greater depth. Qualitative analysis is more appropriate for exploratory research when it is most important to grasp the meanings and nuances of an area of study. Qualitative research allows participants to articulate more clearly and in their own terms, potentially providing more accurate and valid information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0886260511416476">Flavin, 2001</xref>, p. 40).</p>
<p>After all interviews were transcribed verbatim by the author and five undergraduate research assistants, core themes were identified based on multiple readings of the interview data (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0886260511416476">Rubin &amp; Rubin, 1995</xref>). This analysis included several steps including open coding and axial coding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0886260511416476">Miles &amp; Huberman, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0886260511416476">Strauss &amp; Corbin, 1990</xref>). After reading through the transcripts several times, notes were written in margins. More specifically, during this stage of open coding the author read the transcripts numerous times to develop descriptive codes that did not require much interpretation. At this time, the codes focused on who was being named as a source of revictimization or if the SANE believed she had the ability to reduce revictimization. These initial codes allowed the author to better manage the data. Following the initial review of complete transcripts, the author focused on questions asked specifically pertaining to revictimization. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0886260511416476">Miles and Huberman (1994)</xref> stress the benefits of a clear display of data, the author copied and pasted all data pertaining to revictimization into one document. Codes were rewritten in the margins and at this time, the author also used different colors to highlight text. Codes were also further developed at this time. For example, instead of just including the source of revictimization, the author also included how they revictimize rape victims. For example, if a SANE was describing how victims face revictimization when they are forced to wait for medical attention, this section of the transcript was coded as MED-WAIT.</p>
<p>To systematically analyze the data and compare the responses of SANEs from various programs, the second stage of the analysis was completed using axial coding. At this stage, the author attempted to make connections within the data. To better enable a systematic review of the data, all responses about causes of revictimization and methods to reduce it were copied into a table that also listed the state where the respondent work and her length of experience. This allowed the author to more easily recognize similarities and differences in data gleaned from interviews with SANEs.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0886260511416476">
<title>Findings</title>
<p>SANEs described police, medical systems, and legal system as wielding power to revictimize rape victims. In fact, SANEs felt that rape victims were particularly traumatized when members of such systems engaged in victim-blaming behavior or questioning, did not believe them, pressured them to recount the events multiple times to multiple people, failed to give them adequate information, or refused them help or treatment. When specifically asked about sources of revictimization, 30 SANEs (77%) stated that the police, medical system, legal system, or a combination of two or three were a source of revictimization. Of the remaining nine SANEs, four referred to friends and family, three were unable to respond, and two referred to the general public or society being a source of revictimization. Refer to <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0886260511416476">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0886260511416476" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Source of Revictimization</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0886260511416476" xlink:href="10.1177_0886260511416476-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Police</th>
<th align="center">Medical System</th>
<th align="center">Legal System</th>
<th align="center">Family, Friends, or General Public</th>
<th align="center">Unable to Respond</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>21 (54%)</td>
<td>10 (26%)</td>
<td>8 (20.5%)</td>
<td>6 (15%)</td>
<td>3 (8%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>While most SANEs cited the police, medical system, and legal system as a source of revictimization, it is important to explore which of the three was more likely to be viewed by SANEs as a source of revictimization. Specifically, 21 SANEs (54%) cited the police as a source of revictimization, 10 SANEs (26%) cited the medical system as a source of revictimization, and 8 SANEs (20.5%) cited the legal system as a source of revictimization. SANEs could have discussed more than one source of revictimization, so the total exceeds 100%.</p>
<p>Neither does one’s tenure as a SANE nor does one’s age seem to determine who or what will be named as the primary source of revictimization. The state where the SANE was employed did seem to influence the source of revictimization cited. Of the SANEs from State A, three (60%) cited the police as a source of revictimization. SANEs from State B were almost equally likely to cite the police, legal system, and medical system as sources of revictimization. Of the SANEs from State C, 38% cited the police as a source of revictimization, 21% cited the medical system, 21% cited friends or family, 14% cited the legal system, and 14% cited society in general. Of the SANEs from State D, most (69%) cited the police as a source of revictimization. Only 31% cited the medical system, 31% cited friends or family, 8% cited the legal system, and 8% could not answer the question. Again, it is important to note that SANEs could have mentioned more than one source of revictimization, so totals will exceed 100%. Based on these data, it seems that while SANEs were more likely to cite the police as a source of revictimization (54% of total sample), SANEs from States A, C, and D saw the police as particularly revictimizing. In those states, programs are run by hospitals (States A and D) or the prosecutor’s office (State C) rather than by a state agency (State B).</p>
<sec id="section8-0886260511416476">
<title>SANEs’ Perceptions of Revictimization by Police</title>
<p>According to 21 SANEs, rape victims may experience revictimization by police through officers’ invasive questioning, victim-blaming attitudes, doubting victims’ accounts of the incident, general insensitivity, and refusal to proceed with criminal investigations. SANEs indicated that at times police officers intimidate victims during the interview process. As explained by Elizabeth (all names pseudonyms), who has been a SANE for 6 years in State A: “I think when they [the police] use interview tactics it’s more of an interrogation and that’s a big difference. Interviews and interrogations are totally different and I think that police approach the survivor the wrong way.” Donna, who has been a SANE for 8 years in State A, shares a similar sentiment: “Patients have voiced an issue to me about law enforcement [revictimizing them]. The victims don’t like the way they are treated, how they are talked to, and ultimately they feel they are made out to be a criminal.” Although their goal is to get as much information as possible, police may lack sensitivity. Catherine, who has been a SANE for 3 years in State B, comments,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>They [the police] will try to push for that interview. In order to do the right thing they might be a little bit aggressive. Sometimes in their quest to do right they are not sensitive to what the victim is going through emotionally or physically.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Mary, who has been a SANE for 5 years in State B, explains,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Police weren’t really educated regarding victims of sexual assault. They are used to dealing with criminals—people who lie on a regular basis. When the police were called they were not very compassionate. So there again they [victims] are revictimized.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Lia, who has been a SANE for 1 year in State D, describes the police as “not very gentle.” Teresa, who has been a SANE for 7 years in State D, agrees,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>They [the police] are not overly compassionate in interviewing. A lot of the officers I have talked to have the attitude that most of the sexual assaults did not occur. They think the victim is lying for one reason or another and they think it is their job to get the truth out of them.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Clearly, SANEs believe that police officers’ lack of sensitivity may cause victims to feel revictimized. It is possible that in the process of trying to build a strong case, they overlook the importance of treating victims with sensitivity.</p>
<p>In addition, according to SANEs, police may also blame or question victims during the interview, which contributes to revictimization. Catherine reflects, “Sometimes in the interview process police will say, ‘What were you doing there?’ or ‘Why were you doing this?’ So that tends to make victims place blame on themselves sometimes.”</p>
<p>Several of the 21 SANEs who believed that the police were the primary source of revictimization noted that the interview itself may be traumatizing to victims. Police are required to get as much detail as possible about the incident to proceed with the investigation. This obviously requires asking victims to recall a very painful event in as much detail as possible.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0886260511416476">
<title>SANEs’ Perceptions of Revictimization by the Legal System</title>
<p>Eight SANEs identified the legal system as a source of revictimization. Of these eight SANEs, three have been prepared to testify and met with prosecutors several times but did not have to testify because the defendant plea-bargained at the last minute. One has testified 5 times, one has testified more than 50 times as a fact witness and more than 25 times as an expert witness, one could not remember the exact number of times she has been called to testify but indicated she has testified “multiple” times, and two SANEs have testified 1 time. In addition, of these eight SANEs, four received specialized training by prosecutors during their initial training and four received specialized training by prosecutors and observed a mock trial during their training. It is evident that the eight SANEs who identified the legal system as a source of revictimization had ample experience to reflect on.</p>
<p>According to eight SANEs, rape victims may experience revictimization by the legal system because many cases do not make it to trial, many cases are postponed numerous times, victims’ credibility is questioned throughout the pretrial and trial proceedings, and the focus may seem to be on the rights of criminals rather than on the rights of victims. SANEs stated that victims become angry and frustrated when cases are postponed numerous times or do not go to trial, and because of the specific reasons prosecutors do not take cases to trial. According to Debra (State A), many times attorneys will not proceed with the case if alcohol is involved. This is consistent with other research that indicates that victims’ alcohol use significantly decreases the chances of prosecution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0886260511416476">Campbell et al., 2009</xref>). Even if prosecutors have reasons for not continuing with a case, SANEs believe this is defeating and frustrating to victims. Sandra, who has been a SANE in State A for 8 years, explains, “Sometimes if there is not enough evidence for the case to proceed forward then the victim becomes infuriated with the whole system.”</p>
<p>In addition, victims may not be satisfied with plea agreements. Krista (State D) notes that this causes revictimization, “[Victims ask] ‘What do you mean that is all he is going to get?’” Continuances are also frustrating to victims. Kim, a SANE in State B for 7 years, states,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Patients have reported to me that the legal system is their biggest frustration. I think the women who choose to go forward find frustration with the fact that there is a process and it is not something that happens immediately.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Debra, a SANE in State A for 9 years, agrees: “The legal system is horrific. [This county] is famous for our cases being continued up to 20 or more times, which can cause hardships for the victim as far as their job, transportation, and childcare is concerned.”</p>
<p>Even if the case goes to trial, SANEs believe that testifying may cause revictimization. Victims’ credibility, past sexual history, and behavior immediately prior to and during the rape may be questioned. Jane, a SANE in State B for 2.5 years, states,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>If it [the case] goes to court, they [defense attorneys] are not supposed to bring out the past sexual history but a woman cannot just get on the stand and say, “this man raped me” without being put through a battery of questions. A lot of women are probably afraid to testify because they are going to be slammed on the stand. Anything they have done prior in life is going to be judged.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Gloria, a SANE in State C for 11 years, comments, “The legal system is paying lip service to recognizing the needs of victims. It is designed to provide justice for criminals.”</p>
<p>Denise, a SANE in State B for 7 years, agrees, “Defendants have more rights [than victims].”</p>
<p>While SANEs were less likely to cite legal system than police as the primary source of revictimization, data reveal that they have very negative perceptions of the legal system and believe that pretrial and trial proceedings may be traumatizing, distressing, or frustrating to victims.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0886260511416476">
<title>SANEs’ Perceptions of Revictimization by the Medical System</title>
<p>Ten SANEs cited the medical system as the primary source of revictimization. According to SANEs, one source of revictimization is the long wait for medical attention. Phyllis, who has been a SANE for 3 years in State C, explains that forcing victims to wait long periods of time in the emergency room is revictimizing. Eliza who has been a SANE for 6 years in State C agrees:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>They can be revictimized through medical care. I guess I’m talking about when SANEs aren’t involved. I think there is a lot of victimization that occurs in emergency departments because of the way the whole system is. They have to sit and wait if it is not an emergency.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Krista, who has been a SANE for 6 years in State D, agrees that the amount of time a victim waits for medical attention can be revictimizing:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>The biggest concern brought to my attention by victims after the fact for the medical system is if I have a nurse who is on-call and they have to wait an hour and a half that is revictimization. The exam is long so you are tacking on time.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Mary, who has been a SANE for 5 years in State C, refers to the treatment of victims prior to the implementation of the SANE program: “Before we had our program the victims wouldn’t be seen in the ER for hours on end, and they would probably sit in the waiting room for 6-8 hours before they were even seen.”</p>
<p>Other SANEs indicated that although the exam is essential, it can be revictimizing regardless of the skill and compassion of the SANE. What must be completed to gather necessary evidence is very invasive.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0886260511416476">
<title>SANEs’ Perceptions of Their Ability to Reduce Revictimization and Improve the Treatment of Victims</title>
<p>As SANEs are in a unique position to witness the possible revictimization of rape victims by emergency department doctors, police officers, and prosecutors, they were asked if they feel they are able to reduce the impact of revictimization on rape victims. Most SANEs (54%) believed they have this ability. Only four SANEs (10%) said they either could not reduce the impact of revictimization or have not had the opportunity yet. Fourteen SANEs (36%) did not know if they had the ability to reduce revictimization, so did not respond to this question.</p>
<p>The SANEs who believed they could reduce the impact of revictimization provided a variety of strategies including providing thorough and quick medical attention, allowing victims to pause the exam, telling them that the rape is not their fault, educating them on the legal and medical systems, not acting judgmental, asking the victim to consent to each component of the exam, interviewing with police to reduce the number of times the victim must provide the details of the rape, testifying in trials, and intervening on victims’ behalf when necessary. Five SANEs specifically stated they have had to intervene on victims’ behalf when family members or police treated them poorly. Catherine, a SANE in State C who believes that both emergency department doctors and police can revictimize rape victims, explains,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I think certainly when I notice anything happen I’ll take that person aside confidentially and say, “You know that’s not the focus of this program. We try not to judge, or make comments to the victim about anything.” I would just try to educate them about what we should be providing for the victim.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Teresa, a SANE in State D who believes the police are the primary source of revictimization, has confronted officers:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>While they are here yes [we minimize the impact of revictimization] because if we feel an officer is getting out of line we remove them from the room and let them know that they are out of line and if we still don’t see eye-to-eye we ask them to leave. It has happened a couple of times.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Four SANEs stressed the importance of interviewing victims <italic>with</italic> police to reduce repetition. Three SANEs believe it is important to educate victims about the medical and legal systems. Gloria, a SANE in State C who believes the legal system is the primary source of revictimization as is reflected in her response, states,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I think one of the things we strive to do [to reduce revictimization] is to educate the victim about how the system works. We make sure that the victim is very clear that the system is not designed to benefit them per say. The system is designed to protect the rights of the accused.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Two SANEs believe they reduce revictimization by telling victims they are not to blame, and two SANEs testify for victims or tell police officers when they find evidence. Betty Ann, a SANE in State C who believes the legal system is the primary source of revictimization, feels good reducing revictimization during trials by testifying as follows:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>By putting the nurses on the stand that is the end of it. They know their role so well that the victim doesn’t have to get on the stand and testify. The prosecutors share with the defense attorneys that we know what we’re doing and not to mess with us. The presence of the nurses in the courtroom makes a big impact on the victim and the family.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>One SANE stressed the importance of asking victims’ permission during exams, and one SANE tries not to ever act judgmental toward victims. Based on data, it is clear that SANEs have developed a variety of strategies to attempt to reduce revictimization. Some strategies are more directed at victims (i.e., educating victims, telling victims they are not to blame), whereas other strategies are more directed at others who may be a source of revictimization (i.e., intervening on victims’ behalf).</p>
<p>While previous literature details the benefits of SANE programs, SANEs were specifically asked, “How have SANE programs improved treatment of rape victims?” SANEs revealed that they believe they have improved treatment of rape victims in the following ways: shorter wait times for medical attention, one-on-one care, more sensitive treatment, collection of better and more thorough evidence, ability to return power and control to victims, and provision of reliable court testimony.</p>
<p>Sixteen SANEs (41%) specifically discussed that victims do not have to wait as long for medical attention in emergency departments since the implementation of SANE programs. Prior to SANE programs, victims simply waited with everyone else needing emergency medical attention, and as they usually were not bleeding or did not sustain life-threatening injuries, other patients were treated first. Louise describes the experience for victims prior to SANE programs: “They [rape victims] were never a priority. They were always sitting there. In an emergency or triage when you have people that can’t breathe or are bleeding, the rape victim sits.” Judith agrees, “[Prior to SANE programs] they [rape victims] would wait in the waiting room and they would be the last to be seen because they were not hurt. They would wait and sometimes they would leave . . .”</p>
<p>Donna agrees that victims used to “wait hours” before being seen by a doctor. With the implementation of SANE programs, victims are quickly taken back to an examining room. In addition, even if the SANE is not immediately available, victims are afforded more privacy than in a common waiting area.</p>
<p>Eleven SANEs (28%) reflected that the treatment of rape victims has improved now that SANEs are able to focus only on victims and provide them with one-on-one care. SANEs stay with victims until they leave the hospital. They are not leaving the room to treat other patients, as was the case when regular emergency department doctors or nurses treated victims. Marissa explains the difference between treatment by SANEs to treatment by emergency department doctors and nurses:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I think we have helped the victim because you have one nurse who is dedicated to you. If it takes four hours or eight hours that nurse is not going to leave your side. Before the SANE program, you had an ER nurse who was taking care of four or five patients and running in and out of the room not really able to deal with your emotional needs. The physician was doing the exam and he had other patients to see. It was, “OK we are going to pull this hair and it is nice to meet you.”</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Given that SANEs are able to spend more time with victims, it is not surprising that six SANEs mentioned that victims receive more sensitive care than they did prior to the implementation of programs. SANEs also mentioned they improve victims’ treatment by attempting to give them back control and by collecting better evidence than non-SANEs.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0886260511416476" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Even with the presence of SANEs, most (77%) SANEs still believe police, the medical system, or the legal system revictimize rape victims. Although not in the purview of this current research, it is quite possible that victims’ treatment by police, prosecutors, and medical personnel has improved because of SANEs’ presence. Given that possibility, the number of SANEs who believe revictimization still occurs is high.</p>
<p>Research presented here parallels previous research that has indicated the criminal justice, legal, and medical systems are sources of revictimization of rape victims. Police contribute to victims’ distress through failure to ask questions in a sensitive manner, through failure to proceed with investigations if victims do not fit the profile of a “real” victim, and by asking victim-blaming questions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0886260511416476">Campbell, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0886260511416476">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0886260511416476">Edward &amp; Macleod, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0886260511416476">Estrich, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0886260511416476">Madigan &amp; Gamble, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0886260511416476">Maier, 2008</xref>). SANEs included in this research agreed that police officers’ questions are influenced by their views of stereotypical victims, and their interview style may be intimidating, aggressive, and insensitive. Police may also make victims feel as if the rape was their fault and that they do not believe them.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the findings from this current study are supported by research that has found that victims often have negative and traumatizing experiences with the legal system when charges are never filed, plea bargains are unsatisfactory, and they are forced to relive the details of the rape and defend their character and credibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0886260511416476">Campbell et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0886260511416476">Frazier &amp; Haney, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0886260511416476">Frohmann, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0886260511416476">Konradi, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0886260511416476">Konradi &amp; Burger, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0886260511416476">Koss &amp; Achilles, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0886260511416476">Larcombe, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0886260511416476">Martin &amp; Powell, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0886260511416476">Matoesian, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0886260511416476">Taslitz, 1999</xref>). According to SANEs included in this research, rape victims may experience revictimization by the legal system when cases are postponed, dropped, or plea bargained and victims’ credibility is questioned.</p>
<p>Last, as found in previous research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0886260511416476">Crandall &amp; Helitzer, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0886260511416476">Girardin, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0886260511416476">Littel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0886260511416476">Stermac &amp; Stirpe, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0886260511416476">Taylor, 2002</xref>), this research concludes that SANEs believe victims can be revictimized by the medical system when they are forced to wait many hours for medical attention. However, unlike previous research that concludes that revictimization is caused by improperly trained or rushed emergency department doctors and nurses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0886260511416476">Campbell, Patterson, et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0886260511416476">Girardin, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0886260511416476">Plichta et al., 2007</xref>), failure to provide victims with proper information or prophylactic treatment for pregnancy, HIV, or STDs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0886260511416476">Bechtel et al., 2008</xref>), or victim-blaming questions posed by doctors or nurses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0886260511416476">Campbell, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0886260511416476">Girardin, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0886260511416476">Littel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0886260511416476">Taylor, 2002</xref>), SANEs did not mention any of these as causes for revictimization.</p>
<p>While this research contributes to the literature by including the previously unheard perceptions of SANEs, it has a few limitations. First, although it provides an important perspective from individuals essential to the proper treatment of victims, their perceptions of victims’ treatment by police, the medical system, and the legal system, and their perceptions of how they reduce revictimization and improve victims’ treatment may not match victims’ perceptions or experiences. Although it has been acknowledged that recruitment of rape victims for research is challenging (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0886260511416476">DuMont et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0886260511416476">Gregory &amp; Lees, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0886260511416476">Parnis, DuMont, &amp; Gombay, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0886260511416476">Temkin, 1996</xref>), future research should include <italic>both</italic> SANEs <italic>and</italic> the victims whom they assist. Second, it is possible that victims are receiving better treatment by the police, legal system, and doctors due to the presence of the SANE. It is impossible to determine by this research if victims’ treatment improves because of SANEs’ presence. Third, as most SANEs see doctors, law enforcement, and prosecutors as other members of the team who treat victims, they may not recognize when others act in ways that could revictimize victims, or they may be unwilling to reveal the negative behavior of the other members of the team because of fear of jeopardizing collaboration. Last, generalizability is limited. It is impossible to determine if these findings would have differed if interviews had been conducted with SANEs from other states or even other SANEs working in the same states. It is possible that SANEs interviewed do not share the experiences of those who chose not to participate in the research or were unaware that the recruitment for research was taking place.</p>
<p>Despite these limitations, it is important that we understand multiple perspectives of treatment of victims by the criminal justice, legal, and medical system. Thus, this research contributes to this area of study as it includes the often unheard perspective of SANEs. This current study provides a different perspective of victims’ possible revictimization by interviewing SANEs who witness the treatment of victims not only by the medical system but also by the criminal justice and legal systems. SANEs may provide a more accurate assessment of the revictimization of victims by the criminal justice, legal, and medical systems as they are not experiencing the same emotional trauma as victims that may make them reluctant to speak to researchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0886260511416476">Campbell, 1998</xref>). This current research provides a more complete picture because SANEs were asked to reflect on experiences working with multiple victims. It also provides SANEs’ perceptions of how they believe they are able to reduce revictimization and improve victims’ treatment. Although previous research has detailed the benefits of SANE programs, there is a lack of research exploring SANEs’ perceptions of how they are helping victims.</p>
<p>While research has indicated that victims’ treatment has improved as a result of SANE programs, even with the presence of SANEs, most SANEs included in this research continue to witness revictimization by the medical, criminal justice, and legal systems. Therefore, based on this research, it seems that SANE programs are not the complete solution to ending or even reducing the revictimization of rape victims. Efforts to reduce revictimization must increase, or at least continue.</p>
<p>This research offers several recommendations to reduce revictimization of rape victims. First, sensitivity training for police is imperative. Although SANEs may view police as lacking sensitivity, it is important to recognize <italic>why</italic> police may treat victims as they do. Police are trained to question victims in a way that obtains the most evidence and clearest testimony, possibly sacrificing victims’ need for sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0886260511416476">Martin, 2005</xref>) and they may not realize that they are acting in a way that further traumatizes victims (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0886260511416476">Campbell, 2005</xref>). Police must strive to find ways to balance building a good case through direct and invasive questioning while considering the feelings of the victim. Explaining to victims why certain questions must be asked and refraining from questions not required to build a strong criminal case may reduce revictimization. Training may reduce police misperceptions about rape victims (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0886260511416476">Martin, 2005</xref>). This, as well as debriefing with SANEs who witness their interaction with victims, may be helpful.</p>
<p>To reduce revictimization by the legal system, victims should be prepared by prosecutors for the likelihood that the case may not make it to trial, may be postponed, or the defendant may accept a plea bargain. Prosecutors should explain to victims why they drop charges or offer plea bargains. Victims should also be prepared to testify and should be prepared that their credibility may be questioned. While these efforts may certainly not alleviate revictimization, they may reduce it (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0886260511416476">Konradi, 2007</xref>). Last, efforts to reduce the wait time for victims in emergency department should continue. Hospitals should also consider separate waiting rooms for rape victims waiting for medical attention.</p>
<p>In sum, future directives need to continue to improve the treatment of rape victims, which may not be an easy task. As this research gives voice to the responsibility felt by SANEs to reduce the revictimization of victims and examines, <italic>how</italic> they restore victims’ sense of power, and how they believe SANE programs have improved victims’ treatment, other SANEs can use the strategies offered by the SANEs included in this research to reduce revictimization. Specifically, SANEs may want to allow victims to pause the exam, tell them that the rape is not their fault, educate them on the legal and medical systems, not act judgmental, ask the victim to consent to each component of the exam, interview with police to reduce the number of times the victim must provide the details of the rape, and intervene on victims’ behalf if they do not do so already.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The author would like to thank all of the directors and coordinators of SANE programs who helped her gain access to their SANEs. Also, this project would not have been possible without the SANEs who allowed the author to interview them.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The author disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This research was funded by a Provost’s Grant and Faculty Development Grant from Widener University.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0886260511416476">
<label>1.</label>
<p>For example, some programs may require some victim assessment or treatment by doctors or nurses, whereas other programs may give SANEs complete responsibility for victim treatment and assessment. Also, victims’ interactions with medical professionals other than SANEs (doctors, nurses, lab technicians, radiologists) may vary depending on the extent of serious injuries. Although research has noted the benefits of SANE programs to victims, it is important to recognize the possibility that victims of rape continue to be revictimized by doctors and nurses even in hospitals with SANE programs (as indicated by this current research).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0886260511416476">
<label>2.</label>
<p>This sample only has two SANEs of color. This is most likely due to the fact that nurses from minority groups are underrepresented in general health care (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0886260511416476">Ahmann, 2002</xref>), and most SANEs are White (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0886260511416476">Campbell, 2005</xref>; Patterson, Campbell, &amp; Townsend, 2006).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0886260511416476">
<label>3.</label>
<p>Additional interview questions focused on the following areas: training and roles of SANEs, perceptions of rape, rape victims, rapists, multicultural or multiethnic issues surrounding rape, and difficulties or challenges for SANEs or SANE programs. Directors of programs were also asked about the history of their SANE program, the past and present mission of the program, how the program has changed, and how the program is funded.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ahmann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Developing cultural competence in health care settings</article-title>. <source>Pediatric Nursing</source>, <volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>133</fpage>-<lpage>137</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Amey</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bishai</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Measuring the quality of medical care for women who experience sexual assault with data from the National Hospital Ambulatory Medical Care Survey</article-title>. <source>Annals of Emergency Medicine</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>631</fpage>-<lpage>638</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Antognoli-Toland</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Comprehensive program for examination of sexual assault victims by nurses: A hospital-based project in Texas</article-title>. <source>Journal of Emergency Nursing</source>, <volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>132</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Archambault</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Responding to non-stranger sexual assault</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Reuland</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Solving Crime and Disorder Problems: Current Issues, Police Strategies, and Organizational Tactics</source> (pp. <fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>42</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>linPolice Executive Research Forum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bechtel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Impact of Sexual Assault Nurse Examiners on the evaluation of sexual assault in a pediatric emergency department</article-title>. <source>Pediatric Emergency Care</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>442</fpage>-<lpage>447</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bouffard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Predicting type of sexual assault case closure from victim, suspect and case characteristics</article-title>. <source>Journal of Criminal Justice</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>527</fpage>-<lpage>542</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Forensic nursing in the emergency department</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Riviello</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Manual of Forensic Emergency Medicine: A Guide for Clinicians</source> (pp. <fpage>4</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Sudbury, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jones &amp; Bartlett</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>, <month>November</month>). <article-title>The psychological impact of rape victims’ experiences with the legal, medical, and mental health systems</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>813</fpage>-<lpage>828</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Rape survivors’ experiences with the legal and medical systems: Do rape victim advocates make a difference?</article-title> <source>Violence Against Women</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>30</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>What really happened? A validation study of rape survivors’ help-seeking experiences with the legal and medical systems</article-title>. <source>Violence &amp; Victims</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>, <month>November</month>). <source>The effectiveness of Sexual Assault Nurse Examiner programs</source>. <publisher-loc>Harrisburg, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>VAWnet, a National Resource Center on Domestic Violence/Pennsylvania Coalition Against Domestic Violence</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vawnet.org">http://www.vawnet.org</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The community response to rape: Victims’ experiences with the legal, medical, and mental health systems</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Community Psychology</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>379</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bybee</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dworkin</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Predicting sexual assault prosecution outcomes: The role of medical forensic evidence collected by Sexual Assault Nurse Examiners</article-title>. <source>Criminal Justice and Behavior</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>712</fpage>-<lpage>727</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diegel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coats</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A participatory evaluation project to measure SANE nursing practice and adult sexual assault patients’ psychological well-being</article-title>. <source>Journal of Forensic Nursing</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kinnison</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pulley</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adames</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wasco</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Responding to sexual assault victims’ medical and emotional needs: A national study of the services provided by SANE programs</article-title>. <source>Research in Nursing &amp; Health</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>384</fpage>-<lpage>398</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The sexual assault and secondary victimization of female veterans: Help-seeking experiences in military and civilian social systems</article-title>. <source>Psychology of Women Quarterly</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>97</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kinnison</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pulley</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adames</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wasco</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Organizational characteristics of sexual assault nurse examiner programs: Results from the national survey of SANE programs</article-title>. <source>Journal of Forensic Nursing</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bybee</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Emergency medical services for sexual assault victims: Detecting the cracks in service delivery</article-title>. <source>Women’s Health: Research on Gender, Behavior, and Policy</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>-<lpage>101</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lichty</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The effectiveness of Sexual Assault Nurse Examiner (SANE) programs</article-title>. <source>Trauma, Violence, &amp; Abuse</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>313</fpage>-<lpage>329</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wasco</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahrens</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sefl</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Preventing the “second rape”: Rape survivors’ experiences with community service providers</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>1239</fpage>-<lpage>1259</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sefl</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahrens</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wasco</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaragoza-Diesfeld</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Community services for rape survivors: Enhancing psychological well-being or increasing trauma?</article-title> <source>Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>67</volume>, <fpage>847</fpage>-<lpage>858</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. (<year>2005</year>). <source>Current estimates of the number of people age 12+ seeking care at the ED following a sexual assault</source> <comment>(Web-based Injury Statistics Query and Reporting System). Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/ncipc/wisqars/">www.cdc.gov/ncipc/wisqars/</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>20 leading causes of nonfatal violence-related injury, United States</source>. <publisher-loc>Atlanta, GA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Center for Injury Prevention and Control, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://webappa.cdc.gov/cgi-bin/broker.exe">http://webappa.cdc.gov/cgi-bin/broker.exe</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ciancone</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collette</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gerson</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Sexual Assault Nurse Examiner programs in the United States</article-title>. <source>Annals of Emergency Medicine</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>353</fpage>-<lpage>357</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crandall</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Helitzer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Impact evaluation of a Sexual Assault Nurse Examiner (SANE) program</source> (<comment>NCJ 203276</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Institute of Justice</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DiNitto</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P. Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>After sexual assault: Who should examine sexual assault survivors?</article-title> <source>American Journal of Nursing</source>, <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>538</fpage>-<lpage>540</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DuMont</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Investigating the medical forensic examination from the perspectives of sexually assaulted women</article-title>. <source>Social Sciences &amp; Medicine</source>, <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>774</fpage>-<lpage>780</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DuMont</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parnis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Forensic nursing in the context of sexual assault: Comparing the opinions and practices of nurse examiners and nurses</article-title>. <source>Applied Nursing Research</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>-<lpage>183</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edward</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Macleod</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The reality and myth of rape: Implications for the criminal justice system</article-title>. <source>Expert Evidence</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>Emergency Nurses Association</collab>. (<year>2007</year>). <source>Care of sexual assault and rape victims in the emergency department</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ena.org/about/position/position/Sexual_Assault_and_Rape_Victims_-_ENA_White_Paper.pdf">http://ena.org/about/position/position/Sexual_Assault_and_Rape_Victims_-_ENA_White_Paper.pdf</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ericksen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ritch</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shumay</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Clients’ experiences with a specialized sexual assault service</article-title>. <source>Journal of Emergency Nursing</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>86</fpage>-<lpage>90</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Estrich</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <source>Real rape</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flavin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Feminism for the mainstream criminologist: An invitation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Criminal Justice</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>271</fpage>-<lpage>285</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frazier</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haney</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Sexual assault cases in the legal system: Police, prosecutor, and victim perspectives</article-title>. <source>Law and Human Behavior</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>607</fpage>-<lpage>628</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frohmann</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Sexual assault</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Rubington</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Deviance: The interactionist perspective</source> (<fpage>7/e</fpage>) (pp.<fpage>174</fpage> -<lpage>186</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Needham Heights, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Allyn and Bacon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Girardin</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The Sexual Assault Nurse Examiner: A win-win solution</article-title>. <source>Topics in Emergency Medicine</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>124</fpage>-<lpage>131</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>In search of gender justice: Sexual assault and the criminal justice system</article-title>. <source>Feminist Review</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>80</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Halligan</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ehlers</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Posttraumatic stress disorder following assault: The role of cognitive processing, trauma memory, and appraisals</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>419</fpage>-<lpage>431</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>International Association of Forensic Nursing</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>Clinical Forensic Program Registry</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iafn.org/displaycommon.cfm?an=1&amp;subarticlenbr=141">http://www.iafn.org/displaycommon.cfm?an=1&amp;subarticlenbr=141</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kilpatrick</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Resnick</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruggiero</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conoscenti</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCauley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Drug-facilitated, incapacitated, and forcible rapes: A national study</source> (<comment>NIJ 219181</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Justice</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Konradi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Taking the stand: Rape survivors and the prosecution of rapists</source>. <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Praeger</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Konradi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Having the last word: An examination of rape survivors’ participation in sentencing</article-title>. <source>Violence Against Women</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>351</fpage>-<lpage>395</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koss</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Achilles</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Restorative justice responses to sexual assault</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vawnet.org/category/Main_Doc.php?docid=1231">http://www.vawnet.org/category/Main_Doc.php?docid=1231</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lafree</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <source>Rape and Criminal Justice: The social construction of sexual assault</source>. <publisher-loc>Belmont, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wadsworth</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Larcombe</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The “ideal” victim v. successful rape complainants: Not what you might expect</article-title>. <source>Feminist Legal Studies</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>-<lpage>148</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ledray</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Sexual assault nurse examiner (SANE) development &amp; operation guide</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Office for Victims of Crime, U.S. Department of Justice</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ledray</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Expanding evidence collection time: Is it time to move beyond the 72-hour rule? How do we decide?</article-title> <source>Journal of Forensic Nursing</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ledray</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>SANE expert and factual testimony</article-title>. <source>Journal of Emergency Nursing</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>284</fpage>-<lpage>287</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ledray</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simmelink</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Efficacy of SANE evidence collection: A Minnesota study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Emergency Nursing</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>-<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Littel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Sexual Assault Nurse Examiners (SANE) programs: Improving the community response to sexual assault victims</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Justice, Office for Victims of Crime</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Capillo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Differential characteristics of intimate partner, acquaintance, and stranger rape survivors examined by a Sexual Assault Nurse Examiner (SANE)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1066</fpage>-<lpage>1076</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Madigan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gamble</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>The second rape: Society’s continued betrayal of the victim</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lexington Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Magid</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Houry</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koepsell</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ziller</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soules</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jenny</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The epidemiology of female rape victims who seek immediate medical care: Temporal trends in the incidence of sexual assault and acquaintance rape</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</source>, <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>“I have heard horrible stories…” Rape victim advocates’ perceptions of the revictimization of rape victims by the police and medical system</article-title>. <source>Violence Against Women</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <issue>7</issue>, <fpage>786</fpage>-<lpage>808</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P. Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Rape work</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P. Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DiNitto</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>The sexual assault exam: Beyond the hospital emergency room</article-title>. <source>Women’s Health</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P. Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Accounting for the “second assault”: Legal organizations’ framing of rape victims</article-title>. <source>Law &amp; Social Inquiry</source>, <volume>19</volume>(<issue>3/4</issue>), <fpage>853</fpage>-<lpage>890</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matoesian</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>Reproducing rape domination through talk in the courtroom</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DuMont</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Myhr</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Sexual assault forensic medical examination: Is evidence related to successful prosecution?</article-title> <source>Annals of Emergency Medicine</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>639</fpage>-<lpage>647</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huberman</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>An expanded sourcebook: Qualitative data analysis, 2/e</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Monroe</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kinney</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dafeamekpor</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dantzler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The experience of sexual assault: Findings from a statewide needs assessment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>767</fpage>-<lpage>776</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nugent-Borakove</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fanflik</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Troutman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Testing the efficacy of SANE/SART programs: Do They Make a Difference in Sexual Assault Arrest &amp; Prosecution Outcomes?</source> <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Justice</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/nij/grants/214252.pdf">http://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/nij/grants/214252.pdf</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Sexual assault nurse examiner (SANE) program coordinator</article-title>. <source>Journal of Emergency Nursing</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>532</fpage>-<lpage>533</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parnis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DuMont</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gombay</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Cooperation or co-optation? Assessing the methodological benefits and barriers involved in conducting qualitative research through medical institutional settings</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Health Research</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>686</fpage>-<lpage>697</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The linkage between secondary victimization by law enforcement and rape case outcomes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</source>, <volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>328</fpage>-<lpage>347</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greeson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Understanding rape survivors’ decisions not to seek help from formal social systems</article-title>. <source>Health &amp; Social Work</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zwemer</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Unique sexual assault examiner program utilizing mid-level providers</article-title>. <source>Journal of Emergency Medicine</source>, <volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Plichta</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Houseman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Why SANEs matter: Models of care for sexual violence victims in the emergency department</article-title>. <source>Journal of Forensic Nursing</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rovi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shimoni</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Prophylaxis provided to sexual assault victims seen at U.S. emergency departments</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Women’s Association</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>204</fpage>-<lpage>207</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>I. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>Qualitative interviewing: The art of hearing data.</source> <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Speck</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aiken</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>20 years of community nursing service</article-title>. <source>Tennessee Nurse</source>, <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>Sexual Assault Nurse Examiner, Sexual Assault Response Team</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>SANE program locator</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sane-sart.com/staticpages/index.php?page=20031023141144274">http://www.sane-sart.com/staticpages/index.php?page=20031023141144274</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Sexual assault evidence collection more accurate when completed by Sexual Assault Nurse Examiners: Colorado’s experience</article-title>. <source>Journal of Emergency Nursing</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>511</fpage>-<lpage>514</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Starzynski</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ullman</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Filipas</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Correlates of women’s sexual assault disclosure to informal and formal support sources</article-title>. <source>Violence and Victims</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>417</fpage>-<lpage>432</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stermac</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunlap</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bainbridge</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Sexual assault services delivered by SANEs</article-title>. <source>Journal of Forensic Nursing</source>, <volume>1</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>124</fpage>-<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stermac</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stirpe</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Efficacy of a 2-year-old Sexual Assault Nurse Examiner program in a Canadian hospital</article-title>. <source>Journal of Emergency Nursing</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Corbin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>Basics of qualitative research: Grounded theory procedures and techniques</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage Publications, Inc.</publisher-name></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Taslitz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Rape and the culture of the courtroom</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>W. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Collecting evidence for sexual assault: The role of the sexual assault nurse examiner (SANE)</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Gynecology &amp; Obstetrics</source>, <volume>78</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 1</issue>), <fpage>S91</fpage>-<lpage>S94</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Temkin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Doctors, rape, and criminal justice</article-title>. <source>Howard Journal</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ullman</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Do social reactions to sexual assault victims vary by support providers?</article-title> <source>Violence and Victims</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>143</fpage>-<lpage>157</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>U.S. Department of Justice, Office for Victims of Crime</collab>. (<year>2004a</year>, <month>April</month>). <source>Sexual Assault Response Team (SART) Toolkit Cooperative Agreement</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/ovc/fund/pdftxt/SART_toolkit.pdf">http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/ovc/fund/pdftxt/SART_toolkit.pdf</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>U.S. Department of Justice, Office for Victims of Crime</collab>. (<year>2004b</year>). <source>A national protocol for sexual assault medical forensic examinations: Adults/adolescents</source> (<comment>NCJ206554</comment>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Office on Violence Against Women</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr84-0886260511416476">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Woodell</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bowling</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moracco</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Emergency contraception for sexual assault victims in North Carolina emergency departments</article-title>. <source>North Carolina Medical Journal</source>, <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>399</fpage>-<lpage>403</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>