<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="other" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NCP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spncp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nutr Clin Pract</journal-id>
<journal-title>Nutrition in Clinical Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0884-5336</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1941-2452</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0884533611433436</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0884533611433436</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>CAM Corner</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Micronutrients and Inflammatory Bowel Disease</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mullin</surname><given-names>Gerard E.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0884533611433436">Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0884533611433436">Gerard E. Mullin, MD, The Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, 600 N Wolfe St, Carnegie 464, Baltimore, MD 21205; e-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">gmullin1@jhmi.edu</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
  <issue-title>Micronutrients</issue-title>
<fpage>136</fpage>
<lpage>137</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 The American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">The American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This month’s issue of <italic>Nutrition in Clinical Practice</italic> is devoted to the role of micronutrients in health and disease. Micronutrient deficiencies are commonly encountered in inflammatory bowel disease (IBD). Knowledge of the prevalence, presenting signs, and symptoms of micronutrient deficiencies will enable clinicians to suspect, diagnose, and implement therapy in a timely manner. Because the majority of micronutrients are absorbed in the small intestine, micronutrient deficiencies occur more frequently in Crohn’s disease (CD; 25%–69%) than ulcerative colitis (UC; 1%–32%).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0884533611433436">1</xref></sup> Studies that collectively describe the various micronutrient deficiencies in IBD are lacking. Many micronutrients have been shown to be deficient in IBD patients, including iron, calcium, magnesium, folate, zinc, vitamin A, vitamin D, vitamin B<sub>12</sub>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0884533611433436">2</xref></sup> Deficiencies of trace minerals (ie, selenium, copper, chromium) are rare in IBD except in those requiring central parenteral nutrition (PN). Because prior issues of CAM Corner have covered vitamin A and vitamin D, this issue of CAM Corner will concentrate on the more commonly encountered micronutrient deficiencies causing anemia in patients with IBD.</p>
<sec id="section1-0884533611433436">
<title>Anemia</title>
<p>A variety of nutrition deficiencies can be present in IBD and are most commonly due to deficiencies in iron and folate. Anemia is frequently seen in IBD, with prevalence ranging from 6%–74%, but differs whether in a setting of CD or UC.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0884533611433436">3</xref></sup> Anemia worsens the patient’s general condition and quality of life and increases hospitalization rates. The pathogenesis of anemia in IBD involves different factors, including vitamin B<sub>12</sub> and folic acid deficiency, bone marrow suppression secondary to drug therapy, autoimmune hemolytic anemia, and the coexistence of myelodysplastic syndromes. The prevalence of anemia in IBD has been reported by Voegtlin et al,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0884533611433436">4</xref></sup> who observed that anemia was present in 21.2% (51/241) of the IBD patients and more frequently in patients from tertiary referral centers compared with those in general practice settings and healthy controls (28.8% vs 12.9% vs 3.4%; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). In their study, IBD patients from tertiary referral centers suffered more frequently from active disease compared with IBD patients in general practice (36% vs 23%; <italic>P</italic> = .032).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0884533611433436">4</xref></sup> Anemia is a common complication in patients with IBD and significantly more prevalent in patients from referral centers compared with patients from gastroenterologic practices. In IBD, the most common causes of nutrition-related anemia are due to deficiencies of the micronutrients iron, folate, and vitamin B<sub>12</sub>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0884533611433436">
<title>Iron</title>
<p>Iron deficiency is a common nutrient deficiency associated with adult and pediatric IBD and has been reported in 52%–73% of adult patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0884533611433436">5</xref></sup> The cause of IBD iron deficiency anemia (IDA) is multifactorial and due to a combination of iron deficiency and chronic gastrointestinal blood loss and, in some cases, self-imposed dietary restrictions. Because the most common etiology of iron-deficient anemia in IBD is due to gastrointestinal bleeding, IDA is more prevalent in individuals with UC compared with those with CD. Patients may also become anemic due to the effects of systemic inflammation acting through cytokines such as tumor necrosis factor–α and hepcidin, which act to block iron transport and absorption at the intestinal level. Replenishing iron stores are important if warranted as the prevalence of iron deficiency in IBD ranges from 36%–90%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0884533611433436">6</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although oral iron supplementation has been the mainstay of therapy for IDA in IBD, there are no reliable data to recommend one compound over another, and the optimal dose of oral iron for adults has not been established. Options for oral replacement therapy of iron include ferrous sulfate, gluconate, and fumarate, each of which contains different amounts of elemental iron, but gut intolerance is a limiting factor. Intravenous iron sucrose may be a more effective and attractive alternative to oral iron because it is more effective, is better tolerated, and improves quality of life to a greater extent than oral iron supplements.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0884533611433436">7</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0884533611433436">
<title>Folate</title>
<p>Folate is a water-soluble B vitamin that has been shown to prevent DNA damage and cell injury, which can lead to different types of cancer, including those associated with IBD. Anemia may also be due to folate deficiency, which is also quite common in IBD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0884533611433436">6</xref></sup> Most IBD patients are deficient in folic acid, and thus levels should be monitored on all IBD patients at least annually.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0884533611433436">8</xref></sup> Low folate levels in IBD may be caused by medications that impair folic acid transport and malabsorption from loss of surface area due to underlying disease or surgery. Methotrexate is an inhibitor of dihydrofolate reductase, thereby inhibiting the production of folate, which is needed for purine synthesis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0884533611433436">9</xref></sup> Sulfasalazine blocks absorption of folate in the jejunal mucosa. Low folate levels can lead to elevated serum levels of homocysteine due to insufficient methylation of methionine, which places patients at a higher risk for cardiovascular events and thromboembolism, a well-described and potentially lethal extra-intestinal manifestation of IBD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0884533611433436">10</xref></sup> Hyperhomocysteinemia is a known inducer of a hypercoagulable state and is seen in 26.5% of patients with IBD compared with only 3.3% of controls.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0884533611433436">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0884533611433436">12</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0884533611433436">
<title>Vitamin B<sub>12</sub></title>
<p>Vitamin B<sub>12</sub> (cobalamin) is a water-soluble vitamin that is essential for proper functioning of the nervous system and for carbohydrate, protein, and fat metabolism. Vitamin B<sub>12</sub> binds to a specific receptor and is absorbed through the ileal mucosa.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0884533611433436">13</xref></sup> Although patients with ileal CD may be at particular risk for vitamin B<sub>12</sub> deficiency, the unaffected small bowel may have the capability to adapt and increase its ability to absorb vitamin B<sub>12</sub>. Yakut et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0884533611433436">13</xref></sup> reported the prevalence of low B<sub>12</sub> levels in CD to be 22% vs 7.5% in UC (<italic>P</italic> = .014). Depletion of Vitamin B<sub>12</sub> can also be a complication of bacterial overgrowth as a result of bacteria preferentially using B<sub>12</sub>. Distal ileal resection or active disease in this area results in B<sub>12</sub> deficiency as well because the last 60 cm of ileum is where B<sub>12</sub> is absorbed. Vitamin B<sub>12</sub> usually needs to be given parenterally (SQ) due to lack of functional absorptive area in the terminal ileum. Until recently, vitamin B<sub>12</sub> replacement therapy was available only by intramuscular injection. However, cyanocobalamin is now available in oral tablet form. A meta-analysis showed that, in adults, high doses of oral vitamin B<sub>12</sub> (1000 and 2000 µg) were as effective as intramuscular administration in achieving hematological and neurological responses.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0884533611433436">14</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0884533611433436">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Anemia is a common occurrence in IBD and is frequently nutrition related. Patients with UC may be more likely to be iron deficient, whereas patients with CD are more at risk for vitamin B<sub>12</sub> and folate deficiency.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0884533611433436">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mijac</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jankovic</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jorga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Krstic</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nutritional status in patients with active inflammatory bowel disease: prevalence of malnutrition and methods for routine nutritional assessment</article-title>. <source>Eur J Intern Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>-<lpage>319</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0884533611433436">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hebuterne</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Filippi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Jaouni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nutritional consequences and nutrition therapy in Crohn’s disease</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterol Clin Biol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>suppl 3</issue>):<fpage>S235</fpage>-<lpage>S244</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0884533611433436">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gasche</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Berstad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Befrits</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Guidelines on the diagnosis and management of iron deficiency and anemia in inflammatory bowel diseases</article-title>. <source>Inflamm Bowel Dis</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1545</fpage>-<lpage>1553</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0884533611433436">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Voegtlin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vavricka</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schoepfer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of anaemia in inflammatory bowel disease in Switzerland: a cross-sectional study in patients from private practices and university hospitals</article-title>. <source>J Crohns Colitis</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>642</fpage>-<lpage>648</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0884533611433436">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gomollon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gisbert</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Anemia and inflammatory bowel diseases</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>37</issue>):<fpage>4659</fpage>-<lpage>4665</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0884533611433436">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bayraktar</surname><given-names>UD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bayraktar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Treatment of iron deficiency anemia associated with gastrointestinal tract diseases</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>2720</fpage>-<lpage>2725</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0884533611433436">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goodhand</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wahed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rampton</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and tolerability of intravenous iron dextran and oral iron in inflammatory bowel disease: a case-matched study in clinical practice</article-title>. <source>Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1029</fpage>-<lpage>1035</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0884533611433436">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>O’Morain</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Review article: nutrition and adult inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Aliment Pharmacol Ther</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>307</fpage>-<lpage>320</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0884533611433436">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schroder</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Methotrexate in therapy of gastrointestinal diseases [in German]</article-title>. <source>Zeitschrift fur Gastroenterologie</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>623</fpage>-<lpage>637</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0884533611433436">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oussalah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gueant</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Peyrin-Biroulet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analysis: hyperhomocysteinaemia in inflammatory bowel diseases</article-title>. <source>Aliment Pharmacol Ther</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1173</fpage>-<lpage>1184</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0884533611433436">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Danese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gasbarrini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gasbarrini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Genetic and nutritional predictors of hyperhomocysteinemia in inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>490</fpage>-<lpage>491</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0884533611433436">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>De Stefano</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Danese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hyperhomocysteinemia and prevalence of polymorphisms of homocysteine metabolism-related enzymes in patients with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2677</fpage>-<lpage>2682</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0884533611433436">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yakut</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ustun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kabacam</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soykan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Serum vitamin B12 and folate status in patients with inflammatory bowel diseases</article-title>. <source>Eur J Intern Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>320</fpage>-<lpage>323</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0884533611433436">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vidal-Alaball</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cannings-John</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Oral vitamin B12 versus intramuscular vitamin B12 for vitamin B12 deficiency: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Fam Pract</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>285</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>