<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DHG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdhg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Dialogues in Human Geography</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2043-8206</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2043-8214</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2043820612436939</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2043820612436939</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>ARTICLE FORUM 2</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Response</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Comments in reply</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Wainwright</surname>
<given-names>Joel</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff1-2043820612436939">The Ohio State University, USA</aff>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-2043820612436939"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-2043820612436939">Joel Wainwright, Department of Geography, The Ohio State University, Columbus, OH 43210, USA. Email: <email>wainwright.11@osu.edu</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>2</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>71</fpage>
<lpage>75</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In his response Joel Wainwright deploys some passages from Kant to draw out some of the theoretical and political differences between Kojin Karatani and Michel Foucault.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>
<italic>Aufklärung</italic>
</kwd>
<kwd>Foucault</kwd>
<kwd>Kant</kwd>
<kwd>Karatani</kwd>
<kwd>X</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>I thank these commentators for their insightful remarks. It is not for me to reply to their criticisms of Karatani’s thought. Instead, I would like to extend this dialogue with some remarks on the implications of reading Karatani, following upon themes from the three responses.</p>
<p>Each of the respondents places Karatani in conversation with a particular social theorist or body of theory. For Ian Shaw, Karatani provides us with a fruitful counterpoint to Alain Badiou, since both philosophers offer us with an original Marxist conception of the world. Kanishka Goonewardena and Reecia Orzeck place Karatani in conversation with Fernand Braudel and Giovanni Arrighi, with whom he shares a world-historical purview, then conclude that Karatani belongs on the bookshelf alongside Marxist luminaries Henri Lefebvre and Louis Althusser. Lastly, Kiran Asher finds that Karatani’s work provides a powerful means to deepen the postcolonial critique of development and postdevelopment. Let me offer a few remarks on these suggestions, all of which seem valid.</p>
<p>The first point to note is that these names do not overlap (indeed I doubt Badiou, Althusser, and Escobar have ever been linked together). Such a diversity of views on the place of Karatani’s contributions plainly reflects the breadth and novelty of his thought. Why else would readers of Karatani, including these reviewers, imagine him contributing to multiple distinct literatures and place him in company with such luminary philosophers? The impulse to compare Karatani with Western Marxists in particular reflects the degree to which that tradition (only one substream of Marxist philosophy and practice) largely shapes the interpretation of Marx in geography.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-2043820612436939">1</xref>
</sup> This is not to suggest that Karatani’s thought should be seen as opposed to Western Marxism; rather, it is to claim that a profound thinker like Karatani should challenge our reference points. To say this otherwise, I agree with Kiran Asher that Karatani could be read – like Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak, with whom Karatani shares many interesting parallels – as a postcolonial Marxist working both within and outside of ‘western’ philosophy. The same could be said of Kant and Marx.</p>
<p>Rather than judge the merits of the commentators’ specific suggestions, let me offer another potential interlocutor whom geographers might wish to read alongside Karatani: Michel Foucault. Since its critical turn, the discipline’s human geographers have drawn most readily from two theorists above all others: Marx and Foucault. Year in and out, it seems that they are the most-discussed, most-assigned, most-cited social theorists in human geography. In this light, where might Karatani open debates in human geography? Obviously he does not displace Marx (though he could influence how we read him). But Karatani’s work does challenge our discipline’s reverence for Foucault. This claim is clearly one that cannot be elaborated in the space of this short reply.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-2043820612436939">2</xref>
</sup> But let me offer an illustration to suggest how reading Karatani might change our reception of Foucault.</p>
<p>On 5 January 1983, Foucault initiated his second-to-last lecture course with a pair of lectures comprised of commentaries on Kant’s 1784 essay ‘What is Enlightenment?’.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-2043820612436939">3</xref>
</sup> The first hour of Foucault’s lecture reads Kant’s essay to situate it within modern philosophy – Foucault claims that Kant ‘founded the two great traditions which have divided modern philosophy’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-2043820612436939">Foucault, 2010</xref> [1983]: 20) – and to foreshadow the fundamental questions that Foucault will pursue in his lectures. He begins the second hour of his lectures with a ‘rather more precise analysis’ (p. 25) of certain points in Kant’s text, beginning with its famous opening paragraph where Kant defines Enlightenment as ‘man’s emergence from his self-incurred immaturity’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-2043820612436939">Kant, 2004</xref> [1784]: 54) and posits that the motto of Enlightenment is ‘<italic>Sapere aude! </italic>Have courage to use your <italic>own </italic>understanding!’ (p. 54). Foucault patiently unpacks Kant’s key terms and begins to unravel the text’s paradoxes. Foucault gives one of these terms, ‘tutelage’, special emphasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-2043820612436939">Foucault, 2010</xref> [1983]: 28–33), as he examines how Kant argues that Enlightenment – conceptualized as a way out of tutelage – may come about. (To say the least, this is a question that is related to the question of social transformation.) Foucault observes that Kant’s conception of tutelage here is clearly not simply an effect of ‘political-juridical’ repression, that tutelage is not simply the result of a seizure of power (p. 29). Rather Foucault argues that tutelage exists, according to Kant, because ‘men are unable or do not wish to conduct themselves, and others have obligingly come forward to conduct them’ (p. 29). Now before going any further let me say that I am in general agreement with Foucault to this point, but that we should be careful not to agree too quickly with Foucault’s reading of the evidence for this point, or its implications. Let me elaborate.</p>
<p>Foucault extends several points of evidence for his reading, but places special emphasis on the lines which follow where Kant uses three examples to illustrate the condition of tutelage. To quote Kant:<disp-quote>
<p>If I have a book to have understanding in place of me, a spiritual adviser to have a conscience for me, a doctor to judge my diet for me, and so on, I need not make any efforts at all. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-2043820612436939">Kant, 2004</xref> [1784]: 54)<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-2043820612436939">4</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</disp-quote>
Foucault offers a remarkable reading of this sentence in which he posits that these three examples anticipate Kant’s three critiques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-2043820612436939">Foucault, 2010</xref> [1983]: 30–32). This subsection of his lecture concludes with the observation that Kant’s purpose in examining tutelage (and with the three examples) is not to suggest that we who remain under tutelage – i.e. without Enlightenment – are neither suffering some moral lack nor mere repression. Summarizing, Foucault explains:<disp-quote>
<p>I don’t think that Kant is setting his sights on moral faults here, but actually on a sort of deficit in the relationship of autonomy with ourselves which enables us to make use of our reason and our morality. Consequently, what <italic>Aufklärung</italic> [Enlightenment] has to do, and is in the process of doing, is precisely to redistribute the relationships between government of self and government of others. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-2043820612436939">Foucault, 2010</xref> [1983]: 33)<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-2043820612436939">5</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</disp-quote>
The question then arises: how does Kant’s essay allow us to conceptualize the barriers we face in rearranging what Foucault calls ‘the relationship of autonomy with ourselves’?</p>
<p>At this juncture there is a remarkable gap in Foucault’s patient walk through the first two paragraphs of Kant’s text. Immediately after the just-cited sentence where Kant offers his three examples of tutelage – ‘If I have … understanding in place of me … and so on, I need not make any efforts at all’ – Kant offers a lapidary explanation of the <italic>form</italic> of his lacking-courage for <italic>Aufklärung</italic>, writing: ‘I need not think, <italic>so long as I can pay</italic>; others will soon enough take the tiresome job over for me’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-2043820612436939">Kant, 2004</xref> [1784]: 54, my italics). How can we read this sentence except as a critique of the ethical consequences of our collective dependence upon the sale and purchase of labor power? Kant, we might remember, wrote these lines on the eve of the French Revolution, the event which would consecrate the unification of the capital-nation-state trinity. Anticipating Marx’s critique of capitalism, Kant suggests that our release from tutelage will require us to confront the essence of our social formation. For what binds us in tutelage, what saps our courage to think, is the very freedom we associate with having money – especially as it represents potential command of another's labor power. The ‘deficit in the relationship of autonomy to oneself’ that Foucault identifies at the heart of Kant’s critique centers upon the consequences of value form for our relationships with ourselves – and for the very possibility of <italic>Aufklärung</italic>.</p>
<p>Such a reading of Kant is indebted, of course, to Karatani, whose project since the collapse of state communism has been to try to reconstitute Marx’s critique of capitalism in practical moral terms. Karatani and Foucault agree that our political-philosophical struggles today play out upon a terrain shaped decisively by Kant. The question is how, and to what end? In the Preface to <italic>Transcritique</italic>, Karatani explains his intentions in these terms: ‘This, to state it outright, is a project to reconstruct the metaphysics called communism.’ Nothing would be more foreign to Foucault than such a project. Yet nothing, I think, is more urgent today.</p>
<p>Consider state power. The tensions between Foucault and Karatani’s readings of Kant can be further clarified by noting that both critics are concerned with the task of explaining the state. In their approach both thinkers stand at odds with the Hegelian tradition (including Engels, Lenin, and Gramsci). As we discussed in the interview, underlying Karatani’s contention regarding the necessity of overcoming nation, state, and capital simultaneously is an argument that nation and state exist prior to capital – and for autonomous reasons. Karatani argues that ‘the state, like capital, is driven by its own certain <italic>autonomous</italic> power – which won’t be dissolved by the globalization of capitalism’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-2043820612436939">Karatani, 2008</xref>: 579–580). The ‘autonomy’ of state power stems from its roots in a particular form of exchange, i.e. plunder, which is neither free nor reciprocal, and whereby one group threatens to seize control of another’s resources. </p>
<p>Leninists have long underestimated Marx’s own contempt for the state and overestimated the likelihood that the state would wither away after a communist revolution. Today these estimations are no small matter, because in the face of the global dual crisis of capitalism – economic and ecological – we find everywhere countermovements that seek a theory of the possible transcendence of capital-nation-state. And, as Karatani explains:<disp-quote>
<p>When individual national economies are threatened by the global market, they demand the protection (redistribution) of the state and/or bloc economy, at the same time as appealing to national cultural identity [as indeed has occurred throughout the world since the onset of the current crisis – JW]. So it is that any counteraction to capital must be one targeted against the state and nation (community). (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-2043820612436939">Karatani, 2008</xref>: 583)</p>
</disp-quote>
Karatani therefore calls for global revolution in the name of ‘associationism’, that is, for a society based upon free and reciprocal exchange, organized via the association of associations. Practically speaking, this means the creation of a movement of consumers qua workers everywhere, organized through coordinated ‘immanent and ex-scendent’ struggles (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-2043820612436939">Karatani, 2003</xref>: section 7). As Karatani elaborates:<disp-quote>
<p>[C]ountermovements against the state and capitalism in each nation are cause sine qua non. Concretely, this requires the creation of a noncapitalist alternative economy based upon reciprocal exchange at the level of transnational networks – that is, without state dependence. But if these movements were to reach a certain level of development, they would certainly face disruption by the state and capital; transnational networks would be blocked and divided. Therefore, countermovements from ‘outside’ or ‘above’ are just as necessary. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-2043820612436939">Karatani, 2008</xref>: 591)</p>
</disp-quote>
Karatani’s reading of Kant and Marx aims to discern the challenges facing these countermovements as well as to clarify the means to realize alternatives. Drawing on a distinction from Kant’s practical ethics, Karatani concludes that we should not treat X – the task of transcending capital-nation-state – as a constitutive idea, but as a regulative idea. This implies living so as to reorganize society around a form of exchange which is at once free and reciprocal. Such a form of exchange would exist outside the circuit of M-C-M’ and would not treat labor-power as a commodity. The model here is that of associations of combined consumers/producers cooperatives, or better, a society organized as an ensemble of association of free and equal producers (to repeat one of Marx’s expressions for communism). Clearly, building such relations requires transcending value form and money. Thus in order to facilitate the growth of an association of free and equal producers, Karatani reasons, we must ‘establish a financial system (or a system of payment/settlement) based on a currency that does not turn to capital, namely, that does not involve interest’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-2043820612436939">Karatani, 2003</xref>: 297). That is, we must be able to conduct exchanges with a means other than money as we know it (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-2043820612436939">Mann, 2008</xref>). All this is unlikely to occur soon on the global scale, yet again this is the point of X: to articulate a conception of practical ethics so that we may live <italic>as if</italic> it were possible to transcend capital-nation-state, knowing that such transcendence is effectively impossible. This is part of what it means to treat X as a regulative idea.</p>
<p>The need for such an idea is not new, but today it is especially urgent. Writing in the aftermath of the 11 March 2011 Tōhoku earthquake and tsunami – an event which raises fundamental questions of the coming social-ecological form of the world – Karatani writes:<disp-quote>
<p>[G]lobal capitalism will no doubt become unsustainable in 20 or 30 years. The end of capitalism, however, is not the end of human life. Even without capitalist economic development or competition, people are able to live. Or rather, it is only then that people will, for the first time, truly be able to live. Of course, the capitalist economy will not simply come to an end. Resisting such an outcome, the great powers will no doubt continue to fight over natural resources and markets. Yet I believe that the Japanese should never again choose such a path. Without the recent earthquake, Japan would no doubt have continued its hollow struggle for great power status, but such a dream is now unthinkable and should be abandoned. It is not Japan’s demise that the earthquake has produced, but rather the possibility of its rebirth. It may be that only amid the ruins can people gain the courage to stride down a new path. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-2043820612436939">Karatani, 2011</xref>)</p>
</disp-quote>
It will take more than courage to ‘stride down a new path’, in Japan or elsewhere. We would also need a lucid, critical conception of the world. It is in this sense that the potential inherent in an encounter with Professor Karatani’s thought may be realized.</p>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-2043820612436939">
<label>1.</label>
<p>I include myself in this disciplinary self-critique.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-2043820612436939">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Žižek has (I suspect) a similar claim in mind when he writes that <italic>Transcritique</italic> is ‘a must for everyone who wants to break the deadlock of “cultural” resistance to capitalism, and reassert the actuality of Marx’s critique of political economy’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-2043820612436939">Žižek, 2004</xref>: 134).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-2043820612436939">
<label>3.</label>
<p>These lectures are published in English as <italic>The Government of Self and Others</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-2043820612436939">Foucault, 2010</xref> [1983]). Foucault died 25 June 1984.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-2043820612436939">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Foucault cites the same lines (in German and French) in his lecture (2010 [1983]: 30–31).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-2043820612436939">
<label>5.</label>
<p>These relationships – between government of self and others – form the object of Foucault’s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-2043820612436939">1983</xref> course (hence the book’s title). More generally, the task of grasping them ethically dominates Foucault’s late writings.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-2043820612436939">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Foucault</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010 [1983]</year>) <source>The Government of Self and Others: Lectures at the Collège de France, 1982–1983</source>, translated by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Burchell</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-2043820612436939">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kant</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004 [1784]</year>) <article-title>What is enlightenment?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>I</surname>
<given-names>Kant</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <source>Political Writings</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Reiss</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, translated by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Nisbet</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-2043820612436939">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Karatani</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Transcritique: On Kant and Marx</source>, translated by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Kohso</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-2043820612436939">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Karatani</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Beyond capital-nation-state</article-title>. <source>Rethinking Marxism</source> <volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>569</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-2043820612436939">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Karatani</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>How catastrophe heralds a new Japan</article-title>. <source>Counterpunch</source>, <volume>24</volume> <issue>March</issue>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.counterpunch.org/2011/03/24/how-catastrophe-heralds-a-new-japan">http://www.counterpunch.org/2011/03/24/how-catastrophe-heralds-a-new-japan</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-2043820612436939">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mann</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Time, space and money in capitalism and communism</article-title>. <source>Human Geography</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-2043820612436939">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Žižek</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The parallax view</article-title>. <source>New Left Review</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>