<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="product-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CSX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcsx</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Contemp Sociol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Contemporary Sociology: A Journal of Reviews</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0094-3061</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1939-8638</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0094306113477381uu</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0094306113477381uu</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Red October: Left-Indigenous Struggles in Modern Bolivia</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Fabricant</surname><given-names>Nicole</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0094306113477381">Towson University</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0094306113477381"><email>nfabricant@towson.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>284</fpage>
<lpage>286</lpage>
<product>
<source>Red October: Left-Indigenous Struggles in Modern Bolivia</source>, by <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>Jeffery R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <publisher-loc>Leiden, NL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brill</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>. <page-count count="376"/>pp. <price>$136.00</price> cloth. ISBN: <isbn>9789004201552</isbn>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Sociological Association 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Jeffery Webber’s <italic>Red October: Left-Indigenous Struggles in Modern Bolivia</italic> fills an important gap in the literature on social movements in Latin America by reminding readers of the central and critical importance of class in indigenous struggles. While most of the sociological and anthropological work on contemporary indigenous social movements has focused on identity-based demands or a politics of recognition, Webber’s commendable book takes the reader inside the long history of class struggle, social movement unionism, and indigenous resistance to Spanish colonial rule. He introduces the term “combined-oppositional consciousness,” building on Jane Mansbridge’s notion of oppositional consciousness in order to explain the ways in which social movement activists in the early 2000s worked collectively “to undermine, reform or overthrow a system of domination” (p. 27). This collective consciousness comes to a head during the Gas Wars in 2005—whereby the proposed privatization of gas sparked resistance—in the highland city of El Alto. Activists combined a politics of class struggle and indigenous liberation to reclaim critical resources from transnational corporations.</p>
<p>Webber does not begin with the neoliberal period but rather takes the reader on an important tour de force of the complex process of capitalist development and expansion, state formation and racialized, class-based struggles in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. Beginning with the Andean culture of insurrection and the classic struggles of Tomas Katari, Tupaj Katari, Bartolina Sisa, and Zarate Willka, he highlights the ways in which racialized laboring hierarchies and the breakup of indigenous lands, sparked resistance. He argues that state repression, economic exploitation (in the form of mines), and primitive accumulation set the stage for these rich popular cultures of indigenous resistance in early history.</p>
<p>These struggles for reclamation of land, territory, and autonomy in the eighteenth century resemble the battles of the mid-twentieth to the twenty-first century to reclaim national sovereignty from corporate actors. Webber never fully creates this fluid link between anti-colonial resistance movements and the more contemporary populist left-indigenous movements against neoliberal globalization. This fluidity, the importance of the past in the present, seems critical to understand the contemporary period: age-old colonial forms of domination continue to influence and shape both inequality and forms of resistance. Aymara militancy against the Spanish comes to define the “imagined political cultures” whereby Tupaj Katari becomes a critical symbol of populist resistance in the twenty-first century. Webber even states that activists borrowed from and melded the past struggles of Tupaj Katari with Marxist and socialist theories of the twentieth and twenty-first centuries (p. 269). How has neoliberalism and the subsequent displacements set the stage for the melding of two rather distinct traditions of organizing? These indigenous ideals, symbols, and traditions have come to define a new politics of reclamation in Bolivia—and whether someone is of native descent or not, indigeneity has become so malleable and flexible that distinct groups have used it as a way of legitimizing their struggle.</p>
<p>Was it the unintended consequences of neoliberal reforms—which sought to dismantle the power of the most radical labor movement in the history of Latin America—that led to a new form of organizing? Webber argues that the era of dictatorship and state repression of the twentieth century shaped new forms of organizing: the working classes and indigenous peoples played a key role in the struggle for electoral democracy. But it was not until the total “selling off of Bolivia’s sovereignty” to foreign entities that this new politics of reclamation took shape and form. Deeply in debt as the result of a series of military dictators, Bolivia, like most of Latin America, accepted a set of loans from the IMF and World Bank with particular conditions. This New Economic Plan, as it was called in 1985, initially privatized all state-owned industries, liberalized Bolivia’s market, and cut back on services. As Webber articulates, privatization reshaped the world of labor—hundreds of thousands of workers were forced into a reserve-army of the unemployed in expanding urban areas. Ex-miners lived alongside displaced rural peasants who also could no longer survive based on family agriculture. This displacement and subsequent migration mapped a new political landscape whereby union forms of organizing merged with rural <italic>ayllu</italic> horizontal and participatory democratic structures. This was not incidental but rather a result of structural forms of inequality and the destruction wrought by neoliberalism. Webber points toward the Cocalero Movement as one of the new social movements in Bolivia, typifying this left-indigenous politics. Coca growing (a newly dynamic industry rooted in the Chapare) became an important space of work for ex-miners and ex-peasants. While simultaneously, the Chapare also became the center of a U.S. crackdown as international agents launched repressive campaigns of coca eradication. The Cocaleros built a broad-based, anti-imperialist, and anti-neoliberal movement which used indigenous histories and culture as justification for their class-based struggles as poor farmers. The symbol of the coca leaf, as many scholars have pointed out, becomes one of both indigenous identity and class struggle.</p>
<p>Out of the Coca-grower movement emerged current President Evo Morales and his MAS Party (Movement toward Socialism) who had a two-pronged agenda to (a) undo the long history of neoliberal reforms and (b) decolonize Bolivia and incorporate the majority indigenous into the nation-state. However, as Webber notes, Morales’ first four years in office might be viewed as “reconstituted neoliberalism.” While symbolically, Morales’ administration has made great strides for the dispossessed indigenous peoples, one of which was rewriting the constitution, pressures from local elites and transnational actors continue to limit any possibility for more radical reforms. While MAS promised to advance the project of indigenous liberation and socialist emancipation, Webber suggests that instead of placing faith in Morales, we should place our faith in social movements which need to self-mobilize. While Webber is an astute political economist, he tends (in this book and much of his other work) to place more faith in “Radical Left” movements than in the centralized state. As an anthropologist having worked with indigenous social movements for more than fifteen years, I often wish Webber would take the reader into the trenches of the daily frictions of social movement organizing in Bolivia. For instance, I have observed much discrepancy between public discourses of equality and private forms of inequality, performances of “collective” indigenous identities and highly individualistic agendas. I question to what extent these movements have a clear and articulate vision of state-based socialist transformation. Or is Webber calling for the elimination of a state and a form of movement-based anarchism, which might not bring about the social justice agenda he hopes for? The question seems to be rather: how can movements work alongside Morales and push his administration further left, so that he might move beyond symbolic reforms to altering material and structural conditions? This seems to be a more critical question as Bolivia is now faced not only with the legacy of external control and uneven distribution of resources, but also with great ecological problems such as climate change which threatens to alter both urban and rural life as we know it.</p>
</body>
</article>