<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CIN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcin</journal-id>
<journal-title>China Information</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0920-203X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-590X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0920203X12456264m</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0920203X12456264m</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book review: Politics of Difference in Taiwan</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0920203X12456264">University of Tasmania, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>26</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>398</fpage>
<lpage>400</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ngo</surname><given-names>Tak-Wing</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Hong-zen</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds), <source>Politics of Difference in Taiwan</source>. <publisher-loc>London and New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>; <page-count count="x"/> + <page-count count="213"/> pp. with notes, bibliographies, index, tables and illustrations: <isbn>9780415564076</isbn>, <price>£85.00</price> (hbk)</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The last 20 years have seen a proliferation of scholarship about the island of Taiwan. Its complex political and social changes through its democratic transformation and self-conscious identity-making, as well as the tense relationship with mainland China, have offered a rich array of pertinent research opportunities.</p>
<p>The study of Taiwan has developed in that time into a form of area studies, and as ‘Taiwan studies’ has necessarily been interdisciplinary and proscribed in its problematics. The key themes of identity, democracy, cross-straits relations and literature and cinema have drawn on disciplinary methodologies in political science, international relations, Chinese studies and elsewhere. Yet methodology in Taiwan studies remains the aspect of this body of scholarly work in need of the most attention. The field has been overdetermined by the master category of ‘Taiwan’ itself, serving to epistemologically distinguish Taiwan as an object of knowledge, especially in relation to the People’s Republic of China, but also flattening its understanding of the complexities and contradictions within contemporary Taiwanese society.</p>
<p>In that context, <italic>Politics of Difference in Taiwan</italic> represents a statement of methodological intent within Taiwan studies. It breaks away from the domination of the category of ‘Taiwan’ and embraces with a light touch a vocabulary drawn from cultural studies and anthropology to focus on specific themes in contemporary Taiwanese social life and the structures of power and representation that shape them.</p>
<p>Identity is a key theme of the book, but not the well-covered topic of Taiwanese identity, differentiating Taiwan from ‘China’ and inscribing in scholarship the political tension that exists across the Strait. Instead, identity in <italic>Politics of Difference in Taiwan</italic> is that of marginalized groups within Taiwanese society – migrants, indigenous peoples, the gay community, as well as blue-collar workers.</p>
<p>In this way, the book offers an important contribution to a rich and critical portrait of Taiwanese society. Following the editors’ introduction, two well-known Taiwan scholars, Scott Simon and Stéphane Corcuff, open with useful additions to their scholarly project, on aboriginality and the mainlander/Taiwanese (<italic>waishengren</italic>/<italic>benshengren</italic> 外省人/本省人) division in Taiwan. Simon presents a detailed comparison between Taiwan and Canada and a broad critique of the policies of successive Taiwan governments towards indigenous peoples, while recognizing the progress that has been made. He links aboriginal issues in Taiwan to themes of democratic representation and nation-building in his comparisons with the Canadian experience. Corcuff presents a nuanced analysis of the circumstances of <italic>waishengren</italic> in Taiwan and their complex responses to the Taiwanization movements after the lifting of martial law. Corcuff’s chapter introduces a more complex theoretical vocabulary to the topic than his earlier work and his chapter is important in the context of the new Kuomintang era under Ma Ying-jeou.</p>
<p>The next two chapters explore the blue-collar worker experience, among Kaohsiung dockworkers and through the Taiwanese labour movement. Yi-Chi Chen and Tak-Wing Ngo’s chapter on dockworkers offers a detailed empirical account of their identity formations through different periods of Taiwanese history. Ming-sho Ho’s piece on identity politics in the labour movement draws out themes of class and gender in the context of industrialization and post-industrialization and the mobilization of specific notions of masculinity in labour activism.</p>
<p>Migration and marriage are the themes in three chapters by Yen-Fen Tseng and Yukiko Komiya; Melody Chia-Wen Lu; and Wen-hui Anna Tang, Danièle Bélanger and Hong-zen Wang. Tseng and Komiya argue for a class effect in regulating migration, especially of foreign spouses, with those from poorer countries in South-east Asia being subjected to specific education practices. In Lu’s chapter the focus is on mainland Chinese spouses and the creation of regulatory frameworks against the backdrop of shifting social attitudes towards mainland China and Chinese women moving to Taiwan for marriage. Tang, Bélanger and Wang studied Vietnamese spouses who have been victims of domestic violence, using detailed interviews and seeking to explain the basis of the crises of these relationships in terms of shifting relations of social power.</p>
<p>Jens Damm is another well-known Taiwan studies scholar and his chapter covers gay identity in Taiwan and its emergence as a social movement aligned with Taiwan’s liberalization from the 1980s onwards. He also notes the stalling progress towards gay rights under the Chen and Ma governments from the 2000s, highlighting the contrast between the cultural and the political visibility of the gay community in Taiwan.</p>
<p>The final chapter by Anru Lee and Perng-juh Peter Shyong draws together a number of themes around art, urban development and cultural identity, examining the use of public art in the Kaohsiung subway system as an element of a modern expression of Taiwanese developmentalism and of a relationship between governmentality, a public and artists.</p>
<p>As in many edited collections, the styles of writing and scholarly approach vary. The book might have made a greater effort to locate the work within the broader issues of Taiwan studies so as to more clearly define why its micro-social approach is a useful addition to the field. As it is, <italic>Politics of Difference in</italic> Taiwan is a valuable addition to the literature on Taiwan with new and interesting work from well-known scholars in the field. Its tone of critique and detailed empirical information is exactly the kind of approach needed to continue the development of Taiwan studies as a viable form of area studies.</p>
</body>
</article>