<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IRS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spirs</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1012-6902</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7218</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1012690211434336</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1012690211434336</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>On roads traveled and journeys ahead for <italic>IRSS</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wenner</surname><given-names>Lawrence A</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1012690211434336">Loyola Marymount University, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>4</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© International Sociology of Sport Association and SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">International Sociology of Sport Association and SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Now entering its 47th year of publication, the <italic>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</italic> is the oldest and most international of the scholarly journals devoted to the study of sport, culture, and society. While over the years we have consistently endeavored to publish the strongest and most engaging scholarly work on sport, <italic>IRRS</italic> has always been a journal committed to changing things for the better. As ISSA’s membership has expanded and the capability to view sport in cultural context has increased, <italic>IRRS</italic> has become more interdisciplinary and open to diverse strategies that will advance understanding. More recently, as we sought to widen our reach and to improve the professionalism of producing our publication, ISSA and <italic>IRSS</italic> entered into a publication partnership with SAGE Publications. SAGE and its London staff have contributed mightily to the improvement in our production processes, enabling scholars to have their work see the light of day quickly through publishing <italic>OnlineFirst</italic>, even if there was a backlog for that research to appear in our print edition.</p>
<p>In recent years, much of the credit for improving <italic>IRSS</italic> goes to the editorial leadership and hard work of John Sugden who transitioned <italic>IRSS</italic> to its quality today. As many of you know, John graciously took over the reins of <italic>IRSS</italic> at a challenging time. His commitment, along with the dedicated work of Editorial Assistant Gill Rogers, have optimized the editorial office operations and kept <italic>IRSS</italic> on a tight production schedule. This has served the journal, its readers, and ISSA in immeasurable ways. These improvements, when combined with John’s ceaseless efforts as a global advocate for the journal, have made <italic>IRSS</italic> a hospitable place for the best scholarship in sport studies. For this, we all owe John a great debt of gratitude.</p>
<p>As I take over the editorial reins, the quality improvements and increased visibility that John’s leadership has fostered at <italic>IRSS</italic> have provided a new set of opportunities. Starting in 2012, <italic>IRSS</italic> will begin publishing six issues a year. With a 50 percent increase in the number of pages that we can devote to scholarly research, there comes both opportunity and challenges. With its bigger footprint, <italic>IRSS</italic> can continue to expand its influence in our scholarly community. We hope that prospective authors will begin to think of <italic>IRSS</italic> first, as we can now not only promise prompt publishing <italic>OnlineFirst</italic>, but also that their research will appear in print sooner. Our expanded page count also gives us added flexibility to respond to emerging issues by entertaining specially themed issues and getting them to the light of day more quickly. In the coming months, scholars who have interest in proposing and guest editing special issues will be assisted by a revised protocol. In the meantime, those who might be interested should feel free to contact me directly to begin discussion.</p>
<p>The 50 percent increase in pages of <italic>IRSS</italic> will also present special challenges. Collectively, we will need to get the word out that <italic>IRSS</italic> is a quality outlet that is encouraging submissions from broad quarters – not only from around the world, but also from diverse disciplinary lenses, theoretical perspectives, and methodological approaches. In order to advance our reach, in 2012 we will be expanding the number and role of Corresponding Editors who will serve as regional ambassadors for <italic>IRSS</italic>. Here, we bring a distinguished group of Corresponding Editors from around the globe. We hope that potential authors will reach out to Corresponding Editors as ‘first responders’, whether by direct contact or by happenstance at a regional meeting, to discuss their work and assist in fashioning it for <italic>IRSS</italic>.</p>
<p>As with the Corresponding Editors, the Editorial Board has also been expanded. This has been done not only to improve our inclusiveness and regional representation, but also to improve our efficiency in reviewing the greater number of manuscripts that we anticipate will be submitted as we increase our publication capacity. As you review the composition of our new Editorial Board, you will see a nice mix of familiar and new faces. We have made many inroads in advancing the diversity of the board. Gender balance has been improved and we have Editorial Board members with important links to Asia and Latin America, where sport sociology is blooming. Other appointments broaden our representation in Europe. All are strong scholars committed to maintaining the quality of <italic>IRSS</italic>. Observers will also notice, in the Board’s composition, an increase in former and current editors of sport studies journals.</p>
<p>Finally, we have a new team in place in our Editorial Office housed with the gracious support of Loyola Marymount University. This has enabled David Marple, a knowledgeable sport sociologist with experience on the editorial boards of <italic>Sociology of Sport Journal</italic> and the <italic>Journal of Sport and Social Issues</italic>, to join the editorial team as Assistant Editor. While Dave will provide broad support for our operations, his presence will additionally enable <italic>IRRS</italic> to provide special service to authors with manuscripts ‘provisionally accepted’ for publication but which need further work for ‘final acceptance’. We anticipate that Dave’s work will be especially helpful to authors whose first language is not English who need to improve drafts for final consideration by myself as Editor. Finally, I am pleased to welcome Susan Rice as our Editorial Assistant. With superior organization skills honed by experiences as an attorney and educational consultant, Susan will often ‘serve as my hands’ in routine correspondence with the Editorial Board to keep reviews on schedule. Susan will also play a key role as <italic>IRRS</italic> transitions to SageTrack’s online manuscript submission and review system in 2012. Our move to SageTrack will increase our editorial team’s efficiency and enable a smooth transition as we increase production. From our team at SAGE and the Editorial Office we look forward to working with you.</p>
</body>
</article>