<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppip</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part P: Journal of Sports Engineering and Technology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1754-3371</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1754-338X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1754337112442620</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1754337112442620</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The temperature inside football helmets during head impact: a five-year study of collegiate football games</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Rowson</surname><given-names>Steven</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Duma</surname><given-names>Stefan M</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1754337112442620">Virginia Tech – Wake Forest, Center for Injury Biomechanics, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1754337112442620">Steven Rowson, Virginia Tech — Wake Forest University, School of Biomedical Engineering and Sciences, Center for Injury Biomechanics, 440 ICTAS Building, Stanger St, Blacksburg, VA 24061, USA. Email: <email>srowson@vt.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>227</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>12</fpage>
<lpage>19</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>3</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>27</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The objective of this study was to measure in-helmet temperature at the time of impact in a large cohort of football players, as such data can provide new insight to the temperatures helmets should be evaluated at during experimental testing that assess helmet safety. A large cohort of Virginia Tech football players were instrumented with the HIT System (Simbex, Lebanon, NH, USA), which recorded in-helmet temperature and head acceleration for head impacts experienced during 60 games between 2006 and 2010. The average in-helmet temperature at time of impact was 76.4 °F ± 10.1 °F (24.6 °C ± 5.6 °C). In-helmet temperature was strongly correlated to the ambient temperature of the game. Head acceleration resulting from impact varied less than 10% across temperatures, and temperature did not significantly influence head acceleration. These data have implications for the testing conditions used in the laboratory when evaluating the safety of helmets.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Impact biomechanics</kwd>
<kwd>helmet testing</kwd>
<kwd>concussion</kwd>
<kwd>brain injury</kwd>
<kwd>STAR evaluation system</kwd>
<kwd>head acceleration</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1754337112442620" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Of the estimated 1.6–3.8 million sports-related concussions that occur each year in the United States, football is responsible for the greatest number of these injuries, due to its large number of participants and high rate of head impact events.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1754337112442620">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1754337112442620">2</xref></sup> Sports-related concussion is an injury of increasing concern, as recent research has suggested that repetitive concussions may be linked to neurodegenerative processes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1754337112442620">3</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1754337112442620"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1754337112442620">5</xref></sup> It is thought that there are several ways to reduce the incidence of concussion in football, including rule changes, behavior modification, and advances in protective equipment. By changing the rules of football to eliminate any intentional use of the helmet as a weapon, and by teaching players proper tackling techniques that do not involve leading with the head, severe head impacts in football may be greatly reduced.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1754337112442620">6</xref></sup> While reducing the number of severe head impacts in football will likely reduce the incidence of concussion, head impacts are still going to occur. To address the remaining head impacts, advances in the protective design of helmets may further reduce the incidence of concussion in football.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1754337112442620">7</xref></sup> These advances will be driven by research investigating the mechanisms of injury and factors that may contribute to the susceptibility to injury.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1754337112442620">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1754337112442620"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1754337112442620"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1754337112442620"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1754337112442620"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1754337112442620"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1754337112442620">14</xref></sup> This study investigates the effect that temperature may have on the intended protective capabilities of football helmets.</p>
<p>The impact energy management characteristics of football helmets are tested inside laboratories under various conditions in an effort to evaluate the potential for head injury. The National Operating Committee on Standards for Athletic Equipment (NOCSAE) provides a set of voluntary standards that are designed to assess sporting helmets’ ability to prevent skull fracture. The NOCSAE standard for football helmets involves dropping an instrumented humanoid headform onto a specified surface from various heights, using different impact locations on the helmet.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1754337112442620">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1754337112442620">16</xref></sup> While drop height and impact location are varied in these tests, helmet temperature is also controlled and varied. The NOCSAE standard for football helmets specifies that tests be performed at 72 °F ± 5 °F (22.2 °C ± 2.8 °C) to ensure that the mechanical response of the padding inside the helmet is evaluated in a consistent manner. High temperature tests 115 °F ± 5 °F (46.1 °C ± 2.8 °C) are also performed to ensure that the padding does not bottom out due to increased compliance related to higher temperatures. In order for a helmet to pass the standard, all tests at every condition on a helmet must result in the response of the headform being below a specified head acceleration-based injury metric threshold (Severity Index<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1754337112442620">17</xref></sup> &lt; 1200). Helmets that pass the standard are said to be ‘NOCSAE Certified’ and are considered to offer adequate protection against catastrophic head injury.</p>
<p>More recently, a new football helmet rating system, known as the STAR Evaluation System, was introduced to assess football helmets’ ability to reduce concussion risk.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1754337112442620">7</xref></sup> Based on years of on-field data collection from instrumented helmets, this system evaluates helmet performance through a series of 20 drop tests representative of all the head impacts a player may experience throughout a single football season. Exposure and head acceleration-based concussion risk for each drop test are combined to a single value that predicts an overall concussion incidence. The STAR Evaluation System provides consumers with helmet-specific safety information, and is analogous to the New Car Assessment Program (NCAP), where automobile safety is tested in a laboratory and the results are interpreted for and provided to the public.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1754337112442620">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1754337112442620">19</xref></sup> The STAR evaluation is intended to supplement NOCSAE testing, as NOCSAE addresses a helmet’s ability to prevent skull fracture and STAR assesses the comparative performance of helmets to reduce the probability of concussion. While the NOCSAE football helmet standard tests at two temperature conditions, the STAR Evaluation System currently only considers testing helmets at a standard laboratory temperature of 72 °F (22.2 °C).</p>
<p>The effect that intrinsic and extrinsic factors may have on the variables used to assess injury is important to understand.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1754337112442620">20</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1754337112442620"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1754337112442620"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1754337112442620"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1754337112442620">24</xref></sup> To date, little research has been performed investigating the temperature of football helmets during use. The objectives of this study were to measure in-helmet temperature at the time of impact in a large cohort of football players in an effort to:</p>
<list id="list1-1754337112442620" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>define the distribution of in-helmet temperature during collegiate football games;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>determine the relationship between ambient temperature and in-helmet temperature;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>investigate the effect that in-helmet temperature variation may have on resulting head accelerations due to impact.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Such data could give new insight as to which temperatures helmets should be evaluated at during experimental testing to assess helmet safety.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1754337112442620" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="section3-1754337112442620">
<title>Data collection</title>
<p>For a total of 60 collegiate football games between 2006 and 2010, the helmets of Virginia Tech football players were equipped with commercially available instrumentation (HIT System, Simbex, Lebanon, NH, USA) that measured head acceleration and in-helmet temperature. Both Virginia Tech home and away games were included in this study. This system provides the advantage of collecting data from human volunteers, as opposed to cadavers or dummies, where the varying effect of active musculature on the dynamic response is limited.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1754337112442620">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1754337112442620">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1754337112442620">26</xref></sup> An average of 40 helmets were instrumented each year throughout this time period (202 player-seasons) with player participation ranging from 1 to 4 years, and all participants gave informed consent approved by Virginia Tech’s Institutional Review Board (IRB).</p>
<p>The HIT System consists of six accelerometers (Analog Devices, MA, USA) that are mounted on a specifically-designed elastic base so that they remain in contact with the head throughout the duration of impact, ensuring that head acceleration is measured rather than shell vibrations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1754337112442620">27</xref></sup> When an accelerometer exceeded a specified threshold (14.4 g) during play, data acquisition was automatically triggered and data were collected for 40 ms (including 8 ms of pre-trigger data) at 1000 Hz. Once data collection was complete, data were wirelessly transmitted to a computer on the sideline. Resultant linear head acceleration and resultant rotational acceleration at the center of gravity (CG) of the head was computed using a novel algorithm.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1754337112442620">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1754337112442620">29</xref></sup> The HIT System has been well-validated,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1754337112442620">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1754337112442620">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1754337112442620">30</xref></sup> and has been widely adopted by other researchers studying concussion in athletes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1754337112442620">10</xref></sup> This study utilized data collection protocols that are described in greater detail by previous studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1754337112442620">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1754337112442620">31</xref></sup></p>
<p>In addition to the accelerometers, the HIT System is also equipped with a thermistor (ACCX-004, RTI Electronics, Anaheim, CA, USA). The thermistor is recessed 2.5 mm into the inner foam face of the device, and is enclosed within the vinyl casing, and is not in contact with the head of the player or shell of the helmet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1754337112442620">Figure 1</xref>). When data acquisition is triggered due to an accelerometer exceeding the specified threshold, an in-helmet temperature measurement at the time of impact is also recorded. Therefore, for each head acceleration measurement recorded, there is an associated in-helmet temperature for that impact. While the HIT System was used to record head acceleration and in-helmet temperature for every head impact instrumented players experienced during games, the temperature at the time of kick-off for each game was obtained from the Virginia Tech sports statistics department and recorded. Data were collected from games across entire Virginia Tech football seasons, ranging from late August to early January.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1754337112442620" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The thermistor is recessed 2.5 mm into the inner foam face of the device, and is enclosed within vinyl casing.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1754337112442620-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1754337112442620">
<title>Data analyses</title>
<p>The data collected in this study were used to define distributions for in-helmet temperature and game temperature (from weather records) at the time of impact. These data were fitted to skew–normal distributions because the temperature distributions were left-skewed. The skew–normal probability density function (pdf) takes the form of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1754337112442620">equation (1)</xref>, where <italic>x</italic> is temperature, α is the shape parameter, ω is the scale parameter, ξ is the location parameter, and erf is the error function. The cumulative distribution function (cdf) was determined through integration of the pdf with respect to temperature. Goodness of the distribution fit was assessed through comparison of the empirical cdf with the fitted cdf.</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1754337112442620">
<label>(1)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-1754337112442620">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>pdf</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ω</mml:mi>
<mml:msqrt>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>π</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msqrt>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ω</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>erf</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ω</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msqrt>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msqrt>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-1754337112442620" xlink:href="10.1177_1754337112442620-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>The relationship between in-helmet temperature and game temperature was investigated through a least-squares analysis. For each of the 60 games, the average temperature associated with all impacts for that day was computed. A linear regression was performed relating the 60 game temperatures at the time of kick-off to the 60 average in-helmet temperatures using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1754337112442620">equation (2)</xref>, where <italic>T<sub>helmet</sub></italic> is in-helmet temperature, <italic>T<sub>game</sub></italic> is game temperature at the time of kick-off, <italic>m</italic> is the slope, and <italic>b</italic> is the offset. Furthermore, the effect of temperature on head acceleration was investigated. All impacts were grouped into temperature bins of 10°F (5.6 °C) and the median, mean, and 95th percentile head accelerations were compared for each bin. A protected Fisher’s least significant difference analysis utilizing a significance indicator of <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 was used to test significant differences between head accelerations grouped by temperature bins.</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula2-1754337112442620">
<label>(2)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math2-1754337112442620">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>helmet</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>*</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>game</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-1754337112442620" xlink:href="10.1177_1754337112442620-eq2.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1754337112442620" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Throughout the 60 games, data on 35,773 head impacts were recorded. The average in-helmet temperature at time of impact was 76.4 °F ± 10.1°F (24.6 °C ± 5.6 °C), ranging from 32.9 °F (0.5 °C) to 106.2 °F (41.2 °C). The average game temperature for all instrumented games was 63.1 °F ± 13.5 °F (17.3 °C ± 7.5 °C), and ranged from 29 °F (−1.7 °C) to 85 °F (29.4 °C). <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1754337112442620">Table 1</xref> displays additional descriptive statistics for the in-helmet temperature and game temperature distributions. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1754337112442620">Figure 2</xref> displays the probability density functions for in-helmet temperature and game temperature while <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1754337112442620">Table 2</xref> provides the parameter estimates for each skew-normal distribution. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1754337112442620">Figure 3</xref> compares the fitted cumulative distribution functions for in-helmet temperature and game temperature to the empirical data, suggesting excellent fits.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1754337112442620" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Temperature percentiles for the in-helmet temperature and game temperature distributions.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1754337112442620" xlink:href="10.1177_1754337112442620-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">5th percentile</th>
<th align="left">25th percentile</th>
<th align="left">50th percentile</th>
<th align="left">75th percentile</th>
<th align="left">95th percentile</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>In-helmet</td>
<td>58.9 °F (14.9 °C)</td>
<td>70.0 °F (21.1 °C)</td>
<td>78.3 °F (25.7 °C)</td>
<td>83.5 °F (28.6 °C)</td>
<td>90.7 °F (32.6 °C)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Game</td>
<td>40.0 °F (4.44 °C)</td>
<td>52.5 °F (11.4 °C)</td>
<td>67.0 °F (19.4 °C)</td>
<td>73.0 °F (22.8 °C)</td>
<td>80.5 °F (26.9 °C)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig2-1754337112442620" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Skew–normal probability density functions for in-helmet temperature and game temperature. In-helmet temperatures were always greater than game temperature.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1754337112442620-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table2-1754337112442620" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Skew–normal distribution parameter estimates for in-helmet and game temperatures.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1754337112442620" xlink:href="10.1177_1754337112442620-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">α</th>
<th align="left">ξ</th>
<th align="left">ω</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>In-helmet</td>
<td>–2.584</td>
<td>87.77</td>
<td>15.24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Game</td>
<td>–5.930</td>
<td>80.35</td>
<td>21.80</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig3-1754337112442620" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Skew–normal cumulative distribution functions for in-helmet temperature and game temperature. Comparison of the fitted data to the empirical data suggests excellent distribution fits.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1754337112442620-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1754337112442620">Figure 4</xref> displays the relationship between in-helmet temperature and game temperature, as determined by the linear regression analysis. This analysis suggested a strong correlation between in-helmet temperature and game temperature (<italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.72). Estimated values of the regression parameters were as follows: <italic>m</italic> = 0.5187 and <italic>b</italic> = 43.17. Intuitively, as game temperature increased, in-helmet temperature increased.</p>
<fig id="fig4-1754337112442620" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Linear regression analysis between in-helmet temperature and game temperature produced a strong correlation (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.72).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1754337112442620-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1754337112442620">Figure 5</xref> displays the median, average, and 95th percentile linear and rotational head acceleration values for in-helmet temperature ranges that are grouped into 10°F (5.6 °C) bins. There were 331 impacts with in-helmet temperatures less than 50 °F (10.0 °C), 2000 impacts with in-helmet temperatures between 50 °F (10.0 °C) and 60 °F (15.6 °C), 7822 impacts with in-helmet temperatures between 60 °F (15.6 °C) and 70 °F (21.1 °C), 11,420 impacts with in-helmet temperatures between 70 °F (21.1 °C) and 80 °F (26.7 °C), 11,958 impacts with in-helmet temperatures between 80°F (26.7 °C) and 90 °F (32.2 °C), and 2242 impacts with in-helmet temperatures greater than 90 °F (32.2 °C). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1754337112442620">Figure 6</xref> displays the median, average, and 95th percentile linear and rotational head acceleration values for game temperature ranges that are grouped into 10 °F bins. There were 7298 impacts associated with game temperatures below 50°F (10 °C), 7221 impacts with game temperature between 50 °F (10.0 °C) and 60 °F (15.6 °C), 5889 impacts with game temperatures between 60 °F (15.6 °C) and 70 °F (21.1 °C), 13,350 impacts with game temperatures between 70 °F (21.1 °C) and 80 °F (26.7 °C), and 2015 impacts with game temperatures greater than 80 °F (26.7 °C). Similar trends are exhibited in both figures. The greatest 95th percentile head accelerations were experienced with temperatures less than 50 °F (10.0 °C), and the lowest 95th percentile head accelerations were experienced with temperatures between 80 °F (26.7 °C) and 90 °F (32.2 °C). For in-helmet temperature and game temperature, differences between average head accelerations for each temperature bin were not statistically significant.</p>
<fig id="fig5-1754337112442620" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Median, average and 95th percentile head accelerations associated with each in-helmet temperature range. 95th percentile head acceleration varied as much as 8.1% for linear acceleration and 3.9% for rotational acceleration.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1754337112442620-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig6-1754337112442620" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Median, average and 95th percentile head accelerations associated with each game temperature range. 95th percentile head acceleration varied as much as 8.9% for linear acceleration and 8.5% for rotational acceleration.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1754337112442620-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1754337112442620" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>For the first time, these data report the temperatures inside football helmets during use. The overall in-helmet and game temperature distributions were modeled as being skew–normal. This skew–normal distribution may be bimodal, due to including data from Virginia Tech home and away football games. Home games had a mean game temperature of 60 °F (15.5 °C) (median = 61 °F (16.1 °C)) and away games had a mean game temperature of 66 °F (18.8 °C) (median = 72 °F (22.2 °C)). This suggests that the skew–normal distribution could be bimodal, consisting of a normal distribution for home games and a left-skewed distribution for away games paired together. For the purposes of investigating overall distributions, all data were compiled together. Relative to the game temperatures, the in-helmet temperature distribution is shifted towards warmer temperatures and is slightly less skewed. The data collected and analyzed in this study suggest that the temperature inside the helmet at the time of head impact varies throughout play. Furthermore, there was a strong correlation between average in-helmet temperature and game temperature. In-helmet temperature at the time of impact was typically greater than the game temperature, and increased with increasing game temperature. These data are important, because the material properties of a helmet’s padding may vary with temperature.</p>
<p>Variations in the temperature of the helmet may be attributed to a number of factors, including players removing their helmets from their head during play and differences in game temperatures. Many players only wear their helmets on their heads when they are on the field, and remove their helmets when they are standing on the sideline. This allows the inside of the helmet to cool towards the game temperature. When the player puts the helmet back on their head, the helmet warms towards the temperature of the player’s head. This could also be attributed to the fluctuations in game temperatures across the playing season. Games in November are generally colder in temperature than games in September, creating a larger differential between the temperature of the head and that of the game. This generally results in larger variations in helmet temperature during cold weather.</p>
<p>Head acceleration resulting from impact varied less than 10% across temperatures, and temperature did not significantly influence head acceleration. This lack of correlation can be attributed to numerous factors. Head accelerations due to impact during football games can vary based on playing position, opponent quality, team strategy and personnel differences that all vary on a game-to-game basis. Because of this, it is not surprising that this analysis found little difference in head acceleration for varying temperatures. It is feasible that head acceleration would exhibit greater variations due to helmet temperature in the laboratory than the field. Further investigation through controlled laboratory helmet testing is needed to understand the effect of temperature on the mechanical response of energy management systems in football helmets. The temperature distributions reported in this study provide the basis for these tests. Specifically, various helmet models should be tested in a laboratory at varying temperatures in a more controlled experiment.</p>
<p>Furthermore, these data have implications on helmet testing in the laboratory. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1754337112442620">Figure 7</xref> compares the in-helmet temperature distribution for all head impacts to the testing conditions specified by NOCSAE. The average in-helmet temperature at time of impact was 76.4 °F ± 10.1 °F (24.6 °C ± 5.6 °C). This suggests that the ambient testing condition of 72 °C (22.2 °C) is an appropriate temperature representative of what is seen on the field. The high temperature condition of 115 °F (46.1 °C) does not overlap the in-helmet temperature distribution. It is possible that the 115 °F (46.1 °C) temperature condition could lead to stiffer foams to compensate for an unrealistic temperature. The maximum in-helmet temperature was 106 °F (41.1 °C) during the warmest game, which was 85 °F (29.4 °C). While the NOCSAE standard assesses a helmet’s ability to prevent catastrophic injury, the STAR Evaluation System assesses a helmet’s ability to minimize concussion risk. Currently, the STAR Evaluation System only utilizes the ambient testing condition. Future laboratory testing based on the data presented in this study will give further insight into whether warmer and cooler temperatures should be considered when evaluating helmet performance.</p>
<fig id="fig7-1754337112442620" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Comparison of the in-helmet temperature distribution to testing conditions specified in the NOCSAE football helmet testing standard.</p>
<p>NOCSAE: National Operating Committee on Standards for Athletic Equipment; PDF: probability density function.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1754337112442620-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Although this study provides valuable data on in-helmet temperatures at the time of impact, there are several limitations worth noting. First, it is important to realize that the thermistor is not measuring the temperature of the padding inside the helmet. The padding inside the helmet is likely to have a temperature gradient that varies from temperatures approaching the head temperature at the inner-most surface, to temperatures approaching the helmet shell temperature at the outer-most surface. The thermistor was recessed 2.5 mm into the inner foam surface of the HIT System measurement device and enclosed within the vinyl casing. The thermistor was never in contact with the head, and likely provided a temperature measurement somewhere between the two extremes of the temperature gradient present in the padding of the football helmet. Second, this study only instrumented Virginia Tech football players, who typically play in a specific geographic region, limited to the East Coast of the United States. The minimum game temperature was 29 °F (−1.7 °C) and the maximum game temperature was 85 °F (29.4 °C). While this range likely includes the majority of game temperatures experienced throughout the United States, cooler and warmer temperature extremes are likely experienced in different geographic regions. It is possible for researchers to implement similar analyses in different regions to supplement these data, as the HIT System has already been implemented in many different geographic regions within the United States.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1754337112442620">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1754337112442620">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1754337112442620">32</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1754337112442620"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1754337112442620">34</xref></sup> Third, it is worth noting that each game lasted approximately 3.5 hr and that the actual ambient temperature that the helmets were exposed to could have varied from the reported game temperature. This potential variation could have influenced the overall relationship between in-helmet temperature and game temperature, and is the reason average in-helmet temperatures for each game were used in the regression analysis. Finally, it is worth noting that this study only instrumented Riddell football helmets. This is a result of the HIT System currently only being compatible with the Riddell VSR4, Revolution, and Speed helmet models.</p>
<p>In order to accurately assess the response and performance of safety equipment, it is important that the loading condition and testing environment are representative of the impact event being analyzed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1754337112442620">35</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1754337112442620"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1754337112442620"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1754337112442620"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1754337112442620"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1754337112442620"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1754337112442620">41</xref></sup> This study provides the first available dataset of temperatures inside the helmet during competitive football play that can be used to better understand the environmental conditions that football helmets are exposed to under loading scenarios. A large cohort of Virginia Tech football players were instrumented with the HIT System, which recorded temperature and head acceleration for head impacts experienced during 60 games between 2006 and 2010. The average in-helmet temperature at time of impact was 76.4 °F ± 10.1 °F (24.6 °C ± 5.6 °C). In-helmet temperature was strongly correlated to the temperature of the game. Head acceleration resulting from impact varied less than 10% across temperatures, and temperature did not significantly influence head acceleration. While this study gave a preliminary look at how temperature may affect head response, more detailed work is needed to understand the effect of temperature on the mechanical response of energy management systems in football helmets. Specifically, various helmet models should be tested in a laboratory at varying temperatures in a more controlled experiment. These data have implications on the testing conditions used in the laboratory when evaluating the safety of helmets.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-1754337112442620">
<title>Appendix</title>
<sec id="section7-1754337112442620">
<title>Notation</title>
<p><italic>b</italic> offset</p>
<p><italic>erf</italic> error function</p>
<p><italic>m</italic> slope</p>
<p><italic>T<sub>game</sub></italic> game temperature at the time of kickoff</p>
<p><italic>T<sub>helmet</sub></italic> in-helmet temperature</p>
<p><italic>x</italic> temperature</p>
<p><italic>α</italic> shape parameter</p>
<p>ω scale parameter</p>
<p>ξ location parameter</p>
</sec>
</app>
</app-group>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors gratefully acknowledge the National Institutes of Health (National Institute for Child Health and Human Development) R01HD048638 for sponsoring this research.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1754337112442620">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hootman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Agel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of collegiate injuries for 15 sports: summary and recommendations for injury prevention initiatives</article-title>. <source>J Athletic Training</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1754337112442620">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Langlois</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rutland-Brown</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wald</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The epidemiology and impact of traumatic brain injury: a brief overview</article-title>. <source>J Head Trauma Rehabilitation</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>378</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1754337112442620">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gavett</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Chronic traumatic encephalopathy: a potential late effect of sport-related concussive and subconcussive head trauma</article-title>. <source>Clin Sports Med</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>; xi.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1754337112442620">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Omalu</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeKosky</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Chronic traumatic encephalopathy in a national football league player: part II</article-title>. <source>Neurosurgery</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>59</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>1086</fpage>–<lpage>1092</lpage>; discussion: 92–93.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1754337112442620">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Omalu</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeKosky</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Minster</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Chronic traumatic encephalopathy in a National Football League player</article-title>. <source>Neurosurgery</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>57</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>128</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>; discussion: 34.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1754337112442620">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crisco</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenwald</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Let’s get the head further out of the game: a proposal for reducing brain injuries in helmeted contact sports</article-title>. <source>Current Sports Medicine Reports</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1754337112442620">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rowson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duma</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Development of the STAR Evaluation System for Football Helmets: Integrating Player Head Impact Exposure and Risk of Concussion</article-title>. <source>Ann Biomed Engng</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>39</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>2130</fpage>–<lpage>2140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1754337112442620">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Broglio</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schnebel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sosnoff</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Biomechanical properties of concussions in high school football</article-title>. <source>Medicine Science Sports Exercise</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>42</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>2064</fpage>–<lpage>2071</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1754337112442620">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Duma</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manoogian</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bussone</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of real-time head accelerations in collegiate football players</article-title>. <source>Clin J Sport Med</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1754337112442620">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Duma</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Past, present, and future of head injury research</article-title>. <source>Exerc Sport Sci Rev</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1754337112442620">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guskiewicz</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mihalik</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Measurement of head impacts in collegiate football players: relationship between head impact biomechanics and acute clinical outcome after concussion</article-title>. <source>Neurosurgery</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>61</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1244</fpage>–<lpage>1253</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1754337112442620">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rowson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brolinson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goforth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Linear and angular head acceleration measurements in collegiate football</article-title>. <source>J Biomech Engng</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>131</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>061016</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1754337112442620">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoth</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stitzel</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gayzik</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The pathogenesis of pulmonary contusion: An open chest model in the rat</article-title>. <source>J Trauma</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>61</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1754337112442620">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Traumatic pulmonary pathology measured with computed tomography and a semiautomated analytic method</article-title>. <source>Clin Imag</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>32</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>346</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1754337112442620">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>NOCSAE (National Operating Committee on Standards for Athletic Equipment)</collab>. <source>Standard performance specification for newly manufactured football helmets</source>. <year>2011</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1754337112442620">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>NOCSAE (National Operating Committee on Standards for Athletic Equipment)</collab>. <source>Standard test method and equipment used in evaluating the performance characteristics of protective headgear/equipment</source>. <year>2011</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1754337112442620">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gadd</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Use of a weighted-impulse criterion for estimating injury hazard</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of the 10th Stapp car crash conference</conf-name>. SAE paper 660793, <conf-date>1966</conf-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1754337112442620">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hackney</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kahane</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The new car assessment program: five star rating system and vehicle safety performance characteristics</article-title>. SAE paper 851245, <year>1995</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1754337112442620">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laituri</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Considerations of “combined probability of injury” in the next-generation USA frontal NCAP</article-title>. <source>Traffic Inj Prev</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1754337112442620">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stitzel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kemper</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Myopia and hyperopia’s effect on probability of globe rupture due to a foreign body impact</article-title>. <source>Invest Ophth Vis Sci</source> <year>2005</year>; <fpage>46</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1754337112442620">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gayzik</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danelson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Quantification of age-related shape change of the human rib cage through geometric morphometrics</article-title>. <source>J Biomechs</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>41</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1545</fpage>–<lpage>1554</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1754337112442620">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gayzik</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gabler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of crash-induced thoracic loading resulting in pulmonary contusion</article-title>. <source>J Trauma</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>66</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>840</fpage>–<lpage>849</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1754337112442620">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gayzik</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoth</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stitzel</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Finite element-based injury metrics for pulmonary contusion via concurrent model optimization</article-title>. <source>Biomech Model Mechs</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>520</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1754337112442620">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rowson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duma</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Can footwear affect achilles tendon loading?</article-title> <source>Clin J Sport Med</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>344</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1754337112442620">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rowson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNeely</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brolinson</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Biomechanical analysis of football neck collars</article-title>. <source>Clin J Sport Med</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1754337112442620">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beeman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kemper</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Madigan</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of bracing on human kinematics in low-speed frontal sled tests</article-title>. <source>Ann Biomed Engng</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>39</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>2998</fpage>–<lpage>3010</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1754337112442620">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Manoogian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNeely</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Head acceleration is less than 10 percent of helmet acceleration in football impacts</article-title>. <source>Biomed Sci Instrumentation</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1754337112442620">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crisco</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenwald</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An algorithm for estimating acceleration magnitude and impact location using multiple nonorthogonal single-axis accelerometers</article-title>. <source>J Biomech Engng</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>126</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>849</fpage>–<lpage>854</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1754337112442620">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rowson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duma</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rotational head kinematics in football impacts: an injury risk function for concussion</article-title>. <source>Ann Biomed Engng</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>40</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1754337112442620">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rowson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A six degree of freedom head acceleration measurement device for use in football</article-title>. <source>J Appl Biomechs</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1754337112442620">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crisco</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Frequency and location of head impact exposures in individual collegiate football players</article-title>. <source>J Athletic Training</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>549</fpage>–<lpage>559</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1754337112442620">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Broglio</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sosnoff</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Head impacts during high school football: a biomechanical assessment</article-title>. <source>J Athletic Training</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>44</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>342</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1754337112442620">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mihalik</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Measurement of head impacts in collegiate football players: an investigation of positional and event-type differences</article-title>. <source>Neurosurgery</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>61</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1229</fpage>–<lpage>1235</lpage>; discussion: 35.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1754337112442620">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schnebel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gwin</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>In vivo study of head impacts in football: a comparison of National Collegiate Athletic Association Division I versus high school impacts</article-title>. <source>Neurosurgery</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>60</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>490</fpage>–<lpage>495</lpage>; discussion: 5–6.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1754337112442620">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kemper</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Santago</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stitzel</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Biomechanical response of human spleen in tensile loading</article-title>. <source>J Biomechs</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>348</fpage>–<lpage>355</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1754337112442620">
<label>36.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kemper</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reducing chest injuries in automobile collisions: rib fracture timing and implications for thoracic injury criteria</article-title>. <source>Ann Biomed Engng</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>39</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>2141</fpage>–<lpage>2151</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1754337112442620">
<label>37.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Duma</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kemper</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stitzel</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rib fracture timing in dynamic belt tests with human cadavers</article-title>. <source>Clin Anat</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1754337112442620">
<label>38.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Manoogian</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bisplinghoff</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of strain rate on the tensile material properties of human placenta</article-title>. <source>J Biomech Engng</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>131</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>091008</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1754337112442620">
<label>39.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kemper</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stitzel</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Biomechanical response of the human clavicle: the effects of loading direction on bending properties</article-title>. <source>J Appl Biomechs</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1754337112442620">
<label>40.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Manoogian</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bisplinghoff</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic tensile properties of human placenta</article-title>. <source>J Biomechs</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>41</volume>(<issue>16</issue>): <fpage>3436</fpage>–<lpage>3440</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1754337112442620">
<label>41.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duma</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Concussions experienced by major league baseball catchers and umpires: field data and experimental baseball impacts</article-title>. <source>Ann Biomed Engng</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>40</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>150</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>