<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JRA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjra</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Renin Angiotensin Aldosterone Syst</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of the Renin-Angiotensin-Aldosterone System</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1470-3203</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1752-8976</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1470320311427755</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1470320311427755</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Angiotensin converting enzyme insertion/deletion polymorphism and risk of pregnancy hypertensive disorders: a meta-analysis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Zhen</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1470320311427755">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1470320311427755">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1470320311427755">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Fang</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1470320311427755">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1470320311427755">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Yonggang</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1470320311427755">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Fei</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1470320311427755">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Hongbo</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1470320311427755">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1470320311427755"><label>1</label>Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics, the first affiliated hospital of Chongqing University of Medical Sciences, Chongqing, China</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1470320311427755"><label>2</label>Department of Obstetrics, Chongqing Hospital for Maternal and Children’s Care, Chongqing, China</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1470320311427755"><label>3</label>Department of Liver and Vascular Surgery, West China Hospital, Sichuan University, Sichuan Province, China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1470320311427755">Hongbo Qi, Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics, the first affiliated hospital of Chongqing University of Medical Sciences, NO 1, youyi road, Yuan Jia Gang, Chongqing, 400042, China. E-mail: <email>cqhongboqi@163.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1470320311427755">
<label>*</label>
<p>These authors contributed equally.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>184</fpage>
<lpage>195</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><italic>Background:</italic> The angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) gene insertion/deletion (I/D) polymorphism has been reported inconsistently as being associated with risk of pregnancy hypertensive disorders (PHDs). We examined these associations by performing a meta-analysis.</p>
<p><italic>Methods:</italic> Two investigators independently consulted the Medline, Embase, CNKI, and Chinese Biomedicine databases. Odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (95% CIs) were calculated in ﬁxed- and random-effects models when appropriate. Subgroup analyses were performed by ethnicity, types of PHD (gestational hypertension, pre-eclampsia and eclampsia), country and Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) in controls.</p>
<p><italic>Results:</italic> This meta-analysis included 30 case–control studies with 3523 cases and 4817 controls. Overall, we found that the DD variant of the ACE I/D polymorphism was associated with a significantly increased PHD risk. In the subgroup analysis by ethnicity, the results suggested that the DD genotype was significantly associated with risk of PHD development among Asians and Caucasians. Moreover, when stratifying by types of PHD, a significantly increased risk was observed for pre-eclampsia. Interestingly, when stratifying by country, a significantly elevated risk was found among ‘others’ countries (those that were not China or Korea). Limiting the analysis to the studies within HWE, the results were persistent and robust.</p>
<p><italic>Conclusion:</italic> This meta-analysis suggests that the I/D polymorphism of ACE may be associated with PHD risk, especially among Asians and Caucasians.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Angiotensin-converting enzyme</kwd>
<kwd>meta-analysis</kwd>
<kwd>polymorphism</kwd>
<kwd>pregnancy hypertensive disorders</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1470320311427755" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Hypertensive disorders in pregnancy signiﬁcantly increase perinatal maternal and neonatal morbidity and mortality. Pregnancy hypertensive disorders (PHDs) – mainly including gestational hypertension (GH), pre-eclampsia and eclampsia – are the second most common cause of maternal death following postpartum haemorrhage in China.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1470320311427755">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1470320311427755">2</xref></sup> The incidence of PHDs in China is 9%, while incidence of GH, pre-eclampsia, and eclampsia is 5.4, 3.5, and 0.1%, respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1470320311427755">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1470320311427755">2</xref></sup> As reported by Khan et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1470320311427755">3</xref></sup> PHDs are among the top four causes of maternal mortality in developed and developing regions of the world. Two studies, performed by Clark et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1470320311427755">4</xref></sup> and Berg et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1470320311427755">5</xref></sup> reported that PHDs were the ﬁrst and the third most common cause of maternal death among US populations. The best approach to reduce PHD-related complications is early identification of individuals who have higher risk. Despite extensive research in this ﬁeld, the aetiology and pathogenesis of PHDs are still obscure. More and more studies have evidenced that PHDs are diseases with genetic susceptibility.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1470320311427755">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1470320311427755">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>The renin–angiotensin system (RAS) is pivotal in regulating blood pressure and uteroplacental blood ﬂow.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1470320311427755">8</xref></sup> Genes coding for components of the RAS are considered to be candidates that may affect the risk of GH and pre-eclampsia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1470320311427755">9</xref></sup> Angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) is an important circulating enzyme in the RAS, which catalyses the conversion of angiotensin I to angiotensin II and degrades bradykinin. A common insertion/deletion (I/D) polymorphism in intron 16 within the ACE gene was previously reported to be associated with different plasma ACE levels, and individuals carrying the D allele had higher ACE activities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1470320311427755">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1470320311427755">11</xref></sup> The I/D polymorphism within the ACE gene has therefore been extensively studied in several cardiovascular adult diseases, such as coronary heart disease, stroke, and renal disease.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1470320311427755">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1470320311427755">15</xref></sup></p>
<p>Over the last two decades, a number of case–control studies have been conducted to investigate the association between the I/D polymorphism of ACE and PHD risk in humans. However, these studies reported conflicting results. In 2006, Serrano et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1470320311427755">16</xref></sup> published ﬁndings from a meta-analysis (based on 2596 cases and 3828 controls from 22 studies) of the ACE I/D single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) and pre-eclampsia risk. They concluded that the observed small nominal increase in risk of pre-eclampsia associated with the ACE D-allele was due to small-study bias. On the contrary, Medica et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1470320311427755">6</xref></sup> found a statistical signiﬁcance between the ACE I/D polymorphism and pre-eclampsia risk when the polymorphism was considered under a recessive model (odds ratio [OR] = 1.51, 95% confidence interval [CI] = 1.17, 1.94). Both these meta-analyses were based on ACE I/D polymorphism and pre-eclampsia risk, and the sample size was small. In order to derive a more comprehensive estimation of the association between the ACE I/D polymorphism and risk of PHDs (including GH, pre-eclampsia and eclampsia), we conducted a meta-analysis to assess the association between the ACE I/D polymorphism and PHD susceptibility.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1470320311427755" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="section3-1470320311427755">
<title>Publication search</title>
<p>We consulted the PubMed, Embase, CNKI (China National Knowledge Infrastructure) and Chinese Biomedicine databases for all studies on the association between ACE polymorphisms and PHD risk (last search update 15 April 2011). The following key words were used: ‘pregnancy hypertensive disorders’ ‘pregnancy-induced hypertension’ or ‘gestational hypertension’ or ‘preeclampsia’ or ‘eclampsia’, ‘angiotensin-converting enzyme’ or ‘ACE’, and ‘polymorphism’ or ‘mutation’ or ‘variant’. The search was without restriction on language, conducted on human subjects. The reference lists of reviews and retrieved articles were hand-searched at the same time. If more than one article was published by the same author using the same case series, we selected the study where the most individuals were investigated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1470320311427755">
<title>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title>
<p>We reviewed abstracts of all citations and retrieved studies. The following criteria were used to include published studies: (i) case–control studies conducted to evaluate the association between ACE I/D polymorphism and PHD risk; (ii) sufficient genotype data were presented to calculate the ORs and 95% CIs; (iii) The paper should clearly describe PHD diagnoses and the sources of cases and controls. Major reasons for exclusion of studies were (i) no control; (ii) duplicate; (iii) insufficient data were reported.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1470320311427755">
<title>Data extraction</title>
<p>Two investigators extracted information from all eligible publications independently according to the inclusion criteria listed above. Disagreements were resolved by discussion between the two investigators. The following characteristics were collected from each study: ﬁrst author, year of publication, country/region of the ﬁrst or corresponding author, ethnicity, number of cases and controls, genotyping methods, matching variables, minor allele frequency (MAF) in controls, and evidence of Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium (HWE). Different ethnicities were categorized as Asian, Caucasian, and others.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1470320311427755">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>We ﬁrst assessed HWE in the controls for each study using goodness-of-ﬁt test (<italic>chi-square</italic> or <italic>Fisher’s exact</italic> test) and a <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered as signiﬁcant disequilibrium. The strength of the association between PHDs and the ACE I/D polymorphism was estimated using ORs, with the corresponding 95% CIs. The pooled ORs were performed for a co-dominant model (DD vs. II, ID vs. II), a dominant model (DD + ID vs. II), and a recessive model (DD vs. ID + II). We also carried out the stratiﬁed analyses by ethnicity, types of PHDs (GH, pre-eclampsia and eclampsia), country and HWE in controls.</p>
<p>Both the Cochran’s Q statistic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1470320311427755">17</xref></sup> to test for heterogeneity and the <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> statistic to quantify the proportion of the total variation due to heterogeneity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1470320311427755">18</xref></sup> were calculated. A <italic>p-</italic>value of more than the nominal level of 0.10 for the Q statistic indicated a lack of heterogeneity across studies, allowing for the use of a fixed-effects model (the Mantel–Haenszel method)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1470320311427755">19</xref></sup>; if the <italic>p</italic>-value in the Cochran’s Q statistic was less than 0.10, the random-effects model (the DerSimonian and Laird method) was used.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1470320311427755">20</xref></sup> To explore sources of heterogeneity across studies, we did logistic meta-regression analyses. We examined the following study characteristics: ethnicity, country, types of PHD, HWE in controls (yes/no), genotyping methods and study sample size (≤ 200 and &gt; 200 subjects). Sensitivity analysis was performed to assess the stability of results.</p>
<p>Several methods were used to assess the potential publication bias. Visual inspection of funnel plot asymmetry was conducted. The Begg’s rank correlation method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1470320311427755">21</xref></sup> and the Egger’s weighted regression method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1470320311427755">22</xref></sup> were used to statistically assess publication bias (<italic>p</italic> &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant). All analyses were done using STATA software, version 11.0 (STATA Corp., College Station, Texas, USA). All the <italic>p</italic>-values were two-sided.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1470320311427755" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section8-1470320311427755">
<title>Characteristics of studies</title>
<p>A total of 248 papers were relevant to the search words. Through screening of the title and reading the abstract and the entire article, 30 eligible articles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1470320311427755">23</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1470320311427755">52</xref></sup> (26 in English<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1470320311427755">23</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1470320311427755">48</xref></sup> and four in Chinese<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1470320311427755">49</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1470320311427755">52</xref></sup>) were selected for this meta-analysis, including 3523 PHD cases and 4817 controls. Study characteristics are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1470320311427755">Table 1</xref>. There were 15 studies analysing Asian patients, 12 studies analysing Caucasian patients, one study analysing African patients, one Mixed race and one Afro-Caribbean. Studies had been carried out in China, Korea, India, Japan, Turkey, USA, UK, Italy, Poland, Brazil, Finland, South Africa, Greece, Colombia, Canada and Russia. PHD types were distributed as follows: 21 studies were concerned with pre-eclampsia, two studies were separately concerned with pre-eclampsia and GH, two studies were separately concerned with GH, pre-eclampsia and eclampsia, and five studies were a mix of pre-eclampsia, GH and eclampsia. The DNA needed for genotyping had been extracted from peripheral blood in all studies and the genotyping methods used included the classic polymerase chain reaction – restriction fragment length polymorphism (PCR-RFLP) assay in 26 out of 30 studies, polymerase chain reaction with confronting two-pair primers (PCR-CTPP) in two studies, allele-speciﬁc oligonucleotide – polymerase chain reaction (ASO-PCR) in one study, and PCR in one study. Only 12 of 30 (40%) studies described the use of positive controls and a different genotyping assay to conﬁrm the data. The genotype distributions among the controls of all studies were consistent with HWE except for three studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1470320311427755">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1470320311427755">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1470320311427755">52</xref></sup></p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1470320311427755" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Characteristics of studies included in the meta-analysis</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1470320311427755" xlink:href="10.1177_1470320311427755-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">First author [Reference]</th>
<th align="left">Year</th>
<th align="left">Country</th>
<th align="left">Ethnicity</th>
<th align="left">Types Of PHD</th>
<th align="left">No. of case</th>
<th align="left">No. of control</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Case(genotype)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Control(genotype)</th>
<th align="left">MAF in control</th>
<th align="left">HWE in control</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="left">II</th>
<th align="left">ID</th>
<th align="left">DD</th>
<th align="left">II</th>
<th align="left">ID</th>
<th align="left">DD</th>
<th/>
<th/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Huang[47]</td>
<td>2001</td>
<td>China</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>PHD<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1470320311427755">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>60</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>0.49</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wang[49]</td>
<td>2004</td>
<td>China</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>PHD</td>
<td>99</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>0.41</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kaur[20]</td>
<td>2005</td>
<td>India</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>GH/PE/E<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1470320311427755">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>50</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>0.56</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Zhu[48]</td>
<td>1998</td>
<td>China</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>PHD</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0.28</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bai[46]</td>
<td>2002</td>
<td>China</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>PHD</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>205</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>85</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>0.36</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Yan[45]</td>
<td>2011</td>
<td>China</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>PHD</td>
<td>113</td>
<td>113</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>0.43</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Aggarwal[38]</td>
<td>2010</td>
<td>India</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>GH/PE<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1470320311427755">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>104</td>
<td>118</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Roberts[21]</td>
<td>2004</td>
<td>South Africa</td>
<td>African</td>
<td>GH/PE/E</td>
<td>78</td>
<td>338</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>142</td>
<td>152</td>
<td>0.66</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Choi[22]</td>
<td>2004</td>
<td>Korea</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>98</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>0.40</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gurdol[23]</td>
<td>2004</td>
<td>Turkey</td>
<td>Caucasian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>89</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>0.56</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Galao[24]</td>
<td>2004</td>
<td>Brazil</td>
<td>Caucasian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>71</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>0.53</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kim[25]</td>
<td>2004</td>
<td>Korea</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>104</td>
<td>114</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Heiskanen[26]</td>
<td>2001</td>
<td>Finland</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>133</td>
<td>115</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kobashi[27]</td>
<td>2005</td>
<td>Japan</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>122</td>
<td>291</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>120</td>
<td>136</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>0.35</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Morgan[28]</td>
<td>1999</td>
<td>UK</td>
<td>Caucasian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Velloso[42]</td>
<td>2007</td>
<td>Brazil</td>
<td>Caucasian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>0.65</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Serrano[43]</td>
<td>2006</td>
<td>Colombia</td>
<td>Mixed</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>665</td>
<td>1046</td>
<td>143</td>
<td>382</td>
<td>140</td>
<td>209</td>
<td>607</td>
<td>230</td>
<td>0.51</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mello[44]</td>
<td>2003</td>
<td>Italy</td>
<td>Caucasian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>0.43</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bouba[29]</td>
<td>2003</td>
<td>Greece</td>
<td>Caucasian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>102</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>0.54</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dizon[30]</td>
<td>1995</td>
<td>USA</td>
<td>Caucasian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>124</td>
<td>200</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>98</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>0.57</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Levesque[31]</td>
<td>2004</td>
<td>Canada</td>
<td>Caucasian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>174</td>
<td>306</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>151</td>
<td>97</td>
<td>0.56</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mozgovaia[32]</td>
<td>2000</td>
<td>Russia</td>
<td>Caucasian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>73</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>0.64</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Roh[33]</td>
<td>1997</td>
<td>Korea</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>115</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Seremak- Mrozikiewicz[34]</td>
<td>2000</td>
<td>Poland</td>
<td>Caucasian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>110</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>0.59</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tamura[35]</td>
<td>1996</td>
<td>USA</td>
<td>Mixed</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>179</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>0.58</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Watanabe[36]</td>
<td>2001</td>
<td>Japan</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>96</td>
<td>96</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Zhou[37]</td>
<td>1999</td>
<td>China</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>78</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Uma[39]</td>
<td>2010</td>
<td>UK</td>
<td>Caucasian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>105</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>0.50</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Li[41]</td>
<td>2007</td>
<td>China</td>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>PE</td>
<td>133</td>
<td>105</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mando[40]</td>
<td>2009</td>
<td>Italy</td>
<td>Caucasian</td>
<td>GH/PE</td>
<td>253</td>
<td>410</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>124</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>187</td>
<td>151</td>
<td>0.60</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1470320311427755">
<p>PHD, pregnancy hypertensive disorders; MAF, minor allele frequency; HWE, Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium; GH, gestational hypertension; PE, preeclampsia; E, Eclampsia.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-1470320311427755">
<label>a</label>
<p>PHD cases were mixed by GH,PE and E. <sup>b</sup>PHD cases were consisted by separate GH,PE and E. <sup>c</sup>PHD cases were consisted by separate GH and PE.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1470320311427755">
<title>Quantitative synthesis</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1470320311427755">Table 2</xref> lists the main results of this meta-analysis. Overall, we found that the variant DD genotype of the I/D polymorphism was associated with a significantly increased PHD risk (homozygote comparison: OR = 1.48, 95% CI = 1.14–1.92; recessive model comparison: OR = 1.51, 95% CI = 1.23–1.86) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1470320311427755">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1470320311427755" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Stratiﬁed analyses of the angiotesin-converting enzyme gene polymorphism on risk of pregnancy hypertensive disorders (PHDs)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1470320311427755" xlink:href="10.1177_1470320311427755-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variables</th>
<th align="left"><italic>N</italic><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1470320311427755">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">DD versus II</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">ID versus II</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">ID + DD versus II</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">DD versus ID + II</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-value<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1470320311427755">b</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-value<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1470320311427755">b</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-value<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1470320311427755">b</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">OR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic>-value<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1470320311427755">b</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><bold>Total</bold></td>
<td>30</td>
<td><bold>1.48 (1.14, 1.92)</bold></td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td>1.00 (0.84, 1.20)</td>
<td>0.002</td>
<td>1.18(0.96, 1.44)</td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td><bold>1.51(1.23, 1.86)</bold></td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"><bold>Ethnicity</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>15</td>
<td><bold>1.68 (1.05, 2.68)</bold></td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td>0.99 (0.76, 1.30)</td>
<td>0.005</td>
<td>1.23 (0.89, 1.71)</td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td><bold>1.71 (1.14, 2.57)</bold></td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Caucasian</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1.43 (1.00, 2.04)</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>0.99 (0.70, 1.40)</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>1.16 (0.84, 1.61)</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td><bold>1.51 (1.17, 1.95)</bold></td>
<td>0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Others</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>0.99 (0.77, 1.27)</td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td>0.99 (0.80, 1.23)</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>0.99 (0.80, 1.22)</td>
<td>0.28</td>
<td>0.99 (0.83, 1.19)</td>
<td>0.60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"><bold>Country</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>China</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>2.31 (0.85, 6.26)</td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td>1.17 (0.70, 1.97)</td>
<td>0.004</td>
<td>1.63 (0.84, 3.17)</td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td>2.12 (0.89, 5.05)</td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Korea</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>1.26 (0.44, 3.58)</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>0.63 (0.35, 1.11)</td>
<td>0.15</td>
<td>0.77 (0.36, 1.62)</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>1.63 (0.71, 3.75)</td>
<td>0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Others</td>
<td>20</td>
<td><bold>1.28 (1.03, 1.59)</bold></td>
<td>0.05</td>
<td>1.02 (0.90, 1.17)</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>1.12 (0.94, 1.33)</td>
<td>0.09</td>
<td><bold>1.34 (1.12, 1.60)</bold></td>
<td>0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"><bold>HWE in controls</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>27</td>
<td><bold>1.48 (1.10, 1.99)</bold></td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td>0.95 (0.78, 1.16)</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>1.14 (0.91, 1.43)</td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td><bold>1.56 (1.23, 1.97)</bold></td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>1.53 (0.72, 3.26)</td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>1.40 (0.77, 2.55)</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>1.50 (0.77, 2.90)</td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>1.05 (0.85, 1.29)</td>
<td>0.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"><bold>Types of PHD</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GH</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>1.58 (0.99, 2.52)</td>
<td>0.24</td>
<td>1.28 (0.85, 1.92)</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>1.33 (0.91, 1.96)</td>
<td>0.26</td>
<td>1.31 (0.78, 2.19)</td>
<td>0.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PE</td>
<td>25</td>
<td><bold>1.44 (1.11, 1.88)</bold></td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
<td>0.98 (0.82, 1.18)</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>1.14(0.94,1.39)</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td><bold>1.51(1.22,1.87)</bold></td>
<td>&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Eclampsia</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1.31 (0.67, 2.57)</td>
<td>0.84</td>
<td>1.20 (0.61, 2.36)</td>
<td>0.79</td>
<td>1.25 (0.66, 2.37)</td>
<td>0.87</td>
<td>1.15 (0.76, 1.73)</td>
<td>0.99</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1470320311427755">
<p>HWE, Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium; GH, gestational hypertension; PE, pre-eclampsia. For other abbreviations, see text.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-1470320311427755">
<label>a</label>
<p>Number of comparisons. <sup>b</sup>The <italic>p</italic>-value of Q-test for heterogeneity test. Random-effects model was used when the <italic>p</italic>-value for heterogeneity test was &lt; 0.1; otherwise, ﬁxed-effects model was used.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig1-1470320311427755" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Forest plot of placental hypertensive disorder risk associated with the angiotensin- converting enzyme I/D polymorphism in overall analysis (DD vs. II).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470320311427755-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In the subgroup analysis by ethnicity, the results suggested that the DD genotype was significantly associated with risk of PHD development among Asians (homozygote comparison: OR = 1.68, 95% CI = 1.05–2.68; recessive model comparison: OR = 1.71, 95% CI =1.14–2.57) and Caucasians (recessive model comparison: OR = 1.51, 95% CI = 1.17–1.95) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1470320311427755">Figure 2</xref>). Moreover, when stratifying by types of PHD, a significantly increased risk was observed for pre-eclampsia homozygote comparison: OR = 1.44, 95% CI = 1.11–1.88; recessive model comparison: OR = 1.51, 95% CI = 1.22–1.87) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1470320311427755">Figure 3</xref>). Since a large part of the analysed studies investigated Chinese and Korean populations, we also performed a stratified analysis by country, dividing the groups into China, Korea and others. Interestingly, when stratifying by country, a significantly elevated risk was found among ‘others’ countries (homozygote comparison: OR = 1.28, 95% CI = 1.03–1.59; recessive model comparison: OR = 1.34, 95% CI = 1.12–1.60), but not among China or Korea (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1470320311427755">Figure 4</xref>). Limiting the analysis to the studies within HWE, the results were persistent and robust (homozygote comparison: OR = 1.48, 95% CI = 1.10–1.99; recessive model comparison: OR = 1.56, 95% CI = 1.23–1.97).</p>
<fig id="fig2-1470320311427755" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Forest plot of placental hypertensive disorder risk associated with the angiotensin- converting enzyme I/D polymorphism in different ethnicities (DD vs. II).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470320311427755-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-1470320311427755" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Forest plot of placental hypertensive disorder risk associated with the angiotensin- converting enzyme I/D polymorphism in pre-eclampsia (DD vs. II).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470320311427755-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-1470320311427755" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Forest plot of placental hypertensive disorder risk associated with the angiotensin- converting enzyme I/D polymorphism in different countries (DD vs. II).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470320311427755-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1470320311427755">
<title>Heterogeneity analysis</title>
<p>There was heterogeneity among studies in overall comparisons and also subgroup analyses. To explore sources of heterogeneity across studies, we assessed all comparison models by ethnicity, country, HWE in controls, genotyping methods and study sample size. As a result, sample size (DD vs. II: <italic>p</italic> = 0.04; recessive model: <italic>p</italic> = 0.002), but not the ethnicity, country, and HWE in controls or genotyping methods, was found to contribute to substantial heterogeneity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1470320311427755">Table 3</xref>). Moreover, meta-regression analyses indicated that sample size could explain 27.90% (DD vs. II), and 66.31% (recessive model) of the <italic>τ</italic><sup>2</sup>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1470320311427755" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Heterogeneity analysis in this meta-analysis</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1470320311427755" xlink:href="10.1177_1470320311427755-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Genetic model</th>
<th align="left">Cochran’s <italic>Q</italic> statistic <italic>p</italic>-value<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1470320311427755">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left"><italic>I<sup>2</sup></italic> statistic (%)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Meta-regression analysis (coefficients, <italic>p</italic>-value<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1470320311427755">b</xref></sup>)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="left">Ethnicity</th>
<th align="left">Country</th>
<th align="left">HWE in control</th>
<th align="left">Genotyping methods</th>
<th align="left">Study sample size</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>DD versus II</td>
<td>92.16 &lt;0.001</td>
<td>68.5</td>
<td>0.99</td>
<td>0.68</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td>0.86</td>
<td>0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ID versus II</td>
<td>55.07 0.002</td>
<td>47.3</td>
<td>0.81</td>
<td>0.41</td>
<td>0.24</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>0.74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ID + DD versus II</td>
<td>81.86 &lt;0.001</td>
<td>64.3</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>0.27</td>
<td>0.49</td>
<td>0.55</td>
<td>0.32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DD versus ID + II</td>
<td>95.51 &lt;0.001</td>
<td>69.6</td>
<td>0.74</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>0.65</td>
<td>0.38</td>
<td>0.002</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-1470320311427755">
<p>HWE, Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium; for other abbreviations, see text. <sup>a</sup>Cochran’s <italic>Q</italic> statistic test, <italic>p</italic> &lt;0.1 was considered as significant heterogeneity. <sup>b</sup>Meta-regression analysis coefficients, <italic>p</italic> &lt;0.05 was considered as significant factor that contributed to heterogeneity.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1470320311427755">
<title>Sensitivity analysis</title>
<p>In the sensitivity analysis, the inﬂuence of each study on the pooled OR was examined by repeating the meta-analysis while omitting each study, one at a time. This procedure conﬁrmed the stability of our overall results. In addition, when excluding the studies that were not in HWE, the results were persistent and robust (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1470320311427755">Table 2</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1470320311427755">
<title>Publication bias</title>
<p>Funnel plot, Begg’s and Egger’s tests were performed to evaluate publication bias of the literature on PHDs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1470320311427755">Figure 5</xref> displayed a funnel plot that examined the ACE I/D polymorphism and overall PHD risk included in the meta-analysis in the homozygote comparison. The shape of the funnel plot did not reveal any evidence of funnel plot asymmetry. The statistical results still did not show publication bias except in the recessive model (DD vs. II: Begg’s test <italic>p</italic> = 0.13, Egger’s test <italic>p</italic> = 0.26; ID vs. II: Begg’s test <italic>p</italic> = 0.54, Egger’s test <italic>p</italic> = 0.87; dominant model: Begg’s test <italic>p</italic> = 0.64, Egger’s test <italic>p</italic> = 0.21; recessive model: Begg’s test <italic>p</italic> = 0.03, Egger’s test <italic>p</italic> = 0.003).</p>
<fig id="fig5-1470320311427755" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Begg’s funnel plot for publication bias test (DD vs II). Each point represents a separate study for the indicated association. LogOR, natural logarithm of OR; s.e., standard error; horizontal line, mean effect size.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470320311427755-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1470320311427755" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE), a peptidyl carboxypeptidase, is an important member of the RAS family that regulates blood pressure by catalysing the conversion of angiotensin I into the potent vasoconstrictor angiotensin II.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1470320311427755">53</xref></sup> Its action causes vasoconstriction, and elevated ACE activity leads to hypertension.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1470320311427755">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1470320311427755">55</xref></sup> The ACE polymorphism is due to the insertion or deletion of an Alu 289 base pair (bp) sequence located at intron 16. A deletion polymorphism (D allele) has been reported to be associated with increased ACE activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1470320311427755">11</xref></sup> Some investigators have previously reported an association between the D allele of ACE and an increased risk of pre-eclampsia or GH.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1470320311427755">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1470320311427755">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1470320311427755">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1470320311427755">47</xref></sup> Moreover, a previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1470320311427755">56</xref></sup> suggested that the DD genotype of the ACE insertion/deletion (I/D) polymorphism and those of either endothelial constitutive nitric oxide synthase (NOS) 4b/a (aa) or angiotensin-II receptor 1 (AT1R) 1166A&gt;C (CC) may pose a genetic risk factor for pre-eclampsia. Given the different ACE activities for the two polymorphic protein variants of the ACE gene, it is biologically plausible that the ACE I/D polymorphism could be associated with an increased PHD risk.</p>
<p>The present meta-analysis, including 3523 cases and 4817 controls from 30 case–control studies, explored the association between the I/D polymorphism of the ACE gene and PHD risk. To the best of our knowledge, this is the ﬁrst meta-analysis of the comprehensive assessment for the relationship between ACE I/D polymorphism and the risk of PHDs (although previous meta-analyses assessed the association between ACE I/D polymorphism and pre-eclampsia risk). We found that individuals with the variant DD genotype were signiﬁcantly associated with an increased PHD risk. In the subgroup analysis by ethnicity, an increased PHD risk was found among both Asians and Caucasians. Moreover, when stratifying by types of PHD, a significantly increased risk was observed for pre-eclampsia. Limiting the analysis to the studies within HWE, the results were persistent and robust. Although some potential biases could not be eliminated, these ﬁndings indicated that the ACE I/D polymorphism might play a role, although modest, in PHD development, and particularly in pre-eclampsia.</p>
<p>When further stratifying by country, a significantly elevated risk was found among ‘others’ countries (including India, Japan, Turkey, USA, UK, Italy, Poland, Brazil, Finland, South Africa, Greece, Colombia, Canada and Russia), but not among China or Korea. Although the reason for these discrepancies is not well known, some possibilities should be considered. On the one hand, it may be due to the differences in the underlying genetic backgrounds and/or environmental and social factors in different populations studied; on the other hand, other factors such as selection bias, significant heterogeneity due to the sample size and different matching criteria may also play a role – for example, cases and controls were matched by age, race, etc. in some studies, but not matched in other studies; even in studies with cases and controls matched, the matching criteria were not the same in different studies.</p>
<p>Our results showed that the DD genotype may increase risk of pre-eclampsia, which is consistent with a previous meta-analysis based on pre-eclampsia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1470320311427755">6</xref></sup> This is probably because most of the pre-eclampsia studies included in the present paper had already been used in the former meta-analysis. However, the ACE I/D polymorphism seems not to increase the risk of GH or eclampsia. One possible factor that would contribute to the discrepancy between different studies which include different types of PHD is that the polymorphism might play a different role in them. GH is deﬁned as a systolic blood pressure of at least 140 mmHg and/or a diastolic blood pressure of at least 90 mmHg measured on at least two occasions at least 6 hours apart after the 20th week of gestation in women known to be normotensive before pregnancy and before 20 weeks’ gestation. Pre-eclampsia is primarily deﬁned as GH plus proteinuria (300 mg or more per 24-hour period). The definition of eclampsia is secure in the presence of generalized edema, hypertension, proteinuria, and convulsions. All of them are characterized by maternal hypertension, but they have different, well-defined characteristics. The simultaneous presence of more than one risk factor could be necessary for leading to the pathology. Thus, the I/D polymorphism and PHD risk may be more relevant in pre-eclampsia patients because the I/D polymorphism needs to act together with further characteristics that cannot be present in other PHD types. A recent study performed by Amaral et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1470320311427755">57</xref></sup> suggesting that inducible nitric oxide synthase genetic variants may affect the susceptibility to pre-eclampsia, but not to GH, supports our hypothesis. Also, even for the same types of PHD, considering the possible small effect size of the genetic polymorphism to disease and the relatively small sample size in some studies, the discrepancy will become apparent since some of these studies may have been underpowered to detect a small but real association. For GH and eclampsia, there are only four and two studies, respectively, included in the analysis with limited sample sizes; therefore, the results should be interpreted with caution.</p>
<p>It seemed that selection bias could have played a role, because the genotype distribution among control subjects disobeyed the law of HWE in three studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1470320311427755">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1470320311427755">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1470320311427755">52</xref></sup> It is widely believed that deviation from HWE may be due to genetic reasons including non-random mating, or the alleles reﬂect recent mutations that have not reached equilibrium, as well as methodological reasons including biased selection of subjects from the population or genotyping errors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1470320311427755">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1470320311427755">59</xref></sup> Despite the reasons for disequilibrium, the results of genetic association studies might be spurious if the distribution of genotypes in the control groups were not in HWE.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1470320311427755">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1470320311427755">61</xref></sup></p>
<p>When stratifying for HWE in controls, a signiﬁcantly increased risk of PHD was found among those studies with controls in HWE, suggesting that this factor probably had little effect on the overall estimates.</p>
<p>Obvious heterogeneity between studies was observed in overall comparisons and also some subgroup analyses, and then meta-regression analysis was used to explore sources of heterogeneity. We found that the study sample size contributed to potential heterogeneity in this meta-analysis. Moreover, the types of PHD could also be a potential factor contributing to between-study heterogeneity. Different types of PHD are pooled together in this meta-analysis, which is a potential source of large heterogeneity, even though the use of meta-regression analysis did not show it. Another important issue for any meta-analysis is publication bias due to selective publication of reports. In the current study, Begg’s funnel plot and Egger’s test were performed to evaluate this problem. Both the shape of funnel plots and statistical results did not show publication bias except for in the recessive model. It is worthy of mention that the results held when the sensitivity analysis was performed, which implied that the results were reliable.</p>
<p>Some limitations of this meta-analysis should be addressed. First, the total number of cases and controls seemed perfectly; however, the subjects for GH and eclampsia were too small to detect the potentially existence of a small genetic effect. Therefore, more studies with a larger sample size and providing more detail information are needed. Second, a significant publication bias was observed in the recessive model. It is possible that some unpublished studies, which more often provide evidence of negative or null effects, were not included in this analysis. This is because of studies with negative or null results would have been harder to publish than studies with positive results. Third, there was signiﬁcant between-study heterogeneity in the sample numbers from studies of the ACE I/D polymorphism, and the genotype distribution also showed deviation from HWE in some studies.</p>
<p>In spite of these limitations, our meta-analysis also had advantages. First, a comprehensive searching strategy based on computer-assisted and manual searching allowed the eligible studies to be included as far as possible. Second, the quality of case–control studies included in the current meta-analysis was satisfactory and met our inclusion criterion. In addition, the method of this meta-analysis was well designed before initiation, by using explicit methods for study selection, data extraction, and data analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1470320311427755" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In conclusion, this meta-analysis suggests that the ACE I/D polymorphism may contribute to genetic susceptibility for pre-eclampsia. Since limited studies were from Africans, African-Americans and Americans, it is critical that larger and well-designed multicentric studies based on Africans, Africans-Americans and Americans should be performed to re-evaluate the association. Moreover, further studies estimating the effect of gene–gene and gene–environment interactions may eventually provide a better, comprehensive understanding of the association between the ACE I/D polymorphism and PHD risk.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank the anonymous reviewer and the editor for their constructive comments on revising this manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>This work was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 30901720) and PhD Programs Foundation of Ministry of Education of China (No 20090181120111).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>We declare that there is no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mayes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Demianczuk</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davidge</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newburn-Cook</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Impact of pregnancy-induced hypertension on fetal growth</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>180</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buekens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pridjian</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pregnancy-induced hypertension and perinatal mortality</article-title>. <source>J Reprod Med</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wojdyla</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Say</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>WHO analysis of causes of maternal death: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>307</volume>: <fpage>1066</fpage>–<lpage>1074</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Belfort</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dildy</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Maternal death in the 21st century: causes, prevention, and relationship to cesarean delivery</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>199</volume>: <fpage>36.e1</fpage>–<lpage>36.e5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Preventability of pregnancy-related deaths</article-title>. <source>Obstet Gynecol</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>1228</fpage>–<lpage>1234</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Medica</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kastrin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peterlin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Genetic polymorphisms in vasoactive genes and preeclampsia: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Immunology and genetic of preeclampsia</article-title>. <source>Clin Dev Immunol</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schauser</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Puolsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Current topic: the uteroplacental renin-angiotensin system</article-title>. <source>Placenta</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>468</fpage>–<lpage>477</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lachmeijer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pals</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aarnoudse</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>ten Kate</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arngrimsson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Searching for preeclampsia genes: the current position</article-title>. <source>Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ehlers</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riordan</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Angiotensin-converting enzyme: new concepts concerning its biological role</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <year>1989</year>; <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>5311</fpage>–<lpage>5318</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rigat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hubert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alhenc-Gelas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cambien</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Corvol</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soubrier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An insertion/deletion polymorphism in the angiotensin I-converting enzyme gene accounting for half the variance of serum enzyme levels</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source> <year>1990</year>; <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>1343</fpage>–<lpage>1346</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Keavney</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parish</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Large-scale test of hypothesised associations between the angiotensin-converting enzyme insertion/deletion polymorphism and myocardial infarction in about 5,000 cases and 6,000 controls. International Studies of Infarct Survival (ISIS) Collaborators</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>355</volume>: <fpage>434</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Casas</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hingorani</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bautista</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analysis of genetic studies in ischemic stroke: thirty-two genes involving approximately 18,000 cases and 58,000 controls</article-title>. <source>Arch Neurol</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>1652</fpage>–<lpage>1661</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bonnici</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keavney</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danesh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Angiotensin converting enzyme insertion or deletion polymorphism and coronary restenosis: meta-analysis of 16 studies</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>325</volume>: <fpage>517</fpage>–<lpage>520</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Angiotensin-I converting enzyme insertion/deletion polymorphism and its association with diabetic nephropathy: a meta-analysis of studies reported between 1994 and 2004 and comprising 14,727 subjects</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>1008</fpage>–<lpage>1016</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Díaz</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Páez</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Angiotensin-converting enzyme I/D polymorphism and preeclampsia risk: evidence of small-study bias</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e520</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The combination of estimates from different experiments</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source> <year>1954</year>; <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>129</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deeks</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Measuring inconsistency in meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>327</volume>:<fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mantel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haenszel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Statistical aspects of the analysis of data from retrospective studies of disease</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source> <year>1959</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>719</fpage>–<lpage>748</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DerSimonian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analysis in clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Control Clin Trials</source> <year>1986</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mazumdar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Operating characteristics of a rank correlation test for publication bias</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source> <year>1994</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1088</fpage>–<lpage>1101</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davey Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Minder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>315</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khuller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sherawat</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Association of angiotensin-converting enzyme gene polymorphism with pregnancy-induced hypertension</article-title>. <source>Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>929</fpage>–<lpage>933</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moodley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pegoraro</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hypertension-related gene polymorphisms in pre-eclampsia, eclampsia and gestational hyper-tension in Black South African women</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>945</fpage>–<lpage>948</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Association of Angiotensin-converting enzyme and angiotensinogen gene polymorphisms with preeclampsia</article-title>. <source>J Korean Med Sci</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gurdol</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Isbilen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Isbir</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dirican</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The association between preeclampsia and angiotensin-converting enzyme insertion/deletion polymorphism</article-title>. <source>Clin Chim Acta</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>341</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>131</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Galao</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>da Costa</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scheibe</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Figueiredo</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Angiotensin-converting enzyme gene polymorphism in preeclampsia and normal pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>191</volume>: <fpage>821</fpage>–<lpage>824</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Associations of polymorphisms of the angiotensinogen M235 polymorphism and angiotensin-converting-enzyme intron 16 insertion/deletion polymorphism with preeclampsia in Korean women</article-title>. <source>Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heiskanen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pirskanen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hiltunen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Insertion–deletion polymorphism in the gene for angiotensin-converting enzyme is associated with obstetric cholestasis but not with preeclampsia</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>185</volume>: <fpage>600</fpage>–<lpage>603</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kobashi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shido</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Insertion/deletion polymorphism of the angiotensin-converting enzyme gene and preeclampsia in Japanese patients</article-title>. <source>Semin Thromb Hemost</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>346</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Angiotensin-converting enzyme insertion–deletion polymorphism in normotensive and pre-eclamptic pregnancies</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>765</fpage>–<lpage>768</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bouba</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Makrydimas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalaitzidis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Interaction between the polymorphisms of the renin-angiotensin system in preeclampsia</article-title>. <source>Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dizon-Townson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lompe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A common genetic variant of the angiotensin converting enzyme is associated with both preeclampsia and chronic hypertension [abstract]</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>172</volume>: <fpage>374</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levesque</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moutquin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rousseau</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Implication of an AGT haplotype in a multigene association study with pregnancy hypertension</article-title>. <source>Hypertension</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mozgovaia</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malysheva</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ivashchenko</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Branov</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Genetic predisposition to pre-eclampsia: polymorphism of genes involved in regulation of endothelial functions</article-title>. <source>Balkan J Med Genetics</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roh</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A common genetic variant of the angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE) gene and pregnancy induced hypertensive disorders</article-title>. <source>Korean J Obstet Gynecol</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1189</fpage>–<lpage>1199</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seremak-Mrozikiewicz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drews</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malewski</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slomko</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mrozikiewicz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Polymorphic genotypes of the angiotensin-converting enzyme in severe pregnancy-induced hypertension</article-title>. <source>Arch Perinat Med</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johanning</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldenberg</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DuBard</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of angiotensin-converting enzyme gene polymorphism on pregnancy outcome, enzyme activity, and zinc concentration</article-title>. <source>Obstet Gynecol</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>502</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamakawa-Kobayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arinami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evidence for an association of the R485K polymorphism in the coagulation factor V gene with severe preeclampsia from screening 35 polymorphisms in 27 candidate genes</article-title>. <source>Thromb Haemost</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>1594</fpage>–<lpage>1595</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Detection of insertion/deletion polymorphism of angiotensin converting enzyme gene in preeclampsia</article-title>. <source>Chin J Med Genet</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Endothelial nitric oxide synthase, angiotensin-converting enzyme and angiotensinogen gene polymorphisms in hypertensive disorders of pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Hypertens Res</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>477</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Uma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forsyth</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Struthers</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Godfrey</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Polymorphisms of the angiotensin converting enzyme gene in early-onset and late-onset pre-eclampsia</article-title>. <source>J Matern Fetal Neonatal Med</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>874</fpage>–<lpage>879</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mandò</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Antonazzo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tabano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Angiotensin-converting enzyme and adducin-1 polymorphisms in women with preeclampsia and gestational hypertension</article-title>. <source>Reprod Sci</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>819</fpage>–<lpage>826</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Angiotensin-converting enzyme insertion/deletion (ACE I/D) and angiotensin II type 1 receptor (AT1R) gene polymorphism and its association with preeclampsia in Chinese women</article-title>. <source>Hypertens Pregnancy</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Velloso</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalapothakis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reduced plasma levels of angiotensin-(1-7) and renin activity in preeclamptic patients are associated with the angiotensin I-converting enzyme deletion/deletion genotype</article-title>. <source>Braz J Med Biol Res</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Díaz</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Páez</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Angiotensin-converting enzyme I/D polymorphism and preeclampsia risk: evidence of small-study bias</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e520</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parretti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gensini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Maternal–fetal flow, negative events, and preeclampsia: role of ACE I/D polymorphism</article-title>. <source>Hypertension</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>932</fpage>–<lpage>937</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kulane</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Di</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Maternal and fetal angiotensin-converting enzyme gene insertion/deletion polymorphism not associated with pregnancy-induced hypertension in Chinese women</article-title>. <source>J Matern Fetal Neonatal Med</source> <year>2011</year> Jan 20. [Epub ahead of print].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Angiotensinogen and angiotensin-I converting enzyme gene variations in Chinese pregnancy induced hypertension</article-title>. <source>Hua Xi Yi Ke Da Xue Xue Bao</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Study on the relation between the angiotensin converting enzyme gene and pregnancy induced hypertension</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Fu Chan Ke Za Zhi</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Study on a deletion polymorphism of the angiotensin converting enzyme gene in pregnancy induced hypertension</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Fu Chan Ke Za Zhi</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Relationships between polymorphisms of angiotensin-converting enzyme and methylenetetrahydrofolate reductase genes and genetic susceptibility to pregnancy induced hypertension</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Fu Chan Ke Za Zhi</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>372</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ehlers</surname><given-names>MRW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riordan</surname><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Angiotensin-converting enzyme. Biochemistry and molecular biology</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Laragh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds). <source>Hypertension: pathophysiology, diagnosis, and management</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Raven Press</publisher-name>, <year>1990</year>, pp. <fpage>1217</fpage>–<lpage>1231</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Soubrier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hubert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Testut</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nadaud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alhenc-Gelas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Corvol</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Molecular biology of the angiotensin I converting enzyme: biochemistry and structure of the gene</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>476</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Erdos</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Angiotensin I converting enzyme and the changes in our concepts through the years</article-title>. <comment>Lewis K. Dahl memorial lecture</comment>. <source>Hypertension</source> <year>1990</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benedetto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marozio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ciccone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Synergistic effect of renin–angiotensin system and nitric oxide synthase genes polymorphisms in pre-eclampsia</article-title>. <source>Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>678</fpage>–<lpage>682</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palei</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sandrim</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Maternal iNOS genetic polymorphisms and hypertensive disorders of pregnancy</article-title>. <source>J Hum Hypertens</source> <year>2011</year> <month>Jun</month> <day>30</day>. doi: 10.1038/jhh.2011.65<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jhh.2011.65</pub-id>. <comment>[Epub ahead of print]</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chakravarti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Undetected genotyping errors cause apparent overtransmission of common alleles in the transmission/disequilibrium test</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>598</fpage>–<lpage>610</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hosking</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lumsden</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Detection of genotyping errors by Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium testing</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salanti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amountza</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ntzani</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium in genetic association studies: an empirical evaluation of reporting, deviations, and power</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>840</fpage>–<lpage>848</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1470320311427755">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trikalinos</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salanti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khoury</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Impact of violations and deviations in Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium on postulated gene– disease associations</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>163</volume>: <fpage>300</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>