<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JEI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjei</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Early Intervention</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1053-8151</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1053815112470721</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1053815112470721</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Interventions for Toddlers With Autism Spectrum Disorders</article-title>
<subtitle>An Evaluation of Research Evidence</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Schertz</surname><given-names>Hannah H.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1053815112470721">Indiana University, Bloomington, USA</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Reichow</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-1053815112470721">Yale University, New Haven, CT, USA</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Paulo</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Vaiouli</surname><given-names>Potheini</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yildirim</surname><given-names>Emine</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff3-1053815112470721">Indiana University, Bloomington, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1053815112470721">Hannah H. Schertz, School of Education, Indiana University, 201 N. Rose Ave., Bloomington, IN 47405; email: <email>hschertz@indiana.edu</email>.</corresp></author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>34</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>166</fpage>
<lpage>189</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Division for Early Childhood of the Council for Exceptional Children</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Recently emerging intervention studies for toddlers with autism spectrum disorders (ASD) were reviewed through a systematic assessment of intervention outcomes, research rigor, and intervention features. The review includes published peer-reviewed experimental studies of toddlers with high risk for or diagnosis of ASD in which the majority of interventions occurred before age 36 months. Of 20 identified research studies, 6 were group comparison studies, all of which showed small to large magnitudes of effect when a uniform metric was applied. Fourteen were single-case design (SCD) studies, all of which reported effects on a variety of outcomes. When grouped by area of intervention focus (communication, general development, family well-being, imitation, joint attention, and play), commonly identified needs within focus areas were for replication, common measures, and authentic practices. A majority of studies in most focus areas showed strong to acceptable levels of research rigor, though this is an area of ongoing need.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>autism spectrum disorders</kwd>
<kwd>disabilities and development delays</kwd>
<kwd>Part C services</kwd>
<kwd>components of practice</kwd>
<kwd>infants and toddlers</kwd>
<kwd>young children</kwd>
<kwd>instruction</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Research on intervention for toddlers with autism spectrum disorders (ASD) began appearing in the literature over the past decade in response to considerable interest in the potential for earlier intervention to enhance outcomes. These early investigations were furthered by improved general awareness of ASD and early identification initiatives that included toddler screening protocols (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1053815112470721">Robins, Fein, Barton, &amp; Green, 2001</xref>), recommendation by the American Academy of Pediatrics for universal 18-month ASD screening at toddler well-child checks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1053815112470721">Johnson &amp; Myers, 2007</xref>), and a toddler version of the Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule (Luyster et al., 2008). Recently, toddler research in ASD received a boost as private and public funding prioritized early intervention research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1053815112470721">Autism Speaks, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1053815112470721">Interagency Autism Coordinating Committee, 2005</xref>). The emergent stage of toddler intervention research in ASD presents an opportunity to inform early intervention practice and future research at an important juncture.</p>
<p>Our assessment of the need for review of toddler intervention studies first considered reviews of interventions for young children with ASD already conducted, all of which were found to have included all or a majority of children older than age 36 months. These reviews addressed parent-implemented early intervention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1053815112470721">Brookman-Frazee, Vismara, Drahota, Stahmer, &amp; Openden, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1053815112470721">McConachie &amp; Diggle, 2007</xref>), comprehensive intervention programs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1053815112470721">Eikeseth, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1053815112470721">Eldevik et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1053815112470721">Howlin, Magiati, &amp; Charman, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1053815112470721">Reichow &amp; Wolery, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1053815112470721">Rogers &amp; Vismara, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr95-1053815112470721">Virués-Ortega, 2010</xref>), and interventions to facilitate social interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1053815112470721">Reichow &amp; Volkmar, 2010</xref>). Six of the 10 reviews focused on early intensive behavioral intervention studies, the most studied comprehensive intervention approach for preschoolers with autism, and all reported evidence of effects but noted limitations related to methodological concerns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1053815112470721">Eikeseth, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1053815112470721">Eldevik et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1053815112470721">Howlin et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1053815112470721">Reichow, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1053815112470721">Reichow &amp; Wolery, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr95-1053815112470721">Virués-Ortega, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Intervention for preschoolers (ages 3 through 5) typically targets more developmentally advanced outcomes than those for toddlers (ages 1 to 3), is more oriented to group settings, and is guided by policy less integrally centered on families. For these reasons, and because toddlers and families were not prominently featured in the earlier reviews of preschool interventions, findings on preschool interventions can be difficult to generalize to toddlers and their families.</p>
<p>Although the need is clear for toddler intervention research to be reviewed separately, the relatively small collection of studies and their diversity of research designs, intervention purposes, and outcome measures are limiting factors. The reviews of interventions for older children, listed above, grouped similarly focused studies (i.e., peer-mediated, comprehensive, and socially oriented interventions). Because the body of toddler research is smaller, such groupings are unlikely to yield definitive conclusions on intervention effects, but could clarify future research needs on such dimensions as strength of outcomes, research rigor, and replication. A multidimensional review could also begin to explore the intersection between intervention outcomes and practical issues of implementation by reviewing feasibility concerns.</p>
<p>In conducting a systematic review, many decisions must be made (for descriptions of systematic review methods see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1053815112470721">Cooper, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1053815112470721">Higgins &amp; Green, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1053815112470721">Petticrew &amp; Roberts, 2006</xref>). One of the first decisions is how to group (or analyze) across studies, which has been shown to have a significant impact on the conclusions that can be drawn from a review (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1053815112470721">Hattie, 2009</xref>). Most reviews set out to describe the effects of an intervention on specific outcomes. Therefore, it is important to operationalize clearly the outcome variables that will be used in the review. Some reviews group studies by intervention method and attempt to analyze the overall effects of a given intervention. This method is sufficient when a similar intervention is being used to impact similar outcomes, and we have many methods for carrying out such analyses (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1053815112470721">Lipsey &amp; Wilson, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1053815112470721">Odom et al., 2005</xref>). When multiple interventions are used to address multiple outcomes, the “apples and oranges” problem is encountered, and the reviewers must make decisions on how to organize the review and analyze the findings to make meaningful recommendations for practice. When encountering the apples and oranges problem, organizing results by methods across outcomes can provide valuable information related to what works, for whom, and under what conditions.</p>
<p>A valid assessment of outcomes also depends on the rigor by which those outcomes were measured in the reviewed studies. There are many methods of evaluating research rigor in the primary studies included in a systematic review (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1053815112470721">Higgins &amp; Green, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1053815112470721">Jadad et al., 1996</xref>). All methods have advantages and disadvantages depending on the audience and purpose, and there remains no single standard method for evaluating research rigor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1053815112470721">Polanin, 2012</xref>). For quite some time, social scientists have debated how to assess research rigor and how to use the results of such ratings for systematic reviews. One method is to include all studies regardless of rigor, with the assumption that if combined statistically, the stronger studies will provide more weight than the weaker studies, thus providing balance. Others, most notably <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-1053815112470721">Slavin (1986)</xref>, have proposed eliminating poor quality studies from reviews, arguing that the results of studies with poor methodological rigor are more likely to yield results in which we have low confidence. The evidence on the effects of including or excluding low-quality studies is inconclusive with some analyses showing little correlation between study quality and treatment effect (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1053815112470721">Juni, Witschi, Bloch, &amp; Egger, 1999</xref>) and others suggesting that low-quality studies tend to overestimate true effects (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1053815112470721">Moher et al., 1998</xref>). Thus, when conducting a systematic review, it is important to operationalize the approach to assessing rigor and to provide transparency that allows consumers to interpret the findings.</p>
<p>Another element of a multidimensional review is assessment of intervention features with respect to practical issues of implementation. Reporting on the focus of intervention (i.e., intervention content) and elements of intervention delivery (intervention process) could give readers an overview of the extent to which interventions reported to be effective through rigorous research are also appropriate for toddlers and families, and feasible for implementation. A review of intervention focus could describe the extent to which intervention content addresses core concerns for toddlers with ASD, and a review of intervention processes could describe the use of intervention agents and settings that relate to expectations in the field for authentic intervention venues and family roles.</p>
<p>Regarding intervention content, some models used with older children (e.g., professionally implemented interventions focusing on verbal language) may not be developmentally appropriate for toddlers, whose early communicative learning is socially situated within transactional caregiver–child relationships and whose social communication development evolves from preverbal foundations, notably joint attention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1053815112470721">Adamson, McArthur, Markov, Dunbar, &amp; Bakeman, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr93-1053815112470721">Tronick, 2007</xref>). In one example of the importance of joint attention focused relationship-situated learning for toddlers with ASD, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-1053815112470721">Siller and Sigman’s (2008)</xref> longitudinal research found that, independent of initial IQ or language abilities for toddlers with ASD, two factors predicted rates of later language growth: toddlers’ early facility with responding to others’ bids for joint attention and parents’ responsiveness to their children. Research findings on the importance of joint attention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1053815112470721">Bates, Snyder, Bretherten, &amp; Volterra, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1053815112470721">Mundy, Sigman, &amp; Kasari, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-1053815112470721">Tomasello &amp; Farrar, 1986</xref>) and parent responsiveness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1053815112470721">Feldman, Greenbaum, &amp; Yirmiya, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1053815112470721">Landry, Smith, &amp; Swank, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1053815112470721">Mahoney, Kim, &amp; Lin, 2007</xref>) on language outcomes for toddlers with ASD are well replicated in the literature. This evidence has implications for how toddlers’ learning goals are focused and for how parent–child interaction is featured in the intervention design, with its importance extending beyond immediate effects of the intervention.</p>
<p>Beyond addressing toddler-appropriate outcomes, full integration of intervention into toddlers’ and families’ everyday experiences and interactions is emphasized in policy and practice recommendations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1053815112470721">Copple &amp; Bredekamp, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1053815112470721">Individuals with Disabilities Education Act, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1053815112470721">Odom &amp; Wolery, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1053815112470721">Sandall, Hemmeter, Smith, &amp; McLean, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1053815112470721">Schertz, Baker, Hurwitz, &amp; Benner, 2011</xref>). In addition to evidence from well-conducted empirical research, early intervention priorities generate from professional wisdom, experiential knowledge, and stakeholder values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1053815112470721">Reichow &amp; Volkmar, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-1053815112470721">Snyder, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr89-1053815112470721">Straus, Richardson, Glasziou, &amp; Haynes, 2005</xref>). Values-based practices and those based on intervention efficacy may be complementary, as shown by the research showing superior effects for early intervention that is integrated within everyday settings and interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1053815112470721">Dempsey &amp; Keen, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1053815112470721">Dunst, Bruder, Trivette, &amp; Hamby, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1053815112470721">Dunst, Trivette, &amp; Hamby, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1053815112470721">Hebbeler &amp; Gerlach-Downie, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1053815112470721">Mahoney, Boyce, Fewell, Spiker, &amp; Wheeden, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-1053815112470721">Trivette, Dunst, &amp; Hamby, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Another feasibility concern is cost-effectiveness. Studying the impact of varying levels of intervention density requires comparing intervention effects with other variables held constant; however, showing the variance in intervention density even on a small scale, such as in a review of emerging research, could focus questions for future study.</p>
<p>In sum, a broad-based descriptive review of research on intervention for toddlers with ASD and their families is timely for early intervention researchers, practitioners, and families who have a stake in early intervention success. A description of outcomes measured and the extent to which they were achieved, research rigor, intervention focus, and feasibility-related variables could position the field to assess the early status of this research and clarify future research priorities.</p>
<p>The purpose of this review was, thus, to examine research on intervention for toddlers with ASD and their families through an analysis of intervention outcomes, research methods, and intervention features, organized by intervention purpose. Specifically, within intervention focus areas, we aimed to describe and evaluate the nature and strength of intervention outcomes, the rigor of research methods, and the feasibility of reported practices for the field.</p>
<sec id="section1-1053815112470721" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section2-1053815112470721">
<title>Selection criteria</title>
<p>Research studies were included if they met the following criteria: First, the majority of reported intervention time occurred before 36 months of age. In the case of single-case design (SCD) studies with mixed participant ages (i.e., participants with ages both above and below 36 months), we limited our review to the children who were less than 36 months (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1053815112470721">Table 1</xref> notates included participants by study). The age restriction was to assure that the majority of intervention time was spent during the toddler period and that the intervention was designed for toddlers rather than for older children. Second, participants were identified as having or being at high risk for a diagnosis of ASD as determined by one or more of the following: Autism Diagnostic Observational Schedule (ADOS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1053815112470721">Lord, Rutter, DiLavore, &amp; Risi, 1999</xref>), the Autism Diagnostic Interview–Revised (ADI-R; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1053815112470721">Lord, Rutter, &amp; Le Couteur, 1994</xref>), Childhood Autism Rating Scale (CARS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1053815112470721">Schopler, Reichler, &amp; Renner, 1988</xref>), <italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</italic> (4th ed., text rev.; <italic>DSM-IV-TR</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1053815112470721">American Psychiatric Association, 2000</xref>), a reliable toddler autism screening instrument such as the Modified Checklist for Autism in Toddlers (M-CHAT; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1053815112470721">Robins et al., 2001</xref>), and clinical expertise (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1053815112470721">Lord et al., 2006</xref>). We included studies of participants designated to be at high risk for an ASD because diagnostic evaluations of toddler-aged children were not widely available for earlier studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr100-1053815112470721">Zwaigenbaum et al., 2007</xref>). Third, the content of the intervention and how it was delivered was clearly described. Fourth, the reported research used one of the following research designs: randomized controlled trial, quasiexperimental multiple-group comparison, or an SCD (multiple-baseline, withdrawal, or alternating treatments). Finally, the study was published in English in a peer-reviewed journal.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1053815112470721" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Participant and Intervention Descriptions</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1053815112470721" xlink:href="10.1177_1053815112470721-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Participants<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Intervention features<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Study</th>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="center">M/F</th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic> age (months)</th>
<th align="center">Setting</th>
<th align="center">Agent</th>
<th align="center">Density and duration</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Group designs (intervention/control)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053815112470721">Carter et al. (2011)</xref></td>
<td>32/30</td>
<td>51/11</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>Home (child); clinic and home (parent)</td>
<td>Parent for child; SLP for parent</td>
<td>8 parent sessions, 3 parent–child sessions; 15 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1053815112470721">Dawson et al. (2010)</xref></td>
<td>24/24</td>
<td>3.5:1 ratio</td>
<td>23.1/23.9</td>
<td>Home</td>
<td>Therapist, parent</td>
<td>20 hr per week individual, twice monthly parent training; 104 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1053815112470721">Drew et al. (2002)</xref></td>
<td>12/12</td>
<td>11/1; 8/4</td>
<td>21.4/23.6</td>
<td>Home</td>
<td>Parent</td>
<td>3 hr every 6 weeks (professional); 3.5 to 7 hr per week (parent); 52 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1053815112470721">Landa, Holman, O’Neill, and Stuart (2011)</xref></td>
<td>24/24</td>
<td>20/4; 20/4</td>
<td>28.6/28.8</td>
<td>Noninclusive classroom</td>
<td>Professional with parent carryover</td>
<td>10 hr per week classroom, 1.5 hr per month home parent training, parent classes; 26 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr98-1053815112470721">Wetherby and Woods (2006)</xref></td>
<td>17/17</td>
<td>15/2; 13/4</td>
<td>&lt;24</td>
<td>Home, parent–child playgroups</td>
<td>Parent</td>
<td>2 home visits weekly + parent groups; duration varied</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr99-1053815112470721">Zachor, Ben Itzchak, Rabinovich, and Lahat (2007)</xref></td>
<td>19/20</td>
<td>18/1; 19/1</td>
<td>18.8/27.7</td>
<td>Noninclusive classroom; partial for some</td>
<td>Professional</td>
<td>35 hr per week; 52 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Single-case designs<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1053815112470721">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1053815112470721">Brookman-Frazee and Koegel (2004)</xref></td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3/0</td>
<td>34, 32, 29</td>
<td>Home, clinic playroom</td>
<td>Parent</td>
<td>12 sessions; length of session and total duration not specified</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1053815112470721">Cardon and Wilcox (2011)</xref> (4 of 6: E, J, L, A)</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>4/0</td>
<td>33, 28, 32, 33</td>
<td>Clinic</td>
<td>Researcher (SLP)</td>
<td>Three 30-min sessions per week, 5 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1053815112470721">Esch, Carr, and Grow (2009)</xref> (2 of 3: J, M)</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1/1</td>
<td>28, 32</td>
<td>School (separate room)</td>
<td>Researcher</td>
<td>3-5 days/week, 5- to 15-min sessions, 10-20 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1053815112470721">Hine and Wolery (2006)</xref> (1 of 2: C)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0/1</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>Therapy room</td>
<td>Researcher</td>
<td>Five 15-min sessions per week, 10 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1053815112470721">Ingersoll, Dvortcsak, Whalen, and Sikora (2005)</xref> (2 of 3: D, P)</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2/0</td>
<td>30, 32</td>
<td>Clinic</td>
<td>Therapist</td>
<td>2 hr/week, 10 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1053815112470721">Ingersoll and Gergans (2007)</xref> (1 of 3: C)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1/0</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>Clinic</td>
<td>Parent trainer, parent</td>
<td>Two 30- to 40-min sessions per week, 10 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1053815112470721">Jones, Carr, and Feeley (2006)</xref> (4 of 5: P, E, A, D)</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>4/0</td>
<td>25, 26, 34, 26</td>
<td>Study 1: noninclusive classroom, Study 2: home and community</td>
<td>ABA teacher</td>
<td>Study 1: 1-4 sessions/day (time not specified), 2-20 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Study 2: Five sessions/week (time not specified), 5-30 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1053815112470721">Leew, Stein, and Gibbard (2010)</xref></td>
<td>4</td>
<td>4/0</td>
<td>32, 30, 33, 27</td>
<td>Home</td>
<td>Parent</td>
<td>Two to nine 20-min sessions, 2 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1053815112470721">Park, Alber-Morgan, and Cannella-Malone (2011)</xref></td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3/0</td>
<td>29, 31, 29</td>
<td>Home</td>
<td>Parent</td>
<td>Three 40- to 60-min sessions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1053815112470721">Rocha, Schreibman, and Stahmer (2007)</xref> (2 of 3: J, A)</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2/0</td>
<td>27, 26</td>
<td>Clinic</td>
<td>Parent</td>
<td>Three 20-min sessions per week (51 total), 6 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1053815112470721">Schertz and Odom (2007)</xref></td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3/0</td>
<td>24, 33, 22</td>
<td>Home</td>
<td>Parent</td>
<td>1 hr per week; 5 hr per week (parent–child); 9-26 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-1053815112470721">VanDerHeyden, Snyder, DiCarlo, Stricklin, and Vigianos (2002)</xref> (1 of 2: G)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1/0</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>Semi-inclusive classroom</td>
<td>Professional</td>
<td>Not applicable (manipulated environment)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-1053815112470721">Vismara and Lyons (2007)</xref> (2 of 3: child 1, 2)</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2/0</td>
<td>34, 26</td>
<td>Clinic or home</td>
<td>Parent</td>
<td>Two 150-min sessions (5 hr) per week + parent carryover at home, 12 weeks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-1053815112470721">Vismara and Rogers (2008)</xref></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1/0</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>Clinic</td>
<td>Parent</td>
<td>One 90-min session per week with parent + parent carryover, 12 weeks</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1053815112470721"><p>Note: SLP = speech/language pathologist; ABA = applied behavior analysis.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-1053815112470721">
<label>a</label>
<p>Includes age-eligible participants only, specified by first initial.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1053815112470721">
<title>Search methods</title>
<p>The first two authors independently searched the online databases Academic Search Premier and PsycINFO using the search criteria (autis* or pdd or pervasive developmental disorder) <italic>and</italic> intervention <italic>and</italic> (toddler or young child* or preschool or pre-school) in December 2011. In addition, we surveyed pertinent reviews whose inclusion criteria intersected with those of this review (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1053815112470721">Brookman-Frazee et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1053815112470721">Eikeseth, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1053815112470721">Eldevik et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1053815112470721">Howlin et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1053815112470721">McConachie &amp; Diggle, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1053815112470721">Reichow, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1053815112470721">Reichow &amp; Volkmar, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1053815112470721">Reichow &amp; Wolery, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1053815112470721">Rogers &amp; Vismara, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr95-1053815112470721">Virués-Ortega, 2010</xref>). Finally, we searched the “Online First” postings of articles accepted for publication but not yet published for the journals <italic>Autism, Focus on Autism and Other Developmental Disabilities, Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders, Journal of Early Intervention, Research in Autism Spectrum Disorders</italic>, and <italic>Topics in Early Childhood Special Education.</italic></p>
<p>We initially located 679 manuscripts after deleting duplicates in the database search, and no additional studies were identified through reference lists or “online first” searches. Forty manuscripts remained after the first and second authors independently screened each article’s title and abstract, and excluded those that did not describe intervention research or did not include toddler-aged children. We then independently assessed the full papers of the 40 manuscripts, with 20 meeting all inclusion criteria. Of the 20 excluded studies, 7 were excluded due to research design limitations (e.g., no comparison condition for group studies), 2 for insufficient description of the intervention, and 11 because the participants did not fully meet our age criterion. Disagreements were resolved by consensus after comparing evidence.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1053815112470721">
<title>Coding</title>
<p>We first classified each study as using either group comparison or SCD research, and summarized descriptive features of the participants and intervention characteristics as reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1053815112470721">Table 1</xref>. Three participant characteristics were coded from the studies’ participant descriptions. The <italic>number</italic> quantifies the toddler participants in each study. The <italic>age</italic> of the participants is presented as a mean for group research design studies and as specific ages for the SCD studies. Finally, we recorded the <italic>gender breakdown</italic> of the participants. We coded three intervention characteristics. The intervention <italic>setting</italic> was classified by type (home, clinic, or classroom) to determine whether it was the child and family’s natural environment and, for group settings, the extent to which it included natural proportions of toddlers with and without disabilities. The second intervention feature was <italic>agent</italic>, or who delivered the intervention to the child. The third, <italic>density and duration</italic>, was based on the conceptual framework proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1053815112470721">Guralnick (1998)</xref>. Density is defined as the number of hours per week, and duration is defined as the total number of weeks that intervention was provided.</p>
<p>In a second coding scheme, studies were grouped by the <italic>primary intervention focus</italic>, determined by a review of the studies’ purpose statements and reported outcome measures, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1053815112470721">Table 2</xref>. Five areas of intervention focus were identified: general development, communication, family well-being, joint attention, and play. Within these groupings, we determined for each study the reported child-focused intervention strategies and outcomes. We also estimated intervention success, research rigor, and ecological validity.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1053815112470721" position="float">
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption><p>Assessment of Outcomes, Common Strategies, Research Rigor, Ecological Validity, and Limitations by Primary Intervention Focus</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1053815112470721" xlink:href="10.1177_1053815112470721-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<th align="left">Intervention focus</th>
<th align="center">Strategies, with duplicate strategies highlighted<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1053815112470721">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Outcome measures</th>
<th align="center">Success estimates<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1053815112470721">b</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Rigor ratings</th>
<th align="center">Ecological validity<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1053815112470721">c</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Limitations, future research needs</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Communication</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053815112470721">Carter et al. (2011)</xref></td>
<td>MSEL-C</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = −.06</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>Full</td>
<td>Authentic settings and interaction partners</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Predictable routines and environment, video modeling, visual support</td>
<td>VABS-C</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = −.02</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Common measures</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>VABS-S</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .10</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1053815112470721">Esch, Carr, and Grow (2009)</xref></td>
<td>Vocalizations</td>
<td>4 of 4</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>Density and duration: Comparative effects on outcomes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Reinforcement: edible and other, stimulus-stimulus pairing</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Comparison of preverbal vs. verbal approaches on language outcomes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1053815112470721">Ingersoll, Dvortcsak, Whalen, and Sikora (2005)</xref></td>
<td>Expressive language</td>
<td>2 of 2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>None</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Child actions treated as purposeful communication, follow child’s lead, language stimulation</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Replication within and across studies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1053815112470721">Park, Alber-Morgan, and Cannella-Malone (2011)</xref></td>
<td>Picture exchange</td>
<td>3 of 3</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>Full</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Picture Exchange Communication System</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>General development</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1053815112470721">Dawson et al. (2010)</xref></td>
<td>MSEL-C</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .59</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Full</td>
<td>Authentic settings and interaction partners</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Adult <italic>responsivity</italic> and sensitivity to child cues, chaining, enhance child affect and shared engagement, <italic>didactic parent training</italic> in specific curriculum-based strategies, operant conditioning, <italic>shaping, therapy</italic> (speech/language, occupational)</td>
<td>VABS</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .73</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Common measures</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Density and duration: Comparative effects</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Joint attention vs. general developmental approaches: Comparative effects on social communication outcomes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-1053815112470721">Vismara and Rogers (2008)</xref></td>
<td>Vocalizations</td>
<td>2 of 2</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>Partial</td>
<td>Replication within and across intervention approaches</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Antecedent-behavior-consequence, fading, <italic>follow child’s lead, functional assessment</italic>, pivotal response training, prompting, reinforcement, <italic>shaping</italic>, systematic teaching</td>
<td>Imitation</td>
<td>2 of 2</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Research rigor</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Social initiation</td>
<td>2 0f 2</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr98-1053815112470721">Wetherby and Woods (2006)</xref> <italic>Follow child’s lead, functional assessment</italic>, parent–child interaction, positive behavioral support, predictable routines, routines-based intervention</td>
<td>CSBS: social interaction, joint attention, communication</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .98</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>Full</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .88</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .83</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr99-1053815112470721">Zachor, Ben Itzchak, Rabinovich, and Lahat (2007)</xref></td>
<td>ADOS-LC</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .70</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>None</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>ADOS-RSI</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .38</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Group activities, <italic>therapy</italic> (speech/language, occupational)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Family well-being (and child engagement)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1053815112470721">Brookman-Frazee and Koegel (2004)</xref></td>
<td>Child affect</td>
<td>3 of 3</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>Full/partial</td>
<td>Replication of this and other approaches with common measures</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Follow child’s lead, pivotal response training, reinforcement</td>
<td>Parent stress</td>
<td>3 of 3</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Imitation</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1053815112470721">Cardon and Wilcox (2011)</xref></td>
<td>Imitation</td>
<td>4 of 4</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>Authentic settings and interaction partners</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><italic>Reciprocal imitation training</italic> (actions with toys), video modeling</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Replication within and across intervention approaches</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1053815112470721">Ingersoll and Gergans (2007)</xref></td>
<td>Imitation</td>
<td>1 of 1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>Partial</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><italic>Reciprocal imitation training</italic> (object &amp; gesture imitation), corrective feedback for parents, modeling for parents</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Joint attention/social synchrony</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1053815112470721">Drew et al. (2002)</xref></td>
<td>NVIQ</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .71</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>Full</td>
<td>Authentic settings and interaction partners</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Interrupt unwanted behaviors, <italic>reinforcement</italic>, visual support</td>
<td>MCDI-U</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .71</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Common measures</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>MCDI-S</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .56</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1053815112470721">Jones, Carr, and Feeley (2006)</xref></td>
<td>Responding to and initiating joint attention</td>
<td>4 of 4</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>None/partial</td>
<td>Density and duration: Comparative effects</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><italic>Discrete trial training/reinforcement, natural consequences, prompting</italic>, edible <italic>reinforcement</italic></td>
<td/>
<td>4 of 4</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Joint attention vs. communication-focused intervention: Comparative effects on language outcomes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1053815112470721">Landa, Holman, O’Neill, and Stuart (2011)</xref></td>
<td>MSEL-EL</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .15</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>Partial</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><italic>Discrete trial training, follow child’s lead</italic>, interpersonal synchrony promotion, linguistic mapping, <italic>natural consequences</italic>, pivotal response training, <italic>routines-based intervention</italic>, visual support</td>
<td>MSEL-VR</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .32</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Joint attention vs. general development approaches: Comparative effects on social communication outcomes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Initiating joint attention</td>
<td><italic>g</italic> = .31</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Replication within and across approaches</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Research rigor</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1053815112470721">Leew, Stein, and Gibbard (2010)</xref></td>
<td>Competing behaviors</td>
<td>1 of 4</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>Full</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Weighted vest</td>
<td>Joint attention</td>
<td>0 of 4</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1053815112470721">Rocha, Schreibman, and Stahmer (2007)</xref></td>
<td>Responding to joint attention</td>
<td>2 of 2</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>Partial</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><italic>Discrete trial training/reinforcement</italic>, naturalistic behavioral techniques, <italic>pivotal response training, prompting</italic></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1053815112470721">Schertz and Odom (2007)</xref></td>
<td>Joint attention</td>
<td>2 of 3</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>Full</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Child actions treated as purposeful communication, <italic>follow child’s lead</italic>, parent–child interaction, routines-based intervention</td>
<td>Turn taking</td>
<td>3 of 3</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Regarding faces</td>
<td>2 of 3</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-1053815112470721">Vismara and Lyons (2007)</xref></td>
<td>Initiating joint attention</td>
<td>4 of 4</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Partial/full</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><italic>Follow child’s lead</italic>, pivotal response training, <italic>reinforcement</italic></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Play</td>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1053815112470721">Hine and Wolery (2006)</xref></td>
<td>Imitation in play</td>
<td>2 of 2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>Authentic settings and interaction partners</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Video modeling (toy play actions)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Common measures</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-1053815112470721">VanDerHeyden, Snyder, DiCarlo, Stricklin, and Vigianos (2002)</xref></td>
<td>Play</td>
<td>2 of 2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>Link to core social concern in ASD</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Within stimulus prompting (to expand contact with toys)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1053815112470721"><p>Note: MSEL-C = Mullen Scales of Early Learning–Composite; VABS-C = Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales–Communication; VABS-S = Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales–Socialization; VABS = composite; NVIQ = nonverbal IQ; MCDI-U = MacArthur Communicative Development Index– (words understood); MCDI-S = MacArthur Communicative Development Index–Words said; MSEL-EL = Mullen Scales of Early Learning–Expressive Language; MSEL-VR = Mullen Scales of Early Learning–Visual Reception; CSBS = Communication and Symbolic Behavior Scales Developmental Profile; ADOS-LC = Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule–Language and Communication; ADOS-RSI = Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule–Reciprocal Social Interaction; PECS = Picture Exchange Communication System.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-1053815112470721">
<label>a</label>
<p>Duplicates within focus areas are indicated in italics.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-1053815112470721">
<label>b</label>
<p>For group studies, large effects: (<italic>g</italic> ≥ .80); medium effects (<italic>g</italic> = .40-79); small effects (<italic>g</italic> = .20-.39). 1 = <italic>strong</italic>, 2 = <italic>acceptable</italic>, 3 = <italic>insufficient strength</italic>.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-1053815112470721">
<label>c</label>
<p>Full = conducted in (a) the natural environment and (b) with family involvement; partial = only one reported; none = neither reported.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>In addition to the five intervention focus areas, we created a separate (duplicated) grouping of fully parent-implemented interventions. For each, we listed parent-focused intervention strategies. Child- and parent-focused intervention <italic>strategies</italic> were derived from the intervention descriptions in each article. They described specific techniques reportedly used with children and families to achieve targeted outcomes.</p>
<p>Three variables were coded related to research methods and outcomes. First, we recorded up to three primary <italic>outcome measures</italic> (e.g., dependent variables) for each study, choosing the three most relevant outcomes related to global functioning regardless of magnitude of effect if more than three were reported and regardless of whether they were reported as primary or secondary measures.</p>
<p>Second, we adapted the <italic>success estimate</italic> proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1053815112470721">Reichow and Volkmar (2010)</xref> to indicate strength or replicability of effects for group and SCDs, respectively. For group research designs, rather than using effect sizes that may have been reported in the studies, we computed the success estimate as an effect size by comparing posttreatment scores between treatment and comparison groups using Hedges’s <italic>g</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1053815112470721">Hedges &amp; Olkin, 1985</xref>). For SCD studies, we calculated the success estimate using visual analysis to determine whether the intervention was effective for each participant and reported it as a ratio of successful implementations of the independent variable to the total number of implementations attempted. For studies with multiple outcome measures, we calculated a separate success estimate for each outcome.</p>
<p>For <italic>research rigor</italic>, we used the rating rubrics from the Evaluative Method for Determining Evidence-Based Practices in Autism developed by Reichow and colleagues (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1053815112470721">Reichow, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1053815112470721">Reichow, Volkmar, &amp; Cicchetti, 2008</xref>). The evaluative method contains two rating rubrics (one for group design studies and one for SCD studies) that provide a method for rating multiple variables reflecting strong or adequate research design principles (the rubrics are available from the second author). The variable ratings can then be summed within a research report to provide a level of research report strength rating for each study according to the criteria of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1053815112470721">Reichow et al., 2008</xref>. The method has been used to evaluate social skills interventions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1053815112470721">Reichow &amp; Volkmar, 2010</xref>), psychotropic medications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1053815112470721">Siegel &amp; Beaulieu, 2012</xref>), and sight word instruction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr88-1053815112470721">Spector, 2011</xref>), and initial analyses of the method showed good reliability and validity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1053815112470721">Cicchetti, 2011</xref>). We made one modification of the SCD criteria to adapt for the exclusion of participants older than 36 months; for this, we evaluated experimental control across all participants reported in the study, not just the ones included in this review, when studies included participants who did and did not meet our inclusion criteria.</p>
<p>An estimate of <italic>ecological validity</italic> was determined by a “none,” “partial,” or “full” rating based on a simple assessment of each study’s reporting of intervention setting and agent. For a rating of “full,” intervention was assessed as being delivered in the child’s natural environment with the parent having a role in the intervention. For a “none” rating, neither delivery in the child’s natural environment nor parent involvement in the intervention was reported. For a “partial” rating, only one the conditions for setting or agent was met.</p>
<p>Finally, a listing of research needs was generated for each intervention focus area from an assessment of limitations uncovered through the review of coded elements. This assessment considered (a) the extent to which common measures were used within the focus area, (b) whether research was replicated for specific approaches and across intervention approaches within each area, (c) estimates of research rigor, (d) whether the interventions used authentic settings and involved parents, (e) variations in intervention density and duration, (f) the relevance of intervention goals to core concerns in ASD, and (g) comparative effects on outcomes across areas of intervention focus (e.g., preverbal and verbal approaches to promoting social communication and general vs. social-communication-specific intervention).</p>
<p>Each variable in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1053815112470721">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1053815112470721">2</xref> was double coded independently by two of our authors. The extracted data were then compared, and any discrepancy was resolved through mediation and, if necessary, a third opinion. Although we are not reporting interrater agreement data, this is a common coding method used in systematic reviews and meets the standards of the most rigorous systematic review methods (e.g., Cochrane Collaboration; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1053815112470721">Cooper, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1053815112470721">Higgins &amp; Green, 2008</xref>).</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section5-1053815112470721" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Results from the study of toddler intervention research are presented in the three tables. From the 6 group comparison studies and 14 SCD studies, a total of 161 toddler participants received the experimental interventions across the reported studies. Of these, 139 were boys (86%; male:female = 6:1), and the mean participant age at entry was 26.6 months.</p>
<sec id="section6-1053815112470721">
<title>Study Features and Findings by Research Design</title>
<sec id="section7-1053815112470721">
<title>Outcome measures</title>
<p>Findings from the reported research were based on a range of intervention outcomes. All of the six group comparison studies used standardized measures, with one study reporting on a nonstandardized joint attention measure as well (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1053815112470721">Landa, Holman, O’Neill, &amp; Stuart, 2011</xref>). Three of these studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053815112470721">Carter et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1053815112470721">Drew et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1053815112470721">Landa et al., 2011</xref>) used the Mullen Scales of Early Learning (MSEL; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1053815112470721">Mullen, 1995</xref>), and two (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053815112470721">Carter et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1053815112470721">Dawson et al., 2010</xref>) used the Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-1053815112470721">Sparrow, Balla, &amp; Cicchetti, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-1053815112470721">Sparrow, Cicchetti, &amp; Balla, 2005</xref>). Beyond these outcome measures, others were idiosyncratic to individual studies, with one study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr99-1053815112470721">Zachor, Ben Itzchak, Rabinovich, &amp; Lahat, 2007</xref>) using a diagnostic instrument (e.g., Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1053815112470721">Lord et al., 1994</xref>) and two (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1053815112470721">Drew et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr98-1053815112470721">Wetherby &amp; Woods, 2006</xref>) relying on different standardized language measures. The SCD studies used a range of mostly nonstandardized measures that tracked closely with the studies’ intervention foci. Among the SCD studies, the most common focus for outcome measures was joint attention in responding or initiating forms with 5 of 14 studies including this outcome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1053815112470721">Jones, Carr, &amp; Feeley, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1053815112470721">Leew, Stein, &amp; Gibbard, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1053815112470721">Rocha, Schreibman, &amp; Stahmer, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1053815112470721">Schertz &amp; Odom, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-1053815112470721">Vismara &amp; Lyons, 2007</xref>). Four studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1053815112470721">Cardon &amp; Wilcox, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1053815112470721">Hine &amp; Wolery, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1053815112470721">Ingersoll &amp; Gergans, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-1053815112470721">Vismara &amp; Rogers, 2008</xref>) reported on child changes in imitation, and three used measures of verbal communication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1053815112470721">Esch, Carr, &amp; Grow, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1053815112470721">Ingersoll, Dvortcsak, Whalen, &amp; Sikora, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-1053815112470721">Vismara &amp; Rogers, 2008</xref>). Other measures included child affect, parent stress, competing behaviors, picture exchange, social initiations, and play.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1053815112470721">
<title>Success estimates and research rigor</title>
<p>For the group comparison studies, the range of effect sizes was −0.06 to 0.98. Using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1053815112470721">Cohen’s (1988)</xref> guidelines to interpret these effect sizes for the 16 outcome measures across the six group comparison studies, we calculated the following: no effects (&lt;.20) on 4 measures, a small effect (<italic>g</italic> = .20−.39) on 3 measures, a medium effect (<italic>g</italic> = .40−.79) on 6 measures, and a large effect (<italic>g</italic> ≥ .80) on 3 measures. For the SCD studies, all studies had positive success estimates with most participants demonstrating the desired effect with the exception of the study by Leew and colleagues (2010), which showed no changes in competing behaviors or joint attention for a majority of their participants. Finally, of the 20 studies, 3 were rated as methodologically “strong,” 13 as “acceptable,” and 4 as having insufficient strength.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1053815112470721">
<title>Setting</title>
<p>As reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1053815112470721">Table 1</xref>, among the described interventions, 5 were fully conducted in home or fully inclusive early childhood settings, and 10 were delivered in clinics or classroom settings that were not fully inclusive (i.e., did not include typical proportions of children with and without disabilities). The remaining 5 interventions were delivered in some combination of home and clinic or specialized classroom/playgroup settings.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1053815112470721">
<title>Intervention agent</title>
<p>In the 10 studies that did not use parents in a primary intervention role, therapists, teachers, or other professionals implemented the intervention. For 3 of these studies, parents participated in a supporting role (e.g., to embed professionally modeled strategies into daily activities). Parent-implemented studies were fairly evenly dispersed among the five areas of intervention focus except for play, which did not use parent-implemented intervention.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1053815112470721">
<title>Density and duration</title>
<p>The number of hours per week devoted to professionally delivered intervention ranged from a restricted number of sessions focusing on a specific skill to more sustained and broadly focused intervention. Of the latter group, the most professionally time-intensive interventions ranged from 10 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1053815112470721">Landa et al., 2011</xref>) to 35 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr99-1053815112470721">Zachor et al., 2007</xref>) hours per week. Importantly, however, the time parents spent in intervention-related activities in the home was typically not reported.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1053815112470721">
<title>Intervention strategies</title>
<p>We identified a total of 39 child-focused intervention strategies from the descriptions of toddler interventions and an additional 7 strategies from descriptions of fully parent-implemented interventions. Overall, the group comparison studies, most of which were developed as comprehensive interventions, reported a broader range of intervention strategies than did the SCD studies, many of which had a narrower intervention scope and some of which were designed to promote a specific skill, such as imitation. The most commonly reported child-focused intervention strategies were following the child’s lead and reinforcement-based strategies. Parent-focused strategies were largely divided between those that provided didactic training on specific intervention components and those that provided broad-based conceptual support with parent discretion on activity choices. Child-focused intervention strategies found in more than one study within an intervention focus subgroup are italicized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1053815112470721">Table 2</xref>, and the same can be found for parent-focused strategies listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1053815112470721">Table 3</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1053815112470721" position="float">
<label>Table 3</label>
<caption>
<p>Parent-Focused Strategies for Fully Parent-Implemented Interventions</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1053815112470721" xlink:href="10.1177_1053815112470721-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Study</th>
<th align="center">Strategies to support parent learning<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1053815112470721">a</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1053815112470721">Brookman-Frazee and Koegel (2004)</xref></td>
<td><italic>Prompt/prompt fading</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053815112470721">Carter et al. (2011)</xref></td>
<td><italic>Parent conceptual support, didactic parent training, promote parent responsiveness</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1053815112470721">Drew et al. (2002)</xref></td>
<td><italic>Parent conceptual support, didactic parent training</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1053815112470721">Leew, Stein, and Gibbard (2010)</xref></td>
<td><italic>Parent selects activities</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1053815112470721">Park, Alber-Morgan, and Cannella-Malone (2011)</xref></td>
<td>Corrective feedback for parents, <italic>didactic parent training</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1053815112470721">Rocha, Schreibman, and Stahmer (2007)</xref></td>
<td><italic>Didactic parent training, prompt</italic>/prompt fading, modeling</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1053815112470721">Schertz and Odom (2007)</xref></td>
<td><italic>Parent conceptual support, parent selects activities</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-1053815112470721">Vismara and Lyons (2007)</xref></td>
<td><italic>Didactic parent training</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-1053815112470721">Vismara and Rogers (2008)</xref></td>
<td><italic>Didactic parent training</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr98-1053815112470721">Wetherby and Woods (2006)</xref></td>
<td><italic>Parent conceptual support, parent selects activities, promote parent responsiveness</italic></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn7-1053815112470721">
<label>a</label>
<p>Duplicated strategies are indicated in italics.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section13-1053815112470721">
<title>Study Features and Findings by Intervention Focus</title>
<sec id="section14-1053815112470721">
<title>Communication interventions</title>
<p>Outcomes measures used for the four communication-focused interventions showed no overlap among them. The one group comparison study in this group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053815112470721">Carter et al., 2011</xref>) reported no general effects on standardized measures from the intervention. The three SCD studies all reported positive change on observational measures from baseline to intervention conditions for the two or three participants in their studies, and adequate research rigor was assessed for all four studies. Generalized effects cannot be ascertained from this group because of variance in intervention methods, goals (vocalizations, requesting through picture symbols, and expressive language), and outcome measures.</p>
<p>Two of the studies were conducted in family homes and were fully parent-implemented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053815112470721">Carter et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1053815112470721">Park, Alber-Morgan, &amp; Cannella-Malone, 2011</xref>), one was conducted in a clinic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1053815112470721">Ingersoll et al., 2005</xref>), and one was conducted in a separate classroom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1053815112470721">Esch et al., 2009</xref>). All were implemented for 10 to 15 weeks or less. No overlap in reported specific intervention strategies was evident.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1053815112470721">
<title>General development interventions</title>
<p>The four studies that focused on general child development (i.e., with intervention targeting multiple developmental domains) had no common measures among them and are therefore not comparable on common criteria. However, all showed moderate to high success estimates on their own measures. Two studies, one a SCD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-1053815112470721">Vismara &amp; Rogers, 2008</xref>) and one a group comparison design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr98-1053815112470721">Wetherby &amp; Woods, 2006</xref>) reported research design features or procedures with insufficient strength to support reported outcomes with confidence, although they laid out models that can be tested in future studies. Another (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr99-1053815112470721">Zachor et al., 2007</xref>) used a diagnostic instrument to assess outcomes, limiting conclusions that can be drawn from their findings. Dawson and colleagues (2010) reported moderate effects from their 2-year as-yet-unreplicated intervention, the Early Start Denver Model, with evidence supported by strong research rigor.</p>
<p>The studies in this group spanned a full range of intervention settings, including home (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr98-1053815112470721">Wetherby &amp; Woods, 2006</xref>), clinic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-1053815112470721">Vismara &amp; Rogers, 2008</xref>), combined home and clinic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1053815112470721">Dawson et al., 2010</xref>), and special class with partial inclusion for some toddlers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr99-1053815112470721">Zachor et al., 2007</xref>). Parents served as primary intervention implementers in one of these studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr98-1053815112470721">Wetherby &amp; Woods, 2006</xref>). The most professionally time-intensive interventions appeared in this focus area, with all except one implemented over 25 hr per week for at least a full year. The exception (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-1053815112470721">Vismara &amp; Rogers, 2008</xref>) was implemented for 90 min per week for 12 weeks. Strategies shared by two studies each included following the child’s lead, functional assessment, skills shaping, and specialized therapies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1053815112470721">
<title>Family well-being interventions</title>
<p>One study found change on observational and rating scale measures of parent stress and child affect using an SCD for three participant pairs. The research design and methods were assessed as having adequate rigor. Replication of this and other studies is needed before effects can be assessed for this area. The intervention, conducted over 12 sessions, was implemented by parents in combined home and clinic playroom settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1053815112470721">Brookman-Frazee &amp; Koegel, 2004</xref>) and used strategies of pivotal response training, reinforcement, and following the child’s lead.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1053815112470721">
<title>Imitation interventions</title>
<p>Two SCD studies assessed effects of imitation training on observational measures of imitation outcomes, both with findings of observable change from baseline to intervention conditions. Research rigor was assessed as strong (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1053815112470721">Cardon &amp; Wilcox, 2011</xref>) and adequate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1053815112470721">Ingersoll &amp; Gergans, 2007</xref>). Although the two studies used similar methods and assessed similar outcomes, replication is needed.</p>
<p>Both interventions were conducted in clinical settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1053815112470721">Cardon &amp; Wilcox, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1053815112470721">Ingersoll &amp; Gergans, 2007</xref>), and the latter one was partially parent-implemented. Both were of low density and short duration and used reciprocal imitation training supplemented by other strategies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1053815112470721">
<title>Joint attention interventions</title>
<p>The largest group of studies focused on joint attention. Two group comparison studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1053815112470721">Drew et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1053815112470721">Landa et al., 2011</xref>) used standardized measures, with the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1053815112470721">Landa et al. (2011)</xref> study also using an observational measure. No measures were shared between the two. The other five studies used observational measures of joint attention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1053815112470721">Jones et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1053815112470721">Leew et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1053815112470721">Rocha et al., 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1053815112470721">Schertz &amp; Odom, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-1053815112470721">Vismara &amp; Lyons, 2007</xref>) with two using supplemental observational measures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1053815112470721">Leew et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1053815112470721">Schertz &amp; Odom, 2007</xref>). Effects on the standardized measures were assessed as small (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1053815112470721">Landa et al., 2011</xref>) and medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1053815112470721">Drew et al., 2002</xref>), and with adequate research rigor. Most SCD studies in this group documented observable change following intervention for all participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1053815112470721">Jones et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1053815112470721">Rocha et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-1053815112470721">Vismara &amp; Lyons, 2007</xref>), with two studies finding partial effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1053815112470721">Leew et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1053815112470721">Schertz &amp; Odom, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Reports of effects in five rigorously conducted joint attention studies showed considerable overlap in intervention strategies and similar measures among the studies, indicating that joint attention outcomes are likely attainable for toddlers with ASD. As with the other intervention focus areas, however, recommendations for replication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1053815112470721">Gersten et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1053815112470721">Horner et al., 2005</xref>) were not entirely met, intervention procedures varied, and, although similar, the joint attention measures did not use common criteria.</p>
<p>The joint attention focused interventions were delivered in home (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1053815112470721">Drew et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1053815112470721">Leew et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1053815112470721">Schertz &amp; Odom, 2007</xref>), clinic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1053815112470721">Rocha et al., 2007</xref>), special classroom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1053815112470721">Landa et al., 2011</xref>), combined classroom and home (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1053815112470721">Jones et al., 2006</xref>), and combined clinic and home (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-1053815112470721">Vismara &amp; Lyons, 2007</xref>) settings. Five of the seven were fully parent-implemented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1053815112470721">Drew et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1053815112470721">Leew et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1053815112470721">Rocha et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1053815112470721">Schertz &amp; Odom, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-1053815112470721">Vismara &amp; Lyons, 2007</xref>), one was professionally implemented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1053815112470721">Jones et al., 2006</xref>), and the classroom-based intervention was professionally implemented with parent carry-over at home (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1053815112470721">Landa et al., 2011</xref>). Intervention density ranged from 1.5 hr to 10 hr per week with an approximately even distribution between lower and higher density interventions. The duration of intervention ranged from 2 weeks to 1 year with the majority lasting more than 3 months. Shared strategies included discrete trial training and other reinforcement-based strategies (four studies), following the child’s lead (three), pivotal response training (three), visual support (two), prompting (two), and routines-based intervention (two).</p></sec>
<sec id="section19-1053815112470721">
<title>Play interventions</title>
<p>Two SCD studies assessed effects of play-focused intervention on play (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-1053815112470721">VanDerHeyden, Snyder, DiCarlo, Stricklin, &amp; Vigianos, 2002</xref>) and play imitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1053815112470721">Hine &amp; Wolery, 2006</xref>). Both were assessed as showing adequate research rigor, and both reported intervention effects for the single participant in each of their studies. Generalized findings cannot be ascertained for this area because the studies’ outcomes are not comparable and neither was replicated.</p>
<p>The interventions were professionally implemented in a separate therapy room (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1053815112470721">Hine &amp; Wolery, 2006</xref>) and in a special class setting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-1053815112470721">VanDerHeyden et al., 2002</xref>). Each intervention was provided between 1 and 2 hr per week for 10 to 12 weeks using video modeling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1053815112470721">Hine &amp; Wolery, 2006</xref>) and within-stimulus prompting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-1053815112470721">VanDerHeyden et al., 2002</xref>).</p>
</sec></sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-1053815112470721" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The prominence of joint attention as an intervention focus was striking in this review of 20 studies of intervention for toddlers with ASD. This choice of focus reflects researchers’ understanding of the centrality of the toddlers’ difficulty with joint attention, a preverbal social communication milestone that emerges by 12 months of age in typical development, and its close association with later language development. Joint attention difficulties are unique to young children with ASD when compared with groups with other disabilities and typical development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1053815112470721">McArthur, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1053815112470721">Paparella &amp; Kasari, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-1053815112470721">Sigman &amp; Ruskin, 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>The joint attention focused studies, by virtue of their greater number, collectively showed the most replicated evidence of intervention effects compared with other intervention focus areas although, as with the other areas, additional study of joint attention intervention is needed both within and across specific intervention approaches. More shared strategies were evident in the joint attention than in the other focus areas. Also, there was more convergence around outcome measures since most studies used a measure of joint attention to assess intervention effects, though measurement protocols varied. In the other focus areas, joint attention was mentioned as one of several intervention components in each of the four listed general development interventions, was associated with imitation as a justification for an imitation-focused intervention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1053815112470721">Ingersoll &amp; Gergans, 2007</xref>), and was an expected outcome in a communication-focused intervention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053815112470721">Carter et al., 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Researchers’ recognition of preverbal social communication’s importance and the joint attention outcomes their interventions achieved are informative for practitioners, who must determine a meaningful intervention focus for toddlers with ASD. However, although correlational research findings show that the presence of joint attention is a strong predictor of language (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1053815112470721">Mundy et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-1053815112470721">Tomasello &amp; Farrar, 1986</xref>), the actual effects of joint attention <italic>intervention</italic> on language and social outcomes has not been adequately tested; for this, measures that capture broader outcomes are needed.</p>
<p>In the other focus areas, all of which included fewer studies than the joint attention focus area, outcome measures, intervention strategies, levels of research rigor, strength of outcomes, and feasibility indicators varied among the similarly focused studies, limiting the confidence with which conclusions on intervention effects and feasibility could be generated. Furthermore, only two imitation-focused studies and one family well-being-focused study were reported, further restricting analysis for those areas. Taken as a whole, therefore, this review may have greater value as a formative analysis to guide future research rather than as a summative evaluation of efficacy.</p>
<p>The range of outcome measures may reflect a natural process of experimentation in an emerging subfield. Among the standardized measures used in the six group comparison studies listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1053815112470721">Table 1</xref>, common measures were shared by only three, and only in part and with variance in choice of subtests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053815112470721">Carter et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1053815112470721">Dawson et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1053815112470721">Landa et al., 2011</xref>). Most of the SCD studies used measures tailored to their intervention goals and, while some measured similar constructs, their lack of shared measurement protocols limits comparison of results. This diversity in outcome measures illustrates the need for common measures, but perhaps more importantly, the need for convergence around what constitutes meaningful outcomes for toddlers with ASD. Measures focusing on social aspects of communication (as distinct from instrumental aspects such as requesting or following directions) are important, since it is the social rather than instrumental communication function that is the central challenge in ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1053815112470721">Mundy &amp; Stella, 2000</xref>). This need is not well captured in general assessments of child development and may require use of joint attention measures such as were used in some of the SCD studies. Some consensus has emerged around measurement of spoken communication for young children with ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr90-1053815112470721">Tager-Flusberg et al., 2009</xref>), and this could provide a common benchmark for assessing effects of both joint attention focused and verbally focused interventions on verbal competency.</p>
<p>The overall research rigor of the reviewed studies, while showing some gaps, appears to be stronger than that found in a previous review of interventions for young children with ASD published between 2001 and 2005 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1053815112470721">Reichow, Barton, Volkmar, &amp; Cicchetti, 2007</xref>). In the earlier review, a smaller proportion of studies received the highest rating, and a larger proportion received the lowest rating. While rigor in the current review was rated using one instrument by individuals who either developed or were trained by the developer of the rating system, the evaluative method has been shown to have strong validity when compared with similar tools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1053815112470721">Cicchetti, 2011</xref>) and should provide a fair assessment of the current status of research methods being used in early intervention for toddlers with ASDs. This finding is encouraging, and researchers should continue the trend toward stronger internal and external validity. Journal editors should also ensure that only studies meeting high methodological standards are published and disseminated.</p>
<p>Unless research settings and processes reflect conditions under which early interventionists operate, field-based replication of researched intervention models may not be feasible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1053815112470721">Coakley, 2010</xref>). The limited use of authentic settings and interaction partners, with more than half of the studies carried out in clinical or nonintegrated settings, was a general concern. More encouraging was that the majority of studies provided some level of parent involvement in promoting their children’s learning, another aspect of authentic early intervention practice, though a large minority did not.</p>
<p>Replication is a pressing need in the identified focus areas, both within and across specific intervention approaches. A standard of credibility for special education research is for replication in at least two independent methodologically strong randomized controlled trials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1053815112470721">Gersten et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1053815112470721">Lewis-Snyder, Stoiber, &amp; Kratochwill, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-1053815112470721">Silverman &amp; Hinshaw, 2008</xref>) or at least five rigorously designed SCD studies by at least three different researchers with at least 20 participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1053815112470721">Horner et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1053815112470721">Shernoff, Kratochwill, &amp; Stoiber, 2002</xref>). Not surprisingly for emerging research, none of the intervention approaches met this standard.</p>
<sec id="section21-1053815112470721">
<title>Limitations of the Review</title>
<p>Several limitations from the review process itself are pertinent. First, we located a relatively small number of studies. Although this is likely due to the fact that intervention for toddlers with ASDs is a new and emerging area, the limited number of studies constricts the conclusions that we can draw, especially in light of the lack of replicated studies within focus areas. Related to this, although we attempted to locate all relevant studies, the conclusions drawn from all systematic reviews are limited by the possibility of publication bias (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1053815112470721">Rothstein, Sutton, &amp; Borenstein, 2005</xref>), especially the possibility that negative or small effects remain unpublished and therefore more difficult to locate. Although it was beyond the scope of our review, future reviews might consider systematically searching gray literature to find unpublished theses, dissertations, and conference proceedings. Finally, although we divided the studies for analysis according to their intervention purpose, there are other dimensions on which the studies could have been analyzed if the number of studies had been sufficient (e.g., outcome measures, intervention approaches). As acknowledged in the introduction, this decision can have ramifications for the findings of a review, and our review should be considered in light of this limitation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-1053815112470721">
<title>Recommendations for Researchers</title>
<p>Future research needs are summarized in the last column of <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1053815112470721">Table 2</xref> for each intervention focus area, with substantial duplication across the groups. The most commonly identified needs, described above, concern the use of authentic intervention settings and interaction partners, use of common outcome measures, replication within and across settings, and enhanced research rigor.</p>
<p>An additional need, evident from the variance in intervention density and duration shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1053815112470721">Table 1</xref>, is for controlled studies that compare effects for interventions of varying density (e.g., hours per week of professional time) and duration. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1053815112470721">Howlin and her colleagues (2009)</xref> cite randomized controlled trials in which nonintensive but well-focused interventions have produced positive effects for young children with ASD. The oft-cited recommendation by the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1053815112470721">National Research Council (NRC; 2001)</xref> for intensive service levels (i.e., 25 hr per week) should be evaluated systematically with toddler-aged children, for whom intervention research had not been conducted at the time of the NRC’s recommendation and for whom developmental considerations may suggest different approaches than for older children. For toddlers with ASD and their families, this research should sort out how intervention density impacts outcomes, cost-effectiveness, and family and child well-being. The issue of intervention density is confounded with the role of parents in intervention delivery, which should be analyzed as well. Study of intervention duration could assess whether intervention that did not show effects in a short-term implementation (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053815112470721">Carter et al., 2011</xref>) does so when implemented over a longer period.</p>
<p>Two other areas for comparative research are suggested from this review. First, because of the previously discussed association of joint attention development with subsequent communication outcomes, an important question is how joint attention focused interventions compare with communication-focused ones on verbal communication outcomes, assessed longitudinally. This question has implications for whether targeting preverbal social communication outcomes (i.e., working closer to toddlers’ competency level) is more efficient and effective than directly targeting verbal communication outcomes from the outset. A related question is how joint attention focused interventions compare with general development focused ones on standardized assessments. Findings could filter out whether it is social communication (the core area of difficulty) or all developmental domains that are important to target in early intervention for toddlers with ASD.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-1053815112470721">
<title>Recommendations for Practitioners</title>
<p>Early interventionists do not have the luxury of waiting for definitive research to make intervention decisions in the field. While recognizing the limited conclusions that can be drawn from this early research, a few important points are instructive for early interventionists. The foremost trend across the reviewed studies is toward promoting social communication at the preverbal level. Practitioners can draw from specific strategies featured in the reviewed joint attention studies, with special attention to those that were shared among studies conducted by different researchers. Intervention strategies that were featured in other intervention focus areas are also of potential value to address particular intervention needs. Practitioners should recognize that, although research is not yet sufficient to support any particular intervention approach or level of intervention intensity for toddlers with ASD, intervention models that demonstrate both positive outcomes and congruence with principles of authentic early intervention practice provide useful guides for their intervention choices.</p>
</sec></sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<label>Authors’ Note:</label>
<p>Hannah H. Schertz, Department of Curriculum and Instruction, Indiana University; Brian Reichow, Child Study Center, Yale University; Paulo Tan, Department of Curriculum and Instruction, Indiana University; Potheini Vaiouli, Department of Curriculum and Instruction, Indiana University; Emine Yildirim, Department of Curriculum and Instruction, Indiana University.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<p>Reviewed studies are indicated with an asterisk (*).</p>
<ref id="bibr1-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adamson</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McArthur</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Markov</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunbar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bakeman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Autism and joint attention: Young children’s responses to maternal bids</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>439</fpage>-<lpage>453</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab>. (<year>2000</year>). <source>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders</source> (<edition>4th ed.</edition>, text rev.). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>Autism Speaks</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>Autism Speaks Toddler Treatment Network</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.autismspeaks.org/science/initiatives/toddler-treatment-network">http://www.autismspeaks.org/science/initiatives/toddler-treatment-network</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bretherten</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Volterra</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>The emergence of symbols in language and action: Similarities and differences</article-title>. <source>Papers and Reports on Child Language Development</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>106</fpage>-<lpage>118</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Brookman-Frazee</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koegel</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Using parent/clinician partnerships in parent education programs for children with autism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Positive Behavior Interventions</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>195</fpage>-<lpage>213</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brookman-Frazee</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vismara</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drahota</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stahmer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Openden</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Parent training interventions for children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Matson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Applied behavior analysis for children with autism spectrum disorders</source> (pp. <fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>257</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Cardon</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Promoting imitation in young children with autism: A comparison of reciprocal imitation training and video modeling</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>654</fpage>-<lpage>666</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-010-1086-8</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Carter</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Messinger</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Celimli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nahmias</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A randomized controlled trial of Hanen’s “More Than Words” in toddlers with early autism symptoms</article-title>. <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry, and Allied Disciplines</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>741</fpage>-<lpage>752</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7610.2011.02395.x</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D. V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>On the reliability and accuracy of the evaluative method for identifying evidence-based practices in autism</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Reichow</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doehring</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D. V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Volkmar</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Evidence-based practices and treatments for children with autism</source> (pp. <fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coakley</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>State guidance documents for young children with autism spectrum disorders: Content and comparison</article-title>. <source>Infants &amp; Young Children</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Research synthesis and meta-analysis: A step-by-step approach</source> (<edition>4th ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Copple</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bredekamp</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>2009</year>). <source>Developmentally appropriate practice in early childhood programs serving children from birth through age 8</source> (<edition>3rd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Association for the Education of Young Children</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Dawson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Munson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Varley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Randomized, controlled trial of an intervention for toddlers with autism: The Early Start Denver Model</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>125</volume>, <fpage>e17</fpage>-<lpage>e23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A review of processes and outcomes in family-centered services for children with a disability</article-title>. <source>Topics in Early Childhood Special Education</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>42</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Drew</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baron-Cohen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slonims</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wheelwright</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>A pilot randomised control trial of a parent training intervention for pre-school children with autism: Preliminary findings and methodological challenges</article-title>. <source>European Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>266</fpage>-<lpage>272</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dunst</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bruder</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trivette</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamby</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Everyday activity settings, natural learning environments, and early intervention practice</article-title>. <source>Journal of Policy and Practice in Intellectual Disabilities</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dunst</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trivette</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamby</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Meta-analysis of family-centered helpgiving practices research</article-title>. <source>Mental Retardation and Developmental Disabilities Research Reviews</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>370</fpage>-<lpage>378</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eikeseth</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Outcome of comprehensive psycho-educational interventions for young children with autism</article-title>. <source>Research in Developmental Disabilities</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>158</fpage>-<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eldevik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jahr</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eikeseth</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Meta-analysis of early intensive behavioral intervention for children with autism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Child &amp; Adolescent Psychology</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>439</fpage>-<lpage>450</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Esch</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grow</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of an enhanced stimulus-stimulus pairing procedure to increase early vocalizations of children with autism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Behavior Analysis</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>225</fpage>-<lpage>241</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenbaum</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yirmiya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Mother–Infant affect synchrony as an antecedent of the emergence of self-control</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>223</fpage>-<lpage>231</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0012-1649.35.1.223</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gersten</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Compton</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Innocenti</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Quality indicators for group experimental and quasi-experimental research in special education</article-title>. <source>Exceptional Children</source>, <volume>71</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>149</fpage>-<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guralnick</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Effectiveness of early intervention for vulnerable children: A developmental perspective</article-title>. <source>American Journal on Mental Retardation</source>, <volume>102</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>345</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hattie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Visible learning: A synthesis of over 800 meta-analyses relating to achievement</article-title>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hebbeler</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gerlach-Downie</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Inside the black box of home visiting: A qualitative analysis of why intended outcomes were not achieved</article-title>. <source>Early Childhood Research Quarterly</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>28</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0885-2006(02)00128-x</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olkin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <source>Statistical models for meta-analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>J. P. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Cochrane handbook for systematic reviews of interventions</source>. <publisher-loc>Chichester, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Hine</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolery</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Using point-of-view video modeling to teach play to preschoolers with autism</article-title>. <source>Topics in Early Childhood Special Education</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>83</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Horner</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Halle</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Odom</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolery</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The use of single-subject research to identify evidence-based practice in special education</article-title>. <source>Exceptional Children</source>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>165</fpage>-<lpage>179</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Howlin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Magiati</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Systematic review of early intensive behavioral interventions for children with autism</article-title>. <source>American Journal on Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities</source>, <volume>114</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal"><collab>Individuals With Disabilities Education Act. 20 U.S.C. § 1400</collab> (<year>2004</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Ingersoll</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dvortcsak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whalen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sikora</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The effects of a developmental, social-pragmatic language intervention on rate of expressive language production in young children with autistic spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Focus on Autism &amp; Other Developmental Disabilities</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>213</fpage>-<lpage>222</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Ingersoll</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gergans</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The effect of a parent-implemented imitation intervention on spontaneous imitation skills in young children with autism</article-title>. <source>Research in Developmental Disabilities</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>163</fpage>-<lpage>175</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ridd.2006.02.004</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>Interagency Autism Coordinating Committee</collab>. (<year>2005</year>). <source>2005 IACC autism spectrum disorder (ASD) services roadmap</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://iacc.hhs.gov/publications/2005/services-subcommittee-report-may16.shtml#acknowledgements">http://iacc.hhs.gov/publications/2005/services-subcommittee-report-may16.shtml#acknowledgements</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jadad</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>D. J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gavaghan</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McQuay</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Assessing the quality of reports of randomized clinical trials: Is blinding necessary?</article-title> <source>Controlled Clinical Trials</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Identification and evaluation of children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>120</volume>, <fpage>1183</fpage>-<lpage>1215</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">doi/10.1542</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Jones</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feeley</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Multiple effects of joint attention intervention for children with autism</article-title>. <source>Behavior Modification</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>782</fpage>-<lpage>834</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Juni</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Witschi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bloch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The hazards of scoring the quality of clinical trails for meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source>, <volume>282</volume>, <fpage>1054</fpage>-<lpage>1060</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Landa</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Neill</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Intervention targeting development of socially synchronous engagement in toddlers with autism spectrum disorder: A randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7610.2010.02288.x</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Landry</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swank</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Responsive parenting: Establishing early foundations for social, communication, and independent problem-solving skills</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>627</fpage>-<lpage>642</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Leew</surname><given-names>S. V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>N. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gibbard</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Weighted vests’ effect on social attention for toddlers with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>77</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>113</fpage>-<lpage>124</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lewis-Snyder</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stoiber</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kratochwill</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Evidence-based interventions in school psychology: An illustration of task force coding criteria using group-based research design</article-title>. <source>School Psychology Quarterly</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>423</fpage>-<lpage>465</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lipsey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Practical meta-analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Risi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DiLavore</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thurm</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pickles</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Autism from 2 to 9 years of age</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>694</fpage>-<lpage>701</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DiLavore</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Risi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Autism diagnostic observation schedule - WPS (ADOS-WPS)</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Western Psychological Services</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Le Couteur</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Autism Diagnostic Interview–Revised: A revised version of a diagnostic interview for caregivers of individuals with possible pervasive developmental disorders</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>659</fpage>-<lpage>685</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luyster</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gotham</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guthrie</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coffing</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petrak</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Lord</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule—Toddler Module: A new module of a standardized diagnostic measure for autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism &amp; Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>39</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>1305</fpage>-<lpage>1320</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fewell</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spiker</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wheeden</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The relationship of parent-child interaction to the effectiveness of early intervention services for at-risk children and children with disabilities</article-title>. <source>Topics in Early Childhood Special Education</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Pivotal behavior model of development learning</article-title>. <source>Infants &amp; Young Children: An Interdisciplinary Journal of Special Care Practices</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>311</fpage>-<lpage>325</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McArthur</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Joint attention in preverbal children: Autism and developmental language disorder</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>481</fpage>-<lpage>496</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McConachie</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diggle</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Parent implemented early intervention for young children with autism spectrum disorder: A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Journal of Evaluation in Clinical Practice</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>120</fpage>-<lpage>129</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jadad</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klassen</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Does quality of reports of randomized trials affect estimates of intervention efficacy reported in meta-analyses?</article-title> <source>Lancet</source>, <volume>352</volume>, <fpage>609</fpage>-<lpage>613</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>Mullen Scales of Early Learning</source> (<edition>AGS ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Circle Pines, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Guidance Service</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mundy</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sigman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kasari</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>A longitudinal study of joint attention and language development in autistic children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>115</fpage>-<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mundy</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stella</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Joint attention, social orienting, and nonverbal communication in autism</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wetherby</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prizant</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Autism spectrum disorders</source> (pp. <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>77</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brookes</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>National Research Council</collab>. (<year>2001</year>). <source>Educating children with autism</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academy Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Odom</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brantlinger</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gersten</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horner</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Research in special education: Scientific methods and evidence-based practices</article-title>. <source>Exceptional Children</source>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>137</fpage>-<lpage>148</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Odom</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolery</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>A unified theory of practice in early intervention/early childhood special education: Evidence-based practices</article-title>. <source>Journal of Special Education</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>164</fpage>-<lpage>173</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Paparella</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kasari</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Joint attention skills and language development in special needs populations</article-title>. <source>Infants &amp; Young Children: An Interdisciplinary Journal of Special Care Practices</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>280</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Park</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alber-Morgan</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cannella-Malone</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Effects of mother-implemented Picture Exchange Communication System (PECS) training on independent communicative behaviors of young children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Topics in Early Childhood Special Education</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>47</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0271121410393750</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Petticrew</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Systematic reviews in the social sciences: A practical guide</source>. <publisher-loc>Malden, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Polanin</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>, <month>May</month>). <source>Options for assessing study quality</source>. <publisher-name>Oral presentation given at Campbell Colloquium</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Copenhagen, Denmark</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reichow</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Development, procedures, and application of the evaluative method for determining evidence-based practices in autism</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Reichow</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doehring</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D. V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Volkmar</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Evidence-based practices and treatments for children with autism</source> (pp. <fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reichow</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Overview of meta-analyses on early intensive behavioral intervention for young children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>512</fpage>-<lpage>520</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-011-1218-9</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reichow</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Volkmar</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D. V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>, <month>May</month>). <source>The status of research on interventions for young children with autism spectrum disorders</source>. <conf-name>Poster presented at the International Meeting for Autism Research</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Seattle, WA</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reichow</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Volkmar</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Social skills interventions for individuals with autism: Evaluation for evidence-based practices within a best evidence synthesis framework</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>149</fpage>-<lpage>166</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-009-0842-0</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reichow</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Volkmar</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Introduction to evidence-based practices in autism: Where we started</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Reichow</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doehring</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D. V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Volkmar</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Evidence-based practices and treatments for children with autism</source> (pp. <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reichow</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Volkmar</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D. V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Development of the evaluative method for evaluating and determining evidence-based practices in autism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>1311</fpage>-<lpage>1319</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reichow</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolery</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Comprehensive synthesis of early intensive behavioral interventions for young children with autism based on the UCLA Young Autism Project Model</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robins</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fein</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The Modified Checklist for Autism in Toddlers: An initial study investigating the early detection of autism and pervasive developmental disorders</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>-<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Rocha</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schreibman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stahmer</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Effectiveness of training parents to teach joint attention in children with autism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Early Intervention</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>154</fpage>-<lpage>173</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vismara</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Evidence-based comprehensive treatments for early autism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Child &amp; Adolescent Psychology</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rothstein</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Borenstein</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Publication bias in meta-analysis: Prevention, assessment, and adjustments</source>. <publisher-loc>Chichester, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sandall</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hemmeter</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>DEC recommended practices: A comprehensive guide for practical application in early intervention/early childhood special education</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Missoula, MT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Division for Early Childhood, Council for Exceptional Children</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schertz</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hurwitz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benner</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Principles of early intervention reflected in toddler research in autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Topics in Early Childhood Special Education</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>4</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0271121410382460</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Schertz</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Odom</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Promoting joint attention in toddlers with autism: A parent-mediated developmental model</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>1562</fpage>-<lpage>1575</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schopler</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reichler</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Renner</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>The Childhood Autism Rating Scale</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Western Psychological Services</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shernoff</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kratochwill</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stoiber</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Evidence-based interventions in school psychology: An illustration of task force coding criteria using single-participant research design</article-title>. <source>School Psychology Quarterly</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>390</fpage>-<lpage>422</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beaulieu</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Psychotropic medications in children with autism spectrum disorders: A systematic review and synthesis for evidence-based practice</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>1592</fpage>-<lpage>1605</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sigman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruskin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Continuity and change in the social competence of children with autism, Down syndrome, and developmental delays</article-title>. <source>Monographs of the Society for Research in Child Development</source>, <volume>64</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Siller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sigman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Modeling longitudinal change in the language abilities of children with autism: Parent behaviors and child characteristics as predictors of change</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>1691</fpage>-<lpage>1704</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0013771</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>W. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hinshaw</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The second special issue on evidence-based psychosocial treatments for children and adolescents: A 10-year update</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Child and Adolescent Psychology</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr84-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Slavin</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Best evidence synthesis: An alternative to metaanalytic and traditional reviews</article-title>. <source>Educational Researcher</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr85-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Best available research evidence: Impact on research in early childhood</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Buysse</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wesley</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Evidence-based practice in the early childhood field</source> (pp. <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Zero to Three</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr86-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balla</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D. V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <source>Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales</source>. <publisher-loc>Circle Pines, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Guidance Service</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr87-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D. V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balla</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Circle Pines, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Guidance Service</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr88-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Sight word instruction for students with autism: An evaluation of the evidence base</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>1411</fpage>-<lpage>1422</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr89-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glasziou</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Evidence-based medicine: How to practice and teach EBM</source> (<edition>3rd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Edinburgh, Scotland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr90-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tager-Flusberg</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Landa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Defining spoken language benchmarks and selecting measures of expressive language development for young children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>643</fpage>-<lpage>652</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr91-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tomasello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farrar</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Joint attention and early language</article-title>. <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>1454</fpage>-<lpage>1463</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr92-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trivette</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunst</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamby</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Influences of family-systems intervention practices on parent-child interactions and child development</article-title>. <source>Topics in Early Childhood Special Education</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0271121410364250</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr93-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tronick</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The neurobehavioral and social-emotional development of infants and children</article-title>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Norton</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr94-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*VanDerHeyden</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DiCarlo</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stricklin</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vigianos</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Comparison of within-stimulus and extra-stimulus prompts to increase targeted play behaviors in an inclusive early intervention program</article-title>. <source>Behavior Analyst Today</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>188</fpage>-<lpage>197</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr95-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Virués-Ortega</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Applied behavior analytic intervention for autism in early childhood: Meta-analysis, meta-regression and dose–response meta-analysis of multiple outcomes</article-title>. <source>Clinical Psychology Review</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>387</fpage>-<lpage>399</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpr.2010.01.008</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr96-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Vismara</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Using perseverative interests to elicit joint attention behaviors in young children with autism: Theoretical and clinical implications for understanding motivation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Positive Behavior Interventions</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>214</fpage>-<lpage>228</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr97-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Vismara</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The early start Denver model: A case study of an innovative practice</article-title>. <source>Journal of Early Intervention</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr98-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Wetherby</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Early social interaction project for children with autism spectrum disorders beginning in the second year of life: A preliminary study</article-title>. <source>Topics in Early Childhood Special Education</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr99-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>*Zachor</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ben Itzchak</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rabinovich</surname><given-names>A.-L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lahat</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Change in autism core symptoms with intervention</article-title>. <source>Research in Autism Spectrum Disorders</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>304</fpage>-<lpage>317</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr100-1053815112470721">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zwaigenbaum</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thurm</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baranek</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bryson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iverson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sigman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Studying the emergence of autism spectrum disorders in high-risk infants: Methodological and practical issues</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>466</fpage>-<lpage>480</lpage>.</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>