<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="letter" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JHS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjhs</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Hand Surg Eur Vol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Hand Surgery (European Volume)</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1753-1934</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2043-6289</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753193413489071</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1753193413489071</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Letters to the Editor</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Re: Zyluk A. and Szlosser Z. The results of carpal tunnel release for carpal tunnel syndrome diagnosed on clinical grounds, with or without electrophysiological investigations: a randomized study. J Hand Surg Eur. 2013, 38: 44–9</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hems</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1753193413489071">Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, The Victoria Infirmary, Glasgow, UK. Email: <email>t.e.j.hems@doctors.org.uk</email></aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>38</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>690</fpage>
<lpage>690</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The British Society for Surgery of the Hand</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Dear Sir,</p>
<p>I read this article with interest. The authors report that there was no difference in outcome of carpal tunnel release performed in a series of patients with ‘typical’ carpal tunnel syndrome (CTS), which had been diagnosed on clinical grounds alone or if nerve conduction studies had also been performed.</p>
<p>It appears that the nerve conduction studies (NCS) were abnormal in all 45 patients who had tests, showing good correlation with the clinical diagnosis. It is therefore hardly likely that, other than the effect of delay in surgery, there would be any difference in the outcome of operation.</p>
<p>Although I would agree that NCS are not necessary before operation in all patients with typical or ‘classical’ CTS, there is a difficulty in consistent definition of this entity. The authors indicate the basis of diagnosis of ‘typical’ CTS in Table 1 of the article, it is not clear how many of the symptoms each patient had to have to reach a diagnosis. Have the authors considered using a structured system of scoring symptoms and signs, such as those reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193413489071">Kamath and Stothard (2003)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193413489071">Hems et al. (2009)</xref>. These systems provide a more objective basis for diagnosis of ‘typical’ CTS and aid in identifying cases with features where it is best to confirm the diagnosis with NCS.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1753193413489071">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hems</surname><given-names>TEJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Massraf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of a diagnostic questionnaire and protocol for management of carpal tunnel syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Eur</source>. <year>2009</year>, <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>665</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1753193413489071">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A clinical questionnaire for the diagnosis of carpal tunnel syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br</source>. <year>2003</year>, <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<sub-article article-type="letter" id="sub1-1753193413489071">
<front-stub>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reply</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Zyluk</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-1753193413489071">Department of General and Hand Surgery, Pomeranian Medical University in Szczecin, Poland. Email: <email>azyluk@hotmail.com</email></aff>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>Dear Sir,</p>
<p><bold>Re: Zyluk A. and Szlosser Z. The results of carpal tunnel release for carpal tunnel syndrome diagnosed on clinical grounds, with or without electrophysiological investigations: a randomized study. J Hand Surg Eur. 2013, 38: 44–9.</bold></p>
<p>Many thanks for your interest in our article.</p>
<p>Actually, the nerve conduction studies were abnormal in all 45 patients who had tests.</p>
<p>Each patient had to have the majority of the symptoms and signs listed in Table 1 to reach the diagnosis (minimum 4 of 5). Occurrence of these symptoms in the day, at manual work or static grip with flexed wrist was not necessary to be present. Any ‘atypical’ symptomatology resulted in exclusion of the case from the study.</p>
<p>Unfortunately we were not aware of the article of Hems and Miller (2009), as we started our study in 2008. We overlooked the article of Kamath and Stothard (2003) – our apologies. We agree with Mr Hems’ suggestion that using a structured system of scoring symptoms and signs such as those reported in the abovementioned articles provide a more objective basis for diagnosis of ‘typical’ CTS and aid in identifying cases with features where it is best to confirm the diagnosis with NCS.</p>
</body>
</sub-article>
</article>