<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PEN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppen</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0148-6071</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1941-2444</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0148607111430227</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0148607111430227</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Fatty Emaciation</article-title>
<subtitle>A Case Report of Suspected Fat Overload Syndrome in Oral Refeeding</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Macher</surname><given-names>Arielle D.</given-names></name>
<degrees>PA-C, MMSc</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Palazuelos</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, MPH</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Maviglia</surname><given-names>Saverio M.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, MSc</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0148607111430227">Department of Medicine, Hospitalist Service, Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Boston, Massachusetts</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0148607111430227">Arielle D. Macher, Brigham and Women’s Hospital, 75 Francis St, PBBB B-428, Boston, MA 02155, USA; e-mail: <email>amacher@partners.org</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>36</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>481</fpage>
<lpage>484</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>17</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>19</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">The American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Refeeding syndrome has been observed in patients receiving nutrition after a prolonged period of malnourishment and is characterized by multiple metabolic derangements. Besides hypophosphatemia and hypoglycemia, lipemia has been described in association with parenteral nutrition administration to the malnourished. The authors describe one anorexic patient who developed lipemia during oral refeeding, followed by a precipitous drop in hematocrit suggestive of fat overload syndrome.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>anemia</kwd>
<kwd>anorexia</kwd>
<kwd>fat overload syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>hemolysis</kwd>
<kwd>hypertriglyceridemia</kwd>
<kwd>lipemia</kwd>
<kwd>malnutrition</kwd>
<kwd>refeeding syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>parenteral nutrition</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Hyperlipidemia has been reported in anorexia nervosa before hyperalimentation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0148607111430227">1</xref></sup> and it is a known side effect of parenteral nutrition (PN) administration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0148607111430227">2</xref></sup> However, little has been reported about lipemia in the setting of oral refeeding in the extremely malnourished. Our experience with this patient suggests that when treating the emaciated anorectic at risk of refeeding syndrome, close attention should be paid not only to serum electrolytes but also to serum lipids given a number of potentially adverse acute and chronic complications.</p>
<sec id="section1-0148607111430227">
<title>Case Report</title>
<p>A 20-year-old woman with no past medical history presented to a hospital-based clinic to establish primary care. She complained of a 23-kg weight loss over the preceding 4 months to a nadir weight of 34.5 kg in association with food anxiety, caloric obsession, overexercising behavior, and amenorrhea. The patient denied purging or laxative abuse. She was immediately referred to the emergency department due to vital sign abnormalities.</p>
<p>On examination, she was hypotensive at 84/60 mm Hg with a heart rate of 59, temperature of 35.7°C, respirations of 18, and oxygen saturation of 99% on room air. At a height of 162.6 cm, body mass index (BMI) was calculated to be 13.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. Physical exam was most notable for subcutaneous crepitus along the upper chest, which was confirmed by chest computed tomography (CT) visualizing air throughout the soft tissue spaces of both the thorax and abdomen, causing pneumomediastinum (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0148607111430227">Figure 1</xref>) but no evidence of structural damage to the lung. Furthermore, an upper gastrointestinal series recommended by a thoracic surgery consult confirmed the absence of esophageal rupture. Her pneumomediastinum was thought to be spontaneous, associated with anorexia,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0148607111430227">3</xref></sup> and resolved with supportive care, including a 5-day course of prophylactic vancomycin, ciprofloxacin, and metronidazole to prevent mediastinitis. With the exception of hypophosphatemia and mildly elevated transaminases sometimes seen in anorexia and correlative to lower BMI,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0148607111430227">4</xref></sup> admission laboratory data were normal (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0148607111430227">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0148607111430227" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Admission chest computed tomography with subcutaneous emphysema and severe pneumomediastinum.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0148607111430227-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-0148607111430227" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Lab Values at Consecutive Hospital Days</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0148607111430227" xlink:href="10.1177_0148607111430227-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="10">Lab Values (Reference Ranges)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Hospital Day</th>
<th align="center">HCT (36%−48%)</th>
<th align="center">Tri (35–150 mg/dL)</th>
<th align="center">TC (140–199 mg/dL)</th>
<th align="center">LDL (50–129 mg/dL)</th>
<th align="center">HDL (40–60 mg/dL)</th>
<th align="center">ALT (10–50 U/L)</th>
<th align="center">AST (10–50 U/L)</th>
<th align="center">Glu (70–100 mg/dL)</th>
<th align="center">PO4 (2.4–4.3 mg/dL)</th>
<th align="center">kcal</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0</td>
<td>40.8</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>108</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>37.7</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>71</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>667</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>2.9</td>
<td>713</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>37.5</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>99</td>
<td>40</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>2.3</td>
<td>885</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>39.6</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>99</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>852</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>226</td>
<td>125</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>79</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>69</td>
<td>2.1</td>
<td>1248</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>113</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>1692</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>41.4</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>121</td>
<td>87</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>2072</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>119</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>1800</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>34.0<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0148607111430227">a</xref></sup></td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>98</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0148607111430227">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>65</td>
<td>3.3</td>
<td>2861</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>36.0<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0148607111430227">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>871</td>
<td>179</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>91</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0148607111430227">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>72</td>
<td>3.2</td>
<td>2861</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>35.4</td>
<td>539</td>
<td>197</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>89</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>71</td>
<td>3.5</td>
<td>2829</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>27.6</td>
<td>818</td>
<td>187</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>4.1</td>
<td>2700</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13</td>
<td>24.0</td>
<td>501</td>
<td>161</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>4.5</td>
<td>3248</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14</td>
<td>22.2<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0148607111430227">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>379</td>
<td>144</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>80</td>
<td>3.4</td>
<td>3494</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>26.3</td>
<td>226</td>
<td>165</td>
<td>88</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>73</td>
<td>3.4</td>
<td>&gt;3000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td>26.0</td>
<td>295</td>
<td>158</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>77</td>
<td>3.9</td>
<td>&gt;3000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>17</td>
<td>27.7</td>
<td>105</td>
<td>160</td>
<td>98</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>3.3</td>
<td>&gt;3000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18</td>
<td>29.1</td>
<td>137</td>
<td>179</td>
<td>105</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>91</td>
<td>3.8</td>
<td>&gt;3000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>19</td>
<td>28.7</td>
<td>269</td>
<td>198</td>
<td>105</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>80</td>
<td>3.9</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0148607111430227">
<p>Dash signifies no laboratory data available.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0148607111430227">
<p>ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; Glu, glucose; HCT, hematocrit; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; kcal, kilocalorie; LDL, low-density lipoprotein; PO4, phosphate; TC, total cholesterol; Tri, triglycerides.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0148607111430227">
<label>a</label>
<p>Sample noted to be lipemic.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0148607111430227">
<label>b</label>
<p>Not reported due to hemolysis.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0148607111430227">
<label>c</label>
<p>Levocarnitine initiated.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0148607111430227">
<label>d</label>
<p>Transfused 1 unit of red blood cells.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The patient’s caloric needs were calculated by the Fleisch equation to equal 1877 calories daily, encompassing a 1.25 standard activity factor for ambulation and 500 addition repletion calories for weight gain. Calorie counts were conducted daily and revealed that for the first 6 days of admission, the patient ate fewer than 900 calories, even less than her basic metabolic rate of 1101.4 kilocalories. After multiple discussions with psychiatry, nutrition, and the primary team, the patient acquiesced to increasing her intake, requesting food from home and on-site restaurants, which presented some difficulty in accurately assessing her consumption but was accepted by the medical team to increase compliance with weight gain goals. Over the subsequent days, the patient’s intake rapidly peaked, and on hospital day 8, after 2 days being ear or above caloric goal, the patient’s phosphate dropped from 3.6 to 1.9 mg/dL, requiring intravenous repletion. At this juncture, nutrition recommended stabilizing the patient’s oral intake; however, the patient herself continued to request outside food to maximize weight gain and consumption neared 3000 calories (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0148607111430227">Table 1</xref>). The following day, her serum sample was noted by the lab to be grossly lipemic with mild hemolysis. Physical exam was unchanged but for low-grade temperatures up to 37.9°C and new intermittent sinus tachycardia with rates ranging upwards to the 120s. A fasting lipid panel was repeated, and triglycerides were found to have more than tripled to a total of 871 mg/dL.</p>
<p>The metabolic support team was consulted and recommended initiating levocarnitine 1 g per day to decrease hypertriglyceridemia by enhancing fatty acid metabolism through facilitation across the mitochondrial membrane.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0148607111430227">5</xref></sup> The triglycerides remained elevated above 500 mg/dL; however, her hematocrit dropped from 36.0% to a low of 21.1% (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0148607111430227">Figure 2</xref>). An anemia workup guided by a hematology consult found guaiac-negative brown stool on multiple occasions; no ecchymotic changes to suggest hematoma formation, although bleeding into the area of the subcutaneous emphysema was not ruled out (repeat CT scans were not performed per patient request to avoid excessive radiation exposure); negative direct Coomb’s test and normal haptoglobin, fibrinogen, and iron levels; and elevated erythropoietin, vitamin B12, and folic acid. However, the patient did exhibit a mildly elevated lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) at 325 U/L and an initially inadequate reticulocytosis with an index of 0.62%, which gradually increased appropriately to 5.13%. After 1 unit of packed red blood cells, the patient’s hematocrit improved, as did the triglycerides to &lt;300 mg/dL with levocarnitine treatment. She was discharged several days later to an inpatient eating disorder unit.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0148607111430227" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Relationship between hematocrit and triglycerides.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0148607111430227-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0148607111430227">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Eating disorders, particularly anorexia nervosa, have long been associated with hyperlipidemia, and our patient was not an exception, with triglycerides noted to be 226 mg/dL on hospital day 5. The precise mechanism is not yet clearly defined, but the etiology is likely multifactorial, including decreased cholesterol and bile acid turnover due to starvation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0148607111430227">1</xref></sup> decreased thyroid hormone and estrogen secretion,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0148607111430227">6</xref></sup> enhanced cholesterol metabolism,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0148607111430227">7</xref></sup> and inhibition of triglyceride catabolism.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0148607111430227">8</xref></sup> High cholesterol level, even in the starved patient, is not without potential adverse effect, as exemplified by the case report of a 39-year-old anorexic smoker who became hyperlipidemic during hyperalimentation and subsequently developed an inferior wall myocardial infarction during the sixth week of treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0148607111430227">9</xref></sup> However, of the 6 case reports and cohort studies assessing lipid characteristics in anorectics, all reported normalization or trends toward normalization with refeeding.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0148607111430227">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0148607111430227"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0148607111430227">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0148607111430227">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0148607111430227"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0148607111430227">12</xref></sup></p>
<p>During starvation, insulin levels decrease and glucagon increases, with resulting gluconeogenesis from lipid and protein catabolism. With refeeding, insulin levels rebound, causing intracellular uptake of glucose, potassium, and phosphate and a reduction in lipid elimination capacity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0148607111430227">13</xref></sup> Furthermore, insulin itself has a stimulatory effect on lipogenesis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0148607111430227">14</xref></sup> In a study of 15 subjects, 11 of which were of normal BMI, 3 overweight, and 1 obese, all but one had rise of triglycerides when changed from a high-fat to high-carbohydrate diet. Higher insulin activity was associated with a greater triglyceride rise on a high-carbohydrate diet.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0148607111430227">15</xref></sup> These results were replicated by Goldrick et al,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0148607111430227">16</xref></sup> who fed lean but otherwise healthy young adults a high-caloric, high-carbohydrate diet, causing significant elevations in insulin and triglycerides; when returned back to a basic diet, concentrations of insulin and triglycerides began to fall.</p>
<p>Thus, our patient’s hypertriglyceridemia was likely due to increased insulin secretion during refeeding, particularly evident when her caloric intake was more than 1000 calories greater than her calculated requirements. Failure of other studies to detect worsening lipemia during refeeding in anorectics may be partially due to lipid panels not being checked serially over the first few days of treatment. Lipid analyses in patients receiving PN, on the other hand, have been studied in detail, with hypertriglyceridemia observed in 25%−50% of such patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0148607111430227">2</xref></sup> Pancreatitis, hepatic steatosis, and possible increased risk for atherosclerosis are the more commonly cited complications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0148607111430227">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0148607111430227">18</xref></sup></p>
<p>Of greater concern is the rarer “fat overload syndrome” characterized by rather acute-onset hypertriglyceridemia in association with pyrexia, anemia, bleeding tendency, transaminitis, tachycardia, hypertension, and even fatal fat thrombi.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0148607111430227">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0148607111430227">19</xref></sup> Campbell et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0148607111430227">20</xref></sup> described a 7-year-old who developed lipemia, fever, hematemesis, and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) elevation with PN and lipid infusion. With discontinuation of PN and lipid infusions, lipid levels fell to normal after 7 days and hematemesis resolved. A similar case was reported by Heyman et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0148607111430227">21</xref></sup> of a 10-month-old girl admitted with fever, mucosal bleeding, and sclera jaundice while on PN with fat emulsions, where her serum was found to be grossly lipemic. Once PN was discontinued, bleeding ceased with clearance of lipemia on the fourth day. They postulated that lipemia results when lipoprotein lipase becomes saturated and fat cannot be cleared rapidly enough by the reticuloendothelial system. Interestingly, in a study of Lipomul intravenous (IV) fat emulsions to adult oncology patients requiring parenteral feeding, 14 of 15 developed acute anemia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0148607111430227">22</xref></sup></p>
<p>One possible etiology of our patient’s precipitous hematocrit drop in association with hypertriglyceridemia, mild hemolysis, low-grade temperature, and tachycardia is that she developed a variant of fat overload syndrome, although this previously has only been reported with PN fat emulsions. After our patient’s rapid increase in caloric intake, she had classic signs of refeeding syndrome: hypophosphatemia and hypertriglyceridemia, consistent with increased insulin. Once her body adapted to 2000–3000 calories per day, her electrolytes stabilized, and her triglycerides fell below 300 mg/dL. The patient’s anemia appeared and then began to resolve over this same time course.</p>
<p>Our case suggests the need for scrupulous lipid monitoring in patients at risk for refeeding syndrome and raises the possibility of fat overload syndrome occurring in the oral refeeding of malnourished patients, even in the absence of parenteral feeding. Furthermore, it prompted changes at our own institution with establishment of eating disorder–specific treatment guidelines. Meals are now trayed by the kitchen in conjunction with registered dietician recommendations to maximize accuracy. Initial prescribed caloric requirements are still calculated through the Fleisch equation with the addition of an activity factor but are not uptitrated until the patient’s electrolytes have demonstrated stability. Thereafter, caloric intake is increased in 250 caloric increments until regular weight gain goals are met.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Megan McCullough, RD, LDN, CNSC, for her thoughtful assessment of the revised manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>Financial disclosure: none declared.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0148607111430227">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Secondary causes of hyperlipidemia</article-title>. <source>Med Clin North Am</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>-<lpage>141</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0148607111430227">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jauch</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parhofer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rittler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>; <collab>Working Group for Developing the Guidelines for Parenteral Nutrition of the German Association for Nutritional Medicine</collab>. <article-title>Complications and monitoring—guidelines on parenteral nutrition, chapter 11</article-title>. <source>Ger Med Sci</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<comment>Doc17</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0148607111430227">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van Veelen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hogeman</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Elburg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nielsen-Abbring</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heggelman</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mahieu</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pneumomediastinum: a rare complication of anorexia nervosa in children and adolescents. A case study and review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pediatr</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>167</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>171</fpage>-<lpage>174</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0148607111430227">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Divasta</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Difabio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ringelheim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and predictors of abnormal liver enzymes in young women with anorexia nervosa</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>153</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>247</fpage>-<lpage>253</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0148607111430227">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rassoul</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Carnitine and experimental carbohydrate-induced hyperlipoproteinemia</article-title>. <source>Arch Int Pharmacodyn Ther</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>290</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>138</fpage>-<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0148607111430227">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Homma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Homma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iizuka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iigaya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A case of anorexia nervosa with severe hyperlipoproteinemia</article-title>. <source>Int J Eat Disord</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>121</fpage>-<lpage>124</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0148607111430227">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ohwada</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hotta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Etiology of hypercholesterolemia in patients with anorexia nervosa</article-title>. <source>Int J Eat Disord</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>598</fpage>-<lpage>601</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0148607111430227">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rigaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tallonneau</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vergès</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hypercholesterolaemia in anorexia nervosa: frequency and changes during refeeding</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Metab</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0148607111430227">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>García-Rubira</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hidalgo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gómez-Barrado</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cruz Fernández</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Anorexia nervosa and myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Int J Cardiol</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>138</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0148607111430227">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feillet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feillet-Coudray</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bard</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Plasma cholesterol and endogenous cholesterol synthesis during refeeding in anorexia nervosa</article-title>. <source>Clinica Chimica Acta</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>294</volume>(<issue>1-2</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0148607111430227">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arden</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weiselberg</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nussbaum</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shenker</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of weight restoration on the dyslipoproteinemia of anorexia nervosa</article-title>. <source>J Adolesc Health Care</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>199</fpage>-<lpage>202</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0148607111430227">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lejoyeux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bouvard</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Viret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daveloose</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ades</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dugas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Modifications of erythrocyte membrane fluidity from patients with anorexia nervosa before and after refeeding</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>255</fpage>-<lpage>258</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0148607111430227">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crook</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hally</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Panteli</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The importance of the refeeding syndrome</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>7-8</issue>):<fpage>632</fpage>-<lpage>637</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0148607111430227">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feillet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Monnier</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barjon</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Descomps</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crastes de Paulet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evidence for a short-term stimulatory effect of insulin on cholesterol synthesis in newly insulin-treated diabetic patients</article-title>. <source>Metabolism</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1233</fpage>-<lpage>1240</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0148607111430227">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Farquhar</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reaven</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Glucose, insulin, and triglyceride responses to high and low carbohydrate diets in man</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>. <year>1966</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1648</fpage>-<lpage>1656</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0148607111430227">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldrick</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Havenstein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reardon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of overfeeding on lipid and carbohydrate metabolism in lean young adults</article-title>. <source>Metabolism</source>. <year>1972</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>761</fpage>-<lpage>770</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0148607111430227">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lyman</surname><given-names>BMSN</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Metabolic complications associated with parenteral nutrition</article-title>. <source>J Infus Nurs</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0148607111430227">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stanek</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wiles</surname><given-names>CE</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Overfeeding macronutrients to critically ill adults: metabolic complications</article-title>. <source>J Am Diet Assoc</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>795</fpage>-<lpage>806</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0148607111430227">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crook</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Lipid clearance and total parenteral nutrition: the importance of monitoring plasma lipids</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>774</fpage>-<lpage>775</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0148607111430227">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pencharz</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zlotkin</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Bleeding disorder from the “fat overload” syndrome</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>447</fpage>-<lpage>449</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0148607111430227">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heyman</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Storch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ament</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The fat overload syndrome: report of a case and literature review</article-title>. <source>Am J Dis Child</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>628</fpage>-<lpage>630</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0148607111430227">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Viteri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hematologic studies in patients receiving multiple infusions of Lipomul I.V</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1965</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>155</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>