<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PUN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppun</journal-id>
<journal-title>Punishment &amp; Society</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1462-4745</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-3095</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1462474511436286</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1462474511436286</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Christina M. Quinlan, <italic>Inside: Ireland’s Women’s Prisons, Past and Present</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wahidin</surname><given-names>Azrini</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1462474511436286">Queen’s University, Belfast, N. Ireland</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>479</fpage>
<lpage>481</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1462474511436286"><title>Christina M. Quinlan, <italic>Inside: Ireland’s Women’s Prisons, Past and Present</italic>, Irish Academic Press: Dublin, 2010; 272 pp.: 9780716530473, €60 (hbk), 978 0716530473, €24.95 (pbk)</title>
<p>Despite the growing focus on women in prison during the last couple of decades, the experiences of women imprisoned in the Republic of Ireland and their related experiences have not been theorized – indeed, they have seldom been described. Yet, in recent years, their numbers have been steadily increasing. In 2000, Christina Quinlan embarked on a journey to raise awareness of this hitherto neglected group by beginning an empirical investigation of the experiences of women imprisoned in Ireland. Currently women imprisoned in Ireland are housed in Limerick Prison (the oldest operating prison in the country) and in the Dóchas Centre (which opened in 1999 with an accommodation capacity for 105 women), part of the Mountjoy Prison complex in Dublin. In some cases women from the prison system are also held no more than three at a time, in the Central Mental Hospital in Dublin.</p>
<p>This book is a critical in-depth study of women in prison in Ireland over the last 200 years. In a contemporary analysis, drawing on 83 interviews with women in prison, both Irish and non-nationals and ranging from the ages of 17 to 53, Quinlan observed a number of multi-disciplinary management meetings held at the Dóchas Centre; she conducted interviews with 30 prison personnel; she provides a spatial analysis of the use of prison space through an analysis of photographic imagery; and she provides a content analysis of crime-related stories in the main newspapers in the Republic of Ireland, from 1 September 2000 to 1 September 2001. In total Quinlan analysed 672 newspapers to present a rich content analysis of the representation of the female offender in the Irish media.</p>
<p><italic>Inside: Ireland’s Women’s Prisons Past and Present</italic> is a comprehensive work that takes the reader through the complex nuances of Irish society and the rise of coercive confinement for women. Quinlan begins the book by contextualizing the nature of Irish society and the effects of the Great Famine of 1845–1850 and the impact the Famine had on Irish prisons where the prison population rose from 16,696 to 41,989. Following the Great Famine, the Catholic Church grew in strength in Ireland and the people, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1462474511436286">Inglis (1998)</xref>, underwent a devotional revolution.</p>
<p>It is by grounding the reader into the historical, political, social and economic situation in Ireland that the reader learns about the nature of social regulation and the engendering of punishment in the Republic of Ireland. In Chapter 2, Quinlan contexualizes the marginality and vulnerability of women living in extreme poverty in Ireland during the 1900s; this is evidenced for example by the fact that at that time women outnumbered men by a ratio of 3:1 in workhouses.</p>
<p>In the 20th century the female prison population contracted to such a degree that a number of women’s prisons around the country were closed down. This period of retrenchment of the women’s prison population was however short-lived and between 1974 and 2008 the female prison population grew from a daily average in 1974 of 24 women to a daily population of 104 in 2008.</p>
<p>Within this chapter, Quinlan provides an historical exploration of women’s experiences of imprisonment, documenting the changes and developments in penal policy. For example, Quinlan highlights the policy of moving women from prison custody to ‘release’ into the custody of convents, compared with the treatment of male prisoners who on coming to the end of their prison sentences were released on licence into the community.</p>
<p>The following Chapters 3 and 4 apply a theoretical lens by incorporating the work of Foucault, Butler and Goffman to illustrate how the offending female body – those women deemed to be troublesome – is subject positioned and represented and in turn reinvented by the public and professional gaze. Quinlan in her analysis of media reporting of criminal cases of both men and women over a period of one month in the <italic>Irish Times</italic> shows that 98 men appeared in court on criminal charges compared to only five women. What was evidenced was the gendered construction of the female offender in the popular press. The biographies of male offenders were shown to confer agency to the male offender and infer control and power in the execution of the criminal act; in contrast female offenders in their biographies were shown to be essentialized, pathologized, sexualized and deemed as ‘outwith’ femininity (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1462474511436286">Carlen, 1983</xref>).</p>
<p>The following section illustrates how imprisoned women were subject positioned within essentializing discourses of femininity by the staff and professionals working within the women’s prisons. Quinlan documents how the prison structure and regime shaped/inscribed the ways in which women experience imprisonment in Ireland. This section traverses the role of time within prison as well as prison space to show how both space and time affect the day-to-day experience of women in prison The process of <italic>othering</italic> is also clearer delineated in the day-to-day experiences of the women, in the way in which the women are processed in the Dóchas Centre, from being received and processed through to the Healthcare Unit and then to prison accommodation. In the newly built Dóchas Centre the women are provided with en-suite rooms rather than cells to which they have keys. However, the emphasis in the prison remains on security and this, Quinlan shows, is constantly reiterated by the prison’s regime. Thus, although the appearance of the Dóchas Centre is not reminiscent of a typical Victorian prison, it is a prison all the same. Absolute power and disciplinary control lies with the prison staff and the women’s daily lives are structured by the operational needs of the prison.</p>
<p>The use of the women’s narratives is cleverly brought to life in the book and placed within a rich theoretical edifice. Quinlan brings the stories of the women of both Limerick prison and the Dóchas Centre to life with a degree of sensitivity that really does highlight the plight of women in Irish prisons. This chapter, Chapter 4, provides the context of women incarcerated by the State and takes the reader through the key themes that emerged from the interviews. Each of the following subsections, Experiences of Control, Prison Structure, Prison Discipline, Sexuality and Media Representation, detail the process of interpellating women as offenders in the process of reconstituting the subject through what Garfinkel called the process of ritualistic degradation. Quinlan cleverly draws out the voices of women and she demonstrates critically how women are medicalized and posited within a medico-socio discourse. The penultimate chapter provides a photographic narrative of women’s presentations of self within the prison while detailing how women negotiate the disciplinary gaze of the penal regime and in turn attempt to recuperate their identities through the ways in which they make certain types of prison space their own.</p>
<p>Throughout the book Quinlan provides a melancholy account of the women’s prisons in the Republic of Ireland in the 20th century and the violence of incarceration that the women endured and continue to endure on a daily basis. The voices of the women are grounded in a theoretical analysis that draws out the manner in which the identities and subjectivities of Ireland’s imprisoned women are discursively constructed and represented. This book focuses on the profiling of women imprisoned in Ireland, and, on examining the manner in which their identities are shaped by those experiences.</p>
<p>The indictment of the prison system is clearly felt throughout the book and what is particularly concerning is the continuing degradation the women endure and the failure of a system which continues to imprison the poor and the vulnerable.</p>
<p><italic>Inside</italic> is a timely book. It closes the gap surrounding the experiences of women in prison in the Republic of Ireland. The book is accessible and it should engage the interest of readers way beyond the confines of academia and criminal justice.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1462474511436286"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <source>Women in Prison: A Study of Social Control</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1462474511436286"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inglis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Lessons in Irish Sexuality</source>. <publisher-loc>Dublin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University College Dublin Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<sec id="sec2-1462474511436286"><title/>
<p><bold>Azrini Wahidin</bold></p>
<p><italic>Queen’s University, Belfast, N. Ireland</italic></p></sec></back>
</article>