<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">VES</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spves</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Vasc Endovascular Surg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Vascular and Endovascular Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1538-5744</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-9116</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1538574413495460</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1538574413495460</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Clinical Research Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>An Analysis of the Factors Influencing Radiation Dose and Fluoroscopic Time During Renal Artery Stent Placement</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McBride</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538574413495460">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schueler</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538574413495460">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Oderich</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1538574413495460">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Misra</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538574413495460">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1538574413495460"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1538574413495460">
<label>1</label>Division of Vascular and Interventional Radiology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1538574413495460">
<label>2</label>Department of Surgery, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1538574413495460">S. Misra, Department of Radiology, Division of Vascular and Interventional Radiology, Vascular and Interventional Translational Lab, Mayo Clinic, 200 First Street SW, Rochester, MN 55902, USA. Email: <email>misra.sanjay@mayo.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>462</fpage>
<lpage>466</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec>
<title>Purpose:</title>
<p>To determine the factors that affect mean absorbed dose and fluoroscopic times during renal artery stent placement. Materials and</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Methods:</title>
<p>After institutional review board approval, the HI-IQ database was queried for patients undergoing renal artery stent placement only from January 2007 to June 2010. Procedures that were performed as part of other procedures such as iliac artery stents were excluded. The HI-IQ data included fluoroscopy time (<italic>f</italic>) and radiation dose (mGy). Demographic, medical history, procedural details, and advanced preprocedural renal artery stent imaging were obtained. Variables (number of stents, average body mass index , number of stents placed per year and number of years’ service of an interventional physician, pre-procedural imaging, and use of embolic protection device) were analyzed using a <italic>t</italic> test after log transformation and testing for variance with an <italic>F</italic> test.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Results:</title>
<p>A total of 134 patients (75 males, 70.6 ± 10.5 years old) underwent the placement of 177 renal artery stents (unilateral [n = 95], average stent per patient = 1.3). Mean fluoroscopy time was 15.6 minutes and mean absorbed dose to the patient was 1729 mGy. The average fluoroscopic time and absorbed dose was significantly higher with bilateral stent placement compared to unilateral placement (13.8 vs 19.7 minutes, <italic>P</italic> = .002; 1803 vs 2380 mGy, <italic>P</italic> = .03). The average fluoroscopic time was significantly higher in patients undergoing abdominal aortogram prior to renal artery selection and stent placement.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Conclusion:</title>
<p>The placement of more than 1 stent with an abdominal angiogram prior to renal artery stent placement results in increased fluoroscopic time and mean absorbed dose.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>renal artery stenosis</kwd>
<kwd>radiation</kwd>
<kwd>stent</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1538574413495460">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The factors that influence radiation exposure to patients during image-guided interventions such as stent placement, embolizations, and other complex procedures are important to understand in order to improve patient safety. In certain states like Minnesota, there are requirements to report all radiation exposures greater than 15 000 mGy to the state and to the patient as sentinel events.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1538574413495460">1</xref>
</sup> Recently, there have been studies performed to understand factors that influence radiation dose to the patient.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1538574413495460">2</xref>
</sup>
<sup>-4</sup> In 2003, the Radiation Dose in Interventional Radiology Dose (RAD-IR) study provided dosages for common IR procedures.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1538574413495460">3</xref>
</sup> However, this study had some limitations, because it had small numbers of patients and did not analyze the different factors that may contribute to high doses and increased fluoroscopic times.</p>
<p>Renal artery stenosis (RAS) may cause uncontrolled hypertension and or chronic renal insufficiency.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1538574413495460">5</xref>
</sup> In patients &gt;75 years old, atherosclerosis is the primary cause of RAS, and in 90% of the patients, atherosclerosis involves the ostium and or the proximal third of the main renal artery.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1538574413495460">5</xref>
</sup> The preferred treatment for the symptomatic patient with RAS is renal artery angioplasty with stent placement.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1538574413495460">6</xref>
</sup> The reported technical success rates of this procedure are 98% to 100%. It has become a common procedure, and the factors that contribute to the fluoroscopic time and radiation dose during the procedure are not well understood. The purpose of the present article was to investigate the technical and patient factors, such as number of stents that are placed, use of embolic protection device, number of stents placed by the interventional physician, or experience, which influence radiation dose during renal artery stent placement.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1538574413495460" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods and Materials</title>
<sec id="section3-1538574413495460">
<title>Study Population</title>
<p>Institutional review board approval was obtained prior to conducting this study. A retrospective review was conducted for all patients with renal artery stenosis that underwent renal artery angioplasty and stent placement from January 2007 to June 2010. Baseline, procedural data, and follow-up data were obtained from our records. We extracted fluoroscopic time and dosage data for each procedure from our Hi IQ database. We identified 163 patients who underwent renal artery stent placement. Thirteen patients were excluded, because they had a renal artery stent placed and a second procedure such as an aortic stent graft placed or an iliac artery stent. Of the 150 patients, 14 were excluded because they did not have complete fluoroscopic and radiation dosage data, and therefore, 136 patients remained. Two patients did not provide research authorization, thus 134 patients comprised the current study.</p>
<p>A chart review was performed, and the following variables were analyzed including age, gender, body mass index (BMI), and clinical comorbidities (hypertension, renal insufficiency, diabetes, coronary artery disease, dyslipidemia, and tobacco use), preprocedural hypertensive medications, and preprocedural serum creatinine. Operator experience was determined by the number of years the performing interventional physician had been practicing as well as the number of renal stents placed by each physician during the study period (&gt;10 or ≤10). For each procedure, we obtained the fluoroscopy time and dose in miligrays (mGy).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1538574413495460">
<title>Renal Duplex Ultrasound</title>
<p>Renal duplex ultrasound was used for screening and quantification of the severity of the renal artery stenosis.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1538574413495460">7</xref>
</sup> Baseline and follow-up studies were performed with a 2.5 to 4.5 MHz phased array transducer (128/XP; Acuson, Mountain View, California or Sequoia 512; Siemens, Erlangen, Germany). Renal artery stenosis or restenosis was defined on ultrasound using angle-corrected peak systolic velocity–aortic velocity ratios (aortic velocity measured near the origin of the renal artery) at a Doppler insinuation angle of no greater than 60°.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1538574413495460">7</xref>
</sup> A peak systolic velocity greater than 300 cm/sec or ratios greater than 3.5 ratios indicated a renal artery stenosis of at least 60%. Average of 2 to 3 intrarenal segmental artery indices were used to calculate the mean index.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1538574413495460">
<title>Renal Artery Stent Placement</title>
<p>Prior to angiography, informed consent was obtained from the patient for potential renal angioplasty and stent implantation. All procedures were performed with use of the same technique. If the patient had magnetic resonance angiography (MRA) or computed tomography angiography (CTA) imaging demonstrating the renal arteries, selective angiography was only performed, otherwise we performed abdominal aortogram followed by selective renal artery angiography. The right common femoral artery was accessed with 18-gauge, 7-cm angiographic needle (Cook, Bloomington, Indiana). A 6F or 7F vascular sheath (Terumo, Somerset, New Jersey) was placed in the artery over a Bentsen guidewire (Cook). A 6F or 7F internal mammary guide catheter (Boston Scientific, Natick, Massachuttes) was used to engage the origin of the renal artery. Angiography was performed with 4 to 8 mL of Visipaque 320 (GE Healthcare, Princeton, New Jersey). Patients were typically given a bolus of heparin intravenously (50 U/kg of body weight) prior to the placement of the stent. Renal artery stenosis was defined as reduction in a diameter of greater than 80% by visual estimate when compared to its immediate, distal nondilated main renal arterial segment at the time of intervention as defined by the guidelines published by the Society of Interventional Radiology.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1538574413495460">7</xref>
</sup> Renal artery stenosis was defined as “ostial” if they were located within <underline>≤</underline>5-mm distance away from renal artery origin from the aorta and defined as “nonostial” if it was located more than 5 mm away from renal artery origin.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1538574413495460">
<title>Embolic Protection Devices Used</title>
<p>Embolic protection devices (EPDs) were used in 19 patients and used at the discretion of the operator. Two different types of EPDs were used. The first 8 patients had the FilterWire EZ, (Boston Scientific, Natick, and Massachuttes) as their embolic protection device. FilterWire EZ has 1 size and can be used in reference vessel diameters of 3.5 to 5.5 mm with a pore size of 120 to 180 µm. The next 11 patients had SpideRX as their embolic protection device. The SpideRX (ev3, Plymouth, Minnesota) can be used for reference vessel diameters of 2.5 to 7.0 mm with a pore size of 180 to 300 µm.</p>
<p>When using the FilterWire EZ device, the device was manipulated across the stenosis and then unsheathed distally to the renal artery stenosis, and the filter was allowed to appose the vessel wall. If the device could not be advanced across the stenosis, the “buddy wire technique” was used, with a second 0.014-in wire advanced across the stenosis to provide support to deliver the device. A Reflex wire (Cordis, Miami, Florida) was typically used to cross the renal artery stenosis when using the SpideRX device, and the device was brought on the Reflex wire and deployed distal to the stenosis. Diameters of the devices were typically greater than the diameter of the nondiseased artery. Thus, 5-mm devices were used for renal artery diameters less than 5 mm.</p>
<p>Diameters of the device and stent were chosen based on the visual estimate of the diameter of the nondiseased renal artery distal to the stenosis. Typically, no pressure measurements were performed nor were antispasmodic medications such as nitroglycerin administered. Pressure gradients were only measured if there was question of lesion severity. A mean gradient of 10 mm Hg measured simultaneously between aorta and distal renal artery or a systolic gradient of more than 20 mm Hg was considered hemodynamically significant, measured simultaneously using an 0.018-in microcatheter (Turbo catheter, Terumo, Tokyo, Japan) distal to the renal artery stenosis and the 6F or 7F guide in the aorta proximal to the renal artery stenosis. Follow-up angiograms were obtained after stent inflation to the diameter of non-diseased renal artery. The device was removed and captured completely with the catheter proved for that purpose and was then visually examined for any debris.</p>
<p>“Technical success” of the stent procedure was defined as less than 30% residual stenosis by visual estimation after deployment. “Technical success” of the embolic protective device was defined as successful deployment of the device, retrieval of the device, and adequate filtration. All complications were recorded according to the guidelines published by the Society of Interventional Radiology.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1538574413495460">7</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>After the procedure, patients were typically given 300 mg oral clopidogrel (Bristol-Meyers Squibb/ Sanofi, Bridgewater New Jersey) after the sheath was removed and then started on clopidogrel 75 mg/d plus a Bayer aspirin for a minimum of 3 months.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1538574413495460">
<title>Fluoroscopic Time and Radiation Dose</title>
<p>We used 6 different angiography systems, 4 of which were equipped with image intensifiers (IIs) and 2 of which were equipped with flat-panel detectors (FPDs). Each of the II systems was a Siemens Multistar (Siemens Medical Systems, Erlangen, Germany) single-plane C-arm unit with a 40-cm II. These systems incorporated low-dose continuous fluoroscopy, pulsed fluoroscopy, and spectral beam filtration. Patient entrance air kerma rates for the most commonly used dose modes were 13 mGy/min and 6.8 mGy/frame for fluoroscopy (continuous fluoroscopy with Supervision, Brassel et al 1992) and digital acquisition, respectively, in the 20-cm field of view using a 20-cm thick acrylic phantom. Each of the FPD systems was a Siemens Axiom Artis dTA single-plane C-arm unit with a 30 × 40 cm detector, pulsed fluoroscopy, and spectral beam filtration. Patient entrance air kerma rates for the most commonly used dose modes were 35 mGy/min and 3.7 mGy/frame for fluoroscopy (15 pulse per sec) and digital acquisition, respectively, in the 22-cm field of view.</p>
<p>Each of the 6 angiography systems included integrated dosimetry instrumentation that displayed air kerma at the reference point, defined as 15 cm from C-arm isocenter toward the x-ray tube. The displayed reference point air kerma (Ka, r) output was compared to an external ionization chamber measurement for each angiography unit using the measurement protocol detailed in Balter et al.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1538574413495460">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1538574413495460">5</xref>
</sup> A correction factor was determined for each unit, averaged over a range of phantom thicknesses and fluoroscopy and digital acquisition modes, and used to correct patient Ka, r values. Correction factors (displayed: external chamber) ranged from 0.87 to 1.25. Measurements were repeated annually on each system over the course of the study to ensure consistency of the Ka readout.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1538574413495460">
<title>Statistical Methods</title>
<p>Categorical variables are expressed as ratios and percentages. Continuous variables are expressed as means ± standard deviation (SD) or medians with ranges. Descriptive statistics was performed to determine the mean, SD, and range for the reported values. Given the variation in the data, a base-10 logarithmic transformation was performed on the fluoroscopy time data followed by an <italic>F</italic> test for variance and a student’s <italic>t</italic> test for significance with a 95% confidence interval. The resultant values were then back-transformed to provide readers with a scale they may be more accustomed to viewing. Data that have undergone said transformation and back-transformation are designated with an asterisk (*).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1538574413495460">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section10-1538574413495460">
<title>Patient Demographics</title>
<p>A total of 134 patients (75 males) with a mean age of 70.6 ± 10.6 years (33-89 years) comprise the current study (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1538574413495460">Table 1</xref>). The renal artery stenosis was a result of atherosclerosis in 95 patients, fibromuscular dysplasia and atherosclerosis in 20 patients, in-stent stenosis in a previously placed stent in 13 patients, anastomotic stenosis involving transplanted kidneys in 5 patients, and in 3 patients the cause was not noted. The mean BMI was 28.8 ± 6.6 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (13.0-50.8 kg/m<sup>2)</sup>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1538574413495460" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Study Demographics.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1538574413495460" xlink:href="10.1177_1538574413495460-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Variable</th>
<th>Study Group (N = 134)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Male sex (%)</td>
<td>75 (56)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age (mean ± SD years)</td>
<td>70.6 ± 10.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BMI (mean ± SD kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
<td>28.8 ± 6.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Risk Factors (%)</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tobacco </td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Current user</td>
<td>16 (12)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Former user</td>
<td>80 (60)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hypertension</td>
<td>133 (99)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Renal insufficiency</td>
<td>130 (97)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hyperlipidemia</td>
<td>107 (80)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Coronary artery disease</td>
<td>64 (48)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Diabetes mellitus</td>
<td>32 (24)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Etiology of stenosis</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Atherosclerosis</td>
<td>94 (70)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Fibromuscular dysplasia</td>
<td>20 (15)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> In-stent stenosis</td>
<td>13 (10)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Anastomotic</td>
<td>4 (3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other etiology</td>
<td>3 (2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Preprocedural imaging (%)</td>
<td align="center">(N = 132)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Ultrasound only</td>
<td>91 (69)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Advanced imaging</td>
<td>41 (31)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> CTA</td>
<td>14 (11)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> MRA/MRI</td>
<td>21 (16)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Angiography</td>
<td>3 (2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Combination</td>
<td>3 (2)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1538574413495460">
<p>Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; CTA, computed tomography angiography; MRA, magnetic resonance angiography; MRI, magnetic resonance imaging; SD, standard deviation.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The comorbidities for the study group included 133 (99%) patients with hypertension and 130 (96%) with chronic renal insufficiency. The mean number of antihypertensive medications per patient was 3.3 ± 1.5 medication (0-8). The mean preprocedural creatinine was 1.8 ± 1.2 mg/dL (0.5-10.9 mg/dL).</p>
<p>The diagnosis of renal artery stenosis was often made on noninvasive studies prior to the intervention in 132 (99%) patients prior to the stent placement. This was most often ultrasound in 91 (69%) but also included CTA in 14 (9%) or MRA in 8 (8%).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1538574413495460">
<title>Factors Influencing the Average Fluoroscopy Time</title>
<p>The mean fluoroscopy time for the study group was 15.6 minutes (2-61 minutes) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1538574413495460">Table 2</xref>). We analyzed the different factors that may influence fluoroscopy time including the number of stents placed (1 vs more than 1), BMI of the patient, use of embolic device during the procedure, years of service of the performing physician (≤10 vs &gt;10), and the number of patient encounters requiring renal artery stent placement during the study (≤ 10 vs &gt;10).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1538574413495460" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Factors Influencing Radiation dose and Fluoroscopic Time.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1538574413495460" xlink:href="10.1177_1538574413495460-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> </th>
<th>
</th>
<th>N = Mean Fluoroscopy Time ± Standard Deviation </th>
<th>
<italic>P</italic> Value</th>
<th>Mean Absorbed Dose ± Standard Deviation </th>
<th>
<italic>P </italic>Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>All procedures</td>
<td>134</td>
<td>15.6 ± 10.8 minutes</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>1729.0 ± 1253.2 mGy</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of stents placed</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> One </td>
<td>95</td>
<td>13.8 ± 10.5 minutes</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.0002<sup>a</sup>
</td>
<td>1803.4 ± 1310.1 mGy</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.03<sup>a</sup>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> More than one</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>19.7 ± 10.6 minutes</td>
<td>2380.2 ± 1664.9 mGy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Embolic protection device</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>14.9 ± 9.8 minutes</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.15<sup>a</sup>
</td>
<td>1962.2 ± 1439.7 mGy</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.64<sup>a</sup>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No</td>
<td>115</td>
<td>19.7 ± 15.4 minutes</td>
<td>1972.8 ± 1446.6mGy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Aortogram performed</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>17.1 ± 11.3 minutes</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.05<sup>a</sup>
</td>
<td>2090.2 ± 1549.9 mGy</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.3<sup>a</sup>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No</td>
<td>74</td>
<td>14.3 ± 10.3 minutes</td>
<td>1874.9 ± 1347.9 mGy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Preprocedure advanced imaging</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>15.9 ± 13.2 minutes</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.6<sup>a</sup>
</td>
<td>1873.9 ± 1357.8 mGy</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.7<sup>a</sup>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> US only</td>
<td>91</td>
<td>15.4 ± 9.8 minutes</td>
<td>2025.8 ± 1491.0 mGy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> BMI &lt; 30</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>14.6 ± 8.8 minutes</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.5<sup>a</sup>
</td>
<td>2040.6 ± 1490.3 mGy</td>
<td rowspan="2">0.9<sup>a</sup>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> BMI ≥ 30</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>17.0 ± 13.2 minutes</td>
<td>1865.5 ± 1367.3 mGy</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1538574413495460">
<p>
<sup>a</sup>Calculated with a log 10 transformation</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-1538574413495460">
<p>Abbreviation: BMI, body mass index; US, ultrasound.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>In all, 95patients had 1 renal artery stent placed, while 39 patients had 2 or more stents placed. Patients who had 1 stent placed had significantly lower fluoroscopy time than those that had more than 1 stent (13.8 vs 19.7 minutes, respectively, <italic>P</italic> = .0002).We analyzed whether an abdominal angiogram followed by renal artery angiography would significantly increase fluoroscopy time when compared to procedures in which selective renal angiography was only performed. There was a significant increase in the mean fluoroscopy time when compared to those in which selective angiography was only performed (17.1 minutes* vs 14.3 minutes*, <italic>P</italic> = .05). We next assessed for differences in fluoroscopy time based upon whether an embolic protection device was used during the stent placement. There was no significant increase in the mean fluoroscopy time for cases when an embolic protection device was used (19.7) versus in cases when it was not used (14.9; <italic>P</italic> = .15). Finally, we observed a trend to lower average fluoroscopic time for interventional radiologists who performed more than 10 renal stents versus those that performed ≤10 stents (12.1 vs 14.6, respectively, <italic>P</italic> = .1) during the study period. There was no difference in mean fluoroscopy time between physician experiences based on years of service.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1538574413495460">
<title>Factors Influencing Radiation Dose</title>
<p>The average patient radiation dose was 1729 mGy. We analyzed the different factors that may influence radiation dose including the number of stents placed (1 vs more than 1), BMI of the patient, use of embolic device during the procedure, years of service of the performing physician (≤10 vs &gt;10), and the number of patient encounters requiring renal artery stent placement during the study (≤ 10 vs &gt;10). Patients who had 1 stent placed had a mean radiation dose, which was significantly lower than patients who received more than 1 stent (1803 vs 2380.2 mGy, respectively, <italic>P</italic> = .03). There was no difference in the average fluoroscopic dose for any of the other measures.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1538574413495460">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Radiation exposure during image-guided procedures and diagnostic procedures are gaining increasing awareness by patients and regulatory bodies. There are limited studies that have described the radiation does and fluoroscopic time during common interventional procedures. In the present article, we determined the factors that influence radiation and fluoroscopic time during renal artery stent placement. We identified only 1 factor that was associated with increased mean radiation dose which was the number of stents placed during the procedure.</p>
<p>There has been only 1 study that investigated fluoroscopic procedure times and radiation dose renal artery stent placement. In this study, the investigators observed that the mean fluoroscopy time for renal and visceral stents was 21.6 minutes, and the mean dose was 1605 mGy. The authors did not state the factors that contributed to the increased values. In the present study, the average fluoroscopic time was 15.6 minutes, and the average fluoroscopic dose was 1729 mGy. One factor for the decreased fluoroscopic time and dose may be the fact that we selected only renal artery procedures, and this had a more homogenous group of procedures. Additionally, although many different operators performed the procedure, it is performed in a very similar manner using monorail technology through a guide sheath.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the results from the present study demonstrate that factors such as number of renal artery stents placed dictate the mean fluoroscopic time and dose. We found no association among the numbers of years on service, number of stent placed per year, or the use of EPD. Further larger studies are warranted, as this represents a single institution experience.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at" id="fn1-1538574413495460">
<label>Authors’ Note</label>
<p>This paper was presented at the Society of Interventional Radiology Meeting in March 2011 in Chicago, Illinois.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn2-1538574413495460">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-1538574413495460">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1538574413495460">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.revisor.mn.gov/rules/?id=4732.0610">https://www.revisor.mn.gov/rules/?id=4732.0610</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed February 1, 2013</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1538574413495460">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Balter</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schueler</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Radiation doses in interventional radiology procedures: the RAD-IR Study. Part III: dosimetric performance of the interventional fluoroscopy units.</article-title> <source>J Vasc Interv Radiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>919</fpage>–<lpage>926</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1538574413495460">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Balter</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Radiation doses in interventional radiology procedures: the RAD-IR study: part II: skin dose</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Interv Radiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>14</volume>
<issue>(8)</issue>:<fpage>977</fpage>–<lpage>990</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1538574413495460">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Balter</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wagner</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Quality improvement guidelines for recording patient radiation dose in the medical record</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Interv Radiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>15</volume>
<issue>(5)</issue>:<fpage>423</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1538574413495460">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Safian</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Textor</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Renal-artery stenosis</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>344</volume>
<issue>(6)</issue>:<fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1538574413495460">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dorros</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jaff</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mathiak</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Four-year follow-up of Palmaz-Schatz stent revascularization as treatment for atherosclerotic renal artery stenosis</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>98</volume>
<issue>(7)</issue>:<fpage>642</fpage>–<lpage>647</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1538574413495460">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rundback</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sacks</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kent</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Guidelines for the reporting of renal artery revascularization in clinical trials</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Interv Radiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>S477</fpage>–<lpage>S492</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>