<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JAS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjas</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Asian and African Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9096</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1745-2538</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0021909612439684</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0021909612439684</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Secession – the Last Resort for Minority Protection</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>de Villiers</surname><given-names>Bertus</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0021909612439684">State Adminsitrative Tribunal, University of Western Australia, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0021909612439684">Bertus de Villiers, State Administrative Tribunal, PO Box U1991, Perth, 6841, Australia Email: <email>bertus.devilliers@justice.wa.gov.au</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>48</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>81</fpage>
<lpage>96</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>‘Secession’ is a word that brings fear to nations. It reeks of conflict, violence and instability. It is also a measure of last resort. It sometimes brings hope to minorities that are in despair and who feel permanently excluded from policy making. This article looks at some of the faces of secession. It investigates how international law is vague on the one hand and pragmatic on the other hand when it comes to secession. It shows how, in recent times, secession has been endorsed by the international community in cases such as East Timor, Eritrea and Kosovo while in Ethiopia and Canada legal mechanisms exist for managing demands for secession. Consideration is given to some of the pre-requisites for secession. Finally general observations are made about secession as a mechanism to protect minorities.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Federalism</kwd>
<kwd>international law</kwd>
<kwd>minority protection</kwd>
<kwd>secession</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0021909612439684" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Secession is a word that brings fear to the heart of young and old democracies, and especially to young, developing federations. Young federations are often born in the strife of ethnic mobilization and threats of regional secession – refer for example to the experiences of India (Pakistan and Bangladesh), Nigeria (Biafra), Ethiopia (Eritrea) and Indonesia (East Timor). Ethnic minorities in deeply divided societies regularly view secession as the last resort to secure the protection of the rights they believe are neglected, ignored or even suppressed within the existing state in which they find themselves.</p>
<p>Images of Biafra-type violence, the implosion of Yugoslavia, the civil war in Sudan, the violence of Eritrea and the civil war that preceded the independence of East Timor and instability that so often follows in the wake of secession are fresh in the mind. These secessionist conflicts cause grave concern in the mind of many young democracies about the risk that federalism may bring. The forced ‘independence’ that was imposed on <italic>homelands</italic> in apartheid-South Africa is an additional contributing factor to the distaste not only in that country but also in many other African countries towards the word ‘federation’ and the perception that establishing a federation is the first step towards secession.</p>
<p>The question that confronts many young and emerging federations is: does regional autonomy by way of federalism or decentralization encourage or prevent secession? Federalism, especially ethnic federalism where the regional-state<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0021909612439684">1</xref></sup> boundaries are drawn along ethnic lines, is seen by many of the critics of federalism as the first step on a slippery slope towards secession. According to this school of thought the risk of secession is increased by recognizing in the constitution, as Ethiopia has done, the right of individual states to secession. The proponents of federalism, on the other hand, view federalism as a nation-building mechanism that could assist nations to avert rather than encourage secession by giving all the constituent parts of society a share in ‘self-rule’ (autonomy) and ‘shared-rule’ (power-sharing; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0021909612439684">Elazar, 1987</xref>: 7).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0021909612439684">2</xref></sup> They contend that it is through the very flexibility of federalism and the options it offers for asymmetry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0021909612439684">Watts, 2005</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0021909612439684">3</xref></sup> that secession can be averted. They argue that federalism provides a constitutional framework to harness secessionist forces rather than to encourage it.</p>
<p>Secession, in short, has been defined as follows by the Supreme Court of Canada:<disp-quote>
<p>Secession is the effort of a group or section of a state to withdraw itself from the political and constitutional authority of that state, with a view to achieving statehood for a new territorial unit on the international plane. In a federal state, secession typically takes the form of a territorial unit seeking to withdraw from the federation. Secession is a legal act as much as a political one. ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021909612439684">Attorney General of Canada, 1998</xref>: 217)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The answer to the question of whether federalism, and in particular a constitutionally recognized right to secession, encourages or defuses secessionist demands is yet open to answer. There are examples on the one hand where a refusal to acknowledge ethnic diversity can stimulate secessionist demands whether the form of state is federal or unitary – refer for example to Scottish demands for independence from the United Kingdom, Basque demands in Spain and the conflict preceding independence of East Timor. There are also examples on the other hand that the recognition of the right to secession may defuse separatist demands – refer for example to the experiences of Ethiopia where, without guarantees of secession, the nation may have split apart.</p>
<p>There is insufficient evidence to conclude unequivocally that federalism facilitates or encourages secession. On the contrary, there are strong indications, based on comparative experiences of federations with deeply divided populations, that, had it not been for federalism, nations such as India, Switzerland, Belgium, Nigeria and Malaysia may have split into separate, sovereign states.</p>
<p>This article is not intended to propose secession as a necessary option for the protection of minority groups, but it has to be acknowledged that, in some instances, the recognition of the right to secede may be considered as a legitimate, albeit last, option to protect a minority given the circumstances of a particular country. Even if secession is not granted, recognition of the right to secession, as in the case of Ethiopia and Canada, may defuse ethnic mobilization and, perversely, guarantee the national unity.</p>
<p>This article looks at some of the faces of secession. It investigates how international law is vague on the one hand and pragmatic on the other hand when it comes to secession. It seeks to address the question whether federations are more prone to secession than unitary systems. It shows how, in recent times, secession has been endorsed by the international community in cases such as East Timor, Eritrea and Kosovo. Consideration is given to some of the pre-requisites for secession. Attention is also give to the way in which Ethiopia and Canada have attempted to manage secessionist debates by providing a legal mechanism in law. Finally general observations are made about secession as a mechanism to protect minorities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0021909612439684">
<title>Secession in International Law</title>
<p>It is exceptional for a constitution or statute to recognize a legal right of a region or a group to secede. If an entitlement of secession is recognized, it is usually included in a constitution as a last resort to maintain national unity, to convince a region to join a federation; or during a transitional phase when a confederal arrangement is converted into a federal arrangement and safeguards are required to allow members of the confederal arrangement with the right to withdraw before the federation solidifies.</p>
<p>In general, international law recognizes the integrity and sovereignty of existing states and the authority of states to protect their territorial integrity and to resist, within democratic means, efforts to secede. Refer for example to the decision of the Supreme Court of Canada discussed below in which the court found that international law does not recognize the right of a province within the Canadian federation to declare its own independence unilaterally.</p>
<p>At the same time, however, the international community has at many occasions condoned secessionist movements and contributed by way of international law to the creation of new states. Refer for example to the creation of Pakistan, Bangladesh, the splitting up of Yugoslavia and the separation of East Timor from Indonesia. The most recent experiences where international law has accepted the realities that accompany secessionist demands are found in the unilateral declaration of independence of Kosovo and the independence of South Sudan. International law is, at best, vague and very pragmatic when it comes to dealing with secession. It resists secession, but it accepts the reality thereof if no other options are available. One observer succinctly puts it as follows:<disp-quote>
<p>When violence has become so strong that it can no longer be suppressed without an unacceptable level of state terrorism, then the state concerned has, either as a victim of violence or as a perpetrator, lost the legitimacy that enables it to insist on its territorial integrity. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0021909612439684">Szasz, 1999</xref>: 7)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>While it is acknowledged that there is reticence to secession in international law, it is also patently obvious at the same time that international boundaries are constructions of humans at a specific point in time and it cannot always be taken that international state boundaries are cast in stone and immune from alteration. One only needs to refer to the experiences of Europe in state formation during the past two centuries to realize how international boundaries are in flux and can change over time. International boundaries are, therefore, regardless to popular belief, not set in stone.</p>
<p>While secession as a legal entitlement or an enforceable right in a constitution is exceptional, in practice secession does occur from time to time – with the blessing of the international community. Refer for example to the separation of India and Pakistan and then Bangladesh; Malaysia and Singapore; Indonesia and East Timor; the split-up of the Soviet Union; the separation of the Yugoslavian republics; the separation of Eritrea from Ethiopia; the splitting of Slovakia and the Czech Republic; the declaration of independence by Kosovo; and most recently the secession of South Sudan from Sudan. Unwanted, uncertain and unwelcome as secession often is, it is sometimes an option of last resort to defuse the conflict that may result if a new state is not born. Moore puts the tenuous status of some state boundaries from the view of minorities who find themselves within a state against their will as follows:<disp-quote>
<p>In many cases, national minorities are correct to point out that administrative boundaries frequently have no moral basis themselves, or that they were often drawn in accordance with a moral or political conception that is irrelevant in the current political situation, or drawn by the central state in order to facilitate assimilation of the minorities or its control by the dominant group. It is therefore hard to see why these boundaries should be cast in stone, as the only unit in which self-determination can take place. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0021909612439684">Moore, 2001</xref>: 159)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The following general principles have crystallized from the international law approach to secession:</p>
<list id="list1-0021909612439684" list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>there is no right in international law to secession, although the ‘right of peoples to self-determination’ in international law is recognized. International law is, however, not clear as to the definition of ‘peoples’ and it does not seem as if the right to self-determination automatically gives minorities within a sovereign state a legal entitlement to autonomy or secession (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0021909612439684">Sterio, 2010</xref>: 138);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>withdrawal by a sovereign state from a confederal arrangement is not akin to secession since the very nature of a confederal relationship is voluntary and based on the continued recognition of the sovereignty of each member state until such time that the confederal arrangements move into a federal arrangement. A federation is a separate, sovereign entity in international law in contrast to a confederation which is an association of sovereign nations;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>it is extremely rare for sovereign states to include in their constitution or in a statute a right to secede. Although such a clause was in the constitution of the Soviet Union, those constitutional arrangements could not be classified as a democratic, federal state. In contemporary constitutional law, Ethiopia is the only democratic constitution that formally recognizes the right of states to secede although Canada provides by way of statute for provinces to secede;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>sovereign states, especially those with deeply divided societies and especially young democracies, are often hesitant to engage in decentralization or federalism since they are concerned that regional autonomy may fuel secessionist movements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0021909612439684">Wellman, 2011</xref>: 33);<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0021909612439684">4</xref></sup> but there is insufficient evidence to conclude that decentralization by itself encourages secession – decentralization and federalism may in fact have the opposite effect by reducing secessionist pressures;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>the right to secession is, albeit as a last resort, on the range of options that could be considered as a measure of last resort to accommodate minority demands if all other options fail and, although international law does not necessarily encourage secession, it accepts secession as an inevitability in some instances;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>the non-recognition of the right to secession in a constitution does not in itself rule out the possibility of secession, but simultaneously the recognition of the right to secede in a constitution does not by itself mean that secession would necessarily occur. The right of secession may, however, distract from integration and nation-building activities as minorities may seek to maximize their leverage with a threat of secession; and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>international law does not preclude or prohibit secession. Although secession is not encouraged, international law is very pragmatic as is evidenced in the many examples in international law where secession has been endorsed and the new state had been recognized.</p></list-item></list>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0021909612439684">
<title>Country Experiences</title>
<p>In this section, consideration will be given to the way in which countries have dealt with demands for secession and the response of international law to it. Ethiopia is a unique example in contemporary constitutional law where the right to secession is included in the 1994 constitution. So far no state has yet demanded secession although the de facto one party state may inhibit debate about secession. East Timor gained separation from Indonesia with the blessing of the international community after years of conflict following the forcible take-over of the region in 1976. Canada has also since 2000 recognized the right of a province to request secession, but the right is reflected in a statute and not in the constitution. The right of a province in Canada to demand secession is also not as unqualified as it appears the case is in the Ethiopian constitution. Kosovo offers insight into the pragmatism that is adopted by the international community when it comes to secession since its declaration of independence was accepted against very strong arguments by some parts of the international community. Tanzania shows how even a unitary system can be challenged by demands for secession.</p>
<sec id="section4-0021909612439684">
<title>Ethiopia</title>
<p>Article 39(1) of the Federal Constitution of Ethiopia recognizes that ‘every Nation, Nationality and People in Ethiopia has an <italic>unconditional</italic> right to self-determination, including the right to secession’ (author’s emphasis). Similar provisions regarding an ‘unconditional right’ to secession are found in Ethiopian state constitutions, for example the constitution of the Southern Nations, Nationalities and Peoples State contains in a39 a similar clause as the federal constitution in which the ‘unconditional right’ to secession of nations, nationalities and peoples within the state is recognized. This institutionalization of the right to self-determination and secession within a democratic, federal constitution is without parallel in contemporary constitutional law. There is no other constitutional dispensation that recognizes in such an unqualified way the right to secession of a region or an ethnic group.</p>
<p>The Constitution of Ethiopia a39(4) sets out the following procedure for attainment of self-determination, including secession: (a) the demand for secession must be approved by a two-thirds majority of the members<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0021909612439684">5</xref></sup> of the state legislature; (b) the federal government must, within three years from receiving the request, conduct a referendum within the state concerned on the request; (c) the request must be supported by a majority of the population; (d) the federal government must transfer its powers to the newly established nation; and (e) assets must be divided in a manner prescribed by law.</p>
<p>It is not clear from the constitution if these provisions of the constitution of Ethiopia are ‘self-executing’, in the sense that the federal government is obligated to grant an application for secession if the procedures are met, or whether the federal government can refuse to grant an application if, for example, it is of the view that secession may give rise to violence; that it may not be feasible or not practical; that the majority was too slim to justify secession; or that minorities that remain in the proposed new state would be at risk. The author would contend that, regardless of the impression that the constitutional procedure for secession is an automatic process, the federal government (parliament and cabinet) retains an inherent discretion to protect the constitution and territorial integrity of Ethiopia, to fully consider an application for secession and to assess the merit of secession based on all the information at its disposal, to exercise its discretion, to grant secession or to refuse it. This suggestion is consistent with the comments by the Supreme Court of Canada when it decided that the expression of interest by a province to secede must be followed by detailed negotiations as to the necessary detail. As far as Canada is concerned, the right to secession is not self-executing and must be preceded by extensive negotiations. Refer to the following comments by the Canadian Supreme Court:<disp-quote>
<p>For both theoretical and practical reasons, we cannot accept this view [of unilateral secession]. We hold that Quebec could not purport to invoke a right of self-determination such as to dictate the terms of a proposed secession to the other parties: that would not be a negotiation at all. As well, it would be naive to expect that the substantive goal of secession could readily be distinguished from the practical details of secession. <italic>The devil would be in the details</italic>. The democracy principle, as we have emphasized, cannot be invoked to trump the principles of federalism and rule of law, the rights of individuals and minorities, or the operation of democracy in the other provinces or in Canada as a whole. No negotiations could be effective if their ultimate outcome, secession, is cast as an absolute legal entitlement based upon an obligation to give effect to that act of secession in the constitution. Such a foregone conclusion would actually undermine the obligation to negotiate and render it hollow. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021909612439684">Attorney General of Canada, 1998</xref>: 217; author’s emphasis)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The author would contend that similar principles should guide any request in Ethiopia for secession.</p>
<p>The inclusion of the right to secede in the constitution of Ethiopia was and remains a source of controversy, not only locally but also internationally. To one school of thought the secessionist clause was an essential compromise to integrate the divergent fighting forces after the collapse of the previous military dictatorship; to unite and bring stability to Ethiopia; to serve as a safeguard for ethnic minorities against abuse of powers by the central government; and to protect the identities of the respective ethnic groups against the hegemony of the past where one group dominated the rest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0021909612439684">Zenawi, 1994</xref>: 5–6).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0021909612439684">6</xref></sup> The other school of thought contends that it was an error to include the right of secession in the constitution since it erodes rather than builds national unity; it undermines efforts to build a common identity; it makes Ethiopia a prisoner of ethnic mobilization; and it can lead to abuse and threats by ethnic groups within the respective states (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0021909612439684">Habtu, 2010</xref>: 147).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0021909612439684">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Regardless of contemporary debates and assessment of historical wrongs and rights about the secessionist-clause (a39), Habtu insists that:<disp-quote>
<p>the secession clause in the charter and subsequent constitution was an outcome of a necessary bargain to ensure the retention of Ethiopia as one state entity, albeit minus Eritrea. Those who work on the assumption that the EPRDF [the federal governing party Ethiopian Peoples’ Revolutionary Democratic Front] had options other than inclusion of the secession clause are oblivious to the prevailing reality at the time of the July conference [Conference on Peace and Democracy to create a Transitional Government]. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0021909612439684">Habtu, 2010</xref>: 25)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Smis describes the secessionist clause as a paradox for the following reason:<disp-quote>
<p>On the one hand if no federal solution had been adopted with such a broad right to self-determination, not so many sub-nationalities or centrifugal forces would today claim self-determination or threaten with separation. On the other hand, the recognition of the right to self-determination was probably the only way to hold the country together. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0021909612439684">Smis, 2008</xref>: 125)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>So far, only one state, Eritrea, seceded from Ethiopia and that took place prior to the enactment of the federal constitution.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0021909612439684">8</xref></sup> Article 39 remains in the caldron of politics with the ruling party defending it and opposition parties demanding that the constitution be amended to remove it. The article is therefore used by all sides of politics to promote their own stance and this polarization reduces the chances of finding common ground about the future of a39. While some may see it as important from a ‘symbolical’ point of view, others see it as perpetuating ‘divisiveness’ and insist it must be removed from the constitution.</p>
<p>The dominance of a single political grouping at all levels of government in Ethiopia contributes to what appears as a calmness on the surface of the secessionist debate, but that may belie dynamics that may follow the replacement of the dominant single party by other political parties at local, state and even the national level. The right to secession is a reflection of the way in which the federal constitution of Ethiopia came into being – cooperation between nations, nationalities and peoples in which, according to the constitution, sovereignty lies (a8). Some observers insist the inclusion of the right to self-determination in the constitution was a remnant of the previous communist-left regime<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0021909612439684">9</xref></sup> and that the ruling party, the EPRDF, is not really in favour of the right being exercised. Other observers stress that the security and stability of Ethiopia is not solely dependent upon its recognition of the right to secession, but also on its ability to integrate competing political, ethnic and other dynamics. Fiseha and Habib emphasize that ‘whether the federal system will consolidate unity in diversity or fragment among the various groups depends on commitment to the federal principle, accommodation of difference and political pluralism, and more importantly respect for human rights …’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0021909612439684">Fiseha and Habib, 2010</xref>: 153).</p>
<p>As mentioned earlier, Eritrea is the only (former) state within Ethiopia that has sought and received its independence by way of secession. The history of Eritrea has, however, always been unique compared to the experiences of the other Ethiopian states. Eritrea was a colony of Italy from 1889 to 1941 after which attempts were made by Emperor Haile Selassie to integrate the territory into Ethiopia. After the conclusion of the Second World War, the British and Americans favoured a federal relationship between Ethiopia and Eritrea while the Soviet Union supported independence. The population of Eritrea is not homogenous and has close linkages with communities in the Ethiopian states of Tigray and Afar. The Eritreans fought a war for independence against Ethiopia from 1970 until the granting of their independence in 1990. Eritrea is, according to Castellino, one of the ‘best’ examples of how a minority succeeded to obtain by way of secession a new state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0021909612439684">Castellino, 1999</xref>: 401), but account should nevertheless be taken of the violence and bloodshed that accompanied Eritrea’s demands and the unresolved issues between it and Ethiopia.</p>
<p>Various reasons have been suggested why Eritrea opted for secession and what makes Eritrea’s experiences different from the current states of Ethiopia. The main reasons suggested why there was such a strong demand for secession in Eritrea were the centralist control exercised from Addis Ababa over the region, for example the banning of political activity and media in Eritrea; replacement of the Eritrean language with Amharic, the dominant language in Ethiopia; the banning of the use and display of Eritrean symbols; and the refusal to accept for Eritrea a self-governing status within Ethiopia. If the clock could be turned back and Eritrea was afforded the same status and guarantees that the current Ethiopian states enjoy, the demands for secession may have been less successful.</p>
<p>The practical implications of the secessionist clause in the constitution of Ethiopia must yet reveal itself in all dimensions. To remove the right to secession from the constitution is, currently at least, a bridge too far. To demand secession in terms of it is, ironically, also probably not an acceptable to the EPRDF. The secessionist clause remains therefore a symbol which evokes different reactions. The assessment of Habtu seems to be credible when he concludes as follows:<disp-quote>
<p>All that can be concluded, provisionally, is that the viability of multiethnic federalism is indeterminate. Contingent events (such as whether there is equitable power-sharing among ethnic groups, equitable revenue sharing between the federal and regional states, further democratization, and rapid economic and educational development) will shape the outcome of the multiethnic federal experiment … Thus far, multiethnic federalism has undercut the drive for secession by largely removing manifest aspects of ethnic oppression (e.g. language use) that would have rallied ethnonationalist organizations. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0021909612439684">Habtu, 2005</xref>: 334)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0021909612439684">
<title>Canada</title>
<p>The pre-secession procedures and requirements of a39 of the constitution of Ethiopia are consistent with the standard set down by the Supreme Court of Canada in 2000 when it was requested to make a ruling on the desire of Quebec to secede from Canada (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021909612439684">Attorney General of Canada, 1998</xref>: 217). The background to the Supreme Court’s decision is briefly that, after several failed attempts to reform the federal system of Canada to strengthen and expand the autonomy of the province Quebec, the government of Quebec conducted a referendum to determine whether the people of the province wanted to secede from Canada. The ‘no’ vote won with a very slight majority of around 1%. The Quebec government reserved the ‘right’ to conduct another referendum in due course. The federal government commenced court proceedings in regard to the legality of a province to initiate a process of unilateral declaration of independence. The three questions which were referred to the Supreme Court for an advisory opinion and the court’s reply thereto can be summarized as follows:</p>
<list id="list2-0021909612439684" list-type="simple"><list-item><p>1. Under the Constitution of Canada, can the National Assembly, legislature or government of Quebec effect the secession of Quebec from Canada unilaterally?</p></list-item></list>
<p>The answer of the Supreme Court was ‘no’. Unilateral secession by Quebec was not legal, although if the population of Quebec decided by way of a referendum that they wished to secede, negotiations would have to occur between the federal government and the government of Quebec to consider and if necessary, give effect to the request (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021909612439684">Attorney General of Canada, 1998</xref>: 217 at 86).</p>
<p>The court determined that, although a referendum is an important first step when a province seeks to secede, there are other steps that must be followed for the process to be complete and for the constitution to be amended. The court acknowledged that ‘the clear repudiation of the existing constitutional order and the clear expression of the desire to pursue secession by the population of a province would give rise to a reciprocal obligation on all parties to confederation to negotiate constitutional changes to respond to that desire’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021909612439684">Attorney General of Canada, 1998</xref>: 217 at 88). The mere fact that a majority of a province’s population vote in favour of secession does not mean that secession would automatically follow.</p>
<list id="list3-0021909612439684" list-type="simple"><list-item><p>2. Does international law give the National Assembly, legislature or government of Quebec the right to effect the secession of Quebec from Canada unilaterally? In this regard is there a right to self-determination under international law that would give the National Assembly, legislature or government of Quebec the right to effect the secession of Quebec from Canada unilaterally?</p></list-item></list>
<p>The court found that the proposed secession of Quebec was not a matter to be determined under international law since international law ‘does not specifically grant component parts of sovereign states the legal right to secede unilaterally from their “parent” state’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021909612439684">Attorney General of Canada, 1998</xref>: 217 at 111).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-0021909612439684">10</xref></sup> The court went on to make the following important observation:<disp-quote>
<p>A state whose government represents the whole of the people or peoples resident within its territory, on a basis of equality and without discrimination, and respects the principles of self-determination in its own internal arrangements, is entitled to the protection under international law of its territorial integrity. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021909612439684">Attorney General of Canada, 1998</xref>: 217 at 130)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<list id="list4-0021909612439684" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>3. In the event of a conflict between domestic and international law on the right of the National Assembly, legislature or government of Quebec to effect the secession of Quebec from Canada unilaterally, which would take precedence in Canada?</p></list-item></list>
<p>The court found that, even if the majority of the people in Quebec were to decide by way of referendum that they desired for the province to secede from Canada, Quebec cannot dictate the terms of that separation since it must be negotiated with the federal government and be given effect, if agreement is reached, of a constitutional amendment.</p>
<p>It would seem from the court’s decision that the federal government and other provinces cannot merely refuse to grant an application for secession. The federal government therefore does not have a veto, but it has the right and duty to negotiate the manner in which secession is granted as well as the conditions attached thereto. The court said as follows:<disp-quote>
<p>Quebec could not, despite a clear referendum result, purport to invoke a right of self-determination to dictate the terms of a proposed secession to the other parties to the federation. The democratic vote, by however strong a majority, would have no legal effect on its own and could not push aside the principles of federalism and the rule of law, the rights of individuals and minorities, or the operation of democracy in the other provinces or in Canada as a whole. Democratic rights under the constitution cannot be divorced from constitutional obligations. Nor, however, can the reverse proposition be accepted. The continued existence and operation of the Canadian constitutional order could not be indifferent to a clear expression of a clear majority of Quebecers that they no longer wish to remain in Canada. <italic>The other provinces and the federal government would have no basis to deny the right of the government of Quebec to pursue secession, should a clear majority of the people of Quebec choose that goal, so long as in doing so, Quebec respects the rights of others</italic>. The negotiations that followed such a vote would address the potential act of secession as well as its possible terms should in fact secession proceed. There would be no conclusions predetermined by law on any issue. Negotiations would need to address the interests of the other provinces, the federal government, Quebec and indeed the rights of all Canadians both within and outside Quebec, and specifically the rights of minorities. No one suggests that it would be an easy set of negotiations. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021909612439684">Attorney General of Canada, 1998</xref>: 217 at 151; author’s emphasis)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In reply to the decision of the Supreme Court, the government of Canada initiated legislation which was passed by parliament to provide the ‘ground rules’ for processing an application by a province for secession (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0021909612439684">Leslie, 1999</xref>: 135; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0021909612439684">Oliver, 1999</xref>: 65). The so-called ‘Clarity Act’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0021909612439684">Parliament of Canada, 2000</xref>) acknowledges that any of the provinces may initiate a process of secession by way of a referendum under the people of its territory, but that a process of negotiation should then be embarked on to consider the request for secession.</p>
<p>The practical steps provided for by the Clarity Act are similar to what is found in the constitution of Ethiopia, namely submission of the proposed question to the house of commons for it to reply within 30 days thereon, in particular whether the question is clear and unambiguous (a1[3]–[4], Clarity Act); negotiations by the house of commons in regard to secession must take into account whether a ‘clear majority’ of the population supported the question (a2, Clarity Act); and if agreement is reached on the detail of secession, a constitutional amendment would have to be enacted to give effect to the separation of a part of Canadian territory to form a new state (a3, Clarity Act).</p>
<p>Since the enactment of the Clarity Act the demands for secession of Quebec has declined substantially. This may be attributable to several factors. One possible explanation for the cooling-off of the secessionist debate may be that the legal framework that has been created to allow secession has in fact removed the risk of secession since it provides a safeguard for those that may in future seek secession.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0021909612439684">
<title>East Timor</title>
<p>East Timor was joined to Indonesia against its will in 1976 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0021909612439684">Charney, 2001</xref>: 455). The seed of secession was planted by the very way in which Indonesia sought to absorb East Timor as part of its territory. The international community immediately condemned the actions of Indonesia and a long struggle started to grant the region sovereignty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0021909612439684">Purnawanty, 2000</xref>: 61). The integration of East Timor was accompanied with some of the worst violence the world had seen at the time and it is estimated that up to 200,000 people died as a result of the military crackdown.</p>
<p>The struggle of the East Timorese to gain independence highlighted the ambivalence of the international community and the weakness of international law to provide certainty when it comes to demands for secession. At first the international community at the early stages of the East Timor annexation was focused on issues that dominated the Cold War. There was, as a result of other competing issues, no great appetite within the international community to become involved in the self-determination aspirations of the East Timorese. It is only after the collapse of communism in Europe that the United Nations (UN) and the major powers threw their weight behind the struggles of the East Timorese. It is only after the UN-sponsored referendum in 1999 and the establishment of the International Force for East Timor by Resolution 1264 that the secessionist movement gained momentum. East Timor became the first newly born sovereign state in the 21st century on 20 May 2002.</p>
<p>Few examples speak so clearly of the vagaries of international law when it comes to secession than the experience of East Timor. First, regardless of the way in which the territory was annexed, there was no political or legal force or willingness to commit any force so as to restore the status ante. Second, the political will within the international community was not directed at the East Timorese and as a result international law offered them no remedy. Third, even though there were sympathetic states, the ballast necessary for international action was not present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0021909612439684">Sterio, 2010</xref>: 154).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-0021909612439684">11</xref></sup> Fourth, international intervention will not be a given in every instance where a minority is subjected to persecution. It is only when a certain (undefined) threshold is reached, where international opinion, and thereafter international law, may offer a remedy. This explains why, for so many years, the plight of the East Timorese fell on deaf ears. East Timor only became independent when the ‘Great Powers’ determined that its cause was ‘legitimate’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0021909612439684">Sterio, 2010</xref>: 158).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0021909612439684">
<title>Tanzania</title>
<p>The possibility of secession has also provoked heated debates in the United Republic of Tanzania in its relationship with the region of Zanzibar. The international community has not thrown its weight behind the demands of the Zanzibari’s and, unless some major instability erupts or unless there is a domestic agreement to secession, it is unlikely the Zanzibar will be added to the list of sovereign states.</p>
<p>Tanzania and Zanzibar were merged in 1964 and the reasons and merit for the merger remain the subject of often heated debate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0021909612439684">Hopkins, 1971</xref>: 13). No mention was made at the time of union of the right to either of the entities to withdraw and, even today, talk of secession is frowned upon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0021909612439684">Jumbe, 1997</xref>). Complaints by those in Zanzibar about unequal treatment have caused a debate at two levels – on the one hand towards a greater integration with Tanzania and on the other hand the possibility of secession (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0021909612439684">Kabudi, 1993</xref>: 311).</p>
<p>The experience of the relationship between Zanzibar and Tanzania is instructive when it comes to the question of whether granting autonomy increases or reduces the risk of secession. In the case of Zanzibar, there are strong perceptions that their autonomy has over the years been decreased, that centralism has occurred and that these attempt to stymie their sense of uniqueness have been ‘counter-productive’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0021909612439684">Maalim, 2008</xref>: 113). This experience lends support to those who contend that it is not federalism that brings demand for secession – the societal conditions for secession are already present but federalism attempts to harness and control it. Maalim observes as follows: ‘The more the Zanzibaris are integrated into the union, the more they want autonomy’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0021909612439684">Maalim, 2008</xref>: 113). This observation is echoed by Tronvoll who says that ‘the process of centralizing power on behalf of the mainland has thus inspired a counter-force on the isles advocating for stronger autonomy’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0021909612439684">Tronvoll, 2006</xref>: 224). And as attitudes have hardened, the option of secession is more spoken about than ever before.</p>
<p>The relationship between mainland Tanzania and Zanzibar has been described as federal or <italic>quasi</italic> federal by many authors on the basis of the unique status of Zanzibar within the union arrangement. At the time of amalgamation Zanzibar retained autonomy in many areas although a formal federation was not formed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0021909612439684">Mtengwa, 2001</xref>). Zanzibar retained autonomy over all matters that were not explicitly allocated to the national government. In recent years, the national list has grown exponentially at the cost of Zanzibar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0021909612439684">Schmitt, 2004</xref>: 1).</p>
<p>In an application to Tanzania of possible causes that lead to the breakdown of bipolar federations, Tronvoll concludes that the ‘prospect for a sustainable and stable Tanzanian Union seems bleak’(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0021909612439684">Tronvoll, 2006</xref>: 240). According to him the reasons are fivefold: the electors were not asked at the time of union what their wishes were; the unity is being maintained by way of increasing centralization and authoritarian mechanisms; the Zanzibaris have a strong sense of being disadvantaged by the union; the autonomy of Zanzibar is being diminished; and Zanzibar perceived it as being at the losing end of economic development.</p>
<p>Some proponents of secession of Zanzibar contend that, since the area was sovereign before it became part of the Republic of Tanzania, and since there is no treaty or any other legal instrument that sets out the conditions of the union (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0021909612439684">Maalim, 2008</xref>: 133),<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-0021909612439684">12</xref></sup> it retained the inherent right to withdraw from the Republic of Tanzania. Others contend that, once Zanzibar became part of the republic, it lost any rights it may have had to withdraw since a union was formed and not a confederation.</p>
<p>If the position of the two schools are analyzed it seems as if they agree that the test developed by the Supreme Court in Canada in the Quebec matter may be of relevance to the Tanzanian debate since the ultimate decision must be made by the people concerned and, following the example of Canada, for the constitution to be amended. Since, for the time being at least, there is no major ethnic persecution in Tanzania, the most obvious route for secession for Zanzibar would be along the lines of Quebec – namely a popular referendum on the question of sovereignty followed by negotiations about the terms of separation as well as arrangements for continued cooperation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0021909612439684">
<title>Kosovo</title>
<p>The declaration of independence by Kosovo<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-0021909612439684">13</xref></sup> in 2008 also provides insight into how secession is viewed in international law. The International Court of Justice was requested in 2010 to provide an advisory opinion in regard to the lawfulness of the 2008 unilateral declaration of independence by Kosovo.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-0021909612439684">14</xref></sup> The court delivered its opinion on 22 July 2010 saying that the declaration of independence did not violate international law. The court was careful to point out that its opinion should not be read as if there was an entitlement or a right in international law to secession. The opinion was directed at the question of whether Kosovo acted on breach of international law when it declared independence and in this regard the answer was in the negative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0021909612439684">Kosovo Advisory Opinion, 2010</xref>: 56).</p>
<p>The court further highlighted that, in those matters where unilateral independence were resisted, for example the case of Southern Rhodesia, it was related to the unlawful use of force by the authority that demanded independence, while in the case of Kosovo it was not the case. This is consistent with the observations of the Supreme Court of Canada in regard to the unavailability of secession in a free and open country where democratic principles are applied and where the group seeking secession is not subject to persecution or other forms of abuse. The court concluded that an assessment of resolutions of the Security Council of the United Nations ‘confirm that no general prohibition against unilateral declarations of independence may be inferred from the practice of the Security Council’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0021909612439684">Kosovo Advisory Opinion, 2010</xref>: 82). The court therefore ruled that Kosovo, in declaring its independence, did not contravene international law (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0021909612439684">Kosovo Advisory Opinion, 2010</xref>: 84).</p>
<p>Although the court endorsed the independence of Kosovo, the violent events that preceded its independence and the commitment of major nations of the world to its independence played a key role in its becoming a sovereign state. Kosovo shares the experience of East Timor where strong international support for secession followed massive human rights infringements against a minority group. Had it not been for the human rights atrocities followed by widespread international support, Kosovo would in all likelihood not have received its independence.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section9-0021909612439684">
<title>Summary</title>
<p>In summary the following observations can be made about secession as a technique of last resort to protect minorities:</p>
<list id="list5-0021909612439684" list-type="order"><list-item><p>There is no conclusive evidence that federalism in itself encourages or facilitates secession. Unitary systems are also prone to secession. The reasons for secession are manifold, but it can usually be associated with mass human rights infringements; neglect of aspirations or permanent exclusion of minority groups; and decolonization or voluntary break-up of a sovereign state by way of agreement. It is exceptional for a democratic, federal constitution to recognize a right of secession in the way Ethiopia does. Federalism is widely credited as a form of state that can provide to regions and minorities the degree of autonomy they desire by way of self-rule, while at the same time giving them an interest and right to participate in national affairs through ‘shared rule’.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Federalism may contribute to ease secession demands by granting autonomy to minority groups on a territorial or non-territorial basis. Federalism, combined with asymmetrical arrangements, may provide a minority group sufficient comfort and justification to remain within an existing sovereign state rather than to demand secession. Ignoring well motivated requests for autonomy within existing state institutions and structures may cause pressure to build up and thereby hasten secessionist demands, regardless if it is a unitary or federal state.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>International law does not prohibit secession as a matter of principle, but it does recognize the right of sovereign states to protect and defend their territorial integrity. International law does not encourage secession but accepts that it may be an option of last resort if a minority group’s continued exclusion from society leaves little option but to create a new state – whether provided for by a country’s constitution or not. It would seem as if international law prefers a continuation of the status quo and national sovereignty, but once the facts in a particular situation justify secession (for example civil violence, acts of genocide), the new state will most likely be accepted and recognized in international law.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>International law and practice cannot be said to be absolutely clear and consistent about the application of the law regarding secession, protection of territorial integrity and self-determination. As is observed by Maalim, ‘there is no international treaty or clear rules of international customary law that regulate secession’(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0021909612439684">Maalim, 2008</xref>: 115). In the past two decades several new states have been born with the blessing of international law but the pathway towards a new sovereign state was often built on large-scale human rights violations. In some instances, for example South Sudan and East Timor, there was wide support for secession while in other instances, such as the declaration of independence by Kosovo, there was division within the international community. While it may be preferable for self-determination to be exercised within existing state boundaries so as to ‘put a lid on the secession kettle’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0021909612439684">Suksi, 2005</xref>: 223),<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-0021909612439684">15</xref></sup> there are examples where internal arrangements could not prevent a new state from being born.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>If secession is considered by a minority group or a region within a sovereign state, it is not a self-executing right over which the national government has no control and which can be demanded by a region without any consideration of the national interest or the interests of minorities residing in the region that seeks to achieve secession. International law has, however, not crystallized specific requirements to be met in order for a group to be successful in their attempts to secede. If recent successful secessions are considered, it would seem as if the international community is guided strongly by questions of fact in relation to each case. In East Timor and Kosovo the international community was initially reluctant to become involved but large scale atrocities triggered action; in Ethiopia and Canada provision is made for a process to be gone through to consider the public support for secession, the implications to all concerned, the arrangements to be entered into, the protection of minorities, the views of opposition parties, the size of the majority supporting secession and, if all details are agreed, the amendment of the national constitution; and in Tanzania the secessionist movement remains weak with little chance of internal agreement to allow a break-up and so far little, if any, support internationally for secession.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>There is no consistency between the case studies or in international law as to the way, if any, in which the population of part of the country that does not secede expresses their view about the secession. Secession is not merely a breaking away – it is often a divorce which affects the identity of the entire country. An argument can therefore be made that the view of the entire population should be tested about secession not merely the views of those residing in the region that wishes to secede.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Based on the experiences of the case studies considered in this assessment, the following requirements may have to be met for purposes of successful secession: the secession must occur in accordance with a legal framework on which there is domestic agreement (e.g. Canada and Ethiopia); or the secession must be an option of last resort after large-scale human rights infringements and atrocities with the national government being either the protagonist of the violence or unwilling/unable to intervene and protect its citizens (e.g. East Timor and Kosovo); and/or the international community must be supportive of secession – in particular major players such as the Unites States of America (USA), Russia, China, United Kingdom (UK), France and Germany.</p></list-item></list>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>The author acknowledges with great appreciation the grant made available by the Alexander von Humboldt Stiftung to facilitate the research on which this publication is based. The opinions expressed herein are entirely those of the author.</p></ack>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0021909612439684">
<label>1.</label>
<p>In this article ‘states’ refers to the second tier level of government in federations unless reference is made to a specific case study when the terminology used in that country will be employed, for example provinces in South Africa and Canada; laender in Germany; cantons in Switzerland; and states in the USA, Ethiopia and Nigeria.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0021909612439684">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Elazar ‘coined’ the concepts of ‘self-rule’ and ‘shared-rule’ to describe the essence of federalism as an expression of the philosophy underlying federal systems of working together in unity while also working separately as autonomous units.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0021909612439684">
<label>3.</label>
<p>Asymmetry means that certain sub-national jurisdictions are awarded a greater degree of flexibility than their counterparts in the range of matters over which it can make and implement decisions; greater freedom to design institutions that are applicable to the specific jurisdiction; special powers to a develop and utilize economic resources; or special representation within national power-sharing institutions.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0021909612439684">
<label>4.</label>
<p>The irony is that the opposite may be true in some instances where the refusal to decentralize or to federalize has fuelled separatism and secession. McGarry notes as follows: ‘While states are often reluctant to decentralize, for fear it will promote secession, there is evidence that timely and genuine decentralization achieves exactly the opposite effect … The long-time existence of the Canadian and Swiss federations also show that extensive decentralization is consistent with state unity’ (as quoted in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0021909612439684">Wellman, 2011</xref>: 33).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0021909612439684">
<label>5.</label>
<p>The constitution does not specify it; this refers to the total members of the assembly or two-thirds of those present when the vote is taken.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0021909612439684">
<label>6.</label>
<p>The position of those in favour of the secessionist clause was summarized as follows by Meles Zenawi, the current Prime Minister of Ethiopia: the nations, nationalities and peoples were sovereign; democracy allows people to decide what is advantageous to them and have the constitution reflect such a position; the recognition of secession was a key to ‘peace and stability’; the constitution had to recognize that the nations, peoples and nationalities had decided to form a ‘voluntary union’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0021909612439684">Zenawi, 1994</xref>: 5–6).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0021909612439684">
<label>7.</label>
<p>Habtu explains the background as follows: from 1974 to 1991 the military dictatorship imposed a unitary regime under Marxist-Leninist principles. Several of the resistance movements against the regime originated from a rural, ethnic basis into ethnic liberation movements. The ‘liberation fronts’ (such as the Tigray Peoples Liberation Front; the Oromo Liberation Front; the Western Somali Liberation front and the Afar Liberation Front) where therefore primarily ethnic based and the federal constitutional arrangements ‘simply gave recognition to this established fact of territoriality and identity’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0021909612439684">Habtu, 2010</xref>: 147).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0021909612439684">
<label>8.</label>
<p>The secession of Eritrea was however not pursuant of a39 of the constitution of Ethiopia, but resulted from the transitional process from military regime to democracy.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0021909612439684">
<label>9.</label>
<p>Refer for example to the a72 of the 1977 constitution of the Soviet Union which provided that ‘the right to free secession from the USSR shall be preserved for each republic’.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-0021909612439684">
<label>10.</label>
<p>Attorney General of Canada, Reference re Secession of Quebec [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021909612439684">1998</xref>] 2 S.C.R. 217 par 111.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-0021909612439684">
<label>11.</label>
<p>According to Sterio it is essential for the ‘Great Powers’ – being the USA, Russia, France, UK, China, Germany, Italy and Japan – to be supportive of secession before it has any chance of success. The reason is that these countries have ‘enhanced decision-making authority in the institutional context, as well as in the economic realm’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0021909612439684">Sterio, 2010</xref>: 154).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-0021909612439684">
<label>12.</label>
<p>Maalim describes the secrecy that characterized the forming of a union as follows: ‘Not only did the Revolutionary government, without the consent and approval of the Zanzibaris, enter into the Union but also the decision was so confidential that even the Zanzibar Government Chief Legal Adviser was not involved or even made aware of the negotiation to form a Union. Also there is no evidence that Zanzibar ratified the treaty of union as required by the treaty itself and her laws’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0021909612439684">Maalim, 2008</xref>: 133).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-0021909612439684">
<label>13.</label>
<p>Before the break-up of Yugoslavia, Kosovo was one of the six ‘republics’ that made up the federation.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-0021909612439684">
<label>14.</label>
<p>The question which was referred by the General Assembly of the United Nations was: ‘Is the unilateral declaration of independence by the Provisional Institutions of Self-Government of Kosovo in accordance with international law?’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0021909612439684">International Court of Justice, 2010</xref>: par 49).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-0021909612439684">
<label>15.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0021909612439684">Suksi (2005</xref>: 225) goes on to point out that, although international law accepts voluntary secession, unilateral secession is not accepted except in ‘very special circumstances’, for example that of Kosovo.</p></fn>
</fn-group></notes>
<bio>
<p>Bertus de Villiers (BA Law, LL.B, LL.D) is a Member of the State Administrative Tribunal of Western Australia. He is a Visiting Fellow of the Law Faculty of the University of Western Australia. He is an inaugural Fellow of the Western Australian Institute of Dispute Management under the auspices of Murdoch University. He is admitted as a legal practitioner in Australia and South Africa. He was closely involved during the constitutional negotiations in South Africa from 1990–6. Dr de Villiers has travelled widely and has undertaken research on constitutional and political developments in various countries. He has published extensively on a wide range of constitutional issues, in particular topics dealing with federalism, protection of human rights, land reform and cultural diversity. He recently acted as the foreign expert in the Forum of Federation’s leadership training project in Ethiopia on federalism and intergovernmental relations.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Attorney General of Canada</collab> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Reference re Secession of Quebec [1998] 2 S.C.R. 217</source>. <day>30</day> <month>September</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fedyemen.com/en-page/">http://fedyemen.com/en-page/</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 3 March 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Castellino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Order and justice: National minorities and the right to secession</article-title>. <source>International Journal on Minority and Group Rights</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Charney</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Self-determination: Chechnya, Kosovo and East Timor</article-title>. <source>Vanderbilt Journal of Transnational Law</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Constitution of the Federal Republic of Ethiopia</collab> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Ethiopia: Constitution Proclamaition no 1/1995</source>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.africanlegislaturesproject.org/sites/africanlegislaturesproject.org/files/Constitution%20Ethiopia.pdf">http://www.africanlegislaturesproject.org/sites/africanlegislaturesproject.org/files/Constitution%20Ethiopia.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elazar</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <source>Exploring Federalism</source>. <publisher-loc>Tuscaloosa, AL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Alabama Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fiseha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Habib</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Ethiopia</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Diversity and Unity in Federal Countries</source>. <publisher-loc>Montreal</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGill-Queen’s University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Habtu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Multiethnic federalism in Ethiopia: A study of the secession clause in the Constitution</article-title>. <source>Publius: The Journal of Federalism Spring</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Habtu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Ethiopian federalism: Origins, rationale, achievements and challenges</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Habtu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed) <source>Ethiopian Federalism: Principle, Process and Practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Addis Ababa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Forum of Federations</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1971</year>) <source>Political Roles in a New State: Tanzania’s First Decade</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>International Court of Justice</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Accordance with International Law of the Unilateral Declaration of Independence in Respect of Kosovo</source>. <day>22</day> <month>July</month>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icj-cij.org/docket/files/141/15987.pdf">http://www.icj-cij.org/docket/files/141/15987.pdf</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 22 August 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jumbe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>The Partnership: The Union of Tanganyika and Zanzibar – 30 Turbulent Years</source> <publisher-loc>Dar es Salaam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Amana Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kabudi</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The United Republic of Tanzania after a quarter of a century: A legal appraisal of the state of the Union of Tanganyika and Zanzibar</article-title>. <source>African Journal of International and Comparative Law</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>308</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Kosovo Advisory Opinion</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Accordance With International Law of the Unilateral Declaration of Independence in Respect of Kosovo (Request for Advisory Opinion)</source>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icj-cij.org/docket/files/141/15987.pdf">http://www.icj-cij.org/docket/files/141/15987.pdf</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 4 March 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Canada: The supreme court sets rules for the secession of Quebec</article-title>. <source>Publius: The Journal of Federalism</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maalim</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The right of secession under international law and national laws: A case study of Zanzibar in the United Republic of Tanzania</article-title>. <source>Journal of African and International Law</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>The Ethics of Nationalism</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="thesis">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mtengwa</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Constitutional Problems of Unbalanced Federal Systems: An Insight of Union Problems of the United Republic of Tanzania and their Implications to Democracy and the Future of the Union</source>. DPhil Thesis, <publisher-name>Department of Public Administration</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>University of Bergen</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Canada’s two solitudes: Constitutional and international law in reference re secession of Quebec</article-title>. <source>International Journal on Minority and Group Rights</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Parliament of Canada</collab> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Clarity Act: An Act to Give Effect to the Requirement for Clarity as Set Out in the Opinion of the Supreme Court of Canada in the Quebec Secession. Reference S.C. 2000, c.26 assented 29-06-2000</source>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.canadianlawsite.ca/clarity-act.htm">http://www.canadianlawsite.ca/clarity-act.htm</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 4 March 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Purnawanty</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Various perspectives in understanding the East Timor crisis</article-title>. <source>Temple International and Comparative Law Journal</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The diminishing autonomy of sub-national entities in federal countries</article-title>. <source>New Trends in Federalism Working Paper</source> <volume>1</volume>. <publisher-loc>Fribourg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Institute of Federalism</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Ethiopia and the right to secession in international and comparative law</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Brems</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Der Beken</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Federalism and the Protection of Human Rights in Ethiopia</source>. <publisher-loc>Zurich</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lit Verlag</publisher-name>, <fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sterio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>On the right to external self-determination: ‘Selfistands’, secession and the great powers’ rule</article-title>. <source>Minnesota Journal of International Law</source> <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Suksi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Keeping the lid on the secession kettle – a review of legal interpretations concerning self-determination by minority populations</article-title>. <source>International Journal on Minority and Group Rights</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>218</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Szasz</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The irresistible force of self-determination meets the impregnable fortress of territorial integrity: A cautionary fairy tale about clashes in Kosovo and elsewhere</article-title>. <source>Georgia Journal of International and Comparative Law</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tronvoll</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Bridging divided identities – or an agency of political domination? Reassessing the future of the Tanzanian Union</article-title>. <source>International Journal on Minority and Group Rights</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Comparative perspectives on asymmetry in federations</article-title>. <source>Asymmetry Series Queen’s University</source>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.queensu.ca/iigr/working/asymmetricfederalism/Watts2005.pdf">http://www.queensu.ca/iigr/working/asymmetricfederalism/Watts2005.pdf</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 22 November 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wellman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The morality of secession</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed) <source>Secession as an International Phenomenon</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Georgia Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0021909612439684">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zenawi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Ethiopia: Constitutional Commission of the Transitional Government: Debate on the Draft Constitution</source>. <publisher-loc>Addis Ababa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Government Printer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>