<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SOC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsoc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Sociology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0038-0385</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1469-8684</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0038038513475734</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0038038513475734</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Review Symposium</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review Symposium: John Scott <italic>Conceptualising the Social World: Principles of Sociological Analysis</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Gane</surname><given-names>Nicholas</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0038038513475734">University of York, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>191</fpage>
<lpage>193</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">BSA Publications Ltd.</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The position from which this book starts is that social theory is at its most effective when it proceeds through intellectual cooperation and the pursuit of complementary frameworks rather than rival approaches. Against the tendency for sociologists to pursue ‘particular conceptual schemes’ and ‘one-sided intellectual commitments’, Scott proposes that a ‘dynamic synthesis of theories rooted in diverse conceptual perspectives is the means through which a transcendence of partial theorisations and partisan commitments can be achieved’ (p. 3). But what does this mean in practice? Scott advises: we must ‘articulate a common set of <italic>principles</italic> of sociological analysis that can be used in the construction of specific theories’ (p. 4). These ‘principles’ are said to be culture, nature, system, space-time, structure, action, mind and development, and are addressed chapter-by-chapter through the course of the book. A detailed engagement with the arguments of each of these chapters lies beyond the boundaries of a short review. Instead, I will make three points (intended in the spirit of cooperation) in response to the main arguments advanced by Scott.</p>
<p>First, this book attempts to show the compatibility of different theoretical positions by pursuing a strategy of ‘dynamic synthesis’, but Scott says little about the method of such synthesis or the ground upon which it might proceed. There are complex arguments that do not appear in this book about the compatibility of different types of sociological work that are produced out of very different epistemological and political frames, and, more philosophically, about the capacity for knowledge to be born not just out of synthesis but also dissensus. Scott also says little about the choice of theoretical positions that are chosen to be synthesised. Chapter 2 centres on the ‘principle’ of culture, and runs through the work of Durkheim, Halbwachs, Tarde, Saussure, Lévi-Strauss and Lukács, among many others. But there is no Weber, no Simmel, no cultural studies, no postmodernism or post-structuralism, no Bourdieu let alone more daring figures such as Baudrillard or Žižek. At the end of this chapter, Scott declares, confidently, that ‘I have set out the concept of culture that developed in sociology and related disciplines and that came to form a key principle in the construction of the leading conceptual frameworks of the social sciences’ (p. 38). It would be more accurate to say that this book identifies <italic>some</italic> concepts of culture that have been important in the development of <italic>some</italic> conceptual frameworks of the social sciences. Even then it is not altogether clear how Scott synthesises these frameworks to work together, and, perhaps more importantly, to what discernable end.</p>
<p>Second, this book is limited not just in terms of the range of theoretical concepts and positions it deals with but also in its historical scope. Scott focuses mainly on sociological work from the late 19th century through to the 1960s. Contemporary social theory barely features at all. Scott’s view is that there are ‘some fundamental features of social life that are true universals and that theoretical ideas to explain these will have an enduring relevance’ (p. 7). One might ask here of the relation between this book and the world outside of it. Has the world not changed over the past 50 years? Can we be confident that the ‘true universals’ articulated by classical theory still hold true today, or do we need new ways of thinking that place the historicity of these ‘universals’ into question? Scott’s answer is that ‘Reinventing the wheel is far less productive than retaining and improving on inefficient wheels’ (p. 5). To some extent, Scott is right: there are many exciting and productive ways of thinking about the present by re-working concepts and ideas that emerged from the late19th century through to the mid-20th century. But is this all sociology needs? I would argue not. A different way of working (advocated by thinkers such as C. Wright Mills) would be to start from the empirical challenges and problems of the present and to think about the theoretical (and methodological) devices that can be developed in order to address these. One such challenge is how to conceive of sociality and culture in an age of advanced electronic communication. Scott touches on such developments in an isolated paragraph in a chapter on space-time (Chapter 5) before turning back to consider early attempts to think about class differentiation in urban space (p. 126). This leaves one wondering about the historical limits of many of the theoretical frameworks and ideas that Scott seeks to synthesise, and about the degree to which they to have ‘enduring relevance’ today.</p>
<p>Finally, this book is about ‘principles’, or more precisely ‘the broad principles of sociological analysis’ that are ‘able to sustain a cohesive disciplinary conspectus and foundation for social science’ (p. 268). It is not exactly clear, however, what Scott means by a ‘principle’. He says that culture, nature, system, space-time, structure, action, mind and development are principles. But are these principles or rather concepts or possible fields or focal points for analysis? One might also ask why Scott prioritises these ‘principles’ in particular, and in so doing relegates more traditional sociological concepts of class, gender or power to second-order concerns. What becomes clear through the course of this book is that the practice of theoretical synthesis is never neutral: it depends on an initial selection of values or positions (to the exclusion of others), elements of which are then elevated or downplayed according to the theoretical framework one is looking to create. Surprisingly, Scott bypasses reflection on such questions and moves in conclusion to appeal for intellectual cooperation. He states:
<disp-quote>
<p>If sociology is to develop – as I believe it should – as a coordinated and cooperative intellectual venture, then those who see themselves as adherents of one perspective must recognise and respect the work of those who ally themselves with other theoretical perspectives. (p. 272)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The problem with this statement, however, is twofold. First, in order to ‘recognise and respect’ the work of others in this way, surely it is necessary to address the political, cultural or even institutional contexts for the emergence of different (in Scott’s terms ‘rival’) theoretical frameworks. But instead of looking at the reasons for the emergence of different theoretical frameworks and perspectives, Scott pursues a practice of theoretical synthesis by articulating eight principles that are treated as being of universal and therefore global and ahistorical significance. Second, while Scott concludes by making an argument for the recognition and respect of alternative theoretical positions, very few ‘other’ perspectives from within sociology and related disciplines from the past 50 years appear within this book. This leaves the reader with the following impression: this book is a defence of certain principles and ideas from classical and early to mid-20th century social theory rather than a genuine attempt to provide a new cooperative framework for theoretical sociology today.</p>
</body>
</article>