<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PAA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppaa</journal-id>
<journal-title>Pacifica</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1030-570X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1839-2598</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1030570X1202500106</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1030570X1202500106</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>On the Implications of the Idea of Infinity for Postmodern Fundamental Theology</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>Daniel A.</given-names></name></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>2</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>25</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>67</fpage>
<lpage>81</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 Pacifica Theological Studies Association</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Pacifica Theological Studies Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This essay provides a dimensional analysis of the various manners in which mathematics, phenomenology, and theology claim to make present or mediate infinity. Edmund Husserl's 1935 lecture, <italic>Philosophy and the Crisis of European Humanity</italic>, because engaged with each discipline to various degrees, will function as our primary, preparatory text. Husserl's discussion of the ideal objects of mathematics and the Greek attitude will call for further analysis of the relation between mathematics and infinity. Similarly, intentional infinities, insofar as related to transcendental phenomenology, will be compared to Jean-Luc Marion's distinct phenomenology of the icon. Next, the ways in which the infinite God is conceptualised by Husserl and Marion will be juxtaposed in order to demonstrate their disparate, theological thinking. Finally, the notion of multiple infinities will be analogically extended from set theory to the discursive wholes of mathematics, phenomenology, and theology in order to suggest a novel understanding of the role of the infinite within postmodern fundamental theology.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>