<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CPJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcpj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Pediatr (Phila)</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical Pediatrics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0009-9228</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-2707</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0009922811422434</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0009922811422434</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Do Youth Hockey Coaches Allow Players With a Known Concussion to Participate in a Game?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Bramley</surname><given-names>Harry</given-names></name>
<degrees>DO</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922811422434">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kroft</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name>
<degrees>MLA</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0009922811422434">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0009922811422434">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Newberry</surname><given-names>Ty</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0009922811422434">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Silvis</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922811422434">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0009922811422434"><label>1</label>Penn State Milton S. Hershey Medical Center, Hershey, PA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0009922811422434"><label>2</label>York College of Pennsylvania, York, PA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0009922811422434"><label>3</label>USA Hockey, Southeastern District, Washington, DC, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0009922811422434">Harry Bramley, Department of Pediatrics, Penn State Milton S. Hershey Medical Center, Mail Code H085, 500 University Drive, Hershey, PA 17033, USA Email: <email>hbramley@hmc.psu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>51</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>283</fpage>
<lpage>287</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Ice hockey is a high-risk sport for concussion. It is important that coaches have an understanding of concussion, although previous studies have demonstrated poor knowledge of concussion recognition and management by youth coaches. A cross-sectional survey with 7 case scenarios was completed by 314 youth hockey coaches. Each case scenario described a player with a concussion during a game, and scores reflected how the coach would respond to each scenario. Although most coaches would not allow a player to continue participating in a game after suffering a concussion, there was a small percentage that would. Statistical analysis found an inverse relationship between the coaches’ age and consideration of continued participation. This places athletes at significant risk for further injury and is not consistent with current concussion guidelines. USA Hockey should provide additional concussion training for their coaches as well as mandatory health care clearance following a concussion.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>concussion</kwd>
<kwd>traumatic brain injury</kwd>
<kwd>head injuries</kwd>
<kwd>pediatrics</kwd>
<kwd>hockey</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0009922811422434" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>It is estimated that 300 000 sport-related concussions occur each year, and concussions represent approximately 8.9% of all high school athletic injuries.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922811422434">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0009922811422434">3</xref></sup> In addition, 3.8 million recreational and sport-related concussions were estimated to occur annually in the United States.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0009922811422434">4</xref></sup> Over the past decade, an extensive amount of research, literature, and media coverage has been dedicated to sport-related concussion, enhancing our knowledge base and guiding management.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0009922811422434">5</xref></sup> Complications from sport-related concussion, such as chronic traumatic encephalopathy, second-impact syndrome, and postconcussion syndrome are all causes for concern.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0009922811422434">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0009922811422434">10</xref></sup></p>
<p>In both Canada and the United States, ice hockey is a popular sport, with 550 000 and 345 000 registered youth hockey players respectively (HockeyCanada, USAHockey).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0009922811422434">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0009922811422434">12</xref></sup> Sports-related concussions are being reported with increased frequency among children and adolescents. This problem exists for all contact sports but is especially prevalent in ice hockey where concussions account for approximately 15% of all injuries in 9- to 16-year-old players.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0009922811422434">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0009922811422434">14</xref></sup> Hockey is a high-risk sport for concussion given the speed and physicality of play. Compounding the increased frequency of concussions are difficulties in concussion diagnosis and management in youth sports. A study reported that youth coaches frequently failed to recognize a concussive injury, and as a result of unrecognized concussions, many coaches allowed athletes to return to play prematurely.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0009922811422434">15</xref></sup></p>
<p>The consensus statement from the Third International Conference on Concussion in Sport recommends that athletes who have suffered a concussion be removed from the contest and be evaluated by a physician.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0009922811422434">16</xref></sup> With high school sponsored sports, medical clearance is required prior to an athlete returning to play following a concussion. However, in the majority of registered USA Hockey leagues and organizations, there is no mandate for health care clearance prior to returning to play following a concussion. These children return to play solely at the discretion of their parents, coaches, and hockey organizations, who, in the majority of cases, are not health care professionals trained in the proper management of sport-related concussion. Inappropriate management of an athlete with a concussion may increase the risk for further brain injury or, rarely, death caused by second impact syndrome.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0009922811422434">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0009922811422434">9</xref></sup> The objective of this study was to determine the likelihood that youth hockey coaches would allow continued play of a hockey player with a known concussion.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0009922811422434" sec-type="methods">
<title>Participants and Methods</title>
<p>A total of 314 youth ice hockey coaches participating in USA Hockey coaching certification clinics during the fall of 2008 in Maryland, Virginia and Washington, DC, were recruited for participation in the study. Participants were handed the survey by one of the authors during the clinic’s registration, and questions about the study were addressed. Participants were informed that the completion of the survey was voluntary, and completion of the survey indicated acknowledgment of consent. Time to complete the survey was provided prior to the start of the clinic. All coaches (100%) who were recruited completed the survey.</p>
<p>The initial section of the survey obtained basic background data, including the age of the coach, USA Hockey coaching level of certification, playing experience, and whether they had received any formal training in concussion management (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0009922811422434">Table 1</xref>). In addition, the coaches responded to 7 case scenarios in which one of their players suffered a concussion during a game. Using a rating scale ranging from 1 (<italic>never</italic>) to 5 (<italic>always</italic>), they were asked how often they would allow continued participation in a game after a player sustained a concussion. The scenarios varied in the severity of the concussion and the importance of the game. These 7 rating questions were the dependent variables for the study.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0009922811422434" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Participants’ Characteristics</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0009922811422434" xlink:href="10.1177_0009922811422434-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age (n = 308), years</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 20-30</td>
<td>21.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 31-40</td>
<td>28.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 41-50</td>
<td>42.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Older than 50</td>
<td>6.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Years coaching (n = 312)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Less than 5</td>
<td>81.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 5-10</td>
<td>11.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Over 10</td>
<td>6.7%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>USA coaching level (n = 309)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> None</td>
<td>53.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> I</td>
<td>13.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> II</td>
<td>18.1%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> III</td>
<td>11%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> IV</td>
<td>3.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Years played hockey (n = 312)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> None</td>
<td>6.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Less than 5</td>
<td>15.7%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 5-10</td>
<td>16.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> More than 10</td>
<td>61.5%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Internal validation of the questionnaire was conducted using 3 physicians knowledgeable and experienced on current concussion guidelines and management, and it yielded a κ score of 1.</p>
<p>The background characteristics were age, level of USA Hockey certification, coaching experience, and playing experience. The question on USA Hockey coaching level was recorded into 2 answers of <italic>none</italic> versus <italic>any level</italic>. The dependent variables—ratings of continued participation—were treated as interval-level data. Hence the analyses used to investigate differences related to the coaches’ characteristics were either <italic>t</italic> tests or 1-way analysis of variance depending on the number of values in the independent variable. All statistics were calculated using SPSS (SPSS Inc, Chicago, IL).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0009922811422434" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>For any of the 7 rated scenarios, 80% or more of the coaches would never allow a player back into a game after suffering a concussion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0009922811422434">Table 2</xref>). However, variations were found depending on the circumstances.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0009922811422434" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Frequency of Playing With Concussion</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0009922811422434" xlink:href="10.1177_0009922811422434-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">1 Never</th>
<th align="center">2</th>
<th align="center">3</th>
<th align="center">4</th>
<th align="center">5 Always</th>
<th align="center">n</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Is it okay for an athlete to continue playing in a game in which they have suffered a severe concussion?</td>
<td>99.0% (306)</td>
<td>0.6% (2)</td>
<td>0.0% (0)</td>
<td>0.0% (0)</td>
<td>0.3% (1)</td>
<td>309</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Is it okay for an athlete to continue playing in a game in which they have suffered a minor concussion?</td>
<td>83.8% (258)</td>
<td>13.0% (40)</td>
<td>2.6% (8)</td>
<td>0.3% (1)</td>
<td>0.3% (1)</td>
<td>308</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>If a youth hockey player unmistakably appears to have suffered a concussion but clearly insists that they are feeling fine, should they continue playing in that game?</td>
<td>91.5% (281)</td>
<td>6.8% (21)</td>
<td>1.0% (3)</td>
<td>0.0% (0)</td>
<td>0.7% (2)</td>
<td>307</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>If one of your elite players sustained a concussion during the early part of a championship game with many college scouts attending that does not significantly hinder his/her ability to play, would you allow the player to continue to play?</td>
<td>80.8% (248)</td>
<td>14.3% (44)</td>
<td>3.9% (12)</td>
<td>0.3% (1)</td>
<td>0.7% (2)</td>
<td>307</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>If one of your elite seniors sustained a concussion during the early part of his/her final high school game that did not significantly hinder his/her ability to participate, would you allow the player to continue to play?</td>
<td>82.1% (252)</td>
<td>13.0% (40)</td>
<td>3.6% (11)</td>
<td>0.7% (2)</td>
<td>0.7% (2)</td>
<td>307</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>If one of your lesser, lower-caliber players sustained a concussion during the early part of a championship game with many college scouts attending that does not significantly hinder his/her ability to play, would you allow the player to continue to play?</td>
<td>82.8% (255)</td>
<td>13.3% (41)</td>
<td>3.6% (11)</td>
<td>0.0% (0)</td>
<td>0.3% (1)</td>
<td>308</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>If one of your lesser, lower-caliber seniors sustained a concussion during the early part of his/her final high school game that did not significantly hinder his/her ability to participate, would you allow the player to continue to play?</td>
<td>83.0% (254)</td>
<td>13.1% (40)</td>
<td>3.6% (11)</td>
<td>0.0% (0)</td>
<td>0.3% (1)</td>
<td>306</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Some coaches made a distinction between concussions described as minor and severe. With a severe concussion, nearly all the coaches (99.0%) would never allow the player to return to the game. However, with a minor concussion, the percentage of coaches that would never allow the player’s return decreased to 83.8%.</p>
<p>Coaches were more likely to allow participation during the scenarios that were noted to involve an important game, such as a championship game or final high school game. For example, 91.5% would never allow a player to reenter a game that was not defined. However, the percentages ranged from 80.8% to 83.0% when the scenario defined the game as a championship game or final high school game. The coaches did not make a distinction between an elite player and lower caliber player.</p>
<p>Looking at the characteristics of coaches, the variable that was most strongly related to whether or not the player could return to the game was the coach’s age. Whereas coaches of all ages were most likely to never permit the player’s return, there was an inverse relationship between the age of the coach and considering allowing the player back into the game for all but 2 of the scenarios. The younger the coach, the more likely they were to consider allowing the player to continue playing. The 2 exceptions were when the athlete had suffered a severe concussion and when the athlete had suffered a concussion but insisted that he or she was feeling fine.</p>
<p>The scenarios in which age was related to the coach’s ratings as determined by 1-way ANOVA were as follows:</p>
<list id="list1-0009922811422434" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Is it ok for an athlete to continue playing in a game in which they have suffered a minor concussion?—<italic>F</italic>(3, 299) = 4.185, <italic>P</italic> = .006.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>If one of your elite players sustained a concussion during the early part of a championship game with many college scouts attending that does not significantly hinder his/her ability to play, would you allow the player to continue to play?—<italic>F</italic>(3, 298) = 6.675, <italic>P</italic> = .000.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>If one of your elite seniors sustained a concussion during the early part of his/her final high school game that did not significantly hinder his/her ability to participate, would you allow the player to continue to play?—<italic>F</italic>(3, 298) = 6.982, <italic>P</italic> = .000.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>If one of your lesser, lower-caliber players sustained a concussion during the early part of a championship game with many college scouts attending that does not significantly hinder his/her ability to play, would you allow the player to continue to play?—<italic>F</italic>(3, 299) = 6.730, <italic>P</italic> = .000.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>If one of your lesser, lower-caliber seniors sustained a concussion during the early part of a his/her final high school game that does not significantly hinder his/her ability to play, would you allow the player to continue to play?—<italic>F</italic>(3, 297) = 7.672, <italic>P</italic> = .000.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The only other relationship with statistically significant difference was whether or not the coach had a USA Hockey coaching level. Using a <italic>t</italic> test, it was found that if a coach had any USA Hockey coaching level (I-IV), he or she was less likely to allow a player with a minor concussion to return to a game—<italic>t</italic>(268.383) = 2.097, <italic>P</italic> = .037—and also a player who had suffered a concussion but insisted that he or she was fine and wanted to continue to play to return to the game—<italic>t</italic>(238.213) = 1.980, <italic>P</italic> = .049).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0009922811422434" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>We found that the percentage of coaches who considered allowing continued game participation of a concussed player, as indicated by ratings of 3 or higher, ranged from 0.3% when a severe concussion was described to 5.0% with an elite player in a final high school game. McLeod et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0009922811422434">15</xref></sup> found that 26% of youth coaches allowed concussed athletes to return to play. This practice of allowing a concussed athlete to participate in a game places the athlete at risk for significant injury and is counter to current guidelines set forth by the most recent consensus statement on concussion in sport.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0009922811422434">16</xref></sup></p>
<p>Hockey is particularly problematic because concussion is a common injury affecting upward of 15% of injuries in 9- to 16-year-old players.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0009922811422434">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0009922811422434">14</xref></sup> Body checking was demonstrated to increase the risk of all game-related concussion by 3-fold among 11- to 12-year-old players.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0009922811422434">13</xref></sup> In the United States, body checking had been introduced at the Pee Wee age group (ages 11-12 years); however, USA Hockey recently approved some changes in an attempt to reduce the risk of injury, which includes raising the age of legal body checking to the Bantam level (ages 13-14 years).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0009922811422434">17</xref></sup></p>
<p>Rule changes are an important part of risk reduction; however, it is important that all youth hockey coaches are aware that a concussed athlete should be safely removed from the contest and evaluated by a health care professional trained in the proper management of sport-related concussion. In addition, coaches should be aware that the athlete should not be allowed to return to their respective sport until the concussion has completely resolved. USA Hockey has a 5-level coaching tier in place, which provides clinics for coaches to improve coaching skills. Our study found only 2 statistically significant differences out of a possible 7 between the level of coaching and allowing participation, suggesting that these clinics provide minimal education regarding proper concussion management.</p>
<p>The results of this study confirmed that additional education regarding concussion management for youth hockey coaches may be needed. The National Federation of State High School Association mandates concussion training for coaches.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0009922811422434">18</xref></sup> Such training could readily be accomplished during mandatory USA Hockey coaching clinics. Coaches should also be made aware of educational resources such as Heads Up: Concussion in High School Sports (Centers for Disease Control and Prevention), which provides educational materials to athletes, parents, coaches, and health care professionals.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0009922811422434">19</xref></sup></p>
<p>High school football games have a trainer, a team physician, and emergency medical technicians at games, relieving the pressure of decision making regarding return to play for coaches. The Pittsburgh Amateur Hockey League requires that all league games have a certified athletic trainer, emergency medical technician, paramedic, and medical or osteopathic physician to be in attendance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0009922811422434">20</xref></sup> Other youth hockey leagues should consider similar requirements. Having a dedicated licensed health care professional knowledgeable in concussion management present at games may reduce the risk of an athlete with concussion returning to play.</p>
<p>There has been recent legislation passed or being considered in many states regarding concussion management in young athletes. The state of Washington was the first to pass legislation that requires that an athlete be removed from any game if suspected of having a concussion and may not return until evaluated and given clearance to return to play from a licensed health care professional.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0009922811422434">21</xref></sup> USA Hockey should enact similar rules.</p>
<p>It was unclear why younger coaches were statistically more likely to allow return to play of a concussed athlete in many of the scenarios. This may have been related to lack of experience. The majority of the coaches (81.4%) surveyed had less than 5 years of coaching experience.</p>
<p>Our study included a relatively small sample size of only youth hockey coaches. Obviously, a larger sample size would be desirable. Our results therefore are limited to only this population and cannot be extrapolated to other sports.</p>
<p>Our study had a 100% participation rate. An author provided a survey to each participant during the clinic’s registration, questions about the study were addressed, and time was allotted for completion of the survey. We suspect this method was the reason for the high participation rate.</p>
<p>Each scenario described an athlete with a concussion but did not define a concussion for the participant. Additionally, although concussions should not be staged or categorized, the survey distinguished between a mild and severe concussion, which may have been somewhat leading but commonly used terms by coaches. One might think that with all the attention given to concussion in the media, any coach would know that once a concussion has been indentified, the athlete should be removed from play. Were some coaches unaware of the current practice guidelines or associated risks, regardless of the circumstance or whether the concussion was described as mild or severe, or were some just willing to take a risk by allowing a concussed athlete back into play?</p>
<p>This study used clinical vignettes to assess youth hockey coaches’ adherence to concussion guidelines. Although the format of the survey may have overestimated the percentages of coaches adhering to these guidelines, vignettes can be a valid tool for measuring the quality of clinical practice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0009922811422434">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0009922811422434">23</xref></sup></p>
<p>Additional studies should address the effectiveness of education, legislation, media, and presence of health care professionals at games as they relate to return-to-play guidelines and concussion.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0009922811422434">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sosin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sniezek</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thurman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Incidence of mild and moderate brain injury in the United States, 1991</article-title>. <source>Brain Inj</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0009922811422434">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)</collab>. <article-title>Sports-related recurrent brain injuries-United States</article-title>. <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>224</fpage>-<lpage>227</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0009922811422434">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gessel</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dick</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Comstock</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Concussions among United States high school and collegiate athletes</article-title>. <source>J Athl Train</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>495</fpage>-<lpage>503</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0009922811422434">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Langlois</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rutland-Brown</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wald</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The epidemiology and impact of traumatic brain injury: a brief overview</article-title>. <source>J Head Trauma Rehabil</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>375</fpage>-<lpage>378</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0009922811422434">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>
</person-group>; <collab>The Council on Sports Medicine and Fitness</collab>. <article-title>Sport-related concussion in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>597</fpage>-<lpage>615</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0009922811422434">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cantu</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nowinski</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Chronic traumatic encephalopathy in athletes: progressive tauopathy after repetitive head injury</article-title>. <source>J Neuropathol Exp Neurol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>709</fpage>-<lpage>735</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0009922811422434">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Boston University, Center for the Study of Traumatic Encephalopathy. Case studies</collab>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bu.edu/cste/case-studies">www.bu.edu/cste/case-studies</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed May 17, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0009922811422434">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cantu</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Voy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Second impact syndrome: a risk in any contact sport</article-title>. <source>Phys Sportsmed</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0009922811422434">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCrory</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Does second impact syndrome exist?</article-title> <source>Clin J Sport Med</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>-<lpage>149</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0009922811422434">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jotwani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Postconcussion syndrome in athletes</article-title>. <source>Curr Sports Med Rep</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0009922811422434">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>HockeyCanada</collab>. <article-title>Hockey Canada annual report</article-title> <year>2008</year>. <month>July</month> <day>28</day>th. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hockeycanada.ca/index.php/ci_id/55192/la_id/1.htm">http://www.hockeycanada.ca/index.php/ci_id/55192/la_id/1.htm</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed May 17, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0009922811422434">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>USAHockey</collab>. <article-title>USA hockey annual congress: registration report</article-title>. <year>2009</year>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.usahockey.com/uploadedFiles/USAHockey/Menu_Membership/Menu_Membership_Statistics/0809FinalReports.pdf">http://www.usahockey.com/uploadedFiles/USAHockey/Menu_Membership/Menu_Membership_Statistics/0809FinalReports.pdf</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed May 17, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0009922811422434">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shrier</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Risk of injury associated with body checking among youth ice hockey players</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>303</volume>:<fpage>2265</fpage>-<lpage>2272</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0009922811422434">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brust</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Youth ice hockey tournament injuries: rates and patterns compared to season play</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0009922811422434">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bay</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Sport-related concussion misunderstandings among youth coaches</article-title>. <source>Clin J Sport Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>140</fpage>-<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0009922811422434">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCrory</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meeuwisse</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Consensus statement on concussion in sport 3rd international conference on concussion in sport held in Zurich, November 2008</article-title>. <conf-name>Clin J Sport Med</conf-name>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>185</fpage>-<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0009922811422434">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>USA Hockey</collab>. <article-title>USA Hockey board of directors approves all points of progressive checking skill development program</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.usahockey.com/Template_Usahockey.aspx?NAV=AU_02_03&amp;id=305004">www.usahockey.com/Template_Usahockey.aspx?NAV=AU_02_03&amp;id=305004</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed July 11, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0009922811422434">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>National Federation of State High School Association</collab>. <article-title>Concussion in sport: what you need to know</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nfhslearn.com/electiveDetail.aspx?courseID=15000">www.nfhslearn.com/electiveDetail.aspx?courseID=15000</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed May 17, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0009922811422434">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>US Department of Health and Human Services, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. <source>Heads Up Toolkits</source>. <publisher-loc>Atlanta, GA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>. <comment>Documents 99-8262, 99-7423, and 99-8853</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0009922811422434">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Pittsburgh Amateur Hockey League</collab>. <article-title>Rules and regulations 2010-2011 season</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pahockey.com/Documents/PAHL%20RULES%2010-11%20(3).pdf">www.pahockey.com/Documents/PAHL%20RULES%2010-11%20(3).pdf</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed May 17, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0009922811422434">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>Washington State Department of Health</collab>. <article-title>Concussion management for school sports</article-title>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.doh.wa.gov/ehp/ts/School/concussion.htm">www.doh.wa.gov/ehp/ts/School/concussion.htm</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed May 17, 2011</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0009922811422434">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mariette</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liote</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Durieux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ravaud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of response for clinical vignettes on reporting quality of physician practice</article-title>. <source>BMC Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>128</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0009922811422434">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peabody</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glassman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Measuring the quality of physician practice by using clinical vignettes: a prospective validation study</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>141</volume>: <fpage>771</fpage>-<lpage>780</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>