<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IMR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spimr</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of International Medical Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0300-0605</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1473-2300</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0300060513488499</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0300060513488499</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Clinical Notes</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Faecal calprotectin concentrations in gastrointestinal diseases</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Shaodong</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0300060513488499"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Zhenkai</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Heng</surname><given-names>Lu</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Juan</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Boshi</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Xiaochen</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Fangyu</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0300060513488499">Department of Gastroenterology, Jingling Hospital, Nanjing, China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0300060513488499">Dr Shaodong Wang, Department of Gastroenterology, Jingling Hospital, 305 Zhongshan Donglu Road, Nanjing 210005, China. Email: <email>zhxqsd2002@yahoo.com.cn</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>1357</fpage>
<lpage>1361</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec10-0300060513488499"><title>Objective</title>
<p>To quantify faecal calprotectin concentrations in a variety of gastrointestinal disorders in order to determine its diagnostic value.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0300060513488499"><title>Methods</title>
<p>Patients with gastrointestinal symptoms undergoing upper or lower endoscopy and healthy control subjects provided stool samples. Calprotectin was quantified by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0300060513488499"><title>Results</title>
<p>The study recruited 210 patients with definitively diagnosed gastrointestinal diseases and 50 control subjects. Calprotectin concentrations were significantly higher in patients with ulcerative colitis or Crohn’s disease compared with controls, or patients with colorectal polyps or irritable bowel syndrome. The faecal calprotectin concentration significantly differentiated between inflammatory bowel diseases (IBD) and non-IBD (area under ROC curve 0.949). Calprotectin concentrations were significantly higher in patients with oesophageal polyps or gastric neoplasms than in those with chronic gastritis, stomach ulcers, duodenal ulcers or acute pancreatitis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-0300060513488499"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Calprotectin may be a useful noninvasive marker for the diagnosis of IBD.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Calprotectin</kwd>
<kwd>screening</kwd>
<kwd>oesophageal inflammation</kwd>
<kwd>gastric inflammation</kwd>
<kwd>inflammatory bowel disease</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0300060513488499" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Common diagnostic tests for diseases of the gastrointestinal tract include endoscopy, barium X-radiography, contrast radiography, computed tomography and biopsy, but these are limited by high cost and invasiveness. The calcium and zinc binding protein calprotectin is a member of the S-100 protein family with apoptotic and antimicrobial properties.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0300060513488499">1</xref></sup> Calprotectin is resistant to bacterial degradation and is stable for up to 1 week in faecal samples.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0300060513488499">2</xref></sup> The value of calprotectin as a laboratory marker has been shown in chronic inflammatory bowel disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0300060513488499">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0300060513488499">4</xref></sup> and ulcerative colitis,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0300060513488499">5</xref></sup> but the significance of calprotectin in other gastrointestinal diseases remains unclear. The aim of this study, therefore, was to investigate faecal concentrations of calprotectin in a wide range of gastrointestinal diseases, in order to evaluate its clinical significance.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0300060513488499" sec-type="methods"><title>Patients and methods</title>
<sec id="sec3-0300060513488499"><title>Study population</title>
<p>The study recruited patients with gastrointestinal symptoms requiring upper or lower endoscopy, who were admitted to the Department of Gastroenterology, Jingling Hospital, Nanjing, China, between June 2011 and August 2011. Patients were required to have a definitive diagnosis, made on the basis of standard clinical, endoscopic, radiological and histological criteria. Exclusion criteria were serious cardiopulmonary, hepatic, renal, neurological or psychiatric diseases.</p>
<p>Healthy volunteers attending Jingling Hospital, Nanjing, China for routine screening were recruited as control subjects.</p>
<p>The study was conducted with the approval of the Jingling Healthcare local ethics committee, and all participants provided written informed consent.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0300060513488499"><title>Calprotectin ELISA</title>
<p>Patients provided a faecal sample on the day before scheduled colonoscopy; control subjects provided a sample ≤48h after enrolment. Faeces was stored at 4℃ until use. Faeces (50–100 mg) was diluted 1 : 50 (w/v) with extraction buffer (Bühlmann Laboratories AG, Basel, Switzerland<bold>)</bold>, homogenized for 30 min, then stored at 4℃ overnight prior to analysis. Calprotectin was quantified via enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) (Bühlmann Laboratories AG).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0300060513488499"><title>Statistical analyses</title>
<p>Data were presented as mean ± SD, and compared using one-way analysis of variance. Data from patients with ulcerative colitis or Crohn's disease were combined to form the IBD group; data from patients with colonic polyps or irritable bowel syndrome were combined to form the non-IBD group. Logistic regression analysis was used to construct receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves for calprotectin sensitivity and specificity in these groups, and cut-off values were calculated. Statistical analyses were performed with SPSS® software, version 17.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA), and <italic>P</italic>-values &lt; 0.05 were considered statistically significant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0300060513488499" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title>
<p>The study included 210 patients with gastrointestinal symptoms (72 males/138 females; mean age 46.3 ± 22.5 years; age range 18–65 years) and 50 healthy control subjects (25 males/25 females; mean age 40.9 ± 27.3 years; age range 18–70 years). The patient group included 28 patients with ulcerative colitis, 44 with Crohn’s disease, 24 with colorectal polyps, 32 with irritable bowel syndrome (IBS), 20 with oesophagitis, 10 with oesophageal polyps, 12 with chronic gastritis, 11 with gastric ulcers, 10 with duodenal ulcers, seven with acute pancreatitis and 12 with gastric neoplasms.</p>
<p>Data regarding faecal calprotectin concentrations are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0300060513488499">Table 1</xref>. Calprotectin was significantly elevated in patients with ulcerative colitis or Crohn’s disease, compared with controls or patients with colorectal polyps or irritable bowel syndrome (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 for all comparisons). In addition, calprotectin was significantly elevated in patients with oesophageal polyps/gastric neoplasm compared with controls or patients with chronic gastritis/stomach ulcer/duodenal ulcer/acute pancreatitis (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). There were no other statistically significant between-group differences.
<table-wrap id="table1-0300060513488499" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Faecal calprotectin concentrations in healthy control subjects and patients with gastrointestinal disease, stratified according to diagnosis.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0300060513488499" xlink:href="10.1177_0300060513488499-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Group</th>
<th><italic>n</italic></th>
<th>Calprotectin µg/g faeces</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Healthy controls</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>33.94 ± 13.64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patients</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Ulcerative colitis</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>1914.79 ± 2638.80<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0300060513488499">a</xref>bc</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Crohn’s disease</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>3276.03 ± 2259.42<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0300060513488499">a</xref>bc</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Colorectal polyps</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>106.54 ± 70.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Irritable bowel syndrome</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>125.37 ± 155.97</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Oesophagitis</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>743.78 ± 1811.11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Oesphageal polyps/gastric neoplasm</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>1918.71 ± 2567.46<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0300060513488499">a</xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0300060513488499">d</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Chronic gastritis/stomach ulcer/duodenal  ulcer/acute pancreatitis</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>85.87 ± 80.88</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0300060513488499"><p>Data presented as mean ± SD.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0300060513488499"><label>a</label><p><italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs control, <sup>b</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs colonic polyps, <sup>c</sup><italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs irritable bowel syndrome; one-way analysis of variance.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0300060513488499"><label>d</label><p><italic>P &lt; </italic>0.01 vs chronic gastritis/stomach ulcer/duodenal ulcer/acute pancreatitis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>The results of ROC analyses in the IBD and non-IBD groups are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0300060513488499">Figure 1</xref>. The faecal calprotectin concentration significantly differentiated between IBD and non-IBD (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; area under curve 0.949, 95% confidence interval 0.911, 0.988). A cut-off value of 45.40 µg/g resulted in a sensitivity of 0.944 and specificity of 0.643; a cut-off of 110.65 µg/g resulted in a sensitivity of 0.944 and specificity of 0.429.
<fig id="fig1-0300060513488499" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Receiver operating characteristic analysis of the faecal calprotectin concentration in the differentiation between patients with inflammatory and noninflammatory bowel diseases.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0300060513488499-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0300060513488499" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>Calprotectin is a calcium-binding protein that makes up around 60% of the total cytosolic protein content of neutrophils and mononuclear cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0300060513488499">6</xref></sup> It is a heterocomplex protein comprising two heavy (L1H) chains and one light (L1L) chain which are noncovalently linked,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0300060513488499">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0300060513488499"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0300060513488499">9</xref></sup> and is an important regulatory protein in inflammatory reactions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0300060513488499">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0300060513488499">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0300060513488499">11</xref></sup> Studies in paediatric and adult cohorts have demonstrated a correlation between faecal calprotectin concentrations and the severity of mucosal inflammation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0300060513488499">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0300060513488499">12</xref></sup> Faecal calprotectin has also been shown to correlate with changes in C-reactive protein and erythrocyte sedimentation rate in active inflammation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0300060513488499">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0300060513488499"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0300060513488499"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0300060513488499"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0300060513488499"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0300060513488499">18</xref></sup> The stability of calprotectin at room temperature adds to its value as a practical and convenient marker in intestinal inflammation, and for the differential diagnosis of IBD and IBS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0300060513488499">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0300060513488499">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0300060513488499">19</xref></sup></p>
<p>Studies have found significantly higher faecal calprotectin concentrations in some gastrointestinal disorders (including oesophageal/gastric carcinoma, Crohn’s disease, ulcerative colitis and colorectal carcinoma) than in others (Barrett’s oesophagus, gastric ulcer, gastritis/duodenitis, colorectal polyps and adenoma).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0300060513488499">20</xref></sup> In accordance with the findings of others,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0300060513488499">6</xref></sup> faecal calprotectin concentrations were significantly higher in patients with IBD than in those with IBS or colorectal polyps in the present study. In addition, ROC curve analysis confirmed that the faecal calprotectin concentration effectively differentiated between IBD and IBS, with increased calprotectin being associated with a heightened risk of IBD. The elevated levels of calprotectin seen in patients with oesophageal polyps and gastric neoplasms in the present study (in contrast to those with chronic gastritis, stomach ulcer, duodenal ulcer or acute pancreatitis) may be explained by the synthesis of calprotectin by squamous epithelial cells, granulocytes and macrophages,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0300060513488499">21</xref></sup> or by the large wound surface present on these tissues.</p>
<p>In conclusion, findings of the present study indicate that faecal calprotectin may be a useful noninvasive marker for differentiating between IBD and IBS, and we also should note that faecal calprotectin can have high expression in other patients, excluding IBD patients.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec8-0300060513488499"><title>Declaration of conflicting interest</title>
<p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0300060513488499"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0300060513488499"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johne</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagerhol</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Functional and clinical aspects of the myelomonocyte protein calprotectin</article-title>. <source>Mol Pathol</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>50</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0300060513488499"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoepfer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beglinger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Straumann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ulcerative colitis: correlation of the Rachmilewitz endoscopic activity index with fecal calprotectin, clinical activity, C-reactive protein, and blood leukocytes</article-title>. <source>Inflamm Bowel Dis</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1851</fpage>–<lpage>1858</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0300060513488499"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angriman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Scarpa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>D’Incà</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Enzymes in feces: useful markers of chronic inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Clin Chim Acta</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>381</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0300060513488499"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vermeire</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Assche</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutgeerts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Laboratory markers in IBD: useful, magic, or unnecessary toys?</article-title> <source>Gut</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>426</fpage>–<lpage>431</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0300060513488499"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linskens</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>van Bodegraven</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoorl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Predictive value of inflammatory and coagulation parameters in the course of severe ulcerative colitis</article-title>. <source>Dig Dis Sci</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>644</fpage>–<lpage>648</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0300060513488499"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Røseth</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagerhol</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Aadland</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of the neutrophil dominating protein calprotectin in feces. A methodologic study</article-title>. <source>Scand J Gastroenterol</source> <year>1992</year>; <volume>27</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>793</fpage>–<lpage>738</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0300060513488499"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fagerhol</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Release and quantitation of a leucocyte derived protein (L1)</article-title>. <source>Scand J Haematol</source> <year>1980</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0300060513488499"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fagerhol</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Naess-Andresen</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <source>Calprotectin (the LI leukocyte protein). Stimulus response coupling: the role of intracellular calcium-binding proteins</source>, <publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press Inc</publisher-name>, <year>1990</year>, pp. <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0300060513488499"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagerhol</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Naesgaard</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Purification and partial characterization of a highly immunogenic human leukocyte protein, the L1 antigen</article-title>. <source>Eur J Biochem</source> <year>1983</year>; <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0300060513488499"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increased myeloid-derived suppressor cells in gastric cancer correlate with cancer stage and plasma S100A8/A9 proinflammatory proteins</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>190</volume>: <fpage>794</fpage>–<lpage>804</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0300060513488499"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Källberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stenström</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>CD11b(+)Ly6C(++)Ly6G(−) cells show distinct function in mice with chronic inflammation or tumor burden</article-title>. <source>BMC Immunol</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0300060513488499"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolho</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Raivio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fecal calprotectin remains high during glucocorticoid therapy in children with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian J Gastro</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>720</fpage>–<lpage>725</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0300060513488499"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berntzen</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagerhol</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostensen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The L1 protein as a new indicator of inflammatory activity in patients with juvenile rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source> <year>1991</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0300060513488499"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoepfer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Trummler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeholzer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Accuracy of four fecal assays in the diagnosis of colitis</article-title>. <source>Dis Colon Rectum</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1697</fpage>–<lpage>1706</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0300060513488499"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldred</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Polymorphisms within the C-reactive protein (CRP) promoter region are associated with plasma CRP levels</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0300060513488499"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoepfer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beglinger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Straumann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fecal calprotectin correlates more closely with the Simple Endoscopic Score for Crohn's disease (SES-CD) than CRP, blood leukocytes, and the CDAI</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>105</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>162</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0300060513488499"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sostegni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Daperno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Scaglione</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Review article: Crohn's disease: monitoring disease activity</article-title>. <source>Aliment Pharmacol Ther</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0300060513488499"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bitton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Peppercorn</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonioli</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical, biological, and histologic parameters as predictors of relapse in ulcerative colitis</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0300060513488499"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoepfer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Trummler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeholzer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Discriminating IBD from IBS: comparison of the test performance of fecal markers, blood leukocytes, CRP, and IBD antibodies</article-title>. <source>Inflamm Bowel Dis</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0300060513488499"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Summerton</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Longlands</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiener</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Faecal calprotectin: a marker of inflammation throughout the intestinal tract</article-title>. <source>Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>14</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>845</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0300060513488499"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tibble</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigthorsson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Use of surrogate markers of inflammation and Rome criteria to distinguish organic from nonorganic intestinal disease</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>450</fpage>–<lpage>460</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>