<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">VES</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spves</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Vasc Endovascular Surg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Vascular and Endovascular Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1538-5744</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-9116</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1538574412465972</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1538574412465972</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Endovascular Techniques</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Unique Hybrid Approach to the Treatment of an Aberrant Right Subclavian Artery Aneurysm</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Southard</surname>
<given-names>Nicholas M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538574412465972">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Seabrook</surname>
<given-names>Gary R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538574412465972">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tutton</surname>
<given-names>Sean M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1538574412465972">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Almassi</surname>
<given-names>G. Hossein</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1538574412465972">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>Brian D.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538574412465972">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>Kellie R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538574412465972">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Rossi</surname>
<given-names>Peter J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538574412465972">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1538574412465972"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1538574412465972">
<label>1</label>Divison of Vascular Surgery, Medical College of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, WI, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1538574412465972">
<label>2</label>Division of Interventional Radiology, Medical College of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, WI, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1538574412465972">
<label>3</label>Division of Cardiothoracic Surgery, Zablocki VA Medical Center, Milwaukee, WI, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1538574412465972">Peter J. Rossi, Division of Vascular Surgery, Medical College of Wisconsin, 9200 W Wisconsin Ave, Milwaukee WI 53226, USA. Email: <email>prossi@mcw.edu</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>128</fpage>
<lpage>130</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Aberrant right subclavian artery (ARSA) is an uncommon congenital anomaly that often becomes aneurysmal. The ARSAs are often asymptomatic but aneurysms arising in this location are potentially lethal. Due to the high morbidity and mortality rates associated with the traditional open repair methods, less invasive endovascular methods are becoming more popular. This is a case describing a unique hybrid repair of an aneurysmal ARSA in an asymptomatic male.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>aberrant right subclavian artery</kwd>
<kwd>Kommerell diverticulum</kwd>
<kwd>hybrid endovascular procedure</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1538574412465972">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Aberrant right subclavian artery (ARSA), although infrequent, is the most common congenital anomaly of the aortic arch with an incidence of 0.5% to 2%.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1538574412465972">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1538574412465972"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1538574412465972"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1538574412465972">4</xref>
</sup> It originates distal to the left subclavian artery and most commonly courses posterior to the esophagus. In almost two-thirds of cases, the ARSA origin is a saccular outpouching known as a Kommerell diverticulum but rarely do they become aneurysmal.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1538574412465972">5</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Historically, these lesions have been repaired through an open repair with the use of cardiopulmonary bypass and circulatory arrest. These open repairs are associated with morbidity and mortality rates approaching 25%, leading many to use more modern and less invasive endovascular methods.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1538574412465972">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1538574412465972">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1538574412465972">6</xref>
</sup> This is a report of a unique hybrid technique used to treat an incidentally found ARSA arising from an aneurysmal Kommerell diverticulum, during workup for carotid stenosis and lower extremity claudication.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1538574412465972">
<title>Case Report</title>
<p>A 60-year-old male with a history of hypertension, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), chronic kidney disease, schizophrenia, and a 150-pack-year smoking history presented with complaints of bilateral lower extremity claudication and visual changes consistent with amaurosis fugax. Diagnostic workup included a carotid duplex, which demonstrated a critical left internal carotid stenosis prompting a computed tomography angiogram of the neck, chest, abdomen, and pelvis for preoperative planning and to evaluate his claudication. The computed tomographic (CT) angiogram confirmed the high-grade left carotid stenosis and also revealed an ARSA with an aneurysmal Kommerell diverticulum measuring 3.2 cm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1538574412465972">Figure 1</xref>). It also demonstrated severe atherosclerotic disease, with a high-grade stenosis of bilateral renal arteries, infrarenal aorta, and bilateral iliac arteries.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1538574412465972" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Three dimensional reconstruction of the aortic arch from a CT angiogram demonstrating ARSA arising from an aneurysmal Kommerell's diverticulum.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574412465972-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Given the symptomatic nature of his carotid disease, the patient underwent a left carotid endarterectomy (CEA) prior to addressing his aneurysmal ARSA. After recovering from the CEA, he underwent bilateral renal artery stenting in an attempt to improve his renal function. Upon completion of these procedures as well as cardiac stress testing, the patient was scheduled for a 1-stage hybrid procedure to exclude his aneurysmal ARSA. This was done utilizing a multidisciplinary team consisting of vascular and cardiothoracic surgery as well as interventional radiology. The procedure began by performing a left common carotid to left subclavian bypass using an 8 mm polytetrafluoroethylene (PTFE) graft through a supraclavicular incision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1538574412465972">Figure 2</xref>). This was followed by construction of an ascending aorta to right axillary artery bypass through a partial upper sternotomy using one of the limbs of an 18 mm by 9 mm bifurcated PTFE graft. The second limb served as a conduit to deliver and deploy a 34 mm by 15 cm and a 34 mm by 10 cm GORE TAG thoracic endograft from an antegrade direction. Utilizing a retrograde approach for stent graft deployment would have been ideal and would have prevented a sternotomy incision; however, this was not a viable option given the patient’s significant infrarenal aortic and bilateral iliac atherosclerotic disease. In addition to covering the origin of the ARSA, the origin of the left subclavian was also covered to ensure adequate proximal fixation and prevent a type I endoleak. Prior to stent graft deployment, the origin of the right subclavian artery was coil embolized using 16 mm Amplatz septal occluder (St Jude Medical Inc, St Paul, Minnesota; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1538574412465972">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig2-1538574412465972" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sagittal CT image following hybrid repair of ARSA, illustrating the thoracic stent graft excluding the origin of the ARSA (thick arrow). Also visualized is a portion of the left carotid subclavian bypass (thin arrow).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574412465972-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-1538574412465972" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Coronal CT image following hybrid repair of ARSA, illustrating the thoracic stent graft and the endovascular occlusion device in the proximal ARSA (arrow).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538574412465972-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Postoperatively the patient had an extended intensive care stay secondary to developing ventilator-associated pneumonia which required prolonged intubation. In addition, he also had acute kidney injury. Both of these issues resolved and the patient was discharged home on postoperative day 17. Since discharge from the hospital, the patient has recovered well and his 6-month follow-up computed tomography imaging showed reduction in aneurysm size without evidence of endoleak or stent migration. His original presenting symptom of bilateral lower extremity claudication was not lifestyle limiting and will be addressed in the future if his symptoms worsen.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1538574412465972">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Congenital anomalies of the aortic arch are rare. Although infrequent, ARSA is one of the most common occurring anomalies, with a reported incidence of 0.5% to 2%.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1538574412465972">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1538574412465972"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1538574412465972"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1538574412465972">4</xref>
</sup> This embryologic variant of the great vessels occurs due to the abnormal involution of the right fourth aortic arch and right dorsal aorta cranial to the seventh intersegmental artery. The remaining right dorsal aorta and intersegmental artery persist as an ARSA arising from the descending aorta distal to the left subclavian artery.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1538574412465972">7</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The ARSAs are associated with a saccular origin or Kommerell diverticulum in 60% of cases.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1538574412465972">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1538574412465972">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1538574412465972">5</xref>
</sup> With time a small percentage of these become aneurysmal. Most patients with an ARSA are asymptomatic and are incidentally diagnosed following radiologic imaging to investigate other disease states. Approximately 37% of patients develop progressive symptoms of dysphagia, termed dysphagia lusoria, which results from extrinsic compression of the esophagus.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1538574412465972">7</xref>
</sup> Although the exact incidence is unknown, the risk of aneurysm rupture and thromboembolism is believed to be high and the postrupture mortality rate approaches 50%.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1538574412465972">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1538574412465972">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1538574412465972">6</xref>
</sup> This rupture rate does not appear related to the aneurysm size, leading to the belief that all aneurysms associated with an ARSA should be repaired regardless of size or symptoms.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1538574412465972">2</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The first reported successful repair of this lesion was performed by Gross in 1946.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1538574412465972">8</xref>
</sup> This repair was completed through a left thoracotomy with ligation and division of the ARSA without revascularization of the right upper extremity. This technique often resulted in upper extremity ischemia and in some, the development of subclavian steal. Over time, techniques to reestablish flow into the right subclavian artery evolved and were achieved through a sternotomy or thoracotomy incision with or without the use of partial or total cardiopulmonary bypass and circulatory arrest. These various open repairs are associated with a morbidity/mortality rate of approximately 25%, leading many to use more modern and less invasive methods.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1538574412465972">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1538574412465972">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1538574412465972">6</xref>
</sup> Advancements in endovascular techniques have led to hybrid options with combined endovascular and open surgical repair, a preferred alternative in high-risk patients.</p>
<p>The hybrid option allows exclusion of the ARSA with a thoracic endograft following occlusion of the aberrant artery via endovascular embolization techniques and is most often completed from a retrograde approach with femoral access. Our patient’s case was complicated by the fact that a retrograde approach could not be performed secondary to the inability to deliver a device though his atherosclerotic iliac and aortic vessels. To circumvent this issue, an antegrade approach was used and the device was delivered from a conduit sewn onto the ascending aorta.</p>
<p>In most instances, as was the case with our patient, in order to gain an adequate proximal seal the origin of the left subclavian must be covered by the endograft. To reestablish perfusion to the upper extremities, bilateral carotid subclavian bypasses must be performed. In the current patient, flow to the left upper extremity was reestablished in this manner; however, perfusion to the right upper extremity was reestablished through an ascending aorta to right axillary artery bypass via a limb off the ascending aortic conduit.</p>
<p>These hybrid procedures avoid the morbidity associated with cardiopulmonary bypass and circulatory arrest; however, they require long-term follow-up to monitor for the development of an endoleak and stent graft migration. Variations of the hybrid technique must be based on an understanding of both the disease process and the patient’s individual anatomy so that the repair can be tailored to the patient’s specific anatomic problem. Often times, as in this particular case, a multidisciplinary approach spanning multiple specialties is needed.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-1538574412465972">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1538574412465972">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1538574412465972">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bosma</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Montauban van Swijndregt</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vahl</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hybrid treatment of a ruptured diverticulum of Kommerell</article-title>. <source>J Endovasc Ther</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>762</fpage>–<lpage>766</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1538574412465972">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ferrero</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Viazzo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Aneurysm of the aberrant right subclavian artery: surgical and hybrid repair of two cases in a single center</article-title>. <source>Ann Vasc Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>839.e5</fpage>–<lpage>839.e9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1538574412465972">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rispoli</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Varetto</surname>
<given-names>GF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Conforti</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tallia</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rossato</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gandini</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hybrid treatmentof aberrant subclavian artery aneurysm</article-title>. <source>J Cardiovasc Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>737</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1538574412465972">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stone</surname>
<given-names>WM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ricotta</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fowl</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Garg</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bower</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Money</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Contemporary management of aberrant right subclavian arteries</article-title>. <source>Ann Vasc Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>508</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1538574412465972">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Davidian</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kee</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kato</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Aneurysm of an aberrant right subclavian artery: treatment with PTFE covered stentgraft</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>339</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1538574412465972">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kouchoukos</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Masetti</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Aberrant subclavian artery and Kommerell aneurysm: surgical treatment with a standard approach</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>133</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>888</fpage>–<lpage>892</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1538574412465972">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chapman</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Edwards</surname>
<given-names>WH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Coltharp</surname>
<given-names>WH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stoney</surname>
<given-names>WS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dysphagia lusoria: aberrant right subclavian artery with a Kommerell’s diverticulum</article-title>. <source>Am Surg</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>582</fpage>–<lpage>586</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1538574412465972">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gross</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Surgical treatment for dysphagia lusoria</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source>. <year>1946</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>532</fpage>–<lpage>534</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>