<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RAC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sprac</journal-id>
<journal-title>Race &amp; Class</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0306-3968</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-3125</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0306396812454988</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0306396812454988</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Borderline justice</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>Frances</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>54</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>39</fpage>
<lpage>54</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 Institute of Race Relations</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institute of Race Relations</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article reflects on the author’s legal career of over thirty years as a barrister representing migrants and asylum seekers in the UK. It exposes the consistently inhumane treatment meted out by successive governments to migrants and asylum seekers. It examines the ways in which such treatment is embodied in an ever-more punitive regulatory system, often implemented by powerful and profitable corporations, at the state’s behest. The hallmarks of a free society (universal rights not to be detained arbitrarily; access to justice; to fair trial; freedom from double punishment; freedom of movement) and those of a humane one (access to subsistence, shelter and health care) have all been called into question. In the service of relentless ‘common-sense’ racism, the law has been deployed against migrants and asylum seekers. However, through the sustained efforts of migrants and their solidarity groups, human rights lawyers and impartial judges, it has also been used to resist executive abuses of power, exclusion and injustice.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>asylum seekers</kwd>
<kwd>civil rights</kwd>
<kwd>G4S</kwd>
<kwd>Human Rights Act</kwd>
<kwd>ILPA</kwd>
<kwd>immigration detention</kwd>
<kwd>immigration law</kwd>
<kwd>refugees</kwd>
<kwd>Sodexo</kwd>
<kwd>state racism</kwd>
<kwd>Wackenhut</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>October-December 2012</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Borderline justice is marginal justice, justice that constantly disappears and has to be fought for constantly. For the individuals and families at the border, as migrants or asylum seekers, justice is regularly transformed into injustice by political or economic imperatives of exclusion. The laws and administrative practices in this field, often conceived in haste in a spirit of punitive populism, are designed to ward off the strangers or drive them out; they exclude their targets from mainstream legal entitlements, suspend normal guarantees of freedom and the rule of law, and are enacted in wilful disregard of the consequences for those targeted. It is ‘borderline justice’ in another sense, too: the border is no longer just the point of arrival in the country, but has been brought deep into workplaces, colleges, banks, hospitals and marriage registries, as immigration status has become determinative in many areas of daily life.</p>
<p>In the nearly thirty years that I have represented migrants and asylum seekers in the UK, the tensions between law and justice, between order and humanity, have been played out in battles inside and outside the courts around rights and freedoms that were believed secure. The hallmarks of a free society (universal rights not to be detained arbitrarily or without trial; access to justice; to fair and public trial with equality of arms; freedom from double punishment; freedom of movement) and those of a humane one (the principle of universal access to subsistence, shelter and health care at the point of need) have all been called into question, have had to be fought for repeatedly and are increasingly fragile and conditional when applied to migrants and asylum seekers. In my legal lifetime, the law has been deployed, developed, used and abused, stretched and strained for use against migrants and asylum seekers – but also used to resist executive abuses of power, exclusion and injustice, whether by reference to common-law precepts of fairness, the ‘law of common humanity’ or human rights law.</p>
<p>To deter and prevent the ‘disorderly movements’ of undocumented migrants and refugees, visa controls, carrier sanctions, biometrics and e-borders, criminalisation of unauthorised arrival and of assistance have created paper and electronic walls to accompany the military patrols, the surveillance systems and the subcontracting of controls to countries of origin and transit, making concentric fortifications around Europe – and lawyers and solidarity movements have tried to resist these developments. Officials’ and judges’ decision-making is distorted by the ‘culture of disbelief’, a colonial-style set of assumptions about applicants’ dishonesty and behaviour, particularly marked in the handling of family reunion and asylum claims. Many immigration judges find it hard to resist becoming Home Office gatekeepers, allowing anti-asylum attitudes to infect their approach to medical and country experts. Other obstacles in the path of justice include the notorious fast-track system for determining ‘straightforward’ asylum claims, which sets claims up for failure by the use of detention and the imposition of impossible timetables; the visa obstacle race for non-asylum-seeking migrants; the erosion of immigration appeal rights; and, the abolition of legal aid, which vigorous campaigning failed to prevent.</p>
<p>One of the longest battles for fair treatment waged by asylum seekers and migrants has been against the use of enforced destitution to starve out asylum seekers and undocumented migrants, their exclusion from rights to work, social housing and hospital care, and the growth of coalitions of solidarity and resistance to the laws of inhumanity. But there have also been significant battles against government attempts to make labour migration more responsive to volatile global market conditions (creating insecurity for lawful economic migrants and students) and against the double standards surrounding the discussion of family life, with legal battles raging around the rules restricting the entry of foreign partners, children and elderly parents and the separation of families through deportation. Immigration detention, for asylum seekers and others, has become a growth industry, with the convergence of interests between politicians seeking policies of containment, electoral imperatives and private companies seeking profits.</p>
<p>The last decade has seen a shift of emphasis to enforcement. A huge new immigration police force has been created, with virtually none of the safeguards attending the police proper; a security infrastructure of information exchange and data collection and retention has sprung up; and immigration control functions subcontracted to a wide variety of public and private sector agents who are themselves policed in an emerging totalising control. Economic and political imperatives, public and private interests converge in a drive to sweep up refused asylum seekers, irregular migrants and offenders, with little regard to age, health or family ties, and increasingly brutal methods are used in removal, which has led to resistance. And the legal system and the rule of law itself have been corrupted by secret evidence regimes that deny natural justice in the name of ‘national security’; deprivation of citizenship by stealth and deportation to torturing states are all justified by the demonisation of Muslims in the ‘war on terror’.</p>
<sec id="section1-0306396812454988">
<title>The war on migration</title>
<p>Migrants and asylum seekers are vilified and misrepresented by politicians and the press and subjected to injustice at the hands of officials and judges. Our leaders encourage and treat as heroes those people fighting for democracy and human rights in Burma, in Libya, in Egypt and Syria; those who fight women’s oppression and religious persecution in Iran, Afghanistan, Pakistan, Nigeria. But, as soon as these heroes seek sanctuary here in the ‘free world’, they are transformed into a hostile alien threat to our culture and our values, to be kept out by military patrols and bilateral accords and e-borders and carrier sanctions and all the paraphernalia of modern immigration controls.</p>
<p>Then we discover that our government – the bastion of democracy and human rights, as we thought – has been selling arms to repressive regimes, including Libya, Bahrain and Saudi Arabia, Algeria, Egypt, Kuwait, Morocco, Oman, Syria and Tunisia, which have been used to suppress pro-democracy activists and minorities, and the Ministry of Defence and British universities have trained soldiers from China, Sudan and Uzbekistan, Sri Lanka and Colombia. The governments of repressive regimes have, in turn, acted as subcontractors in the outsourcing of torture of British and UK-based Muslims suspected of support for terrorism and to keep asylum seekers from coming here. We have to ask: how many other repressive regimes is our government propping up and doing dirty deals with? How many refugees have been created by British government policies?</p>
<p>Many refugees don’t claim asylum<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0306396812454988">1</xref></sup> because of the corralling of asylum seekers in fast-track detention camps and dispersal slums and the low recognition rate for certain nationalities. But among the undocumented, the ‘irregulars’, are also those who have migrated to the UK over the past thirty years because, increasingly, there is no land, no work, no possibility of feeding, clothing and educating a family, no future at home and no legal routes to earning a livelihood anywhere else. They are the ‘economic migrants’, the ‘bogus asylum seekers’ of popular myth, hounded as ‘illegals’ and rounded up when they are discovered using false documents to secure sub-minimum wage work. But how valid is the distinction the law draws between economic and political desperation? Justice Collins recognised that ‘the so-called economic migrants are frequently trying to escape conditions which no one in this country would regard as tolerable’.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0306396812454988">2</xref></sup> What does this have to do with us? Sivanandan memorably said, ‘We are here because you are there’. One way or another, most of those who come to these shores without official permission are refugees from globalisation, from a poor world getting poorer as it is shaped to serve the interests, appetites and whims of the rich world, a world where our astonishing standard of living, our freedoms, the absurd array of consumer novelties, fashions and foods available to us, and thrown away by us, are bought at the cost of the health, freedoms and lives of others. This cost is felt in the terms of trade and intellectual property agreements, in the imposition on poor countries of policies that remove food self-sufficiency and drive small producers off the land, in the substitution by agribusiness of biofuels for food production in the vast tracts of Africa and Asia bought up by corporations for profit, in the soaring food prices in the poor world that sparked riots in Egypt and Tunisia.</p>
<p>The entire system of immigration controls, not just in the UK, but throughout Europe, the US and Canada, Australia, Japan, South Korea, the Gulf states, is built on the most massive global injustice. At the heart of globalisation is a ruthless social Darwinism, which immigration controls reflect and reinforce. For the global elite, it has never been easier to move about the globe, as biometric technology opens gates literally at the blink of an eye and new immigration rules smooth the path of the wealthy, even as fees have increased steeply to reflect the commercial value of UK residence. As requirements for eligibility multiply, increasingly the biblical parable is reversed, and only the rich may traverse the needle’s eye to enter the kingdom. The points-based system for immigration introduced in 2008 awards points for youth, salary, qualifications and talent. If you don’t have all these attributes, you’re not wanted; even if you do, your residence is increasingly contingent and precarious. If you’re not computer literate and don’t speak English, you can’t even apply for a visa in most countries – forms must be filled in online and in English. This brave new world is for the corporate class and closed to the rest.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0306396812454988">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>This global mis-distribution of wealth and mobility rights is taken for granted, just as the feudal order was, and in the rich world it is the migrants, not the governments and corporations, who wear the mark of Cain for seeking to disturb this unnatural order. The asylum seekers and migrants I have met over my career are ordinary people who decided to leave home because of intolerable living conditions, war, persecution or the fear of it – or, to study at a British university, to join family members already here, to make good, to support families at home, and so on. They are as different from their tabloid caricatures as it is possible to be. But they continue to be portrayed as inherently dangerous, posing an existential threat to the body politic, to our way of life, as well as more tangible threats to our standard of living, our public services, our safety and security. For them, it is real-life militarised external border controls, to match the metaphors of invasion; a large, mobile, fully-fledged and virtually unregulated internal border police force; total control and degradation for asylum seekers; segregation of foreign national prisoners, and the drive to deport the rejects and undesirables in ever-greater numbers. And, as society has become increasingly ‘governed by immigration’, in that immigration control has become prioritised as a policy aim, more and more public and private sector bodies have been recruited to perform immigration policing functions. Voluntary sector groups and charities have been co-opted, too, into the reception, processing and ‘voluntary removal’ of asylum seekers, into becoming accessory to the detention of children.</p>
<p>Immigration control has become a huge industry, employing an ever-greater proportion of the workforce. In common with many other former public services, it has become big business. Private companies are ubiquitous. Visa applicants in many countries deal not with consular staff at embassies, but with Gerry’s, Worldbridge and VFS, which receive the applications and increasingly perform the biometric testing required for visas. Refused asylum seekers receive Sodexo smartcards redeemable only in Tesco, Asda, Sainsbury’s or Morrisons, may wear Sodexo electronic tags and may be monitored by Sodexo telephone monitoring systems. Immigration detainees are mostly held in centres run and staffed by G4S, Serco and Reliance, multinational security companies that also provide deportation ‘escorts’ and are now cornering the asylum hostel market. Not all asylum seekers are locked up, but a fair proportion are: those whose claims are deemed ‘straightforward’, as well as some undocumented migrants and nearly all foreign ex-offenders awaiting deportation.</p>
<p>Unlike criminal prisoners, immigration prisoners have no date of release towards which the days and weeks can be counted off. The law imposes no time limit on immigration detention, and when, in 2008, the EU adopted a directive stipulating an absolute limit of eighteen months, the UK opted out, complaining it wasn’t long enough. With no idea for how long they will remain locked up, they are more like hostages, waiting daily for news of their fate. Detention is extremely costly, yet the numbers in detention have risen from about 200 each day in 1990 to around 3,500 each day in 2010. Over two-thirds of those held in detention have claimed asylum at some point. In 1984, the High Court ruled that a migrant’s five-month detention was unlawful, as there was no imminent prospect of deporting him. Yet, now, one-quarter of detainees awaiting deportation are held for over a year.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0306396812454988">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>Why are so many vulnerable people detained? What on earth possesses ministers and officials to deny people’s liberty, to jeopardise their health, sanity and even their lives? According to Wackenhut’s religious affairs officer, detainees at Tinsley House (near Gatwick airport) were ‘detained as a result of having acted against the will of God’.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0306396812454988">5</xref></sup> Deterrence (to stop asylum seekers coming),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0306396812454988">6</xref></sup> isolation (to prevent the growth of solidarity)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0306396812454988">7</xref></sup> and administrative expediency (to make processing claims and removal easier) have all been cited. Another policy rationale is the preservation of order: asylum seekers and migrants are seen as somehow embodying illegality and disorder.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0306396812454988">8</xref></sup> The burgeoning private security industry, whose lobbyists swarm in Westminster and whose directors have often come through the revolving door of politics, has also influenced policy. As governments rely on global security firms for more and more functions, the influence of lobbyists and the ‘locking in’ of administrations to contracts made by their predecessors add to the pressure to keep increasing detention rather than trying alternatives. A confluence of private and public interests demands more and more incarceration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0306396812454988">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>Harmondsworth detention centre has been privately run since the 1970s, and, as ministers sought more immigration detention places, American corporations like Wackenhut and Corrections Corporation of America saw opportunities to expand their operations into the UK. There were close relations between the security industry, rightwing thinktanks (such as the Adam Smith Institute) and Conservative MPs, including influential members of the Home Affairs Committee (whose brief included immigration detention).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0306396812454988">10</xref></sup> In 1991, Group 4 (now G4S) was awarded the contract to run Campsfield House, a former young offenders’ institution at Kidlington, near Oxford, which opened in November 1993 as a dedicated immigration detention centre. It was described as a ‘secure hostel’, but with 20-foot fences, barbed wire and electronically opened gates, it was the first of many new immigration prisons. Trades unionists, refugee and migrant support and anti-racist groups greeted its opening with banners saying, ‘Refugees are not criminals’, ‘Close down Campsfield’. Opposition spread to Oxford dons, eighty-six of whom wrote to the prime minister urging him to respect the spirit of the Refugee Convention by not detaining asylum seekers. The Campaign to Close Campsfield has held monthly pickets of the detention centre ever since it opened.</p>
<p>Where else does privatisation flourish? Detainees needing medical care might be seen by Primecare Forensic Medical or Nestor Healthcare Services staff. Under rules promulgated in 2001, new arrivals were to be medically screened within twenty-four hours for signs of torture or serious illness, to ensure that torture survivors were not inadvertently detained, in recognition of the profound distress, terror, suicide attempts or self-harm that can result.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0306396812454988">11</xref></sup> But a test case in 2006 brought by two detained torture survivors revealed that, for years, the private medical provider in detention centres had not done routine screening – because the Home Office regarded it as unnecessary and inappropriate and refused to pay for it.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0306396812454988">12</xref></sup> A spate of cases since has shown that officials continue to authorise the detention of torture survivors and severely ill people in the teeth of medical advice, and sometimes despite court orders. Dr Frank Arnold, former clinical director of Medical Justice, blames privatisation for the routine lack of essential medication for serious illnesses, including HIV and diabetes, routine failures of investigation, examination and treatment of detainees’ medical conditions, even when torture is alleged, routine handcuffing of male detainees for outpatient consultations and inpatient treatment in hospitals and routine cancellation of hospital visits when UKBA refuses to bear transport and escort costs, a state he describes as ‘institutional medical abuse’.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0306396812454988">13</xref></sup></p>
<p>The net spreads wider. World-Check, Thompsons-Reuter and other large media groups perform terrorism-financing blacklist checks. And that does not include the computer companies, such as Siemens, Raytheon and IBM, providing the networks, the biometrics databases and recognition systems, the international information exchanges and the software for the interfaces required by education providers; and, the arms and defence companies providing everything from satellite maritime surveillance systems in the Mediterranean to the handcuffs, helmets and leg restraints used in deportation … The relentless expansion of the immigration security industry and its inherent violence are justified by the relentless common-sense racism propagated by politicians and media, an inverted narrative of victimhood which, for decades, has painted British taxpayers as the victims of foreign hordes of opportunist criminals, scroungers, cheats and terrorists. The resulting culture of suspicion and exclusion embraces all migrants and spills over to settled black and ethnic minority communities. But, as governments increasingly serve the interests of the corporations rather than the people, and as the revolving doors between politicians and the boards of corporations become normalised, there is more than just political capital to be made out of policies of segregation, detention, deportation and securitisation of asylum and immigration.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0306396812454988">
<title>Lawyers in the struggle</title>
<p>Political struggles are increasingly played out in the law courts. In parallel, more lawyers have become involved as committed partisans, forsaking the role of remote expert and consciously putting themselves on the side of historically marginalised and excluded groups, including migrants and asylum seekers. In the 1970s, the nature of the legal profession was changed by the social movements sweeping through society. Law centres were set up by radical lawyers working with community activists to ensure the same access to justice for benefits claimants, social housing tenants, compulsorily detained mental patients, parents threatened with removal of their children, sacked workers and immigrants as had by wealthy corporations. Young lawyers set up the Legal Action Group and the Free Representation Unit; they flocked to the Haldane Society of Socialist Lawyers and the National Council for Civil Liberties (now Liberty). Many had worked on their local Race Relations Board or Community Relations Council, as volunteers for the Joint Council for the Welfare of Immigrants (JCWI) or their local advice centre or for women’s groups like Rights of Women. In the years that followed, groups for radical lawyers proliferated in parallel with popular and community organisations, providing an infrastructure of legal expertise for the grassroots movements fighting for civil rights, justice and equality.</p>
<p>Like many coming into the legal profession in the 1970s, my politics were formed by the movements of that era, primarily the anti-racist movement, which embraced campaigns against the ‘sus’ law,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0306396812454988">14</xref></sup> police brutality and racist immigration laws as well as against the fascists who swaggered through Southall and Brick Lane behind protective police cordons. Immigration law was in its infancy as a legal discipline, but was intensely politically charged and was an area where state racism was confronted in every case. The privilege of the Bar, where formal dinners (compulsory for Bar students) always ended with port, was in stark contrast with our clients’ lives, but I was lucky to get a place in a young, radical chambers. It took me a few years to begin getting immigration cases, as women were not considered clever enough for this kind of work – other than crime, the family courts were seen as the place for women barristers. However, the depth of injustice faced by our clients dwarfed the difficulties we faced as women barristers. Many radical young lawyers went into immigration law, in both branches of the profession, and the Immigration Law Practitioners’ Association (ILPA) was formed in 1984 to provide a forum for immigration lawyers, discussion and training. It has grown into a powerful voice for reform, lobbying the Home Office for migrants’ and asylum rights, taking test cases, conducting research and briefing MPs and peers on legislative proposals.</p>
<p>Immigration law, in the form of statutes, rules and regulations, grew exponentially in response to the arrival of large numbers of asylum seekers from the late 1980s onwards, and, as demand for legal expertise in the field grew, so more and more lawyers turned to immigration, often driven by radical politics or plain dislike of the political and media witch-hunt. By the end of the millennium, many lawyers from migrant backgrounds, and many more women, had come into the field to defend migrant rights. Today, the number of immigration lawyers is shrinking again, as legal aid cuts decimate high-street firms and specialist practices: the two major non-profit organisations, Refugee and Migrant Justice and the Immigration Advisory Service, employing hundreds of lawyers between them and providing immigration services to tens of thousands, went under in 2010 and 2011.</p>
<p>Although much has changed, the institutions and language of the law, and particularly the Bar, remain elitist and intimidating. The first we barristers see of a client is still a set of papers tied up in pink ribbon: a brief containing a decision, whether a refusal of a family, work or study visa, asylum refusal or a decision to deport, supported by reasons, statements of evidence, records of interviews and correspondence. Part of our job is to articulate the sense of unfairness that the decision embodies in language recognisable to a judge. Preparation for a case involves searching for the legal principles to do so, as well as (crucially) ensuring that the evidential basis is there, which means going through the facts thoroughly. If it is an asylum case, what country information has the Home Office used and is it reliable? What other country information is there? Will we need expert evidence to corroborate the client’s account of events or to discuss his or her likely treatment on return? Is there medical evidence to corroborate any injuries described? If not, can we contact Freedom from Torture or the Helen Bamber Foundation or, if the client is detained, Medical Justice, for a report?</p>
<p>I can hear some readers asking, ‘but are the clients telling the truth?’ ‘What if they’re lying?’ But I would respond, ‘in what other field is lying so readily assumed?’ Of course, it’s part of the job to test clients’ accounts rigorously, questioning them in readiness for the grilling they will receive from the Home Office representative in court. But I can count on the fingers of one hand the clients I disbelieved.</p>
<p>Some cases involve situations that the law has simply never dealt with before, which provides the opportunity to work from first principles. If the law is unclear, the battle will be in convincing the court of the interpretation that best protects rights from unwarranted intrusion. The task then is to marshal cases, precedents and arguments in support of that interpretation. If the law (whether statute or case law) is against the client, then we must ask: ‘is that law itself open to challenge, via the Human Rights Act or other international or common-law principles?’ What do the international conventions – the Refugee and Human Rights Convention, the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child, the Convention on the Elimination of all forms of Discrimination against Women – have to say about this situation? What about UN resolutions? How have other common-law jurisdictions resolved the legal issues? If there is already a campaign against the law or provision at issue, is this a good test case or does it have weaknesses that could result in a bad legal decision and make things worse for more people? Are other lawyers seeking to challenge the provision in other cases and, if so, should we try to link up with them? Or would our case be better off standing alone? These are some of the technical and tactical questions that might arise. The legal arguments that we present to the court are informed by the politics of the movements we are involved in as well as by the obvious legal issues arising from the case. These arguments determine the shape of the case that the judges hear, and judicial creativity generally rests on the work of the barristers whose arguments frame the courts’ judgements.</p>
<p>Legal strategies are discussed at the conferences with solicitors and clients, where, in appropriate cases, ways of ‘bringing the community into the courtroom’ are planned. Friends, neighbours, detention visitors, church and trade union contacts may all have a part to play in mobilising support, which can be deployed in the courtroom so as to make a real difference, particularly in bail applications and deportation appeals, where community ties are important to the decision. The mere presence of people in the public gallery (friends, not hostile journalists!) improves the quality of decisions; when immigration judges know they are being watched, they tend to behave with more regard for justice than when the only people in the hearing room are the appellant, the lawyers (if any), the Home Office representative and a dozing court usher. For a fighting lawyer, there is nothing more dispiriting than an empty courtroom. But the community has to be brought into the courtroom in another sense, too, by bringing the reality of clients’ lives into focus as powerfully as possible to judges inevitably insulated by their position of privilege and under political, bureaucratic and time pressure to see cases as purely intellectual exercises.</p>
<p>Legal action necessarily proceeds through individual cases and, in this sense, appears antithetical to political action, which is essentially collective. But many fighting lawyers also work with campaign groups, helping to turn cases into issues. Many battles have been fought simultaneously inside and outside the courtroom, on issues such as enforced destitution of asylum seekers, separation of families through harsh immigration rules, immigration detention and the use of secret evidence in national security deportation cases.</p>
<p>Most of the thousands of cases I have worked on during my career raised no new points of law. If the successes had value over and above the relief they brought to individual clients and their families, it was as part of the great mass of challenges to Home Office decisions and the careless racism that informed them. Very few made legal history and, of those that did, they often didn’t set out to do so. Bakhtaur Singh’s case, where the House of Lords ruled that a person’s value to the community should be taken into account in an appeal against deportation, is typical. A friend involved in the Asian youth movement asked me to represent Bakhtaur, a musician, priest and long-term overstayer facing deportation. He organised a 100-strong picket of the court, and many community leaders sat in the public gallery. It was this community support that provided the legal ammunition to take the case further when the adjudicator dismissed the deportation appeal saying that he couldn’t take into account Bakhtaur’s value to the community. The point arose organically through the legal proceedings and took Bakhtaur to the House of Lords, with veteran immigration lawyer Ian Macdonald QC now heading the legal team. Bakhtaur simultaneously stood as a parliamentary candidate on a ‘no deportations’ platform.</p>
<p>Mrs Shah’s case was another unplanned intervention. With its joined case of Mrs Islam, it became a leading case, establishing that women fleeing domestic violence could be refugees, but it started as a last-ditch attempt to prevent a woman being returned to a violent husband who would probably kill her. There was no public campaign around her case, but the global women’s movement had led to pioneering cases in Canada and Australia, changing the way that women were perceived in refugee law, and this thinking was incorporated into the legal arguments that eventually persuaded the House of Lords. (It is much easier to do this now, as the jurisprudence of the Canadian, Australian, New Zealand and US courts is freely available on the internet.)</p>
<p>Some cases are brought more deliberately as part of campaigns against government action. When the 1996 social security regulations excluded certain asylum seekers from subsistence benefits, some of us were so alarmed that we decided to look for a way of challenging the regulations in court, and the judicial review by the JCWI was the result. Organisations like JCWI could not get public funding for legal challenges, but a destitute claimant joined JCWI in the judicial review and she was eligible for legal aid, which funded the case and enabled us to get the regulations quashed. It has now become more common for campaigning organisations, such as JCWI, Liberty, Bail for Immigration Detainees (BID) and Medical Justice, to get involved in test case litigation, either as claimants or as interveners in cases brought by others, to ensure that wider policy considerations are not neglected. The work of representing such an organisation is generally unpaid or <italic>pro bono</italic> (short for <italic>pro bono publico</italic>, for the public good), but there is no shortage of lawyers willing to put as much time and effort into them as into their paid cases. Immigration lawyers are not generally interested in making big money.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0306396812454988">
<title>Making executive power accountable</title>
<p>What happened in the JCWI case on asylum and benefits illustrated the cat-and-mouse nature of the legal struggles in this field, which can lead to enormous frustration. When the courts ruled the social security regulations excluding asylum seekers illegal, the government simply re-enacted them as primary legislation, which made them immune from legal challenge because of the doctrine of parliamentary supremacy. Parliament and the media are described as the two great checks on executive power, apart from the courts, but when they are supine (as parliament was in that case) or, worse, support and legitimate that power (as the media, with honourable exceptions, have done in immigration and asylum), the courts’ role becomes even more important.</p>
<p>The law is intensely dynamic and as far from the Mosaic stone tablets as it is possible to be – constantly fought over, in flux, pulled this way and that by conservatives and progressives in the courts and in the increasingly vocal struggle between the executive and judicial branches of government, and sometimes the legislature too. A growing executive contempt for the rule of law – marked by secret, unlawful detention policies, systematic failure to comply with legal safeguards for vulnerable people and attempts to muscle through measures abolishing the higher courts’ scrutiny of immigration decisions – has been increasingly resisted in the past decade or so by the higher judiciary, whether because of the examples set by a few stalwart human rights defenders among them, or because some of the radical lawyers of a generation ago are now sitting on the judicial bench, or whether the resistance is provoked by the sheer overweening arrogance of the executive. But, as senior judges have shown more willingness to castigate Home Office conduct as a public disgrace, and law lords have condemned proposed legislation as an affront to the constitution, ministers complain that judges are subverting their work and making their task impossible. There is loud ministerial heckling of judges who declare legislation incompatible with human rights obligations, or who overrule policy decisions that violate foreign national offenders’ or asylum seekers’ rights, and there are signs that more executive-friendly judges are being appointed to the highest courts as well as further attempts to insulate legislation from judicial scrutiny. The constant battle between executive and judiciary carries on a great tradition: in the words of historian E. P. Thompson, ‘One way of reading our history is as an immensely protracted contest to subject the nation’s rulers to the rule of law.’<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0306396812454988">15</xref></sup></p>
<p>The developments described here span three incarnations of government, from the Thatcher and Major Tory administrations (1979–1997), through Blair and Brown’s New Labour (1997–2010), to the Cameron-Clegg Con-Dem Coalition. When I started dealing with immigration cases in the early 1980s, hardly any primary (economic) immigration was permitted; it had been virtually ended by the 1971 Immigration Act. Thatcher’s government imposed further restrictions: first, on the entry of dependants of the Commonwealth settlers who had come in the previous decade; and, later, to prevent and deter asylum seekers. As she slashed the social infrastructure, defeated organised labour and opened the country to globalised capital with her programme of privatisation, cuts and financial deregulation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0306396812454988">16</xref></sup> immigrants were the enemy without and miners the enemy within. We immigration lawyers were kept busy trying to prove that the primary purpose of marriages was not immigration, that children were related to the parents they were joining in the UK and that people arrested as illegal immigrants weren’t.</p>
<p>From the mid-1980s, we were also seeking to show that asylum seekers were genuine refugees. Kurds, Tamils, Somalis, Iranians, Angolans and Algerians, Chinese, Rwandans and Congolese were joined by Nigerians, Croatians, Bosnians, Kosovars, Czech and Slovak Roma and, later still, Zimbabweans, Ethiopians, Eritreans, Sudanese, Iraqis, Afghans … Although governments claim that most asylum seekers are disguised economic migrants, the country-of-origin statistics for those claiming asylum tell a different story, reflecting all the zones of repression and conflict.</p>
<p>Initial indications of Labour progressiveness on immigration, such as the abolition of the primary purpose rule, were belied by its adoption of anti-asylum rhetoric and policies, a huge growth in immigration powers of detention, enforcement, removal, internal controls, matched by savage cuts to legal aid. Challenges to enforced destitution, deportation and detention all became common. The iniquities of ‘managed migration’, which recruited and discarded educated and highly skilled migrants in line with market needs, gave rise to case law, too. But Labour’s Human Rights Act is a powerful weapon for accountability.</p>
<p>The present coalition government has used nationalist rhetoric to seek to slash migration of all but the wealthy. Against a background of unprecedented income inequality and attempts to dismantle the welfare state and privatise health and education, it has sought to tune immigration policy even more finely to the needs of the globalised market state. The courts hear cases of illegal capping and robotic controls and of colleges closed down for inefficient policing of their students. The Coalition came into power on a civil liberties ticket, but has forced through the almost complete destruction of civil legal aid and proposes legislation to curtail the reach of the Human Rights Act and to wrap the veil of secrecy round more types of judicial process.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0306396812454988">
<title>Racism and the suppression of empathy</title>
<p>It is often claimed that immigration law has been decoupled from racism since the bad old days of the 1960s and1970s, when ‘immigration’ meant settlement of former colonial subjects from Africa, the Caribbean and the Indian subcontinent, and laws emerged from, reflected, legitimated and reproduced that colour-coded racism. But the anti-asylum laws and practices of the 1980s and 1990s were informed by a non-colour-coded, but just as virulent, ‘xeno-racism’<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0306396812454988">17</xref></sup> directed against poor eastern Europeans, particularly Roma. A ferocious anti-Muslim racism underlay the national security measures of the 2000s and the debate about Britishness instituted by Labour and carried forward in Cameron’s critique of multiculturalism, which suggests that you can’t be properly British and properly Muslim at the same time. A deep vein of xenophobic nationalism informs the anti-human rights campaign and the deportation drive against foreign national prisoners. Nationalism doesn’t have to be racist: Scottish nationalism is evolving as a progressive cause, but, in the Union Jack, nationalism and xenophobia or racism seem inextricably interwoven.</p>
<p>Institutional racism is alive and well in government, in the United Kingdom Border Agency (UKBA), the modern incarnation of the Home Office Immigration and Nationality Directorate, and in the immigration judiciary. It is, of course, important to distinguish institutional racism from personal attitudes, although the former informs the latter. Many times I marvelled at this paradox: how could presenting officers (UKBA civil servants who present their cases in the Tribunal), who were generally friendly and pleasant to me, display such contempt and lack of human understanding in their questioning of my clients? Home Office officials and immigration judges are not evil monsters, but many lose their human empathy in their dealings with migrants and asylum seekers. Sociologist Zygmunt Bauman has compellingly described the processes whereby natural human empathy is manipulated by the powerful to produce moral indifference to the fate of marginalised groups, and, although he was trying to understand the Holocaust, his description of the suppression of empathy and moral responsibility resonates here.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0306396812454988">18</xref></sup> He describes how physical and spiritual separation, which distance us from the effects on others of what we do (or what is done in our name), dilutes our sense of empathy, while demonisation of the targeted group puts them outside the realm of moral responsibility. We transfer our empathy and sense of responsibility to a ‘mini-moral community’, defined by employer, by race, class or religion. This allows decisions about the targeted group to be based on ‘rational’ or technical, rather than moral, considerations.</p>
<p>This suppression of empathy underlies atrocities from Rwanda to Abu Ghraib, accounts for the widespread indifference to migrant deaths at the border and in prisons and allows officials to discount the humanity of those they deal with. The higher judiciary are not immune from these processes; it is not hard to find judgements from them that display a want of empathy. But these judges’ prominence as defenders of common-law values of fairness and human rights against executive intrusion provides a powerful countervailing pressure. Of course, these same values enable many officials and low-level judges to resist the pressures to group loyalty over human solidarity and to refuse to reify the people whose cases they decide. (And there are some terrible, lazy, negligent and downright crooked lawyers who see clients purely as income streams and do untold damage to them.) But we are all up against a racist system and, in large measure, the work of lawyers in this field is part of the fight against racism. The cloak of invisibility conferred by the political and media dehumanisation of migrants and asylum seekers, which hides in plain view the struggles of people seeking safety and security, against immiseration and destitution, the psychological and physical damage wrought by detention, the known and unknown dangers of deportation, is constantly pierced by the campaigning groups who picket and blockade detention centres and airports to prevent deportations, who march against forced destitution, who lobby and harry and brief and report and protest at the treatment of people as less than human because of birth and nationality.</p>
<p>There are similar laws and policies – and struggles – across Europe, Australia, the US and Canada, South Korea, the Gulf states, Israel, South Africa – wherever, in fact, refugees and poor migrants seek sanctuary and livelihood. Migrants are, too, not the only group facing policies of marginalisation and demonisation in the global economy. The Dale Farm and Meriden evictions of Travellers demonstrated how those who insist on retaining old ways, such as Traveller communities, are systematically excluded and criminalised. And the poor, the sick, the disabled, the workless, are today suffering similar exclusion and demonisation by politicians and the press, as those who can’t work find their lives squeezed out to mere existence, just like asylum seekers. The opening of a new, state-of-the-art court building in October 2011, designed to ensure the UK’s supremacy as a forum for international commercial litigation, reminds us that justice is not immune from the privatisation/marketisation process, becoming a commodity available only to those who can pay for it.</p>
<p>The legal struggles fought in this field demonstrate how vital access to justice is; vital in restraining the executive, providing accountability and protecting and occasionally extending rights. When given the freedom to do so, the courts, particularly the higher courts, sometimes fulfil their function of doing justice. But judges’ powers are limited; they cannot overrule acts of parliament, and they can only respond to the cases brought to them. The shrinking pool of immigration lawyers can’t hope to help more than a fraction of those suffering injustice, a fraction that will be reduced further when immigration is taken outside the scope of legal aid. And many of the really pernicious measures against asylum seekers and migrants are contained in acts of parliament.</p>
<p>The myriad asylum and detainee support groups up and down the country are beginning to come together to develop new strategies, and there is room for more strategic deployment of lawyers’ expertise in the new movement. But it is the tripartisan consensus on restriction of asylum and migrant rights that needs to be challenged head on. The global injustices giving rise to migration and refugees need to form part of any public defence of migrants’ and asylum rights. It is justice, not charity, that is demanded. Loud and sustained defence of the Human Rights Act and access to the European Court of Human Rights (ECtHR) are vital. The Right has been given virtually a clear run in the attack on human rights in the media; where is the voice of the anti-racist Left? The arguments for universality of basic human rights and for the rule of law need to be made again and again, making common cause with the struggles of other excluded and marginalised groups in the process and building solidarity against corporate values. The year 2011 saw the world catch alight with resistance from the ‘99 per cent’; migrants’ struggles for recognition and humanity form a large part of that resistance.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<p><italic>Frances Webber</italic> is Vice-chair of IRR’s Council of Management and a former barrister who specialised in immigration, refugee and human rights law until her retirement in 2008. She coedited <italic>Macdonald’s Immigration Law and Practice</italic> (2001, 2005) and <italic>Halsbury’s British Nationality, Immigration and Asylum</italic> (2002). She lectures part-time at Warwick University and Birkbeck College and speaks and writes on migration and human rights issues. This article is adapted from the introduction to her forthcoming book, <italic>Borderline Justice: the fight for refugee and migrant rights</italic> (Pluto Press, forthcoming).</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<p>The cases cited in the endnotes are available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bailii.org">http://www.bailii.org</ext-link>.</p>
<ref id="bibr1-0306396812454988">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal"><article-title>Refugees, in law, are people who are outside their own country and unable or unwilling to return owing to well-founded fear of persecution on grounds of race, religion, nationality, membership of a particular social group or political opinion</article-title>. Refugees are recognised, not created, by the grant of refugee status. Many refugees remain unrecognised, either because they do not apply for asylum or because they are wrongly refused. Asylum seekers are people who seek recognition and protection as refugees.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0306396812454988">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<source>R (Q and others) v SSHD</source> [<year>2003</year>] EWHC 195 (Admin), para. 56.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0306396812454988">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">See, for example, <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bauman</surname><given-names>Zygmunt</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <source>Globalization: the human consequences</source> (<publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>, <year>1998</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0306396812454988">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<source>Detained Lives: the real cost of indefinite immigration detention</source> (<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>London Detainee Support Group</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>); see also <source>Out of Sight, Out of Mind: experiences of immigration detention in the UK</source> (<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>BID</publisher-name>, <month>July</month> <year>2009</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0306396812454988">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<source>CARF</source> 39 (<year>1997</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0306396812454988">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Home Office, Immigration and Nationality Directorate</collab>, <source>Annual Report 1986</source>, cited in <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dunstan</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <source>Cell Culture: the detention and imprisonment of asylum seekers in the United Kingdom</source> (<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Amnesty International</publisher-name>, <year>1997</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0306396812454988">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>David Blunkett justified accommodation centres for the segregation of asylum seekers on the ground that, in the community, they became more difficult to remove</collab>; HC Deb. (<day>24</day> <month>April</month> <year>2002</year>), col. 353.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0306396812454988">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="book"><article-title>Shahram Khosravi describes irregular migrants and asylum seekers as ‘anti-citizens’, like dangerous antibodies to be quarantined</article-title>, in <source>‘Illegal’ Traveller</source> (<publisher-loc>Basingstoke</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0306396812454988">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>For details of the close links between politicians and the private security industry</collab>, see <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bacon</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <source>The Evolution of Immigration Detention in the UK: the involvement of private prison companies</source> (<publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Refugee Studies Centre</publisher-name>, <year>2005</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0306396812454988">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="other">Ibid.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0306396812454988">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="book"><source>A Civilised Society: mental health provision for refugees and asylum seekers in England and Wales</source> (<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>MIND</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0306396812454988">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>R (D and K) v SSHD</source> [<year>2006</year>] EWHC 980 (Admin).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0306396812454988">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ‘<article-title>Medical implications of immigration detention in the UK</article-title>’, <conf-name>paper presented to conference at the Refugee Studies Centre</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Oxford University</conf-loc>, <conf-date>December 2008</conf-date>. <article-title>A recent Medical Justice report, Detained and Denied: the clinical care of immigration detainees living with HIV</article-title> (<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Medical Justice</publisher-name>, <month>March</month> <year>2011</year>), describes the routine failure to provide medication and care to detained HIV patients.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0306396812454988">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>Loitering with intent to commit an arrestable offence, s. 4 Vagrancy Act 1824, which was heavily used to control the movements of young black people in the 1970s until its abolition in 1981</collab>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0306396812454988">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <source>Writing by Candlelight</source> (<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Merlin</publisher-name>, <year>1980</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0306396812454988">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
See <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sivanandan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ‘<article-title>Imperialism in the silicon age</article-title>’, in <source>Catching History on the Wing: race, culture and globalisation</source> (<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0306396812454988">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
See <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sivanandan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ‘<article-title>Poverty is the new black</article-title>’, in <source>Catching History on the Wing</source>, ibid.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0306396812454988">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bauman</surname><given-names>Zygmunt</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <source>Modernity and the Holocaust</source> (<publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>, <year>1989</year>), cited in <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pemberton</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ‘<article-title>A theory of moral indifference: understanding the production of harm by capitalist society</article-title>’, in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hillyard</surname><given-names>Paddy</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>., eds, <source>Beyond Criminology: taking harm seriously</source> (<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>, <year>2004</year>).</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>