<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DVR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdvr</journal-id>
<journal-title>Diabetes &amp; Vascular Disease Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1479-1641</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1752-8984</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1479164112441006</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1479164112441006</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Predictors of and survival after incident stroke in type 1 diabetes</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Secrest</surname><given-names>Aaron M</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>Catherine T</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Costacou</surname><given-names>Tina</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Rachel G</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>Trevor J</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1479164112441006">Department of Epidemiology, University of Pittsburgh, PA, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1479164112441006">Trevor J Orchard, Department of Epidemiology, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA 15260, USA. Email: <email>orchardt@edc.pitt.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>10</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Few studies have examined stroke risk in type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM). Stroke incidence, predictors, and survival were thus explored in this study. Pittsburgh Epidemiology of Diabetes Complications (EDC) Study participants (<italic>n</italic> = 658) with childhood-onset T1DM were followed biennially for 18 years. Baseline (1986–1988) mean age and diabetes duration were 28 and 19 years respectively. Stroke incidence and type was determined via survey or physician interview and, when possible, confirmed with medical or autopsy records. During follow-up, 31 (4.7%) strokes occurred (21 ischaemic, 8 haemorrhagic, 2 unclassified) in participants of mean age = 40.2 years (range 23–60). In exploratory multivariable Cox modelling, diabetes duration, systolic blood pressure (SBP), non-high density lipoprotein cholesterol (non-HDLc), white blood cells (WBC), and pulse significantly predicted ischaemic stroke. Adding overt nephropathy (ON) (hazard ratio = 4.4, 95% CI, 1.5–12.4) to the model replaced SBP. Participant survival after stroke was 80.6%, 45.2%, and 9.6% at 1, 5, and 10 years, respectively, and significantly worse after haemorrhagic stroke (<italic>p</italic> = 0.03). These risk factors merit careful evaluation and management to prevent stroke in T1DM, which occurs at least 20 years earlier than in the general population.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Incidence</kwd>
<kwd>predictors</kwd>
<kwd>stroke</kwd>
<kwd>survival</kwd>
<kwd>type 1 diabetes</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1479164112441006" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM) increases the risk of many long-term complications, especially renal and cardiovascular disease. Although many T1DM studies have included stroke as part of a composite cardiovascular endpoint, few have specifically focused on cerebrovascular disease in T1DM.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1479164112441006">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1479164112441006"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1479164112441006"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1479164112441006"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1479164112441006"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1479164112441006">6</xref></sup> Three recent studies have reported that T1DM is associated with an increased risk of stroke compared to nondiabetic persons, especially before 50 years of age.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1479164112441006">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1479164112441006"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1479164112441006">7</xref></sup> Mortality from stroke is increased 3- to 4-fold in T1DM compared to the general population.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1479164112441006">3</xref></sup> Prospective studies examining predictors of stroke in T1DM have shown that, univariately, conventional cardiovascular risk factors (i.e. hypertension and dyslipidaemia), as well as proteinuria, increase stroke risk in this population, but are limited in the number of stroke events with limited follow-up.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1479164112441006">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1479164112441006">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1479164112441006">4</xref></sup> Data are lacking on survival after stroke in T1DM.</p>
<p>Using the Pittsburgh Epidemiology of Diabetes Complications (EDC) cohort with 18 years of follow-up, our objectives were: (a) to determine the incidence of stroke in a large T1DM population; (b) to examine univariate and explore multivariable associations between baseline variables and incident stroke; (c) examine univariate and explore multivariable associations between time-varying variables and incident stroke; (d) to estimate median survival after incident stroke.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1479164112441006" sec-type="methods">
<title>Participants and methods</title>
<sec id="section3-1479164112441006">
<title>Study population</title>
<p>Complete methodology for patient selection, examination, and laboratory testing in the Pittsburgh EDC Study has been described in detail.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1479164112441006">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1479164112441006">9</xref></sup> Briefly, the EDC Study began in 1986–1988 consisting of 658 individuals diagnosed 1950–1980 with childhood-onset T1DM (age &lt; 17 years) and seen at Children’s Hospital of Pittsburgh within one year of diagnosis. Mean age and diabetes duration were 28 and 19 years, respectively, at baseline (1986–1988). Participants have been followed biennially by survey, and by physical examination biennially for the first 10 years and then again at 18 years. Research protocols were approved by the University of Pittsburgh Institutional Review Board and all participants provided written informed consent.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1479164112441006">
<title>Outcome variable</title>
<p>Incident stroke (as well as hospitalisation for any reason) was assessed biennially via survey. Medical/autopsy records were obtained, when possible, to verify stroke occurrence and type and were reviewed by a physician (TJO). Confirmatory medical/autopsy records were obtained for 77% of the events. Stroke was defined as a neurological deficit of acute onset lasting ≥24 hours without other evident cause.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1479164112441006">
<title>Predictor variables</title>
<p>Blood pressure was measured with a random-zero sphygmomanometer after a five-minute rest according to the Hypertension Detection and Follow-up Program protocol.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1479164112441006">10</xref></sup> Hypertension was defined as a blood pressure ≥140/90 mm Hg or antihypertensive medication use. Height and weight were measured to calculate body mass index (BMI). An ever smoker was defined as one who had smoked ≥100 lifetime cigarettes.</p>
<p>Fasting blood samples were taken to measure glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA<sub>1</sub>), lipids, lipoproteins, and serum creatinine. Original HbA<sub>1</sub> values were converted to Diabetes Complications and Control Trial (DCCT)-aligned HbA<sub>1c</sub> for all analyses. Total cholesterol and triglycerides were measured enzymatically, and high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDLc) was determined with a heparin and manganese chloride precipitation technique.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1479164112441006">11</xref></sup> Non-HDLc was the difference between total cholesterol and HDLc levels.</p>
<p>White blood cell (WBC) counts were obtained using a Coulter Counter (model S-plus IV, Beckman-Coulter, Fullerton, CA) and fibrinogen assayed using a biuret colorimetric procedure and a clotting method. Serum and urinary albumin were measured by immunonephelometry,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1479164112441006">12</xref></sup> and creatinine was assayed using an Ectachem 400 Analyzer (Eastman Kodak, Rochester, NY). Renal damage status was based on urinary albumin excretion rates (AER) from two of three timed urine collections and assessed as follows: microalbuminuria, AER = 20–200 μg/min; overt nephropathy (ON), AER &gt; 200 μg/min or, in the absence of urine, a serum creatinine level &gt; 2 mg/dl, renal failure or renal transplantation. Glomerular filtration rate (GFR) was estimated using the Cockcroft-Gault equation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1479164112441006">13</xref></sup></p>
<p>Coronary artery disease (CAD) was defined as CAD death, fatal or nonfatal myocardial infarction and confirmed either by hospital records or by Q-waves on electrocardiogram (Minnesota code 1.1, 1.2), angiographic stenosis ≥50% confirmed by hospital records, revascularisation, EDC-diagnosed angina or ischaemic ECG changes (Minnesota code 1.3, 4.1–4.3, 5.1–5.3, 7.1) which include minor Q-waves, ST depression, T-wave inversion/flattening, or left bundle branch block. Lower extremity arterial disease (LEAD) included claudication (based on the Rose questionnaire), amputation, or ankle brachial index &lt;0.8.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1479164112441006">14</xref></sup></p>
<p>Proliferative retinopathy (PR) was assessed using stereoscopic fundus photographs of fields 1, 2, and 4 with a Zeiss camera, read by the Fundus Photography Reading Center (University of Wisconsin-Madison) and classified based on the modified Airlie House system.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1479164112441006">15</xref></sup> For participants refusing fundus photographs or unable to attend an EDC clinic visit (<italic>n</italic> = 43), PR was defined as receiving laser phototherapy for proliferative diabetic retinopathy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1479164112441006">
<title>Mortality data</title>
<p>Vital status was determined as of 1 January 2010 via participant contact and searches in both the Social Security Death Index and the National Death Index. Each death was confirmed by death certificate. In addition, attempts were made to obtain the following, if appropriate: pertinent medical records, autopsy/coroner’s reports; and interview with next-of-kin regarding the circumstances surrounding the death. Each decedent’s underlying cause of death, and all contributing causes, was determined by a Mortality Classification Committee of at least two physician epidemiologists using all available data based on standardised procedures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1479164112441006">16</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1479164112441006">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Baseline traditional cardiovascular and diabetes-specific risk factors were analysed univariately using the Student’s <italic>t</italic>-test (or Mann-Whitney U-test for non-parametric comparisons) and the <italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup> test (or Fisher’s exact test) by incident stroke status. Due to the small number of events, in addition to comparing ischaemic stroke and no stroke, all incident strokes (ischaemic and haemorrhagic) were combined for multivariable analysis. Significant univariate variables were made available to exploratory multivariable Cox regression models. The proportional hazards assumption was visually assessed, then verified by testing time-varying interaction terms.</p>
<p>Since many variables were significant univariately, exploratory analysis was performed by grouping variables into 3 groups: 1) demographic, 2) complications and 3) clinical, with diabetes duration included in all exploratory models. Independent variables were analysed both at baseline and as time-varying updated means. In the second method, updated means of each continuous variable were calculated as the overall mean of said variable for each participant at every cycle (i.e. the average of all data up to and including the present cycle), until either an event occurred or follow-up ended. Variables found to be significant in exploratory multivariable analysis were combined into Cox regression models with backward elimination. Survival plots by stroke status were based on Kaplan-Meier life-tables. Statistical significance was defined as <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05. All HRs are reported per increase of 1 SD for continuous variables. SPSS 18.0 (IBM, Chicago, IL) was used for survival analyses and SAS 9.2 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC) was used for all other analyses.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section8-1479164112441006" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Four (0.6%) persons suffered a stroke prior to study entry and were excluded. In addition, one individual was lost to follow-up after the initial visit and thus excluded. During a mean (±SD) follow-up of 15.4 (±4.9 years), 31 participants (4.7%) suffered an incident stroke, six of which were fatal. This represents an unadjusted incidence rate of 3.1 (95% CI, 2.0-4.1) strokes/1000 person-years, which did not differ by sex. The incidence of stroke increased with both age and diabetes duration in this T1DM cohort. The mean age at stroke onset was 40.2 years (range 23–60). Ten participants who suffered an incident stroke (32%) had evidence of coronary artery disease prior to the stroke, while three (10%) had a prior transient ischaemic attack (TIA). Stroke type was determined for 29 of the 31 incident strokes: 21 were ischaemic, 8 were haemorrhagic and two could not be classified.</p>
<sec id="section9-1479164112441006">
<title>Baseline predictors of stroke</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1479164112441006">Table 1</xref> presents baseline data based on incident stroke status and type. Persons with incident stroke were significantly older and had a longer diabetes duration at baseline compared to persons with no stroke, but no difference existed by sex or race. Baseline systolic blood pressure (SBP) was significantly higher for those with ischaemic stroke, whereas diastolic blood pressure was significantly higher for those with haemorrhagic stroke. Compared to individuals without stroke, non-HDLc, triglycerides, AER, fibrinogen and WBC count were elevated and estimated GFR (eGFR) was decreased, in those with ischaemic stroke. Compared to those without stroke, those with haemorrhagic stroke had elevated pulse, non-HDLc, triglycerides and AER but their daily insulin dose and hematocrit were decreased, in. HbA<sub>1c</sub> was only univariately significant for haemorrhagic stroke. Of note, individuals with incident stroke (both types) were more likely to have a history of renal damage (microalbuminuria (MA) or overt ON), but only those with ischaemic stroke were more likely to have smoked.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1479164112441006" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Baseline characteristics of Pittsburgh EDC participants by incident stroke status (<italic>n</italic> = 651).<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1479164112441006">a</xref></sup></p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1479164112441006" xlink:href="10.1177_1479164112441006-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">No stroke</th>
<th align="left">Incident ischaemic stroke</th>
<th align="left">Incident haemorrhagic stroke</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><italic>n</italic></td>
<td>622</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age, mean (±SD), yrs</td>
<td>27.3 (±7.8)</td>
<td>31.6 (±8.7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
<td>34.6 (±6.6)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diabetes duration, mean (±SD), yrs</td>
<td>19.0 (±7.4)</td>
<td>24.5 (±7.3)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">***</xref></td>
<td>25.8 (±5.4)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Female, % (n)</td>
<td>49.3 (307)</td>
<td>52.4 (11)</td>
<td>50.0 (4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>African-American, % (n)</td>
<td>2.2 (14)</td>
<td>0.0 (0)</td>
<td>12.5 (1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HbA1c, mean (±SD)</td>
<td>8.7 (±1.5)</td>
<td>9.1 (±1.8)</td>
<td>10.0 (±1.7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Daily insulin dose, mean (±SD), units/kg</td>
<td>0.79 (±0.24)</td>
<td>0.89 (±0.42)</td>
<td>0.58 (±0.12)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Systolic BP, mean (±SD), mm Hg</td>
<td>113.2 (±15.5)</td>
<td>123.6 (±14.1)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
<td>122.5 (±15.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diastolic BP, mean (±SD), mm Hg</td>
<td>72.6 (±10.9)</td>
<td>75.7 (±13.2)</td>
<td>82.6 (±12.8)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BP medication use, % (n)</td>
<td>4.7 (28)</td>
<td>15.0 (3)</td>
<td>25.0 (2)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hypertension, % (n)</td>
<td>15.0 (93)</td>
<td>28.6 (6)</td>
<td>37.5 (3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pulse, mean (±SD), beats/min</td>
<td>78.3 (±9.9)</td>
<td>75.1 (±9.4)</td>
<td>89.3 (±9.9)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Body mass index, mean (±SD), kg/m<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>23.5 (±3.2)</td>
<td>24.4 (±3.5)</td>
<td>22.0 (±2.4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Waist-hip ratio, mean (±SD)</td>
<td>0.82 (±0.07)</td>
<td>0.85 (±0.09)</td>
<td>0.85 (±0.11)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HDL cholesterol, mean (±SD), mg/dL</td>
<td>53.9 (±12.4)</td>
<td>54.4 (±11.8)</td>
<td>50.4 (±11.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Non-HDL cholesterol, mean (±SD), mg/dL</td>
<td>135.4 (±41.7)</td>
<td>171.1 (±53.1)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">***</xref></td>
<td>173.9 (±52.5)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Triglycerides, median (interquartile range), mg/dL</td>
<td>81.0 (60.0–120.0)</td>
<td>121.0 (79.0–186.0)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
<td>201.0 (89.8–266.8)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>eGFR, mean (±SD), ml min<sup>−1</sup> 1.73 m<sup>-2</sup></td>
<td>113.5 (±43.6)</td>
<td>90.1 (±36.9)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
<td>76.3 (±51.7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Albumin excretion rate, median (interquartile range), μg/min</td>
<td>15.2 (7.3–124.4)</td>
<td>358.5 (30.7–1274)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">***</xref></td>
<td>246.3 (91.1–531.2)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Serum albumin, mean (±SD), g/dL</td>
<td>4.63 (±0.65)</td>
<td>4.24 (±0.65)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
<td>4.45 (±0.51)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Serum creatinine, median (interquartile range), mg/dL</td>
<td>0.90 (0.70–1.10)</td>
<td>1.00 (0.80–1.10)</td>
<td>1.10 (0.58–4.08)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fibrinogen, median (interquartile range), mg/dL</td>
<td>270.0 (225–330)</td>
<td>320.0 (278–375)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
<td>340.0 (248–420)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WBC count, mean (±SD), × 10<sup>9</sup>/L</td>
<td>6.55 (±1.88)</td>
<td>8.31 (±2.43)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">***</xref></td>
<td>5.61 (±1.43)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hematocrit, mean (±SD)</td>
<td>44.3 (±4.7)</td>
<td>43.7 (±5.8)</td>
<td>40.6 (±6.9)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prevalent CAD, % (n)</td>
<td>7.2 (45)</td>
<td>14.3 (3)</td>
<td>25.0 (2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prevalent LEAD, % (n)</td>
<td>11.2 (70)</td>
<td>23.8 (5)</td>
<td>25.0 (2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prevalent microalbuminuria, % (n)</td>
<td>45.6 (284)</td>
<td>90.5 (19)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">***</xref></td>
<td>87.5 (7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prevalent overt nephropathy, % (n)</td>
<td>23.6 (147)</td>
<td>66.7 (14)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">***</xref></td>
<td>62.5 (5)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prevalent proliferative retinopathy, % (n)</td>
<td>29.8 (182)</td>
<td>52.4 (11)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
<td>50.0 (4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ever smoker, % (n)</td>
<td>37.1 (225)</td>
<td>66.7 (14)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
<td>37.5 (3)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1479164112441006">
<p>Incident stroke versus no stroke: *p ≤ 0.05; **p ≤ 0.01; ***p ≤ 0.001.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-1479164112441006">
<label>a</label>
<p>Excludes four prevalent cases and two unclassified strokes and one lost-to-follow-up.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-1479164112441006">
<p>BP: blood pressure; CAD: coronary artery disease; EDC: Epidemiology of Diabetes Complications; eGFR: estimated glomerular filtration rate; HDL: high density lipoprotein; LEAD: lower extremity arterial disease; WBC: white blood cell.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Exploratory multivariable analyses of baseline predictors consistently showed diabetes duration and non-HDLc as significant predictors of any stroke, and these effects did not materially change in the four models (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1479164112441006">Table 2</xref>). The effects of SBP and HBA<sub>1c</sub> were only significant in Model 1, which also included eGFR as a measure of renal function. The effect of renal damage, ON, was highly predictive (HR = 4.3), even after accounting for diabetes duration and non-HDLc, and replaced both SBP and HbA<sub>1c</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1479164112441006">Table 2A</xref>, Model 2). Substituting subclinical renal damage, MA, for clinical ON was also predictive of stroke (HR = 5.1, 95% CI, 1.5–18.1), as was the continuous measure, AER (HR = 1.8, 95% CI, 1.2–2.6 per SD increase).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1479164112441006" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Cox regression models for baseline predictors of (A) any stroke and (B) ischaemic stroke in type 1 diabetes.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1479164112441006" xlink:href="10.1177_1479164112441006-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="3">(A) Incident stroke<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">SD</th>
<th align="left">Model 1<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1479164112441006">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">Model 2<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1479164112441006">b</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Diabetes duration</td>
<td>7.508</td>
<td>1.87 (1.21–2.87)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
<td>2.01 (1.33–3.03)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SBP</td>
<td>15.984</td>
<td>1.39 (1.03–1.86)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
<td>Not selected</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Non-HDLc</td>
<td>43.117</td>
<td>1.58 (1.17–2.13)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
<td>1.50 (1.11-2.02)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HbA<sub>1c</sub></td>
<td>1.532</td>
<td>1.46 (1.02–2.09)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
<td>Not selected</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>eGFR</td>
<td>44.274</td>
<td>0.58 (0.36–0.91)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
<td>Not selected</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prevalent ON</td>
<td/>
<td>–</td>
<td>4.33 (1.85–10.1)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AIC (no covariates)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1479164112441006">c</xref></sup></td>
<td/>
<td>325.2 (366.1)</td>
<td>324.1 (366.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><hr/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="3">(B) Incident ischaemic stroke only<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">SD</th>
<th align="left">Model 3<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1479164112441006">d</xref></sup></th>
<th align="left">Model 4<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-1479164112441006">e</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><hr/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diabetes duration</td>
<td>7.508</td>
<td>1.63 (1.00–2.67)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
<td>1.66 (1.02–2.70)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SBP</td>
<td>15.984</td>
<td>1.56 (1.05–2.31)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
<td>Not selected</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Non-HDLc</td>
<td>43.117</td>
<td>1.66 (1.15–2.39)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
<td>1.50 (1.03–2.19)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WBC count</td>
<td>1.917</td>
<td>1.64 (1.14–2.36)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
<td>1.58 (1.08–2.31)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pulse</td>
<td>9.970</td>
<td>0.55 (0.34–0.88)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
<td>0.53 (0.32–0.88)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prevalent ON</td>
<td/>
<td>–</td>
<td>4.37 (1.54–12.4)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1479164112441006">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AIC (no covariates)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1479164112441006">c</xref></sup></td>
<td/>
<td>213.8 (239.2)</td>
<td>209.6 (239.2)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1479164112441006">
<p>Values shown are hazard ratios: 95% CI per 1 SD increase; <italic>p</italic>-values: *<italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.05; **<italic>p</italic>≤ 0.01; ***<italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.001.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-1479164112441006">
<label>a</label>
<p>Model 1 allowed for diabetes duration, SBP, non-HDLc, HbA<sub>1c</sub>, eGFR, ever smoker, and prevalent LEAD.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-1479164112441006">
<label>b</label>
<p>Model 2 allowed for Model 1 variables and prevalent ON.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-1479164112441006">
<label>c</label>
<p>AIC for models 1 and 2, <italic>n</italic> = 642 with 31 events, and for models 3 and 4, <italic>n</italic> = 628 with 21 events.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn8-1479164112441006">
<label>d</label>
<p>Model 3 allowed for diabetes duration, SBP, non-HDLc, WBC, pulse, eGFR, and ever smoker.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn9-1479164112441006">
<label>e</label>
<p>Model 4 allowed for Model 3 variables and prevalent ON.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn10-1479164112441006">
<p>AIC: Akaike’s Information Criterion; CAD: coronary artery disease; eGFR: glomerular filtration rate; LEAD: lower extremity arterial disease; HDLc: high density lipoprotein cholesterol; ON: overt nephropathy; SBP: systolic blood pressure; SD: standard deviation; WBC: white blood cell.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Consistent baseline predictors of ischaemic stroke included diabetes duration, SBP, non-HDLc, WBC and pulse (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1479164112441006">Table 2B</xref>). Unlike the overall stroke models in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1479164112441006">Table 2A</xref>, when ON was included (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1479164112441006">Table 2B</xref>, Model 4), these other baseline predictors remained significant, except for SBP. Despite the small numbers, multivariable analysis revealed that the strongest baseline predictors of haemorrhagic stroke were diabetes duration (HR = 3.5, 95% CI, 1.6–7.6), HbA<sub>1c</sub> (HR = 2.5, 95% CI, 1.4–4.5) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) (HR = 2.0, 95% CI, 1.2–3.5).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1479164112441006">
<title>Time-varying updated-means</title>
<p>Exploratory models using time-varying updated-means for all continuous variables were quite similar to the baseline models above. Predictors of incident stroke included longer diabetes duration (HR = 1.57), higher SBP (HR = 1.38), higher non-HDLc (HR = 1.67), higher HbA<sub>1c</sub> (HR = 1.26) and lower eGFR (HR = 0.50) (Supplementary Table 1, Model 1). When prevalent ON was added to the model, it was strongly predictive of stroke (HR = 4.54) and replaced both SBP and non-HDLc. Both higher HbA<sub>1c</sub> (HR = 1.26) and lower eGFR (HR = 0.53) remained in the fully-adjusted model (Supplementary Table 1, Model 2).</p>
<p>The major predictors of ischaemic stroke using time-varying updated-means were longer diabetes duration, ever smoker, higher SBP and higher non-HDLc; however, neither diabetes duration nor ever smoker reached statistical significance (<italic>p</italic> = 0.08 for both, Supplementary Table 1, Model 3). When prevalent ON was added, only longer diabetes duration (HR = 1.70) and prevalent ON (HR = 8.22) remained predictive in the final model (Supplementary Table 1, Model 4).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1479164112441006">
<title>Survival after stroke</title>
<p>In this cohort, six (19.4%) incident strokes were fatal. The only significant baseline predictor of fatal incident stroke was HbA<sub>1c</sub> (HR = 2.3, 95% CI, 1.1–4.9); sex, diabetes duration, renal damage, hypertension and dyslipidaemia were not significant (data not shown). In participants with a non-fatal incident stroke (<italic>n</italic> = 25), 40.0% suffered at least one additional stroke over a median follow-up time of 3.9 years (range 0.6–14.9).</p>
<p>As of 1 January 2010, 27 (87.1%) individuals with an incident stroke had died. Overall median survival time after incident stroke was 3.8 years; 5.1 and 1.0 years for ischaemic and haemorrhagic stroke, respectively. The underlying cause of death was as follows: nine (33.3%) died of a stroke, nine (33.3%) died of a myocardial infarction or CAD death, eight (29.6%) died of another diabetes-related cause (e.g. diabetic ketoacidosis, end-stage renal disease, sepsis), and one (3.7%) died of multiple sclerosis. Of note, two individuals with a fatal haemorrhagic stroke had a prior ischaemic stroke.</p>
<p>Survival after incident stroke is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1479164112441006">Figure 1</xref>. Overall, 1-year survival after stroke was 80.6%; 5-year survival was 45.2%; and 10-year survival was 9.6%. Stratification by stroke type, despite limited numbers (haemorrhagic stroke, <italic>n</italic> = 8), showed significant differences in survival, with 1-year survival after ischaemic stroke at 95.2% vs. 50.0% for haemorrhagic stroke (<italic>p</italic> = 0.03). A similar pattern persisted for 5-year survival (52.4% vs. 25.0%, respectively).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1479164112441006" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Survival (Kaplan-Meier) after incident stroke in type 1 diabetes participants of the Pittsburgh EDC Study.</p>
<p>EDC: Epidemiology of Diabetes Complications.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1479164112441006-fig1.tif"/></fig>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section12-1479164112441006" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>We report that stroke incidence in a large childhood-onset T1DM population is 3.0/1000 person-years during follow-up (mean 15.4 years), with no differences seen by sex. More than two-thirds of the incident strokes were ischaemic, consistent with other studies,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1479164112441006">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1479164112441006"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1479164112441006">4</xref></sup> and were usually not preceded by either CAD (32%) or TIA (10%), similar to the pattern seen in the general population. In exploratory analyses, renal damage, both at baseline and during follow-up, was the strongest predictor of overall and ischaemic stroke in T1DM. Survival after stroke was very low, especially for haemorrhagic stroke, consistent with findings that haemorrhagic strokes are often more severe.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1479164112441006">17</xref></sup></p>
<p>Very few reports exist on stroke in T1DM for comparison. The largest study to date, the Diabetes UK Study, of &gt;23,000 individuals with insulin-treated diabetes (diagnosed prior to age 30) examined only fatal strokes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1479164112441006">3</xref></sup> The authors found overall stroke standardised mortality ratios of 3.1 for males and 4.4 for females. However, only 19% of our cohort had a fatal incident stroke, and &gt;66% of those with a non-fatal stroke died of a cause other than stroke, so a study capturing only fatal strokes potentially misses a large segment of affected individuals.</p>
<p>The risk for any stroke in the U.K. General Practitioners Research Database Study was increased 3.7-fold for males and 4.8-fold for females with T1DM compared to matched controls.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1479164112441006">6</xref></sup> In the Nurses’ Health Study, the relative risk for haemorrhagic and ischaemic stroke was 4.5 and 7.9 respectively, compared to non-diabetic women, over 24 years of follow-up.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1479164112441006">5</xref></sup> Our incidence rate (4.7%) for any stroke in the EDC Study is approximately four times higher than that seen in the 20–59 year-old general population in the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) 2005–2008 (1.2%).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1479164112441006">18</xref></sup></p>
<p>Few data exist on predictors of stroke in T1DM. In 2001, Fuller et al. combined data from multiple countries to look at risk factors for stroke (fatal and non-fatal) in T1DM.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1479164112441006">2</xref></sup> They found significant univariate associations between stroke and baseline SBP, ON and ECG abnormalities, although the latter was only significant in men. However, a number of risk factors, including diabetes duration, plasma glucose, serum cholesterol and smoking history, were not predictive. In contrast, diabetes duration was one of the strongest predictors in the present study. A more recent report from the Fremantle Diabetes Study found that the strongest univariate predictor of ischaemic stroke in T1DM was serum HDLc, with diabetes duration and history of antihypertensive medication use also showing predictive value; however, only <italic>five</italic> incident ischaemic strokes occurred in their cohort.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1479164112441006">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>Not surprisingly, we found different predictors for ischaemic versus haemorrhagic stroke. Diabetes duration, which, in childhood-onset diabetes serves as a proxy for age, strongly predicted both types of stroke. Blood pressure was also a significant predictor for both, SBP for ischaemic stroke and DBP for haemorrhagic stroke. Blood pressure has consistently been shown to be a risk factor for stroke both in T1DM<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1479164112441006">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1479164112441006">19</xref></sup> and in the general population.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1479164112441006">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1479164112441006">21</xref></sup> It should be noted that SBP lost significance by adding ON to multivariable models of ischaemic and overall stroke. The interplay between hypertension and derangements in the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS) secondary to chronic kidney disease (CKD) are well known in both diabetes and the population at large,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1479164112441006">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1479164112441006">23</xref></sup> and early and consistent use of RAAS inhibitors (ACE inhibitors and angiotensin II receptor blockers) have been shown to delay and/or prevent CKD in diabetes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1479164112441006">24</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1479164112441006">25</xref></sup> Similarly, increased non-HDLc levels predicted stroke in our population and the timely addition of statin therapy for T1DM patients with dyslipidaemia has shown clear antithrombotic benefit which translates into reduced rates of stroke.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1479164112441006">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1479164112441006">27</xref></sup> WBC, as a marker of inflammation, was also predictive of ischaemic stroke, as has been reported in the general population.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1479164112441006">28</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1479164112441006"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1479164112441006">30</xref></sup> Baseline HbA<sub>1c</sub> was only predictive of haemorrhagic strokes and not ischaemic strokes, in our T1DM cohort. We have shown previously that baseline HbA<sub>1c</sub> is not as predictive of CAD (i.e. ischaemic heart disease) as other insulin resistance-related factors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1479164112441006">31</xref></sup></p>
<p>When strokes occur in T1DM, they appear to have more detrimental effects on overall health and survival than seen in the general population. In fact, our median survival after incident stroke of 3.8 years is nearly half the median survival of seven years after incident stroke in individuals aged 65–74 in the general population.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1479164112441006">20</xref></sup></p>
<p>Our EDC cohort has several strengths for evaluating the predictors of incident stroke and survival after stroke, including its prospective design with biennial examinations prior to stroke, its long-term follow-up to ascertain mortality, and its detailed classification of cause of death by an expert committee, using a standardised protocol to determine the primary and contributing causes of death.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1479164112441006">16</xref></sup> Ascertainment of relevant demographic and clinical variables has allowed us to incorporate these into our analysis to minimise confounding. The longitudinal nature of the data also allows the assessment of the effect of progression from normoalbuminuria to renal disease on mortality. Our renal disease data are quite consistent with those published from the FinnDiane study, thus strengthening the overall validity, particularly given the different socioeconomic and healthcare backgrounds from which both cohorts derive.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1479164112441006">32</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1479164112441006">33</xref></sup></p>
<p>However, this study has its limitations. First, relatively few (<italic>n</italic> = 31) strokes occurred during 18 years of follow-up. While we feel this figure is accurate, we are limited in our analyses to simple univariate and exploratory multivariable Cox modelling. These analyses will hopefully provide direction for future studies in T1DM, but should be validated in other large T1DM cohorts. Also, our cohort is hospital-based, which may limit the generalisability of these results; however, a comparison of the EDC study population with the Allegheny County T1DM registry showed our EDC cohort to be epidemiologically representative of the local T1DM population.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1479164112441006">34</xref></sup> As MRIs were not available to detect subclinical stroke, these data only capture clinical strokes, thus presenting only part of the stroke picture. Also, we relied on biennial surveys and clinical examinations to ascertain stroke events and only 77% of the strokes could be confirmed by medical/autopsy records. Of the seven stroke events that could not be confirmed, four patients were started on anticoagulant therapy after their stated stroke, suggesting that a stroke might have occurred. In addition, we were unable to gather sufficient clinical data (especially hospital records from strokes occurring in the 1980s and 1990s) to adequately explore predictors of survival after stroke. Finally, the EDC population consists of participants with long-standing diabetes. Thus, these findings partially reflect outdated diabetes management and care and may not be generalisable to individuals recently diagnosed with T1DM, whose experience may more closely resemble that of the DCCT intensive therapy cohort.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1479164112441006">35</xref></sup></p>
<p>As with the general population, stroke in T1DM is largely ischaemic and usually not preceded by either a CAD or TIA event. The strongest predictors of stroke in T1DM were diabetes duration and modifiable risk factors, including increased blood pressure (ischaemic and haemorrhagic), dyslipidaemia (ischaemic), poor glycaemic control (haemorrhagic) and ON (ischaemic). Thus, careful diabetes management could minimise or prevent this major complication, which occurs at least 20 years earlier than in the general population.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We are indebted to the EDC Study participants for their efforts in helping to understand the natural history of T1DM. Preliminary data were presented at the 68<sup>th</sup> Annual American Diabetes Association Scientific Sessions in San Francisco, CA in June 2008.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This work was supported by the National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (R01-DK034818 and F30-DK082137 for A.M.S.).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interests</label>
<p>The authors have no relevant conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1479164112441006">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deckert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prognosis of diabetics with diabetes onset before the age of thirty-one. I. Survival, causes of death, and complications</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source> <year>1978</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1479164112441006">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for cardiovascular mortality and morbidity: the WHO Multinational Study of Vascular Disease in Diabetes</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>44</volume>(<supplement>Suppl 2</supplement>): <fpage>S54</fpage>–<lpage>S64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1479164112441006">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laing</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swerdlow</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mortality from cerebrovascular disease in a cohort of 23 000 patients with insulin-treated diabetes</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>418</fpage>–<lpage>421</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1479164112441006">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of first stroke in Type 1 diabetes: The Fremantle Diabetes Study</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>553</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1479164112441006">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Janghorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Willett</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prospective study of type 1 and type 2 diabetes and risk of stroke subtypes: the Nurses’ Health Study</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1730</fpage>–<lpage>1735</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1479164112441006">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Soedamah-Muthu</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mulnier</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>High risk of cardiovascular disease in patients with type 1 diabetes in the U.K.: a cohort study using the general practice research database</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>798</fpage>–<lpage>804</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1479164112441006">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sundquist</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Type 1 diabetes as a risk factor for stroke in men and women aged 15–49: a nationwide study from Sweden</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1261</fpage>–<lpage>1267</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1479164112441006">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dorman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maser</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of complications in IDDM by sex and duration. Pittsburgh Epidemiology of Diabetes Complications Study II</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source> <year>1990</year>; <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1116</fpage>–<lpage>1124</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1479164112441006">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dorman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maser</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Factors associated with avoidance of severe complications after 25 yr of IDDM. Pittsburgh Epidemiology of Diabetes Complications Study I</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source> <year>1990</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>741</fpage>–<lpage>747</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1479164112441006">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>Hypertension Detection and Follow-up Program Cooperative Group</collab>. <article-title>The hypertension detection and follow-up program</article-title>. <source>Prev Med</source> <year>1976</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1479164112441006">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Warnick</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albers</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Heparin-Mn2+ quantitation of high-density-lipoprotein cholesterol: an ultrafiltration procedure for lipemic samples</article-title>. <source>Clin Chem</source> <year>1978</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>900</fpage>–<lpage>904</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1479164112441006">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buffone</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>New approach to evaluation of proteinuric states</article-title>. <source>Clin Chem</source> <year>1977</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>666</fpage>–<lpage>670</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1479164112441006">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cockcroft</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gault</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prediction of creatinine clearance from serum creatinine</article-title>. <source>Nephron</source> <year>1976</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1479164112441006">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erbey</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Glycemia (or, in women, estimated glucose disposal rate) predict lower extremity arterial disease events in type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Metabolism</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1479164112441006">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<source>Early Treatment of Diabetic Retinopathy Study Coordinating Center: Manual of operations</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Maryland School of Medicine</publisher-name>, <year>1980</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1479164112441006">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<article-title>International evaluation of cause-specific mortality and IDDM</article-title>. <collab>Diabetes Epidemiology Research International Mortality Study Group</collab>. <source>Diabetes Care</source> <year>1991</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1479164112441006">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dehlendorff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Haemorrhagic and ischemic strokes compared. Stroke severity, mortality, and risk factors</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>40</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>2068</fpage>–<lpage>2072</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1479164112441006">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Center for Health Statistics</collab>. <article-title>Current National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES), 2005–2008</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/nchs/about/major/nhanes/currentnhanes.htm">www.cdc.gov/nchs/about/major/nhanes/currentnhanes.htm</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 14 July 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1479164112441006">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morrish</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for macrovascular disease in diabetes mellitus: the London follow-up to the WHO Multinational Study of Vascular Disease in Diabetics</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source> <year>1991</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>590</fpage>–<lpage>594</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1479164112441006">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Go</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lloyd-Jones</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Heart disease and stroke statistics, 2011 update: a report from the American Heart Association</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>e18</fpage>–<lpage>e209</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1479164112441006">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sturgeon</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Folsom</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Longstreth</surname><given-names>WT</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for intracerebral haemorrhage in a pooled prospective study</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>2718</fpage>–<lpage>2725</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1479164112441006">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abuissa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Keefe</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The role of renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system-based therapy in diabetes prevention and cardiovascular and renal protection</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Obes Metab</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1157</fpage>–<lpage>1166</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1479164112441006">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fogo</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms of progression of chronic kidney disease</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Nephrol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>2011</fpage>–<lpage>2022</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1479164112441006">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gress</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shahar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hypertension and antihypertensive therapy as risk factors for type 2 diabetes mellitus. Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities Study</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>342</volume>: <fpage>905</fpage>–<lpage>912</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1479164112441006">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zinman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Renal and retinal effects of enalapril and losartan in type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>361</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1479164112441006">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tehrani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mobarrez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Antovic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Atorvastatin has antithrombotic effects in patients with type 1 diabetes and dyslipidemia</article-title>. <source>Thromb Res</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>e225</fpage>–<lpage>e231</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1479164112441006">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of cholesterol-lowering therapy in 18,686 people with diabetes in 14 randomised trials of statins: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>371</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1479164112441006">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Folsom</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosamond</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shahar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prospective study of markers of haemostatic function with risk of ischaemic stroke. The Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) Study Investigators</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>736</fpage>–<lpage>742</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1479164112441006">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gillum</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Makuc</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>White blood cell count and stroke incidence and death. The NHANES I epidemiologic follow-up study</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <year>1994</year>; <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>894</fpage>–<lpage>902</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1479164112441006">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Leukocyte count as a predictor of cardiovascular events and mortality in postmenopausal women: the Women’s Health Initiative Observational Study</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>165</volume>: <fpage>500</fpage>–<lpage>508</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1479164112441006">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erbey</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Insulin resistance-related factors, but not glycemia, predict coronary artery disease in type 1 diabetes: 10-year follow-up data from the Pittsburgh Epidemiology of Diabetes Complications Study</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1374</fpage>–<lpage>1379</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1479164112441006">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Groop</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The presence and severity of chronic kidney disease predicts all-cause mortality in type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>1651</fpage>–<lpage>1658</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1479164112441006">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Secrest</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>In the absence of renal disease, 20 year mortality risk in type 1 diabetes is comparable to that of the general population: a report from the Pittsburgh Epidemiology of Diabetes Complications Study</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>2312</fpage>–<lpage>2319</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1479164112441006">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wagener</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sacks</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>LaPorte</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh study of insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus. Risk for diabetes among relatives of IDDM</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source> <year>1982</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1479164112441006">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zinman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Modern-day clinical course of type 1 diabetes mellitus after 30 years' duration: the diabetes control and complications trial/epidemiology of diabetes interventions and complications and Pittsburgh epidemiology of diabetes complications experience (1983–2005)</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>169</volume>: <fpage>1307</fpage>–<lpage>1316</lpage>.</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>