<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PPE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spppe</journal-id>
<journal-title>Politics, Philosophy &amp; Economics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1470-594X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-3060</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1470594X10387520</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1470594X10387520</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Scarce justice</article-title>
<subtitle>The accuracy, scope, and depth of justice</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Tucker</surname>
<given-names>Aviezer</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1470594X10387520"/>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1470594X10387520"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1470594X10387520">Gvirtzman Memorial Foundation, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1470594X10387520">Aviezer Tucker, Gvirtzman Memorial Foundation, USA Email: <email>avitucker@yahoo.com</email>
</corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1470594X10387520">
<p>
<bold>Aviezer Tucker</bold> is the author of <italic>The Philosophy and Politics of Czech Dissidents from Patocka to Havel</italic> (Pittsburgh University Press, 2000) and <italic>Our Knowledge of the Past: A Philosophy of Historiography</italic> (Cambridge University Press, 2004). He is now writing a book that presents a political theory of post-totalitarianism. He lives in Prague and New York.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>76</fpage>
<lpage>96</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The scarcity of resources required to produce justice is manifested in the relation between the accuracy, depth, and scope of materially possible forms of justice. <italic>Ceteris paribus</italic>, increases in the accuracy of justice must come at the expense of its depth and scope, and vice versa, though they are not linearly proportioned. The accuracy of justice is the degree of agreement between the possible results of attempts to implement a theory or principles of justice and the desired result according to that theory or those principles of justice. The scope of justice measures how broadly the principle or theory of justice is intended to apply. The depth of justice measures the gap between existing social norms and the theory or principles of justice we examine within the specified scope. This three-dimensional model explains public policies, laws, and regulations that increase the scope or depth of justice at the cost of a decrease in its accuracy – rough forms of justice such as measures of transitional justice, affirmative action, mandatory sentencing, simplified tax codes, collective guilt and victimhood, and general amnesties. The scarcity of resources necessary for justice can contract or expand. The normative choice between principles of justice that prefer accuracy and those that favor scope or depth usually corresponds, respectively, with rights-based deontological theories and consequentialist ethics.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>justice</kwd>
<kwd>scarcity</kwd>
<kwd>transitional justice</kwd>
<kwd>consequentialism</kwd>
<kwd>deontology</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1470594X10387520">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>This article studies the material <italic>possibilities</italic> of all normative theories of justice. Most philosophical discussions of justice present, interpret, defend, infer, or criticize particular theories of justice. Most of these discussions have been ideal, from Plato to Rawls and beyond. Ideal principles and systems of justice need not consider whether they or their reasonable approximations are materially <italic>possible</italic> in various social contexts because ideals exist on a different ontological plain. The ideal approach to the philosophical examination of justice has come under increasing criticism recently (for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1470594X10387520">
Farrelly, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1470594X10387520">
Mills, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Ideal schemes of normative justice are not relevant for social reality without examining the possibilities of their material realization. These possibilities are constrained because of the universal scarcity of resources necessary for the actualization of any system of justice. The implementation and administration of justice requires resources: human resources, such as trained and honest judges, law-abiding police, and a competent bureaucracy; material resources, such as buildings, computers, and libraries; and intangible resources, such as time and information. As much as all these resources are necessarily finite, resources for justice are scarce. Since <italic>ought</italic> must imply <italic>can</italic>, if an ideal theory of justice prescribes the impossible, it is irrelevant. Since the kind of normative choices people, institutions, and policies make depends on the range of possibilities available to them, understanding such choices requires familiarity with the range of possibilities.</p>
<p>I argue that the scarcity of resources required to produce justice is manifested in the relation between what I term the <italic>accuracy</italic> and the <italic>depth</italic> and <italic>scope</italic> of materially possible forms of justice. <italic>Ceteris paribus</italic>, increases in the accuracy of justice must come at the expense of its depth or scope (or both) and vice versa, though they are not linearly proportioned (a measure of increase in one dimension does not come at the expense of an equal measure of decrease in other dimensions, and vice versa). Some increases are more ‘expensive’ than others.</p>
<p>Let me introduce the terminology that I will use here: the basic terms ‘accuracy’, ‘scope’, and ‘depth’. The accuracy of justice is the degree of agreement between the possible results of attempts to implement a theory or principles of justice and the desired result according to that theory or those principles of justice. For example, if the principle of justice we examine is that guilty criminals should be convicted and innocents should be acquitted, its accuracy is measured by the margins of error in the legal system we examine: What percentage of verdicts are in error, in terms of culprits who are acquitted and innocents who are convicted? The scope of justice measures how broadly the principle or theory of justice is intended to apply. Should it govern social interactions globally, nationally, locally, or in some section of a population? A universal theory of justice such as utilitarianism may be applied in a single local institution (for example, a university) or in a town, a region, or a country, all presenting different scopes of the same universal theory. It is usually cheaper to apply a theory of justice locally than globally. The depth of justice measures the gap between existing social norms and the theory or principles of justice that we examine within the specified scope (without a specified scope, it is impossible to assess the depth). Usually, the wider the gap is, the more expensive will be the implementation for any agency that attempts to implement and enforce the principles or theory of justice. For example, the right to life as a principle of justice is shallower in Copenhagen than in Iraq’s Karbala because the residents of Copenhagen generally respect each other’s right to life, whereas the residents of Iraq do so to a considerably lesser extent. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1470594X10387520">
Brandt (1992)</xref> discussed the costs of a social transformation from one moral code to another, the cost of teaching and learning a new morality. Over time, these are the costs of making justice shallower in a social unit. Such transformations are usually slow and expensive.</p>
<p>All possible justice must come in three dimensions: scope, depth, and accuracy. Without these three dimensions, principles of justice are disembodied ideas floating in an ephemeral universe devoid of material existence. ‘Justice’ without scope does not apply to anybody. ‘Justice’ without depth is descriptive rather than normative. ‘Justice’ without accuracy is arbitrary. I argue that given the scarcity of resources for justice, <italic>ceteris paribus</italic>, increases in any of these dimensions of justice must come at the expense of decreases in other dimensions. In other words, the implementation of any ideal theory of justice requires compromises regarding its scope, depth, and accuracy. Depending on the scarcity of resources, it is necessary to compromise on how accurately reality should reflect the dictate of theory, on how many people are governed by the principle of justice or on the extent to which it is possible to change conflicting social norms and habits. Since there is give and take between these three dimensions of justice, given the same scarcity of resources and the same theory of justice, there are many <italic>possible</italic> outcomes, depending on whether accuracy is preferred to scope and depth or vice versa. This is true of all theories of justice in all contingent social and historical contexts. These possibilities are the topic of this article.</p>
<p>I use this three-dimensional model to theorize and explain public policies, laws, and regulations that increase the scope or depth of justice at the cost of a decrease in its accuracy, that is, <italic>rough</italic> forms of justice, such as measures of transitional justice, affirmative action, mandatory sentencing, simplified tax codes, collective guilt and victimhood, general amnesty, and laws requiring the publication of the names of sex offenders. I examine how, over time, the scarcity of resources necessary for justice can contract or expand, allowing simultaneous growth or contraction in its depth, scope, and accuracy. Finally, I argue that the normative choice between principles of justice that prefer accuracy and those that favor scope or depth usually corresponds, respectively, with rights-based deontological theories and consequentialist ethics.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1470594X10387520">
<title>Justice and inaccuracy</title>
<p>Systems of justice can never have as much resources as they could use: judges, jurors, and investigators can always use more assistants and investigators, and more physical resources such as better offices, computers, and libraries. They could always use more time to investigate and deliberate. But justice delayed is justice denied, so even if more temporal resources are available, such resources may lead to diminishing and then negative marginal returns.</p>
<p>Any system of justice must be constituted of laws, rules, or regulations, implemented and enforced by institutions and individuals, to avoid partiality and arbitrariness. Similar arguments have been made in support of <italic>rule consequentialism</italic> over <italic>act consequentialism</italic>, in favor of measuring the ethical value of <italic>rules</italic> rather than of <italic>concrete</italic> acts, according to the degree of benefit of their consequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1470594X10387520">
Brandt, 1992</xref>). But the repeated interpretation of universal rules by institutions and people inevitably generates errors. When people are treated as members of classes rather than as individuals, the accuracy of justice, its fit to individual circumstances, suffers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1470594X10387520">
Goodin, 1985</xref>: 142–3; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1470594X10387520">
Schmidtz, 2006</xref>: 19–20).</p>
<p>All rules, whether legal or ethical, must be interpreted by people embedded in institutions. Without interpretation, it is impossible to connect the general rule with concrete reality. However, this creates the possibility of misinterpretation or, more often, inaccurate interpretation. Institutional and individual interpreters may develop biased interpretations influenced by their interests or misinterpret the principles because their hermeneutic skills are limited. Individuals may lack <italic>judicious virtues and skills</italic>. Judicious virtues minimize influences on judgment that may increase the margins of error in the interpretation and application of laws and regulations, for example, emotional reactions such as compassion or anger are judicial vices that may cause a judge to be excessively forgiving or vengeful and insufficiently just. Huff et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1470594X10387520">
1996</xref>: 64) concluded that the most significant reason for the conviction of innocents is police and prosecution overzealousness. Informally, Lord Hailsham defined judicial vice as ‘Judgeitis', as ‘pomposity and self-regard’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1470594X10387520">
Mortimer, 1987</xref>: 13).</p>
<p>The accuracy of justice in a given social domain is the degree of agreement between theory and reality. The repeated application of any theory of justice to real situations has a degree of accuracy. Amalgamated and compared with the theory, deviations from prescribed results comprise margins of error (I use ‘rough’, ‘inaccurate’, and ‘possessing margins of error’ synonymously, as referring to the same phenomena in different linguistic contexts). For example, theories of justice may suggest that fair teachers award grades according to merit or need or virtue or some combination of these. According to a meritocratic principle of justice, a just grading is one in which the grade corresponds with the merit of the exams or papers. But making a decision in borderline cases is prone to error. We may even have heard of <italic>other</italic> teachers who failed to recognize the originality of some students altogether and grossly undervalued their groundbreaking research or overvalued the work of unoriginal students who echoed their own opinions, thus broadening the margins of error. At universities that adhere to a managerial model of government, as in the UK, where the management is appointed rather than elected and is measured by the state according to the percentage of students that graduate, management has a strong incentive to inflate or just falsify grades. For example, managers who are not philosophers can end up regrading Logic exams because students may find them more challenging and have worse marks in them. The resulting marks have little correspondence with merit. This institutional structure, the managerial model of higher education, in which managers have the authority to assign marks, radically increases the roughness of justice in this context to the point of arbitrariness. The adjacent social cost is the devaluation of university degrees as signals bearing information about the merit of their holders (compare <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1470594X10387520">
Tucker, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Even the best legal and judicial systems generate inaccuracies, not just in meting out too light or too severe punishments that do not quite fit the crime, but also in convicting innocent defendants and acquitting guilty criminals. To maintain their popular credibility and legitimacy, judicial institutions, judges, and lawyers tend to deny or suppress the inevitability of errors in the administration of justice, though they know better (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1470594X10387520">
Laudan, 2006</xref>: 45–6). It is difficult to infer and compute the inaccuracies or margins of error in retributive justice, since had cases of error been known as such, they would have been prevented in the first place (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1470594X10387520">
Forst, 2004</xref>: 58). However, Forst (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1470594X10387520">
2004</xref>: 5) extrapolated from research that concluded that since 1976 in the United States 1.3% of death row inmates were wrongly convicted that each year about 10,000 people are wrongly convicted in the U.S. Wrongly convicted is a broader category than the category of innocent people who were convicted, because some of those wrongly convicted may have nevertheless committed the crimes that they were convicted of. For example, a criminal may be wrongly convicted for the crime he committed by means of evidence that the police had planted (as in Orson Welles' movie <italic>Touch of Evil</italic>). But this is just one indicator. Surveys of judges and lawyers estimate erroneous convictions as being between 0.5 percent and 3.0 percent, and erroneous acquittals at about 20 percent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1470594X10387520">
Laudan, 2006</xref>: 70–1). Due process and a system of appeals should increase the accuracy of justice, but cannot eliminate margins of error altogether.</p>
<p>The popular media has exposed cases of judicial error, of innocents who were incarcerated or even executed for crimes they had not committed and criminals who were acquitted or released only to commit the same type of crime again, especially in the case of pedophiles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1470594X10387520">
Filler, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1470594X10387520">
Hindman, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1470594X10387520">
Murr and Sinderband, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1470594X10387520">
Nobles and Schiff, 2000</xref>). Such scandals have led to discussions in the legal professions Criminology and Law, of errors or miscarriages of justice. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1470594X10387520">
Walker &amp; Starmer 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1470594X10387520">
Nobles &amp; Schiff 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1470594X10387520">
Forst 2004</xref>). Hundreds of men who had been convicted of sexual crimes were proved innocent and acquitted following the introduction of DNA fingerprinting (Scheck et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1470594X10387520">
2001</xref>). But even simple justice-enhancing DNA fingerprinting that can acquit men wrongly convicted of sexual crimes is a scarce resource. Hundreds of thousands of prisoners convicted of sexual crimes in the USA would have liked to be tested, but the resources for administering the test were too scarce to allow most of them to do so (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1470594X10387520">
<italic>New York Times</italic>, 2004</xref>). In the United Kingdom, cases of judicial error involving terrorism, such as of the Birmingham Six, acquitted a decade and a half after being convicted as IRA bombers, had a similar effect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1470594X10387520">
Walker, 1999</xref>: 47–9), as did the 2006 campaign by the tabloid press to condemn judges who released sexual offenders who would later offend again. Such judicial errors had adjacent social costs: recidivist criminals who were acquitted became free to repeat their crimes. When innocents are convicted society needs to pay the cost of their incarceration and then when the judicial mistake is discovered and rectified, pay reparations. Perhaps most expensive is the loss of faith in the judicial system. Forst (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1470594X10387520">
2004</xref>: 4) defined errors of justice in terms of costs, as ‘the sum of the costs imposed on the innocent person and his or her dependents and the costs imposed on society for failure to sanction the true offender’. This definition fits retributive justice, to the exclusion of distributive justice, and is consequentialist. It does not consider errors of justice that do not have costs, for example, when an acquitted criminal does not offend again.</p>
<p>The inevitability of error in the practice of retributive justice stems from universal epistemic and economic constraints and scarcities: all judgment is based on beliefs. Most, if not all, such beliefs are probabilistic inferences from evidence, especially testimony. It is rational to base judgments on probable beliefs, for example, beyond reasonable doubt in the case of conviction in retributive justice. Lower probabilities of ‘clear and convincing evidence’ and ‘the preponderance of evidence’ are accepted in civil law and in administering distributive justice, for example, in establishing need in welfare cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1470594X10387520">
Laudan, 2006</xref>). Probable beliefs are not necessarily true. Further evidence may lead to revisions in the distribution of probabilities over competing beliefs. Better explanations of old evidence, such as biased eyewitness accounts or forced confessions, may affect the probabilities of old beliefs. Short of omniscient, people are likely to err sometimes, falling in the gap between probable beliefs and the truth.</p>
<p>Errors may have different distributions. Robert <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1470594X10387520">
Goodin (1985)</xref> and Larry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1470594X10387520">
Laudan (2006)</xref> noted that the direction of the margins of error of justice can be manipulated by the severity of the rules of evidence and the burden of truth. The inevitability of margins of error in any human judgment is one of the strongest arguments against irreversible punishments such as capital punishment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1470594X10387520">
Laudan, 2006</xref>: 60). In civil cases, clear and convincing evidence or even the preponderance of evidence are sufficient. In some cases, when the punishment is particularly light, when the cost of an error for society and the accused is low, such as for engaging in an activity without a license, the burden of proof may lie with the defense.</p>
<p>Goodin has suggested that the degree of shifting in the margins of error of justice in the direction of ‘generosity’ depends on the frequency of errors of conviction and punishment multiplied by their <italic>cost</italic>. The cost of executing an innocent is much higher than fining somebody erroneously for walking a dog without a license, and so the burden of proof and presumption of innocence are lighter in the latter. Goodin concluded that when the economy sours and there are more demands for welfare, the state should become more ‘generous' by increasing the margins of error of distributive justice in the direction of generosity because the social cost of error is higher during economic downturns, when poor people suffer more from denial of welfare. This conclusion is counterintuitive because under conditions of increased scarcity of resources due to reduced taxation revenues (or, these days, from bailing out failed banks and other ‘too big to fail’ firms), bureaucracies tend to shift the margins of error in the opposite direction, screening prospective applicants more carefully to reduce the pressure on increasingly scarce resources. For example, in recent cases of massive and broad-scope restitution and compensation for victims of totalitarianism, bureaucracies have attempted to shift the margins of error from compensating the undeserving to denying the claims of deserving victims (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1470594X10387520">
Elster, 2004</xref>: 183). This shifting of the margins of error results from a scarcity of resources for compensating all deserving victims, let alone all possibly deserving victims. Requiring a more onerous burden of proof of claims for restitution is designed to ensure that only the most clearly deserving cases are rewarded from limited resources.</p>
<p>Goodin recognized, if not quite came to grips with, the scarcity of welfare resources. He considered the social costs of different directions of error, but ignored the social costs of straining scarce resources that may either plunge the economy into greater dire straits by forcing the government to tax or borrow even more or exhaust its scarce resources before all those worthy of any distribution of welfare receive their due. Generosity to some may have to come at the expense of depriving others. Though Goodin concluded correctly that some margins of error are inevitable in any administration of justice, he did not examine the reasons for broader or narrower margins of error (the scarcity of justice) only their direction.</p>
<p>Common law recognizes the roughness (the margins of error) of justice implicitly in the principles of the presumption of innocence, the benefit of the doubt, the assignment of the burden of proof, and the demand for proof beyond reasonable doubt. These principles shift the margins of error (the inaccuracies) in the direction of acquitting the guilty to reduce errors in the direction of convicting the innocent. <italic>Ceteris paribus</italic>, the higher is the standard of proof in retributive justice, the higher will be the ratio of erroneous convictions to erroneous acquittals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1470594X10387520">
DeKay, 1996</xref>: 95; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1470594X10387520">
Laudan, 2006</xref>: 30, 68).</p>
<p>Historically, the presumption of innocence and the burden of proof were introduced to counter the overwhelming power of the state to shift the margins of error in the direction of convicting the innocent at the expense of acquitting the guilty. Legal systems in which the presumption of innocence and the burden of proof are not recognized or widely respected do indeed display a shift in the direction of the margins of error toward convicting the innocent, manifested empirically by a higher ratio of convictions to prosecutions, a lower ratio of appeals to convictions, and lower percentages of overturned convictions on appeal when compared to systems of justice in which these principles are respected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1470594X10387520">
Scruton, 1990</xref>). Presumption of innocence may be interpreted as a countervailing, balancing force to the state, designed to achieve symmetrical margins of error in retributive justice. More recent measures similarly designed to balance the margins of error in criminal justice in favor of the accused are disclosure by the prosecution and public legal assistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1470594X10387520">
Walker, 1999</xref>: 39). Further such measures may tip the balance excessively in favor of acquitting the guilty, for example, the proposed exclusion of confessions as evidence in the United Kingdom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1470594X10387520">
Walker and Starmer, 1999</xref>: 3–30).</p>
<p>Larry Laudan argued recently that it is possible to increase the accuracy of verdicts in the USA by shifting the margins of error from acquitting the guilty to convicting the innocent, by changing the established rules of evidence and proof. He believed that allowing the prosecution as well as the defense to appeal, admitting confessions even if the accused were not informed of their rights, admitting evidence that resulted from illegal acts such as seizure by the police, admitting some types of hearsay, and so on would lead to more accurate criminal justice because all the relevant evidence would be considered by the jury (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1470594X10387520">
Laudan, 2006</xref>: 136–7). I think that such reforms would increase the roughness of administered criminal justice. In the short term, it is very difficult to increase the accuracy of justice without compromising on its other dimensions, scope or depth. The process of administering criminal justice in common law systems is different from that of testing competing scientific theories against evidence, most notably in two aspects. First, trials are conducted in an adversarial system. In criminal cases, the two sides are usually grossly unmatched. Without the rules of evidence limiting the overwhelming power of the state, it could shift, and indeed had been shifting, the direction of the margins of error vastly in the direction of convicting the innocent, thus widening the margins of error. It is rare for any group that advocates a controversial scientific theory to have the full power of the state behind it. When this happened, it resulted in Lysenko’s dominance of Soviet biology and Nazi race ‘theory’ and ‘heroic psychology’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1470594X10387520">
Cocks, 1997</xref>). Reducing the burden of proof and the presumption of innocence would, and indeed did, lead to the judicial parallel of Lysenko’s biology. Second, jurors are not and cannot be as good in evaluating evidence as the scientific community. The scientific community is composed of experts who spend years honing their skills at interpreting evidence. The scientific community has many more members who can examine obscure evidence and make innovative inferences than a jury. It also has unlimited time to replicate experiments, deliberate, and reach optimal results. Since juries work under severe constraints in time, human resources, and expertise, restricting their margins of error requires the assistance of rules and the expertise of judges.</p>
<p>Laudan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1470594X10387520">
2006</xref>: 145) was aware of these objections, but he dismissed them in the name of ‘commonsense’. He stated more than argued that it is implausible that shifting the power in adversarial trials in favor of the state would increase the roughness of justice. He undertook a thought experiment, asking the reader to imagine being ‘an innocent defendant in a criminal trial’ and then to choose between ‘a Preponderance of Evidence standard and a prosecutor’s office on hard financial times or a very high Standard of Proof and a resource-rich prosecutor’s office’. A clear preference for the second settled the issue for Laudan. However, Laudan did not factor into this thought experiment the prior probability of anybody, innocent or guilty, being prosecuted by a poor prosecutor’s office in the first place. During the Middle Ages, for example, weak states hardly brought anybody, innocent or not, to trial. The horrendous and barbaric punishments associated with medieval jurisprudence were the result of the need to create deterrence when the huge majority of crimes were unsolved and unpunished. Laudan’s thought experiment should have started with an innocent comparing the two options <italic>prior to being accused</italic>. The rational computation then would multiply the low prior probability of being prosecuted by a weak state by the likelihood of the conviction of an innocent by a weak state under a lower evidential threshold and compare the result with the prior probability of an innocent being prosecuted by a strong state multiplied by the likelihood of conviction given a strong state and more demanding rules of evidence. From the perspective of an innocent who wishes to avoid conviction (as distinct from the perspective of an innocent citizen who wishes to avoid becoming the victim of crime), I think the first option is clearly preferable because conviction is much less likely.</p>
<p>The present sets of rules of evidence and due process in common law have evolved and accumulated over centuries. If this resulted from an evolutionary process whereby civil societies adapted to the changing powers and threats of the state, common law legal history is evolutionary, spontaneous, and undirected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1470594X10387520">
Hayek, 1982</xref>). Some anachronisms and historical vestiges would accumulate, such as various rituals and costumes. But the evolutionary historical process would also indicate that the accumulated rules are likely to increase the accuracy of justice to near optimum given scarce resources. There would be then a prima facie case for the optimal accuracy of present rules of evidence. Debating these rules requires knowledge of history and comparative politics, not contestable and subjective ‘commonsense’.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1470594X10387520">
<title>The depth and scope of justice</title>
<p>The depth of justice depends on its acceptance within its scope. People comply with a system of justice by a combination of habit, imitation, deference, respect for norms, social solidarity, and legitimacy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1470594X10387520">
Holmes and Sunstein, 1999</xref>: 175). <italic>Shallow</italic> justice relies on such acceptance. <italic>Deep</italic> justice must force compliance by <italic>coercion</italic>. For example, the right to life is shallower when almost all those within its scope accept it and actively assist the state in enforcing it than when people dispute each other’s right to live and share values of fragile honor vindicated by vengeance and sacrificial heroism. Distributive justice expressed by progressive tax laws is much deeper in Russia and Italy than in Sweden or the USA, as measured by rates of avoidance and the social legitimacy of taxation.</p>
<p>When nearly all, but not all, respect the same principles of justice, the few who do not have a free-riding advantage over the rest. Preventing free riding requires coercing and punishing the free riders, otherwise they multiply and the mutual respect of principles of justice that keeps together the fabric of just society weakens to the point of tearing apart. But when principles of justice are too deep, they become impossible:<disp-quote>
<p>the cost of rights enforcement is sometimes prohibitively high because pernicious social norms often cannot be broken without resorting to unconscionable force ... Rights enforcement is dependent both on coercive authority and on social norms, good or bad. It is limited because coercive authority is limited by scarce resources and because, whereas socially beneficial norms can make rights and coercion unnecessary, socially divisive norms can cripple them both or undermine them futile. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1470594X10387520">
Holmes and Sunstein, 1999</xref>: 170)</p>
</disp-quote>Attempts to implement deeper justice in some scopes are subject to diminishing and then negative returns. A government capable of entirely neutralizing the influence of private resources to impose a system of justice it favors would have to be so immensely powerful that nothing could stop it from using this power to benefit its own members at the expense of society and, consequently, increase injustice. For example, in scopes where justice in the allocation of property rights is deep, diminishing returns are manifested in the cost of enforcing such rights – what property owners would need to pay through taxes to the state or as fees to private militias. Negative returns set in when the state or the militias in charge of enforcing a deep distribution of property rights accumulate enough power to use it to accumulate property themselves at the expense of the just owners. Radically deep property-redistribution schemes in the 20th century (such as under communism and nationalism) failed to further the rights of the poor partly because state officials amassed extensive powers to bring about such change and then used them to benefit themselves. Shallower redistributive schemes that did not require much coercion, for example, the privatization of fields by French peasants in the French Revolution, were far more successful (Tucker et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1470594X10387520">
2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Beyond negative returns, there are impossible worlds. ‘Justice’ that is so very deep and of such broad scope that nobody can bring it about is utopian. For example, screening the whole of German society after the Second World War to purge Nazis and their collaborators was too deep and broad to be possible. The Act for Liberation from National Socialism and Militarism of 1946 attempted to denazify German society through a questionnaire that classified Germans according to their degree of complicity with Nazism. Adult Germans were required to provide the relevant information about themselves by honestly filling in the questionnaire so that sanctions from imprisonment to exclusion from public employment could be applied. The scarcity of human resources for the implementation of justice made it impossible to check the veracity of the answers. Unsurprisingly, this administrative process failed. Few were actually excluded from public office and even then only for short durations, for example Martin Heidegger, who then went to teach in Switzerland. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1470594X10387520">
Herz (1982)</xref> speculated that the scope and depth of denazification were so extensive because its designers intended it to fail. Instead of consulting anti-Nazi and non-Nazi locals who would have been able to identify a narrow scope of Nazis with particularly bloody hands, a shallower and narrower scope of justice, they demanded an impossibly deep and broad justice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1470594X10387520">
<title>The ratio of roughness to scope and depth</title>
<p>The scarcity of justice is expressed by the ratio of the accuracy of justice to its scope multiplied by its depth. As I mentioned above, scope is measured by the description of the people to whom the principles of justice in question apply; depth is measured by the gap between the norms and mores of the people within the scope and the norms the principle or theory of justice would demand; and accuracy is measured by the margins of error (roughness) of actual justice in comparison with what the theory stipulates. The degree of accuracy and the scope multiplied by depth are inversely proportional.</p>
<p>These relations may also be described in terms of the <italic>virtues</italic> of theories of justice as they are implemented in the world. These virtues partly resemble Kuhn’s five virtues of scientific theories: accuracy, consistency, scope, simplicity, and fruitfulness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1470594X10387520">
Kuhn, 1977</xref>; compare <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1470594X10387520">
Sarkar, 2007</xref>). In some cases in the history of science, these virtues came at each other’s expense – an increase in the scope of a scientific theory came at the expense of its accuracy and vice versa. The accuracy, scope, and fruitfulness of scientific theories are measured by their relations to the world. Consistency and simplicity are internal virtues. Likewise, the three virtues of theories of justice (accuracy, scope, and depth) also come at each other’s expense. Accuracy and scope are shared virtues of scientific theories and theories of justice. Depth, which reflects required change in the world rather than its description, is uniquely normative; and fruitfulness, the discovery and explanation of new phenomena, is exclusively scientific.</p>
<p>The internal virtues (consistency and simplicity) are shared by scientific theories and theories of justice. <italic>Consistency</italic> is obvious in the case of justice: a good theory of justice does not contain inconsistent rules that imply conflicting normative judgments, or it becomes a ‘tragic’ theory of justice in the Hegelian sense. <italic>Simplicity</italic> correlates positively with scope and negatively with accuracy. As David Schmidtz (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1470594X10387520">
2006</xref>: 24) put it, a simple theory of justice is incomplete or inaccurate, a complex one may be unwieldy. A simple theory of justice can be applied broadly, but would generate more inaccuracies than a more complicated theory. For example, the tax code is one of the tools that governments may attempt to use to realize theories of distributive justice. <italic>Ceteris paribus</italic>, the more complicated is the tax code, the more accurately it will be able to serve a desired distributive outcome (barring unintended consequences), but also the narrower will be its scope because richer or smarter people will take advantage of complex loopholes and poorer or less sophisticated folks who cannot understand a complex code or afford the services of accountants may be disadvantaged. It would also generate social costs in the form of uncollected taxes and the social perception that sophisticated free riding pays off and is unpunished.</p>
<p>A simpler tax code is rougher because it contains fewer categories. But a simple tax code has a broader scope because the wealthy have fewer loopholes and anybody can understand it. The roughest possible fiscal policy, which does away even with progressive taxation, is that of a flat tax that eliminates the incentive for high earners to hide their marginally highest income. A flat tax is particularly popular in weak states whose citizens do not believe in paying taxes and where the choice is between a broad-scope and simple, but rough fiscal justice and a more accurate and complex, but narrow justice, whereby few pay exactly what they should and many circumvent the law (Åslund, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1470594X10387520">2007</xref>: 116–9). A flat tax is enforceable even when human resources such as trained accountants are scarce. It also has the social benefit of encouraging the creation of a law-abiding society with fewer free riders.</p>
<p>The more <italic>complex</italic> are laws and regulations, the more accurate would be their interpretations of theories of justice. Kant proposed one golden rule of justice; Rawls had two principles. Schmidtz’s basic idea is the internalization of otherwise external costs. Applying such general principles accurately to the complexity of life in the form of rules and regulations of action requires complex systems of rules that may specify what is just even in unusual or special circumstances and determine which of many possible interpretations is correct. But complex legal systems have a narrower scope than simpler ones because complex regulations are costlier to implement and easier to circumvent by using loopholes. Complex regulations may be more accurate interpretations of a theory of justice, but if there is a scarcity of intelligent, well-trained, or experienced judges and regulators, they may lead to even more inaccuracies when the implementers cannot understand the regulations. Conversely, a simple law code or constitution would not be able to cover all particular cases, but would be simple enough for all to understand.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1470594X10387520">
<title>Rough justice in practice</title>
<p>Weak states that sense the scarcity of justice most acutely must choose between limiting the scope of justice and accepting rough forms of justice. Holmes and Sunstein have suggested that states often limit the scope of justice by enforcing ‘universal’ rights selectively, that is, enforcing them only when they are not too expensive (too ‘deep’ in my terminology) and neglecting them when costly (deep) because ‘enforcement is expensive, especially uniform and fair enforcement ... Rights are familiarly described as inviolable, peremptory, and conclusive. But these are plainly rhetorical flourishes. Nothing that costs money can be an absolute’ (1999: 43, 97). Laudan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1470594X10387520">
2006</xref>: 58–9) has suggested that the high standards of accuracy that are required in capital punishment cases in the USA make the process so expensive that it is about 24 times more expensive to execute someone than to lock them up for life without parole. He has suggested that this may partly explain why only one in 250 murders in the USA results in capital punishment: since the process is so expensive, the state compromises on scope in favor of a high degree of accuracy. Ackerman (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1470594X10387520">
1992</xref>: 74–7) has noted that, because of scarcity, broad-scope corrective justice is impossible after totalitarianism – the prosecution and judges are not cooperative and new democratic governments cannot create an alternative judiciary overnight.</p>
<p>Conversely, it is possible to increase the <italic>scope</italic> of justice by decreasing its <italic>accuracy</italic>. More justice for the many would be achieved at the expense of some injustice for the few. In post-totalitarian societies, the scarcity of resources for the administration of justice implies that the rule of law as conceived in established democracies is beyond their means. Weak, post-totalitarian, democratically elected governments cannot rely on the judicial and executive branches of government to observe the rule of law and implement and enforce their laws because the executive and the judiciary inherited from the pre-democratic regime are at worst disloyal and at best incompetent, while civil society still exists in a fairy rudimentary form. Following years of oppression and social atomization, and consequently the inculcation of a culture of opportunistic free riding, many aspects of justice remain ‘deep’ for a generation or two after the end of totalitarianism. Ackerman (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1470594X10387520">1992</xref>: 72) aptly characterized post-totalitarian governments as having ‘high moral capital, [and] low bureaucratic capacity’.</p>
<p>Under such conditions of extreme scarcity of justice, rough forms of justice replace judicial with bureaucratic decision-making, and bureaucrats with computer programs. Usually, trained and experienced professionals such as judges are able to make more accurate, nuanced, flexible, and sensitive judgments than ad hoc bureaucratic committees. Expert and experienced humans are better able to interpret theories and rules of justice accurately than contemporary software programs based on simple algorithms. However, when there are few law-abiding, honest, and competent judges and corruption is rife, governments may prefer rough, but broad-scope justice. ‘A few crude, bureaucratically feasible reforms will do more justice, and prove less divisive, than a quixotic quest after the mirage of corrective justice’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1470594X10387520">Ackerman, 1992</xref>: 73). Software programs cannot take bribes to issue construction permits or business licenses or to pass an entrance exam to a university. Software programs are rough because, beyond simple cases, competent and honest humans would have produced more accurate justice, at least at current levels of technology.</p>
<p>When the scope of justice is particularly broad, even mature and productive legal systems that can administer the rule of law within a narrower scope are forced to resort to measures of rough justice. For example, following the end of the cold war, a flurry of new demands for restitution and reparations relating to victims of the Second World War surfaced during the 1990s. East European victims were no longer denied their claims because they lived in communist countries and the USA ceased having a geopolitical interest in acquiring the friendship of Germany, Austria, and Switzerland by ignoring claims against their governments and companies. Consequently, millions of new claims by former slave and forced laborers and by the owners of and heirs to identifiable property such as bank accounts, insurance policies, real estate, and works of art were made. Subsequently, rough, but broad-scope justice had to be administered. As Stuart Eizenstat, who negotiated these forms of rough justice, concluded:<disp-quote>
<p>We developed novel concepts that may have applicability in future mass violations of human rights, like ‘rough justice’ to pay mass numbers of victims, rather than the individualized justice that courts provide; acceptance of loose standards of proof, given the decades that have passed; and the creation of administrative remedies, like the German Fund for Remembrance, Reconciliation and the Future, the Austrian Fund for Reconciliation, Peace and Cooperation, and the French rough justice fund. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1470594X10387520">
Eizenstat, 2004</xref>: 353)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>A particularly rough form of justice is collective justice. Collective justice distributes rights or duties and benefits or sanctions to a <italic>class</italic> of people who share a property irrespective of their other particular characteristics and circumstances, thereby saving on the costs of individual adjudications and offering a broad scope of rough justice. The first legally defined and implemented case of collective guilt was in the Nuremberg trials. Scarce human resources and the paucity of evidence after the Second World War led to the designation of certain organizations, such as the SS and the Gestapo, as criminal organizations. Membership of these organizations was designated as punishable, irrespective of the actions individual members may or may not have committed. Post-communist lustration was likewise an attempt to increase the scope of justice at the expense of its accuracy. It designated certain categories of former employees of the communist secret services as a class that should be excluded from employment in the higher echelons of the civil service and the government. New post-communist governments had no resources to conduct mass trials of officers of the secret police. They could manage only a few trials in front of the few competent non-communist judges available. Instead, a rough, but affordable measure appeared to be the exclusion from positions of political power of all officers of the former secret police, irrespective of what they may or may not have perpetrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1470594X10387520">
David, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1470594X10387520">
Tucker, 2006</xref>). Some lustration measures of varying scope were enacted in most Central and Eastern European post-totalitarian countries. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1470594X10387520">
Kaminski and Nalepa (2006)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1470594X10387520">
Nalepa (2008)</xref> discuss lustration in similar terms to roughness. They suggest that false acquittals and convictions are better criteria for evaluating ‘transitional justice’ than conformity with the rule of law. Nalepa considers which bureaucratic procedures could increase <italic>accuracy</italic> (decrease the margins of error of lustrations) given an extreme scarcity of information and rule of law.</p>
<p>Lustration resembles mandatory sentencing in its roughness and its attempt to circumvent the judiciary. Democratic legislatures enact mandatory sentencing to prevent judges from meting out sentences that the legislature considers too lenient. Mandatory sentencing is rough because it does not allow judges to use their knowledge of the unique circumstances of each case to fit punishment accurately to the crime. For example, according to the US ‘three strikes' law against drug offenders, soft drug users who have what is considered a commercial quantity of soft drugs (which may be a small amount they sell to a few others in order to pay for their expensive addiction), like drug barons, are sentenced for life on their third conviction. Political lobbies attempt to use mandatory sentencing as a blunt and rough measure to force their vision of justice through against what they perceive as judicial resistance. For example, some feminists and liberals demanded mandatory sentencing for some sex offenders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1470594X10387520">
Kelly, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1470594X10387520">
Rendell, 2006</xref>), while some conservatives advocated mandatory capital punishment for all kinds of murder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1470594X10387520">
O’Sullivan, 1992</xref>) and for drug dealers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1470594X10387520">
De Lama, 1988</xref>), as is already the case in Singapore and other Asian countries.</p>
<p>Rough collective corrective justice for the prisoners of totalitarian regimes achieved broad scope through general amnesties. Following totalitarian judicial processes that patently violated due process, post-totalitarian retrials for all offenders convicted under totalitarianism would have been way too broad and deep to be possible. A rough measure of post-totalitarian justice is to simply issue a general amnesty. In a general amnesty, all prisoners are released and rehabilitated, whether political prisoners, opponents of the regime who were convicted on trumped up nonpolitical charges, innocent citizens who were convicted because they were not granted due process, or convicted criminals who did commit the nonpolitical crimes for which they were convicted. A general amnesty is a blunt, but affordable instrument of rough justice. General amnesties immediately followed the establishment of all the post-totalitarian regimes.</p>
<p>Similar measures of rough justice have been enacted by traditional liberal democracies when facing a scarcity of justice. When the US federal government wished to institute deep and broad-scope racial justice, it could not rely on the cooperation of state officials in the local executive and judicial branches of government, especially in Jim Crow states. Federal laws may demand that institutions of higher education disregard race in their admission policies and that employers have color-blind hiring practices, but such laws would not have been enforced by many local officials. The National Guard could not have enforced such broad and deep justice. Its resources were too scarce for the task. Instead, the US federal government enacted and has been enforcing rough, but broad-scope justice. It has been enforcing affirmative action policies to fix the percentages of students and employees who belong to groups traditionally discriminated against. Rough justice was affordable since measuring percentages of bureaucratically constructed ethnic minorities can be monitored by the government, which can then use the sanction of access to federal funds, grants, and contracts to enforce compliance. This rough justice generates wide margins of error: some people who are admitted or hired do not merit these social goods, whereas others will be denied goods that should have been theirs had admission and hiring been meritocratic. However, this rough instrument allows the implementation of a broad scope of deep justice that otherwise would have been impossible.</p>
<p>Pedophiles have a higher recidivism rate than other serious criminals; prison terms deter or reform them less than they do other criminals. Therefore, prevention after release from prison must play a larger role for pedophiles than for other criminals. This is an issue of justice for children, of protecting their rights, rather than retributive justice against the criminals who have already served their sentence, just as lustration is more a matter of justice for the citizens of post-communist countries, who should not be victimized yet again because their old oppressors have retained positions of power. There is a social cost for having former offenders who are not or even cannot be reformed (politically or sexually) on the loose. Still, the cost of round-the-clock police surveillance of each released pedophile is prohibitive. Instead, a rough justice measure requires released pedophiles to register with their local authorities and that these lists are made available to locals who can then act as enforcers, as in the 1996 Megan’s Law in the USA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1470594X10387520">
Filler, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1470594X10387520">
Hindman, 1997</xref>) or ‘Sarah’s Law’ in the UK. Such measures are rough because despite the higher than average recidivism rate of pedophiles, some may learn during their incarceration to bring their demons under control or become incapable of doing harm in the future, for example, due to the infirmities of old age. However, even this rough measure of justice has a more limited scope than envisioned: in the USA, half of released sex offenders do not register with their local authorities, who do not have sufficient resources to keep track of them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1470594X10387520">
Murr and Sinderbrand, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>Similarly, since post-communist governments did not have the resources to force their judiciaries to enforce lustration, some post-communist governments published or leaked lists of secret police officers, agents, and informants. As in the case of pedophiles, weak state organs passed on enforcement to society. Again as in the case of pedophiles, this is a case of very rough justice because the published lists did not mention how each name came to be on the list, whether the person was an ideological fanatic, a malicious informer, a ruthless careerist, a victim of secret police blackmail, or a person who became an informer under torture. All received the same sanction.</p>
<p>Public policies of rough justice can be found everywhere, though they are more common in more areas of public policy in post-totalitarian societies, where the state and civil society are weak, justice resources are very scarce, and many kinds of justice are deep. ‘Rough justice’ is a theoretically and heuristically more fruitful and useful term for explaining post-totalitarian justice than ‘transitional justice’. It supports Posner and Vermeule’s argument (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1470594X10387520">
2003</xref>) that transitional justice is not different in kind from ordinary justice; rather, such justice occupies a particular end of the spectrum of justice in general. In established democracies, rough justice is usually practiced only in extreme situations, in isolated subsystems of the legal system, whereas in post-totalitarian societies, it is the main and most prominent character of the justice system’s coming to terms with the legacies of totalitarianism.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1470594X10387520">
<title>Increasing the supply of justice</title>
<p>The scarcity of justice is reflected in the relation between its depth, scope, and accuracy. All else being equal, <italic>in the short term</italic>, growth in one must come nonlinearly at the expense of the others. But obviously all things do not remain equal always. Over time, increases or decreases in the supply of resources for the implementation of justice may lead to simultaneous increases or decreases in the accuracy, scope, and depth of justice.</p>
<p>A long-term change in social mores may decrease the depth of justice, and release productive resources for the expansion of the scope or accuracy of justice. The gradual pacification of liberal law-abiding societies and the creation of a broad overlapping consensus on many aspects of justice after the Second World War have made many aspects of justice shallower. For example, the changes US society has undergone since the 1960s, becoming more tolerant and less racist, have allowed some forms of justice to become shallower (compare <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1470594X10387520">
Posner and Vermeule, 2003</xref>). Conversely, governments in societies that have gone through civil strife are faced with the task of actualizing deep forms of justice that had been shallow prior to the outbreak of strife. There is a lower supply of justice in the former Yugoslavia, Rwanda, and Northern Ireland than before the outbreak of civil strife, when members of different groups still respected some of each other’s rights voluntarily.</p>
<p>Productivity affects the supply of justice just as it affects the supply and production of other goods. Many of the measures that states have instituted in the past century to reduce the roughness of retributive justice, without compromising on its scope or depth, would have been impossible earlier. For example, the broad interpretation of due process in the USA by the Warren Supreme Court (1953–69) would have been impossible had there not been enough lawyers and sufficient public resources to grant each defendant the right to counsel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1470594X10387520">
Forst, 2004</xref>: 13–16).</p>
<p>The productivity of justice is affected by the structures and rules of the institutions in charge of administering it and by the qualities of the people who compose those institutions. Over time, it is possible to reform judicial systems, to increase their efficiency and productivity. This requires overcoming bureaucratic resistance to change, training new bureaucrats, and the replacement of inefficient officials with more competent and productive ones, while not decreasing the independence of the judiciary. Professional skills, virtues, and competences such as wisdom, foresight, and rational organization all affect the supply of justice. If incompetent, ignorant, or confused judges who do not observe due process, admit inadmissible evidence, exclude relevant evidence, or forget the proceedings of previous sessions are replaced with competent ones, the supply of justice increases, and vice versa. Radical political revolutions are followed often by appointments, dismissals, purges, and promotions of judges, state bureaucrats, and law school teachers exclusively or chiefly on the basis of political loyalty. Politically reliable, but incompetent administrators of justice decrease the supply of justice, quite apart from the injustices that follow political control of the judicial process.</p>
<p>Under general conditions of growth or decline in the resources available for the implementation of justice, there can sometimes be reinforcing mechanisms between the three dimensions of justice. When the scope of justice expands, other forms of justice may become shallower in populations that were earlier excluded from the scope of justice and therefore distrustful of the justice that emanated from the discriminating political center. Likewise, when justice becomes visibly more accurate, the increase in trust in the judicial system will make justice shallower in general. Alternatively, when justice decreases its scope or is visibly rougher, there can be an increase in its depth in general.</p>
<p>Post-totalitarian states choose rough forms of justice often because they wish to achieve broad-scope justice. Later, following a growth in productivity or the availability of resources for justice, they may be able to afford more accurate justice and address the inaccuracies of the past through corrective justice, for example, by paying reparations to the victims of internment in war. Conversely, after practicing a form of justice that is limited in scope, but accurate, and once the supply of justice increases, society may wish to revisit older cases that were not adjudicated earlier, as was the case, for example, in post-authoritarian countries such as Argentina and Chile.</p>
<p>Justice may be imported or outsourced like economic goods. Occupation authorities and international tribunals may increase the supply of justice. Accurate, deep, post-totalitarian retributive justice is executed chiefly by outsiders: occupation authorities, as in the Nuremberg and Tokyo trials; international tribunals such as those for the former Yugoslavia; and unification authorities in East Germany. Post-totalitarian states can afford such justice only a generation after the end of totalitarianism, once they produce enough professionals who can administer accurate, broad-scope, and deep justice. Mixed tribunals held on domestic soil with foreign participation may be the optimal option to maximize justice in the immediate aftermath of totalitarianism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1470594X10387520">
Snyder and Vinjamuri, 2003/04</xref>: 17–18).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1470594X10387520">
<title>Ethical choice between scope, depth, and accuracy</title>
<p>If the choice between the accuracy, scope, and depth of justice cannot be avoided by increasing the supply of resources that produce justice, principles of justice need to outline criteria for distributing the scarce resources available for justice between these three goals. To be consistent, these meta-principles of justice, too, would be subjected to margins of error. In order to apply to themselves, they will also specify the choice between accuracy and scope and depth itself is accurate, but limited or whether broad and rough.</p>
<p>Generally, when such choices were debated and made, democratic politicians tended to prefer scope at the expense of accuracy, whereas human rights activists and lawyers tended to prefer accuracy to scope. These groups have conflicting professional interests in this context: democratically elected politicians have an interest in satisfying the broadest scope of potential voters; lawyers have individual clients; and human rights activists represent individuals who may not be popular. In a broader philosophical context, these conflicting tendencies reflect what Max Weber and Karl Jaspers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1470594X10387520">
1986</xref>: 418) term ‘the ethics of social responsibility’ versus ‘the ethics of moral conviction’. The ethics of responsibility are consequentialist: they justify means by ends. The ethics of conviction are deontological: they are founded on the duty to respect the rights of others irrespective of the consequences. Ethical consequentialists would compute the likely effects of accuracy versus scope and depth, and, I shall argue, would in many cases prefer scope and depth to accuracy. Kantian deontologists, like human rights absolutists, would give accuracy lexical priority over scope or depth.</p>
<p>Deontology in its currently most popular form, theories of rights (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1470594X10387520">
Dworkin, 1984</xref>)) focuses on the absolute rights of individuals, which should ‘trump’ all other considerations, most notably consequentialist ones. Rough justice can violate the absolute rights of individuals, for example, the absolute right to due process or to be judged individually rather than as a member of a collective entity. Deontological theories of rights would give lexical priority to accuracy over scope and depth because the alternative would knowingly result in the violation of rights that should trump any other moral consideration. Accordingly, deontologists often oppose measures of rough justice such as lustration, denazification, and Megan’s Law.</p>
<p>Consequentialism is not focused on individuals, but on the amalgamated results of actions in a population. Nor does consequentialism recognize moral absolutes such as rights. These properties of consequentialism remove the barriers that prevent deontologists from accepting rough justice. Rough justice offers a broader scope of justice by compromising on its accuracy. When evaluating a measure of rough justice, the consequentialist who wishes to maximize justice would add the degrees of additional justice each member of the broader scope of justice would gain, and then deduce from it the sum of degrees of injustice each member of the class of people likely to fall within the margin of error would incur. If the value is greater than zero, consequentialists would support the measure of rough justice. If less than zero, they would oppose it. If the margins of error of justice include considerably fewer people than those affected by the broader scope and if the injustices they are likely to suffer are not great, the consequentialist computation would support rough justice. For example, if as a measure of rough justice, all former employees of the secret police of a totalitarian state are excluded from participating in politics and occupying high civil service positions, this is a measure of collective rough justice that violates the rights of individuals to due process. But since justice is very scarce in post-totalitarian states, individual trials are impossible. Such a rough measure would enact some retribution against most of the secret policemen who acted against the freedoms and violated the rights of citizens. It would also protect the large majority of the population from the sort of mischief former secret policemen in power are likely to engage in, such as corruption, embezzlement, blackmail, and work in the interest of foreign powers. It would also punish some secret policemen, probably very few, who did not violate civil or human rights, for example, if they spied on the armed forces of foreign countries. If consequentialists subtract the unjust damage done to the few from the justice done to the many, the result is a positive increase in the total justice in society, and therefore the consequentialist would endorse such a measure of rough justice.</p>
<p>The consequentialist computation must also factor in indirect external social costs such as the degree of illegitimacy and loss of confidence in the system of justice that could result from known wide margins of error (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1470594X10387520">
Forst, 2004</xref>: 7). If the margins of error are so wide and so obvious that society loses trust in the justice system and ceases to accept it altogether, rough justice would result in the radical deepening of justice and an overall increase in its scarcity. Loss of confidence in the institutions of justice, a general deepening of justice, may also result from the opposite, from justice that is precise and of a very narrow scope, when a class of people who are patently guilty, such as the leaders and henchmen of a totalitarian regime, keep their spoils and remain beyond the scope of justice. This may lead to much rougher forms of justice when vigilante groups go outside of the distrusted legal and judicial system, for example, in France after the Second World War (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1470594X10387520">
Rousso, 2006</xref>). Another indirect consideration is the social cost of turning a class of criminals who are likely to offend again loose on society because there are insufficient resources to bring them to trial individually.</p>
<p>Consequentialist computations are always mentioned in the rhetorical context of political arguments in favor of rough justice: crime prevention would be served by putting away the guilty, even if few innocents are also swept along. Lustration, denazification, and the exposure of the background of released pedophiles should bar bad people from access to power, resources, or opportunities to repeat their crimes. Better to restitute or privatize properties quickly and roughly than to wait for the creation of regulatory authorities that will eventually allow precise restitution while in the interim the properties are stolen or managed inefficiently. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1470594X10387520">
Posner and Vermeule (2003)</xref> have noted, it is a common mistake to presume that transitional justice is exclusively about the past, that it is <italic>retroactive</italic> or <italic>retrospective</italic> justice. Actually, the legislators who plan and enact transitional justice are concerned more often with the future direction of reform and democratization in their countries. Transitional justice is justified as a means for the achievement of these consequences.</p>
<p>The application of broad-scope, but rough justice is bound to generate injustices that may require expensive corrective justice later, including redress in the form of compensation, restitution, rehabilitation to cover the medical and psychological costs of the error, and the symbolic restoration of dignity (to borrow the categories of corrective justice of the South African Truth and Reconciliation Committee). ‘Criminal justice systems should be judged, <italic>inter alia</italic>, on the number of injustices produced by them in the first place, and, secondly, on their willingness to recognize and correct those mistakes' (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1470594X10387520">
Walker, 1999</xref>: 61).</p>
<p>Deontologists and consequentialists may agree on rough corrective justice designed to correct mass violations of human, civil, or special (for example, property) rights, such as a general amnesty or the rough restitution and compensation after the collapse of totalitarianism. Such rough measures of collective justice do not violate directly anybody’s rights (though there may be indirect social costs to releasing criminals who may reoffend in a general amnesty and compensations to undeserving claimants may be at the expense of other social projects including resources for justice) so deontologists may not object to them, while the above consequentialist computation will support them.</p>
<p>Deontology may have an advantage over consequentialism when the consequentialist computation is impossible as a result of information constraints. If it is impossible to assess the consequences reliably (to assess how many people would be affected by an increase in the roughness of justice and to what extent, and how many people would fall victim to injustice and to what extent), one might as well give up the attempt to compute consequentially, and do the right deontological thing rather than speculate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1470594X10387520">
Elster, 1995</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ackerman</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <source>The Future of the Liberal Revolution</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Åslund</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>How Capitalism was Built: The Transformation of Central and Eastern Europe, Russia, and Central Asia</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brandt</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <source>Morality, Utilitarianism and Rights</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>; <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cocks</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Psychotherapy in the Third Reich: The Göring Institute</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>David</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>From Prague to Baghdad: Lustration systems, their impact and application</article-title>. <source>Government and Opposition: An International Journal of Comparative Politics</source> <volume>41</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>DeKay</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The difference between Blackstone-like error ratios and probabilistic standards of proof</article-title>. <source>Law and Social Inquiry</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>De Lama</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Reagan retools drug offensive: President calls for new panel to map strategy</article-title>. <source>Chicago Tribune</source>, <comment>19 May, p. 1</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dworkin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Rights as trumps</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Waldron</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Theories of Rights</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eizenstat</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Imperfect Justice: Looted Assets, Slave Labor, and the Unfinished Business of World War II</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Public Affairs</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Elster</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>On doing what one can: An argument against post-communist restitution and retribution</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Kritz</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Transitional Justice</source>, <issue>Vol. I</issue>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>US Institute of Peace</publisher-name>, <fpage>566</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Elster</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Closing the Books: Transitional Justice in Historical Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Farrelly</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Justice in ideal theory: A refutation</article-title>. <source>Political Studies</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>844</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Filler</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Making the case for Megan’s Law: A study in legislative rhetoric</article-title>. <source>Indiana Law Review</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Forst</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Errors of Justice: Nature, Sources, and Remedies</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goodin</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Erring on the side of kindness in social welfare policy</article-title>. <source>Policy Studies</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hayek</surname>
<given-names>FA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <source>Law, Legislation, and Liberty</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Herz</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Denazification and related policies</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Herz</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>From Dictatorship to Democracy: Coping with the Legacies of Authoritarianism and Totalitarianism</source>. <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hindman</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Megan’s Law and its progeny: Whom will the courts protect?</article-title> <source>Boston College Law Review</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holmes</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sunstein</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>The Cost of Rights: Why Liberty Depends on Taxes</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Norton</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huff</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rattner</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sagarin</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Convicted But Innocent: Wrongful Conviction and Public Policy</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jaspers</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <source>Karl Jaspers: Basic Philosophical Writings</source>. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Ehrlich</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> (eds). <publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ohio University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kaminski</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nalepa</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Judging transitional justice: A new criterion for evaluating truth revelations procedure</article-title>. <source>Journal of Conflict Resolution</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kelly</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Suspended sentence for rape sends out dangerous message – support group</article-title>. <source>The Irish Times</source>, <comment>14 May, p. 7</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kuhn</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>) <source>The Essential Tension: Selected Studies in Scientific Tradition and Change</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Laudan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Truth, Error, and Criminal Law: An Essay in Legal Epistemology</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mills</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Ideal theory as ideology</article-title>. <source>Hypatia</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mortimer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <source>Character Parts</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murr</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sinderbrand</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Holes in the safety net</article-title>. <source>Newsweek</source> <volume>141</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>40</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nalepa</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>To punish the guilty and protect the innocent: Comparing truth revelation procedures</article-title>. <source>Journal of Theoretical Politics</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">New York Times</collab> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Dawdling over DNA</article-title>. <comment>21 September, p. A26</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nobles</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schiff</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Understanding Miscarriages of Justice: Law, the Media, and the Inevitability of Crisis</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>O’Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Simply killing</article-title>. <source>The National Review</source> <volume>44</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>6</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Posner</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vermeule</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Transitional justice as ordinary justice</article-title>. <source>Harvard Law Review</source> <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>761</fpage>–<lpage>825</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rendell</surname>
<given-names>EG</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Time for legislature to throw book at sex offenders, meth fiends and gun runners</article-title>. <article-title>US Fed News Service Including US State News</article-title>, <comment>11 August</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rousso</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The purge in France: An incomplete story</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Elster</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Retribution and Reparation in the Transition to Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sarkar</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Group Rationality in Scientific Reasoning</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Scheck</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Neufeld</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dwyer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Actual Innocence: When Justice Goes Wrong and How to Make it Right</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Signet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schmidtz</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Elements of Justice</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Scruton</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Totalitarianism and the rule of law</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Paul</surname>
<given-names>EF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Totalitarianism at the Crossroads</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction Books</publisher-name>, <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Snyder</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vinjamuri</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003/04</year>) <article-title>Trials and errors: Principle and pragmatism in strategies of international justice</article-title>. <source>International Security</source> <volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tucker</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Paranoids may be persecuted: Post-totalitarian transitional justice</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Elster</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Retribution and Reparation in the Transition to Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tucker</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Race to the bottom</article-title>. <source>Prague Post</source>, <comment>1 July, p. 4. Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.praguepost.com/opinion/251-race-to-the-bottom.html">http://www.praguepost.com/opinion/251-race-to-the-bottom.html</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tucker</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ruibal</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cahill</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>et</surname>
<given-names>al.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The new politics of property rights</article-title>. <source>Critical Review</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Miscarriages of justice in principle and practice</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Starmer</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Miscarriages of Justice: A Review of Justice in Error</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackstone Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1470594X10387520">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Starmer</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>1999</year>) <source>Miscarriages of Justice: A Review of Justice in Error</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackstone Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>