<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GCT</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spgct</journal-id>
<journal-title>Gifted Child Today</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1076-2175</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1076217512444550</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1076217512444550</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Features</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Talk is Cheap</article-title>
<subtitle>Exploring Alternative Strategies for Counseling Gifted Adolescent Males</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>Meredith Greene</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1076217512444550">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1076217512444550">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1076217512444550"><label>1</label>Annapolis Valley Regional School Board</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1076217512444550"><label>2</label>University of Connecticut</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1076217512444550">Meredith Greene Burton, Annapolis Valley Regional School Board, c/o BRHS, P.O. Box 40, Bridgetown, NS B0S 1C0, Canada email: <email>meredith.greeneburton@staff.ednet.ns.ca</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>35</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>208</fpage>
<lpage>214</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Adolescent gifted males behave, develop, and learn differently than their female peers. While there are many similarities between the genders, the unique socialization processes, typical characteristics, and common experiences of gifted males are important for school counselors and teachers of gifted boys to recognize and understand. Counselors should not rely on their usual talk therapy approaches when working with boys. To better support adolescent gifted males in schools, counselors and teachers may have to use different strategies to engage them in the counseling process so that they may become successful in school and in life.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>school counseling</kwd>
<kwd>gifted</kwd>
<kwd>adolescent males</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<graphic id="img1-1076217512444550" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1076217512444550-img1.tif"/>
<sec id="section1-1076217512444550" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Boys will be boys. We hear it all the time. It serves as an excuse for everything from messy bedrooms to aggressive behaviors. All work and no play makes Jack a dull boy, and Jack consistently underachieves in school. We shrug our shoulders, raise our eyebrows, or smile wryly. Popular sitcoms on television provide countless examples of idolized “bad boys.” It’s a man’s world. Or is it? Do teachers and counselors act on our beliefs that boys are somehow different from girls? Stereotypes and adages aside, and acknowledging that of course every individual is unique, we know that boys share many tendencies, characteristics, traits, preferences, and behaviors related to their gender. However, a National Education Association (NEA) study reported that preschool and elementary school children are taught by 75% more female than male teachers, and men comprised less than 25% of all teachers in U.S. public schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1076217512444550">NEA, 2010</xref>). According to a 2006 <italic>NEA Today</italic> article, the percentage of female teachers has increased in every decade, from 67% in the 1970s and 1980s to 79% in the 2000s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1076217512444550">Kopkowski, 2006</xref>). This predominance of female teachers in public schools led me to reflect on my own counseling practices because I am one of those female teachers.</p>
<p>I have learned much about, and from, gifted males in my 30 years as a teacher, guidance counselor, and district consultant in a public school system. For 10 years, I was the sole school counselor for Grades 9 through 12 and, at the same time, taught an advanced credit of enrichment and independent study to gifted 11th and 12th graders. I am often asked to come to other schools to consult with staff about gifted students. Most of these consultations concern gifted males who were “reluctant learners.” Many were not interested in what school had to offer them and were underachieving academically. While pursuing my doctoral studies, I facilitated seminars for honors students who were fresh out of high school. These gifted males were nearing the end of their teen years but were still trying to figure out how to “grow up gifted.” I discovered that indeed boys will be boys in that there are certain predictable challenges and recurring issues for gifted males throughout their preteen and teen years.</p>
<p>Boys and girls do share many similarities in their development, intellectually, morally, emotionally, socially, and physically, but there are important differences as well. As a subset of the male population, gifted boys share many typical boy traits but may face additional challenges linked to their exceptional abilities and personality traits.</p>
<p>In general, gifted youth and their nongifted age peers are as alike as they are different. As they mature, all youth seek ways to fit in, try to make sense of the world around them, and develop their identity. In the preteen and teen years, peers become very important as socialization kicks into high gear. Gifted youth are typically emotionally and socially hardy. However, some gifted boys do face unique challenges in school, mainly due to their exceptional abilities and early maturation in some areas, often called asynchronous development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1076217512444550">Silverman, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>It is important to acknowledge here that gender is only one of many factors contributing to a person’s unique makeup. Who we are and how we behave are also influenced by internal forces such as our temperament, intelligence, and natural abilities and external forces that include culture and socialization. However, the focus of this article is alternative counseling strategies for adolescent males, and therefore it is important to examine boys’ experiences first. If boys will be boys, then we need to understand both the boy experience and the gifted boy experience before we can create more boy-friendly educational and counseling conditions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1076217512444550">
<title>The Boy Experience</title>
<p>There are many biological and physiological differences between boys and girls, including their anatomy, biochemistry, and brain development and function. For example, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1076217512444550">Gurian (2001)</xref>, females tend to develop verbal functioning earlier, are more attentive to social cues and contexts, rely on hearing, and develop fine motor coordination earlier. Boys tend to develop visual-spatial functioning earlier, explore their environment through touching and handling objects, rely on sight, and lag in fine motor coordination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1076217512444550">Clark, 2008</xref>). Boys are said to have fewer calming hormones than girls and thus are more likely to fidget and act impulsively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1076217512444550">Gurian, 1996</xref>). It seems that boys tend to be action oriented, whereas girls are more relation oriented. These differences are not inherently good or bad and are not political but scientific differences.</p>
<p>Much has been written about how boys make their way in the world, dealing with real and perceived social pressures and expectations. Popular books such as <italic>Real Boys</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1076217512444550">Pollack, 1998</xref>), <italic>Smart Boys</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1076217512444550">Kerr &amp; Cohn, 2001</xref>), and <italic>Guyland</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1076217512444550">Kimmel, 2008</xref>) give detailed explanations of boys’ socialization and learned coping strategies. Pollack’s “Boy Code” of independent stoicism, male pride and toughness, dominance for power, and hiding emotional warmth paints a picture of the “typical male.” Kerr and Cohn describe the Bartleby syndrome in which boys refuse to complete work that they do not prefer to do, leading to academic underachievement. From an early age, boys learn to repress their real emotions and never ask for help. Kimmel’s “Real Guys’ Top Ten List” has one major theme—the only emotion boys can show is anger because any other feeling is a sign of weakness. It is easy to see how a cycle of aggressive behaviors can develop because boys do not tend to turn their anger or upset inward, but instead, turn on other boys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1076217512444550">Gurian, 1996</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1076217512444550">
<title>The Gifted Boy Experience</title>
<p>Gifted children and youth are typically as well adjusted, or more well adjusted, than their peers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1076217512444550">Colangelo, 2002</xref>), but with certain exceptional abilities come certain social or emotional challenges. For gifted boys, the added challenge is to navigate the “The Boy Code” that contradicts much of who they are. Some additional challenges are asynchronous development, supersensitivity, intensity, peer relations (reconciling their love of learning in an anti-intellectual youth culture), and multipotentiality leading to trouble making decisions about careers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1076217512444550">Rysiew, Shore, &amp; Leeb, 1998</xref>).</p>
<p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1076217512444550">Kerr and Cohn (2001)</xref>, the asynchronous development of gifted boys can lead to difficulties. The physical development of many gifted boys lags behind their intellectual prowess. This can prove difficult for gifted boys when athletic prowess is typically so valued among their male peers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1076217512444550">Kerr &amp; Cohn, 2001</xref>). Gifted boys whose emotional or social development is not in sync with their intellect may appear immature. Their characteristic high energy levels can lead them to misbehave more in classrooms. While all boys may be subjected to “The Boy Code” as they grow up, it becomes particularly problematic for gifted boys who may suffer from internal turmoil when they attempt to live by “The Boy Code” while at the same time being full of emotional sensitivity and intellectual intensity. Extreme sensitivity makes peer teasing even worse for the gifted boy as outbursts of tears are not part of “The Boy Code.” Furthermore, intense interests and excitement for learning are often not appreciated by peers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1076217512444550">
<title>Common Issues for Counseling Referral of Adolescent Males</title>
<p>More boys in school are referred for learning disabilities, emotional disturbances, troublemaking/acting out, negative attitude toward school, and academic underachievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1076217512444550">Mead, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1076217512444550">Neu &amp; Weinfeld, 2007</xref>). In my school, some of these referrals came from teachers, others from parents, and some from school administrators dealing with discipline issues. A referral to counseling does not immediately lead to counseling services or support. Many times, the male students who were referred to me did not want to participate in counseling. They would often tell me that they did not need the help, or could handle things on their own. They used expressions like, “I just have to man up and deal with it,” or “Talking about it won’t help.”</p>
<p>In my own experiences as a guidance counselor for middle school and high school students, and as a counseling facilitator for college honors students, I came to understand one of the most insidious emotional difficulties for gifted adolescent males—frustration: frustration from boredom in classes, frustration from not understanding their peers, frustration that the fine motor control of their hands could not carry out the astounding ideas in their heads. Frustration is a complicated emotion. Simply defined by the online Encarta Dictionary, it is a feeling of disappointment, exasperation, or weariness caused by goals being thwarted or desires unsatisfied. These feelings can manifest in many different ways, but I came to recognize signs of “The Boy Code” firmly entrenched in the gifted males I counseled. Disappointment often looked like nonchalance: indifference about school, detachment from peers, disinterest in popular activities, or insouciance about coursework. As a school counselor, most of the gifted teen males referred to me by teachers and parents were academically underachieving. The boys I talked to were chronically bored in their classes, especially in middle school and introductory-level courses. Some of them purposefully underachieved by not completing the work that they deemed unnecessary or not challenging enough. They resented having to “sit and wait” for the rest of the class to catch up. They were offended by certain teachers’ lack of in-depth knowledge on a topic of interest. Sometimes, they sped through their assignment just to get it done, making careless mistakes along the way that lead to less than stellar results. Teachers and parents could not understand why the gifted boys’ grades were so low or why some work was not even submitted. I prefer to view this as selective achievement rather than underachievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1076217512444550">Hébert &amp; Schreiber, 2010</xref>). The gifted males I spoke with knew exactly why they were not achieving. Many were bored by what school had to offer. The feelings of disappointment were often masked by a marked disdain for schoolwork. One gifted boy remarked to me: “I know what everyone wants, but I just can’t make myself do this senseless, mindless work.”</p>
<p>Twice-exceptional students tended to experience the most frustration from feelings of academic inadequacy. They were frequently being asked to produce work that was impossible for them due to their learning challenges. These boys expressed their frustration with the school’s lack of assistive technology to help them put their thoughts on paper. Even more exasperating was that some teachers did not “believe in” the use of assistive technology, seeing it as a crutch rather than a necessary aid. The twice-exceptional students I knew were acutely aware of the discrepancies between what they knew and what they could actually produce on their own. They expressed frustration that their gifts, interests, and strengths were ignored as teachers only paid attention to remediating their deficits. These gifted boys with learning disabilities were infuriated that some teachers of high-level or advanced courses did not welcome them in their classrooms or did not make adjustments to allow them to succeed. They wanted opportunities to be tested orally, use assistive technology (including spell checkers and calculators, depending on their specific challenges), and the chance to pursue advanced studies in their areas of strength.</p>
<p>It is not unusual for boys to show their frustration by becoming aggressive. Many of the exasperated gifted boys I counseled were either class clowns or verbal bullies. Finishing easy work quickly, verbally adept boys begin to entertain themselves and their classmates. They liked puns, used plays on words, pointed out the hilarious in the banal, did witty impressions, or amused their peers with comical anecdotes. I often asked teachers to imagine having a young Jerry Seinfeld or Robin Williams in their classrooms. Gifted comics often start their careers in classrooms! If comedy is not in the blood, this verbal agility can become more aggressive in nature. Wit can easily turn into sarcasm, and humor is lost when the words are condescending. Classroom peers bear the brunt of this disdain, further aggravating tenuous relationships with peers and teachers. Counseling a comedian is more straightforward than dealing with a verbal bully. A counselor can encourage him to perfect his one liners and clever remarks, learning the craft of comedy. He can begin to develop his wisecracks into a legitimate career. Verbal bullies are more complicated. They often think they are being funny, and the problem is that no one but them gets the joke. They appear unfeeling and arrogant. When I could get these bullies to talk to me instead of verbally sparring with me, I discovered that they were often just fed up with having few intellectual peers and took out their frustration on those they viewed as academically weak students. My counseling sessions for this type of gifted student emphasized developing empathy and patience, as well as doses of humility. We talked about considering people’s feelings and learning to exercise patience with deep breathing or counting to 10 in their heads whenever they felt like speaking inappropriately. We discussed how they felt in situations where they were not the smartest or the best so that they might empathize more with their peers. In addition, we explored course options and activities where they could be with intellectual peers or with teachers who would provide more challenging work.</p>
<p>Some of the gifted boys acting out in class were referred to me because of suspected attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD). First of all, boys in general are more likely than girls to be diagnosed with ADHD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1076217512444550">Mead, 2006</xref>). However, gifted boys often demonstrate extremely high activity levels and low impulse control, impatience, and physical restlessness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1076217512444550">Webb et al., 2005</xref>). These behaviors mimic ADHD symptoms. Certain classroom behaviors of gifted boys (poor concentration, low task commitment, challenging teacher’s authority) resemble those of boys with learning disabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1076217512444550">Shaywitz, Morris, &amp; Shaywitz, 2008</xref>). These gifted boys were actually quite capable of sustained attention on things that mattered to them. One such gifted boy was failing his English Language Arts course because he could not sit still during lectures and refused to complete the reports on the required reading. I know that he spent several hours each night writing an original screenplay.</p>
<p>Inappropriate behaviors happened at home as well. I consulted with parents who were at wit’s end because their 6-year-old gifted boy seemed to have severe anger management issues. Apparently, he smashed and destroyed all of their small appliances and electronic devices. Their child did not seem inordinately angry to me and there were no reports from school of such emotional outbursts. I went to the family garage with the boy to see evidence of the damage. He called the garage his lab and showed me his latest effort. As he explained what he was doing, I almost laughed out loud.</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>I’m really curious about how things work and I like to take them apart to see inside. What really bugs me is that I can’t figure out how to get some of them open or how to get some of them back together again. I try to use Dad’s tools but they’re heavy. So, I just smash them (the electronics) to pieces and see what’s what.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>He was frustrated for sure, but not because of any deep-seated emotional angst. Once he was given child-sized tools and a box full of interesting junk to tinker with, his angry outbursts were over.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1076217512444550">
<title>Male-Friendly Counseling Strategies</title>
<p>In my roles as teacher and guidance counselor, I came to realize that I needed to expand my repertoire of instructional and counseling approaches if I wanted to respond to the needs of my male students. In this section, five broad categories of male-friendly counseling strategies will be discussed, including engaging gifted boys in the counseling process, adopting a different counseling style, incorporating popular media, examining course options, and facilitating mentorships and other arrangements outside of school. Many of these strategies would benefit males and females, gifted or otherwise, because good, basic counseling techniques are universal. However, when counseling gifted adolescent males, these are particular techniques to consider. While counseling is the focus of this article, these strategies are also effective for many teaching and learning environments.</p>
<sec id="section6-1076217512444550">
<title>Engaging Boys in the Counseling Process</title>
<p>First, counselors have to get the gifted boys in the door. Look around the work space. Are male images displayed? Will boys feel valued when they look at your wall art and signage? Do you have male-friendly (nonfiction) magazines and books available? Are there various seating arrangements that do not include a desk? Boys are more physical and take up more physical space so giving boys more room to sprawl and move is important (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1076217512444550">Gurian, 1996</xref>). I tried to leave lots of legroom between chairs and tables so boys did not feel as constricted. Are the wall colors the cooler ones that appeal to males, like silver, blue, black, gray, and brown? Counselors may not have the luxury of repainting their office walls, but accents or accessories could be in the male-preferred cool colors. Do you have interesting objects for boys to look at and handle since they prefer to be doing something while talking? These can be as simple as construction toys, desk puzzles, bean bags, Koosh balls, modeling clay, or smooth stones. Counselors are trained to maintain friendly but steady eye contact with their clients, but boys like to keep their hands busy. This does not mean they are not listening. I have bought magnetic words for my filing cabinet, a variety of desk puzzles with interlocking metal pieces, and a small tic-tac-toe board. I could still conduct my counseling session while boys arranged the magnetic words (sometimes with very funny results), took apart the puzzles, or beat me at tic-tac-toe.</p>
<p>Before any real counseling can be done, gifted boys have to buy into the process. Whereas girls tend to quickly engage in deep and lengthy conversations about their feelings, it usually takes boys longer to warm up enough to share feelings, and even then, conversations will be brief. When traditional talking-about-feelings counseling is not their relational style (boys tend to be doers, not feelers), boys may resist the counseling. Typically, males prefer to get to know someone in less formal settings than a 50-min session in an office (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1076217512444550">Good &amp; Brooks, 2005</xref>). This is another reason to avoid sitting behind a desk. Using the games and puzzles mentioned above is another way to let boys ease into the counseling process.</p>
<p>One of the paradoxes of counseling gifted boys is that words matter, yet do not matter. It matters what counselors call their sessions. Boys are more likely to engage in a problem-solving meeting or decision-making consultation than a counseling session. These words imply some control for the boy as well as a focus on a goal-oriented, solution-focused meeting. Boys might not flock to a therapy discussion group but might voluntarily attend a leadership development or coaching workshop. Leadership development and counseling therapy have much in common (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1076217512444550">Shallcross, 2010</xref>). The words school counselors use to name their sessions carry weight. Just as important is the duration of a session. Gifted boys can be very impatient, and boys tend to zone out when faced with too many words (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1076217512444550">Gurian, 2001</xref>). Think in terms of sound bites when talking with gifted boys, using fewer words for maximum effect. Brief sessions are highly effective and in school counseling situations are more feasible. Brief interventions are key approaches for most cognitive and solution-focused therapies. Most gifted students come to school counselors for help with solvable problems, not deep psychological issues. School counselors can see gifted male clients on a regular basis and keep the sessions brief. Teachers and counselors can help boys keep things in perspective and encourage them to talk to us about neutral or happy times, not just difficult ones. This builds rapport and helps the student as well. One of the biggest underlying concepts of most brief interventions is the conversational shift that is necessary. In these approaches, conversation is not problem dominated but solution oriented. The focus is on the construction of a solution, not the deconstruction of the problem. Gifted boys appreciate this action orientation, and they feel that their opinions count, further buying into the counseling process.</p>
<p>A final word on words—Tone is everything. When possible, use humor. Many males see humor as a way of showing affection and bonding with other men (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1076217512444550">Shallcross, 2010</xref>). This does not mean that school counselors have to tell jokes. I always displayed cartoons on my office door and changed them regularly. Calvin and Hobbes cartoons are particularly appropriate. Some students came by my office every day just to read the cartoon. These humorous images provided openers for future conversations. Students’ reactions gave me an idea of who was identifying with the cartoon’s central theme.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1076217512444550">
<title>A Different Helping Style</title>
<p>In counseling, the relationship is everything; without mutual trust and respect, nothing else works. Genuineness is essential. Phonies are spotted quickly, and any therapeutic attempts will be lost. Any counselor should know to build rapport and trust based on a client’s interests, but with boys, it is important not to ask too many questions at first. The relationship will be built gradually. Find out who he is and what he likes. This is not a mere exercise in rapport building. Adolescent males are not likely to sit down and just open up about feelings. Start with their heads using a cognitive-behavior therapy approach. Instead of asking for feelings, ask about thoughts. Attending to their cognitive strengths first will help them understand and manage the emotional side of things later. Rather than “How do you feel when so-and-so teases you?” try something like “What goes through your mind when you’re the target of a taunt?”</p>
<p>Highly developed verbal skills are sometimes equated with giftedness. This is not always the case as many gifted youth and especially boys have exceptional visual-spatial abilities. Boys tend to learn better with movement and pictures, rather than just with words. For this reason, counselors should make use of a variety of media so as not to rely solely on verbal skills (drawings, paintings, photographs, cartoons). Respond to the needs of visual-spatial learners. Use visual presentations and technology when possible, cut down on the verbal-auditory nature of counseling, and adopt the less is more philosophy of speaking (use demonstrations, diagrams, charts, photos, thought webs, graphs, and mind maps). I tried to draw things out on a notepad as I talked with boys, doodling simple graphics to physically show them what I was saying.</p>
<p>Boys like to move more than girls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1076217512444550">Gurian, 1996</xref>) and are more likely to have a personal conversation while engaged in another activity. Doing something active instead of merely sitting for a session will increase the possibility of a longer interaction. Incorporate activities into the counseling session, and get out of the office if possible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1076217512444550">Good &amp; Brooks, 2005</xref>). Boys become more comfortable with a shared activity—have or make a snack together, take a walk, talk about their favorite team, shoot hoops with Nerf balls, or play a game of checkers. Allow them to occupy their hands, and do not insist on eye contact. Let their hands be busy while their minds are wrestling with the issues. With athletic boys, I would let them scrunch up the scrap paper we were using and then shoot for the trash can. A simple but effective strategy is to ask a boy to help with an office task, such as posting something on the bulletin board or changing the seating arrangement. One of the gifted teen boys I saw fairly regularly was struggling with career decisions. I asked him to help me organize my college-prep books and materials, and as we filed we chatted about different career possibilities.</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>“Attending to their cognitive strengths first will help them understand and manage the emotional side of things later.”</p>
</disp-quote>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1076217512444550">
<title>Incorporate Popular Media</title>
<p>To further explore issues in a nonthreatening way, use popular media and technology. Books, music, cartoons, and film clips can evoke personal feelings to examine from a third-person perspective. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1076217512444550">Hébert (2009)</xref> recommends using biographies with gifted boys who may have trouble defining and verbalizing their feelings. His publications provide lists of many appropriate books and movies for gifted boys. When incorporating bibliotherapy techniques, remember that boys tend to prefer nonfiction books about how things work or real events, exciting characters, and plenty of adventure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1076217512444550">Gurian, 1996</xref>). I once tutored gifted teenaged brothers who had just arrived in Canada. They had very limited English but were extremely talented musicians and came with exceptional academic backgrounds. They learned near-perfect English within a year, and we used <italic>Rolling Stone</italic> magazine as our primary resource. For gifted boys who are not avid readers, have them bring in a favorite song to share, not to analyze. Be prepared to listen to some heavy metal, rap, or alternative-rock music. Talk about it together. Find out what he likes about it. At the very least, you are building a stronger relationship even if you are not discussing the problem. Spending time surfing the Internet together is another way to do something while talking. Have the gifted boy show you a few of his favorite websites for learning about his interests. Many adolescent males who are not high achievers in school display amazing gifts and talents outside of school. I think of the gifted adolescent males I knew who spent hours honing their skills outside of school. They designed websites and iPhone apps, produced original comic books, played incredible guitar solos in rock bands, wrote and performed stand-up comedy acts, and did professional skateboarding stunts. Counselors and teachers need to understand that school is not the only place where gifts show up and that academic gifts and talents are not more valuable than any others.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1076217512444550">
<title>Examine Course Options</title>
<p>Looking at options for course selection is especially important for gifted adolescent males who do not excel in reading or writing or who are underachieving. Gifted boys may not have an awareness of their personal learning styles and expression preferences. They may need to research which courses are more suited to their own skills and preferences. Are the courses hands-on, fast paced, less reliant on words and writing? Are there real-life applications, experiments, visual-spatial content, and more use of technology? Which courses have less drill, repetition, and rote memorization, and more problem solving? I have spent many sessions with gifted boys going through course descriptions in the school handbook. As we read the descriptions together, I asked questions like, “Does this type of work appeal to you?” “Can you see yourself being successful in this type of environment?”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1076217512444550">
<title>Mentoring and Other Outside Arrangements</title>
<p>Gifted and talented males are motivated by learning the way things work and the ways professionals work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1076217512444550">Rogers, 2002</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1076217512444550">Olenchak (2002)</xref> believes that a mentoring relationship with a positive adult role model is extremely beneficial for a gifted adolescent male, especially one who is underachieving or discouraged at school. Mentoring and other outside-school arrangements like foreign travel, internships, and service learning opportunities can provide intellectual male role models, hands-on approaches, field trips, and real-life experiences that are important to the self-development of gifted boys who tend to gauge their behavior by external comparison (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1076217512444550">Olenchak, 2002</xref>). One gifted boy in my class wanted to be a sculptor. Finding him a local potter to work with was the start of his sculpting career. Another of my gifted students was determined to build a robotic arm. With very few tools, US$50 from my budget, and a head full of ideas, he and his mentor, a farmer in our community with a large tool shed and a penchant for inventing, built a robotic arm from old VCRs.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1076217512444550" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The male-friendly strategies outlined in this article are not solely for counselor use. Many of these strategies can be used by teachers of gifted boys as well. Attending to gender-related differences is not unfair or unnecessary. Understanding how gifted boys tend to socialize with peers, develop cognitively and metacognitively, and deal with feelings will help counselors and teachers identify difficulties more accurately and provide more appropriate services for these boys in school. By examining their own helping styles, environments, and resources, counselors can begin to make changes so that gifted boys may be more likely to seek out and engage in counseling services. To further enhance the counseling process for gifted boys, counselors can incorporate more male-friendly strategies, such as matching learning style to courses, using popular media, and arranging mentorships. It is up to counselors, teachers, and parents to find ways to develop more inviting attitudes and conditions for gifted adolescent males to get the emotional support they need.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of Interest</label>
<p>The author(s) declare no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the authorship and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Bio</title>
<p>Meredith Greene Burton, PhD, earned her doctorate under Drs. Joseph Renzulli and Sally Reis at the University of Connecticut where she specialized in personal and career counseling of gifted teens. She currently teaches resource and enrichment in a Grade 6-12 school in the Annapolis Valley of Nova Scotia and is an online instructor for UConn’s Master’s of Gifted Education program. She is a member of a provincial gifted education committee and the program chair for the Nova Scotia Summit of Gifted Education and Talent Development.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>No wonder they behave differently</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Gosfield</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Expert approaches to support gifted learners: Professional perspectives, best practices, and positive solutions</source> (pp. <fpage>33</fpage>-<lpage>42</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Minneapolis, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Spirit Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Colangelo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>, <month>fall</month>). <article-title>Counseling gifted and talented students</article-title>. <source>National Research Center/GT Newsletter (#RM02150)</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gifted.uconn.edu/nrcgt/newsletter/fall02/fall022">http://www.gifted.uconn.edu/nrcgt/newsletter/fall02/fall022</ext-link></comment> .html</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Good</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>The new handbook of psychotherapy and counseling with men: A comprehensive guide to settings, problems, and treatment approaches</source> (<edition>rev. ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gurian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>The wonder of boys: What parents, mentors and educators can do to shape boys into exceptional men</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin Putnam</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gurian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Boys and girls learn differently: A guide for teachers and parents</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hébert</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Guiding gifted teenagers to self-understanding through biography</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>VanTassel-Baska</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olenchak</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Social-emotional curriculum for gifted student</source> (pp. <fpage>259</fpage>-<lpage>287</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Waco, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prufrock Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hébert</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>An examination of selective achievement in gifted males</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Education of the Gifted</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>570</fpage>-<lpage>605</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Smart boys: Talent, manhood, and the search for meaning</source>. <publisher-loc>Scottsdale, Arizona</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Great Potential Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kimmel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Guyland: The perilous world where boys become men</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harper Collins</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kopkowski</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>, <month>September</month>). <article-title>Then and now</article-title>. <source>NEA Today</source>, <comment>Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nea.org">http://www.nea.org</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>, <month>June</month>). <source>The evidence suggests otherwise: The truth about boys and girls</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Education Sector</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>National Education Association</collab>. (<year>2010</year>, <month>March</month>). <article-title>Status of the American public school teacher 2005-2006</article-title>. <source>NEA Today</source>. <comment>Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nea.org">http://www.nea.org</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neu</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weinfeld</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Helping boys succeed in school: A practical guide for parents and teachers</source>. <publisher-loc>Waco, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prufrock Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Olenchak</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>, <month>Summer</month>). <article-title>Being a gifted boy: What we have learned</article-title>. <source>Duke Newsletter</source>, <volume>2</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tip.duke.edu/taxonomy/term/941">http://www.tip.duke.edu/taxonomy/term/941</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Real boys: Rescuing our sons from the myths of boyhood</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Henry Holt and Company</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Reforming gifted education</source>. <publisher-loc>Scottsdale, AZ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Great Potential Press Inc</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rysiew</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shore</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leeb</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Multipotentiality, giftedness, and career choices: A review</article-title>. <source>Journal of Counseling &amp; Development</source>, <volume>77</volume>, <fpage>423</fpage>-<lpage>430</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shallcross</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>, <month>August</month>). <article-title>Men welcome here</article-title>. <source>Counseling Today Online</source>, Retrieved from American Counseling Association, <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ct.counseling.org/2010/08/men-welcome-here/">http://ct.counseling.org/2010/08/men-welcome-here/</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shaywitz</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaywitz</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The education of dyslexic children from childhood to young adulthood</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Psychology</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>451</fpage>-<lpage>475</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Asynchronous development</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Neihart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The social and emotional development of gifted children: What do we know?</source> (pp. <fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Waco, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prufrock Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1076217512444550">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amend</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goerss</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beljean</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olenchak</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Misdiagnosis and dual diagnoses of gifted children and adults: ADHD, bipolar, OCD, Asperger’s, depression, and other disorders</source>. <publisher-loc>Scottsdale, AZ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Great Potential Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>