<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HTH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphth</journal-id>
<journal-title>Hand Therapy</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1758-9983</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1758-9991</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1758998313495636</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1758998313495636</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Report</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Orthotic device and exercise regime for flexor pollicis longus tendon repair in cases with possible Linburg–Comstock anomaly</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Barabas</surname><given-names>Anthony</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1758998313495636">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1758998313495636"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>Nola</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1758998313495636">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1758998313495636"><label>1</label>Plastic Surgery Department, Queen Victoria Hospital, East Grinstead, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1758998313495636"><label>2</label>Plastic Surgery Department, Great Ormond Street Hospital, London, UK</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1758998313495636">Anthony Barabas, Plastic Surgery Department, Queen Victoria Hospital, Holtye Rd, East Grinstead, West Sussex, RH19 3DZ, UK. Email: <email>tonybarabas@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>64</fpage>
<lpage>66</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
    <copyright-holder content-type="society">The British Association of Hand Therapists</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The Linburg–Comstock anomaly is a variation on normal anatomy of the flexor pollicis longus of the thumb and the flexors of the index finger. If not recognised this may contribute to complications after a flexor pollicis longus repair. This article looks at a case where the anomaly may have led to re-rupture of the tendon repair and proposes an orthosis and exercise regime to manage this anatomical variant.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Linburg–Comstock anomaly</kwd>
<kwd>flexor pollicis longus tendon</kwd>
<kwd>rupture</kwd>
<kwd>flexor digitorum tendon</kwd>
<kwd>index finger</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>edited-state</meta-name>
<meta-value>corrected-proof</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1758998313495636" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Linburg and Comstock described an anomalous intertendinous connection between the flexor pollicis longus (FPL) and the flexor digitorum profundus (FDP) tendon of the index finger.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1758998313495636">1</xref></sup> This is commonly found at the level of the carpal tunnel or distal forearm and less frequently results from a muscle belly common to the FPL and FDP tendons. Epidemiological studies demonstrate that Linburg–Comstock anomaly is a relatively common occurrence in approximately a third of the population and is more common in women.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1758998313495636">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1758998313495636">2</xref></sup> Linburg and Comstock described a screening test of passively restricting finger flexion while actively flexing the thumb. In the presence of the anomaly this can lead to pain in the distal radial forearm and wrist.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1758998313495636">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>The increased rupture rate of FPL tendon repairs compared to other flexor tendons is attributed to several factors: the relative difficulty of repairing an FPL tendon; the relative avascularity of the FPL tendon in zone 2 and the increased mobility<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1758998313495636">3</xref></sup> and independence of function of the FPL when compared to other digits. Two publications have identified Linburg–Comstock anomaly as a possible contributor to FPL tendon repair rupture due to traction on the tenorraphy with flexion of the index finger.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1758998313495636">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1758998313495636">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>The largest published study of FPL repairs (<italic>n</italic> = 118) demonstrated a slightly increased rupture rate in repairs where the thumb alone was splinted (17% rupture rate), compared with cases where both thumb and fingers were splinted (15% rupture rate), but this was not statistically significant. In this latter group the fingers were strapped back to the dorsal orthotic device at all times, except when the patient was carrying out thumb exercises as the authors recognised that in some patients the thumb flexed when the fingers flexed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1758998313495636">6</xref></sup> Although not mentioned by its eponymous name, the authors appear to have identified an abnormal connection between the index FDP and FPL. This may have been due to either the Linburg–Comstock anomaly or post-surgical or traumatic adhesions. The authors propose that this factor could have contributed to the increased rupture rate in group one.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1758998313495636"><title>Case study</title>
<p>A 42-year-old female patient sustained a laceration to her thumb. She underwent an FPL tendon repair in zone two. A four-strand modified Kessler technique was used with a 4/0 prolene core suture and a 6/0 nylon epitendinous suture. Post-operatively a standard dorsal thumb orthosis was applied, leaving the fingers free.</p>
<p>The therapy protocol was for the thumb to be protected by the orthosis continuously for the initial four weeks with a controlled exercise regime and then for a further two weeks in between exercises. However, on day 6 the patient reported that she could no longer flex at the thumb interphalangeal joint (IPJ) during her exercises. She recounted that, while lifting a heavy object with her free fingers, her thumb had flexed against the orthosis strapping and she was aware of a “giving way” sensation. Re-exploration revealed that passive extension or flexion of the index distal interphalangeal joint produced advancement and retraction of the FPL tendon stump. This demonstrated the presence of an abnormal inter-connection between the FDP of the index and the thumb FPL suggesting a possible Linburg–Comstock anomaly. It was not possible, however, to easily identify at what level this aberrant connection occurred. It did not seem related to the area of trauma and therefore seemed unlikely to be an adhesion. It was not possible to easily divide the anomaly so the FPL tendon was re-repaired in the same manner as detailed previously. Due to the findings at re-operation a modified post-operative orthosis was fashioned with a dorsal hood including the index finger (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1758998313495636">Figure 1</xref>). The modified orthosis held the wrist in neutral and the thumb approximately 30 degrees of abduction. The index finger was held at 25 degrees flexion at the metacarpophalangeal joint and the interphalangeal joints extended.
<fig id="fig1-1758998313495636" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Modified orthosis designed for a patient with Linburg–Comstock anomaly or traumatic/surgical adhesions. Both thumb and index are controlled by dorsal splint hoods.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1758998313495636-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>This modification reduced the risk of additional tension occurring with index finger movement at the FPL repair site during healing. The exercise regimen was modified from the standard one such that the index finger and thumb were mobilised together. Following this re-repair and the use of the modified orthosis, no subsequent complication was recorded.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1758998313495636" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>This case draws attention to the relatively common connection between the thumb and index flexor tendons, known as the Linburg–Comstock anomaly and its possible contribution to the failure of an FPL repair. An abnormal inter-connection whether due to a congenital Linburg–Comstock anomaly or post-trauma or surgical adhesion should be assessed in the pre-, intra- and post-operative phases in all patients presenting with FPL injury.</p>
<p>If the anomaly is identified and it is not possible to easily divide, the orthotic device should include both index and thumb and the exercise regime modified to reduce the risk of repair failure.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back><ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>The authors thank Juliet Trumper, hand therapist Queen Victoria Hospital East Grinstead for her assistance with the case and the fabrication of the orthosis. The patient gave full consent to the publication of this case study and illustration.</p></ack>
<sec>
<title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1758998313495636"><title>Conflict of interest</title>
<p>None declared.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1758998313495636"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linburg</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Comstock</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anomalous tendon slips from the flexor pollicis longus to the flexor digitorum profundus</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg [Am]</source> <year>1979</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1758998313495636"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamitouche</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Baeten</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Linburg–Comstock syndrome. Epidemiologic and anatomic study, clinical applications</article-title>. <source>Chir Main</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1758998313495636"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sirotakova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Early active mobilization of primary repairs of the flexor pollicis longus tendon with two Kessler two-strand core sutures and a strengthened circumfrential suture</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>535</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1758998313495636"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barabás</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Flexor pollicis longus tendon repair in patients with Linburg–Comstock anomaly</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Eur</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1758998313495636"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Calif</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Failure of flexor pollicis longus repair caused by anomalous flexor pollicis longus to index flexor digitorum profundus interconnections: a case report</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>486</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1758998313495636"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sirotakova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Early active mobilization of primary repairs of the flexor pollicis longus tendon</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>647</fpage>–<lpage>653</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>