<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HJB</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphjb</journal-id>
<journal-title>Hispanic Journal of Behavioral Sciences</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0739-9863</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6364</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0739986312473580</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0739986312473580</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Approaches to Learning and Hispanic Children’s Math Scores</article-title>
<subtitle>The Moderating Role of English Proficiency</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Bumgarner</surname><given-names>Erin</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0739986312473580">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0739986312473580">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Brooks-Gunn</surname><given-names>Jeanne</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0739986312473580">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0739986312473580"><label>1</label>The National Center for Children and Families, Teachers College, Columbia University, New York, NY, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0739986312473580">Erin Bumgarner, Massachusetts Healthy Families Evaluation, Tufts University, 177 College Avenue, Medford, MA 02155. Email: <email>erin.bumgarner@tufts.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>35</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>241</fpage>
<lpage>259</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Accumulating evidence suggests that children’s approaches to learning (ATL) at kindergarten entry predict their academic achievement years later. However, the gains associated with ATL may be diminished for Hispanic immigrant children, many of whom are English language learners (ELLs). We tested whether ATL predicted math scores in a sample of first- and second-generation Hispanic immigrants drawn from the Early Childhood Longitudinal Study—Kindergarten cohort. We further tested whether English proficiency moderated this association. Separate models by study wave (kindergarten, first grade, and third grade) were run to examine whether associations among English proficiency, ATL, and math changed over time. Results indicated that ATL, measured at the previous wave, predicted math scores in first and third grade, but not kindergarten. Moreover, in third grade, ATL predicted math only for children who were proficient in English. The implications for Hispanic immigrant children are discussed.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>approaches to learning</kwd>
<kwd>English proficiency</kwd>
<kwd>Hispanic immigrant</kwd>
<kwd>math scores</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>To succeed in an academic setting, young children are expected to demonstrate behaviors and characteristics that facilitate their own and other classmates’ learning. Known collectively as approaches to learning (ATL), these behaviors and characteristics include self-control, persistence, attentiveness, independence, and responsibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0739986312473580">McClelland, Acock, &amp; Morrison, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0739986312473580">McDermott, Leigh, &amp; Perry, 2002</xref>). In a classroom context, children who demonstrate positive ATL are able to follow directions, participate in group activities, and regulate their behavior despite distractions or frustrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0739986312473580">Blair, 2002</xref>). Mounting evidence indicates that positive ATL at kindergarten entry are a strong predictor of future academic success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739986312473580">Duncan et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0739986312473580">Li-Grining, Votruba- Drzal, Maldonado- Carreño, &amp; Haas, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0739986312473580">McClelland et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0739986312473580">Pagani, Fitzpatrick, Archambault, &amp; Janosz, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Most studies documenting this association have used racially/ethnically diverse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739986312473580">Duncan et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0739986312473580">Pagani et al., 2010</xref>) or predominantly White (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0739986312473580">Blair &amp; Razza, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0739986312473580">Matthews, Ponitz, &amp; Morrison, 2009</xref>) samples. To date, no one has tested whether the association between ATL and math achievement applies to Hispanic immigrant children. Hispanic immigrant children lag behind their native-Hispanic peers in academic outcomes in kindergarten and beyond (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0739986312473580">Reardon &amp; Galindo, 2009</xref>). Interestingly, however, Hispanic immigrant children score higher than native-Hispanic immigrant children on ATL skills such as initiative and self-control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0739986312473580">DeFeyter &amp; Winsler, 2009</xref>). In fact, some evidence suggests that there is little or no difference between Hispanic immigrant children and their native-White peers on ATL. In one study, Hispanics as a whole scored lower than Whites as a whole on ATL in kindergarten, but such differences were not visible in the upper two SES quintiles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0739986312473580">Galindo &amp; Fuller, 2010</xref>). In another study, teachers rated Mexican immigrant children as having better ATL scores than their native-White peers with similar socioeconomic backgrounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0739986312473580">Crosnoe, 2006b</xref>).</p>
<p>Taken together, these studies indicate that Hispanic immigrant children score similarly to native-White children on ATL despite having far lower math scores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0739986312473580">Crosnoe, 2006b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0739986312473580">DeFeyter &amp; Winsler, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0739986312473580">Reardon &amp; Galindo, 2009</xref>). This appears to contradict past research demonstrating a robust positive association between ATL and achievement. Thus, questions remain about the generalizability of past findings to Hispanic immigrant children in particular. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0739986312473580">Galindo and Fuller (2010)</xref> identified a positive association between ATL and math in an exclusively Hispanic sample, but they did not distinguish between immigrant and nonimmigrant Hispanics. They also did not examine math after the spring of kindergarten, although ATL has been found to predict later math achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739986312473580">Duncan et al., 2007</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section1-0739986312473580">
<title>English Proficiency and ATL</title>
<p>One reason why the positive association between ATL and math scores may not apply to Hispanic immigrant children is the high proportion of such children who struggle with English proficiency. To date, however, the possibility that English language proficiency moderates the association between ATL and math among Hispanic immigrants has not been tested. There are several lines of research to support this possibility.</p>
<p>First, people are limited in the amount of information they can store in their working memory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0739986312473580">Cowan, 2005</xref>). Children learning a second language must retain a greater amount of information in their working memory than their English-proficient peers because they must simultaneously work to learn new vocabulary, construct multiple meanings of words, and process and communicate mathematical ideas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0739986312473580">Moschkovich, 2007</xref>). Thus, the same lesson, when taught in English, should make more demands on the working memory of an ELL than on a fluent English speaker. As a result, ELLs may reap fewer rewards from learning behaviors such as attentiveness and persistence, particularly if new material exceeds the capacity of their working memory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0739986312473580">Paas, Touvinen, Tabbers, &amp; Van Gerven, 2003</xref>). Otherwise stated, children with limited English proficiency may not profit as much as children with high English proficiency at similar levels of ATL.</p>
<p>In addition, children learning English may confront barriers accessing the types of educational resources that can reinforce the material being attended to at school. From an acculturation perspective, language is understood to be a vehicle for experiencing new cultural activities and integrating into the host society (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0739986312473580">Portes &amp; Schauffler, 1994</xref>). Put differently, language allows children to engage in classroom activities and build relationships with peers and teachers. A child who lacks strong English language skills may find it difficult to establish these relationships, particularly because many teachers have a limited understanding of second language acquisition and have not received adequate training in instructional techniques to serve ELLs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0739986312473580">Karabenick &amp; Noda, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0739986312473580">Walker, Shafer, &amp; Iiams, 2004</xref>). Thus, children who have limited English skills may be less likely to ask questions of peers or discuss lessons with them, thereby limiting opportunities for clarification and insight.</p>
<p>Finally, many ELLs have parents who are also learning English (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0739986312473580">Hernandez, Takanishi, &amp; Marotz, 2009</xref>). While many Hispanic immigrant parents have high educational aspirations for their children, they may struggle to help their children with homework assignments due to their own limited English proficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0739986312473580">Moreno &amp; Lopez, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0739986312473580">Ramirez, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0739986312473580">Zarate, 2007</xref>). This mismatch between parental language and the language of schooling becomes even more salient in later years as the school material becomes increasingly challenging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0739986312473580">Zarate, 2007</xref>). Therefore, children with limited English may not benefit as much from ATL as children with strong English skills because their parents may be less likely to reinforce the material being taught in the classroom.</p>
<p>For all these reasons, children who are not yet proficient in English may have less access than their English-proficient peers to educational resources that can reinforce the content they attend to in the classroom. Thus, further research is needed to determine whether children who are not yet proficient in English benefit less from ATL than children who are proficient.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0739986312473580">
<title>The Present Study</title>
<p>The present study poses two questions. First, we ask whether there is a positive association between ATL and math achievement in an exclusively Hispanic immigrant (first- and second-generation) sample. Second, we ask whether English language proficiency moderates the association between ATL and math scores among Hispanic immigrant children. We include only first- and second-generation Hispanic immigrants because third-generation Hispanic immigrants in our sample were nearly all proficient in English. We hypothesized that ATL would more strongly predict math scores for children who were proficient in English than for their peers who were not proficient. Our hypothesis is based on the expectation that children who are not proficient in English benefit less from ATL because they do not fully process the information that they are attending to due to cognitive overload and/or limited access to educational supports.</p>
<p>This research question is addressed using a large, nationally representative data set, the ECLS-K. Past research on Hispanic children has often been limited in generalizability to particular regions or schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0739986312473580">DeFeyter &amp; Winsler, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0739986312473580">Suárez-Orozco, Rhodes, &amp; Milburn, 2009</xref>), whereas the ECLS-K contains a national sample of Hispanic children. It also collected repeated measures of ATL, English proficiency, and math achievement between kindergarten and third grade, making it particularly well-suited to answer our research questions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0739986312473580" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section4-0739986312473580">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>The ECLS-K is a nationally representative sample of children who entered kindergarten in the fall of 1998, when data collection first occurred. Data were collected again in the spring of kindergarten (1999), the fall and spring of first grade (1999-2000), the spring of third grade (2002), the spring of fifth grade (2004), and the spring of eighth grade (2007). Data were collected from a variety of sources, including children, parents, teachers, and school administrators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0739986312473580">NCES, 2009</xref>). The present study examines data from the spring of kindergarten through the spring of third grade,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0739986312473580">1</xref></sup> although data were extracted from the ECLS-K-8 public use data set, which is the most recent version.</p>
<p>The ECLS-K used a multistage probability sample design, in which counties or groups of counties were the primary sampling units (PSUs), schools or kindergarten programs were the second-stage units, and individual children were the third and final stage units. During the ECLS-K base year, there were 21,409 kindergarten students, representing 1,280 schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0739986312473580">NCES, 2009</xref>). Of these, 3,826 students were Hispanic. Because a majority of third-generation Hispanic immigrant children are already proficient in English, we selected only first- and second-generation immigrant children (<italic>n</italic> = 1,374). First-generation children were defined as children born in a country other than the United States to foreign-born parents. Second-generation children were defined as children born in the United States to foreign-born parents. Children with Individual Education Programs (IEPs) in either first grade or third grade (<italic>n</italic> = 72) were also excluded, as they may demonstrate unique associations between ATL and math scores. Finally, we excluded nine children who did not receive any of the cognitive assessments (either because they spoke a language other than English or Spanish or were disabled). These exclusions resulted in a sample of 1,293 children.</p>
<p>To be eligible for the present analysis, children had to have math score data in the fall and spring of kindergarten, spring of first grade, and spring of third grade. This resulted in the exclusion of 305 (24%) children. Compared to the remaining 988 children, excluded children were less likely to be proficient in English in the spring of first grade, had lower ATL scores in the fall of kindergarten, had mothers who were slightly younger at the time of first birth, and had slightly higher externalizing scores in the fall of kindergarten. However, the application of survey weights that account for both nonresponse and the ECLS-K sampling design allow us to generalize our findings to all Hispanic immigrant children who entered kindergarten in 1998.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0739986312473580">
<title>Measures</title>
<sec id="section6-0739986312473580">
<title>Math</title>
<p>Math scores were measured at the fall of kindergarten, spring of kindergarten, spring of first grade, and spring of third grade. The math test, designed for the ECLS-K, covered number properties and operations; measurement; geometry and spatial sense; data analysis, statistics and probability; and patterns, algebra, and functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0739986312473580">NCES, 2005</xref>). Although the test’s content varied over time, item response theory (IRT) scores yielded a single metric across waves. Children who were not proficient in English were given the math assessment in Spanish.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0739986312473580">
<title>English proficiency</title>
<p>Children from homes where English was not the primary language were administered the Oral Language Development Scale (OLDS) to assess their English language proficiency. The OLDS consisted of three scales drawn from the prekindergarten/kindergarten/first grade version of the CTB/McGraw Hill Language Assessment Scales (PreLAS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0739986312473580">Duncan &amp; DeAvila, 1998</xref>). The OLDS measured both receptive and productive language skills using three subtests: “Simon Says,” “Art Show,” and “Let’s Tell Stories.” These tests measured listening comprehension of simple directions, oral vocabulary, and the child’s natural speech, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0739986312473580">NCES, 2002</xref>). Based on a national norming sample using the PreLAS, a score of 37 or higher on the OLDS was considered by the ECLS-K as indicative of English proficiency. Children who were not proficient were reassessed during subsequent waves. The OLDS was not administered after the spring of first grade because almost all children were proficient by that time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0739986312473580">NCES, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>The present study used OLDS scores from the fall of kindergarten, spring of kindergarten, and spring of first grade. Because many children scored at the upper limit of this instrument, indicating a ceiling effect, we created a binary measure of proficiency. At each wave, children were coded as proficient if they obtained a score of 37 or higher. In addition, children not screened with the OLDS were automatically coded as proficient.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0739986312473580">
<title>Approaches to learning (ATL)</title>
<p>ATL scores were reported by teachers during the fall of kindergarten, spring of kindergarten, and spring of first grade using the Approaches to Learning scale. Teachers rated each child on a 1 to 4 scale (1 = <italic>never</italic> to 4 = <italic>very often</italic>) to describe how often s/he engaged in the following behaviors: keeps belongings organized, shows eagerness to learn new things, works independently, easily adapts to changes in routine, persists in completing tasks, and pays attention well. By third grade, an additional item asked how often the child follows classroom rules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0739986312473580">NCES, 2005</xref>). Split-half reliabilities for the ATL scale were high (.89 in kindergarten-fall, .89 in kindergarten-spring, and .89 in first grade-spring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0739986312473580">NCES, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0739986312473580">2005</xref>). This is the same measure used in previous studies of ATL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0739986312473580">Crosnoe, 2006a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739986312473580">Duncan et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0739986312473580">Galindo &amp; Fuller, 2010</xref>). To facilitate interpretation of the tests for moderation in this study, the score was mean-centered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0739986312473580">Aiken &amp; West, 1991</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0739986312473580">
<title>Control variables</title>
<p>Control variables were selected based on previous literature linking them to ATL and math. These included child’s sex, age (in months), health status (0 = <italic>excellent</italic> to 4 = <italic>poor</italic>), whether the child attended center child care before kindergarten, whether child born prematurely, and mother’s age at first birth, as reported by the mother in the fall of kindergarten. The following variables were created by ECLS-K: whether the mother worked before the child entered kindergarten, whether the parents were married at the time of the child’s birth, the number of siblings the child had at kindergarten entry, and family socioeconomic status. This last measure is a continuous variable (ranging from −4.75 to 2.75) that combines data from the fall and spring of kindergarten. Five measures (family income, mother’s and father’s education, and mother’s and father’s occupational prestige) were standardized and then averaged.</p>
<p>We controlled for prior externalizing behavior because it is associated with both ATL (e.g., teacher ratings of attention; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0739986312473580">Abikoff, Courtney, Pelham, &amp; Koplewicz, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0739986312473580">Stewart, Cummings, &amp; Singer, 1981</xref>) and achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0739986312473580">Hinshaw, 1992</xref>). At each wave, teachers rated how often the child argues, fights, gets angry, acts impulsively, and disturbs ongoing activities (1 = <italic>never</italic> to 4 = <italic>very often</italic>). Items were averaged. Split-half reliabilities for this scale are reported to be high (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0739986312473580">NCES, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0739986312473580">2005</xref>). Finally, controls for geographic characteristics included region (Northeast, South, West, and Midwest) and urbanicity (large city, city fringe/small city, and small town/rural).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0739986312473580">
<title>Missing Data</title>
<p>Rates of missingness on predictor and control variables ranged from 0 to 15%, with most variables missing in fewer than 5% of cases. Based on the assumption that data were missing at random (that is, their missingness could be modeled by observed characteristics; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0739986312473580">Allison, 2009</xref>), we used multiple imputation to create five data sets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0739986312473580">McCartney, Burchinal, &amp; Bub, 2006</xref>). The ICE command in Stata (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0739986312473580">Royston, 2007</xref>) conducts multiple imputation based on a regression switching protocol using chained equations. Although the outcome variables were used in imputation models for other missing variables, they themselves were not imputed, as recommended by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0739986312473580">von Hippel (2007)</xref>. The five data sets were analyzed using the MIM prefix for regression analyses in Stata (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0739986312473580">Royston, 2007</xref>), which combines coefficients and standard errors across imputed data sets.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0739986312473580">
<title>Analytic Strategy</title>
<p>All analyses were conducted using Stata 10.0. We ran regression models to predict ECLS-K math test scores at each of the three waves: spring of kindergarten, spring of first grade, and spring of third grade. The use of separate models for each wave allowed for the possibility that the implications of ATL and English proficiency for math skills varied over time. All models controlled for the child’s math achievement score at the previous wave (fall of kindergarten, spring of kindergarten and spring of first grade, respectively). Thus, the dependent variable in each model captured the change in math score since the previous wave. In each model, ATL and English proficiency were measured as of the previous wave (fall of kindergarten, spring of kindergarten, and spring of first grade, respectively).</p>
<p>At each wave, three hierarchical models were estimated. The first model included the main effect of ATL as well as all covariates listed above, including math from the previous wave. The second model added English proficiency. The third model added an interaction term (ATL × English Proficiency) to test if English proficiency moderated the association between ATL and math.</p>
<p>To account for the complex survey design of ECLS-K and nonrandom attrition, weights were applied to each model. For all analyses the C1_5FC0 weight was used. Applying a single weight to all analyses allowed the same underlying sample to be used across waves.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0739986312473580" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section13-0739986312473580">
<title>Sample Descriptives</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0739986312473580">Table 1</xref> presents weighted means for all study variables. The average socioeconomic status of the Hispanic immigrant children in our sample was low (<italic>M</italic> = −0.61, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.63), given that this measure is standardized to have a mean of 0 and a standard deviation of 1 in the full ECLS-K sample. At the time of the child’s birth, about two-thirds (<italic>M</italic> = 0.64, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.48) of the children’s parents were married. Approximately 40% (<italic>SD</italic> = 0.49) of the children attended some form of center-based child-care before kindergarten. About half of the Hispanic immigrant children in our analytic sample were from the western region of the United States (<italic>M</italic> = 0.53, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.50).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0739986312473580" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Means and Standard Deviations for All Study Variables.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0739986312473580" xlink:href="10.1177_0739986312473580-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="3"><italic>Child characteristics</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sex</td>
<td>0.50</td>
<td>0.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age (in months), fall K</td>
<td>67.32</td>
<td>4.14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Born premature</td>
<td>0.13</td>
<td>0.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Health, fall K</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>0.91</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Early childhood center care</td>
<td>0.40</td>
<td>0.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mother worked before kindergarten</td>
<td>0.53</td>
<td>0.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Parents married, fall K</td>
<td>0.64</td>
<td>0.48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Number of siblings, fall K</td>
<td>1.64</td>
<td>1.21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mother’s age at first birth</td>
<td>22.07</td>
<td>4.74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Socioeconomic status, fall &amp; spring K</td>
<td>−0.61</td>
<td>0.63</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Externalizing behavior, fall K</td>
<td>1.51</td>
<td>0.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Externalizing behavior, fall 1st</td>
<td>1.59</td>
<td>0.53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Externalizing behavior, spring 1st</td>
<td>1.59</td>
<td>0.58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3"><italic>Geographic controls</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> South</td>
<td>0.28</td>
<td>0.45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> West</td>
<td>0.53</td>
<td>0.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Midwest</td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>0.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Northeast</td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td>0.33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Small town/rural</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> City fringe/small city</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>0.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Large city</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>0.48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3"><italic>English proficiency</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kindergarten fall</td>
<td>0.45</td>
<td>0.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kindergarten spring</td>
<td>0.62</td>
<td>0.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1st grade spring</td>
<td>0.84</td>
<td>0.37</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3"><italic>Approaches to learning (ATL)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kindergarten fall</td>
<td>2.96</td>
<td>0.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kindergarten spring</td>
<td>3.10</td>
<td>0.66</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1st grade spring</td>
<td>3.01</td>
<td>0.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3"><italic>Math</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kindergarten spring</td>
<td>29.42</td>
<td>9.55</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1st grade Spring</td>
<td>53.74</td>
<td>15.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 3rd grade Spring</td>
<td>88.54</td>
<td>22.34</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0739986312473580"><p><italic>Note</italic>. <italic>n</italic> =1,483,101. Longitudinal weights were applied using C1_5FC0.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Hispanic immigrant children’s scores on ATL increased slightly between the fall of kindergarten (<italic>M</italic> = 2.96, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.65) and fall of first grade (<italic>M</italic> = 3.10, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.66), but decreased slightly by the spring of first grade (<italic>M</italic> = 3.01, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.69). The proportion of children who were proficient in English increased as the children progressed through school (45% in the fall of kindergarten, 62% in the spring of kindergarten, and 84% in the spring of first grade).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0739986312473580">
<title>Regression Results</title>
<p>Model 1 results revealed that ATL became more predictive of math scores over time (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0739986312473580">Table 2</xref>). Math scores in the spring of kindergarten were not associated with ATL scores from the fall of kindergarten. By the spring of first grade, however, math scores were associated with children’s ATL in the spring of kindergarten (<italic>B</italic> = 2.80, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). By the spring of third grade, the association between math and earlier ATL was over two and a half times stronger it had been in the spring of first grade (<italic>B</italic> = 7.07, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0739986312473580" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Summary of Regressions Predicting Math From ATL and English Proficiency.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0739986312473580" xlink:href="10.1177_0739986312473580-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Kindergarten spring<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">1st grade spring<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">3rd grade spring<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic> = 1,483,101)<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic> = 1,483,101)<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic> = 1,483,101<hr/>)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7"><italic>Model 1</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ATL</td>
<td>0.77</td>
<td>0.57</td>
<td>2.80<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0739986312473580">***</xref></td>
<td>0.71</td>
<td>7.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0739986312473580">***</xref></td>
<td>1.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7"><italic>Model 2</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ATL</td>
<td>0.88</td>
<td>0.59</td>
<td>2.80<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0739986312473580">***</xref></td>
<td>0.71</td>
<td>6.86<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0739986312473580">***</xref></td>
<td>1.23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> English proficiency</td>
<td>1.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0739986312473580">*</xref></td>
<td>0.60</td>
<td>.94</td>
<td>1.08</td>
<td>7.52<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0739986312473580">***</xref></td>
<td>1.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7"><italic>Model 3</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ATL</td>
<td>0.85</td>
<td>0.72</td>
<td>3.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0739986312473580">**</xref></td>
<td>1.07</td>
<td>3.15</td>
<td>2.12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> English proficiency</td>
<td>1.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0739986312473580">*</xref></td>
<td>0.60</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>1.07</td>
<td>8.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0739986312473580">***</xref></td>
<td>1.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ATL × English proficiency</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.87</td>
<td>−0.53</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>4.48<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0739986312473580">*</xref></td>
<td>2.01</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0739986312473580"><p>Note. ATL = Approaches to learning. Models control for the following characteristics: sex, age, born premature, mother’s age at first birth, whether mother worked before kindergarten, socioeconomic status, whether enrolled in early childhood center care, health, region, urbanicity, parental marital status, number of siblings at baseline, and externalizing behavior and math score at the previous wave. Longitudinal weights were applied using C1_5FC0.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0739986312473580">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt;.05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Model 2 added English proficiency to the models at each wave. The pattern of associations between ATL and math remained largely unchanged. Like ATL, English proficiency became more predictive of math over time, although not consistently. Children who were proficient in English in the fall of kindergarten scored higher on math in the spring of kindergarten (<italic>B</italic> = 1.36, <italic>p</italic> = .02). However, children who were English-proficient in the spring of kindergarten did not score higher on math in the spring of first grade. Children who were proficient at the end of first grade scored far higher than their nonproficient peers at the end of third grade (<italic>B</italic> = 7.52, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001).</p>
<p>Model 3 results indicated that the interaction between ATL and English proficiency was significant for math scores in the spring of third grade only (<italic>B</italic> = 4.48, <italic>p</italic> = .03). At this wave, the main effect of ATL was nonsignificant (<italic>B</italic> = 3.15, <italic>p</italic> = .15), indicating that there was no association between ATL and math for children who were not English-proficient. The main effect for English proficiency was significant (<italic>B</italic> = 8.15, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). Because the ATL scale was mean-centered, this result indicates that English proficiency significantly predicted math in the spring of third grade for children of average ATL skills.</p>
<p>The moderating effect of English proficiency on the association between ATL and math scores in the spring of third grade is illustrated graphically in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0739986312473580">Figure 1</xref>. Predicted math scores for children who were and were not proficient in English in the spring of first grade were computed at hypothetical low (one standard deviation below the mean) and high (one standard deviation above the mean) scores on ATL in first grade. Estimated values adjust for all controls as well as math in the spring of first grade. The slope of each line corresponds to the difference in predicted math scores between low- and high-scorers on ATL. The significance test for simple slopes was calculated using the computational tools provided online by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0739986312473580">Preacher, Curran, and Bauer (2006)</xref>. Among children who were proficient in English by the spring of first grade, those who were high in ATL scored 7.7 points higher on math in the spring of third grade than those who were low in ATL. This simple slope significantly differed from 0, <italic>t</italic>(966) = 6.24, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. However, among children who were not proficient in English by the spring of first grade, first grade ATL scores were <italic>not</italic> associated with third grade math scores. Specifically, the difference in math scores between children who were low and children who were high on ATL scores did not significantly differ from zero (<italic>B</italic> = 3.15, n.s.), <italic>t</italic>(966) = 1.48, <italic>p</italic> = .14.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0739986312473580" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The association between ATL scores in the spring of first grade and math scores in the spring of third grade according to English proficiency in the spring of first grade.</p>
<p><italic>Note</italic>. The simple slope for children who were proficient in English by the end of first grade (B = 7.75) was significantly different from zero (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001) but the simple slope for children who were not proficient in English by the end of first grade (<italic>B</italic> = 2.90) was not significantly different from zero (<italic>p</italic> = .16). Models control for the following characteristics: sex, age, born premature, mother’s age at first birth, whether mother worked before kindergarten, socioeconomic status, whether enrolled in early childhood center care, health, region, urbanicity, parental marital status, number of siblings at baseline, and externalizing behavior and math score at the previous wave. Longitudinal weights were applied using C1_5FC0. Weighted <italic>n</italic> = 211,383.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0739986312473580-fig1.tif"/></fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0739986312473580" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The present study addressed two questions. First, we asked whether the positive association between ATL and math scores that has been demonstrated in large, national samples was evident in an exclusively Hispanic first- and second-generation immigrant sample. Second, we asked whether English proficiency moderated this association. Our results were complicated, and suggest that the association between ATL and math among Hispanic immigrant children shifts over the early years of school. In the spring of kindergarten, there was no association between math scores and earlier ATL. In the spring of first grade, however, math scores were positively associated with earlier ATL. Specifically, a 1-point increase in ATL in the spring of kindergarten was associated with a 2.80 point increase in math in the spring of first grade (Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> = .18, which should be regarded as small; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0739986312473580">Cohen, 1988</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0739986312473580">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>By the spring of third grade the association between math scores and earlier ATL persisted only among English-proficient children. Among children who were not proficient, ATL in the spring of first grade was not associated with math in the spring of third grade. Among children who were proficient, a 1-point increase in ATL in the spring of first grade was associated with a 4.48 point increase in math in the spring of third grade (<italic>d</italic> = .20, which is considered small; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0739986312473580">Cohen, 1988</xref>).</p>
<p>It is difficult to compare these results to those of Hispanic nonimmigrants and other race/ethnicities because most other studies have not identified year-specific associations. However, the sizes of the association between ATL and math in first grade, and the association between ATL and math in third grade for English-proficient children, are comparable to those previously found for diverse national samples between kindergarten ATL and later math. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0739986312473580">Duncan et al. (2007)</xref> reported that ATL in the fall of kindergarten had an effect size of 0.10 in the prediction of change in math between fall of kindergarten and spring of third grade in the ECLS-K. Based on all Hispanics in the ECLS-K, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0739986312473580">Galindo and Fuller (2010)</xref> estimated an effect size of .29 in the prediction of change in math over the kindergarten year by ATL. Our estimated associations for Hispanic immigrants fall between these estimates.</p>
<sec id="section16-0739986312473580">
<title>ATL, English Proficiency, and Math in Hispanic Immigrants</title>
<p>We failed to find an association between ATL in the fall of kindergarten and math in the spring of kindergarten. Our findings appear to contradict <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0739986312473580">Galindo and Fuller (2010)</xref>, who found a positive association between the two using an exclusively Hispanic sample from the ECLS-K. However, they included all Hispanic children in their analyses, whereas we excluded third-generation and higher generation Hispanic children because they are likely to be proficient in English (calculations not shown). To the extent that English proficiency facilitates the positive effects of ATL skills, the inclusion of third-generation and higher generation children in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0739986312473580">Galindo and Fuller’s (2010)</xref> Hispanic sample may have driven the positive association between ATL and math.</p>
<p>In our sample, by third grade ATL was predictive of math for only those Hispanic immigrant children who were proficient in English. It is possible that this pattern actually emerged in second grade, when data were unavailable. We offer two possible explanations for our findings. First, there may be other, as-yet untested variables modifying the association between ATL and math among Hispanic immigrant children. One such variable may be the quality of classroom instruction. The literature finds that many Hispanic immigrant children attend schools where the teachers are relatively inexperienced and the quality of instruction is poor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0739986312473580">Crosnoe, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0739986312473580">Justice, Mashburn, Hamre, &amp; Pianta, 2008</xref>). ATL may do little to raise math scores for Hispanic immigrant children when they are in classrooms where the quality of instruction is low. Thus, unmeasured variation in classroom quality over time in the ECLS-K may have produced fluctuating associations between English proficiency and ATL.</p>
<p>Second, ATL may not have been conditioned on English proficiency until third grade because of the changing demands of math learning. Word problems become more complex each year, with more sophisticated and technical vocabulary. Therefore, each year math becomes a greater reflection of a child’s language ability, both written and oral (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0739986312473580">Collier, 1987</xref>). Accordingly, struggles with proficiency may increasingly undermine ATL over time.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0739986312473580">
<title>English Proficiency Among Hispanic Immigrants</title>
<p>Analyses indicated that 16% of our sample was still not proficient in English by the end of first grade, although all children had entered U.S. schools in the fall of kindergarten. Research suggests that this percentage may not be unusual because children typically require between 4 and 7 years to develop academic proficiency in a second language (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0739986312473580">Collier, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0739986312473580">Hakuta, Butler &amp; Witt, 2000</xref>). While it is possible that some of the children who lacked English proficiency by the end of first grade had an undiagnosed learning disability (recall that children with an IEP were excluded from the sample), it is reasonable to conclude that the majority were typically developing children whose English proficiency was still evolving. The results of our study suggest that children who take longer to develop English language skills may be at risk of lower math scores. Future research is needed to evaluate potential strategies for remediating slow English language acquisition.</p>
<p>Early childhood education for Hispanic immigrant children may be one promising way to increase children’s English language skills at an early age. Supplemental analyses (not shown) indicated that children who were not proficient in English by the end of first grade were significantly less likely to have attended center-based child care than their peers who were proficient in English (25% versus 44%). Past research has shown that Hispanic immigrant children tend to improve their English language skills more than other children in center-based child care (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0739986312473580">Gormley &amp; Gayer, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0739986312473580">Magnuson, Lahaie, &amp; Waldfogel, 2006</xref>). Nevertheless, they are less likely than White or Black children to attend center-based care (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0739986312473580">Iruka &amp; Carver, 2006</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0739986312473580">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>One limitation in this study is our relatively simplistic measure of English proficiency. Unfortunately, the measure of English proficiency in the ECLS-K data set is not administered to all children, and therefore it is not possible to adequately gauge the English proficiency skills of children once they are deemed proficient enough to take the assessments in English. Also, a measure of the children’s Spanish language proficiency would have allowed us to assess how bilingualism, not just English proficiency, relates to the association between ATL and math.</p>
<p>Second, the use of a teacher-reported measure of ATL merits a note of caution. Teachers may provide inaccurate descriptions of children’s behavior because of stereotypes about minority groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0739986312473580">Pigott &amp; Cowen, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0739986312473580">Zimmerman, Khoury, Vega, Gil, &amp; Warheit, 1995</xref>). However, since this sample is entirely Hispanic, such inaccuracies should not introduce systematic bias.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0739986312473580" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>In summary, this study found that ATL scores did not significantly predict math scores for Hispanic immigrant children until first grade. By third grade, the association between ATL and math was significant, but only for children who were proficient in English. Furthermore, our analyses revealed that approximately 16% of Hispanic first- and second-generation children were not proficient in English by the end of first grade. Thus it is important to identify protective factors and early intervention programs that foster the development of English language skills among Hispanic immigrant children at an early age.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0739986312473580">
<label>1.</label>
<p>English proficiency was not measured after the spring of first grade. Because our models use attention at the previous wave as a predictor, we cannot predict math scores after the spring of third grade.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0739986312473580">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Effect sizes were calculated by dividing the unstandardized coefficient by the SD of math scores in the prior wave.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Erin Bumgarner</bold> works as a project manager at the Massachusetts Healthy Families Evaluation Project at Tufts University. She recently finished her PhD in Developmental Psychology at Columbia University, where she worked as a graduate research fellow at the National Center for Children and Families. Dr Bumgarner earned her MA at Boston College in Applied Developmental and Educational Psychology and her BA in Psychology and Spanish from American University in Washington D.C. Her research focuses on how policy and programs can be used to improve the long-term outcomes of low-income children. She is particularly interested in early interventions such as early childhood education and home visiting programs, and how they can best serve children from linguistically and culturally diverse backgrounds.</p>
<p><bold>Anne Martin</bold> is a senior research scientist and the coordinator at the National Center for Children and Families. She earned her doctoral and master’s degrees in public health from Columbia University. She is interested in early childhood development and adolescent sexual behavior. Her research has focused on the effects of early intervention, the interplay between maternal and paternal supportive parenting, child care/classroom quality, adolescent sexual behavior, and young children’s early self-regulation and cognition.</p>
<p><bold>Jeanne Brooks-Gunn</bold> is the Virginia and Leonard Marx Professor of Child Development and Education at Teachers College and the College of Physicians and Surgeons at Columbia University and she directs the National Center for Children and Families. She is interested in factors that contribute to both positive and negative outcomes across childhood, adolescence, and adulthood, with a particular focus on key social and biological transitions over the life course. She designs and evaluates intervention programs for children and parents (Early Head Start, Infant Health and Development Program, Head Start Quality Program). Other large-scale longitudinal studies include the Fragile Families and Child Well-being Study and the Project on Human Development in Chicago Neighborhoods (co-PI of both). She is the author of 4 books and over 350 publications.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abikoff</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Courtney</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pelham</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koplewicz</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Teachers’ ratings of disruptive behaviors: The influence of halo effects</article-title>. <source>Journal of Abnormal Child Psychology</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>519</fpage>-<lpage>533</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aiken</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>West</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Multiple regression: Testing and interpreting interactions</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Missing data</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Millsap</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maydeu-Olivares</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The SAGE handbook of quantitative methods in psychology</source> (pp. <fpage>72</fpage>-<lpage>89</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>School readiness: Integrating cognition and emotion in a neurobiological conceptualization of children’s functioning at school entry</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>111</fpage>-<lpage>127</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Razza</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Relating effortful control, executive function, and false belief understanding to emerging math and literacy ability in kindergarten</article-title>. <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>78</volume>, <fpage>647</fpage>-<lpage>663</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc. Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Age and rate of acquisition of second language for academic purposes</article-title>. <source>Teachers of English to Speakers of Other Languages</source> (<source>TESOL) Quarterly</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>617</fpage>-<lpage>641</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Working memory capacity</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychology Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crosnoe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Double disadvantage or signs of resilience? The elementary school contexts of children from Mexican immigrant families</article-title>. <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>303</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crosnoe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006a</year>). <article-title>Health and the education of children from racial/ethnic minority and immigrant families</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health and Social Behavior</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crosnoe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006b</year>). <source>Mexican roots, American schools: Helping Mexican immigrant children succeed</source>. <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Feyter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winsler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The early developmental competencies and school readiness of low-income, immigrant children: Influences of generation, race/ethnicity and national origins</article-title>. <source>Early Childhood Research Quarterly</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>411</fpage>-<lpage>431</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dowsett</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Claessens</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Magnuson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huston</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klebanov</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Japel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>School readiness and later achievement</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>1428</fpage>-<lpage>1446</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeAvila</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Pre-language assessment scale 2000</source>. <publisher-loc>Monterey, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CTB/McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Galindo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The social competence of Latino kindergartners and growth in mathematical understanding</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>579</fpage>-<lpage>592</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gormley</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gayer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Promoting school readiness in Oklahoma: An evaluation of Tulsa’s pre-K program</article-title>, <source>Journal of Human Resources, XL</source>, <fpage>533</fpage>-<lpage>558</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hakuta</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Witt</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>How long does it take English learners to attain proficiency?</source> <publisher-loc>Stanford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The University of California Linguistic Minority Research Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takanishi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marotz</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Life circumstances and public policies for young children in immigrant families</article-title>. <source>Early Childhood Research Quarterly</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>487</fpage>-<lpage>501</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hinshaw</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Externalizing behavior problems and academic underachievement in childhood and adolescence: Causal relationships and underlying mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>111</volume>, <fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>155</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Iruka</surname><given-names>I. U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carver</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Initial results from the 2005 NHES Early Childhood Program Participation Survey</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Education</publisher-name>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nces.ed.gov/pubsearch/pubsinfo.asp?pubid=2006075">http://nces.ed.gov/pubsearch/pubsinfo.asp?pubid=2006075</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Justice</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mashburn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamre</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pianta</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Quality of language and literacy instruction in preschool classrooms serving at-risk pupils</article-title>. <source>Early Childhood Research Quarterly</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Karabenick</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Noda</surname><given-names>P. A. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Professional development implications of teachers’ beliefs and attitudes toward English-Language Learners</article-title>. <source>Bilingual Research Journal</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li-Grining</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Votruba-Drzal</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maldonado-Carreño</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Children’s early approaches to learning and academic trajectories through fifth grade</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>1062</fpage>-<lpage>1077</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Magnuson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lahaie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waldfogel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Preschool and school readiness of children of immigrants</article-title>. <source>Social Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>87</volume>, <fpage>1241</fpage>-<lpage>1262</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ponitz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Early gender differences in self-regulation and academic achievement</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>101</volume>, <fpage>689</fpage>-<lpage>704</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCartney</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burchinal</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bub</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Best practices in quantitative methods for developmentalists</article-title>. <source>Monographs of the Society for Research in Child Development</source>, <volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>, Serial No. 285).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McClelland</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Acock</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The impact of kindergarten learning-related skills on academic trajectories at the end of elementary school</article-title>. <source>Early Childhood Research Quarterly</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>471</fpage>-<lpage>490</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leigh</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Development and validation for the Preschool Learning Behaviors Scale</article-title>. <source>Psychology in the Schools</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>353</fpage>-<lpage>365</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Latina parent involvement: The role of maternal acculturation and education</article-title>. <source>The School Community Journal</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>83</fpage>-<lpage>101</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moschkovich</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Bilingual mathematics learners: How views of language, bilingual learners, and mathematical communication impact instruction</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Nasir</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Diversity, equity, and access to mathematical ideas</source> (pp. <fpage>89</fpage>-<lpage>104</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Teachers College Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>National Center for Education Statistics</collab>. (<year>2002</year>). <source>Early Childhood Longitudinal Study-Kindergarten Class of 1998–99 (ECLS–K), Psychometric report for kindergarten through first grade</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>National Center for Education Statistics</collab>. (<year>2005</year>). <source>Early Childhood Longitudinal Study-Kindergarten Class of 1998–99 (ECLS–K), Psychometric report for the third grade</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>National Center for Education Statistics</collab>. (<year>2009</year>). <source>Early Childhood Longitudinal Study-Kindergarten Class of 1998–99 (ECLS–K): Eighth grade methodology report</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Paas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Touvinen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tabbers</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Gerven</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Cognitive load measurement as a means to advance cognitive load theory</article-title>. <source>Educational Psychologist</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pagani</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Archambault</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Janosz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>School readiness and later achievement: A French Canadian replication and extension</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>984</fpage>-<lpage>994</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pigott</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cowen</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Teacher race, child race, racial congruence, and teacher ratings of children’s school adjustment</article-title>. <source>Journal of School Psychology</source>, <volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Portes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schauffler</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Language and the second generation: Bilingualism yesterday and today</article-title>. <source>International Migration Review</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>640</fpage>-<lpage>661</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Preacher</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Computational tools for probing interaction effects in multiple linear regression, multilevel modeling, and latent curve analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational and Behavioral Statistics</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>437</fpage>-<lpage>448</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Dismay and disappointment: Parental involvement of Latino immigrant parents</article-title>. <source>The Urban Review</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reardon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Galindo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The Hispanic-White achievement gap in math and reading in elementary grades</article-title>. <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>853</fpage>-<lpage>891</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Royston</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Multiple imputation of missing values: Further update of ice, with an emphasis on interval censoring</article-title>. <source>The Stata Journal</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>445</fpage>-<lpage>464</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>The overlap between hyperactive and unsocialized aggressive children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Suárez-Orozco</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Milburn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Unraveling the immigrant paradox: Academic engagement and disengagement among recently arrived immigrant youth</article-title>. <source>Youth &amp; Society</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>185</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>von Hippel</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Regression with missing Ys: An improved strategy for analyzing multiply imputed data</article-title>. <source>Sociological Methodology</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>83</fpage>-<lpage>117</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iiams</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>“Not in my classroom”: Teacher attitudes towards English language learners in the mainstream classroom</article-title>. <source>NABE Journal of Research and Practice</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>130</fpage>-<lpage>160</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zarate</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group>(<year>2007</year>). <source>Understanding Latino parental involvement in education: Perceptions, expectations and recommendations</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Tomás Rivera Policy Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0739986312473580">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khoury</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warheit</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>).<article-title>Teacher and parent perceptions of behavior problems among a sample of African American, Hispanic, and non-Hispanic White Students</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Community Psychology</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>181</fpage>-<lpage>197</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>