<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="abstract">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IAB</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spiab</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Political Science Abstracts</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0020-8345</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1751-9292</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/002083451206200406</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_002083451206200406</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Abstracts</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>VI: National and Area Studies/Études Nationales et Régionales</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>8</month><year>2012</year></pub-date>
<volume>62</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>534</fpage>
<lpage>549</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 International Political Science Association</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">International Political Science Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>62.5432 Al-RAHIM, Ahmed H. — <bold>Whither political Islam and the “Arab Spring”?</bold> <italic>Hedgehog Review</italic> 13(3), Fall 2011: 8–22.</p>
<p>Three major events in the history of the Middle East and North Africa help understand the nature of recent protests in the region. The first is Napoleon's invasion of Egypt in 1798, followed by the “Arab liberal age”, or the period of assimilation of Western modernity by Muslim thought from 1798 to 1939, and the postcolonial context of nationalism and nation-states. The political discourse has markedly shifted away from pan-Arabism and pan-Islamism to a nationally-based agenda with clearly defined goals. Three current political models indicate possible future trajectories for political Islam today: the Turkish secular national model as founded by M.K. Atatürk in 1923; the 1979 Islamic revolution in Iran; the post-2003 invasion model of parliamentary, democratic government in Iraq.</p>
<p>62.5433 ALEXANDROVA-ARBATOVA, Nadia — <bold>Western Balkans: yet another intersection of global politics.</bold> <italic>Südosteuropa Mitteilungen</italic> 52(1), 2012: 12–19.</p>
<p>The Western Balkans is very sensitive to predominant trends and structural changes concerning its global economy and international relations. It is also seen as a field of dynamic political transformation and socio-economic processes that are strongly influenced and guided by the EU, which has emerged as the unchallenged international actor in the region. However, the EU international and regional positions are challenged by the ongoing world financial and economic crisis. Moreover, recent years have witnessed the growing activity and complex interplay of interests of Russia, Turkey and China in the Balkan region. A Balkan harmony that can be achieved only within the context of Europeanization of the region requires a well thought EU-strategy, based on multilateral cooperation. [R]</p>
<p>62.5434 ALGOTSSON, Karl-Göran — <bold>De svenska partierna och Lavaldomen (The Swedish political parties and the [European Court of Justice's] <italic>Laval</italic> verdict).</bold> <italic>Statsvetenskaplig Tidskrift</italic> 113(4), 2011: 403–422.</p>
<p>The Swedish labor market has been characterized hitherto by collective agreements, by strong trade unions, and by far-reaching rights to take industrial action. At the same time, Sweden has been a member state of the EU since 1995. The fundamental basis of the Union is freedom of movement for goods, services, capital, and labor. The question is whether the Swedish labor-market model is threatened by freedom of movement within the EU. The verdict of the European Court of Justice in the <italic>Laval</italic> case [2007] would seem to indicate that it is. This article describes and explains the positions taken by Swedish political parties on the question of what Swedish legislation ought to follow from the ECJ's decision in the <italic>Laval</italic> case. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5435 ALTERMAN, Jon B. — <bold>Seeing through the fog: Libya and transition.</bold> <italic>SAIS Review of International Affairs</italic> 32(1), Winter-Spring 2012: 147–156.</p>
<p>The demise of the Qaddafi clique leaves Libyans and foreigners alike in a quandary as to what Libya's future is and what role the US might play in steering things in a positive direction. In a period of broader transition in the Middle East, a successful outcome in Libya can have a larger impact as a model for interactions between transitional governments and the outside world on the one hand and between the US and like-minded allies confronting complex contingencies on the other. What happens in Libya will continue to matter to the US, with no clear way for the US to guarantee success or even make it likely. [R]</p>
<p>62.5436 ALTMANN, Franz-Lothar — <bold>Die Auswirkungen der Griechenland-Krise auf die Nachbarstaaten (The effects of the Greek crisis on the neighboring countries).</bold> <italic>Südosteuropa Mitteilungen</italic> 52(1), 2012: 20–29.</p>
<p>The economic and financial crisis in Greece affects the neighboring countries in various ways: the pragmatic drop in domestic consumption [affects] Greek imports, Greek investors lack the financial means for FDI abroad, and Greek banks have enormous problems to secure their basic capital fixture, the latter a challenge that must increase dramatically [because] Greek banks in particular hold the majority of Greek state bonds. A repatriation of capital assets from the Greek bank subsidiaries in the Balkan countries thus becomes very probable, causing related problems for the credit markets in the respective countries. A collateral damage for these countries is the fortification of the negative image of the Balkans in general as a region of political and economic shakiness, and a further increase of enlargement fatigue in the EU. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5437 AMUZEGAR, Jahangir — <bold>The Islamic Republic of Iran: facts and fiction.</bold> <italic>Middle East Policy</italic> 19(1), Spring 2012: 25–36.</p>
<p>Some fundamental characteristics of the Islamic regime have escaped proper scrutiny and are shrouded Some fundamental characteristics of the Islamic regime have escaped proper scrutiny and are shrouded in myth. The regime's true political nature, the country's constitutional structure, the power and position of its top leaders, the political challenges it poses to the region and the world, the reasons for its long-term viability in the face of stiff global sanctions, and its ideological influence on the region's political movements remain largely misunderstood and misinterpreted. This brief review attempts to dispel seven of these myths. [R] [First article of a symposium on “A shifting balance of power: Israel, Turkey and Iran in the changing Arab world”, with contributions by Robert MALLEY, Karim SADJADPOUR and ömer TAŞPINAR. See also <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5331, 5356, 5360]</p>
<p>62.5438 AN-NA<sup>c</sup>IM, Abdullahi Ahmed — <bold>Islam, Sharia and democratic transformation in the Arab world.</bold> <italic>Friedens-Warte</italic> 87(1), 2012: 27–42.</p>
<p>The author emphasizes the self-determination of local actors who must struggle on their own terms, and the internal dynamics of how rebellions may evolve into transformative revolutions over time. Regarding the outcomes of 2011 rebellions across the Arab world, the author proposes engaging Islamists in open political contestation, within the same constitutional and democratic framework that apply to all citizens. The article focuses on the mediation of tensions in this relationship between <italic>Sharia</italic> (the normative system of Islam) and the post-colonial state through the separation of Islam and the state, while affirming and regulating the connectedness of Islam and politics. [R] [First article of a thematic issue on “Rebellion and revolution in the Arab region—from the perspective of peace research”. See also <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5187, 5221, 5561]</p>
<p>62.5439 ANERE, Ray — <bold>Papua New Guinea in 2011: politics confused, but democracy stable.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 227–232.</p>
<p>The current power struggle has taken on historical proportions, interrupting the four-year-old Somare government in Papua New Guinea one year short of its full five-year term. In August 2011, Speaker of Parliament J. Nape declared the Office of Prime Minister vacant, resulting in Parliament electing P. O'Neill as the new prime minister. Late in the year, the Supreme Court ruled otherwise. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5440 ANTWI-BOATENG, Osman — <bold>After war then peace: the US-based Liberian diaspora as peace-building norm entrepreneurs.</bold> <italic>Journal of Refugee Studies</italic> 25(1), March 2012: 93–112.</p>
<p>The US-based Liberian diaspora's role in the country's 14-year civil war and its aftermath is paradoxical. Consistent with existing literature on the role of diasporas in conflict, the group largely played a role contributing to the outbreak of the Civil War and its continuation. However, in a paradigmatic shift, the group is currently contributing towards the peace-building process by serving as norm entrepreneurs. Factors contributing to this shift include a strong demand in the homeland for a change in the “rules of the game”, a shift in US foreign policy towards promotion of democracy in Africa, and a concerted regional and international effort at promoting peace-building norms. The inclusiveness of the mechanisms for norm-transfer, the conduct of the messengers and local perception of norms, affect the degree to which they are received. [R]</p>
<p>62.5441 ANUGWOM, Edlyne — <bold>Something mightier: marginalization, occult imaginations and the youth conflict in the oil-rich Niger Delta.</bold> <italic>Africa Spectrum</italic> 46(3), 2011: 3–26.</p>
<p>This contribution examines the role of occult imaginations in the struggle against perceived socio-economic marginalization by youth militias from the Ijaw ethnic group in the oil-rich Niger Delta region of Nigeria. It argues that the asymmetric power between the federal government/transnational oil corporations (TNOCs) and the militias may have privileged the invocation of the supernatural as a critical agency of strength and courage by the youth militias. The conflict in the region embodies a cultural revision which has been necessitated by both the uncertainty of the oil environment and the prevailing narratives of social injustice. Hence the Egbesu deity, seen historically as embodying justice, has been reinvented by the youth militias and imbued with the powers of invincibility and justice in the conflict with the government and oil companies. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5442 ARANDA, Rafael; RODRÍGUEZ BURGUETE, Lionel — <bold>La ruta asfaltada de la alternancia en México: de los centros urbanos a sus periferias (The asphalt road of political alternation in Mexico: from urban centers to periphery areas).</bold> <italic>Foro internacional</italic> 207, Jan.–March 2012: 92–132. [Résumé en français]</p>
<p>In Mexico, political changes emerge principally in cities, where socio-economic flows converge at the junctions of the intercity federal highway network. Many of these poles of regional development and urban/industrial corridors were the triggers for transfers of political power in their respective areas of influence, which followed the urban hierarchy marked out by the intercity highway network. The country was broken up into a mosaic of sub-national pluralist competitive units that co-existed with authoritarian enclaves, where marginalization with regard to the socio-economic flows of the urban hierarchy made them resistant to the effects of democratization. [R]</p>
<p>62.5443 ASAL, Victor; BROWN, Mitchell; DALTON, Angela — <bold>Why split? Organizational splits among ethnopolitical organizations in the Middle East.</bold> <italic>Journal of Conflict Resolution</italic> 56(1), Feb. 2012: 94–117.</p>
<p>Why do political organizations split? Drawing insight from organizational theory and social movement literature, this article explores the effect of organizational factors on group schism. Using a new data set of 112 ethnopolitical organizations in the Middle East, the article examines to what extent organizational factors such as leadership structure, organizational legality, and tactical intensity, as well as contextual variables such as state violence and external support for the organization, influence group schism. [R, abr.] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4507]</p>
<p>62.5444 BASORA, Adrian A. — <bold>Do the post-communist transitions offer useful lessons for the Arab uprisings?</bold> <italic>Orbis</italic> 56(2), Spring 2012: 278–288.</p>
<p>In January 2011, when the Arab protest movements were just beginning in Tunisia and Egypt, few experts predicted the speed and extent of their spread. Fewer still suggested that there were significant analogies to the wave of post-communist revolutions that swept through Europe and Eurasia starting in 1989. However, such comparisons have become more frequent as the uprisings have continued. This article examines whether the current uprisings and political ferment in the Arab world have enough in common with the transitions that began two decades ago in Eastern Europe to provide useful analytical and policy comparisons. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5267]</p>
<p>62.5445 BECK, Peter M. — <bold>North Korea in 2011: the next Kim takes the helm.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 65–71.</p>
<p>North Korea underwent a seemingly seamless leadership transition from father to son in the midst of a struggling economy and widespread hunger. The North drew even closer to China but also reached out to the US and Russia for the first time in several years. Meanwhile, inter-Korean relations remained in a deep freeze. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5446 BELLOFIORE, Riccardo; GARIBALDO, Francesco; HALEVI, Joseph — <bold>The global crisis and the crisis of European neomercantilism.</bold> <italic>Socialist Register</italic> 2011: 120–146.</p>
<p>The present crisis in the Eurozone reflects the partition of the EU into three groups, one of which is formed by neo-mercantilist countries centered on Germany. The root causes of stagnation are found in the evolution of European neo-mercantilism as it unfolded after 1945. Net surpluses within Europe were the crucial factor in Germany's performance. The crucial question is, therefore, how did Germany manage to sustain its unchallenged oligopolistic dominance in the EU? Two main closely interrelated and reinforcing processes have profoundly changed European and global “industrial capital”: centralization without concentration, and a model of competition based on the pursuit of a never-ending expansion of all kind of consumption, engendering the necessity to seek new markets. [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4448]</p>
<p>62.5447 BELOW, Katharina, <italic>et al.</italic> — <bold>Der Aufstieg der BIC-Staaten als Wissensmächte? (Are the BIC countries [Brazil, India and China] emergent knowledge powers?).</bold> <italic>Zeitschrift für Politik</italic> 59(1), 2012: 3–22.</p>
<p>Several indicators are selected to explore the BICs' development as knowledge powers. The BIC countries [Brazil, India and China] indeed are on their way towards building their own powerful technological innovation capacity. However, in terms of the control over the global knowledge structure, they still remain quite marginalized. In sum, the pact at which the gap between BIC countries and the industrial nations is being closed is much less rapid and alarming than often portrayed in the media. Yet these general trends nonetheless should attract the strategic attention of Germany and other industrial nations to reorganizing their policies in order to adapt to a changed distribution of global knowledge power and to profit from the various advantages inherent in these developments. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5448 BENKORICH, Nora — <bold>La tentation de la lutte armée contre le pouvoir baasiste en Syrie. Passé (1976–1982) et présent (2011) (The temptation of an armed struggle against Ba'ath power in Syria. Past (1976–1982) and present (2011)).</bold> <italic>Le Débat</italic> 168, Jan.–Feb. 2012: 155–167.</p>
<p>The current situation in Syria resembles the armed jihad struggle against the regime, which was initiated in 1976 by an underground branch of the Muslim Brotherhood and culminated in the tragic events of Hama in February 1982. The new stage in Riyad al-Asaad's Free Syrian Army fighters' activity can thus be better understood in the light of these historical events. The flow of politicized literature and ideological distortions tends to drawn evidence of real value. By juxtaposing official memoirs of two former Muslim Brotherhood militants and memoirs by two jihadists, in addition to a number of testimonies, it is possible to reconstitute this period and to link it with the current events. [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5330]</p>
<p>62.5449 BENKORICH, Nora — <bold>Les minorités dans le “printemps syrien”. Tous avec Bachar? (The minorities in the “Syrian Spring”. All with Bachar [al-Assad]?).</bold> <italic>Le Débat</italic> 169, March-Apr. 2012: 23–34.</p>
<p>The fact that the Syrian ethnic minorities comprise multiple religious elements leads to the question: why not understand the ethnic groups through the denominational prism? The phenomenon of identity affirmation based on religious criteria, from which the Sunni majority has not been spared, is subsidiary for the non-Arab minorities to which ethnic identity, is theoretically excluded from the nation by Ba'ath's pan-Arabism, which prevails over religious identity. Thus, the Syrian Kurds (Sunni Muslims and Christian, Alawi and Yezidi minorities), Armenians (Gregorian Christians with a Catholic minority), Cherkessians (Sunni Muslims) and Assyrians (Nestorians, Chaldeans, Catholic and Orthodox Syrians) perceive themselves above all as ethnic minorities and express themselves as such (with the exception of the Assyrian clergy, who play in both the religious and ethnic registers). [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5479]</p>
<p>62.5450 BENRAAD, Myriam — <bold>Fin de l'occupation et crise en Irak: la clé de voûte sunnite (The end of the occupation and the crisis in Iraq: the Sunni keystone).</bold> <italic>Politique étrangère</italic> 77(1), Spring 2012: 161–172. [Résumé en français]</p>
<p>The US withdrew in December 2011 from a profoundly divided Iraq, the setting of daily violence and a deep social and political crisis. One of the factors that weighed most on the present situation has been the marginalization of Sunnis throughout the US occupation. Indeed, the Sunni problem undermines prospects for a durable reconciliation and above all raises the threat of a partition, both geographic and symbolic, of the country. [R]</p>
<p>62.5451 BJÖRKDAHL, Annika — <bold>A gender-just peace? Exploring the post-Dayton peace process in Bosnia.</bold> <italic>Peace and Change</italic> 37(2), Apr. 2012: 286–317.</p>
<p>This article is rooted in the understanding that global ideas of liberal democratic peace and the gendered dynamics of peace-building need to be confronted. It explores the challenges of localizing liberal democratic peace by exploring efforts such as those undertaken by women's organizations in Bosnia-Herzegovina to promote a gender-just peace. The Dayton Peace Accord was the new “social contract” that set the standard for postwar societies. The gendered hierarchies built into this peace and the absence of women in the peace process created a “peace gap” that was gendered despite the fact that gender empowerment has become a standard tool in international peace-building. The post-Dayton peace process was characterized by a conservative backlash which has become a hallmark of women's postwar experience. [R]</p>
<p>62.5452 BONNEY, Norman — <bold>Scottish independence, state religion and the [UK] monarchy.</bold> <italic>Political Quarterly</italic> 83(2), Apr.–June 2012: 360–367.</p>
<p>The plans of the Scottish Executive/Government for the independence of Scotland, which are very sketchy, are explored in relation to desire to retain the monarchy. The Scottish Parliament has expressed support for the removal of religious discrimination from succession to the throne and instituted an alternative state religion—measures which suggest an alternative relationship between religion and the monarchy will be required in an independent Scotland. Repealing the Act of Union will require decisions as to whether the monarchy remains as Christian, Protestant and Presbyterian in Scotland or whether some alternative religious or secular arrangements will be developed. Accepting the existing religious settlement of the monarchy, or varying it, will generate challenging issues for a Scottish administration that is seeking to be more religiously inclusive. [R]</p>
<p>62.5453 BRUN, Cathrine; VAN HEAR, Nicholas — <bold>Between the local and the diasporic: the shifting centre of gravity in war-torn Sri Lanka's transnational politics.</bold> <italic>Contemporary South Asia</italic> 20(1), March 2012: 61–75.</p>
<p>In May 2009, Sri Lankan government armed forces defeated the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam (LTTE) after more than a quarter of a century of civil war. With the elimination of most of the LTTE leadership and the waning of its hold over Tamils in Sri Lanka and abroad, the scene was set for a transformation of relations between the diaspora and those at home. It is the dynamics of this transformation that we explore in this article, which traces the shifting center of gravity in Tamil politics between actors in the homeland and those in the diaspora. Drawing on P. Bourdieu's notion of a “political field”, we characterize what we call the local, diasporic and transnational political fields in the Sri Lankan setting. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5454 BYMAN, Daniel — <bold>Regime change in the Middle East: problems and prospects.</bold> <italic>Political Science Quarterly</italic> 127(1), Spring 2012: 25–46.</p>
<p>The author discusses the diplomatic and security implications of the Arab Spring. He finds that new alignments have begun in the Arab world and that the region's stability is being shaken. He argues that these changes affect an array of declared US interests. [R]</p>
<p>62.5455 CAGNAT, René — <bold>Afghanistan: danger de mort ! Partie II (Afghanistan: deadly danger! Part II).</bold> <italic>Revue Défense nationale</italic> 747, Feb. 2012: 112–118. [Résumé en français]</p>
<p>In this second essay [Part I: <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.2614], the author exposes the Central Asian trap which risks on snaring the NATO forces by virtue of their dependence on logistic supply. A generalized “Afghanization” of Central Asia is developing along two mutually supporting lines, drugs and terrorism. Hopes of stabilization of the area seem compromised. [R] [Part III: <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5456]</p>
<p>62.5456 CAGNAT, René — <bold>Afghanistan: danger de mort ! Partie III (Afghanistan: deadly danger! Part III).</bold> <italic>Revue Défense nationale</italic> 748, March 2012: 86–94. [Résumé en français]</p>
<p>In his previous articles [Part I: <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.2614; Part II: <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5455], the author emphasized the need for ISAF, and French forces in particular, to leave the increasingly uncontrollable Pashtun region of Afghanistan and, to consider a withdrawal towards the northern region of that country and, more broadly, Central Asia. A new fight needs to be undertaken across the entire territory, alongside Russia and the CSTO, possibly with the Shanghai Cooperation Organization as well, against Islamic terrorism and drug trafficking in order to save the vital area of Turkistan from foreign influence. [R]</p>
<p>62.5457 CALLE, Marie-France — <bold>Le Pakistan de tous les dangers (Pakistan: all dangers).</bold> <italic>Politique internationale</italic> 135, Spring 2012: 281–298.</p>
<p>The war in Afghanistan, declared in 2001 by a US-led coalition, has deeply changed Pakistan's regional game. Allied with Washington in the fight against the Taliban, albeit against its will, Pakistan expanded its presence on the international scene. But the Afghan conflict has [generated] an unprecedented native terrorism. The all-powerful army paid the highest price. Another, and perhaps more surprising element is now in the process of reshuffling the cards in Islamabad, namely the rise of the judicial branch, which is intensifying pressure on President Zardari, accused of corruption, and on Prime Minister Gilani, suspected of covering up his president. Even if the return of a military dictatorship is rather unlikely, a real democracy is not going to be established any time soon. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5458 CALVO, Ernesto; MURILLO, M. Victoria — <bold>Argentina: the persistence of Peronism.</bold> <italic>Journal of Democracy</italic> 23(2), Apr. 2012: 148–161.</p>
<p>Despite a rocky first term, Peronist President C. de Kirchner saw her popularity rebound, leading to a huge reelection victory in 2011. Why is Peronism still the dominant “brand” in Argentine politics, and how has she come to own it so thoroughly? [R]</p>
<p>62.5459 ÇANCI, Haldun; ŞEN, Şevket Serkan — <bold>Turkish politics and policies under the impact of the 1980s PKK revolt and the Gulf War of the early 1990s.</bold> <italic>European Review</italic> 20(2), May 2012: 222–232.</p>
<p>This article examines Turkish politics and policies during the 1980s and 1990s in light of occurrences in Turkey and neighboring states, with particular attention to the impact of the 1980s PKK revolt and the outbreak of the Gulf War in 1990. It outlines the political debates among the major political parties and the perspectives of the Turkish army generals on the important political issues of the period. These events, and those of the subsequent decade, have led to the emergence of a new status quo in Turkey that has had major political and economic repercussions. [R]</p>
<p>62.5460 CARMODY, Pádraig — <bold>The scramble for biofuels and timber in Africa.</bold> <italic>Whitehead Journal of Diplomacy and International Relations</italic> 12(1), Winter-Spring 2011: 125–136.</p>
<p>The globalization of social systems is characterized by increasing entropy. It is this ordered entropy, together with the reactions of those who are opposed to it, which will define international relations in the 21st c. In order to understand entropy, the nature and organization of competition around two of the most important land-based natural resources in Africa—biofuels and timber—as well as their role in globalization need to be explained. While globalization is often thought to be associated with the rise of a global informational economy, natural resources remain central to understanding social relations of globalization, particularly in the context of the new scramble for Africa's natural resources. [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4433]</p>
<p>62.5461 CASE, William — <bold>Brunei in 2011: early electoralism and social progress.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 233–237.</p>
<p>Brunei Darussalam remained untroubled throughout 2011. The government experimented with greater political openness and social reforms. It organized an election for at least part of its Legislative Council. It continued to make advances on women's and environmental issues. Meanwhile, the oil-based economy mostly remained steady. Foreign relations were benign. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5462 CEBECI, Erol; ÜSTÜN, Kadir — <bold>The Syrian quagmire: what's holding Turkey back?</bold> <italic>Insight Turkey</italic> 14(2), 2012: 13–21.</p>
<p>While keeping the violence under a certain threshold so as not to provoke immediate international action, the Assad regime has benefited from the entangled and often conflicted international interests in Syria. The opposition has been unable to deal a serious blow to the regime and international pressure has so far yielded no major results. There exists no clear international leadership or consensus on how to handle Syria. The Arab League and Turkey, along with other countries, have created the “Friends of Syria” group after the failure of the UN Security Council resolution on Syria, but Russian and Iranian backing for the Assad regime is seriously limiting options. Given its support for the people against authoritarian regimes during the Arab Spring and its anti-Assad stance, expectations for Turkey to “do something” are increasingly more pronounced. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5463 CHADDA, Maya — <bold>India in 2011: the state encounters the people.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 114–129.</p>
<p>The year 2011 was marked by several important developments: a massive uprising of the people, spearheaded by a powerful civil society movement for the reform of India's corrupt and criminalized democracy; an attempt by the central government to reform antiquated land acquisition laws for public use; a growing disillusionment with the United Progressive Alliance government; the slowing down of India's eight-yearlong run of rapid growth; and a growing convergence of interests between India and other powers in the region, except China. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5464 CHAFE, William H. — <bold>The American narrative: is there one and what is it?</bold> <italic>Daedalus</italic>, Winter 2012: 11–17.</p>
<p>Nearly four centuries of American history have witnessed the evolving conflict between two competing sets of values: a belief that acting on behalf of the common good should guide social and political behavior, and a belief that unfettered individual freedom should dominate political and social life. Tracing this conflict from Puritanism through the American Revolution, the Civil War, the rise of industrialism, the Progressive Era, the New Deal, the Great Society, and the conservative revival of the Nixon/Reagan era, the essay reveals this clash of values as pivotal to understanding the narrative of American history, with contemporary political battles crystallizing just how basic this conflict has been. [R] [First article of a thematic issue, “On the American narrative”, edited and introduced, pp. 5–10, by Denis DONOGHUE. See also <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4799]</p>
<p>62.5465 CHELLANEY, Brahma — <bold>Asia's worsening water crisis.</bold> <italic>Survival</italic> 54(2), Apr.–May 2012: 143–156.</p>
<p>Asia is drawing on tomorrow's water to meet today's needs, threatening the continent's economic and political rise and environmental sustainability. [R]</p>
<p>62.5466 CHEN Ming-Tong — <bold>Taiwan in 2011: focus on crucial presidential election.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 72–80.</p>
<p>Developments in Taiwan's politics, economy, society, and external relations in 2011 were closely tied to the presidential election contest. In the months leading up to the election, incumbent President Ma Ying-jeou held a slight lead in the polls over DPP Chairwoman Tsai Ing-wen. J. Soong's late entry into the race had little impact on the outcome, and Ma Ying-jeou was re-elected. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5467 CHU Yin-Wah — <bold>Studies of Japanese society and culture: sociology and cognate disciplines in Hong Kong [China].</bold> <italic>Japanese Journal of Political Science</italic> 13(2), June 2012: 201–221.</p>
<p>This paper reviews the studies of Japanese society and culture undertaken by Hong Kong-based sociologists and scholars in related disciplines. It presents information on research projects funded by the Research Grants Council, Social Sciences Citation Index (SSCI), and Arts and Humanities Citation Index (A&amp;HCI) journal articles, authored and edited books, book chapters, non-SSCI and non-A&amp;HCI journal articles, as well as master and doctoral theses written by scholars and graduate students associated with Hong Kong's major universities. The main topics of research are Japan's capitalist development and corporate growth, meanings and social ramifications of traditional and popular culture, education, gender, and marriage, as well as aspects of work and employment, whereas the major research methods include document analysis, ethnography, and in-depth interviews. [R, abr.] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5517]</p>
<p>62.5468 COLBURN, Forrest D.; CRUZ S., Arturo — <bold>Personalism and populism in Nicaragua.</bold> <italic>Journal of Democracy</italic> 23(2), Apr. 2012: 104–118.</p>
<p>For much of its history, Nicaragua has shown a predilection for personalist and populist rule. What explains the persistence and allure of these phenomena, and what obstacles do they pose for democracy in Nicaragua? [R]</p>
<p>62.5469 COMPAIN, Florence — <bold>Birmanie: une démocratisation en trompe-l'oeil? (Burma [Myanmar]: a make-believe democratization?).</bold> <italic>Politique internationale</italic> 135, Spring 2012: 299–330.</p>
<p>Is Burma now experiencing its own <italic>perestroika</italic>, as a large number of Western observers seem o believe? The military junta in power since the 1962 coup d'état officially dissolved itself in 2011. Henceforth, the government says that it wants to move towards a “flourishing and disciplined democracy”. Emblematic regime opponent Aung San Suu Kyi was even elected to the parliament. In reality, the picture is not so idyllic. The head of state, Thein Sein, an unrestrained admirer of the North Korean regime, [is not] a real reformer. The new constitution, approved in 2008, has a number of shadow zones, and seems to leave considerable power in the hands of the military. A secret document drawn up by the authorities in 2004 indicates that recent advances would only be an illusion forged by the junta. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5470 COOK, David — <bold>The Arab Spring and failed political legitimacy.</bold> <italic>Hedgehog Review</italic> 13(3), Fall 2011: 37–45.</p>
<p>One can look at the Arab Spring in terms of classical political legitimacy, with the obvious exceptions of Algeria and the Sudan, both of which are ruled by military regimes searching for some type of legitimacy. The other major exception to the political-legitimacy interpretation is that of Iraq. Yet, a religious interpretation for the Arab Spring so far has been lacking. Both Tunisia's and Egypt's revolt could be seen as that of Muslim majorities against secularized elites. The most interesting development from a religious point of view has been the downfall of the anti-governmental jihad of the 1980s and 1990s in every country going through the Arab Spring, and the concurrent rise of the mainstream Muslim political opposition as exemplified by the Muslim Brotherhood.</p>
<p>62.5471 COOLEY, Laurence; PACE, Michelle — <bold>Consociation in a constant state of contingency? The case of the Palestinian Territory.</bold> <italic>Third World Quarterly</italic> 33(3), 2012: 541–558.</p>
<p>It has become common to regard consociational democracy as a method of managing conflict in ethnically divided societies, but little attention has been paid to its applicability to societies where the primary political cleavage is between secular and religious forces. This article examines the applicability of consociationalism to the case of the Palestinian Territory. While Palestinian society is characterized by “pillarization” along a secularist/Islamist cleavage, formal power-sharing between the representatives of the two main Palestinian factions—Fatah and Hamas—has proved elusive. However, rather than seeking to explain the seeming inability of the factions to share power by reference to the nature of the cleavage, we instead highlight the contextual factors that have made power-sharing difficult to achieve. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5472 CUNNINGHAM, Kathleen Gallagher; BAKKE, Kristin M.; SEYMOUR, Lee J. M. — <bold>Shirts today, skins tomorrow: dual contests and the effects of fragmentation in self-determination disputes.</bold> <italic>Journal of Conflict Resolution</italic> 56(1), Feb. 2012: 67–93.</p>
<p>Why do political organizations split? Drawing insight from organizational theory and social movement literature, this article explores the effect of organizational factors on group schism. Using a new data-set of 112 ethnopolitical organizations in the Middle East, the article examines to what extent organizational factors such as leadership structure, organizational legality, and tactical intensity, as well as contextual variables such as state violence and external support for the organization, influence group schism. [R, abr.] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4507]</p>
<p>62.5473 D'COSTA, Bina — <bold>Bangladesh in 2011: weak statebuilding and diffident foreign policy.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 147–156.</p>
<p>Bangladesh has achieved some impressive social and developmental goals in its health and education sectors. It has also effectively dealt with the adversities caused by the downturn of the global economy, and focused on strengthening its military capabilities to protect its national interests. However, environmental issues, growing international scrutiny about a fair war crimes trial, human rights concerns, the India-Bangladesh border, and transit and water-sharing arrangements remain key challenges. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5474 DALPINO, Catharin — <bold>Thailand in 2011: high tides and political tensions.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 195–201.</p>
<p>While the pro-Thaksin Pheu Thai Party was favored to win Thailand's parliamentary elections in July, the party's 53% majority gave it a mandate stronger than expected. However, two months into her administration, the government of Prime Minister Y. Shinawatra was challenged by Thailand's worst floods in half a century. The crisis initially exacerbated the partisan political divide and gave a new twist to the urban-rural tensions that fueled Thailand's five-year political crisis. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5475 DE CASTRO, Renato Cruz — <bold>The Philippines in 2011: muddling through a year of learning and adjustment.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 210–219.</p>
<p>Early this year, a majority of Filipinos indicated in a national survey that they are not sure if B. Aquino III will succeed or fail in his presidency. This uncertainty stems from his unconventional style of governance and the gravity of the domestic and international problems he faces. Moreover, his style of governance is generally perceived by the Filipinos as reactive and lackluster—a fact attributed to his first year in office, a difficult period of learning and adjustment. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5476 DE SAS KROPIWNICKI, Zosa Olenka — <bold>The politics of child prostitution in South Africa.</bold> <italic>Journal of Contemporary African Studies</italic> 30(2), Apr. 2012: 235–265.</p>
<p>This paper argues that policies, interventions and discourses pertaining to child prostitution have been guided by overarching political agendas that have masked the underlying structural basis of this phenomenon. These political agendas have shifted in accordance with the locus of power, control and resistance in South Africa since the 19th c. On the basis of a historical analysis, this paper identifies distinct periods in which child prostitution was used to legitimate policies in favor of social control rather than social development. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5477 DORAN, Charles F. — <bold>Power cycle theory and the ascendance of China: peaceful or stormy?</bold> <italic>SAIS Review of International Affairs</italic> 32(1), Winter-Spring 2012: 73–88.</p>
<p>The greatest issue facing statecraft today is the assimilation of China into the system of the great powers. With uncertainty in the international system increasing concurrently as China transitions through critical points along its current power trajectory, this essay seeks to provide foreign policy makers intimately involved in US-China relations with a broader understanding of the distinction between Chinese engagement and appeasement by comparing applications of the principles of relative power change embedded in power cycle theory to China's troubled past and historic cases of large-scale conflict. [R]</p>
<p>62.5478 DŽIHIĆ, Vedran; SEGERT, Dieter — <bold>Lessons from “post-Yugoslav” democratization: functional problems of stateness and the limits of democracy.</bold> <italic>East European Politics and Societies</italic> 26(2), May 2012: 239–253.</p>
<p>State weakness is one of the main obstacles for democratic stability. Yet [in] certain circumstances, even a mere electoral democracy may gain stable support from the citizenry. Mere electoral democracy is best understood as a regime of elite governance endowed by a certain support from the citizens but without any ambition of the ruling elite to increase the quality of democratic rule. This article explores the historical reasons of this specific type of political regime in Bosnia and Herzegovina, Croatia, and Serbia. Departing from the empirical examples from the Western Balkans, the article comes to some rather general conclusions about the concept and sequence of democratization: Conducting elections too early may produce serious challenges to sustainable democratization. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5479 EL KAROUI, Hakim — <bold>Où va le monde arabe? (Where is the Arab world going?).</bold> <italic>Le Débat</italic> 169, March-Apr. 2012: 4–17.</p>
<p>One year after the “Arab Spring”, an analysis of Arab prospects proves necessary in the currently paradoxical situation: democracy has been delivered of an Islamism that only yesterday admitted its abhorrence for it; the West seems to have disappeared from a region where it used to be omnipresent and where its political system is being imposed; Qatar, the West's great friend, seeks to impose its <italic>Pax Qatari</italic>. As far as the economy is concerned, not only has it not started off again, but it seems to be altogether absent from the debates, even if the revolutions were incited by the social situation. Three surprises therefore need to be analyzed: political, geopolitical and economic. [First article on “The current state of the Arab revolutions. Part II”. See also <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5449. Part I, See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5330]</p>
<p>62.5480 El-KHAWAS, Mohamed — <bold>Egypt's unfinished revolution [2011—].</bold> <italic>Mediterranean Quarterly</italic> 23(1), Winter 2012: 52–66.</p>
<p>Egypt's revolution has produced odd results. President H. Mubarak was replaced in 2011 by the military, which plans to stay in office until 2013. The interim government has been trying to reconcile the differing demands of young revolutionaries and emerging political parties. It has been struggling to deal with an ailing economy and deteriorating security. Although the goal is to transfer power to a democratically elected government, building an infrastructure for sustainable democratic institutions has been slow, messy, and difficult. Youth are disappointed in the outcome of their efforts to reform the country, fearing that the demands that triggered the revolution may not be met. [R]</p>
<p>62.5481 ELGINDY, Khaled — <bold>Egypt's troubled transition: elections without democracy.</bold> <italic>Washington Quarterly</italic> 35(2), Spring 2012: 89–104.</p>
<p>The most formidable threat to Egyptian democracy comes from the ruling military council itself, which may end up leaving Egypt looking less like Turkey and more like Pakistan, where a military that refuses to truly relinquish power results in a weak and dysfunctional government. [R]</p>
<p>62.5482 EMMERSON, Donald K. — <bold>Southeast Asia: minding the gap between democracy and governance.</bold> <italic>Journal of Democracy</italic> 23(2), Apr. 2012: 62–73.</p>
<p>Do democracy and good governance necessarily go hand-in-hand? In most Southeast Asian countries, a gap exists between the two. How should we understand good governance in an authoritarian context? And what does poor governance mean for the legitimacy of democracy? [R]</p>
<p>62.5483 ENNKER, Benno — <bold>Zweierlei Krisen in Russland: Machterosion und Neuorientierung (Dual crises in Russia: power erosion and new orientation).</bold> <italic>Osteuropa</italic> 62(3), March 2012: 3–20.</p>
<p>After its [2012] presidential election, Russia's political situation only seems clear. Although V. Putin will again become president, the political system is more fragile than ever: the rulers' legitimacy is weak; the modernizing impulse of the last decade has faded. The structural weaknesses of a form of state capitalism in which bureaucratic elites strive to exhaust the revenues derived from raw material exports remain unsolved. The power vertical is eroding. The democracy movement, however, has also reached a dead end. The politics of the street has exhausted itself. It too faces a re-orientation. [R]</p>
<p>62.5484 EVANS, Geoffrey; ROSE, Pauline — <bold>Understanding education's influence on support for democracy in Sub-Saharan Africa.</bold> <italic>Journal of Development Studies</italic> 48(4), Apr. 2012: 498–515.</p>
<p>Is education consequential for popular endorsement of democracy in developing societies and, if so, what are the mechanisms that account for this influence? We investigate the micro-foundations of the education-democracy nexus using a survey of 18 sub-Saharan African countries. We demonstrate that educational level is the strongest influence on support for democracy and rejection of non-democratic alternatives via its impact on comprehension of, and attention to, politics. This is consistent with a cognitive interpretation of the effects of education on democratic values rather than one which treats education as a marker of economic resource inequalities. [R]</p>
<p>62.5485 FAIR, C. Christine — <bold>Pakistan in 2011: ten years of the “war on terror”.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 100–113.</p>
<p>Pakistan came into sharp conflict with the US and the international community in 2011 over its long-standing support of Islamist militants. The killing of Osama bin Laden left many speculating whether Pakistan's intelligence agencies were either complicit in harboring him or incompetent. Pakistan's various conflicts, as well as Pakistan Taliban violence, continue to claim thousands of lives. Economic growth remains inadequate to provide jobs for its ever-growing population, and both the civilian and military leaderships appear unwilling to make structural economic changes to attract vital international developmental aid. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5486 FARHAT, Nadim — <bold>Le conflit communautaire belge entre contingence identitaire et déterminisme historique. Analyse de <italic>path dependence</italic> de la formation des communautés et des trajectoires institutionnelles (The Belgian communal conflict between contingent identities and historical determinism. A path dependence analysis of the communities' formation and institutional trajectories).</bold> <italic>Revue française de Science politique</italic> 62(2), Apr. 2012: 231–254. [Résumé en français]</p>
<p>In the context of the communal relationships in Belgium, the evocation of past causes is common-place in the analysis of the tensions and conflicts that mark these relations. The adoption of the path dependence framework of analysis elaborated in the field of historical sociology allows testing the affirmation that the Belgian past shapes the conflictual present. The recourse to this theoretical and methodological scaffold seeks to explain, by following the evolution of a historical trajectory initiated at the end of the 19th c., the regular conflicts and the model of increasing autonomy that characterize Belgian political scene. [R]</p>
<p>62.5487 FARIS, David M. — <bold>La révolte en réseau: le “printemps arabe” et les médias sociaux (Network uprisings: The “Arab Spring” and the social media).</bold> <italic>Politique étrangère</italic> 77(1), Spring 2012: 99–110. [Résumé en français]</p>
<p>In Egypt, digital activism has developed since the mid-2000s, with many bloggers contributing to the denunciation of the abuses by the Mubarak regime. This phenomenon did not emerge in Tunisia, given the censorship of internet. However, in the two cases, blogs, along with the <italic>Facebook</italic> social network, played an important role in the 2011 revolutions. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5543]</p>
<p>62.5488 FFORDE, Adam — <bold>Vietnam in 2011: questions of domestic sovereignty.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 176–185.</p>
<p>Tensions in the international arena are linked here to problems in contemporary Vietnam. Eroding domestic political authority is related to the lack of political reconstruction to suit a market economy and an increasingly open society. At the close of 2011, it appears that there is as yet no clear path forward. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5489 FILALI-ANSARY, Abdou — <bold>The languages of the Arab revolutions [2010–2011].</bold> <italic>Journal of Democracy</italic> 23(2), Apr. 2012: 5–18.</p>
<p>The upheavals that have been shaking the Arab-Muslim world are revolutions in discourse as well as in the streets. Arabs are using not only traditional and religious vocabularies, but also a new set of expressions that are modern and represent popular aspirations. [R]</p>
<p>62.5490 FLANDREAU, Marc; FLORES, Juan H. — <bold>The peaceful conspiracy: bond markets and international relations during the Pax Britannica.</bold> <italic>International Organization</italic> 66(2), Apr. 2012: 211–241.</p>
<p>This article provides foundations to K. Polanyi's famed argument that monopoly power in the global capital market served as an instrument of peace during the <italic>Pax Britannica</italic> (1815–1914). We focus on the role of intermediaries and certification. We show that when information and enforcement are imperfect, there is scope for the endogenous emergence of “prestigious” intermediaries who enjoy a monopoly position and as a result, control government actions. They can implement conditional lending: they subject the distribution of credit to the adoption of peaceful policies. Prestigious intermediaries act that way because of their concern with maintaining an unblemished track record when wars increased risks of default. Our analysis, which brings together insights from different disciplines, provides a significant extension to, and departure from, recent research on how countries accumulate reputational capital. [R]</p>
<p>62.5491 FLEMING, Michael — <bold>The regime of violence in socialist and postsocialist Poland.</bold> <italic>Annals of the Association of American Geographers</italic> 102(2), March 2012: 482–498.</p>
<p>This article contributes to the geographical debate about the nature of violence in socialist and post-socialist Poland. It responds to M. Bradshaw and A. Stenning's (<italic>East Central Europe and the Former Soviet Union: The Post-Socialist States</italic>, London, 2004) call to account for the uniqueness of post-socialism. By comparing “regimes of violence”, which characterize particular socio-economic formations, a clearer conception of post-socialism can emerge, showing how different configurations of violence have dominated the socialist and post-socialist periods, respectively, and how violence has been directed toward non-Polish ethnocultural groups. The article indicates the important role that representational violence is playing in making post-socialism, where class-for-itself subjectivities are specific targets of marginalization. [R]</p>
<p>62.5492 FRINGS, Marc — <bold>Zivilgesellschaft in Indonesien (Civil society in Indonesia).</bold> <italic>Aus Politik und Zeitgeschichte</italic> 62(11–12), 12 March 2012: 43–49.</p>
<p>Civil society has strongly gained in influence in Indonesia since 1998, in particular NGOs, which now fulfill a central watchdog function against the powerful. Following the political and administrative decentralization, NGOs with political agendas are also active at the grassroots level which was previously dominated by social organizations. [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5495]</p>
<p>62.5493 FUKUOKA, Yuki — <bold>Politics, business and the state in post-Soeharto Indonesia.</bold> <italic>Contemporary Southeast Asia</italic> 34(1), Apr. 2012: 80–100.</p>
<p>In Indonesia, democratic transition has led to the ascendance of business in the political arena. A growing number of entrepreneurs-turned-politicians have captured office, taking over positions previously been held by bureaucratic elites. Despite the expectation that post-Suharto Indonesia would embark on a swift process of change towards a regulatory state, the patrimonial features of the Indonesian state continue to display more fundamental continuity. This article presents an alternative framework through which to better understand changing state-business relations in Indonesia. It argues that the fall of the Suharto regime in Indonesia has had the effect of facilitating the transformation of the patrimonial state: from a patrimonial administrative state to a patrimonial oligarchic state. Democratization has changed the old hierarchy of state-business relations over the distribution of patronage. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5494 GAINSBOROUGH, Martin — <bold>Southeast Asia: elites vs. reform in Laos, Cambodia, and Vietnam.</bold> <italic>Journal of Democracy</italic> 23(2), Apr. 2012: 34–46.</p>
<p>Vietnam and its smaller neighbors Laos and Cambodia remain bastions of illiberalism and one-party rule despite rapid economic growth and falling poverty. What will it take to reform their elitist political cultures and curtail the use of public office for private ends? [R]</p>
<p>62.5495 GAMINO, Doris K. — <bold>Annäherung an ein unbekanntes Land (Approaching an unkown country [Indonesia]).</bold> <italic>Aus Politik und Zeitgeschichte</italic> 62(11–12), 12 March 2012: 3–8.</p>
<p>There is no such person as “an Indonesian”: the country has a population of 240 million, divided between 300 ethnic groups and 17, 000 islands. Since Suharto's fall in 1998 Indonesia has undergone a political transformation process with in first freely elected president in 2004. Despite the current economic boom, the country remains governed by old habits of corruption and kleptocracy. [First article of a thematic issue on “Indonesia”. See also <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4663, 5024, 5492, 5503, 5525, 5546, 5592]</p>
<p>62.5496 GEORG, Co-Pierre; MEINERT, Philipp — <bold>Globale Finanzmarktaufsicht (The global financial market outlook).</bold> <italic>Aus Politik und Zeitgeschichte</italic> 62(13), 26 March 2012: 35–40.</p>
<p>The international regulatory framework for banks (Basel III) contains considerable improvements in the coordination of monitoring of financial markets. The causes of market failure have become easier to control; but a similar mechanism for the failure of politics has yet to be invented. Although the stability pact was reinforced, this has nothing to do with the market distortions that were politically motivated. [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5247]</p>
<p>62.5497 GHOBADZADEH, Naser; RAHIM, Lily Zubaidah — <bold>Islamic reformation discourses: popular sovereignty and religious secularisation in Iran.</bold> <italic>Democratization</italic> 19(2), Apr. 2012: 334–351.</p>
<p>Disputes over the outcome of the June 2009 presidential election in Iran rapidly developed into a contest about the legitimacy of the Islamic state. Far from being a dispute between religious and non-religious forces, the main protagonists in the conflict represented divergent articulations of state-religion relations within an Islamic context. In contrast to the authoritarian legitimization of an Islamic state, the Islamic reformation discourse is based on secular-democratic articulations of state-religion relations. This article focuses on the ideas of four leading Iranian religious scholars who advocate a secular-democratic conceptualization of state authority. Disputing the religious validity of divine sovereignty, they promote the principle of popular sovereignty based on Islamic sources and methods. This reformist conceptualization is rooted in the notion that Islam and the secular-democratic state are complementary. [R]</p>
<p>62.5498 GLEAVE, Eric; ROBBINS, Blaine; KOLKO, Beth — <bold>Trust in Uzbekistan.</bold> <italic>International Political Science Review</italic> 33(2), March 2012: 209–229.</p>
<p>Although trust is a lively area of research, it is rarely investigated in countries outside of commonly available cross-national public-opinion datasets. In an effort to fill this empirical void and to draw conclusions concerning the general determinants of trust, the current article employs detailed survey data from a frequently overlooked Central Asian country, Uzbekistan, to test the relationship between particularized trust and demographic traits previously identified as influential. While a number of Uzbek demographic characteristics coincide with previously identified determinants of trust, age and education yield negative effects not previously found. Interestingly, individual-level demographic variables become insignificant when controlling for regional, religious, and linguistic variation. We conclude with a discussion of the theoretical implications. [R]</p>
<p>62.5499 GONZÁLEZ MARRERO, Secundino — <bold>La democracia en Sudáfrica (Democracy in South Africa).</bold> <italic>Revista española de Ciencia política</italic> 28, March 2012: 55–84.</p>
<p>The transition to democracy in South Africa carried with it an enormous emotional burden as well as an interesting challenge to political science. Emotional, because of the characteristics of the outgoing authoritarian regime, based on racial segregation and the political exclusion of most of the population. Emotional, also, due to the charisma and great civic example of someone. Nelson Mandela who understood that the future of South Africa depended on avoidance all types of revenge on, or exclusion of, the once exclusionary segment. An institutional system that would allow for the harmonious coexistence of different ethnic groups in the country was necessary. And that is where political science played a key role. Directly inspired by the work of Arend Lijphart, the South African transition was carried out according to an institutional design almost based entirely on the paradigm of “consensus democracy”. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5500 GOODHAND, Jonathan — <bold>Sri Lanka in 2011: consolidation and militarization of the post-war regime.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 130–137.</p>
<p>Local elections consolidated the M. Rajapaksa administration's grip on power. State-led efforts to stimulate economic growth continued with major infrastructure projects in the northeastern and southern parts of Sri Lanka. No significant progress was made toward a political settlement and reconciliation with the Tamil community, and the government came under increasing international pressure about its conduct in the last months of the civil war after the release of the UN Advisory Panel report. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5501 GREENWOOD, Maja Touzari Janesdatter; WAEVER, Ole — <bold>København-Kairo, Tur-Retur: en sikkerhedsteori møder revolutionen (Copenhagen-Cairo on a roundtrip: a security theory meets the revolutions).</bold> <italic>Tidsskriftet Politik</italic> 15(1), 2012: 15–25.</p>
<p>Securitization Theory has been criticized for limited applicability to the non-western world. When, in 2010, the Center for Advanced Security Theory began a collaboration with the Danish Egyptian Dialogue Institute and Al-Ahram Center for Political and Strategic Studies in Cairo, Securitization Theory was challenged on two levels: the theory was to both analyze and act politically in a Middle Eastern context, and then during the Arab Spring, the role of the entire Egyptian security sector was re-evaluated. These unique circumstances prompted reflections on the use of non-traditional and traditional security concepts, how the Egyptian revolution could be understood through Securitization Theory, as well as what the experiences of this project will mean for further theory development. This article discusses these points in light of the Danish delegation's experiences. [R, abr.] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5594]</p>
<p>62.5502 GRIGORIADIS, Ioannis; ÖZER, Irmak — <bold>Mutations of Turkish nationalism: from neo-nationalism to the Ergenekon affair.</bold> <italic>Middle East Policy</italic> 17(4), Winter 2010: 101–113.</p>
<p>Turkish nationalism has undergone significant transformation since the 1980s. The end of the Cold War allowed for rapprochement between leftist and rightist forces which found a common enemy in globalization and European integration. The rise of <italic>ulusalcilik</italic>, neo-nationalism, is the most characteristic fruit of this process. With an anti-Western and isolationist agenda, it aimed to counter Turkey's democratic reform process. The Ergenekon affair demonstrated how both traditional and new nationalists can cooperate to derail Turkey's European integration by toppling its democratic regime.</p>
<p>62.5503 GROSSMANN, Kristina; PATOCK, Roman; STANGE, Gunnar — <bold>Aceh nach Konflikt und Tsunami (Aceh [Indonesia] between the [secession] conflict and the [2004] tsunami).</bold> <italic>Aus Politik und Zeitgeschichte</italic> 62(11–12), 12 March 2012: 37–43.</p>
<p>The tsunami disaster in the Aceh province in December 2004 occurred in the middle of a war of secession. It triggered a dynamic that cut through the political, social and economic paralysis. Aceh remains the only province to have introduced the <italic>Sharia</italic> criminal law, but the situation is much less tense than during the conflict, and the fear and uncertainty of this period seem to have disappeared. [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5495]</p>
<p>62.5504 GUARDIANCICH, Igor — <bold>The uncertain future of Slovenian exceptionalism.</bold> <italic>East European Politics and Societies</italic> 26(2), May 2012: 380–399.</p>
<p>The political-economy literature has so far almost unanimously regarded Slovenia as the social-democratic exception in Central and Eastern Europe, due to a combination of highly consensual democratic institutions, low party polarization, strong social partners, and developed social dialogue. However, the situation, since the fall of the Liberal Democracy of Slovenia (LDS), which governed in 1992–2004, seems to be swiftly changing. Polarization has increased, union legitimacy declined, and social dialogue—especially in the aftermath of the 2007–2009 financial crisis—has all but collapsed. The 2010 pension reform is an archetypical example of how Slovenia now much more resembles its quarrelsome Eastern neighbors than the idealized exception that political scientists usually point at. [R]</p>
<p>62.5505 HABIYAREMYE, Alexis — <bold>CHINAFRIQUE, AFRICOM, and African natural resources: a modern scramble for Africa?</bold> <italic>Whitehead Journal of Diplomacy and International Relations</italic> 12(1), Winter-Spring 2011: 79–93.</p>
<p>Africa's endowment in natural resources is widely recognized as phenomenal. In the post 9/11 [2001] context, African oil and strategic mineral ores have been increasingly seen by the US administration as being of “vital US interest”. This led to an enhanced US military involvement in Africa, to secure unimpeded access to these resources. For similar reasons, China, as an emerging economic giant, has also significantly increased its presence in Africa to become a major trade partner. In this geopolitical configuration of Sino-American rivalry, whether resource-rich African countries stand to benefit from their natural resources will depend on the ability of their leaders to put in place the necessary infrastructure and institutions that enable them to add value to these resources and exorcise the “resource curse”. [A] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4433]</p>
<p>62.5506 HADDAD, Bassam — <bold>Syria's stalemate: the limits of regime resilience.</bold> <italic>Middle East Policy</italic> 19(1), Spring 2012: 85–95.</p>
<p>The stalemate between regime and opposition in Syria has been constructed as a zero-sum game from the very beginning, increasing the risks tremendously for all parties involved, most notably for the regime. The actors opposing the regime include the army, uniformed security forces and paramilitary groups; opposing groups that attempt to undermine the cohesion; nonviolent forces which confront the suppressing security apparatuses in demonstrations and protests; elements within the nonviolent groups who engage in violence and try to drag the others along. Social “incubators” support both protesters and the regime. Such breakdown acknowledges the peaceful and democratic nature of the opposition, but also indicates the increasingly militarized elements that have confronted the regime, particularly since the summer of 2011.</p>
<p>62.5507 HADIZ, Vedi R.; ROBISON, Richard — <bold>Political economy and Islamic politics: insights from the Indonesian case.</bold> <italic>New Political Economy</italic> 17(2), Apr. 2012: 137–155.</p>
<p>We argue that the trajectory of Islamic politics in Indonesia has been shaped within larger processes of state-formation and socio-economic and political changes associated with the advance of the market economy and the pressures of globalization. We incorporate the Indonesian case into a vast and well-developed debate hitherto focused on North Africa and the Middle East. We offer a distinct interpretation that goes beyond the prevailing understanding of Islamic politics in Indonesia as the product of conflicts over ideas, doctrine or culture or the institutional requisites of authoritarianism or democracy. Islamic politics has been underpinned variously by the conservatism of small propertied interests, the populism of marginalized urban and small town middle classes and the ambitions of the upper middle classes and business. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5508 HANKS, Reuel R. — <bold>Crisis in Kyrgyzstan: conundrums of ethnic conflict, national identity and state cohesion.</bold> <italic>Journal of Balkan and Near Eastern Studies</italic> 13(2), June 2011: 177–188.</p>
<p>A closer look at the causes and consequences of the cycles of violence that have plagued interethnic relations in southern Kyrgyzstan for the past two decades allows for the identification and contextualization of factors, underlining such destructive behavior, in a country that only a few years ago was promoting itself as “Switzerland of Central Asia”. While ethnic differences certainly provide some basis for the violence, economic, social and political issues are frequently the triggers for heightened friction between the Kyrgyz and the Uzbeks. Often lost in the discussion is the fact that Central Asia is a post-colonial space. Political stabilization in Kyrgyzstan is of utmost importance to the security and development of the entire region, and is closely linked to American and Western interests there.</p>
<p>62.5509 HAOKIP, Thongkholal — <bold>Political integration of Northeast India: a historical analysis.</bold> <italic>Strategic Analysis</italic> 36(2), March 2012: 304–314.</p>
<p>Most nation-states in Asia and Africa that gained independence from colonial rulers during the middle of the 20th c. are diverse in their ethnic composition. The national governments make efforts to politically integrate their constituent units in the face of the continuing resistance of several ethnic groups. India adopted various means to integrate the more than 600 princely states and other loosely administered areas. Although the issue of integration has been largely settled in the mainland, various radical groups in the Northeastern region still question the extension of the Indian state. This article provides a historical analysis of the process of integration of the various states of Northeast India. [R]</p>
<p>62.5510 HARADA, Yutaka — <bold>Policy issues regarding the Japanese economy—the Great Recession, inequality, budget deficit and the aging population.</bold> <italic>Japanese Journal of Political Science</italic> 13(2), June 2012: 223–253.</p>
<p>This paper discusses issues relating to the Great Recession, inequality, and the budget deficit and burden of an aging population. Japan's Great Recession is basically explained by monetary shocks. Just the bubble and its bursting are not solely responsible for the prolonged slump. There is no empirical evidence for the assertion that certain structural problems lessened the efficiency of the Japanese economy in the 1990s. TFP (total factor productivity) in the 1990s did not decline compared with the early 1980s. Fiscal policy and the diminution of the financial intermediary function can explain the Great Recession only in small part. [R, abr.] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5517]</p>
<p>62.5511 HAZONY, Yoram — <bold>Ist die Idee des Nationalstaats überholt? Israel aus europäischer Sicht (Is the idea of the nation-state obsolete? Israel—the European perspective).</bold> <italic>Merkur</italic> 65(1), Jan. 2011: 1–18.</p>
<p>If the growing hostility towards Israel is motivated by the fact that the nation-state no longer rallies support, how come the sharpest critics of Israel are advocating the creation of a sovereign nation-state for the Palestinian Arabs? According to the new paradigm, Israel's right to statehood (from a European perspective) is outdated, and should be replaced with the Kantian argument whereby true moral perfection is achieved only through self-denial, as in the creation of the EU, where both people and nations finally surrender their sovereignty. Only when Europeans instead become aware of their national traditions and independence, will the Israeli context perhaps become relevant in a positive way.</p>
<p>62.5512 HILAL, Leila — <bold>Charting transitions in the Middle East: lessons learned from Tunisia and Egypt.</bold> <italic>Insight Turkey</italic> 14(2), 2012: 1–12.</p>
<p>Egypt and Tunisia saw mass street protestors quickly topple entrenched autocrats without significant violence or foreign intervention. One year on, Egypt is still ruled by elements of the Mubarak regime with vested interests in the former order. It is also racked by political battles and economic troubles that are threatening its transition. Tunisia, on the other hand, is moving steadily closer toward a potential democratic consolidation. What explains the differences? This commentary discusses the prior institutional characteristics of the two countries. It then examines three areas of early transitional choices that contributed to Tunisia's progress and undermined Egypt's. It [argues] that oppositional movements should avoid constitutional and institutional vacuums, establish broadly representative civilian-led transitional planning mechanisms, and follow appropriately-timed, transparent electoral sequencing. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5513 HWANG Insang — <bold>Recent studies on the Japanese economy and business in South Korea.</bold> <italic>Japanese Journal of Political Science</italic> 13(2), June 2012: 265–298.</p>
<p>This study summarizes and discusses the trends and main features of South Korean studies on Japan's economy and business since the 1960s. I consulted 271 publications (articles and books) for this study. Academic and individual publications comprise 69.7% (189 publications) of the total; public and corporate research institutes 30.3% (82 publications). Therefore, academic and individual researches constitute a majority of the publications. The most pressing issues for South Korea are those of business administration, such as Japanese corporate governance, Zaibatsu, and Japanese firms, which have been mainly studied by academic and individual researchers. The second most important issues are those of international economics such as FTA, FDI, and the trade deficit between South Korea and Japan, mainly researched by government research institutes and individual researchers. [R, abr.] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5517]</p>
<p>62.5514 JENSEN, Steffen — <bold>Shosholoza: political culture in South Africa between the secular and the occult.</bold> <italic>Journal of Southern African Studies</italic> 38(1), March 2012: 91–106.</p>
<p>I explore the relationship between two central strands in contemporary political culture in South Africa, the secular and the occult. These two strands are often seen as running parallel to one another and perceived as mutually exclusive, where one is dominant while the other is confined to obscurity and rendered invisible. Contrary to this view, I argue that historically both strands have co-existed in South Africa, and further that they animate one another. Indeed in South African politics the secular and the occult co-exist interdependently; their separation is a practice that legitimates specific forms of politics and the formation of political culture. I explore and illustrate the co-dependency and intertwining of these political strands through ethnographic data collected in Mpumalanga between 2002 and 2006 relating to witchcraft accusations. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5515 JOHNSON, Deborah — <bold>Sri Lanka—a divided [Catholic] Church in a divided polity: the brokerage of a struggling institution.</bold> <italic>Contemporary South Asia</italic> 20(1), March 2012: 77–90.</p>
<p>As analysts observe the “retreat” of the promise of secular modernity, it is easy to be left with little or no grounded understanding of how religious organizations are engaging in spaces of contested politics or how this engagement can help us to understand more appropriately what “religion” or “politics” mean to individuals and communities on personal and organizational levels. Within this broader debate, this paper introduces a research project that explores one form of religious practice: the ability of religious leaders to cross violent or politicized borders in times of contestation and conflict. The empirical focus on the Sri Lankan Catholic Church, in Tamil areas in the north, presents the activity of priests in such circumstances as a form of “brokerage”, facilitated and constrained by their religious, institutional setting. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5516 JORDÁN, Javier — <bold>Una aportación empírica al debate teórico sobre la naturaleza organizativa del terrorismo yihadista en Europa occidental (An empirical contribution to the theoretical debate on the organizational nature of Jihadist terrorism in Western Europe).</bold> <italic>Revista española de Ciencia política</italic> 28, March 2012: 87–106.</p>
<p>This paper presents the first results of a research project on the activity and organizational structure of Jihadist terrorism in Western Europe. It also offers an empirical contribution to the theoretical debate on the nature of that terrorism; specifically the relevance of formal organizations, particularly Central Al Qaeda, and its implications, based on information from open sources on a sample of 85 terrorist incidents between 2001 and 2010. The analysis focuses on three aspects: the relationships of terrorist cells with larger organizations, their links with training camps abroad, and Jihadi insurgency scenarios and the degree of success of terrorist incidents. [R]</p>
<p>62.5517 KAMO, Yoshinori — <bold>Sociological analyses of Japanese society in Japan, 2005–2010.</bold> <italic>Japanese Journal of Political Science</italic> 13(2), June 2012: 165–190.</p>
<p>Japanese sociologists' work on Japanese society from 2005 through 2010 is critically examined. Articles published in the <italic>Japanese Sociological Review</italic> (<italic>JSR</italic>) during this period are analyzed along with books reviewed in the same journal. These publications are classified by their substantive areas and types of inquiries (quantitative, qualitative, theory, etc.). “Culture and social consciousness” is the area where the largest numbers of articles and books have been recognized by <italic>JSR</italic>, followed by “class, stratification, and mobility” and “industry, labor, and organization”. Overall characteristics of sociological studies of Japanese society in Japan are summarized. The discrepancy between contemporary social phenomena and sociological research is also noted, using an example of freeters and neets, among others. [R] [First article of a thematic issue on “Japanese studies in Japan and its vicinities: economics and sociology”, edited and introduced by Takashi INOGUCHI. See also <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4553, 5467, 5510, 5513, 5552]</p>
<p>62.5518 KARAGIANNIS, Emmanuel — <bold>European converts to Islam: mechanisms of radicalization.</bold> <italic>Politics, Religion and Ideology</italic> 13(1), March 2012: 99–113.</p>
<p>While European converts to Islam represent only a tiny percentage of Europe's Muslim population, members of that group have participated in major Islamist terrorist plots and attacks on European soil. Although the radicalization process has not been the same for all individuals, it could be still possible to understand the circumstances under which some European converts turned to violence. Therefore, the article focuses on a number of mechanisms that may have contributed to the radicalization of European jihadi converts, including personal victimization, political grievance, the slippery slope effect, the power of love and the inspirational preaching. [R]</p>
<p>62.5519 KATZ, Katrin; CHA, Victor — <bold>South Korea in 2011: holding ground as the region's linchpin.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 52–64.</p>
<p>The year 2011 saw South Korea deepen bilateral cooperation with the US while building its status as a global player on the international stage. These developments were facilitated by broader regional dynamics—particularly with respect to Japan and China—that helped push Washington and Seoul closer together. Key issues with the potential to redirect South Korea's bilateral and global trajectories in the coming months include the Korea-US Free Trade Agreement, the death of Kim Jong-il and policy toward North Korea, and election-year politics in South Korea. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5520 KAUFMANN, Eric, <italic>ed.</italic> — <bold>Dissidents in the North, economic crisis in the South. Is the peace dividend safe?. A symposium on Northern Ireland.</bold> <italic>Political Quarterly</italic> 83(2), Apr.–June 2012: 203–298.</p>
<p>Editor's introduction, “The Northern Ireland Peace Process in an age of austerity”, pp. 203–209. Contributions by Kevin BEAN, “‘New dissidents are but old provisionals writ large’? The dynamics of dissident republicanism in the new Northern Ireland”, pp. 210–218; Jonathan TONGE, “‘No-one likes us, we don't care’: ‘dissident’ Irish republicans and mandates”, pp. 219–226; Martyn FRAMPTON, “Dissident Irish republican violence: a resurgent threat?”, pp. 227–236; Peter SHIRLOW, “A prosperity of thought in an age of austerity: the case of Ulster loyalism”, pp. 238–246; Henry PATTERSON, “Unionism after Good Friday and St Andrews”, pp. 247–255; Niall Ó DOCHARTAIGH, “Republicanism domesticated? All-Ireland politics in an age of austerity”, pp. 256–264; Paul DIXON, “In defense of politics: interpreting the peace process and the future of Northern Ireland”, pp. 265–276; John BEW and Martyn FRAMPTON, “Debating the ‘stalemate’: a response to Dr. Dixon”, pp. 277–282; Paul DIXON, “Bew and Frampton: recognizably neoconservative”, pp. 283–286; Mark DEVENPORT, “The media in Northern Ireland: a Stormont correspondent's view”, pp. 287–291; Greg McLAUGHLIN and Stephen BAKER, “The media, the peace dividend and ‘bread and butter’ politics”, pp. 292–298.</p>
<p>62.5521 KAZAMIAS, Alexander — <bold>The “anger revolutions” in the Middle East: an answer to decades of failed reform.</bold> <italic>Journal of Balkan and Near Eastern Studies</italic> 13(2), June 2011: 143–156.</p>
<p>This article analyzes the events of the “Arab Spring” in their earlier stages. It argues that the popular revolts in Tunisia, Egypt and Libya possess the hallmarks of what historians would normally describe as “revolutions”, but uses primary evidence to dispute the widespread assertion that these should be explained as “<italic>Facebook</italic> revolutions”. The core thesis is that the recent uprisings in the Middle East mark the beginning of the end of the post-colonial Arab state. Following a prolonged crisis originating in the mid-1970s, the post-colonial Arab states degenerated into patrimonial autocracies that failed to modernize despite substantial Western economic and political support. The 2010–2011 revolutions are presented as the culmination of a protracted historical crisis. [A]</p>
<p>62.5522 KER-LINDSAY, James; ECONOMIDES, Spyros — <bold>Standards before status before accession: Kosovo's EU perspective.</bold> <italic>Journal of Balkan and Near Eastern Studies</italic> 14(1), March 2012: 77–92.</p>
<p>Although Kosovo has been recognized by most members of the EU, five states still refuse to accept its unilateral declaration of independence. Kosovo's “European perspective” would therefore appear to be hampered by its contested status. However, while the dispute over its independence is significant, and certainly makes establishing relations with the EU more difficult than might otherwise have been the case, it is not as problematic as it may appear. For the meantime, Kosovo remains a long way away from meeting even the most basic requirements for formal EU integration. At this stage, the key task facing the EU is state-building. Somewhat paradoxically, this has not required a united position on status. Only when Kosovo is ready for full EU membership would its contested status become a wholly decisive issue for its “European perspective”. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5523 KIMURA, Ehito — <bold>Indonesia in 2011: a glass half-empty.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 186–194.</p>
<p>Corruption and political infighting continued to dominate the headlines in Indonesia in 2011. While lawmakers and political parties continued to be deeply unpopular, new developments dragged President S. Bambang Yudhoyono's popularity down to all-time lows. Religious violence ticked upward and took new forms. Meanwhile, the economy posted strong gains, and the government continued to look for ways to raise its profile on the international stage. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5524 KLEINMANN, Scott Matthew — <bold>Radicalization of homegrown Sunni militants in the United States: comparing converts and non-converts.</bold> <italic>Studies in Conflict and Terrorism</italic> 35(4), Apr. 2012: 278–297.</p>
<p>Are the mechanisms and processes that lead to radicalization different for Muslim converts and non-converts in the US? While many scholars attempt to explain why people violently radicalize, the theories are diverse and most treat converts and non-converts the same. This study answers this question by categorizing the many radicalization theories into three levels of analysis so that cases of radicalization can be analyzed across and within disciplines. Out of 83 case studies, individual-level factors are more prevalent among converts than non-converts. Group-level processes similarly affect both groups. Mass-level mechanisms are not significant factors in radicalization. [R]</p>
<p>62.5525 KNÖRR, Jacqueline — <bold>Zum Verhältnis ethnischer und nationaler Identität (The relations between [Indonesia's] ethnic and national identity).</bold> <italic>Aus Politik und Zeitgeschichte</italic> 62(11–12), 12 March 2012: 16–23.</p>
<p>In post-colonial societies with heterogeneous populations, national identities are built in a different way than those imagined in the European model of the nation state. However, ethnic diversity does not in any way exclude national unity. Indonesia is the world's largest Muslim country and Islam is also an element of the common national identity, although non-Muslims are often considered lacking in loyalty to the Indonesian state. [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5495]</p>
<p>62.5526 KOCJANČIČ, Rudi — <bold>Bosnia and Herzegovina between Dayton and Brussels.</bold> <italic>Journal of Comparative Politics</italic> 4(2), July 2011: 67–89.</p>
<p>After numerous appeals for reform from the international community and the pro-reform part of the Bosnian-Herzegovinian public, in 2006 the Presidency of Bosnia and Herzegovina proposed that the Parliamentary Assembly as the constituent assembly adopt constitutional amendments in the first stage of constitutional reform. All these changes would contribute to the more efficient and stable operation of Bosnian-Herzegovinian institutions. According to the proposed amendments, all matters relating to the EU would be within the exclusive competence of central institutions. Despite intense efforts by the international community, the House of Representatives was unable to achieve the two-thirds majority of votes required for the adoption of the proposed amendments; at the same time, key political parties rejected the “Butmir Package of Constitutional Amendments” prepared by the representatives of the US and EU in 2009. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5527 KOWALSKI, Alexandra — <bold>The nation, rescaled: theorizing the decentralization of memory in contemporary France.</bold> <italic>Comparative Studies in Society and History</italic> 54(2), Apr. 2012: 308–331.</p>
<p>For more than forty years now, the French state has produced, legitimized, and supported local identities through national policies of historic preservation and public discourses about heritage. Rather than simply replaying the old, anxious, and nostalgic tune of national identity, the advent of heritage in France marked a singular moment of cultural transformation and rupture. The national past became articulated, in public speech and political practice, with the cultures and identities of local and regional territories. Given France's centralist tradition, and its political culture that is often cast as the archetype of “an ideology concerned with boundedness, continuity, and homogeneity”, this historical transformation presents a puzzle, to which this paper provides answers through historical and theoretical inquiry. [R]</p>
<p>62.5528 KRÓKOWSKA, Katarzyna — <bold>The fall of democracy in Syria.</bold> <italic>Perceptions</italic> 16(2), Summer 2011: 81–98.</p>
<p>This paper analyzes social, economic and political factors during the years between Syria's independence (1946) and its unification with Egypt (1958) that led to the fall of democracy. Bitter social conflicts, aggravated by a deep sense of insecurity among the Syrian population, in combination with economic disparities and military intervention, led to the destabilization of the state. In order to identify the reasons behind the fall of Syria's democracy, this paper analyzes social conflict, institutional weakness, the rise of radical parties, the politicization of the military and the role of an unfavorable external environment. It draws attention to changes in class such as the weakening of Syria's liberal elites whose legitimacy diminished as they failed to meet the challenges posed by late industrialization and foreign competition. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5529 KURU, Ahmet T. — <bold>The rise and fall of military tutelage in Turkey: fears of Islamism, Kurdism, and communism.</bold> <italic>Insight Turkey</italic> 14(2), 2012: 37–57.</p>
<p>What explains the rise and fall of military tutelage over Turkish democracy? This article argues that the military's civilian allies, particularly in the judiciary, political parties, and the media, provided it with political power. The reason why these civilian supported the military tutelage over democracy was their ideological fears of “Islamic reactionism”, “Kurdish separatism”, and “communism”. Yet since 2007, the military's political influence has declined due to the weakening of its ideological allies and the rise of a counter-elite, mainly the alliance of the pro-Islamic conservatives and the liberals. The article reviews the alternative state-centric, culturalist, and institutionalist explanations, while comparing the pre-2007 and post-2007 periods of civil-military relations. [R]</p>
<p>62.5530 LACHER, Hannes; GERMANN, Julian — <bold>Before hegemony: Britain, free trade, and nineteenth-century world order revisited.</bold> <italic>International Studies Review</italic> 14(1), March 2012: 99–124.</p>
<p>This article argues that neo-Gramscian theorizations of “hegemony” have failed to illuminate the role of 19th-c. Britain in the rise of a liberal world economy in three respects: (1) they have provided mutually exclusive accounts of the social forces underpinning domestic and international hegemony; (2) they have failed to show Britain's agency in the making of a liberal world order; (3) they have posited a uniformity of social forces and liberal state forms that elides the differences between British and continental societies, thereby obscuring the real reasons for the general shift to liberal internationalism. We argue that it was the structural differences in the economic, social, and political organization of Britain and continental Europe that made free trade without a hegemon possible. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5531 LAMBERT, Jennifer — <bold>Political reform in Qatar: participation, legitimacy and security.</bold> <italic>Middle East Policy</italic> 18(1), Spring 2011: 89–101.</p>
<p>Qatari political reform is that rare case in the literature on international norms that demonstrates how important elite agency can be in explaining their diffusion. Without the Qatari leadership's decision to embrace political reform, the norms of elections and women's rights likely would not be adopted any time soon. While the international normative structure is important, the case of Qatari political reform serves as a reminder that domestic agents also count.</p>
<p>62.5532 LANDIS, Joshua — <bold>The Syrian uprising of 2011: why the Asad regime is likely to survive to 2013.</bold> <italic>Middle East Policy</italic> 19(1), Spring 2012: 72–84.</p>
<p>Will President Bashar al-Asad make it to 2013? Chances are he will. Despite his regime's rapid loss of legitimacy, its growing isolation and tanking economy, no countervailing force has yet emerged that can take it down. Four elements are important in assessing the regime's chances of surviving to 2013: its own strengths, the opposition's weaknesses, the chances of foreign intervention, and the impact of sanctions and economic decline. [R]</p>
<p>62.5533 LONG, Baudoin — <bold>The Hamas [Palestine] agenda: how has it changed?</bold> <italic>Middle East Policy</italic> 17(4), Winter 2010: 131–143.</p>
<p>The image of Hamas in the West has long been linked to its suicide attacks against Israeli civilians. The 2006 elections produced a major change, marking the entrance of Hamas into politics and making it a player that cannot be ignored. Some concluded that Hamas was changing its tone, adopting a softer and more political position. Its new moderation has possibly raised the issue of its inclusion in the peace process. Nonetheless, one might wonder what changes Hamas has really undergone and to what extent it has changed its radical agenda. We focus first on the main changes in Hamas's stance and strategy in the wake of the 2006 elections, [and examine] the reasons for both Hamas's promotion of violence and the reduction of violence vis-à-vis Israel. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5534 LUE, Jen-Der — <bold>The great economic transformation: social dilemmas of Chinese capitalism.</bold> <italic>Comparative Sociology</italic> 11(2), 2012: 274–289.</p>
<p>The transition from socialism to capitalism involves overcoming tremendous, and unavoidable, difficulties of growth and distribution, and controversial reforms. The case of China presents an important opportunity by inviting us to understand its distinctive experiences from comparative perspectives. While its market-oriented reforms have achieved remarkable growth records, the costs of privatization and liberalization have had to be absorbed by social policy, and redistributed among different social strata and specific units. This study focuses on the reconstruction of state-owned enterprises, the social security system, and industrial relations to show China's unique path toward a market economy. As a Leninist government continues to enjoy ample room for policy maneuvers and civil organizations are absent in social policy making, the Chinese case of “great transformation” apparently rests on an unstable ground. [R]</p>
<p>62.5535 MAHADEVAN, Prem — <bold>The Maoist insurgency in India: between crime and revolution.</bold> <italic>Small Wars and Insurgencies</italic> 23(2), May 2012: 203–220.</p>
<p>Since 2004, the Indian government has described the country's Maoist insurgency as a grave threat to domestic security. A study of the sustaining dynamics behind Maoist violence suggests that the rebels are growing operationally stronger due to profits derived from organized crime. Having built up a parasitic economy that operates within the boundaries of nominal state control, they are proceeding to undermine that same control. In effect, the Maoists have assumed characteristics of a Mafia group. With India's economic growth having surged in recent years, their ability to finance aggressive operations and consolidate their subversive infrastructure has increased correspondingly. [R]</p>
<p>62.5536 MALEY, William — <bold>Afghanistan in 2011: positioning for an uncertain future.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 88–99.</p>
<p>Afghanistan confronted further turbulence in 2011, involving the assassination of prominent figures, tense regional relations, and uncertainty about where the draw down of foreign forces in Afghanistan might lead. Popular confidence in Afghanistan's future direction remains weak, and President H. Karzai has had little success in boosting his government's standing. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5537 McCALL ROSENBLUTH, Frances — <bold>Japan in 2011: cataclysmic crisis and chronic deflation.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 15–27.</p>
<p>Japan's government under the Democratic Party of Japan has limped along for another year, hampered by a divided legislature and an aging population reluctant to pay for the pensions and services it requires. The natural disasters of March 2011 were a tragic sideshow to the deep political problems that continue to plague Japan. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5538 McLAUREN, Lauren M. — <bold>The cultural divide in Europe: migration, multiculturalism, and political trust.</bold> <italic>World Politics</italic> 64(2), Apr. 2012: 199–241.</p>
<p>One of the defining features of modern states is their incorporation of notions of political and social community based on shared language, history and myths. However, large numbers of citizens in modern states have come to believe their national communities are under threat from several modern forces, including immigration. Using the European Social Survey (2002–2009), this article explores the extent to which perceived threats posed by large-scale immigration undermine national political communities by reducing trust in national politicians and political institutions. The findings indicate that even after controlling for other predictors of trust in the political system, concerns about the effect of immigration on the national community have an impact on trust in politics. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5539 MERRY, Robert W. — <bold>America's civic deadlock and the politics of crisis.</bold> <italic>National Interest</italic> 119, May-June 2012: 10–20.</p>
<p>Congress is paralyzed. The national debt continues to skyrocket. And America's prevailing political consensus, in force since the days of FDR, can no longer address the country's most basic problems. The question of what will replace it has become a defining issue for America, and until it is resolved our politics will be market by ongoing crisis. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4495]</p>
<p>62.5540 MIETZNER, Marcus — <bold>Indonesia's democratic stagnation: anti-reformist elites and resilient civil society.</bold> <italic>Democratization</italic> 19(2), Apr. 2012: 209–229.</p>
<p>Seen as a stand-out exception from the global recession of democracy in the pre-2011 period, Indonesia has been praised as an example of a stable post-authoritarian polity. But a closer look at Indonesia's record in recent years reveals that its democratization is stagnating: there have been several attempts to roll back reforms introduced in the late 1990s and early 2000s, not all successful. Indonesia's democratic consolidation is now frozen at 2005–2006 levels. However, the reason for this democratic stasis is not related to Diamond's notion of societal dissatisfaction with bad post-authoritarian governance. Opinion polls clearly show continued support for democracy despite citizen disgruntlement over the effectiveness of governance. Instead, anti-reformist elites are the main forces behind the attempted roll-back, with civil society emerging as democracy's most important defender. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5541 MITCHELL, Lincoln — <bold>Georgia: the issue is not democracy.</bold> <italic>Survival</italic> 54(2), Apr.–May 2012: 97–112.</p>
<p>By viewing Georgia's upcoming elections entirely through the lens of democratic advance or retreat, the West risks overlooking the real political developments in the post-Soviet states. [R]</p>
<p>62.5542 MOISSERON, Jean-Yves; BAYOUMI, Manar — <bold>La Méditerranée comme concept et représentation (The Mediterranean as concept and representation).</bold> <italic>Revue Tiers-Monde</italic> 209, Jan.–March 2012: 179–198.</p>
<p>For almost the whole past half century the Mediterranean has been the central reference for European public action aimed at the countries bordering the Mediterranean. But repetitive difficulties have impeded these regional ambitions in contrast to the progress accomplished at the same time in the construction of Europe. Partial responsibility for this failure finds its origins in the choice of using a geographic framework. The Mediterranean, as a concept and in its physical representation, is partially at the origin of its failure to integrate the Euro-Mediterranean region. The use of a “Mediterranean myth” makes us ignore the true dynamics of the area upon which a common space between Europe and the Arab World could be built. [R]</p>
<p>62.5543 MOKHEFI, Mansouria — <bold>Maghreb [2011]: révolutions inachevées? (The uncompleted revolutions in North Africa).</bold> <italic>Politique étrangère</italic> 77(1), Spring 2012: 71–84. [Résumé en français]</p>
<p>The events of 2011 were specific to the experience and history of each country, yet shook the sociopolitical, ideological and cultural situation of all North Africa. Islamists will have to confront exercising power and dealing with huge problems. North Africa surely does not recognize itself in Western, and especially European types of democracy. And new actors and models are emerging in the region, all the way the Turkish experience to Qatari activism. [R] [First of a series of articles on “The Arab revolutions: first assessment”, edited and introduced, pp. 66–70, by Denis BAUCHARD. See also <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4775, 5285, 5299, 5328, 5487]</p>
<p>62.5544 MORIN, Olivier — <bold>Tunisie: le vertige démocratique (Tunisia: the democratic vertigo).</bold> <italic>études</italic>, Apr. 2012: 449–460.</p>
<p>The Tunisian people are proud of “their” revolution. This feeling of collective dignity was meant to be translated into democracy. That was the stake of the first free elections on 23 October 2011 to the Constitutional Assembly, won by the Ennahda party. Following enthusiasm generated by Tunisia's democratic impetus, the election results could not fail to cause uncertain comments. [R, transl.]</p>
<p>62.5545 MØLLER, Jørgen — <bold>Et (u)forudseeligt Mellemøsten: samfundsvidenskaben, point predictions og pattern predictions (The (un)predictable Middle East: social science, point predictions, and pattern predictions).</bold> <italic>Tidsskriftet Politik</italic> 15(1), 2012: 26–34.</p>
<p>The 2011 “Arab Spring” or “Arab uprisings” took observers by surprise, thereby reinvigorating the criticism that political scientists are poor at prediction. This article argues that social science is incapable of predicting such events systematically. The argumentation is based on F. Hayek's distinction between sciences that deal with simple and complex phenomena. The latter category, where the social sciences should be situated, are unable to make “point predictions”. What social science can do is to make that which Hayek terms “pattern predictions”. Based on established theories within the study of regime change, such pattern predictions are offered with respect to the longer-term consequences of the Arab uprisings. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5594]</p>
<p>62.5546 MUHIBAT, Shafiah F. — <bold>Indonesien—eine aufsteigende Regionalmacht? (Indonesia—a rising regional power?).</bold> <italic>Aus Politik und Zeitgeschichte</italic> 62(11–12), 12 March 2012: 9–16.</p>
<p>Indonesia is gaining influence on the regional and the global scale, aiming to become a member of the BRICS club and including democracy and human rights in its foreign policy. But although it has international ambitions and has earned some diplomatic successes, domestic political progress remains wobbly and Indonesia needs to strengthen its own institutions and show leadership qualities in the region in order to become an effective regional power. [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5495]</p>
<p>62.5547 MULLINS, Sam — <bold>Iraq versus lack of integration: understanding the motivations of contemporary Islamist terrorists in Western countries.</bold> <italic>Behavioral Sciences of Terrorism and Political Aggression</italic> 4(2), May 2012: 110–133.</p>
<p>Despite being nearly 10 years into the “Global War on Terror”, there is still confusion as to what motivates the perpetrators of terrorist attacks, particularly those in the West. This article gives an overview of “homegrown” jihadi activities in the West and examines the range of driving forces cited by and attributed to them. It clarifies the relative contributions of local inequalities, global political events such as the occupation of Iraq, religious beliefs and social processes as motivating factors. Implications for theories of terrorism and for counter-terrorism strategies are discussed. [R]</p>
<p>62.5548 MURPHY, Taggart R. — <bold>A loyal retainer? Japan, capitalism and the perpetuation of American hegemony.</bold> <italic>Socialist Register</italic> 2011: 147–173.</p>
<p>The key to understanding the repair and continued reinforcement of American hegemony since the system-shaking tremors of the 1970s can be found in the postwar experience of Japan and its neighbors. Within that experience lies a paradox: it was precisely Japan's deviations from orthodox capitalist methods—the distinctive marks that characterize its political economy—that help explain the continuation of an American-centered world capitalist system long after one might have expected its manifest contradictions to bring it down. Japan's resistance to the full transforming power of capitalist relations forms a crucial explanation for both Japan's willingness and its ability to support the global capitalist order. [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4448]</p>
<p>62.5549 MUSGRAVE, Paul — <bold>The making of the pundit, 2010: when strong ties trump weak ones.</bold> <italic>PS</italic> 45(2), Apr. 2012: 265–269.</p>
<p>Many observers have argued that social media such as <italic>Facebook</italic> and <italic>Twitter</italic> will help opposition activists coordinate and overcome authoritarian regimes; others believe that such tools will have little impact. Evidence from the “Arab Spring” is inconclusive, with advocates for each position finding support in the events in Tunisia, Egypt, and elsewhere. When do social media help political movements succeed? Motivated by an experience serving as a “campaign manager” for a colleague's bid to become the <italic>Washington Post's</italic> “Next Great Pundit”, I argue that relying on internet-based social networking tools may lead campaigns to perform more poorly when the regime is able to change the election's rules in mid-campaign. Examples from Middle Eastern politics suggest that real-world political activists recognize these distinctions and adjust their messaging accordingly. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5550 NARANGOA, Li — <bold>Mongolia in 2011: resources bring friends and wealth.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 81–87.</p>
<p>Mongolia has been successfully developing its external relations and mining sectors for some years, but 2011 marked a new stage in its success in these areas. The mining boom pushed economic growth to a new level; Mongolia is now one of the fastest-growing economies in the world. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5551 NATALI, Denise — <bold>The politics of [Iraqi] Kurdish crude [petroleum].</bold> <italic>Middle East Policy</italic> 19(1), Spring 2012: 110–118.</p>
<p>ExxonMobil's entry in the Kurdish Region not only challenges [Iraqi] central government authority but gives the Kurdish Regional Government (KRG) greater leverage in developing its own oil market. In the absence of an independent revenue source and control of the pipeline export infrastructure, the KRG may eventually have to compromise with Baghdad to assure IOC payment and the viability of its oil market. Given the ongoing political distrust between Baghdad and Arbil and the potential value of Iraqi petroleum to world markets, it is in the interest of the US to encourage such a compromise. Promoting Iraqi oil exports through the northern corridor via Turkey will not only boost Iraq's emergent energy sector, but also strengthen US energy security in an otherwise volatile region. [First of a series of articles on “Building political infrastructure”. See also <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4676, 4693, 4866]</p>
<p>62.5552 NOGUCHI, Asahi — <bold>Shifting domestic and international perceptions of Japan's economy.</bold> <italic>Japanese Journal of Political Science</italic> 13(2), June 2012: 255–264.</p>
<p>Japan's remarkable economic success especially from the 1960s to the 1980s has attracted extensive worldwide attention. However, the world's admiration has plummeted since the 1990s, when the Bubble Economy burst, bringing on chronic stagnation. Since then, the world has regarded the Japanese economy less as a desirable model and more as an evident failure with many lessons for other economies. These external judgments, positive and negative, have also affected how the Japanese perceive their own economy. This article reviews how these domestic and international perceptions of Japan's economy have varied. It situates the companion articles by Hwang Insang (<italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5513) and Harada (<italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5510) in the historical context of studies of the Japanese economy. This article especially discusses the tendency to overestimate characteristics that supposedly are specific to Japan and different from other market-oriented economies. [R, abr.] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5517]</p>
<p>62.5553 NORRIS, Pippa; INGLEHART, Ronald F. — <bold>Muslim integration into Western cultures: between origins and destinations.</bold> <italic>Political Studies</italic> 60(2), June 2012: 228–251.</p>
<p>This article first considers theories about the impact of growing social diversity in Western nations. We classify two categories of society: Origins (defined as Islamic countries of origin for Muslim migrants, including twenty nations with plurality Muslim populations) and destinations (defined as Western countries of destination for Muslim migrants, including 22 OECD member states with Protestant or Roman Catholic majority populations). Using this framework, we demonstrate that, on average, the basic social values of Muslim migrants fall roughly midway between those prevailing in their country of origin and their country of destination. We conclude that Muslim migrants do not move to Western countries with rigidly fixed attitudes; instead, they gradually absorb much of the host culture, as assimilation theories suggest. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5554 NUNN, Alex — <bold>The political economy of [UK] competitiveness and social mobility.</bold> <italic>British Politics</italic> 7(2), June 2012: 86–110.</p>
<p>Social mobility has become a mainstream political and media issue in recent years in the UK. Part of the reason for this is that it can serve as a mechanism to discuss policy concerns that appear to be about social justice without questioning important aspects of neo-liberal political economy. The article charts the policy rhetoric on social mobility under both New Labour and the current Coalition Government. Under New Labour, the apparent commitment to social mobility was in fact subsumed beneath the pursuit of neo-liberal competitiveness, albeit imperfectly realized in policy. Under the Coalition Government, the commitment to raising levels of social mobility has been retained and the recently published <italic>Strategy for Social Mobility</italic> [April 2011] promises that social mobility is what the Coalition means when it argues that the austerity program is balanced with “fairness”. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5555 O'SHANNASSY, Michael — <bold>Malaysia in 2011: the more things stay the same, the more things change?</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 165–175.</p>
<p>Ethno-religious controversies, noisy demands for political change, and growing concerns over the slow pace of crucial economic reforms all served to highlight Malaysia's constantly shifting sociopolitical terrain in 2011. With the prospect of an early general election, it remains to be seen whether the ruling coalition can regain the middle ground. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5556 OBYDENKOVA, Anastassia V. — <bold>Democratization at the grassroots: the European Union's external impact [in Russia].</bold> <italic>Democratization</italic> 19(2), Apr. 2012: 230–257.</p>
<p>By the end of Russia's regime-transition to democracy (1991–2001), Russia displayed a mosaic of different sub-national regimes. A number of economic, social, and cultural factors have been investigated to explain how the sub-national regime transitions produced such heterogeneous results. This article focuses on the role of the EU in the democratic regime-transition in the regions of Russia and, in this context, explores the international dimension of sub-national regimes. The main question is: what was the role of the EU, if any, in the formation of different outcomes of sub-national regime-transitions? [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5557 ONUOHA, Godwin — <bold>Contemporary Igbo nationalism and the crisis of self-determination in Nigeria.</bold> <italic>African Studies</italic> 71(1), Apr. 2012: 29–51.</p>
<p>This article examines an aspect of Nigerian ethno-nationalism less [examined] compared to other ethno-nationalist mobilizations of the Ijaw, Ogoni and Yoruba ethnic extractions. [In] response to the persistent “national question” and a political culture that has structured power relations, political claims and recognition from the colonial to the post-colonial era, the advent of the Movement for the Actualization of the Sovereign State of Biafra (MASSOB) marks a reinvention of Igbo nationalism. Unlike other ethno-nationalist mobilizations, the salient character of MASSOB finds expression in its separatist inclinations, its rejection of a state-led process and rootedness in the aborted secessionist war for Igbo self-determination between 1967 and 1970. This article emphasizes the dialectical relations between ethnic groups and state, and deploys ethnicity as a critical “exit point” for marginalized groups in a multi-ethnic state. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5558 OSHA, Sanya — <bold>The order/other of political culture: reflections on Nigeria's fourth democratic experiment.</bold> <italic>Socialism and Democracy</italic> 25(2), July 2011: 144–163.</p>
<p>There are evidently continuities of militarism in relation to Nigerian democracy. Militarism and democracy do not constitute separate or distinct categories, as they frequently meet at the level of constitutional processes, governmental policy-making and various other sociopolitical processes. Democracy is usually understood and employed as a technical concept fashioned along the imperatives of the Bretton Woods institutional order. Thus it becomes a concept without precise historical and cultural linkages and which draws its political force from an unproblematized understanding of the discourse of universal rights human rights. It is in these terms, however, that the struggles for Nigerian democracy were waged. [A]</p>
<p>62.5559 PARMAR, Sarabjeet Singh — <bold>Somali piracy: a form of economic terrorism.</bold> <italic>Strategic Analysis</italic> 36(2), March 2012: 290–303.</p>
<p>Piracy over the years has been driven by geography, political instability and the availability of safe havens. Apart from these established factors, economics too play a role. This article reviews and examines Somali piracy, which has flourished due to the international community ignoring the growing instability in Somalia, the rampant illegal fishing and toxic waste dumping. It examines the international response, the legal and economic factors and advocates that piracy be viewed as a form of economic terrorism and be combatted as such, as well as by land-based operations. [R]</p>
<p>62.5560 PERSICHINO, Roger — <bold>Crise institutionnelle ou crise identitaire? (An institutional or an identity crisis [in the US]?).</bold> <italic>Le Débat</italic> 169, March-Apr. 2012: 56–66.</p>
<p>In September 2011, F. Fukuyama claimed that the 112th Congress was the most inefficient Congress in recent US history. A closer look at the Congress's legislative weaknesses helps to understand the modern US political system outside of this efficiency frame. The US political system is a functional mechanism which adapts itself to new economic and demographic realities. There is indeed a political crisis in the US, but not an institutional one. The situation imposes to consider the legislative paralysis and the discrepancy between political supply and demand. Rather than in an institutional dysfunction, the crisis is located in the context of “creedal passion”, as defined by S Huntington more than thirty years ago.</p>
<p>62.5561 PETERSEN, Niels — <bold>Der Arabische Frühling und das Recht auf Demokratie (The Arab Spring and the right to democracy).</bold> <italic>Friedens-Warte</italic> 87(1), 2012: 43–68.</p>
<p>The Arab Spring has shown that the democratization of the Arab states does not necessarily have to be a utopia. This contribution analyzes the role of international law in this process. It first deals with the question whether there is a right to democratic governance in international law. It concludes that international law only addresses the process of democratization, but does not require states to be democratic. However, governments have to meet certain minimum standards of legitimacy. In the second part, the contribution analyzes means to implement the principle of legitimacy in international law. It deals with resolutions by the UN Security Council, unilateral military interventions, interventions by invitation as well as non-military sanctions. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5438]</p>
<p>62.5562 PHILLIPS, Andrew — <bold>Horsemen of the Apocalypse? Jihadist strategy and nuclear instability in South Asia.</bold> <italic>International Politics</italic> 49(3), May 2012: 297–317.</p>
<p>Since 9/11 [2001], counter-terrorism officials have fretted over the possibility of jihadist terrorists obtaining and deploying a nuclear weapon. I offer a reconceptualization of the jihadist terrorist nuclear threat that focuses alternatively upon the remote but real possibility that jihadist terrorists may try to provoke an Indo-Pakistani nuclear confrontation. Such a confrontation would serve jihadist goals by aggravating religious polarization on the sub-continent while dramatically weakening the Pakistani state. The system-destabilizing consequences of such a catastrophe would likely also offer the jihadists their best opportunity to revive their faltering movement, which otherwise appears fated to terminal decline. In the light of this assessment, I argue that a higher priority must be accorded towards strengthening Indo-Pakistani crisis-stability and advancing regional reconciliation. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5563 PIAZZA, James A. — <bold>The opium trade and patterns of terrorism in the provinces of Afghanistan: an empirical analysis.</bold> <italic>Terrorism and Political Violence</italic> 24(2), Apr.–June 2012: 213–234.</p>
<p>Contemporary terrorist movements in Afghanistan are frequently alleged to be fueled, in part, by the country's voluminous opium trade. Experts argue that terrorist groups currently active in Afghanistan, like the Afghan Taliban, the Islamic Movement of Uzbekistan, Hizbul Islami, and various al-Qaeda affiliates, use drug-trade profits to recruit and pay cadres, acquire weapons and equipment, and bribe officials while becoming more powerful, and deadly, in the process. This study empirically examines the relationship between the opium trade and terrorism in Afghanistan by conducting a series of negative binomial regression estimations on terrorist attacks and casualties in the 34 Afghan provinces for the period 1996 to 2008. The analysis also considers various economic development, infrastructure, geographic, security, and cultural factors when examining causes of terrorism in the provinces. [R, abr.] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4456]</p>
<p>62.5564 PIERRET, Thomas — <bold>Le Baas syrien face à l'Islam sunnite. Conflits et connivences (The Syrian Baath Party facing Sunnite Islam: conflicts and connivances).</bold> <italic>Le Débat</italic> 168, Jan.–Feb. 2012: 146–154.</p>
<p>Rather than attempt an exhaustive analysis of the Syrian denominational question, it is important to address it via the more restricted topic of the regime's relations with the Sunnite sphere of influence. This implies the Islamist oppositional movements on the one hand and the <italic>ulama</italic>, or the religious scholarly elite, on the other. The Syrian case has four significant aspects: the regime's position in relation to political Islam; cult-management and relations with the religious elite; the Sunnite resentment, created by the rumors of Shi'ite missionary activities in the country; the role of economic liberalization in the regime's recent reconciliation with the religious elite. The study of these factors allows for the analysis of religious actors' position in the current situation. [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5330]</p>
<p>62.5565 POND, Elizabeth — <bold>Justice and democracy in the Balkans [Serbia].</bold> <italic>Survival</italic> 54(2), Apr.–May 2012: 77–96.</p>
<p>A generation after the Balkan wars of the 1990s, Serbs have struggled to achieve accountability and reconciliation. Belgrade's record may not offer a blueprint for others, but it has not yet failed. [R]</p>
<p>62.5566 PONGSUDHIRAK, Thitinan — <bold>Southeast Asia: Thailand's uneasy passage.</bold> <italic>Journal of Democracy</italic> 23(2), Apr. 2012: 47–61.</p>
<p>In 2011, Thais reelected a party backed by deposed prime minister Thaksin Shinawatra. Why is his brand of populism so irrepressible, and what can be done to reconcile the voting power of Thailand's rural lower classes with the establishment dug in around the Thai monarchy? [R]</p>
<p>62.5567 PRINA, Federica — <bold>Power, politics and participation: the Russian Federation's national minorities and their participatory rights.</bold> <italic>Netherlands Quarterly of Human Rights</italic> 30(1), 2012: 65–95.</p>
<p>This article reveals obstacles to Russia's implementation of the Framework Convention for the Protection of National Minorities, focusing on participatory rights (Art. 15). Russia does not meet the requirements of Art. 15, [because] the form of participation offered to minorities is devoid of guarantees that it will be “effective”. An analysis of the two forms of participation—representation in elected bodies and consultative mechanisms, with a particular reference to national Cultural Autonomy—reveals an over-reliance on informal networks and practices in the management of majority-minority relations. Mechanisms for participation are locked into a system that has features partly originating from the Soviet period and partly from policies introduced by V. Putin. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5568 PUDDINGTON, Arch — <bold>The Freedom House Survey for 2011: the year of the Arab uprisings.</bold> <italic>Journal of Democracy</italic> 23(2), Apr. 2012: 74–88.</p>
<p>Although in 2011 declines in freedom exceeded gains for the sixth straight year, the uprisings in the Arab world represent the most significant challenge to authoritarian rule since the collapse of Soviet communism. [R]</p>
<p>62.5569 RACHMAN, Gideon — <bold>Europe's zero-sum dilemma.</bold> <italic>National Interest</italic> 119, May-June 2012: 43–48.</p>
<p>The European debt debacle has made a mockery of the original hopes that inspired the European project. Nationalist sentiment is on the rise, and the win-win logic of shared prosperity has been replaced by a zerosum dynamic in which one country's gain is viewed as another's loss. The EU may not survive the current crisis—and even if it does, it could be a severely diminished organization. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4495]</p>
<p>62.5570 RAFAAT, Aram — <bold>Kurdish Islam and the question of Kurdish integration into the Iraqi state.</bold> <italic>Journal of Social, Political and Economic Studies</italic> 37(1), Spring 2012: 3–37.</p>
<p>The author examines the role of religion in Kurdish national aspirations, with particular reference to the manner in which it affects the relationship between Kurds living in Iraq and attempts to integrate Iraqi Kurds into the Iraqi state. [R]</p>
<p>62.5571 ROTHE, Dawn L.; MAGGARD, Scott — <bold>Factors that impede or facilitate post-conflict justice mechanisms?</bold> <italic>International Criminal Law Review</italic> 12(2), 2012: 193–217.</p>
<p>This article reviews post-conflict justice (PCJ) [and] analyzes factors that impede or facilitate the implementation of mechanisms to address the atrocities of a conflict. Grounded in an extensive new dataset covering all conflicts in Africa between 1946 and 2009, we extend previous research by including empirical testing of previously untested assumptions and variables impacting PCJ, most notably, the role of power, politics, economics, and geo-strategic interests at the state and international political levels as well as combining previously tested variables amongst and between each other. Further, the aspects of PCJ, including conflicts where mechanisms were not deployed are included in the analysis along with those coded as symbolic in nature. We discuss the pragmatic issues associated with testing the concept of <italic>Realpolitik</italic> and policy implications based on our analysis. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5572 SAADULLAH KHAN, M. Zakir — <bold>Democracy and economic freedom: a static panel data analysis of South Asia.</bold> <italic>CEU Political Science Journal</italic> 7(1), Feb. 2012: 32–49.</p>
<p>Economic freedom leads to and maintains democracy—this hypothesis popularly known as Hayek-Lipset-Friedman hypothesis has been examined empirically in this study for South Asian region. Using data on economic freedom and political freedom (democracy) for a panel of live South Asian countries over the period 1995–2008, the Granger-causality test confirms that democratic society must be economically free: it does not happen other way round. Applying static panel data estimation technique, this study also finds significant positive relationship between democracy and economic freedom and the degree of responsiveness of economic freedom on democracy is found less proportionate in South Asian countries. It is also found that economic prosperity fosters democracy in this region, whereas government spending does not have significant impact on the level of democracy in South Asian countries. [R]</p>
<p>62.5573 SALE, Giovanni — <bold>La “modernizzazione difensiva” in Medio Oriente (“Defensive modernization” in the Middle East).</bold> <italic>Civiltà cattolica</italic> 3883, 7 Apr. 2012: 3–16.</p>
<p>During the 19th c., the European principles of modernization conquered progressively most of the Southern countries, introducing clear, sometimes radical, changes. They consisted in the affirmation of a new economic-development model, more sensitive to the international market logic, and in the adoption of the idea of the nation-state, opposed to the political and religious concept of the Muslim <italic>umma</italic>, i.e. the universal community of believers. This pro-European adaptation was interpreted by some American historians according to the “defensive developmentalism” approach. That concept is very interesting when applied to some of the transformation processes of the Middle Eastern world. [R, transl.]</p>
<p>62.5574 SAUNDERS, Robert A. — <bold>Undead spaces: fear, globalisation, and the popular [US] geopolitics of zombiism.</bold> <italic>Geopolitics</italic> 17(1), 2012: 80–104.</p>
<p>In recent years, zombies have enjoyed a dramatic renaissance in various forms of popular culture. This essay argues that the current obsession with the walking dead, and particularly the looming threat of humanzombie conflicts, is a reflection of the dangers of invasive alterity associated with uncontrolled spaces in a globalized world. This shift is especially prevalent in the US following 9/11 [2001], as zombies have become phantasmal stand-ins for Islamist terrorists, illegal immigrants, carriers of foreign contagions, and other “dangerous” border crossers. Through three case studies which examine zombie “outbreaks” on the local, national, and global levels, respectively, I discuss the importance of borders and geopolitical spaces in recent fictional depictions of humanzombie conflicts. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5575 SCIUBBA, Jennifer Dabbs — <bold>Demography and instability in the developing world.</bold> <italic>Orbis</italic> 56(2), Spring 2012: 267–277.</p>
<p>Demography provides a framework for analyzing the effect of population on national security and a tool to assess how demographic trends in the developing world will influence conflict over the next twenty years. Population is connected to national security as an indicator of challenge and opportunity, a multiplier of conflict and progress, and a resource for power and prosperity. This indicator-multiplier-resource framework is then applied to the three influential demographic issues of the developing world: (1) youthful populations; (2) transitional age structures; and (3) urbanization. These diverse demographic trends reveal a growing divergence among states in the developing world and the need to continue to plan for the spectrum of warfare, though there will be an increasing number of supportive and capable states. [R, abr.] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5267]</p>
<p>62.5576 SHARMA, Kishor — <bold>Foreign aid, governance and economic development in Nepal.</bold> <italic>Asia Pacific Journal of Public Administration</italic> 33(2), Dec. 2011: 95–115.</p>
<p>This article contributes to the aid-effectiveness debate using Nepal as a case study, a country which has failed to accelerate growth and reduce poverty and inequality despite being a significant aid-recipient for over half a century. The weak aid-absorption capacity and lack of commitment to institutional reform appear to be the reasons for aid-ineffectiveness. Nepal needs to embark on major reforms in governance, institutions and policy aimed at rural development. The commitment of donors to give more aid without fundamental reforms in these areas will only enable the ruling elite to remain in power without achieving the objectives of helping the poor and disadvantaged groups who live in the rural and remote areas. [R]</p>
<p>62.5577 SHNEIDERMAN, Sara; TURIN, Mark — <bold>Nepal and Bhutan in 2011: cautious optimism.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 138–146.</p>
<p>Nepal's political transition to a democratic federal republic remains incomplete. A November 2011 agreement on post-conflict integration and rehabilitation offers reason for hope. Continued disagreements over the structure of the federal state and its form of government have delayed the constitution-making process. Corruption, impunity, and weak infrastructure combine to erode Nepali confidence in effective governance. Bhutan's democratic exercise continues to be carefully controlled by entrenched elites, but the country held its first-ever local elections successfully and economic growth stabilized. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5578 SIOUSSIOURAS, Petros; VAVOURAS, Ioannis — <bold>Political rights, development, and corruption in the Balkan and Arab Mediterranean countries.</bold> <italic>Mediterranean Quarterly</italic> 23(1), Winter 2012: 89–103.</p>
<p>This essay provides an account of the phenomenon of corruption in the Balkan and Arab countries of the Mediterranean. The analysis focuses on the effects that the political system-approached through the lens of political rights-and the level of economic development have on corruption. These factors are of critical importance for analyzing the scale of corruption in the region and should form the core of any anti-corruption strategies. [R]</p>
<p>62.5579 SOUTHGATE, Douglas — <bold>National interests, multinational actors, and petroleum development in the Ecuadorian Amazon.</bold> <italic>Whitehead Journal of Diplomacy and International Relations</italic> 12(1), Winter-Spring 2011: 137–151.</p>
<p>A critique of the broad narrative about petroleum development in the Ecuadorian Amazon involves the analysis of the narrative's three constituent hypotheses: that the country was entirely dominated by foreign firms; that the vast majority of Ecuadorians benefited little or not at all from petroleum development; that environmental trade-offs in the Oriente were decided by multinational actors and not by the Ecuadorian government. Each of the three hypotheses is inconsistent with the historical record. The government quickly started consolidating its authority in the Ecuadorian Amazon and the industry was soon nationalized, which allowed it to capture nearly all the returns created by multinational investment. Moreover, the national government and Petroecuador have been primarily responsible for the environmental management in the Oriente, not foreign firms. [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4433]</p>
<p>62.5580 STEINHARDT, H. Christoph — <bold>How is high trust in China possible? Comparing the origins of generalized trust in three Chinese societies [Mainland China, Hong Kong and Taiwan].</bold> <italic>Political Studies</italic> 60(2), June 2012: 434–454.</p>
<p>Although China is an outlier in terms of generalized trust, it has attracted little scholarly attention so far. Employing survey data from Mainland China, Hong Kong and Taiwan, this article makes use of the comparative leverage provided by political and socio-cultural variation to investigate two plausible reasons for the high levels of measured trust in Mainland China: a spillover from high institutional confidence; and problems of measurement validity. The study finds a comparatively strong link between institutional confidence and trust in Mainland China, which suggests that high confidence in institutions contributes to high levels of generalized trust in this context. By situating the Chinese case in the debate on the institutional foundation of generalized trust, the article suggests a heuristic to interpret this finding and points out its theoretical implications. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5581 STEPAN, Alfred — <bold>Tunisia's transition and the twin tolerations.</bold> <italic>Journal of Democracy</italic> 23(2), Apr. 2012: 89–103.</p>
<p>Of all the “Arab Spring” countries, so far only Tunisia has managed to make a transition to democracy. Tunisians now have a chance to show the world a new example of how religion, society, and the state can relate to one another under democratic conditions. [R]</p>
<p>62.5582 SULLIVAN, Jonathan; SEILER-HOLMER, Gudrun — <bold>Mapping the Taiwan studies field.</bold> <italic>Issues and Studies</italic> 47(3), Sept. 2011: 1–28.</p>
<p>There are legitimate concerns about the health and sustainability of the Taiwan Studies field. Using newly collected empirical data on research output and a survey of the attitudes of Taiwan scholars in the west and in Taiwan, this article provides a starting point for mapping the field. While generally buoyant, Taiwan studies faces several divisions, for example between western and Taiwan-based scholars, between English- and Chinese-language research and between area specialists and disciplinary specialists. These divisions contribute to a research field that, as we show empirically, is relatively low on collaboration, is dominated by political science, and is disseminated in lower impact journals. The article concludes with some suggestions for addressing these problems. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5583 SUMMERS, Tim — <bold>(Re)positioning Yunnan [China]: region and nation in contemporary provincial narratives.</bold> <italic>Journal of Contemporary China</italic> 75, May 2012: 445–459.</p>
<p>This paper identifies imaginings since the early 1990s to reposition Yunnan from a peripheral Chinese province to the center of various regional constructs which involve territories across the PRC's borders, primarily in what are now known as southeast and south Asia. These narratives, which change over time and between actors, are justified using Yunnan's past linkages with territories along the “southern silk road” and through a naturalized presentation of its geographical location and characteristics, are based on the premise of good neighborly relations, and are driven by imperatives of development. They find practical expression in provincial engagement with regional institutions, and in infrastructure and other programs. However, the imaginings to reposition the province are at the same time constrained by the demands of territorial integrity and national security. [R, abr.] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5403]</p>
<p>62.5584 TADEM, Teresa s. Encarnacion — <bold>Creating spaces for Asian interaction through the anti-globalization campaigns in the region.</bold> <italic>Modern Asian Studies</italic> 46(2), March 2012: 453–481.</p>
<p>This paper discusses the political opportunity structures which facilitated the creation of sites of interaction and protest against the Asian Development Bank during the Bank's Annual General Meeting in Chiang Mai, Thailand, in 2000. The factors which facilitated the coming together of Thai social movements and their regional and international counterparts are mainly their shared critique of the neo-liberal paradigm and its adverse effects on their respective countries. The strategies they used to highlight these effects enhanced their sites of engagement and confrontation with the Bank and included dialogue with Bank officials, demonstrations, and the use of the media to highlight their concerns. [R, abr.] [Part of a thematic issue on “Sites of Asian interaction”, edited by Tim HARPER and Sunil AMRITH]</p>
<p>62.5585 TÂMAŞ, Sergiu — <bold>Schimbâri istorice în raporturile de putere (Historic changes in power relations).</bold> <italic>Sfera Politicii</italic> 165, Nov. 2011: 3–11.</p>
<p>Mankind is experiencing a period of historical discontinuity. The major changing vector is represented by the emergent economies, whose high development rates have made them become the main contributors to global growth. One of the main consequences of this transition is the remodeling of world order, the change in the global balance of power, through the transition from the unipolar world dominated by the US to the multipolar one in which the emergent powers' position is increasingly taken into account. The progress registered by the emergent economies requires a review of theories, concepts and principles that orientate economic and political contemporary practice. [R] [Introduction to a thematic issue, “Twenty years after the fall of communism”. See also the contributions of Adrian TOP; Alexander GHALEB; Emanuel COLIPAŞ; Sonia CATRINA; Alexandru ŞTEFÂNESCU; Aurora MARTIN; Olesea TÂRANU; Iulian CHIFU; Cristina ABOBOAIE; CHO Youngwon; Cristian-Ion POPA; Sabin DRÂGULIN; Vasile PLEŞCA]</p>
<p>62.5586 TAN, Kenneth Paul — <bold>Singapore in 2011: a “new normal” in politics?</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 220–226.</p>
<p>In 2011, Singaporeans voted in parliamentary and presidential elections. The social networking media, dominated by alternative reporting and commentary, played a significant role in generating political interest and mobilizing oppositional thinking and support. Faced with a stronger oppositional presence and a politically emboldened electorate, the People's Action Party government won the elections but achieved its worst results ever. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5587 TOBIN, Sarah A. — <bold>Jordan's Arab Spring: the middle class and anti-revolution.</bold> <italic>Middle East Policy</italic> 19(1), Spring 2012: 96–109.</p>
<p>Why is Jordan an exception? Why did the people's desire for reform not materialize in large-scale protests and revolution? Why has King Abdullah not faced the same pressures as other rulers throughout the region? Based on ethnographic fieldwork and recent interviews, this paper examines the role of the emergent middle class in Amman in shaping national politics, especially anti-revolutionary positions during the Arab Spring. I argue that a heightened notion of middle-class status and “aspiring cosmopolitanism” provides a newly significant form of social organization in Amman. [R]</p>
<p>62.5588 TOPLAK, Cirila — <bold>Hybridization of democracy in Central and Eastern Europe: between “imported” democratic model and inherent political culture.</bold> <italic>Journal of Comparative Politics</italic> 4(1), Jan. 2011: 76–90.</p>
<p>In the last two decades, Central and Eastern Europe has gone through an intensive transformation process in which the adopted global neo-liberal political-economic model, the specifics of Europeanization and the traditionally non-liberal corporate political cultures in the region merged to produce hybrid political systems that bear many features of oligarchies. “Minimal democracies” of Central and Eastern Europe have not only been established on a state-reductive political system that benefits most the corporate economic sector, but also represent a sort of a hybrid that emerged from adaptation of an “imported” political model to the political culture in the region. The hybridization is the most visible in, yet not limited to, newly founded sovereign states without prior democratic tradition. The author considers more closely political parties and free elections. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5589 TSAI, Awi Mona; SIMON, Scott — <bold>Imagining first nations: from Eeyou Istchee (Québec) to the Seediq and Truku on Taiwan.</bold> <italic>Issues and Studies</italic> 47(3), Sept. 2011: 29–70.</p>
<p>In Canada, indigenous communities have gained recognition as First Nations endowed with specific and potent constitutional rights. This legal status has made Canadian First Nation into models for indigenous demands around the world, including in Taiwan. This paper (1) reflects on Canadian and Taiwanese examples to understand how indigenous communities have constructed national identities and achieved recognition as First Nations with inherent legal rights; (2) explores how indigenous peoples in Canada and Taiwan have achieved recognition as participants in democratic politics and as sites of constitutional rights; and, last but not least, (3) appreciates what lessons they can learn from one another. [R]</p>
<p>62.5590 TSYGANKOV, Andrei P. — <bold>Russia and the CIS in 2011: uncertain economic recovery.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 42–51.</p>
<p>During 2011, Russia made progress in recovering from the global financial crisis and moved toward further political centralization. Moscow also continued to prepare for an uncertain new world by pursuing pragmatic relations with Western and non-Western powers and by seeking to increase its influence among the states of the Commonwealth of Independent States. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5591 TURNELL, Sean — <bold>Myanmar in 2011: confounding expectations.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 157–164.</p>
<p>Overall, 2011 was a year of significant change in Myanmar. By year-end, there was hope that political and economic reforms—incomplete and fragile—were at last under way. Myanmar continued to be an important regional exporter of energy and resources, but in other areas underperformed. Myanmar's international relations improved, and US Secretary of State H. Clinton visited at the end of November. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5592 UFEN, Andreas — <bold>Politischer Islam in Indonesien seit 1998 (Political Islam in Indonesia since 1998).</bold> <italic>Aus Politik und Zeitgeschichte</italic> 62(11–12), 12 March 2012: 30–36.</p>
<p>Islam in Indonesia as a consequence of the democratization begun in 1998 and accelerating globalization has become more versatile. Islamic forces have benefitted from new ways of disseminating their ideas through pamphlets, interpretations of faith, missionaries or educational institutions. But Islamists do not hold the upper hand in the culture “war”: a majority of the population favors democracy and the market economy. [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5495]</p>
<p>62.5593 UN Kheang — <bold>Cambodia in 2011: a thin veneer of change.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 202–209.</p>
<p>Cambodia's economy in 2011 recovered from the global economic downturn with a rise in garment exports. Hun Sen and the ruling Cambodian People's Party further consolidated power via the exercise of rule by law and patronage politics. Relations with Thailand returned to normal; ties with China strengthened with increased assistance and trade. The Khmer Rouge Tribunal proceeded amid allegations of political interference by the Cambodian government, making the further expansion of indictments unlikely. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5594 UTVIK, Bjørn Olav — <bold>Islamister i åpnere landskap: hvilken rolle i det nye Midtøsten? (Islamists in a more open landscape: what role in the new Middle East?).</bold> <italic>Tidsskriftet Politik</italic> 15(1), 2012: 6–14.</p>
<p>The political successes of Islamists following the Arab uprisings of 2011 makes understanding Islamism more important than ever. They have long been central to oppositional politics in the Arab world. Now they may well become a dominant factor in the emerging new regimes. A necessary starting point is to recognize that the Islamists played a pivotal role in the Arab spring from the start. Furthermore, to grasp the possible ways in which the Islamists may influence developments to come, research must turn away from essentializing their Islamic ideology and discover the contradictory impulses driving these complex and dynamic social movements. [R] [First article of a thematic issue on “The Arab revolts—social uprisings and science”. See also <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5075, 5501, 5545, 5595]</p>
<p>62.5595 VALBJØRN, Morten; BOSERUP, Rasmus Alenius — <bold>Genpolitisering og postdemokratisering: studiet af mellemøstlig politik i lyset af de arabiske revolter (Repoliticization and postdemocratization: the study of Middle East politics in the context of the Arab revolts).</bold> <italic>Tidsskriftet Politik</italic> 15(1), 2012: 43–51.</p>
<p>A prominent theme in the current debate on the implications of the Arab revolts revolves around the questions about whether we are witnessing the emergence of a truly new Middle East in a “transition to democracy”, or whether the region is still stuck in a “transition to nowhere” similar to past decades. Based on a critique of both of these views, the article suggests that the Arab world should instead be perceived as being in a “transition to somewhere” marked by a multi-level repoliticization. Against this background, we explore how this “return of politics” in Arab societies is reflected above, below and beyond the level of the regime and how this can be grasped by an “upgraded” version of the post-democratization approach to Arab politics. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5594]</p>
<p>62.5596 VARGOVČIKOVÁ, Jana — <bold>Le Groupe de Visegrad, 20 ans après (The Visegrad Group, after 20 years).</bold> <italic>Politique étrangère</italic> 77(1), Spring 2012: 147–160. [Résumé en français]</p>
<p>The Visegrad Group (Poland, Hungary, Czech Republic, Slovakia) has, in 20 years, left its mark on the geopolitical map of Central Europe. Can this group become a serious sub-regional player in the EU? Though locally it proves undeniably effective, it seems to have only a reactive efficiency in Brussels. Its ability to intervene in the European Neighborhood Policy or the Union's energy policy will be a test of its weight in the future. [R]</p>
<p>62.5597 VILLORIA, Manuel; JIMÉNEZ, Fernando — <bold>Cuánta corrupción hay en España? Los problemas metodológicos de la medición de corrupción (2004–2011) (How much corruption is there in Spain? The methodological problems of measuring corruption, 2004–2011).</bold> <italic>Revista de Estudios políticos</italic> 156, Apr.–June 2012: 13–47.</p>
<p>According to a recent democratic audit and different perceptions of corruption surveys, the quality of the Spanish democracy is falling and one of the most important reasons for that is corruption. Is this perception of widespread corruption based on objective data? This article analyses the different methods to measure corruption and assesses their methodological problems. In general terms, study rates of prosecution or conviction for misuse of office are not reliable. The rates and surveys of victimization is a way to quantify corruption, but the only corruption measured through this instrument is “bribes”. The other way to measure corruption is subjective, based on perceptions. But perceptions are not the same as corruption and they lead to an “echo chamber” problem and insensitivity to actual trends. As a result, fighting corruption effectively requires more micro knowledge of the incentives and constraints affecting the problem. [R]</p>
<p>62.5598 WALKER, Graham — <bold>Scotland's sectarianism problem [UK]: Irish answers?</bold> <italic>Political Quarterly</italic> 83(2), Apr.–June 2012: 374–383.</p>
<p>A series of developments during the 2010–11 football season has led to an intense public debate over the question of the nature and extent of religious sectarianism in Scotland. The Scottish National Party (SNP) government has responded with a new piece of legislation which has been widely criticised and has prompted some commentators to speculate about a political “own goal”. This article provides a guide to the debate around sectarianism and its historical and political dimensions. It also suggests that the Irish roots of the problem in Scotland should be properly acknowledged, and that a possible way forward could involve cooperation between Scotland, Northern Ireland and the Republic of Ireland within the structures and procedures of the British-Irish Council (BIC). [R]</p>
<p>62.5599 WANG Xiaolu — <bold>Hidden income in China and its implications.</bold> <italic>SAIS Review of International Affairs</italic> 32(1), Winter-Spring 2012: 61–72.</p>
<p>This article discusses the existence and quantity of hidden or “gray” income in China, its sources, and how it has contributed to domestic income because it leads to unequal and unfair income distribution and weakened domestic demand, puts social stability at risk, and threatens to undermine future economic development. It recommends a number of reforms to improve China's budgetary and taxation systems as well as its government administrative system in order to build a more transparent and better-regulated national administrative framework. [R]</p>
<p>62.5600 WEIL, Robert — <bold>Is the torch passing? The Maoist revolution in India.</bold> <italic>Socialism and Democracy</italic> 25(3), Nov. 2011: 1–71.</p>
<p>Revolutionary forces led by the Communist Party of India (Maoist) and its military wing have an active presence in at least a third of the country. Their goal is to overthrow the entire Indian political, economic and social system. The impact on which direction India moves can hardly be exaggerated. As the US loses its imperial grasp and the bourgeois democratic system fails to meet the needs of the vast majority of people, the Maoist revolution is confronting issues with worldwide relevance. Success in the revolutionary struggle in India would resonate far beyond its own borders.</p>
<p>62.5601 WHALEN, Christopher — <bold>US debt culture and the dollar's fate.</bold> <italic>National Interest</italic> 119, May-June 2012: 32–42.</p>
<p>America's economic history over the past seven decades has been a story of ever-expanding government, ever-expanding debt and an ever-expanding money supply. Now the price is coming due. If the US cannot get its fiscal house in order, the dollar's privileged position as the world's reserve currency may be at risk—at a time when there seem to be few if any plausible alternatives. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4495]</p>
<p>62.5602 WILLIAMS, Phil — <bold>The terrorism debate over Mexican drug trafficking violence.</bold> <italic>Terrorism and Political Violence</italic> 24(2), Apr.–June 2012: 259–278.</p>
<p>Arguments that Mexico is the victim of growing terrorism are both exaggerated and unconvincing. [Despite] many murders of innocent civilians, these killings do not seem to have been motivated by a political, ideological, or religious cause. This analysis [considers] that the violence is a complex and multi-layered phenomenon with a variety of different rationales and motivations. From this perspective, a pyramidal approach to the violence can be identified, at the base of [which] is the notion of drug-related violence as the medium of rational strategic competition in a highly lucrative illicit market. A second layer emphasizes factionalism within the organizations as well as a process of contracting out for much of the violence to youth gangs and specialists. And a third perspective puts emphasis more on the degeneration of norms and inhibitions. [R, abr.] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4456]</p>
<p>62.5603 WINTER, Lucas — <bold>Conflict in Yemen: simple people, complicated circumstances.</bold> <italic>Middle East Policy</italic> 18(1), Spring 2011: 102–120.</p>
<p>The Huthi conflict in Yemen, which arose within complex circumstances including the rise of Salafism and the effects of the Iraq ware, has now become embedded in a web of larger issues: the nature of political power in Yemen, regional competition between Saudi Arabia and Iran, and the future of Zaydism. Yemen's troubles continue to mount and balancing between security and stability is likely to become even more difficult for the embattled government. With other Arab states being forced to navigate previously uncharted territory, the future of this conflict appears as uncertain as that of the region as a whole.</p>
<p>62.5604 WITSOE, Jeffrey — <bold>Caste and democratization in post-colonial India: an ethnographic examination of lower caste politics in Bihar [India].</bold> <italic>Democratization</italic> 19(2), Apr. 2012: 312–333.</p>
<p>This article examines the case of lower-caste politics in the populous north Indian state of Bihar in order to show the ways in which the liberal democratic model fails to capture the realities of democracy in postcolonial India. In order to explain the rise of lower-caste politics, I examine the ways in which relationships between state institutions, caste networks and locally dominant groups shape contemporary political possibilities, necessitating a re-evaluation of the relationship between liberalism and democracy in India. With state institutions unable to effectively enforce rights, a caste-based notion of popular sovereignty became dominant—as an idea (the lower-caste majority should rule) and as the everyday rough-and-tumble of an electoral politics that ultimately revolves around the force of numbers. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5605 YAHAYA, Issoufou — <bold>“Boko Haram” au Nigéria: le fanatisme religieux comme projet politique (<italic>Boko Haram</italic> in Nigeria: religious fanaticism as a political project).</bold> <italic>Sfera Politicii</italic> 164, Oct. 2011: 12–21.</p>
<p>Since 11 September 2011, Islamist violence has changed. Bandits for some, heroes for others, proselytes use barbarism to political ends. In Nigeria, the tragic irruption in July 2009 of the <italic>Boko Haram</italic> sect, with its cruelty against the symbols of the state, remains in all minds. [R, abr., transl.] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.4432]</p>
<p>62.5606 ZHENG Yongnian — <bold>China in 2011: anger, political consciousness, anxiety, and uncertainty.</bold> <italic>Asian Survey</italic> 52(1), Jan.–Feb. 2012: 28–41.</p>
<p>This paper identifies major trends in China in 2011 and analyzes their implications. The past year has witnessed a continuous rise of anger among social groups, as demonstrated in various forms of social protests. Chinese intellectuals are becoming increasingly politically conscious and calling for political reform. However, the leadership is trapped in the politics of power succession; uncertainty is widespread. [R] [See <italic>Abstr.</italic> 62.5384]</p>
<p>62.5607 ZHUKOV, Yuri M. — <bold>Roads and the diffusion of insurgent violence: the logistics of conflict in Russia's North Caucasus.</bold> <italic>Political Geography</italic> 31(3), March 2012: 144–156.</p>
<p>How does insurgency spread? Existing research on the diffusion of violence at the local level of civil war tends to under-specify the theoretical mechanisms by which conflict can be expanded, relocated or sustained, and overlooks the real-world logistical constraints that combatants face on a daily basis. This paper addresses both problems by taking a closer look at the role of road networks in the diffusion of insurgent activity. By explicating the logic of diffusion in a simple epidemic model and exploiting new disaggregated data on violence and road networks in the North Caucasus, this analysis challenges the conventional view that insurgent logistics are either self-sufficient or highly flexible. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5608 ZIMELIS, Andris — <bold>(Non)determinants of corruption: a sceptical view from Eastern Europe.</bold> <italic>Journal of Comparative Politics</italic> 4(2), July 2011: 4–26.</p>
<p>The article assesses the current state of corruption literature and conducts relevant empirical tests. It explores the validity of the corruption indicators regarded as having high explanatory power and juxtaposes them with empirical facts from several Eastern European countries. The article points out the existing problems with corruption indicators and the oversimplification of the term corruption as well as calls for a more comprehensive approach to studying corruption. [R]</p>
<p>62.5609 ZOU, S. Thangboi — <bold>Emergent micro-national communities: the logic of Kuki-Chin armed struggle in Manipur [India].</bold> <italic>Strategic Analysis</italic> 36(2), March 2012: 315–327.</p>
<p>The granting of scheduled tribe status to the Kuki-Chin people eroded their allegiance to clan and linguistic/dialectal identities. While they do not have any problem with a pan-ethnic identity, their primary loyalty is to their own clans and communities. Invocation of kinship ties by different groups does not necessarily translate into a common political agenda. There are at least 15 armed groups among them that have combined into two larger groups—the United People's Front (UPF) and the Kuki National Organization (KNO)—and signed a peace agreement with the state and central governments. Whereas the militant groups deviated from the macro-nationalist project of the Indian state, their micro-nationalist struggle is not informed by any coherent ideology. [R, abr.]</p>
<p>62.5610 <bold>A changing Middle East [2010—].</bold> <italic>Middle East Policy</italic> 18(3), Fall 2012: 35–120.</p>
<p>Articles by Ann M. LESCH, “Egypt's Spring: causes of the Revolution”, pp. 35–48; Erin A. SNIDER and David M. FARIS, “The Arab Spring: US democracy promotion in Egypt”, pp. 49–62; Ahmed S. HASHIM, “The Egyptian military, part one: from the Ottomans through Sadat”, pp. 63–78; Khaled FATTAH, “Yemen: a social <italic>intifada</italic> in a Republic of Sheikhs”, pp. 79–85; Seymen ATASOY, “The Turkish example: a model for change in the Middle East?”, pp. 86–100; Katherine Blue CARROLI, “Not your parents' political party: young Sunnis and the new Iraqi democracy”, pp. 101–120.</p>
<p>62.5611 <bold>ägypten (Egypt).</bold> <italic>Internationale Politik—Global Edition</italic> 2012(3–4): 18–63.</p>
<p>Articles [in German] by Anja ZOROB; Jan Claudius VÖLKEL; Dima TARHINI.</p>
<p>62.5612 <bold>Roundtable on loyalty and criticism in the relations between World Jewry and Israel.</bold> <italic>Israel Studies</italic> 17(2), Summer 2012: 77–128.</p>
<p>Articles by Gabriel SHEFFER, “Loyalty and criticism in the relations between World Jewry and Israel”, pp. 77–85 [Response by Steven BAYME, pp. 111–119]; Yehezkel DROR, “Diaspora-Israel relations: a long-term perspective”, pp. 86–91; Leonard SAXE and Matthew BOXER, “Loyalty and love of Israel by diasporan Jews”, pp. 92–101; Daniel GORDIS, “From a Jewish people to a Jewish religion: a shifting American Jewish <italic>Weltanschauung</italic> and its implications for Israel”, pp. 102–110; Steven BAYME, “On Gabriel Sheffer's ‘Loyalty and criticism in the relations between World Jewry and Israel”, pp. 111–119 [See pp. 77–85]; Eliezer DON-YEHIYA, “Jewish orthodoxy and its attitude to Israel”, pp. 120–128.</p>
<p>62.5613 <bold>USA (Die) vor der Präsidentschaftswahl (The US before the [2012] presidential election).</bold> <italic>Politische Studien</italic> 441, Jan.–Feb. 2012: 15–55.</p>
<p>Articles by Reinhard MEIER-WALSER; Philip D. MURPHY; Heinz GÄRTNER; Jana PUGLIERIN; Josef BRAML; Thomas SILBERHORN.</p>
</body>
</article>