<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TRA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptra</journal-id>
<journal-title>Trauma</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1460-4086</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0350</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1460408612437303</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1460408612437303</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Review Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Early computed tomography scanning in multisystem trauma: The evidence</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>PAF</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1460408612437303">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1460408612437303"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1460408612437303">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1460408612437303">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1460408612437303"><label>1</label>Intensive Care Unit, James Cook University Hospital, Middlesbrough, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1460408612437303"><label>2</label>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust, Northern General Hospital, Sheffield, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1460408612437303"><label>3</label>Emergency Department, Wansbeck General Hospital, Ashington, UK</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1460408612437303">PAF Hunt, Specialist Registrar in Emergency Medicine and Intensive Care Medicine, Intensive Care Unit, James Cook University Hospital, Marton Road, Middlesbrough, TS4 3BW, UK. Email: <email>paulantonyhunt@doctors.org.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>287</fpage>
<lpage>300</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The utility of computed tomography as a radiological investigation following multisystem trauma is already well established in current practice. This article examines the existing evidence and rationale behind the use of early computed tomography scanning in the management of the multisystem trauma patient, with a particular emphasis on the use of ‘whole body’ computed tomography scanning as a component of their initial management in the Emergency Department.</p>
<p>The use of computed tomography has been shown to be superior to plain radiography for the detection of injuries in important body regions including the spine, thorax, abdomen and pelvis. Computed tomography scan of the head and cervical spine is also well established as the first investigation of choice for significant traumatic brain injury. The potential benefits of whole body computed tomography include reduced time to diagnosis and intervention, as well as significant improvements in clinical outcome and survival. Concerns regarding a whole body computed tomography approach relate to the increased ionising radiation dosage that patients will be exposed to, and perceived risks of the secondary transfer and scanning room environment itself. Potential barriers to the use of whole body computed tomography are also explored and discussed.</p>
<p>This article also presents a proposed clinical algorithm derived from the results of a recent Delphi study into whole body computed tomography following blunt multitrauma, along with conclusions and recommendations from the subject matter panel review process.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Computed tomography (CT)</kwd>
<kwd>whole body computed tomography (WBCT)</kwd>
<kwd>multisystem trauma</kwd>
<kwd>polytrauma</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1460408612437303" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>The utility of computed tomography (CT) as a radiological investigation following multisystem trauma is already well established in current practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1460408612437303">ACS, 2008</xref>). The National Confidential Enquiry into Patient Outcomes (NCEPOD) report in 2007 demonstrated that more than half of multiple-injured patients in England and Wales received ‘less than good’ care. Among the principle recommendations from this report was that when CT scans were required ‘<italic>the routine use of “top to toe” scanning is recommended in the adult trauma patient if no indication for immediate intervention exists</italic>’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1460408612437303">NCEPOD, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>In general, the clinical management of trauma patients in the United Kingdom relies upon individual decision making by the trauma team leader, in conjunction with advice from relevant speciality teams. This includes decisions relating to radiological imaging such as CT. A recent survey of UK Emergency Departments revealed that only 22.3% had a formal policy in place for ‘whole body’ computed tomography (WBCT) use. A further 23.4% made decisions to use WBCT scanning on a case-by-case basis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1460408612437303">Smith and Mason, 2011</xref>). The Delphi consultation process with UK hospital clinicians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1460408612437303">Hunt, 2010</xref>) revealed that several institutions have already developed, or are in the process of establishing, WBCT scan guidelines or protocols for victims of blunt trauma. There is relatively little published data or subsequent recommendations for the use of WBCT for trauma patients from institutions in the United Kingdom. Examples include Southampton General Hospital (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1460408612437303">Sampson et al., 2006</xref>) and University Hospitals Coventry and Warwickshire (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1460408612437303">Smith et al., 2011</xref>). However, the criteria for requesting WBCT vary, with authors suggesting that WBCT be performed on the basis of mechanism of injury alone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1460408612437303">Smith et al., 2011</xref>), in the presence of head injury because of the unreliability of clinical examination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1460408612437303">Self et al., 2003</xref>), on the basis of the anatomical pattern of injury (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1460408612437303">Sampson et al., 2006</xref>) or a combination of several independent variables including the injury mechanism, anatomical pattern and physiological parameters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1460408612437303">Wurmb et al., 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>The recently published National Audit Office (NAO) report into major trauma care in England does not explicitly discuss the issue of WBCT scanning in trauma. It does, however, reiterate the value of CT scanning in patients with major trauma to quickly reveal unsuspected injuries, and the importance of having mechanisms in place to ensure that timely CT scanning is undertaken. This should reduce the need for additional investigations and, in turn, the time to ‘definitive care’. The report also acknowledged that data from the Trauma Audit Research Network (TARN) seemed to demonstrate that there are many situations where trauma patients who required a CT scan in their initial management did not receive one (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1460408612437303">NAO, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>In this article, we aim to examine the evidence and rationale behind the use of early CT scanning in the management of the multisystem trauma patient, with a particular emphasis on the use of WBCT scanning.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1460408612437303"><title>Definitions</title>
<p>For the purpose of this article, we have defined ‘early CT’ as an investigation undertaken in the initial stages of managing the trauma patient, for example, during examination and resuscitation following arrival in the ED.</p>
<p>The following definition of blunt multisystem trauma was agreed by the subject matter expert panel during the course of the WBCT Delphi study referred to later in this article (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1460408612437303">Hunt, 2010</xref>):
<list id="list1-1460408612437303" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Injuries occurring due to a relevant blunt trauma mechanism (e.g. road traffic collision deceleration, fall or blast).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Injuries involving two or more regions of the body (with or without evidence on plain X-ray or other imaging).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Continued cardiorespiratory or central neurological compromise despite initial resuscitation.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>‘Focussed’ CT refers to selective scanning of specific regions of the body where injuries are seen or suspected after clinical examination. WBCT refers to a non-selective scanning approach, and usually involves a non-contrast-enhanced CT scan of the head and neck followed immediately by a contrast-enhanced CT scan of the thorax, abdomen and pelvis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1460408612437303"><title>Focussed CT or WBCT?</title>
<p>Very few studies have explicitly investigated the potential benefit of WBCT over ‘focussed’ CT or ‘organ-specific’ CT scanning in multisystem trauma. The diagnostic accuracy of focussed CT scanning of different body regions is discussed further below, but, to the best of our knowledge, there is no data regarding the sensitivity or specificity of WBCT as an independent diagnostic test for the detection of significant traumatic injuries. Nonetheless, many UK acute hospitals regularly utilise a WBCT scanning approach in the management of multisystem trauma patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1460408612437303">Smith and Mason, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Focussed CT scanning is clearly appropriate where there are signs of significant injury to specific organ systems or body regions following trauma. Evidence of a traumatic brain injury would warrant a CT head scan according to established criteria – for example, from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1460408612437303">NICE (2007)</xref>. Similarly, the presence of a blunt abdominal injury and relevant clinical features may suggest CT scanning of the abdomen to determine if there is a significant splenic or hepatic injury that may require emergency surgery. However, the decision whether to undergo a more focussed versus a ‘whole body’ scan approach relies upon multiple factors including consideration of the patient's physiology, mechanism of injury, clinical features, as well as non-clinical factors such as logistical constraints. There is a paucity of evidence with which to guide this decision-making process or to help determine what factors, if any, may recommend one approach over the other in any given patient.</p>
<p>There are several barriers to conducting effective randomised controlled trials to investigate the true utility of a focussed versus WBCT scanning approach in multisystem trauma. For example, one Dutch study group reported difficulties in recruiting the necessary number of patients into a cluster randomised controlled trial that compared WBCT alone to ‘conventional’ radiography followed by focussed CT. This was reportedly due to the perceived superiority of the WBCT approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1460408612437303">Saltzherr and Goslings, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Organisational processes, rather than clinical deficiencies, are often implicated in poor trauma care (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1460408612437303">NCEPOD, 2007</xref>). Therefore, in order to demonstrate that patient outcome may be improved by using a WBCT versus a ‘conventional’ focussed CT approach, these factors would need to be considered and allowed for. However, correcting for such regional variations in quality and service infrastructure would be complex if not impossible.</p>
<p>As a result, most of the available evidence regarding the use of WBCT or focussed CT in trauma, and comparisons between the different approaches, involves retrospective analyses of case series or ‘before-and-after’ type studies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1460408612437303"><title>Evidence for the use of focussed CT in multisystem trauma</title>
<p>One of the perceived benefits of CT is the improved detection of traumatic injuries. The use of CT has been shown to be superior to plain radiography for detecting injury in important body regions including the spine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1460408612437303">Antevil, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1460408612437303">Brown, 2005</xref>), thorax (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1460408612437303">Albrecht et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1460408612437303">Exadaktylos, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1460408612437303">Karmy-Jones, 2004</xref>), abdomen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1460408612437303">Albrecht et al., 2004</xref>) and pelvis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1460408612437303">Kessel, 2007</xref>). CT scan of the head and cervical spine is also well established as the first investigation of choice for significant traumatic brain injury (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1460408612437303">NICE, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Few studies exclusively investigate the role of ‘selective’ or ‘focussed’ CT scanning for multisystem trauma. In their prospective observational study of 465 trauma patients with a significant mechanism of injury, Deunk and colleagues found that additional injuries were found in patients who had ‘routine’ CT of abdomen, pelvis and lumbar spine, rather than ‘selective’ CT based on abnormal clinical findings, abdominal ultrasound or lumbar-spine or pelvic X-ray abnormalities. They estimate that 6.4% of patients had their clinical management changed as a result of ‘routine’ CT that would not have occurred with ‘selective’ CT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1460408612437303">Deunk et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1460408612437303"><title>The use of WBCT scanning in multisystem trauma</title>
<p>In their prospective investigation of 296 trauma CT studies over a 7-year period, Sampson et al. noted that a small, but significant number of injuries were detected by CT that had not been demonstrated by plain radiography. ‘Missed’ cervical spine injury was detected by CT in 6% of all cases and ‘missed’ pneumothorax detected by CT in 12% of cases. The CT protocol they used consisted of non-contrast head and cervical spine plus oral, and intravenous contrast-enhanced thoracic, abdomen and pelvis scans. Although the number of cases fulfilling the study criteria were small (less than 0.05% of estimated total ED admissions over the 7-year period), the authors concluded that a wide range of significant injuries had been demonstrated rapidly, accurately and safely, and that the overall impact on workload was small (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1460408612437303">Sampson et al., 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>A before-and-after study examining the consequences of introducing a mechanism of injury-based WBCT policy at University Hospitals Coventry and Warwickshire showed that unanticipated injuries were detected in 8% of cases in which the lack of clinical findings in that body region would not have otherwise triggered a request for a CT of that area. However, a significant change in clinical management occurred in only 1% of cases and several of the WBCT scans performed showed no signs of injury at all (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1460408612437303">Smith et al., 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>A prospective observational study involving 1000 trauma patients demonstrated an alteration in clinical management in 18.9% of patients as a direct result of WBCT. One of the conclusions was that a ‘significant’ mechanism of injury alone could be used as justification for a WBCT scan, even in patients with no discernable signs of thoracic or abdominal injury. The authors found that the rate of injury detection in the thorax, abdomen or pelvis was no different between awake patients with normal clinical examination findings and patients who were difficult to evaluate because of a depressed level of consciousness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1460408612437303">Salim et al., 2006</xref>). However, criticism has been levelled at this study due to apparent methodological weaknesses, main concern being that a more indiscriminate use of WBCT scans, as suggested, would result in a significant increase in radiation-related complications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1460408612437303">Snyder, 2008</xref>). The clinical significance of the change in treatment was not fully explored by Salim and his colleagues, and no comment on long-term patient outcomes was made.</p>
<p>Self and colleagues further argue that clinical examination is unreliable in trauma patients, particularly in those with closed head injury. The authors conducted a database review of blunt trauma patients with closed head injuries who had undergone a CT head, and also had CT of thorax, abdomen and pelvis performed. There was a change in management in around a quarter of cases after CT, and this figure was independent of whether or not patients had ‘positive’ examination findings in those body regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1460408612437303">Self et al., 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>In all such studies that rely on data interpretation after the event, there is the assumption that an appropriate and comprehensive clinical examination was carried out and recorded consistently. It is certainly possible that bias may be introduced by an over-reliance upon CT imaging, where readily available, in preference to clinical examination alone. This should be taken into account when comparing outcomes in trauma from different imaging protocols.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1460408612437303"><title>Patient outcomes after WBCT</title>
<sec id="sec7-1460408612437303"><title>Time to diagnosis or intervention</title>
<p>Implementation of a WBCT policy has been associated with reduced time to completion of diagnostic imaging and to the formulation of a definitive management plan when compared to ‘standard’ X-rays (chest, pelvis, lateral cervical spine) augmented with focussed ultrasound scanning of the abdomen and ‘targeted’ CT of certain body areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1460408612437303">Wurmb et al., 2009</xref>). This was a retrospective non-interventional review of patient management, and so there are likely to have been differences between the WBCT and non-WBCT patients.</p>
<p>A before-and-after study looking at the effect of a WBCT policy on multiple-injured patients concluded that, when compared to ‘conventional’ X-rays and focussed CT, it reduced the time to the start of emergency surgery when it was required (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1460408612437303">Wurmb et al., 2011</xref>). However, it is not clear whether the findings on WBCT were directly responsible for the decision to undertake emergency surgical intervention. Another before-and-after study demonstrated a mean reduction in time to a definitive diagnosis of 29 min and a mean reduction in the time spent in the ED of 34 min (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1460408612437303">Weninger et al., 2007</xref>), although this does not necessarily translate to a significant improvement in mortality or morbidity.</p>
<p>Such protocolised use of WBCT must again be considered in the context of organisational changes and general improvements in the management of trauma patients over time. Establishing a convincing <italic>causal</italic> link between the use of WBCT and reduced time to a definitive clinical intervention must take this into account. Also, definitions such as ‘definitive management’ prevent direct comparisons on a retrospective basis due to inherent variability in clinical approaches and service organisation between institutions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1460408612437303"><title>Clinical outcome</title>
<p>In their large retrospective multicentre study of 9259 patients, Huber-Wagner et al. utilised data from the German Trauma Society trauma registry to compare outcomes following polytrauma of 9259 patients who either underwent WBCT or non-WBCT. The Standardised Mortality Ratio (SMR) based on Trauma Revised Injury Severity Score (TRISS) methodology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1460408612437303">Boyd et al., 1987</xref>) was shown to be significantly lower for patients following WBCT than for those given non-WBCT, suggesting that integration of WBCT into early trauma management significantly increased the probability of survival in patients with polytrauma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1460408612437303">Huber-Wagner et al., 2009</xref>). However, this study was limited by its retrospective design and by missing data in the trauma registry that permitted the calculation of TRISS in only 49% of patients. WBCT protocols were not clearly defined and inconsistency was noted in the grading of injuries. Considerable statistical adjustments were undertaken to account for variations in hospital level, and other potential confounding factors including logistical and organisational variability between centres. It should also be noted that unadjusted overall survival between the whole body and non-whole body groups was no different, although the mean Injury Severity Score (ISS) in the whole body group was significantly higher. As ISS is a retrospective score and CT findings will contribute to this calculation, so it is possible that ISS in the whole body group was higher simply because more injuries were detected. Bias was also introduced by way of ‘immortal time bias’ – for example, patients receiving WBCT naturally survived (at least for as long as the scan took to carry out), while patients who died before reaching the CT were assigned to the comparison group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1460408612437303">Andersohn et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Two other before-and-after studies have reached conflicting conclusions about the effect of WBCT on patient outcome. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1460408612437303">Wurmb et al. (2011)</xref> demonstrated no differences in length of hospital stay, intensive care days or overall survival in their cohort of trauma patients. In contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1460408612437303">Weninger et al. (2007)</xref> reported a reduction in intensive care days, ventilator days and rates of organ failure among trauma patients after the introduction of a WBCT policy. The heterogeneity of the patient populations within and between these two studies are potentially significant confounding factors and highlights one of the main difficulties in attempting to analyse such data meaningfully.</p>
<p>A meta-analysis of the pooled results from the studies by Huber-Wagner et al., Weninger et al. and Wurmb et al. showed no differences in survival between trauma patients who did or did not undergo WBCT as part of their trauma management (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1460408612437303">Stengel et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1460408612437303"><title>Concerns about the use of WBCT</title>
<sec id="sec10-1460408612437303"><title>Ionising radiation</title>
<p>One of the main concerns regarding WBCT scans is the high-dose and often cumulative exposure to ionising radiation. The exact impact of this may be difficult to determine for certain, as the only long-term data available is from people who have been exposed to far higher doses of radiation, such as atomic bomb survivors. The risks from CT have been extrapolated after assuming that the linear association between increased dose and increased risk at higher levels of radiation still applies at lower levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1460408612437303">McCollough et al., 2009</xref>). However, examination of a British registry shows that radiation workers – who have a high cumulative radiation exposure – do indeed show higher lifetime risks of developing both solid organ cancers and leukaemias (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1460408612437303">Muirhead et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1460408612437303">Brenner and Elliston (2004)</xref> estimate the radiation-induced mortality for ‘full-body’ CT scanning to be 1 in 1250 with a total dose of 15 mSv. However, many multiple-injured patients could receive several times that amount of radiation during their hospital stay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1460408612437303">Salottolo et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1460408612437303">Winslow et al., 2008</xref>). Wedegartner et al. demonstrated that patients were exposed to up to three times more ionising radiation when undergoing WBCT (multislice) compared to conventional radiography with organ-specific CT in polytrauma. The highest radiation burden was noted to occur during abdominal and pelvic scans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1460408612437303">Wedegartner et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>In their review, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1460408612437303">Brenner and Hall (2007)</xref> observed that, although no large-scale epidemiologic studies of the cancer risks associated with CT scans have been reported, estimates suggest that around 0.4% of all cancers in the United States may be attributable to the radiation from CT investigations. In another study, the estimated lifetime risk of fatal cancer from cumulative in-hospital radiation (from CT and X-rays) was estimated at 0.78% for trauma patients who spent at least 30 days in an Intensive Care Unit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1460408612437303">Kim et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Importantly, children are thought to have 10 times the sensitivity to radiation as adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1460408612437303">Slovis, 2002</xref>), and <italic>effective</italic> radiation doses are often higher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1460408612437303">Munk et al., 2009</xref>). This contributes to a probable increased lifetime risk of developing fatal cancer in children than in adults, with infants and younger children being even more susceptible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1460408612437303">Brenner et al., 2001</xref>). Efforts made to reduce the amount of ionising radiation delivered to a patient must be balanced with the need to avoid compromising image quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1460408612437303">Donnelly et al., 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>Although newer generation CT scanners may deliver higher radiation doses than their predecessors, other improvements mean that doses can be minimised for individual patients, dependent on body region, age and size of patient, without affecting the quality of the image produced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1460408612437303">Anderson et al., 2006</xref>). WBCT can also be performed as a ‘single pass’ scan, rather than as a group of sequential scans. This can be significantly quicker than sequential scanning and deliver a lower radiation dose, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1460408612437303">Ptak et al., 2003</xref>) without affecting image quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1460408612437303">Fanucci et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1460408612437303">Nguyen et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-1460408612437303"><title>Other concerns with WBCT scanning</title>
<sec id="sec12-1460408612437303"><title>Safe patient transfer and the CT scanner environment</title>
<p>Additional risks are involved when transferring and managing a patient in the CT scanning room environment compared to the relatively ‘safe’ resuscitation room although this risk could be negated by closer positioning or co-location of resuscitation resources with the scanning facility. It has been demonstrated that the entire process of carrying out a WBCT scan, including patient handling, can be performed in less than 30 min in optimal conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1460408612437303">Leidner and Beckman, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1460408612437303">Self et al., 2003</xref>). As previously mentioned, improvements in the time taken to establish a definitive management plan may outweigh the potential risks of transfer and conduct of CT scanning.</p>
<p>The decision regarding which patients are sufficiently ‘stable’ to go to scan requires a high degree of clinical acumen, and is as much affected by organisational factors such as CT proximity to, or co-location with, the resuscitation room, as it is by clinical factors. Provision of a ‘resuscitation room-adjacent’ CT scanner was one of a number of recommendations from NCEPOD, but in 2007, only 57.4% of hospitals in England and Wales had this facility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1460408612437303">NCEPOD, 2007</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-1460408612437303"><title>Potential clinical delay</title>
<p>Another concern regarding severely injured trauma patients is that additional or unnecessary clinical delays to surgical intervention may affect their outcome. For example, patients arriving in the ED with blunt abdominal injuries and hypotension requiring laparotomy were estimated to have a 1% greater chance of dying for every 3 min ‘extra’ spent in the ED in the first hour and a half of management (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1460408612437303">Clarke et al., 2002</xref>). In England and Wales, only 27.8% of patients who required a laparotomy had their operation started within 3 h of their arrival in hospital if they had a CT scan of their thorax, abdomen and/or pelvis first (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1460408612437303">NCEPOD, 2007</xref>). An important question is whether the potential benefits of early surgical intervention outweigh the potential benefits of keeping a patient in the ED to establish a firm diagnosis, perhaps by including the use of WBCT. Determining which patients should <italic>not</italic> undergo WBCT and instead go straight to theatre is therefore just as important a clinical question to answer as determining those who will benefit from WBCT scanning during their initial ED assessment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-1460408612437303"><title>Diagnostic error</title>
<p>Errors in diagnosis are known to be common when managing multitrauma victims, especially in the most unstable patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1460408612437303">Stanescu et al., 2006</xref>). Overall rates of ‘missed injury’ have been falling over the last 25 years, making it difficult to assess the effect of the fairly recent introduction of WBCT to trauma management (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1460408612437303">Stengel et al., 2009</xref>). Missed injuries from WBCT scanning have been reported, particularly with certain intra-abdominal injuries such as small bowel perforation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1460408612437303">Albrecht et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1460408612437303">Röhrl et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1460408612437303">Smith et al., 2011</xref>). In a recent study, 3.5% of all injuries were not immediately detected or communicated following WBCT scanning, although the clinical significance of these was not commented upon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1460408612437303">Rieger et al., 2009</xref>). Interpretation of WBCT should be carried out by an appropriate experienced ‘trauma’ radiologist, or could combine the opinions of several different radiologists specialising in relevant body regions. Possible inaccuracies can be reduced by the cross-checking of images with a second radiologist, but this approach is likely to introduce further delays between the ‘initial’ and ‘final’ image analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1460408612437303">Heyer et al., 2005</xref>). All this, however, requires significant resources and has implications for workforce planning, particularly when ‘out-of-hours’ CT scan reporting is required.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-1460408612437303"><title>Patient selection for WBCT scanning</title>
<p>Appropriate selection criteria for WBCT scanning are vital to ensure maximum benefit, while minimising risk. Concerns about the risks of ionising radiation and the risks associated with movement of a potentially unstable, injured patient to and from the CT scanner room are valid arguments against the unregulated use of WBCT in all trauma patients. The <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1460408612437303">American College of Radiology (2010)</xref> do have ‘appropriateness criteria’ for the use of CT for trauma in the head, chest, abdomen or spine, although it is unclear whether these could be used in combination for a potential WBCT protocol. In the United Kingdom, the Royal College of Radiologists (RCR) recommends standards for CT and interventional radiology which call for 24 hour/day availability and an interventional response within 30 minutes of call. Scanners must be properly sited (close to the ED) and be properly equipped rooms. The RCR is also developing imaging standards for severe trauma to accompany this advice (personal communication: Tony Nicholson, 6 June 2010).</p>
<p>Many centres currently use predetermined criteria for selecting patients for WBCT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1460408612437303">Leidner and Beckman, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1460408612437303">Linsenmaier et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1460408612437303">Wurmb et al., 2007</xref>) that resemble established pre-hospital trauma triage criteria such as those used in the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1460408612437303">Sasser et al., 2009</xref>) and by the London Trauma Network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1460408612437303">London Ambulance Service, 2009</xref>). Such pre-hospital trauma triage criteria, however, have been associated with over-triage rates as high as 50% when fully implemented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1460408612437303">American College of Surgeons, 2006</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1460408612437303">Wurmb et al. (2007)</xref> used a final calculated ISS of &lt; 16 to denote ‘over-triage’ in their study of 126 consecutive multiple-injured intubated or ventilated patients who had received WBCT according to pre-determined selection criteria. The authors calculated that 30.6% of scans could be deemed unnecessary (a positive predictive value of 69.4%) and that there were 2/35 (5.7%) false negatives in the ISS &lt; 16 group (a negative predictive value of 94.3%). Although these findings are interesting, it should be noted that this was a highly selected patient group and that retrospective application of the ISS would be of little use in the acute clinical situation. Published evidence concerning the diagnostic efficacy of WBCT or the effectiveness of WBCT selection criteria is lacking, but a retrospective study, aiming to establish the diagnostic accuracy of WBCT and to evaluate the potential clinical benefits of this approach on patient outcomes, has recently been completed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1460408612437303">Current Controlled Trials, 2010</xref>). However, the results of this study are yet to be reported (personal communication with lead investigator, Dirk Stengel, 21 March 2011).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec16-1460408612437303"><title>Conclusions and further work</title>
<p>Overall, there is a paucity of good evidence with which to advise best practice in the use of WBCT scanning. However, it is possible to state from the best evidence currently available that appropriately implemented WBCT scanning protocols can result in detection of clinically significant injuries that may not be demonstrated by plain radiological imaging, or a focussed CT scan approach alone. Carrying out this investigation early in the assessment of the multitrauma patient could enable the identification of clinically significant injuries that require urgent intervention and therefore result in improved mortality and morbidity outcomes. Further research is needed to focus on possible improvements in mortality or morbidity outcomes from a protocol-driven WBCT scan approach in multisystem trauma.</p>
<p>In the United Kingdom, a recent Delphi study was carried out as the first step in developing a wider research programme investigating this topic. From this Delphi study, a series of consensus statements from subject-matter experts across the United Kingdom regarding the practice of WBCT scanning in blunt multitrauma were formulated, and this provided some initial recommendations for best practice and highlighted areas where further research would be required. Proposed organisational standards for WBCT scanning in multisystem trauma and a provisional ED protocol have been produced as a result of the Delphi consultation and are shown in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1460408612437303">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1460408612437303">2</xref>, respectively. Although representing a low level of evidence, the organisational standards and clinical protocol that have been developed through this study offers a potential WBCT scanning approach based upon expert opinion that may be adapted for local implementation as appropriate. Prospective clinical evaluation of the protocol will also be a further important research objective (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1460408612437303">Hunt, 2010</xref>).
<fig id="fig1-1460408612437303" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Proposed recommendations for the use of whole body computed tomography (WBCT) in blunt multitrauma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1460408612437303">Hunt, 2010</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1460408612437303-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig2-1460408612437303" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Provisional Emergency Department protocol for whole body computed tomography (WBCT) scanning in blunt multitrauma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1460408612437303">Hunt, 2010</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1460408612437303-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Unanswered research questions regarding the utility of WBCT scanning include which, if any, injury mechanism and/or clinical factors would result in measurably better outcomes compared to the use of a focussed CT scanning protocol for multisystem trauma. Prospective evaluation of existing WBCT protocols or, preferably, de novo evidence-based development and then prospective validation of a new clinical decision tool is required. Direct prospective comparison, ideally by use of a randomised trial design, between WBCT and ‘conventional’ plain radiography with or without focussed CT or additional ultrasound would represent the highest level of evidence yet presented to support or refute such approaches. ‘Hard’ outcomes, such as patient mortality and morbidity, would need to be included, as well as other measures such as diagnostic accuracy of imaging and time to ‘definitive’ intervention.</p>
<p>The true long-term risks of exposing a greater number of trauma patients to CT or WBCT have not yet been fully established. Precise rates of radiation-related complications and mortality from cancers attributable to the use of ionising radiation in trauma patients are unknown. Local or national measures of cost effectiveness or cost utility of different strategies for the use of CT or WBCT have also not been established.</p>
<p>Importantly, the use of CT should not be seen as an alternative to thorough and comprehensive physical examination in the ED nor should it supersede the use of senior, experienced clinicians in leading the resuscitation and ongoing management of the multiple-injured patient, while maintaining effective and well-resourced trauma systems. Also, traumatic injuries that are not evident at the time of CT scanning may develop over time, and changes in a patient's condition would mandate a re-evaluation of the patient and their injuries in the context of their injury mechanism and individual patient factors. Despite the implicit suggestion in the study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1460408612437303">Salim et al. (2006)</xref>, it would be inappropriate to use a routine WBCT scanning approach as a method to exclude significant injury, in order to enable early discharge from the ED following multisystem trauma.</p>
<p>The justification for WBCT seems intuitively to be strongest in those with immediately evident multiple significant injuries or who have the potential for such injuries from a certain mechanism or subsequent physiological manifestations. Factors such as the mechanism of injury, anatomical injury pattern, physiological signs and patient's response to resuscitation or to a specific clinical intervention will help determine whether a patient would require WBCT scanning in the course of their initial assessment or, indeed, some other early intervention such as emergency surgery. Scoring systems, such as ISS, are usually calculated retrospectively and often include findings from diagnostic imaging or at operative intervention, and therefore are unlikely to be helpful in the initial evaluation of a potentially severely injured trauma patient.</p>
<p>The ability of hospitals to deliver urgent WBCT scanning and reporting, as well as any subsequent urgent interventions that may be required, on a 24-h basis is one of the main limiting factors. ‘Major’ trauma may only contribute less than 0.2% of the ED workload in England (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1460408612437303">NAO, 2010</xref>), but 7% of hospitalised trauma patients are shown to go on to die (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1460408612437303">Christensen et al., 2008</xref>). Currently, there are efforts to expand the ED consultant workforce and thus increase consultant presence in the ED ‘out-of-hours’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1460408612437303">College of Emergency Medicine, 2008</xref>). Furthermore, a re-organisation of trauma care into Regional Trauma Networks has commenced in London and is planned for all Strategic Health Authorities in England during the 2011/2012 financial year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1460408612437303">Nicholson, 2010</xref>). It will be interesting to see how this may influence observed patterns of WBCT scan use. If patients with severe multiple injuries are being sent only to a limited number of hospitals, it may well be sensible to focus the resources required for the appropriate use of WBCT to these sites, particularly if the resources for definitive management that may subsequently be required are also only available in these hospitals.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec17-1460408612437303"><title>Clinical bottom line</title>
<p>The use of WBCT scanning will undoubtedly become more common in the initial management of patients with multisystem trauma. The developing concept of regional trauma networks and trauma centres is likely to lead to a concentration of resources in larger hospital EDs. This will require a robust and evidence-based approach to ensure resuscitation and CT facilities are utilised safely and effectively in appropriately selected patients, and that this approach will assist in diagnosing significant injuries without introducing unnecessary delay to the definitive management of those injuries. It cannot be automatically assumed that the introduction of WBCT will bring about immediate benefits to patient care, and further research is required to establish appropriate guidelines or protocols ideally based upon good quality prospective randomised controlled trials. A focussed CT scan approach would normally be indicated for significant single-region injuries such as a solitary traumatic brain injury or penetrating torso injury in absence of other injuries. However, it should be recognised that in the obtunded patient with a significant head injury, attention should also be paid to the presence of injuries such as spinal, thoracic, or pelvis or long bone fractures when considering the injury mechanism.</p>
<p>Significant controversy remains regarding the role of WBCT in terms of the balance of risk and benefit. A lack of evidence to suggest reliable reductions in mortality and morbidity is a concern when considering the significant lifetime risk of radiation-induced complications, and the potential additional risks of patient transfer and delay to operative intervention where trauma services are not optimally delivered. Significant confounding factors to existing research into these issues include the variability in clinical services and organisational structure between different regions and hospital trusts. Another key factor will include successful integration with established pre-hospital care services to ensure that the right patient reaches the right hospital at the right time.</p>
<p>Decision making regarding the use of CT scanning will continue to be the responsibility of experienced clinical teams. Trauma patients with apparent or potential serious injuries should be managed by suitably experienced senior clinicians and within a clinical governance system that allows appropriate logistical and multidisciplinary support.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec18-1460408612437303"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commerical, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>von Schlippenbach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahel</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The role of whole body spiral CT in the primary work-up of polytrauma patients—comparison with conventional radiography and abdominal sonography (in German)</article-title>. <source>RöFo</source> <volume>176</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1142</fpage>–<lpage>1150</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>American College of Radiology (2010) Appropriateness criteria. Overview: searching for clinical conditions. Available at:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://acsearch.acr.org/">http://acsearch.acr.org/</ext-link> (accessed 24 March 2011).</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>American College of Surgeons</collab> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Resources for the Optimal Care of the Injured Patient</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IL: American College of Surgeons</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>American College of Surgeons, Committee on Trauma</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <source>ATLS: Advanced Trauma Life Support Program for Doctors</source>, <edition>8th edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American College of Surgeons</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersohn</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Giannoudis</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Strohm</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Effect on survival of whole-body CT during trauma resuscitation (Correspondence)</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>374</volume>(<issue>9685</issue>): <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucey</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Varghese</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Sixty-four multi-detector row computed tomography in multitrauma patient imaging: early experience</article-title>. <source>Current Problems in Diagnostic Radiology</source> <volume>35</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>188</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Antevil JL, Sise MJ, Sack DI, et al. (2006) Spiral computed tomography for the initial evaluation of spine trauma: a new standard of care? <italic>Journal of Trauma</italic> 61(2): 382--387</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Boyd CR, Tolson MA and Copes WS (1987) Evaluating trauma care: The TRISS method. <italic>Journal of Trauma</italic> 27: 370--378</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliston</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Estimated radiation risks potentially associated with full-body CT screening</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source> <volume>232</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>738</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliston</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Estimated risks of radiation-induced fatal cancer from pediatric CT</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Roentgenology</source> <volume>176</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Computed tomography—an increasing source of radiation exposure</article-title>. <source>The New England Journal of Medicine</source> <volume>357</volume>(<issue>22</issue>): <fpage>2277</fpage>–<lpage>2284</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Brown CV, Antevil JL, Sise MJ, Sack DI (2005) Spiral computed tomography for the diagnosis of cervical, thoracic, and lumbar spine fractures: its time has come. <italic>Journal of Trauma</italic> 58(5): 890--895</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ridley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecky</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Outcomes and costs of blunt trauma in England and Wales</article-title>. <source>Critical Care</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>R23</fpage>–<lpage>R23</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Trooskin</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Doshi</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Time to laparotomy for intra-abdominal bleeding from trauma does affect survival for delays up to 90 minutes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Trauma</source> <volume>52</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>420</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="web"><collab>College of Emergency Medicine</collab>. <article-title>The way ahead 2008-2012</article-title>, <year>2008</year>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.collemergencymed.ac.uk/asp/document.asp?ID=4474">http://www.collemergencymed.ac.uk/asp/document.asp?ID=4474</ext-link> (accessed 15 December 2010)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Current Controlled Trials</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Diagnostic efficacy and effectiveness of primary whole-body computed tomography (Pan-CT) in severe and multiple trauma</article-title>. <source>ISRCTN41462125. From the International Standard Randomised Controlled Trial Number (ISRCTN) Register.</source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.controlled-trials.com/ISRCTN41462125/Diagnostic+efficacy+effectiveness+of+primary+whole-body+computed+tomography">http://www.controlled-trials.com/ISRCTN41462125/Diagnostic+efficacy+effectiveness+of+primary+whole-body+computed+tomography</ext-link> (accessed 24 March 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deunk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Routine versus selective computed tomography of the abdomen, pelvis, and lumbar spine in blunt trauma: a prospective evaluation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Trauma</source> <volume>66</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1108</fpage>–<lpage>1117</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Minimizing radiation dose for pediatric body applications of single-detector helical CT: strategies at a large Children's Hospital</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Roentgenology</source> <volume>176</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Exadaktylos AK, Sclabas G, Schmid SW, et al. (2001) Do we really need routine computed tomographic scanning in the primary evaluation of blunt chest trauma in patients with ‘normal’ chest radiograph? <italic>Journal of Trauma</italic> 51: 1173–1176</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fanucci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiaschetti</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rotili</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Whole body 16-row multislice CT in emergency room: effects of different protocols on scanning time, image quality and radiation exposure</article-title>. <source>Emergency Radiology</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heyer</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rduch</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of multiple trauma victims with 16-row multidetector CT (MDCT): a time analysis (in German)</article-title>. <source>RöFo</source> <volume>177</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1677</fpage>–<lpage>1182</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huber-Wagner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefering</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Qvick</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Effect of whole-body CT during trauma resuscitation on survival: a retrospective, multicentre study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>373</volume>(<issue>9673</issue>): <fpage>1455</fpage>–<lpage>1461</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Hunt PAF (2010) ‘Whole body’ CT scanning following blunt multitrauma: a Delphi study CEM: Rod Little Prize Session. <italic>Emergency Medicine Journal</italic> 27: A7. DOI: 10.1136/emj.2010.103150.19</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Karmy-Jones R, Jurkovich GJ (2004) Blunt chest trauma. <italic>Current Problems in Surgery</italic> 41(3): 211--380</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Kessel B, Sevi R, Jeroukhimov I, et al. (2007) Is routine portable pelvic X-ray in stable multiple trauma patients always justified in a high technology era? <italic>Injury</italic> 38(5): 559--563</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gracias</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name><surname>Maidment</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Cumulative radiation dose caused by radiologic studies in critically ill trauma patients</article-title>. <source>Journal of Trauma</source> <volume>57</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>510</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leidner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckman</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Standardized whole-body computed tomography as a screening tool in blunt multitrauma patients</article-title>. <source>Emergency Radiology</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linsenmaier</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Krötz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Häuser</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Whole-body computed tomography in polytrauma: techniques and management</article-title>. <source>European Radiology</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1728</fpage>–<lpage>1740</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="web"><collab>London Ambulance Service NHS Trust</collab>. <article-title>Triage protocols and LAS</article-title>, <year>2009</year>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.healthcareforlondon.nhs.uk/assets/Publications/Major-trauma/Major-trauma-event-20090910Triage-Protocol-Mark-Whitbread.ppt">http://www.healthcareforlondon.nhs.uk/assets/Publications/Major-trauma/Major-trauma-event-20090910Triage-Protocol-Mark-Whitbread.ppt</ext-link> (accessed 24 March 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCollough</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Guimarães</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>In defense of body CT</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Roentgenology</source> <volume>193</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muirhead</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Hagan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Haylock</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mortality and cancer incidence following occupational radiation exposure: third analysis of the National Registry for Radiation Workers</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Cancer</source> <volume>100</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munk</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Strohm</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Saueressig</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Effective dose estimation in whole-body multislice CT in paediatric trauma patients</article-title>. <source>Pediatric Radiology</source> <volume>39</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>252</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>National Audit Office (2010) <italic>Major Trauma Care in England</italic>. HC 213 Session 2009–2010. London: The Stationery Office</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence: National Collaborating Centre for Acute Care (2007) <italic>Head Injury: Triage, Assessment, Investigation and Early Management of Head Injury in Infants, Children and Adults</italic>. NICE Clinical Guideline No56. London. Available at:</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.nice.org.uk/CG056">www.nice.org.uk/CG056</ext-link>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>NCEPOD (2007) Trauma: Who cares? A Report of the National Confidential Enquiry into Patient Outcome and Death. London. Available at: www.ncepod.org.uk/2007report2/Downloads/SIP_summary.pdf</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Platon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanmuganathan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of a single-pass continuous whole-body 16-MDCT protocol for patients with polytrauma</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Roentgenology</source> <volume>192</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Establishment of Regional Networks of Trauma Care</article-title>. <comment>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/prod_consum_dh/groups/dh_digitalassets/@dh/@en/@ps/documents/digitalasset/dh_119423.pdf">http://www.dh.gov.uk/prod_consum_dh/groups/dh_digitalassets/@dh/@en/@ps/documents/digitalasset/dh_119423.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 24 March 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ptak</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhea</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Novelline</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Radiation dose is reduced with a single-pass whole-body multi-detector row CT trauma protocol compared with a conventional segmented method: initial experience</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source> <volume>229</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>902</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rieger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Czermak</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>El Attal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Initial clinical experience with a 64-MDCT whole-body scanner in an emergency department: better time management and diagnostic quality?</article-title> <source>Journal of Trauma</source> <volume>66</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>648</fpage>–<lpage>657</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Röhrl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Diehl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Whole-body MSCT of patients after polytrauma: abdominal injuries (in German)</article-title>. <source>RöFo</source> <volume>177</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1641</fpage>–<lpage>1648</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sangthong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Whole body imaging in blunt multisystem trauma patients without obvious signs of injury: results of a prospective study</article-title>. <source>Archives of Surgery</source> <volume>141</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>468</fpage>–<lpage>473</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saltzherr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Goslings</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Effect on survival of whole-body CT during trauma resuscitation (letter)</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>374</volume>(<issue>9685</issue>): <fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salottolo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar-Or</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleishman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Current utilization and radiation dose from computed tomography in patients with trauma</article-title>. <source>Critical Care Medicine</source> <volume>37</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1336</fpage>–<lpage>1340</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennessy</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Computed tomography whole body imaging in multi-trauma: 7 years experience</article-title>. <source>Clinical Radiology</source> <volume>61</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sasser</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivent</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Guidelines for field triage of injured patients. Recommendations of the National Expert Panel on Field Triage</article-title>. <source>MMWR Recommendations and Reports</source> <volume>58</volume>(<issue>RR-1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Self</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The benefit of routine thoracic, abdominal and pelvic computed tomography to evaluate trauma patients with closed head injuries</article-title>. <source>The American Journal of Surgery</source> <volume>186</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>609</fpage>–<lpage>613</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slovis</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>CT and computed radiography: the pictures are great but is the radiation dose greater than required?</article-title> <source>American Journal of Radiology</source> <volume>179</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The use of whole-body computed tomography for trauma patients: survey of UK Emergency Departments</article-title>. <source>Emergency Medicine Journal</source>. <comment>Epub ahead of print. DOI: 10.1136/emj.2011.111708</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolrich-Burt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellings</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>‘Major Trauma’ CT scanning: the experience from a regional trauma centre in the UK</article-title>. <source>Emergency Medicine Journal</source>. <comment>28: 378--382</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Whole-body imaging in blunt multisystem trauma patients who were never examined</article-title>. <source>Annals of Emergency Medicine</source> <volume>52</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanescu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Talner</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Diagnostic errors in polytrauma: a structured review of the recent literature</article-title>. <source>Emergency Radiology</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stengel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Primary pan-computed tomography for blunt multiple trauma: can the whole be better than its parts?</article-title> <source>Injury</source> <volume>40</volume>(<issue>suppl. 4</issue>): <fpage>S36</fpage>–<lpage>S46</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wedegartner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Diagnostic imaging in polytrauma: comparison of radiation exposure from whole-body MSCT and conventional radiography with organ-specific CT (in German)</article-title>. <source>RöFo</source> <volume>176</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1039</fpage>–<lpage>1044</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weninger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauritz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridrich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Emergency room management of patients with blunt major trauma: evaluation of the multislice computed tomography protocol exemplified by an urban trauma center</article-title>. <source>Journal of Trauma</source> <volume>62</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>584</fpage>–<lpage>591</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winslow</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinshaw</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Quantitative assessment of diagnostic radiation doses in adult blunt trauma patients</article-title>. <source>Annals of Emergency Medicine</source> <volume>52</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wurmb</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Frühwald</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopfner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Whole-body multislice computed tomography as the primary and sole diagnostic tool in patients with blunt trauma: searching for its appropriate indication</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Emergency Medicine</source> <volume>25</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1057</fpage>–<lpage>1062</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wurmb</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Frühwald</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopfner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Whole-body multislice computed tomography as the first line diagnostic tool in patients with multiple injuries: the focus on time</article-title>. <source>Journal of Trauma</source> <volume>66</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>658</fpage>–<lpage>665</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1460408612437303"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wurmb</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Quaisser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Balling</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Whole-body multislice computed tomography (MSCT) improves trauma care in patients requiring surgery after multiple trauma</article-title>. <source>Emergency Medicine Journal</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>300</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>