<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HAS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphas</journal-id>
<journal-title>Humanity &amp; Society</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0160-5976</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0160597611433266</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0160597611433266</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Judging Victims: Why We Stigmatize Survivors, and How They Reclaim Respect</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bailey</surname>
<given-names>Emma G.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0160597611433266"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0160597611433266">
<italic>Western New Mexico University, New Mexico, USA</italic>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>36</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>87</fpage>
<lpage>88</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dunn</surname>
<given-names>Jennifer L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <source>Judging Victims: Why We Stigmatize Survivors, and How They Reclaim Respect</source> <publisher-loc>Boulder, CO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lynne Rienner Publishers</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>. <page-count count="241"/> pp. <price>$55.00</price>. ISBN: <isbn>978-1-58826-702-3</isbn></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Association for Humanistic Sociology 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Association for Humanistic Sociology</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>
<italic>Judging Victims: Why We Stigmatize Survivors, and How They Claim Respect</italic> demonstrates how the images of victims of gendered violence have changed over time and attempts to answer why this is so. Jennifer L. Dunn, Associate Professor of Sociology and Graduate Director at the Southern Illinois University Carbondale, explores this change through a social constructionist perspective. This perspective, largely framed by Best’s “claims-making,” leads her to assert “people who are perceived as responsible in any way for their own victimization are not readily designated or treated as victims” (p. 2). According to Dunn, this perception stems from our assumption or background assertion that all individuals have agency or free will and hence our actions are our own to which we are then held accountable. In the case of victims of gendered violence, Dunn argues that given our background assertion of agency, victims are seen as responsible for the violence done to them. Dunn concludes those who are most affected by violence (i.e., victims), must play a central role in the construction of the social problem and the social movement that addresses their claims. However, victims’ very participation in the construction of their identity leads to a dilemma. On one hand, victims need society’s compassion and action activated by the claim of victim of the social problem, but on the other hand society is not sympathetic to victims and most of the time we end up blaming the victim and deny them the identity they claim, simply through their process of having claimed it.</p>
<p>In setting the stage for her theoretical argument, Dunn begins with the survivor movements of 1971 and takes the reader through the last 35 years. In this section, readers will learn a bit of history about the Radical Feminist Movement and Antirape Movement, the Battered Women’s Movement, the Incest Survivor’s Movement, the Survivor’s Network of those Abused by Priests, as well as the position of counter movements or backlash against the claims made by the survivor movements. However, she writes this chapter to show how the survivor movements’ claims-making shifts over time and to set up her larger theoretical argument. The meat of the book, as Dunn notes, lies in the chapters that set down her “four ideal typical possibilities of the social construction of victims” (p. 24): blameworthy victims, blameless victims, pathetic victims, and admirable victims. In delineating each typology, Dunn employs an astounding array of literature to demonstrate her point. In her construction of ideological types, Dunn relies on the voices of victims themselves (or the voice from the backlash) to illustrate how the collective identity is formed and used. With each type, Dunn demonstrates the tension between the stigma of passivity and the need to be seen as victim not responsible for their own victimization. In the chapters addressing blameworthy victims, blameless victims, and admirable victims, Dunn also presents what each movement worked to achieve for the victims themselves such as domestic violence shelters, and so on.</p>
<p>Dunn also dedicates a chapter exploring how her “story about stories” (p. 195) contributes to contemporary feminist sociological literature, the discipline of victimology, and to victims and survivors of gendered violence themselves. Her work draws on standard social constructionist theoretical work to demonstrate her own unique contribution. What is of most interest to me, however, lies in Dunn argument that her work takes into account power relations or structure. In this regard, I will grant that Dunn presents a very gendered reality, whereby victims are considered victims because they have violated a gender norm of one kind or another. Her social constructionist approach does not take into account structure or power relations beyond this and for me her claim that her work plays an efficacious role for victims rings hollow. While she claims that meaning must change in order to have social change, she clearly places the work of meaning construction on the victims themselves. And further, she never once questions from where our background assertions come. In short, she fails to see the very society that she says blames the victim. Social change indeed implies the need for changed meanings, but without systemic change the victims will be forever in a pursuit of finding the right identity that may ultimately only ameliorate their own condition, but by no means stop gendered and sexual violence. Dunn’s work contributes to a theoretical discussion, but not to the latter one of ceasing violence against women.</p>
</body>
</article>