<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SIR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsir</journal-id>
<journal-title>Studies in Religion/Sciences Religieuses</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0008-4298</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2042-0587</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0008429812469901c</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0008429812469901c</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews / Comptes Rendus</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Reviews / Comptes Rendus: Redescribing Paul and the Corinthians by Ron Cameron and Merrill P. Miller, eds</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>Ian</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff1-0008429812469901">University of Toronto</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>127</fpage>
<lpage>129</lpage>
<product>
<source>Redescribing Paul and the Corinthians</source> Society of Biblical Literature, Early Christianity and Its Literature 5 <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>Ron</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Merrill P.</given-names></name></person-group>, eds <publisher-loc>Atlanta, GA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Society of Biblical Literature</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>. xiii + <page-count count="323"/> pp.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) / Le(s) auteur(s), 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The Canadian Corporation for Studies in Religion</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A great deal of recent scholarship on Paul can be classified as theological modernism: an approach that has tended to revolve around the dualism of the material/spiritual and orthodox/heretical. The result has been the treatment of ancient Christians as if they were modern with regard to religion, morals, sociality, and subjectivity. <italic>Redescribing Paul and the Corinthians</italic> (the second book produced by the Society of Biblical Literature’s Seminar on Ancient Myths and Modern Theories of Christian Origins) moves away from theological modernism, asking new questions and bringing new theories to Paul and the Corinthians.</p>
<p>One of the major themes in this volume is the examination of the disjunction between Paul and the Jesus-christos associations that the seminar hypothesizes to be the site of Paul’s interactions in Corinth. The opening essays by Jonathan Z. Smith and Burton L. Mack (essays with which the rest of the essays in this book are in conversation) are the most focused on this disjunction. Smith (“Re: Corinthians”) addresses this disjunction by comparing the Corinthians with the Atbalmin (a group in 20th-century Papua New Guinea) with respect to their treatments of the dead. He suggests convincingly that we can deploy the West Papuans’ interest in ancestors and the land of the dead to help to explain Paul’s Christ myth at Corinth. Mack’s essay, “Rereading the Christ Myth: Paul’s Gospel and the Christ Cult Question,” focuses on the Christ myth (1 Cor. 15:3–5) and the ritual text (1 Cor. 11:23–25) and argues that both “can be traced to mythmaking within the Jesus schools at some point where the thought of Jesus as a martyr for their cause was entertained” (37). Mack reads both sections of 1 Corinthians alongside contemporary martyrologies. In places where Paul’s Jesus myth does not line up with traditional martyr myths, Mack suggests that the Jesus-christos associations in Corinth had their own Jesus-as-martyr myths and ritual meals.</p>
<p>Where Smith and Mack stress the disjunctions between Paul and the Corinthians, William E. Arnal cautions us against stressing these disjunctions too much. In his essay, “Bringing Paul and the Corinthians Together? A Rejoinder and Some Proposals on Redescription and Theory,” Arnal asks what has occasioned Paul’s construction/deployment of a/his Christ myth, and might this incongruity mesh, rather than conflict, with that of the Corinthians? Arnal suggests that both Paul and the Corinthians were concerned with issues of Jewish ethnicity related to the meaning of a national deity of a nation (Israel) that no longer existed as such, “and what all of this means for the issue of identity, for being an Israelite under these circumstances” (90).</p>
<p>The remainder of the essays deal less directly with Smith and Mack, but are certainly still informed by them. Stanley K. Stowers contributes two essays, “Kinds of Myth, Meals, and Power: Paul and the Corinthians,” and “Does Pauline Christianity Resemble a Hellenistic Philosophy?” In “Kinds of Myth” Stowers argues that the Corinthians were never the stable social body Paul wanted them to be, and that we can better understand their social formation as a field of intellectual competition and cultural production (110). Stowers understands Paul’s mythmaking as the construction of a paideai (or “culture”), which would have been appealing given the social emphasis placed on the acquisition of paideai in the Greco-Roman world. In his second essay, Stowers compares the ekklesia in Corinth to Hellenistic philosophy on the basis of seven points of contact. He concludes that Pauline Christianity, as well as other kinds of Christianity, did resemble Hellenistic philosophies, but not necessarily because they derived from Hellenistic philosophies, or ever borrowed directly from them (236), but because of their common focus on intellectual practices.</p>
<p>Complementing Stowers’ examination of Hellenistic philosophies as social models for Paul’s ekklesia is John S. Kloppenborg’s review of households, thiasoi and collegia, and the synagogai (“Greco-Roman Thiasoi, the Ekklesia at Corinth, and Conflict Management”). Kloppenborg assesses the utility of each of these models with respect to conflict management in Corinth, arguing that both the nature of the conflicts present in 1 Corinthians, and the ways in which they were managed, most closely resemble the conflicts and conflict management found in thiasoi and collegia. The last essay to be reviewed is Richard Ascough’s “Paul’s ‘Apocalypticism’ and the Jesus Associations at Thessalonica and Corinth.” Ascough employs Smith and Mack’s four steps of redescription (Description, Comparison, Rectification of Categories, and Redescription) in order to address Paul’s apocalyptic language in 1 Thessalonians. He compares the situation in 1 Thessalonians with contemporary Greco-Roman burial societies, and concludes that the issues Paul addresses regarding the Thessalonian dead reflect burial practices and notions of the afterlife consistent with known Greco-Roman burial associations. Paul’s apocalypticism, argues Ascough, shows the Thessalonians that, contrary to what they think, the dead are not divorced from the Jesus association and are still full members, albeit “sleepers” (181).</p>
<p>Any study of Paul would be remiss not to engage with the contributions made by this book. Two in particular stand out. First, the emphasis on Paul’s intellectual labor: Smith and Mack both illustrate the intellectual labor present in Paul’s mythmaking, and the notion of Paul as intellectual is taken over in Stowers’ two essays, both in terms of the ways Paul’s ekklesia resembled Hellenistic schools, and in the way that Paul’s mythmaking can be understood as the construction of a paideai. Second, the effort to compare Paul’s ekklesia with Greco-Roman associations: the contributions by Ascough and Kloppenborg demonstrate clearly the interpretive gains to be made by comparing Paul’s ekklesia with Greco-Roman associations, while at the same time stressing that this comparison does not require us to say that Paul’s ekklesia were associations (this emphasis is especially clear in Kloppenborg’s essay).</p>
<p>If there is one criticism of this book it is that, even though <italic>Redescribing Paul</italic> is on the cutting edge of scholarship, many of the essays within are relatively old (the seminar sessions were in the early 2000s), and some have been in print for some time now (“Re: Corinthians” was published in an essay collection in 2004, and “Does Pauline Christianity Resemble a Hellenistic Philosophy?” in 2001). This minor criticism aside, <italic>Redescribing Paul and the Corinthians</italic> represents a significant step forward in the study of Paul, the Corinthians, and early ekklesia more generally and is essential reading for anyone working on any of these topics.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>Ian Brown<break/>
<italic>University of Toronto</italic>
</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>