<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">WIH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spwih</journal-id>
<journal-title>War in History</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0968-3445</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0385</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0968344512454380g</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0968344512454380g</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: <italic>Finland’s War of Choice: The Troubled German-Finnish Coalition In World War II</italic> by Henrik O. Lunde</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Gilmour</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0968344512454380">University of Edinburgh, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>528</fpage>
<lpage>529</lpage>
<product>
<source>Finland’s War of Choice: The Troubled German-Finnish Coalition In World War II</source>. <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lunde</surname><given-names>Henrik O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <publisher-loc>Haverton, PA, and Newbury</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Casemate</publisher-name>. <year>2011</year>. <page-count count="409"/> pp., <fpage>16</fpage> pp. b/w photos. <price>£22.50</price> hardback. ISBN <isbn>978 1 935149 48 4</isbn></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The first and perhaps most famous Finnish work of fiction, Alexis Kivi’s <italic>Seven Brothers</italic>, recounts the adventures of argumentative siblings. Henrik Lunde in his valuable book also chronicles – or rather expertly dissects – the relationships between similarly fractious Finnish and German <italic>Waffenbrüder.</italic> He also analyses their conduct in the battles with the Soviet Union between June 1941 and September 1944 that Finland refers to as the ‘Continuation War’, portrayed generally as the nation’s irredentist struggle to regain the territory lost to the Soviet Union in the 1939–40 ‘Winter War’.</p>
<p>Lunde runs a military expert’s eye over the fault lines of this ill-starred partnership which arguably contributed to Germany’s military failure in the east. Additionally, throughout the book, he devotes considerable attention to the military-political-diplomatic interactions, which considerably enhances the reader’s appreciation of the apparent ambiguities in Finnish conduct. For example, Lunde details the crucial role of the United States as a restraint on Finnish inroads into the Soviet Union (pp. 144 and 224) and an influence on Finland’s exit from the conflict (pp. 258 and 304). Lunde contends convincingly that Finnish objectives for entering into joint action with Germany were limited to territorial recovery (and perhaps minor gains in East Karelia) and above all to obtain the protection of one totalitarian superpower against the apparent rapaciousness of another. This restraint clashed with the German concept of a total war against the <italic>Untermensch</italic> for <italic>Lebensraum</italic> that required the destruction not only of an ideology, Bolshevism, but also the nation of Russia. The Finnish leadership, while sharing Nazi distaste for Communism, nevertheless perceptively feared the reaction of a potentially resurgent Soviet Union, and so had interest neither in signalling its agreement with German aims by assisting in the capture of Leningrad, nor in severing the Soviet rail link to Murmansk providing essential western supplies to the underequipped Red Army fighting for survival. Furthermore, Finland’s participation meant that Germany squandered scarce resources of men and materiel in the largely static defence of Finland while the Finns demanded weaponry and food shipments in order to hold off the Soviets. These diverted resources had a considerable and perhaps decisive impact on German military operations to the south and east.</p>
<p>Lunde comments that the prolonged and rather static defensive stance of the Finnish military after 1941 probably contributed to the speed of the inevitable collapse against superior Soviet forces during the offensives of 1944. This brought on the final crisis in the relationship. The Finns were simultaneously negotiating with the USSR for their exit from the struggle (with significant assistance from Sweden) while assuring the Germans of their commitment to the joint effort in order to secure the supplies and assistance needed to keep the Soviets at bay and secure an independent Finland. Here, Lunde quotes Clausewitz: ‘One country may support another’s cause, but will never take it as seriously as it takes its own’ (p. 309). German support enabled the heroic and costly Finnish defence in ‘the largest battle in Nordic history’ (p. 306) around Tala-Ihantala. Finnish resistance there led to the withdrawal of five Soviet divisions and so hastened the German collapse on the eastern front. Finland had once again attained its objectives at German expense. Nevertheless, Soviet pressure to expel the Wehrmacht within the terms of the armistice splintered the relationship and brought the Finnish army into direct conflict with its recent partners.</p>
<p>So ended this flawed arrangement which Lunde describes as a ‘classic study in how not to enter into a military coalition’ (p. 380). Furthermore, throughout the book, the author provides profuse evidence and detailed analysis of how and where the relationship went wrong and how this affected military operations – mainly to German disadvantage.</p>
<p>Lunde’s masterly fusion of sources creates a riveting and informative narrative. His attention to the detail of military deployment may at times dismay the more general reader (for example the lists on pp. 209 and 355 that might usefully have been in appendices), but this is more than compensated for by an abundance of maps detailing operations in unfamiliar areas together with a judicious selection of excellent illustrative quotes from memoirs, correspondence, and secondary sources.</p>
<p>This book is a necessary companion for any serious student and researcher of Nordic twentieth-century history, not least because it provides the material to address the question that I am frequently asked, even by colleagues: ‘How did Finland survive as an independent nation at the end of the Second World War?’ The reverberations of the ‘Continuation War’ linger, and with two books, the recent <italic>Nordic Narratives of the Second World War: National Historiographies Revisited</italic> (edited by Henrik Stenius, Mirja Österberg and Johan Östling; Lund: Nordic Academic, 2011) and the forthcoming <italic>Hitler’s Scandinavian Legacy</italic> (edited by Jill Stephenson and John Gilmour; London: Continuum), that debate on Finnish conduct continues.</p>
</body>
</article>