<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjmq</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journalism &amp; Mass Communication Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1077-6990</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1077699012442840</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1077699012442840</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Explaining Research: How to Reach Key Audiences to Advance Your Work by Dennis Meredith</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>Louisa</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1077699012442840">Bowling Green State University, Bowling Green, OH, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>89</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>324</fpage>
<lpage>325</lpage>
<product><source>Explaining Research: How to Reach Key Audiences to Advance Your Work</source>. <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>Dennis</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>. <page-count count="357"/> pp. <price>$35</price> pbk.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 AEJMC</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Association for Education in Journalism &amp; Mass Communication</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>“Broader impact” is one of the two key criteria for government agencies in selecting research proposals for funding. But deciding how to create that broader impact is a challenge for many academic researchers, because we are so preoccupied with designing research and with writing research articles that we seldom have the time to think about how to explain and publicize our research to target or wider audiences. Science writer Dennis Meredith’s book is a handy reference to busy researchers to create the broader impact for their research work.</p>
<p><italic>Explaining Research</italic> is also an enjoyable read, not only because the author is a good writer, but because of his understanding of the psychology of his target readers: the researchers. He understands that many researchers, especially scientists and engineers, do not like to be under the spotlight, but they also take great pride in their work. Yet to get funding, get promotion, or establish the impact of the research, researchers need to know how to explain to lay audiences what their research is about, why it is newsworthy to media to gain media coverage and win the support of their peers in the field. To those who are actively seeking funding for their research, chapter 19, “Persuade Administrators, Donors and Legislators,” is a must-read. Meredith explains the common characteristics of these constituents and how to handle relationships with them.</p>
<p>Meredith organizes his chapters by actions, and readers are urged to follow the series of actions he outlines to achieve success in explaining research. For example, in chapter 3, “Give Compelling Talks,” the suggested actions are (1) free yourself from text, (2) organize your talk to grab and inform, (3) make your talk memorable, (4) use engaging visuals, (5) practice produces power persuasion, (6) use good stagecraft, (7) manage questions, (8) give lay audiences what they want, and (9) synergies your effort.</p>
<p>I especially like chapter 21, in which Meredith clearly shows the distinction and commonalities between journalists and academic researchers. He also warned us of a wrong expectation of the journalist to be knowledgeable and well prepared for the topic. Quoting from Sharon Dunwoody’s study, he explains the accuracy for news articles is different from academic research because of differences between technical and communicative accuracy. Journalists write for their readers, not for the researchers. They do not have much time to think about the subject. They must arouse the interest of their readers, and they do not have an obligation to advance the research agenda of the researchers.</p>
<p>Reading the book is like having a friend give you career advice. You need to expect, and not worry about, colleagues’ envy if you are successful in explaining your research and receiving publicity. If the project is not ready for prime time, then don’t publicize it, because the consequences of premature release of the results outweigh the benefits of press coverage. He also talks about how to manage the university administration and work with a university’s chief information officer in dealing with reporters.</p>
<p>This book covers all mass media that researchers need to use to communicate their research, from the basic research talk to utilization of new technologies such as creating e-newsletters, wikis, blogs, podcasts, social networks, and webinars. He also covers how to produce informative research videos. Researchers are also encouraged to write magazine articles and newspaper essays for lay audiences so that they can build their authority in their field to the public, and show that they are concerned about the broader political and social implications of their field. The public does not read scholarly journal articles, but does consume the popular press. Meredith details the process of how to break into writing for the popular press by showing the editorial process, which includes the marketing and pitching of articles, the editing process, and the publishing business.</p>
<p>Overall, the book keeps to its promise of teaching readers how to explain research to different audiences. I am delighted to see that Meredith addresses the downside of publicity to researchers in the last chapter: When researchers spend all this effort publicizing themselves, how much time do they have left to do good research? Meredith does point out the more important problem now is public misunderstanding and indifference toward research and science, rather than too much publicity.</p>
</body>
</article>