<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NSQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spnsq</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nurs Sci Q</journal-id>
<journal-title>Nursing Science Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0894-3184</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7409</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0894318413477146</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0894318413477146</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Scholarly Dialogue</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Nursing Leadership and Health Policy</article-title>
<subtitle>A Dialogue with Nurse Leaders</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>Pamela N.</given-names></name>
<degrees>RN; PhD; FAAN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0894318413477146">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Swider</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name>
<degrees>RN; PhD; FAAN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0894318413477146">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bigley</surname><given-names>Mary Beth</given-names></name>
<degrees>RN; DrPH</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0894318413477146">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0894318413477146"><label>1</label>Professor and Director of Center for Community Health, University of Wyoming</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0894318413477146"><label>2</label>Professor and Coordinator, Advanced Public Health Nursing, Rush University</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0894318413477146"><label>3</label>Acting Director of the Division of Science and Communications in the Office of the Surgeon General at Department of Health and Human Services</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0894318413477146">Pamela N. Clarke, RN, PhD, FAAN, Professor, University of Wyoming, School of Nursing, Dept. 3065, 1000 E. University Ave., Laramie, Wyoming 82079 E-mail: <email>pclarke@uwyo.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>26</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>136</fpage>
<lpage>142</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>National public health policy influencing the entire population is particularly exciting when nurses serve as key players informing the process. The leaders in this dialogue participated in the process by sharing their disciplinary knowledge and experience. They were selected to work with bureaucrats to design healthcare for the future. This dialogue among two nurse leaders demonstrates a path to top leadership in the United States. Swider and Bigley here share their stories of how they moved beyond clinical practice to involvement in their communities and the nation. Through public health and policy initiatives, both nurse leaders have helped shape healthcare to provide better patient-centered care at all levels. This dialogue not only shares their successes, but also sets the stage for others in nursing to use policy to transform healthcare for the future.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>health policy</kwd>
<kwd>nursing leadership</kwd>
<kwd>nursing science</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Interviewing two nurse leaders actively involved with some of the biggest current national health policy in the United States (US) was a unique opportunity. The two scholars were asked to focus on the development of their nursing leadership perspectives and to describe their path in becoming consultants to the president in this time of health reform. As they detail their career development it is notable how research and practice came together. With careers solidly embedded in nursing knowledge and practice with a vision for better healthcare at the population level, these two nurse leaders quickly became nationally recognized.</p>
<p>Susan Swider is a professor in the College of Nursing at Rush University in Chicago, Illinois. She is the Specialty Coordinator of the College’s Advanced Public Health Nursing program. Over the past 20 years, her research has focused on program development and evaluation of community health workers and engaging urban communities in health promotion. Dr. Swider was selected for this dialogue specifically because of her appointment as a member of President Obama’s Advisory Group on Prevention, Health Promotion, and Integrative and Public Health. The White House formally announced the new appointments to this board on Wednesday, January 26, 2011. In a statement released by the White House, President Obama said, “Our nation will be greatly served by the talent and expertise these individuals bring to their new roles. I am grateful they have agreed to serve in this Administration, and I look forward to working with them in the months and years ahead” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0894318413477146">The White House, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Dr. Mary Beth Bigley is currently the Acting Director of the Division of Science and Communications in the Office of the Surgeon General at the Department of Health and Human Services. Dr. Bigley received a doctorate in Health Systems and Policy at The George Washington University’s School of Public Health and Health Systems, and a Master of Science of Nursing (MSN) as an adult nurse practitioner. She leads Surgeon General initiatives that include the development of all evidence based documents such as the 2012 Surgeon General’s Youth Tobacco Report, the Surgeon General’s Calls to Action and <italic>My Family Health Portrait–</italic>a family health history project.</p>
<speech>
<speaker>Pamela Clarke (PC):</speaker>
<p>Would you talk about the evolution of your career and how your experiences led to your current national leadership positions?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Susan Swider (SS):</speaker>
<p>I moved from acute care into community practice, and worked with patients to help them maintain and improve their health status, at whatever stage they were at in life. This practice was a tremendous learning experience for me, as I came to experience just how much my patients’ health and well-being was shaped outside of clinical settings. The experience helped me develop skills in collaborating with patients to help them set and meet health goals that were relevant in their lives. When I moved to graduate study in public health nursing, this knowledge and skill-set prepared me to work with my mentor, Dr. Beverly McElmurry, to examine collaboration with communities to address health needs, as in the World Health Organization (WHO) philosophy of Primary Healthcare (PHC). I worked with a team of nurses and community residents to implement PHC in urban settings in the US, with residents educated as Community Health Workers (CHW) who could assist their neighbors in accessing needed health services. Additionally, they identified and addressed health issues in their homes and communities that they could improve the health and lives of themselves and their families. National and local foundations and government agencies funded this work. The team piloted the model for 5 years in two low-income communities in Chicago, which led to an AmeriCorps project in Chicago that is still functioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0894318413477146">Swider &amp; McElmurry, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0894318413477146">McElmurry et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0894318413477146">McElmurry, Swider, &amp; Norr, 1991</xref>). The key to this work was viewing health broadly and in partnering with communities to help them address their health needs.</p>
</speech>
<p>The next step was to conduct and publish an integrative literature review of studies documenting the effectiveness of CHW interventions, that is, where community residents were most effective in working with their neighbors. Based on the existing literature at the time, I concluded that there were few data to support effectiveness in any one specific role, but there was consensus that CHW generally targeted those underserved by the healthcare system, or those whose health needs were not being met (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0894318413477146">Swider, 2002</xref>). The review has been widely cited and led to my work with colleagues developing randomized control trials to demonstrate the effectiveness of CHW with two very specific diseases and communities: the Mexican-American Trial of Community Health Workers (MATCH) study examining the effectiveness of CHW working with Latinos to improve self-management of diabetes, and LaCura, a study examining the effectiveness of CHW working with Puerto Rican families and their children with asthma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0894318413477146">Martin et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0894318413477146">Martin et al., in press</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0894318413477146">Rothschild et al., in press</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0894318413477146">Swider, Martin, Lynas, &amp; Rothschild, 2010</xref>). Additionally, I was an invited participant in a national consensus conference on setting a research agenda for CHW research and I have worked locally on establishing standardized training and evaluation of CHW work. The recent Affordable Care Act specifically calls for expansion of the CHW role to address healthcare disparities. This role still holds much promise for helping reach vulnerable and underserved communities and for providing a broad perspective on health promotion and disease prevention.</p>
<p>Local efforts in health promotion and disease prevention led to my service on the Board of Directors of Erie Family Health Center, a federally qualified health center in Chicago serving underserved populations. The role of Erie was to bring quality primary care into communities and to partner with our communities to promote health. My work at Erie and in the community around CHW interventions, led to my nomination and election as a member of the Institute of Medicine of Chicago in 2007. My interest in health disparities and working with underserved communities has also influenced my teaching. I currently serve as the coordinator for the specialty program in advanced public health nursing (APHN). I and my colleague Dr. Pamela Levin have received three consecutive Health Resources and Services Administration grants (2004-2013) through the advanced education in nursing mechanism to support work to ensure that the Rush University curriculum was based on the national competencies for Public Health Nursing; to put the program online so that Public Health Nurses (PHNs) from across the country could access specialty study at the APHN level; to recruit nurses from underrepresented minority groups into the program; and to move the program to the practice doctorate level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0894318413477146">Swider et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0894318413477146">Swider et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The most important recognition of my work to date was the nomination to serve on a federal advisory group for the National Prevention Strategy, mandated under the Affordable Care Act. In January 2011, I was appointed by President Obama as one of only two nurses to serve on the Advisory Group on Prevention, Health Promotion, and Integrative and Public Health. This twenty-three member group serves to advise the National Prevention Council, a group of cabinet officers chaired by the Surgeon General, in their development and implementation of the National Prevention Strategy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0894318413477146">National Prevention Council, 2011</xref>). This is the first-ever national effort to change the focus of healthcare to prioritize prevention.</p>
<p>The Affordable Care Act works to increase access to care and promote disease prevention and health promotion initiatives. While US healthcare outcomes are not in the top 10 of all nations, the US healthcare system is the most expensive in the world. Thus, working to prevent disease is critical to improving the health of the American population within the constraints of national resources. The advisory group is working to promote implementation of the National Prevention Strategy, which is an ideal role for nurses, as it calls for coordination of care, use of preventive services, and efforts to create healthy and safe communities as well as empower people. In many ways, this is a natural fit with my career to this point: recognizing the importance of social determinants of health and a broad public health perspective to maximize health promotion, and partnering with communities and others with relevant expertise in community health and development. The ultimate goal is to revise and redirect our healthcare system to focus on creating healthy communities, partnering with people to improve their health and preventing illness as a national priority. I look forward to the next few years working with this important initiative, to use the accumulated experiences and opportunities to continue to make a significant contribution to improving the health of the nation.</p>
<speech>
<speaker>Mary Beth Bigley (MBB):</speaker>
<p>Throughout my nursing experience I have had (and still have) mentors who are forward thinkers who embrace concepts of lifelong learning. They always encouraged me to pursue more advanced leadership roles. I started at a diploma school then transferred after a year to pursue a Bachelor of Science in Nursing (BSN). During my BSN years, I became active in the state student nurses’ association and eventually was elected president. In addition to my BSN, I received a BS degree in health administration. These formative years shaped my understanding and drive to pursue leadership roles in nursing and further prompted my desire to shape the important roles nurses play as members of the healthcare team.</p>
</speech>
<p>In my first nursing position, I quickly found new opportunities; learning telemetry and other aspects of critical care nursing, volunteering for hospital committees, and teaching new nurses as I became an expert in the field. When I moved to Washington, DC, I continued to work in critical care and also stayed active in hospital committees and local nursing groups. After 8 years as a hospital nurse, I started thinking about obtaining an advanced degree and decided on a Master of Science in Nursing (MSN) as an adult nurse practitioner. Initially I was torn between a Master in Business Administration (MBA) or a MSN but the thought of sitting behind a desk and not having contact with patients and family swayed my decision to focus on a more clinical degree. As an adult nurse practitioner I continued to work in the critical care area, but was fortunate to also start teaching part time, and eventually I secured a full-time faculty position. Being in Washington, DC, and working in an academic health center that encouraged faculty to be active in the national healthcare policy arena, meant that I was able to pursue leadership positions in nursing and I was recommended and appointed to the DC Board of Nursing early in my career.</p>
<p>Years later, after several other appointed and elected leadership positions in nursing, and now sitting behind a desk, my position in the Office of the Surgeon General provides me with many opportunities to influence public health and healthcare policy. I came to realize that the ability to influence policy was an important role that could have profound and far-reaching influence on nursing–and still make a difference in the lives of patients and their families.</p>
<speech>
<speaker>PC:</speaker>
<p>Specifically, would you describe how your nursing background has influenced your leadership in the broad area of healthcare?</p></speech>
<speech>
<speaker>SS:</speaker>
<p>As I said earlier, each position influenced my ongoing development. I worked in acute care for a while upon graduation and developed an enormous frustration with how often patients returned to the acute care setting for things I thought they needed help with at home, such as diet and medication management. This prompted me to move into home care, where I was overwhelmed with how little relevance much of my earlier practice had for the lives of people in community settings–that is, most of their lives! Home care led to public health and graduate school, which led me to feminist theory and the WHO model of PHC. The common thread is the idea of collective voice–the importance of having people in communities as full partners in health and wellness. We conducted several projects in inner city Chicago using the PHC approach, with the core intervention of training and working with local residents as CHW. This model has guided my research for the past 20 years and it led me to study policy and public participation in the policy process. For the past 2 decades my career has focused on public health, public voice, and public policy. I have demonstrated this with research into CHW effectiveness, teaching policy analysis for nursing activism, local policy activity with a federally qualified health center board and school-based health center financing, teaching public health nurses to develop evidence-based population interventions based on assessment data, and my current work with the National Prevention Strategy.</p></speech>
<speech>
<speaker>MBB:</speaker>
<p>Nurses are trained to be expert communicators. We learn to listen to patients, their family, the physicians, and the other health consultants (nutritionists, physical therapists), then nurses take all the information and synthesize it into a plan. But the plan does not just sit in the chart. Nurses communicate it to the team of clinicians, patient, and family and are a key part of putting the plan into action.</p>
</speech>
<p>Like most nurses, I practiced the art of being an expert communicator every day. I believe that this is why the two themes that are threaded throughout my nursing career are collaboration and teamwork. As a staff nurse, I worked in environments where team rounds were emphasized and nurses were always <italic>front and center</italic> to present the patient. Also, it was expected that nurses would volunteer for service on hospital committees. One committee that stands out in my volunteer service is the hospital’s ethics committee. One of the many functions of this committee was to help families and individuals understand options of care and their outcomes. I had to think beyond the immediate care to see the bigger picture and to help others understand care options. Later, as a faculty member I participated in and led interdisciplinary committees. I recognized the value of having nursing representation on committees and took every opportunity to volunteer for university committees. That committee work significantly contributed to my personal growth.</p>
<p>In addition to teaching nursing courses, I also taught interdisciplinary classes and the importance of team-based care. Students in their early years of education are forming their identity and the way in which students tackle their subject matter depends on their previous experiences in this area. Nurse practitioner students are already nurses and therefore approach assignments and discussion through the lens of the nursing model. When medical and nursing students learn together, it helps each side appreciate the role of the other on the heath care team. It also meant that nurses were able to bring many aspects of nursing science (like caring) into the interdisciplinary course. That helped medical and physician assistant students to understand the role of the family and to see the patient as part of the team, as well as an individual living in the community. The many collaborations made it natural for me to role model the importance of a team approach to healthcare.</p>
<p>In my current position I’m challenged to tackle a wide variety of public health issues, the science that underpins them and also to communicate these issues to a diverse range of audiences. I’m the first to say I’m not the expert in every area of public health so it is essential that I collaborate with colleagues, who are the true experts of the subject matter. Working together, the teams use the evidence base to compile the documents that are issued by the Surgeon General–whose authority and standing adds greatly to the public perceptions of the value of this important work.</p>
<speech>
<speaker>PC:</speaker>
<p>In terms of leadership, describe how nursing science provides a unique perspective for planning and thinking about the health of the public.</p></speech>
<speech>
<speaker>SS:</speaker>
<p>Health outcome data demonstrates that the US healthcare system needs to broaden its perspective to include the social determinants of health. Our almost exclusive focus on medical care and treatment has led to the US having overall poor population health outcomes in comparison to other developed nations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0894318413477146">Davis, 2010</xref>). Nursing has traditionally had a broad perspective on health and illness. The unique perspective of nursing is the combination of biological and psychosocial expertise of clients and their health needs, whether at individual, family, or community levels. In my experience, nurses use this broad perspective to help them in their relationships with patients, enabling them to truly examine patients’ experiences of health and illness as the area of focus. This is apparent in nursing research, which has always been translational in nature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0894318413477146">Grady, 2010</xref>). It is also apparent in nursing specialty practice, where medical expertise is combined with a holistic perspective for patient-centered treatment, as well as in generalist practice, where nurses are the providers of care and address patient and family needs from a broad perspective. One example of the importance of the nursing role is the Nurse Family Partnership model, which focuses on nurses as the center of a home visiting intervention with high-risk first time mothers because of that unique combination of communication ability, holistic perspective to client care and clinical assessment and judgment skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0894318413477146">National Family Partnership, 2012</xref>).</p></speech>
<speech>
<speaker>MBB:</speaker>
<p>In this position, I have a unique opportunity to use the knowledge and skills that I have mastered throughout my career to influence public health and public health policies. During my tenure at the Office of the Surgeon General, I have had the privilege to oversee and manage the draft of a variety of Surgeon General’s documents and released 10 reports on a range of public health topics such as tobacco, underage drinking, healthy homes, and breastfeeding. Each Surgeon General has unique priorities. My background means that I can offer a perspective as a clinician and a carer, and my understanding of population health helps to frame Surgeon General documents so that they are meaningful to a broad audience.</p>
</speech>
<p>The family health history project was one of the first projects I was introduced to while a Senior Health Fellow in the Office of the Surgeon General. The project was 2 years old and the webpage that hosted the “My Family Health Portrait” tool was starting to look outdated. Working with colleagues at National Institute of Health’s Genome Institute, we convened a group to draft standard nomenclature to build an interoperable tool. At the beginning of the project, “family health history” was referred to as “family medical history.” For me, <italic>health</italic> conferred the idea of prevention, more consistent with the nursing perspective, where medical conferred the idea of sickness. Over time, hearing no objections from the workgroup, the term family health history tool was adopted and in 2010 the new interoperable and standardized tool was released (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0894318413477146">Feero, Bigley, Brinner, Kristin, &amp; Family Health History Workgroup, 2008</xref>). This project remains one of the most notable learning experiences in my career. I learned about building webpages, health information technology standards, and above all genetics, something that was not taught in my nursing programs, yet I’m able to bring it all together in a way that is uniquely nursing. I continue to learn as we are validating risk assessment tools to be added to the family health history tool.</p>
<p>I have also had the opportunity to co-lead the Department of Human and Health Services/Department of Housing and Urban Development (HHS/HUD) collaboration, Health and Homes Working Group. This workgroup drafted recommendations to align health, homes and social services. I remember describing Maslow’s hierarchy of needs to my HUD colleagues as we discussed ways to achieve our mission and charge from the Secretaries. Maslow’s hierarchy puts the need for water, food, and shelter ahead of health, a concept, which helped the workgroup understand the charge and the priorities. Using this model we framed recommendations and subsequently implemented the recommendations that provided stable housing, health, and social services to homeless individuals and families.</p>
<speech>
<speaker>PC:</speaker>
<p>I believe that nurses are uniquely positioned in conceptualizing visionary healthcare for the future. Discuss your vision for nursing’s role in healthcare for the future.</p></speech>
<speech>
<speaker>SS:</speaker>
<p>Nursing is at the cusp of becoming very influential in the healthcare system–if we capitalize on our current opportunities. The first opportunity is that of the National Prevention Strategy and a focus on prevention and public health. Nurses are the largest group of health professionals in the public health system, so we are ideally positioned to take leadership with an increased focus on disease prevention and health promotion, particularly for vulnerable and underserved communities. Additionally, the Affordable Care Act calls for the development of Accountable Care Organizations, a new type of value-based payment system. The success of this model will depend on the care coordination done in each system–a key-nursing role. Nursing has demonstrated in numerous areas that nursing clinical judgment, in combination with the ability to be trusted by and communicate with patients, and our understanding of the social determinants of health and patient resource needs, makes nurses, especially PHNs, the ideal care coordinators. Nursing science needs to facilitate these efforts by establishing the evidence base for the effectiveness of prevention at individual and communities levels, and care coordination models for groups of patients. Nursing leadership needs to ensure that nurses get involved in these opportunities and demonstrate effectiveness in the right arenas for progress.</p></speech>
<speech>
<speaker>MBB:</speaker>
<p>The passing of the Affordable Care Act opened up many opportunities for nursing. Nurses understand how to best bridge community care with clinical care, and to incorporate concepts of population health as new models of healthcare delivery. School nurses have been doing this for years. They understand the benefits of preventive service delivered in community. Also, they can articulate the challenges of communicating with children, clinicians, parents, and most importantly, they have developed systems to relay normal and abnormal findings to appropriate parties to ensure that children receive optimal care. Nurses are vital to the adoption and utility of electronic health records. In addition to inputting data in clinical settings, these systems can be used to improve patient outcomes and define the nursing role on the healthcare team. Care coordination, traditionally a nursing function, can be enhanced with electronic health records.</p>
</speech>
<p>The real opportunity for nurses is to understand and engage in infusing health into all aspects of people’s lives. Individuals spend a very small percent of their lifetime in a clinical encounter. The remainder of one’s’ lifetime is outside of a clinical setting. This time has been coined by many as “white space.” Nurses have a unique opportunity to influence health in the “white space” by infusing prevention and wellness into all aspects of community living.</p>
<p>The Affordable Care Act lays the groundwork for infusing prevention into health and into the “white space.” The Affordable Care Act call for the formation of the National Prevention, Health Promotion and Public Health Council, that is chaired by the Surgeon General and comprised of heads of departments and offices across the federal government. Coordinating the work of this Council and working with staff from the 17 departments, we have defined prevention as it is represented in the mission of each of the departments, drafted a prevention framework, and started to gather the evidence-based supporting literature that comprised prevention. In June 2011, the Council released the National Prevention Strategy: America’s Plan for Better Health and Wellness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0894318413477146">National Prevention Council, 2011</xref>). It presented a shared commitment to the health of individuals, families, and communities through prevention. The strategy recognized the way that federal departments such as housing, transportation, education, and justice can contribute to health through health-promoting policy goals, including healthy and safe community environments, injury prevention, violence-free living, and active living. For the first time in the history of our nation, we have a cross-sector integrated national strategy that identifies priorities for improving the health of all Americans.</p>
<p>The National Prevention Council’s work to achieve the National Prevention Strategy’s vision, working together to improve the health and quality of life for individuals, families, and communities by moving the nation from a focus on sickness and disease to one based on prevention and wellness, has been supported by the National Prevention Council Action Plan, released June 2012 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0894318413477146">National Prevention Council, 2012</xref>). This Action Plan highlights important opportunities that the National Prevention Council and its diverse 17 member departments, agencies, and offices–representing sectors such as housing, transportation, education, environment, and defense–are creating to ensure the health, well-being, and resilience of the American people. Overseeing this effort has uniquely positioned me in conceptualizing visionary healthcare for the future and these documents present nursing with many new roles in healthcare for the future.</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<label>Authors’ Note</label>
<p>The opinions expressed are those of the authors and do not reflect the viewpoint of the Department of Health and Human Services.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Mirror, mirror on the wall: How the performance of the U. S. healthcare system compares internationally</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.commonwealthfund.org/~/media/Files/Publications/Fund%20Report/2010/Jun/1400_Davis_Mirror_Mirror_on_the_wall_2010.pdf">http://www.commonwealthfund.org/~/media/Files/Publications/Fund%20Report/2010/Jun/1400_Davis_Mirror_Mirror_on_the_wall_2010.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feero</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bigley</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brinner</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kristin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <collab>&amp; Family Health History Multi-Stakeholder Workgroup of the American Health Information Community</collab>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>New standards and enhanced utility for family health history information in the electronic health record: An update from the American Health Information Community’s Family Health History Multi-Stakeholder Workgroup</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>723</fpage>-<lpage>728</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grady</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Translational research and nursing science</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ninr.nih.gov/NR/rdonlyres/BBDBBECA-703C-4457-991A4B19A901DD66/0/NursingOutlookMay_June2010PAGTranslationalresearch.pdf">http://www.ninr.nih.gov/NR/rdonlyres/BBDBBECA-703C-4457-991A4B19A901DD66/0/NursingOutlookMay_June2010PAGTranslationalresearch.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swider</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olinger</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tumialán Lynas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rothschild</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Recruitment of Mexican-American adults for an intensive diabetes intervention trial</article-title>. <source>Ethnicity and Disease</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mosnaim</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greve</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swider</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rothschild</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (in press). <article-title>Home asthma triggers: Barriers to asthma control in Chicago Puerto Rican children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Care for the Poor and Underserved</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McElmurry</surname><given-names>B .J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swider</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bless</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norr</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Community health advocacy: Primary health care nurse-advocate teams in urban communities</article-title>. In <collab>National League for Nursing</collab> (Ed.), <source>Perspectives in nursing 1989-1991</source> (pp. <fpage>117</fpage>-<lpage>131</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National League for Nursing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McElmurry</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swider</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norr</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>A community based primary health care program for integration of research, practice and education</article-title>. In <collab>National League for Nursing</collab> (Ed.), <source>Curriculum revolution: Community building and activism</source> (pp. <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>90</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National League for Nursing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>National Prevention Council</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>National prevention strategy</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U. S. Department of Health and Human Services, Office of the Surgeon General</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>National Prevention Council</collab>. (<year>2012</year>). <source>National Prevention Council action plan: Implementing the National Prevention Strategy</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U. S. Department of Health and Human Services, Office of the Surgeon General</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>Nurse Family Partnership</collab>. (<year>2012</year>). <source>Proven results</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nursefamilypartnership.org/proven-results">www.nursefamilypartnership.org/proven-results</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rothschild</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swider</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lynas</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (in press). <article-title>The Mexican-American trial of community health workers (MATCH): Design and baseline characteristics of a randomized controlled trial testing a culturally tailored community diabetes self-management intervention</article-title>. <source>Contemporary Clinical Trials</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swider</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Outcome effectiveness of community health workers: An integrative literature review</article-title>. <source>Public Health Nursing</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swider</surname><given-names>S. M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ailey</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Breakwell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cowell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNaughton</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Rourke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Matching a graduate curriculum in public/community health nursing to practice competencies</article-title>. <source>Public Health Nursing</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>190</fpage>-<lpage>195</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swider</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cowell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Breakwell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wallinder</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Community/public health nursing (C/PHN) practice leaders views of the Doctorate of Nursing Practice</article-title>. <source>Public Health Nursing</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>405</fpage>-<lpage>411</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swider</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lynas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rothschild</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Project MATCH: Training for a promotora intervention</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Educator</source>, <volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>98</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swider</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McElmurry</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>A women’s health perspective in primary health care: A nursing and community health worker demonstration project in urban America</article-title>. <source>Family and Community Health</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0894318413477146">
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>The White House, Office of the Press Secretary</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>President Obama announces more key administration posts</source> [Press release]. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2011/01/26/president-obama-announces-more-key-administration-posts">http://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2011/01/26/president-obama-announces-more-key-administration-posts</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>