<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ISW</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spisw</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Social Work</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0020-8728</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7234</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0020872811428923</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0020872811428923</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Achilihu, Stephen (2010) <italic>Do African Children Have Rights?</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Parada</surname><given-names>Henry</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Saracostti</surname><given-names>Mahia</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Reininger</surname><given-names>Taly</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Brownell</surname><given-names>Gracie</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0020872811428923">University of Texas Arlington, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>55</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<issue-title>Special issue: Social Work in Latin America</issue-title>
<fpage>429</fpage>
<lpage>432</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Achilihu</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Do African Children Have Rights?</source> <publisher-name>Universal Publishers</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>, <page-count count="280"/> pp., <price>$25.95</price> (<comment>paper</comment>).</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">IASSW, ICSW, IFSW</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This commendable book is a comparative and legal analysis of the United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child (CRC). Utilizing substantive research, the author carefully analyzes the extent to which the CRC influenced regional and national policies that affect African children who are without a doubt the most vulnerable group in a society plagued by economic, political and social problems. Furthermore, the text familiarizes readers with African policies and how they were influenced by the CRC. Themes in this book can be summarized into two principles: children should have the right to life, survival, protection, and development (physical, mental, social, spiritual and education), and children with and without parents should be protected and taken care of by parents, society and public authorities respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0020872811428923">Declaration of the Rights of the Child, 1959</xref>).</p>
<p>The book begins with a list of acronyms of regional and national policies discussed throughout the book. The author, Stephen N. Achilihu is a priest of the Catholic diocese of Aba (Nigeria) and a child rights activist. Achilihu acknowledges his personal experiences of growing up as an African child, his academic experience of studying law, and his career experiences of attending several international conferences. He writes in the introduction that ‘Africa is one of the continents in the world where the rights of the child is still a mirage’ and adds that ‘The sad reality for many African children is that violation of children’s rights is not seen as a serious problem’ (p. XIV). Thus, the writer clearly identifies the violation of children’s rights and the lack of recognition of their violations as important issues that call for immediate action. Organized into five chapters, this book aims to educate its readers on the plight of African children and the actions that are needed to improve their situation.</p>
<p>The first chapter describes the development of CRC including its history, drafting process, contents and the roles of states, inter-governmental organizations and non-governmental organizations in the ratification, implementation and monitoring phases of the CRC. Chapter two addresses the protection of people’s rights in Africa through African treaties. In this chapter, the author examines the provisions, structure, and impact of significant African treaties on the lives of African children. Here, the book provides in-depth information about the protection of children within a Muslim jurisdiction. This section of the book covers topics like the Islamic law (Shari’ah), Islamic family law, legal reform in a Muslim jurisdiction, and human rights instruments used in Islamic states. Chapter three covers issues related to the domestication of the CRC reflected within the national laws and policies of African countries. Dividing Africa into four sections (western, eastern, central and southern), the author analyzes the countries’ constitutions and national legislations to determine the extent to which the CRC has been incorporated into national laws in Africa.</p>
<p>Chapter four covers a broad range of topics which the author considers important across Africa. In relation to the CRC, the topics he discusses include: the conflict between the CRC and customary laws, children’s socio-economic rights, poverty, child trafficking, child labor, children in armed conflicts, refugee children and the protection of children from abuse, violence and exploitation. This book concludes in the fifth chapter where the author notes that although some children have benefitted from CRC-influenced policies, many remain excluded. He wraps up by noting that almost all the countries in Africa, except Somalia have ratified the CRC and that several countries have conducted comprehensive reviews of children in their respective countries, while others have amended key legislations conforming to the CRC. The actions taken in adherence to the CRC indicate African governments’ recognition of children’s issues as a political priority. The author proposes several recommendations which he believes are important and necessary steps to improve and protect the rights of Children in Africa and also bridge the gap he thinks exists between international obligations and national actions, and also between laws and practice.</p>
<p>This book could be enriched by incorporating findings from qualitative studies about social problems and obstacles African children experience (e.g. child labor, child trafficking, child soldiering, etc.) that can be improved by national policies. By doing this, the author allows the voices of African children to be heard and also provides in depth understandings of African children’s experiences, as compared to the usual empirical evidence found in quantitative studies. Also, I would have liked to see more assessment of African children’s knowledge of their rights and their level of awareness of CRC-influenced legislations that impacts their welfare. Evident strengths of this book lie in the extensive research undertaken by the author on the history of the CRC, its influence on regional African policies as well as African countries’ constitution and national policies. Using statistics and concrete examples of national policies and its provisions, the author illustrates the extent to which provisions of the CRC have been implemented in national legislations of African states. The text highlights the disconnect between the values and standards of the CRC and African laws at the regional and national levels. It also underscores the relationships between violations of African children’s rights and the lifelong consequences African children face, which the author argues pose a direct threat to peace, stability and development in Africa (p. XIV).</p>
<p>Another strength of this book is the conclusion which provides steps African states can take to establish legal and institutional foundations that will ensure that principles of the CRC are incorporated and implemented at all levels of African policies. Additionally, the book includes reference guides and tables (provided in appendix A and B) which serve as helpful resources in understanding the extent to which the CRC has been incorporated in African laws affecting children. Although the author writes from a policy perspective, this book’s audience is not limited to policy analysts and professionals in the legal field. Instead, it is full of helpful information which will shock and inspire social workers, advocates, students, and international and national agencies interested in understanding the plight of African children and legislations that affect children.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>Reference</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0020872811428923">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Declaration of the Rights of the Child</collab> (<year>1959</year>) <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cirp.org/library/ethics/UN-declaration/">http://www.cirp.org/library/ethics/UN-declaration/</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed 14 March 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>