<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">APA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spapa</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Am Psychoanal Assoc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0003-0651</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1941-2460</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0003065112470561</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0003065112470561</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Panel Report</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Desire and Being Desired</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Cirio</surname><given-names>Phoebe A.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0003065112470561">141 North Meramec Avenue, Suite 304 St. Louis, MO 63105 E-mail: <email>phoebe777@aol.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>61</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>135</fpage>
<lpage>144</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Psychoanalytic Association 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Psychoanalytic Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The presenters on this panel were asked to focus their attention on the unique role played by desire in psychoanalysis. The inspiration was a cover story in the <italic>New York Times Magazine</italic> (January 25, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0003065112470561">2009</xref>) that asked the question “What is female desire?” In his effort to answer that question, the author, David Bergner, referenced a variety of research into female desire. Results were reported from sociological and cultural studies. Also included were laboratory studies in which male and female, homo- and heterosexual subjects were shown films of human and animal sexual behavior. Consistently in these studies, women subjects reported themselves as less aroused than was indicated by the physical measures of arousal collected during the viewing. This discrepancy between self-report and physiological measurement stimulated the curiosity of the researchers, and of Bergner himself. Since, however, there was no psychoanalytic contribution to the piece, there was no way to approach the role of the unconscious in explaining this finding. The article attempted to be thorough, but psychoanalysis, with its unique perspective on the unconscious, was missing. Because of this omission I proposed a panel on female desire, a topic that eventually expanded to include the condition of desiring and being desired irrespective of gender. There seems no lack of curiosity about desire in the contemporary imagination. The recent commercial success of <italic>Fifty Shades of Grey</italic> has occasioned great interest in the question of why average women find masochistic fantasies sexually arousing.</p>
<p>In introducing and framing the panel, Melinda Gellman reminded us that psychoanalysis began in the conundrum of desire. Anna O.’s hysterical pregnancy, and the onset of “labor” during a therapy session, enacted her desire for Josef Breuer. Panicked by what he could not understand, he fled. Fortunately for psychoanalysis, he referred his patient to Freud, who strove to theorize the intense passion that had driven Breuer out of practice. He arrived at a conception of desire that was, according to Gellman, “endogenous and sexual, organized in the drives and instincts that guide human behavior.” This desire originates within each of us, and then seeks, and creates, its objects. Freud, in describing the oedipal wishes of a child, tells us that the child “usually follows some indications from its parents.” Thus does Freud posit that parents too are sexual subjects, and that their child unconsciously knows of their desire.</p>
<p>Gellman described the great diversity in how desire is theorized in contemporary psychoanalysis; our patients desire love, money, and power. The consulting room must contain, and we must strive to interpret, desires that are forbidden, painful, and guilt-inducing. And it is increasingly accepted that desire in the psychoanalytic setting is bidirectional. The analyst too desires. But in the theater of the clinical setting, the freedom to express desire, and especially to enact it, is not equal. Gellman referred to a recent paper by Muriel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0003065112470561">Dimen (2011)</xref>, in which she describes her analysis as a young graduate student. At the end of an analytic hour she asked her analyst for a hug. As she broke from the hug, she kissed him on the cheek. “No,” he said, “how about a real kiss?” When she kissed him on the mouth, “he returned the favor with his tongue” (p. 36). He told her he had better stop because he was getting an erection. Dimen considers the harm that came from this breach of the analytic frame, and concludes that the greater harm came from the silence that followed. Analyst and analysand never spoke of what happened between them.</p>
<p>Analysts feel longing, and desire too, Gellman reminded us. But while Dimen had compassion for her analyst, she holds to the need for the prohibition on sexual contact with patients. Gellman, citing Dimen, stressed the perils of dissociating desire in the analytic dyad. Desire, in all its multiplicity, has psychoanalytic relevance. We strive to find the meaning of desire for each patient, in different times and relational contexts.</p>
<p>Marillia Aisenstein said that when she thinks of desire, she must also think of love. Desire, thinking, and dreaming are all present in love. In the love letters exchanged by Freud and his fiancée, Martha Bernays, we can see nascent theories of wishful hallucination, and of word and thing presentations. These letters describe their longing for each other, and how they dream and imagine their beloved present. Aisenstein defined the terms <italic>wish, need</italic>, and <italic>desire.</italic> A wish may contain a desire. But desire also involves the idea of force, and so requires the addition of the libidinal drive. Need refers to biological need, that is, something that fulfills a vital function. Psychic work is required to transform need into desire. How that transformation occurs was the subject of Aisenstein’s paper, which she anchored in Freud’s premise that psychology is rooted in desire.</p>
<p>Aisenstein tells us that in the “Project for a Scientific Psychology” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0003065112470561">Freud (1895)</xref> posits that the helpless infant, distressed by a painful stimulus such as hunger, has but one remedy: feeding at the breast. When the baby associates this feeling of satisfaction with the mother’s breast, a memory trace is created. Unpleasurable affects, and states of desire, are remembered through such traces. The memory trace is reinforced when the infant first feels the internal tension of hunger, and then the sudden release of satiety; and so the infant associates the tension in the ego with the object of desire. The baby first wishes for and desires the milk, and then desires the mother who provides it.</p>
<p>The link between milk and mother is anaclitic. Through psychic work the infant uses the memory trace of mother bringing milk in the past, to create a soothing hallucination of mother bringing milk in the present. There is a leap from the experience of past satiation from feeding on milk, to the recognition of, and desire for, the object, the mother, in the present. Desire arises from need. When the baby experiences its own desire, it is born as a subject, capable of desire. Thinking, and fantasy life, begin when the infant desires.</p>
<p>To give a clearer idea of Freud’s idea of hallucinatory wish-fulfillment, Aisenstein quotes <italic>The Interpretation of Dreams</italic>: “nothing but a wish can set our mental apparatus at work” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0003065112470561">Freud 1900</xref>, p. 567). A dream integrates a conscious desire with an unconscious wish, and presents the facts “as I wished them to take place.” It is desire that puts the mind to work.</p>
<p>This capacity for thinking and waiting develops via primary masochism. In “The Economic Problem of Masochism” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0003065112470561">Freud 1924</xref>), a very early primary masochism binds the contradictory forces of the libido and the death drive in the baby’s ego, and primes the infantile psyche for waiting. Then it is the mother, whose psychic work through reverie soothes the uncomfortable baby and helps it tolerate the waiting. The mother envelops the baby with soothing. Her reassurance eases its fears and helps it wait. If waiting is to be tolerable, it must be invested masochistically. The baby finds the pleasure in waiting through the psychic work of desiring. Investment in the delay lies at the basis of desire: the baby can think about, and imagine, the pleasure to come. The structure of desire is essentially masochistic; there must be a renunciation of immediate satisfaction, and an investment in waiting.</p>
<p>Aisenstein concluded with a discussion of transference. In “The Dynamics of Transference” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0003065112470561">Freud 1912</xref>), she said, “transference is pure desire transferred onto the analyst.” But a second theory of transference emerged after 1920. Transference is the fundamental urge to repeat what is “beyond the pleasure principle.” The two theories can coexist. Trauma results in unbearable tension, and the transference is driven not by the seeking of pleasure but by the need to repeat. Because of what Aisenstein terms a “compulsion to transfer,” patients who resist desire can access it via analysis. She described classical neurotic patients whose transferences are based on desire. But other patients, including those with borderline and psychosomatic pathology, organize their psychic life “against desire,” and so defend themselves against the object.</p>
<p>Aisenstein provided a vignette from a patient, in a very long treatment, who had used physical exertion to numb herself to love and desire. A turning point in the treatment occurred when the patient revealed that she had experienced tachycardia for many years, and had concealed the symptom because she enjoyed it. Aisenstein was angry, and her own heart raced, when she learned of the risk the patient took in never disclosing a potentially serious medical condition to her, or to her other doctors. She interpreted to the patient that she had enjoyed the sensation of love, the rapid heart rate, all alone: “You are in love without wanting to address it to anyone . . ., and above all not to me.” The treatment continued for years after this significant session, and at the last session the patient gave her analyst a book of poetry, in which she thanked her for helping her learn that she can love and think without danger.</p>
<p>Donald Moss, like Aisenstein, took up the issue of psychic work in desire, but more directly. He invoked Freud’s concept (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0003065112470561">1915</xref>) that drives “exert a demand . . . upon the mind for work in consequence of its connection to the body” (p. 122). Not desiring places one in a secure, and unending, present tense; time has no meaning because it is unvarying. There is no past, no future: only now. Desire mobilizes. One goes off in search of an object. But this object introduces uncertainty: it could join with you and fulfill your desire, or refuse you. One moves from the comfort of not wanting, to the discomfort of wanting, and needing, satisfaction. When there is desire there is the potential of satisfaction, but also the risk of despair. In a state of desire, one cannot set the terms, or foretell the outcome. Not knowing the outcome in advance requires psychic work. Working requires forward momentum, leaving the present, and pursuit of the future. One sacrifices certainty and gets contingency. Movement replaces stasis.</p>
<p>Moss described two types of patient. The first type treats the demand of desire as a catastrophe that must be averted. A line from the poem “Litany” by Stefan George, “Kill the longing, close the wound!” captures the wish of such a patient to be permanently rid of desire, and thus end the demand for psychic work. For these patients, the work of desire, of longing, is unbearable. The analyst for such patients must be able to preserve a sense of time, past, present, and future, because the patient will try to obliterate time. Being able to remain in the context of time, knowing that there is more than the present, makes the work of the analyst bearable. If the analyst loses the sense of time, there develops a countertransference of being entombed, or buried alive. This countertransference can manifest itself in a desire of the analyst to obliterate the patient, who himself seems intent on destroying the analyst. Such patients seek to replace the movement of time with unity with the other. All that remains is unity in oblivion, because self and other, as distinct objects, are obliterated.</p>
<p>Moss then described a second type of patient, one torn between a desire that is unbearable to tolerate, and the alternative, which is easier to bear: shutting things down. Patients in this category are torn between the terrifying fact of their desire and an equal resistance unable to completely quash desire. The result is anguish and psychic pain. The demand of the drive for psychic work is resisted, but not fully, and torment is the result.</p>
<p>Moss described how, when the analyst is the object of desire, he feels pursued. The patient is certain that the analyst is the object long desired, but until now he had abandoned all hope of finding him. The analyst is what the patient has believed was lacking in himself. Being desired in this way envelops the analyst and engenders tensions within him. The analyst is not allowed to be a separate person, and feels stalked. Moss illustrated his point with clinical material in which a patient, engrossed in berating himself, smoothly and effectively moves to agree with the analyst, regardless of what the analyst says, erasing any difference between their minds. An interpretation by the analyst is obliterated when the patient assures the analyst that he is correct about him, more correct than the patient could ever hope to be about himself, and that the patient will forever lack the capacity to see himself differently. Finally, the analyst, feeling defeated, lapses into silence. He feels obliterated and violated. To satisfy his desire, the patient has erased any difference between himself and the other, causing the analyst to collapse and making analysis impossible.</p>
<p>Moss concluded with a quote from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0003065112470561">Loewald (1980)</xref>: “we must have . . . an image of that which needs to be brought into its own. . . . —an image that the analyst has to focus in his mind, thus holding it in safe keeping for the patient to whom it is mainly lost” (p. 226). Moss continued with his understanding that psychoanalysis falls within the broader category of the work of desire. Both psychoanalysis, and desire and being desired, incarnate possibility by preserving an object “that would otherwise be enslaved to desire’s relentless demand to obliterate the future, and turn the present into a state of permanent satisfaction.”</p>
<p>During a break for discussion after the first two papers, Moss and Aisenstein remarked on the convergence between their papers. Though they worked independently, the patient described by Aisenstein, who shut her desire down, fit Moss’s Type One patient. Both Moss and Aisenstein placed desire within the context of psychic work, but they conceptualize the work differently. Aisenstein described how the infant uses psychic work to imagine the breast, and the feeling of satiety to come, in order to soothe its hunger. And it is from this waiting that the infant acquires thought. Moss’s Type One patient obliterates desire by creating a perpetual now. Time stops. For such a patient there is no separation between himself and his object, there is no future, there is only now. For Moss, psychic work means the object is kept in mind before being found. Thus, the work of desire means tolerating a time when the object can be thought about but not possessed or enjoyed. The patient who destroys his own desire remains mired in the present, fused with the other.</p>
<p>Carol Gilligan and Deborah Luepnitz both consider the manifestations of desire in social and cultural contexts. Often the women in Gilligan’s studies have not been able to articulate what they desire. Considering abortions in the wake of Roe v. Wade, many of them thought it selfish to put their own wants and needs before those of others, particularly the men in their lives. When questioned about what they wanted, they could say what others needed, but did not know what they really wanted. The interviewer asked them the question “If it’s good to be empathic with people and responsive to their desires and concerns, why is it selfish to respond to yourself?” Often the women responded, “Good question.” What had been a “morality of selflessness” began to come apart. Abdicating their own voices often caused the relationships they wanted to sustain to unravel; their deference to others signified an abdication of responsibility for themselves. In ceding her voice to others, a woman made them responsible, and blamed them, for the choices she had in fact made. She then often blamed herself for having listened to them.</p>
<p>In subsequent research, Gilligan and her colleagues found that pre-teenage girls resist silencing an honest voice. One girl spoke of separating her mind, which she associated with her “real thoughts and feelings,” not from her body but from her brain, which she associated with her intelligence and education. In essence, she was resisting losing her mind. Many girls spoke of their need to project an impression of themselves they knew to be false. At thirteen, Tracy called an honest voice “stupid,” meaning that to say what she really thought and felt either was stupid or sounded so.</p>
<p>Boys too feel pressed in adolescence to conceal desires they have come to associate with being girlish or gay. Preadolescent boys in a study by Niobe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0003065112470561">Way (2011)</xref> spoke with self-awareness of the divide between their feelings of deep love and affection for other boys, their male friends; by late adolescence, boys spoke of no longer having close friendships with other boys or hedged any depiction of emotional intimacy with other boys, using the phrase “no homo.” Like girls, they became reticent about revealing their desires within a culture where such desires are considered “stupid” or unmanly. Gilligan trusts that the true feelings are still there, inside, waiting to be expressed in a receptive setting. Both young girls and young boys desire honesty, intimacy, and caring, but will express these relational desires openly only if they have a welcome reception.</p>
<p>Gilligan wonders if the legacy of the ethos of feminine self-sacrifice is the equation of women’s liberation with selfishness. Women students she speaks to now wonder why they should care about the feelings of others. But, Gilligan asks, do young women today employ callousness as a guise, to cloak and protect them as they enter zones previously off-limits to women, zones as diverse as faculty clubs and combat units? Is silence about the norms in these zones the price women must pay for entering them? Is the price for sexual freedom not to question the norm of “hooking up,” or sex as a “benefit” of friendship?</p>
<p>Gilligan contends that the Arab Spring demonstrates the fundamental human desire to have a voice, to be listened to and heard. We want to live in relationship, rather than feeling invisible and subject to the desires of another. She described a troubling loss of voice that occurs in adolescence. Something happens when girls begin to differentiate between “what I feel” and “what I really feel,” and between “what I think” and “what I really think.” Between the two is the initiation of dissociation, something she calls the “reconstruction of desire.” Girls acquire the ability, and feel the need, to hold parts of their experience outside of awareness. Through a process of initiation, they begin to separate what they believe they are supposed to feel from what they really, truly, feel inside. This dissociation affects both boys and girls. It is present in the myth that boys want sex, and girls want relationship. Boys and girls want both. But somehow, revealing to another their heart’s desire seems too dangerous, so they adopt a pose with which to conceal themselves. But the true feelings do lie within. Given the power of association to undo dissociation, it takes an associative leap to undo the effects of a culturally scripted and enforced initiation and to bring desire and curiosity into awareness.</p>
<p>Deborah Luepnitz next provided a Lacan-informed perspective on desire. Lacan thought the matter of desire was missing from American psychoanalysis. Instead, Luepnitz argues, psychoanalysis became a medical subspecialty designed to facilitate adjustment to social and sexual norms. For Lacan, desire is defined in contrast to need and demand. Need refers to biological imperatives such as hunger; demand, which can be likened to want, is the call to the Other. The call may indicate need, but is not entirely about need. Desire is what is left when need is subtracted from demand. Needs and demands can be satisfied. Desire cannot. Desire cannot be reduced to drives; they are only a manifestation of it.</p>
<p>The big “O” Other does not refer to a person. It is a radical otherness that can be associated with culture, fate, death, God, or the unconscious. No desire is pure or unmediated, and it is the norm to struggle with desire. It can take a lifetime to know one’s desire, and, for Lacan, that is the point of psychoanalysis.</p>
<p>Desire is discovered by the infant in the mother. If the mother desires something, it is because she lacks it. The child wants to fill her desire, to complete her, but also discovers that he cannot be enough for her. The child can be loved and wanted, but the mother also loves others, and the child will never be enough. Whom or what she loves is less important than the fact of her loving elsewhere. The child learns that he is not sufficient to satisfy his mother’s needs. However, some children are phallic objects. Here Lacan uses the term <italic>phallus</italic> to signify a false completeness—false because we are mortal, and incomplete. Children who serve as phallic objects might think they are defined by this ascribed purpose: to suffer, replace a dead child, or achieve greatness. They are desired as a trophy or appendage, not for themselves alone, and may grow up psychotic, or enter relationships in which their own desires are obliterated by the other.</p>
<p>The trophy child has foreclosed the opportunity to grapple with <italic>che vuoi?</italic> —“What do you want?” in Italian. It is the question “What does the Other want from me?” <italic>Che vuoi</italic> begins the quest for one’s own desire. If certainty about oneself originates outside oneself, if <italic>che vuoi</italic> is foreclosed, it may be due to the family até. Lacan refers to this as the family curse or crime. To fully understand a symptom in the current generation, one must explore at least the two generations preceding it.</p>
<p>Luepnitz, like Gilligan, referred to the desire for democracy bursting forth in the Arab Spring. She also sees democracy, and desire, in the Occupy movement here at home. She noted that Occupy has frustrated many by not issuing demands. But Slavoj Žižek argues that while they have no demands, their message is not without content. Luepnitz quoted from his speech to the Occupiers in Zuccotti Park, where he cautioned them not to be placated: “We know that people often desire something but do not really want it. Don’t be afraid to really want what you desire.”</p>
<p>The fragility of owning one’s own desire was vividly enacted during the panel program. In a break for questions and discussion after the first two papers, Sandra Buechler commented that, as she has grown older, she has become more hesitant to interpret her patient’s desire for her. This comment was tabled until the end of the program, and might have been forgotten had someone in the audience not reminded us of it. The question made us all conscious of the fear of not having our desires mirrored back to us. Gilligan noted, in response to the question, that patriarchal culture is uncomfortable with female desire, much less the desire of older women. It is easier for the culture if women just want what we are supposed to want, not what we do want.</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>Panel held at the Winter Meeting of the American Psychoanalytic Association, New York, January 14, 2012. Panelists: Melinda Gellman (Chair), Marillia Aisenstein, Donald Moss, Carol Gilligan, Deborah Luepnitz.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0003065112470561">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bergner</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>What is female desire? A postfeminist generation of researchers is discovering things Dr. Freud could never have imagined</article-title>. <source>New York Times Magazine</source>, <month>January</month> <volume>25</volume>, <year>2009</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0003065112470561">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dimen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Lapsus linguae, or a slip of the tongue? A sexual violation in an analytic treatment and its personal and theoretical aftermath</article-title>. <source>Contemporary Psychoanalysis</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0003065112470561">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1895</year>). <article-title>Project for a scientific psychology</article-title>. <source>Standard Edition</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0003065112470561">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1900</year>). <article-title>The interpretation of dreams</article-title>. <source>Standard Edition</source> <volume>4/5</volume>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0003065112470561">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1912</year>). <article-title>The dynamics of transference</article-title>. <source>Standard Edition</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0003065112470561">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1915</year>). <article-title>Instincts and their viscissitudes</article-title>. <source>Standard Edition</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0003065112470561">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1924</year>). <article-title>The economic problem of masochism</article-title>. <source>Standard Edition</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0003065112470561">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Loewald</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>On the therapeutic action of psychoanalysis</article-title>. In <source>Papers on Psychoanalysis</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0003065112470561">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Way</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Deep Secrets: Boys’ Friendships and the Crisis of Connection</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>