<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SPP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spspp</journal-id>
<journal-title>Social Psychological and Personality Science</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1948-5506</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1948-5514</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1948550612471061</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1948550612471061</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Rise and Fall of Self-Control</article-title>
<subtitle>Temptation-Elicited Goal Activation and Effortful Goal-Directed Behavior</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>van Koningsbruggen</surname>
<given-names>Guido M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1948550612471061">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1948550612471061"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stroebe</surname>
<given-names>Wolfgang</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1948550612471061">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aarts</surname>
<given-names>Henk</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</contrib>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p>
<bold>Guido M. van Koningsbruggen</bold> is an assistant professor and interested in behavior regulation.</p>
<p>
<bold>Wolfgang Stroebe</bold> is a professor of social psychology.</p>
<p>
<bold>Henk Aarts</bold> is a professor of cognitive social psychology.</p>
</bio>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1948550612471061">
<label>1</label>Department of Communication Science, VU University Amsterdam, The Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1948550612471061">
<label>2</label>Department of Psychology, Utrecht University, The Netherlands</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1948550612471061">
<label>3</label>Department of Social Psychology, University of Groningen, The Netherlands</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1948550612471061">Guido M. van Koningsbruggen, Department of Communication Science, VU University Amsterdam, De Boelelaan 1081, 1081 HV Amsterdam, The Netherlands Email: <email>g.m.van.koningsbruggen@vu.nl</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>546</fpage>
<lpage>554</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Social and Personality Psychology Consortium</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Environmental cues of temptation generally frustrate people’s long-term goal attainment. However, recent research suggests that temptation cues promote, rather than hamper long-term goal congruent effects in successful self-regulators. While previous work has started to shed light on the cognitive features of this rise and fall of self-control, the present research aims to significantly advance this study by exploring important implications for actual behavior in the domain of dieting. In combining a temptation cue exposure procedure with a concurrent schedules task, results of two studies demonstrated that tempting food cues increased unsuccessful, but not successful dieters’ effortful behavior toward high-calorie food. In contrast, tempting food cues increased successful dieters’ efforts toward low-calorie food, but did not affect unsuccessful dieters. The findings suggest that the behavior of both unsuccessful and successful dieters in response to tempting food cues is goal-directed rather than impulsive.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>self-control</kwd>
<kwd>temptation</kwd>
<kwd>effort</kwd>
<kwd>dieting</kwd>
<kwd>goal conflict</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The presence of temptations generally frustrates people’s attainment of long-term goals. A delicious cake in the window of a bakery may trigger dieters to enter the bakery to buy a cake, even though they try to lose weight. An exciting trailer of a movie may motivate a student to watch the movie instead of studying for an exam. While environmental cues of temptations easily disrupt long-term goal striving for many people (e.g, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1948550612471061">Metcalfe &amp; Mischel, 1999</xref>), current research on temptations and goal pursuit suggests that temptations may also assist long-term goal congruent effects on behavior (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1948550612471061">Fishbach, Friedman, &amp; Kruglanski, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1948550612471061">Fishbach, Zhang, &amp; Trope, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1948550612471061">Trope &amp; Fishbach, 2000</xref>). Intriguingly, for people who see themselves as successful self-regulators, temptation cues automatically bring to mind their long-term goal which should make it easier to resist these temptations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1948550612471061">Fishbach et al., 2003</xref>). At this point, little is known about the behavioral implications of this temptation-elicited activation of long-term goals, and especially how temptation cues can mobilize different patterns of physical effort that either undermine or facilitate long-term goals. The current article therefore aims to advance our knowledge about the rise and fall of self-control by integrating a behavioral economics paradigm with recent work on environmentally triggered goal-directed behavior. We examined this in the domain of eating and dieting behavior: an area in which temptations interfere with long-term goal pursuit for many, but not all people.</p>
<p>With the increasing worldwide prevalence of overweight and obesity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1948550612471061">Finucane et al., 2011</xref>), dieting has become a popular strategy of weight control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1948550612471061">Kruger, Galuska, Serdula, &amp; Jones, 2004</xref>). Although dieters often manage to lose weight in the beginning, most fail in maintaining their weight loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1948550612471061">Mann et al., 2007</xref>). Chronic dieters, also referred to as <italic>restrained eaters</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1948550612471061">Herman &amp; Polivy, 1980</xref>), are especially unsuccessful in controlling their food intake in the presence of tempting food cues. Although they are motivated to restrict food intake to control their body weight, exposure to cues of tempting food easily disrupts their self-control. However, exposure to tempting food cues does not lead to indulgence for all dieters. Compared to dieters who perceive themselves as unsuccessful in their dieting attempts (unsuccessful dieters), those seeing themselves as successful in their dieting attempts (successful dieters), appear successful in keeping their diet and controlling their weight (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1948550612471061">Fishbach et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1948550612471061">Papies, Stroebe, &amp; Aarts, 2008</xref>). Before elaborating on the processes of self-regulatory success, we first provide a brief overview of how temptation cues generally frustrate dieters’ long-term goal pursuit.</p>
<sec id="section1-1948550612471061">
<title>The Fall of Self-Control</title>
<p>In the domain of dieting behavior, many studies demonstrated the disruptive influence of temptation cues on the self-control of dieters. For instance, the presence or even the smell of palatable food elicits preparatory responses like a strong desire to eat tasty food and increased salivation in dieters compared to normal eaters (or unrestrained eaters; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1948550612471061">Brunstrom, Yates, &amp; Witcomb, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1948550612471061">Fedoroff, Polivy, &amp; Herman, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1948550612471061">LeGoff &amp; Spigelman, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1948550612471061">Tepper, 1992</xref>). Moreover, dieters are more likely to overeat after exposure to temptation cues such as the sight, smell, thought, or taste of palatable food (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1948550612471061">Fedoroff et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1948550612471061">Harris, Bargh, &amp; Brownell, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1948550612471061">Jansen &amp; Van den Hout, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1948550612471061">Rogers &amp; Hill, 1989</xref>).</p>
<p>Two conflicting explanations have been offered for the difficulty of dieters in resisting food temptations. From the perspective of dual system theories such as the reflective–impulsive model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1948550612471061">Strack &amp; Deutsch, 2004</xref>) such behavior is impulsive. Impulses are assumed to be triggered by the impulsive system from the activation of associative clusters in long-term memory, which have been created through frequent coactivation of external stimuli (e.g., ice cream), affective reactions (e.g., regarding taste), and behavioral tendencies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1948550612471061">Hofmann, Friese, &amp; Wiers, 2008</xref>). Impulsive processes of behavior determination are assumed to operate automatic and require little effort.</p>
<p>In contrast, the goal conflict model of eating assumes that the eating behavior of dieters is dominated by two conflicting goals: eating enjoyment and dieting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1948550612471061">Stroebe, Mensink, Aarts, Schut, &amp; Kruglanski, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1948550612471061">Stroebe, Van Koningsbruggen, Papies, &amp; Aarts, in press</xref>). Although dieters want to enjoy the pleasure of eating palatable food (usually high in calories), they also want to lose or at least not gain weight. Importantly, several experiments have shown that tempting food cues not only activate the goal of eating enjoyment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1948550612471061">Hofmann, Van Koningsbruggen, Stroebe, Ramanathan, &amp; Aarts, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1948550612471061">Papies, Stroebe, &amp; Aarts, 2007</xref>), but at the same time inhibit the long-term goal of dieting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1948550612471061">Papies et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1948550612471061">Stroebe et al., 2008</xref>). Accordingly, because tempting food cues switch on the eating enjoyment and inhibit the dieting goal, the hedonic goal of eating enjoyment exerts more influence on subsequent behavior than the inhibited dieting goal, thereby increasing the likelihood of overeating. However, direct evidence on whether overeating is impulsive or a goal-directed response in pursuit of eating enjoyment has so far been lacking.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1948550612471061">
<title>The Rise of Self-Control</title>
<p>Contrary to the literature confirming the disruptive influence of temptation cues on people’s self-control, current research on temptations and goal pursuit suggests that for some people temptations increase the cognitive accessibility of long-term goals typically undermined by these temptations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1948550612471061">Fishbach et al., 2003</xref>). According to this theory of temptation-elicited goal activation, a facilitative link between temptation and goal develops when people repeatedly and successfully exert self-control in tempting situations. For instance, when a dieter repeatedly declines when offered palatable food because he or she thinks of his or her diet, a link between palatable food and dieting thoughts may develop. Subsequent exposure to palatable food should then automatically activate the dieting goal, allowing for more motivational control over thought and action related to eating.</p>
<p>Temptation-elicited goal activation has been demonstrated across several self-regulatory domains, and is most pronounced for people for whom the goal is important and perceive themselves as successful self-regulators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1948550612471061">Fishbach et al., 2003</xref>). Indeed, research showed that tempting food cues activate the long-term dieting goal in successful dieters, while they inhibit this goal in unsuccessful dieters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1948550612471061">Fishbach et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1948550612471061">Papies et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1948550612471061">Van Koningsbruggen, Stroebe, Papies, &amp; Aarts, 2011</xref>). These studies used the perceived self-regulatory success in dieting scale (developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1948550612471061">Fishbach et al., 2003</xref>) to differentiate between successful and unsuccessful dieters. For successful dieters, tempting food cues thus switch on the dieting goal and because of its increased accessibility, the dieting goal exerts more influence on subsequent motivational behavior than the less accessible eating enjoyment goal. Consequently, temptations may facilitate long-term goal congruent effects on behavior.</p>
<p>At this point, however, little is known about the implications of temptation-elicited long-term goal activation for actual behavior. Research showed that the intention to refrain from eating palatable food strongly predicted the self-reported eating behavior of successful, but not of unsuccessful dieters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1948550612471061">Papies et al., 2008</xref>). In addition, successful dieters have a lower body mass index (BMI; e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1948550612471061">Meule, Papies, &amp; Kübler, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1948550612471061">Papies et al., 2008</xref>). These findings fit with the idea that temptations increase the cognitive accessibility of the dieting goal and in turn may promote long-term goal congruent effects on behavior among successful dieters. A more direct demonstration of the behavioral implications of facilitative temptation-goal associations has been reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1948550612471061">Fishbach, Friedman, and Kruglanski (2003</xref>, Study 5). In this study, brief exposure to tempting food cues increased the accessibility of the dieting goal and made participants more likely to choose an apple over a Twix bar. Although this process is assumed to only occur among successful self-regulators, this study did not differentiate between successful and unsuccessful dieters and did not use a validated measure of dieting motivation. The exact influence of temptation-elicited goal activation on actual behavior as a function of perceived self-regulatory success thus remains largely unclear.</p>
<p>Moreover, an important question that has not yet received attention in research on temptation-elicited goal activation is that if temptations actually activate a dieting goal rather than eliciting an automatic dieting response (i.e., impulse), goal pursuit should make people more persistent and expend more effort on tasks instrumental to attain the activated goal (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1948550612471061">Carver &amp; Scheier, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1948550612471061">Fishbach &amp; Ferguson, 2007</xref>). Successful self-control triggered by temptations should thus result in increased effortful behavior toward objects instrumental for attaining the long-term goal (e.g., low-calorie foods for dieters), while it should not boost effortful behavior toward temptation-relevant objects (e.g., high-calorie foods for dieters). Although a simple choice task in which people have to choose between two alternatives (e.g., apple vs. candy bar) is conceptually relevant because it resembles a real-life situation, it does not allow one to conclude whether this reflects a simple impulsive response or goal-directed behavior. Hence, whereas previous work has started to shed light on the cognitive features of temptation-elicited goal pursuit, the present research scrutinized its impact on actual effortful goal-directed behavior. Specifically, we tested the hypothesis that temptation cues would mobilize different patterns of physical effort that either undermine or facilitate long-term goals depending on individuals’ level of perceived self-regulatory success.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1948550612471061">
<title>The Present Research</title>
<p>To test the proposed impact of temptation-elicited goal activation on persistence and effort in obtaining goal-relevant objects (food in the present research), we measured participants’ performance in a concurrent schedules task after exposing them to tempting food cues. The concurrent schedules task—a behavioral task widely used in research adopting a behavioral economics perspective (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1948550612471061">Saelens &amp; Epstein, 1996</xref>)—is a task in which participants have to earn points that can be traded for high- and/or low-calorie food. However, when the task proceeds, it becomes harder to earn points for one of the food options (i.e., participants have to persist and invest more effort to obtain it). Increased working for the hard-to-get option reflects more effortful behavior toward that particular food.</p>
<p>In Study 1, we assessed effortful behavior toward high-calorie food by gradually increasing the difficulty to obtain this food option (i.e., making task performance instrumental to attain the eating enjoyment goal). Effortful behavior toward low-calorie food was assessed in Study 2 by gradually increasing the difficulty to obtain this food option (i.e., making task performance instrumental to attain the dieting goal). Because tempting food cues switch on the eating enjoyment goal in unsuccessful dieters while at the same time decreasing the influence of the dieting goal, we predicted that tempting food cues would increase effortful behavior toward high calorie, but not low-calorie food among unsuccessful dieters. In contrast, because tempting food cues activate the dieting goal for successful dieters, we predicted that such cues would increase effortful behavior toward low calorie, but not toward high-calorie food among successful dieters.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1948550612471061">
<title>Study 1</title>
<sec id="section5-1948550612471061" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section6-1948550612471061">
<title>Design and participants</title>
<p>This study used a cue exposure condition (food vs. control) between-participants design, with difficulty to obtain the high-calorie food as a within-participants factor, and chronic dieting and success in dieting as continuous variables. Ninety-eight students completed the study in return for course credit or a small fee. Inspection of the data, however, revealed four influential outliers on the dependent measure (two participants’ data points had leverage values beyond 3 times the average; two participants had standardized residuals &gt;6 standard deviation (<italic>SD</italic>) above the mean; cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1948550612471061">Stevens, 2002</xref>) and three persons participated in another study on eating and dieting behavior just before completing the present study. These participants were therefore excluded, and the final sample consisted of 91 participants (50 female; <italic>M</italic>
<sub>age</sub> = 22.51, <italic>SD</italic>
<sub>age</sub> = 6.12). Participants were assigned randomly to the food or control exposure condition.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1948550612471061">
<title>Materials and Measures</title>
<sec id="section8-1948550612471061">
<title>Cue exposure</title>
<p>A letter detection task was used to expose participants to tempting food or control cues (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1948550612471061">Hofmann et al., 2010</xref>). Participants had to indicate as quickly and accurately as possible, by pressing a key, whether a letter presented very briefly on the screen was the letter “A” or “L.” Before each decision, a word was briefly presented. The letter detection task contained 75 trials, and every trial began with a fixation point (*) for 1,000 ms. In each trial, participants were presented briefly with either a randomly selected tempting food word (food cue exposure) or nonword (control cue exposure). We used five food (chocolate, cookies, pizza, French fries, chips) and five nonwords (jolging, nistierd, bagou, felin, gnefpar), and each word was presented 15 times. The cue word was preceded by a premask (unreadable letter string) that remained for 400 ms. Then the word was presented for 34 ms, followed by a postmask (unreadable letter string) for 400 ms. Finally, participants were presented randomly with the letter “A” or “L” for 100 ms, followed by a question mark that remained on the screen until the participant responded. When participants responded correctly (vs. erroneously) a green circle (vs. red cross) was presented for 1,000 ms. The intertrial interval was 500 ms.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1948550612471061">
<title>Concurrent schedules task</title>
<p>Participants were told that they had to earn points for food by repeatedly making a choice between two food items displayed on the screen. It was explained that by pushing the mouse buttons (left or right) points could be earned for the food item displayed on the corresponding side of the screen. Participants were informed that every 10 points equals 10 g of the matching food and that they could trade their points for food afterward. They were also told that when the task proceeds it would get harder, but not impossible to earn points for one of the two options.</p>
<p>The task consisted of five rounds. Participants made a series of choices until 20 points in each round (high-calorie + low-calorie food points) were earned. The pictures of the high calorie (M&amp;M’s) and low calorie (white grapes) food items were displayed on the screen for each choice (the location of the high-calorie food was counterbalanced), and participants were instructed to press one of the mouse buttons corresponding to one of the food options. After each mouse click, participants received feedback whether they had earned a point or not. The foods were selected on the basis of a pilot study in which participants (<italic>n</italic> = 20) rated the palatability of these and 18 other food items (1 = <italic>not at all palatable at the moment</italic>, 9 = <italic>highly palatable at the moment</italic>). M&amp;M’s were rated as most palatable high-calorie food and matched with the low-calorie white grapes on palatability (<italic>M</italic>
<sub>M&amp;M’s</sub> = 5.60, <italic>SD</italic>
<sub>M&amp;M’s</sub> = 2.26 vs. <italic>M</italic>
<sub>white grapes</sub> = 5.90, <italic>SD</italic>
<sub>white grapes</sub> = 2.32, <italic>t</italic>(19) &lt; 1, <italic>p</italic> = .62).</p>
<p>In the first round, the difficulty to obtain the high-calorie and low-calorie foods were both fixed at two (fixed ratio of 2; FR2). This means that a point is earned after every two clicks on the same mouse button. During the whole task, the difficulty to obtain the low-calorie food stayed at FR2. However, the difficulty to obtain the high-calorie food doubled in every round (FR2, FR4, FR8, FR16, FR32). Thus, in the last round participants had to click on the same mouse button 32 times to earn 1 point for the high-calorie food. The task was similar to concurrent schedules tasks used in previous research (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1948550612471061">Giesen, Havermans, Nederkoorn, Strafaci, &amp; Jansen, 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1948550612471061">
<title>Chronic dieting</title>
<p>Chronic dieting was assessed with the Concern for Dieting subscale of the Revised Restraint scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1948550612471061">Herman &amp; Polivy, 1980</xref>). This scale has been used in previous research on eating behavior and has been recommended to identify participants’ chronic motivation to control their weight by dieting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1948550612471061">Blanchard &amp; Frost, 1983</xref>). The scale assesses the motivation to restrain eating by 6 items such as <italic>How often are you dieting?</italic> and <italic>How conscious are you of what you are eating?</italic> Participants also reported their body weight and height.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1948550612471061">
<title>Perceived self-regulatory success</title>
<p>Success in dieting was assessed with the 3-item scale developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1948550612471061">Fishbach et al. 2003</xref> (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1948550612471061">Meule et al., 2012</xref>, for a validation of this scale) by asking participants to indicate on a 7-point scale how successful they were in losing weight, watching their weight, and how difficult they found it to stay in shape (last item reverse coded).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1948550612471061">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>Participants completed the computerized session individually and started with the cue exposure task, presented as research on speed and accuracy in detecting letters. They then completed the behavioral task that was announced as a food game. After completing the chronic dieting and success in dieting scales, participants were debriefed. No participants indicated awareness of the words presented in the cue exposure task or guessed the hypothesis under investigation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1948550612471061">
<title>Results and Discussion</title>
<p>The number of responses for high-calorie food was analyzed in the general linear model (GLM) with difficulty to obtain the high-calorie food (FR2, FR4, FR8, FR16, FR32) as within-participant factor, cue exposure (food vs. control) as between-participants factor, and dieting and success (standardized) as continuous predictors. The analysis revealed a main effect of difficulty to obtain the high-calorie food, <italic>F</italic>(4, 332) = 3.69, <italic>p</italic> = .006, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .04, that was qualified by a significant Cue exposure × Difficulty × Dieting × Success interaction, <italic>F</italic>(4, 332) = 4.14, <italic>p</italic> = .003, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .05. To gain an insight into this interaction and to test our specific hypothesis that tempting food cues differentially affect unsuccessful and successful dieters, we investigated the effects of difficulty and cue exposure for dieters (1 <italic>SD</italic> above the mean of the chronic dieting scale; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1948550612471061">Aiken &amp; West, 1991</xref>) at two levels of success (i.e., unsuccessful at −1 <italic>SD</italic> and successful at +1 <italic>SD</italic> of the success scale; cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1948550612471061">Papies et al., 2008</xref>).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1948550612471061">1</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>For unsuccessful dieters, the analysis revealed a Cue exposure × Difficulty interaction, <italic>F</italic>(4, 332) = 2.26, <italic>p</italic> = .06, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .03 that just failed to reach significance. In the control-cue condition, no significant trends emerged (the quadratic trend had the smallest <italic>p</italic> value, <italic>F</italic>(1, 44) = 2.40, <italic>p</italic> = .13, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .05). In contrast, in the food-cue condition, the significant upward linear trend of difficulty, <italic>F</italic>(1, 39) = 5.35, <italic>p</italic> = .026, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .12, indicates that unsuccessful dieters increased working for high-calorie food points when the difficulty to obtain them increased (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1948550612471061">Figure 1A</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1948550612471061" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mean responses for high-calorie food for unsuccessful (A) and successful dieters (B) as a function of cue exposure condition and difficulty to obtain the high-calorie food (Study 1). FR (fixed ratio) reflects the number of responses required to earn one high-calorie food point.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1948550612471061-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The analysis for successful dieters revealed neither a main effect of difficulty, <italic>F</italic>(4, 332) = 1.47, <italic>p</italic> = .21, nor a significant Cue exposure × Difficulty interaction, <italic>F</italic> &lt; 1. Overall, the significant quadratic effect of difficulty, <italic>F</italic>(1, 83) = 6.63, <italic>p</italic> = .012, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .07, suggests that although successful dieters started to work to obtain high-calorie food points, this was attenuated as the difficulty to obtain them increased (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1948550612471061">Figure 1B</xref>). Thus, tempting food cues did not affect persistence and effort in obtaining high-calorie food points for successful dieters.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Results suggest that tempting food cues increase unsuccessful dieters’ effortful (i.e., goal-directed) behavior toward high-calorie food, as they increased working for high-calorie food following exposure to tempting food cues. In contrast, successful dieters did not work harder to obtain palatable food when exposed to tempting food. These findings are consistent with the idea that temptations trigger facilitative goal associations among successful self-regulators (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1948550612471061">Fishbach et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1948550612471061">Papies et al., 2008</xref>) which in turn prevent effortful behavior toward temptation-relevant objects.</p>
<p>We also predicted that temptation-elicited goal activation should make successful self-regulators more persistent and to invest more effort in obtaining objects instrumental for the long-term goal. Thus, tempting food cues should increase effortful behavior toward low-calorie food among successful dieters. In contrast, because temptations trigger inhibitory goal associations in unsuccessful self-regulators, we expected that food cues should not increase unsuccessful dieters’ effortful behavior toward low-calorie food. Because the difficulty to obtain the low-calorie food was not manipulated, we cannot infer this from the present study. In Study 2, we therefore tested these hypotheses by gradually increasing the difficulty to obtain the low-calorie food in the behavioral task, while holding the difficulty to obtain the high-calorie food constant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1948550612471061">
<title>Study 2</title>
<sec id="section15-1948550612471061" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section16-1948550612471061">
<title>Design and participants</title>
<p>Ninety-four students completed the study in return for course credit or a small fee. Inspection of the data, however, revealed seven influential outliers on the dependent measure (four participants’ data points had leverage values beyond 3 times the average; three participants had standardized residuals &gt;3 to &gt;5 <italic>SD</italic> above the mean; cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1948550612471061">Stevens, 2002</xref>). These participants were therefore excluded, and the final sample consisted of 87 participants (48 female; <italic>M</italic>
<sub>age</sub> = 21.25, <italic>SD</italic>
<sub>age</sub> = 3.02). The design was similar to Study 1 and participants were also assigned randomly to the cue exposure conditions.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1948550612471061">
<title>Materials, Measures, and Procedure</title>
<p>Participants were either exposed to tempting food or control cues using the same task as in Study 1. Afterward, effortful behavior toward low-calorie food was assessed with the concurrent schedules task. In contrast to Study 1, we now increased the difficulty to obtain the low-calorie food (i.e., it was doubled in every round: FR2, FR4, FR8, FR16, FR32), while the difficulty to obtain the high-calorie food stayed at FR2. This way, we could determine participants’ persistence and effort in obtaining low-calorie food when exposed to tempting food compared to a control condition. As in Study 1, participants then completed the chronic dieting and dieting success scales.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1948550612471061">
<title>Results and Discussion</title>
<p>As in Study 1, the number of responses for low-calorie food was analyzed in the GLM with difficulty to obtain the low-calorie food (FR2, FR4, FR8, FR16, FR32) as within-participant factor, cue exposure condition as between-participants factor, and dieting and success as continuous predictors. The analysis revealed a main effect of difficulty, <italic>F</italic>(4, 316) = 3.96, <italic>p</italic> = .004, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .05, and a Difficulty × Dieting interaction, <italic>F</italic>(4, 316) = 2.97, <italic>p</italic> = .020, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .04. However, these effects were qualified by a significant Cue exposure × Difficulty × Dieting × Success interaction, <italic>F</italic>(4, 316) = 2.69, <italic>p</italic> = .031, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .03.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1948550612471061">3</xref>
</sup> As in Study 1, we investigated this interaction further for dieters at two levels of success.</p>
<p>For unsuccessful dieters, the analysis revealed a main effect of difficulty, <italic>F</italic>(4, 316) = 5.19, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .06. Overall, the significant quadratic effect of difficulty, <italic>F</italic>(1, 79) = 17.77, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .18, suggests that although unsuccessful dieters started to work to obtain low-calorie food points, this was attenuated as the difficulty to obtain them increased (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1948550612471061">Figure 2A</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig2-1948550612471061" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mean responses for low-calorie food for unsuccessful (A) and successful dieters (B) as a function of cue exposure condition and difficulty to obtain the low-calorie food (Study 2). FR (fixed ratio) reflects the number of responses required to earn one low-calorie food point.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1948550612471061-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>For successful dieters, the analysis revealed a main effect of difficulty, <italic>F</italic>(4, 316) = 4.32, <italic>p</italic> = .002, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .05, and a significant Cue exposure × Difficulty interaction, <italic>F</italic>(4, 316) = 3.69, <italic>p</italic> = .006, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .05. While the analysis did not yield a significant trend effect of difficulty in the control-cue condition as can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1948550612471061">Figure 2B</xref>, the significant upward linear effect of difficulty in the food-cue condition, <italic>F</italic>(1, 39) = 11.25, <italic>p</italic> = .002, η<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1948550612471061">2</xref>
</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .22, indicates that successful dieters increased working when the difficulty to obtain the low-calorie food points increased. In contrast to unsuccessful dieters, tempting food cues thus increased working for low-calorie food points for successful dieters.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1948550612471061">4</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Results confirm our hypothesis that successful self-regulators become more persistent and invest more effort in obtaining objects instrumental for the long-term goal upon confrontation with temptations: Successful dieters increased working for low-calorie food when exposed to tempting food. In contrast, unsuccessful dieters’ efforts in obtaining low-calorie food were not influenced by the tempting food cues.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1948550612471061">
<title>General Discussion</title>
<p>Temptation cues generally frustrate people’s attainment of long-term goals. However, for successful self-regulators, temptations initiate, rather than inhibit, cognitive and motivational processes that should make it easier to resist temptations and attain long-term goals (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1948550612471061">Fishbach et al., 2003</xref>). While previous work has started to shed light on the cognitive features of this rise and fall of self-control, the present research examined important implications for actual behavior in the domain of dieting. In combining a cue exposure procedure with a concurrent schedules task, Study 1 showed that tempting food cues increased effortful behavior toward high-calorie food among unsuccessful, but not successful dieters. In contrast, Study 2 demonstrated that tempting food cues increased successful dieters’ efforts toward low-calorie food, but did not affect unsuccessful dieters. Together, these studies suggest that behavior in response to tempting food is goal-directed, even though temptations mobilize different patterns of physical effort that either undermine or facilitate dieters’ long-term goals.</p>
<p>The findings are consistent with the goal conflict model of eating (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1948550612471061">Stroebe et al., in press</xref>). This model proposes that tempting food cues inhibit the dieting goal and activate the eating enjoyment goal, especially in unsuccessful dieters. Accordingly, the eating enjoyment goal exerts more influence on subsequent behavior than the inhibited dieting goal, leading to failures in self-control. Unsuccessful dieters’ behavior in the present studies indeed suggests that our cue exposure procedure triggered inhibitory goal associations for those dieters and subsequently led to behavior undermining their long-term dieting goal. Incorporating work on temptation-elicited long-term goal activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1948550612471061">Fishbach et al., 2003</xref>), the goal conflict model additionally proposes that tempting food cues activate instead of inhibit the dieting goal for successful dieters, resulting in more motivational control over thought and action related to eating. Consistent with this, current results demonstrate that tempting food cues triggered behaviors facilitating the long-term dieting goal among successful dieters. This extends earlier work on temptation-elicited long-term goal activation that mainly focused on cognitive features and did not assess the moderating role of prior success when testing the behavioral consequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1948550612471061">Fishbach et al., 2003</xref>), or solely relied on self-report behavior measures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1948550612471061">Papies et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1948550612471061">Van Koningsbruggen et al., 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>In contrast to studies that assess food choice where behavior can reflect impulsive (i.e., the thoughtless choice of a preferred food item) as well as goal-directed behavior (i.e., the investment of effort in pursuit of calorific or dieting food), the use of a behavioral economics paradigm allows for making clearer inferences regarding goal-directed behavior. Results in the control conditions further suggest that without prior temptation, neither the eating enjoyment nor dieting goals are active before one is allowed to work for food. However, once goals are activated through repeated exposure to tempting food cues, successful and unsuccessful dieters mobilize different patterns of physical effort toward food that are either harmful or beneficial for self-control. The fact that they invest a great deal of effort over an extended period of time suggests that their behavior is goal-directed rather than reflecting an impulsive response. Although this has long been assumed for behavior in the service of the dieting goal, it fits less with theoretical assumptions made about behavior in pursuit of eating enjoyment in the context of dual system theories (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1948550612471061">Hofmann et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1948550612471061">Strack &amp; Deutsch, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>In conclusion, applied to the domain of dieting behavior, the present approach demonstrated how temptation-goal associations influence effortful behavior toward temptation and long-term goal-relevant objects among successful and unsuccessful self-regulators. As such, it not only provides insight into the intriguing issue of why some dieters are more successful than others, but also, more generally, directly demonstrates the implications of temptation-elicited goal activation on people’s effortful goal-directed behavior.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>We thank Janneke Giesen and Remco Havermans for providing us with the computerized concurrent schedules task. We also thank Niek Strohmaier for his assistance in data collection.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn5-1948550612471061">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn6-1948550612471061">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: The work in this article was financially supported by a grant (ZonMw grant 121520001) from the Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<title>Notes</title>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1948550612471061">
<label>1</label>
<p>This estimation procedure in the GLM allows for testing our hypotheses without conducting median splits, thus retaining all observations in the analyses.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1948550612471061">
<label>2</label>
<p>Since normal eaters are not trying to diet, a distinction according to dieting success seems irrelevant. Nevertheless, we also investigated the cue exposure effects for normal eaters. For successful normal eaters, results revealed no significant effects. For unsuccessful normal eaters, results revealed a Cue exposure × Difficulty interaction, <italic>F</italic>(4, 332) = 3.04, <italic>p</italic> = .018, η<sup>2</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .04. In the control condition, there were no significant trends. In the food-cue condition, the significant quadratic effect of difficulty, <italic>F</italic>(1, 39) = 19.86, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, η<sup>2</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic> = .34, suggests that although unsuccessful normal eaters started to work for high-calorie food, this was attenuated as the difficulty increased. These findings are consistent with research showing that normal eaters downregulate their initial hedonic response over time, while dieters do not (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1948550612471061">Hofmann et al., 2010</xref>) and the goal conflict model that assumes that normal eaters are less influenced by tempting food cues.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1948550612471061">
<label>3</label>
<p>In both studies, participants also rated the palatability of the foods (1 = <italic>not at all palatable</italic>, 9 = <italic>highly palatable</italic>) and indicated their hunger level (1 = <italic>not at all hungry</italic>, 7 = <italic>extremely hungry</italic>). Age, sex, chronic dieting, success, BMI, palatability, and hunger scores did not differ between conditions in Study 1, <italic>F</italic>s &lt; 1–1.97, <italic>p</italic>s = .93–.16, all η<sup>2</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic>s &lt; .03, and Study 2, all <italic>F</italic>s &lt; 1, <italic>p</italic>s = .94–.57, all η<sup>2</sup>
<italic>
<sub>p</sub>
</italic>s &lt; .01. Furthermore, the observed Cue exposure × Difficulty × Dieting × Success interactions remained significant when controlling for age, sex, BMI, palatability, or hunger scores.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1948550612471061">
<label>4</label>
<p>The analyses for unsuccessful and successful normal eaters did not reveal significant effects.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aiken</surname>
<given-names>L. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>West</surname>
<given-names>S. G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Multiple regression: Testing and interpreting interactions</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Blanchard</surname>
<given-names>F. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frost</surname>
<given-names>R. O.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Two factors of restraint: Concern for dieting and weight fluctuation</article-title>. <source>Behaviour Research and Therapy</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/0005-7967(83)90208-5</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brunstrom</surname>
<given-names>J. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yates</surname>
<given-names>H. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Witcomb</surname>
<given-names>G. L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Dietary restraint and heightened reactivity to food</article-title>. <source>Physiology and Behavior</source>, <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/j.physbeh.2004.01.001</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carver</surname>
<given-names>C. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Scheier</surname>
<given-names>M. F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>On the self-regulation of behavior</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fedoroff</surname>
<given-names>I. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Polivy</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Herman</surname>
<given-names>C. P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The effect of pre-exposure to food cues on the eating behavior of restrained and unrestrained eaters</article-title>. <source>Appetite</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1006/appe.1996.0057</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Finucane</surname>
<given-names>M. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stevens</surname>
<given-names>G. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cowan</surname>
<given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Danaei</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>J. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Paciorek</surname>
<given-names>C. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ezzati</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>National, regional, and global trends in body-mass index since 1980: Systematic analysis of health examination surveys and epidemiological studies with 960 country-years and 9·1 million participants</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source>, <volume>377</volume>, <fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>567</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(10)62037-5</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fishbach</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ferguson</surname>
<given-names>M. F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The goal construct in social psychology</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Kruglanski</surname>
<given-names>A. W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Higgins</surname>
<given-names>T. E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Social psychology: Handbook of basic principles</source> (pp. <fpage>490</fpage>–<lpage>515</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fishbach</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Friedman</surname>
<given-names>R. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kruglanski</surname>
<given-names>A. W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Leading us not unto temptation: Momentary allurements elicit overriding goal activation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>296</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1037/0022-3514.84.2.296</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fishbach</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Trope</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Counteractive evaluation: Asymmetric shifts in the implicit value of conflicting motivation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/j.jesp.2009.09.008</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Giesen</surname>
<given-names>J. C. A. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Havermans</surname>
<given-names>R. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nederkoorn</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Strafaci</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jansen</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Working harder to obtain more snack foods when wanting to eat less</article-title>. <source>Behaviour Research and Therapy</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/j.brat.2008.09.007</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>J. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bargh</surname>
<given-names>J. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brownell</surname>
<given-names>K. D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Priming effects of television food advertising on eating behavior</article-title>. <source>Health Psychology</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>404</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1037/a0014399</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Herman</surname>
<given-names>C. P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Polivy</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Restrained eating</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Stunkard</surname>
<given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Obesity</source> (pp. <fpage>208</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Saunders</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hofmann</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Friese</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wiers</surname>
<given-names>R. W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Impulsive versus reflective influences on health behavior: A theoretical framework and empirical review</article-title>. <source>Health Psychology Review</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1080/17437190802617668</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hofmann</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Van Koningsbruggen</surname>
<given-names>G. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stroebe</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ramanathan</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aarts</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>As pleasure unfolds: Hedonic responses to tempting food</article-title>. <source>Psychological Science</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1863</fpage>–<lpage>1870</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1177/0956797610389186</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jansen</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Van den Hout</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>On being led into temptation: “Counterregulation” of dieters after smelling a “preload”</article-title>. <source>Addictive Behaviors</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/0306-4603(91)90017-C</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kruger</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Galuska</surname>
<given-names>D. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Serdula</surname>
<given-names>M. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>D. A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Attempting to lose weight: Specific practices among U.S. adults</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/j.amepre.2004.02.001</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>LeGoff</surname>
<given-names>D. B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spigelman</surname>
<given-names>M. N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Salivary response to olfactory food stimuli as a function of dietary restraint and body weight</article-title>. <source>Appetite</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/S0195-6663(87)80024-7</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mann</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tomiyama</surname>
<given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Westling</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lew</surname>
<given-names>A. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Samuels</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chatman</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Medicare’s search for effective obesity treatments: Diets are not the answer</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1037/0003-066X.62.3.220</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Metcalfe</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mischel</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>A hot/cool-system analysis of delay of gratification: Dynamics of willpower</article-title>. <source>Psychological Review</source>, <volume>106</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Meule</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Papies</surname>
<given-names>E. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kübler</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Differentiating between successful and unsuccessful dieters: Validity and reliability of the perceived self-regulatory success in dieting scale</article-title>. <source>Appetite</source>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>822</fpage>–<lpage>826</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/j.appet.2012.01.028</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Papies</surname>
<given-names>E. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stroebe</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aarts</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Pleasure in the mind: Restrained eating and spontaneous hedonic thoughts about food</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>810</fpage>–<lpage>817</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/j.jesp.2006.08.001</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Papies</surname>
<given-names>E. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stroebe</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aarts</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Healthy cognition: Processes of self-regulatory success in restrained eating</article-title>. <source>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>1290</fpage>–<lpage>1300</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1177/0146167208320063</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>P. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hill</surname>
<given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Breakdown of dietary restraint following mere exposure to food stimuli: Interrelationships between restraint, hunger, salivation, and food intake</article-title>. <source>Addictive Behaviors</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/0306-4603(89)90026-9</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Saelens</surname>
<given-names>B. E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Epstein</surname>
<given-names>L. H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Reinforcing value of food in obese and non-obese women</article-title>. <source>Appetite</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1006/appe.1996.0032</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stevens</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Applied multivariate statistics for the social sciences</source> (<edition>4th ed</edition>.). <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Strack</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Deutsch</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Reflective and impulsive determinants of social behavior</article-title>. <source>Personality and Social Psychology Review</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stroebe</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mensink</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aarts</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schut</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kruglanski</surname>
<given-names>A. W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Why dieters fail: Testing the goal conflict model of eating</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/j.jesp.2007.01.005</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stroebe</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Van Koningsbruggen</surname>
<given-names>G. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Papies</surname>
<given-names>E. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aarts</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>in press</year>). <article-title>Why most dieters fail but some succeed: A goal conflict model of eating behavior</article-title>. <source>Psychological Review</source>. Advance online publication. doi: 10.1037/a0030849</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tepper</surname>
<given-names>B. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Dietary restraint and responsiveness to sensory-based food cues as measured by cephalic phase salivation and sensory specific satiety</article-title>. <source>Physiology and Behavior</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/0031-9384(92)90276-8</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Trope</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fishbach</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Counteractive self-control in overcoming temptation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>506</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1037//0022-3514.79.4.493</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1948550612471061">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Van Koningsbruggen</surname>
<given-names>G. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stroebe</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Papies</surname>
<given-names>E. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aarts</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Implementation intentions as goal primes: Boosting self-control in tempting environments</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Social Psychology</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>557</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1002/ejsp.799</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>