<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="abstract">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EEG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">speeg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical EEG and Neuroscience</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1550-0594</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1550059412471275</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1550059412471275</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Abstracts</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Abstracts From Presentations at the Joint Meeting of the EEG and Clinical Neuroscience Society (ECNS), the International Society for Brain Electromagnetic Topography (ISBET), the International Society for Neuroimaging in Psychiatry (ISNIP), and the Evoked Potentials International Conference (EPIC) in Bristol, Tennessee, USA, September 12-15, 2012</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>44</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>70</fpage>
<lpage>86</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© EEG and Clinical Neuroscience Society (ECNS) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">EEG and Clinical Neuroscience Society</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1550059412471275">
<title>Keynote Speaker</title>
<sec id="section2-1550059412471275">
<title>The Challenging Realities of Personalized Medicine in Brain Disorders</title>
<sec id="section3-1550059412471275">
<title>Evian Gordon<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>CEO and Chairman, Brain Resource, San Francisco, CA, USA</p>
<p>Personalized Medicine seeks to move away from the current trial and error approach to matching the biological characteristics of each person with the best medication and dose for them. Most Personalized Medicine research in Psychiatry using molecular measures alone have failed to replicate. Therefore, there are now growing efforts expanding Genomic Biomarkers in Psychiatry and Neurology to Neuroimaging (all Brain-based biological and cognitive measures). The goal is to shed light on biologically relevant characteristics (biomarkers, circuits and temporal dynamics) of the patient and then increasingly elucidate which of these predict a specific treatment response. This presentation outlines the role of a platform including a standardized large International Database of norms and 10 brain disorders to confirm/disconfirm Biomarker treatment predictions.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1550059412471275">
<title>Symposia</title>
<sec id="section5-1550059412471275">
<title>Autonomic Changes and Epileptiform Processes in Unipolar Depressive Patients</title>
<sec id="section6-1550059412471275">
<title>Petr Bob<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Charles University, Prague, Czech Republic</p>
<p>Clinical evidence indicates that anti-epileptic treatment is useful in some patients with unipolar depression, and specific influence of stress with potential effects on epileptiform activity in temporo-limbic structures may play a role. In this context, there is a lack of clear evidence that could provide a method for indication of anticonvulsant treatment. In the light of current findings, the temporo-limbic seizure-like symptoms that appear also in nonepileptic conditions with indirect clinical=manifestations may occur in a form of various forms of cognitive, affective, memory, sensory behavioral and somatic symptoms (the so-called complex partial seizure-like symptoms). Presented psychophysiological findings indicate that non-linear characteristics (transinformation and Lyapunov Exponents) calculated from bilateral electrodermal activity (EDA) during rest and Heart Rate Variability (HRV) during incongruent Stroop task could reflect epileptiform changes because of spreading of the epileptiform activity into autonomic nervous system, which may reflect specific cognitive and affective changes related to occurrence of complex seizure-like symptoms in depressive patients.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1550059412471275">
<title>Predictive Value of isolated Epileptiform Discharges for a Favorable Therapeutic Response to Antiepileptic Drugs in Non-epileptic Patients</title>
<sec id="section8-1550059412471275">
<title>Nash Boutros<sup>1</sup> and Sandra Kirollos<sup>2</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Department of Psychiatry, Wayne State University, Detroit, MI, USA</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ, USA</p>
<p>It has been questioned whether psychiatric patients who do not experience seizures but have isolated epileptiform discharges (IEDs) should be treated with anti-epileptic drugs (AEDs). Thus, the purpose of this review is to assess available evidence regarding the efficacy of AEDs on behavioral symptoms in non-epileptic psychiatric patients. While IEDs have been reported in many psychiatric conditions, they are most commonly observed in patients with repeated aggression, panic attacks or are diagnosed with an autistic spectrum disorder (ASD). We limited our search to these three disorders because of the higher likelihood of finding controlled treatment studies. For panic disorder, four case reports, four case series, and one controlled study were found. For aggression, we identified three case reports, two case series, and three controlled studies. For ASD, there were two case reports, three case series, and two controlled studies. Overall, all case reports and case series and most controlled studies show that use of an AED is associated with clinical and at times improved EEG abnormalities. Most studies show that psychiatric symptoms, in patients with EEG abnormalities, improved when an AED was used for treatment even in the absence of frank seizures. Overall, the use of an anticonvulsant to treat non-epileptic psychiatric patients seems promising. The literature remains extremely limited, and many more well-designed and controlled studies are necessary.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1550059412471275">
<title>Neurophysiological Studies of Auditory Verbal Hallucinations: Committee Report from the International Consortium on Hallucinations</title>
<sec id="section10-1550059412471275">
<title>Judith Ford<sup>1</sup>, Daniel Mathalon<sup>1</sup>, Thomas Dierks<sup>2</sup>, Derek Fisher<sup>3</sup>, Christopher Herrmann<sup>4</sup>, Daniela Huble<sup>5</sup>, Jochen Kindler<sup>5</sup>, Thomas Koenig<sup>5</sup>, Werner Strik<sup>5</sup>, and Remko van Lutterveld<sup>6</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>San Francisco VA Medical Center, UCSF, San Francisco, CA, USA</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>University Hospital of Psychiatry, University of Bern, Switzerland</p>
<p><sup>3</sup>Dept of Psychology, Mount Saint Vincent University, University of Ottawa, Canada</p>
<p><sup>4</sup>Carl von Ossietzky University, Oldenburg, Germany</p>
<p><sup>5</sup>University Hospital of Psychiatry, University of Bern, Switzerland</p>
<p><sup>6</sup>University Medical Center, Rudolf Magnus Institute of Neuroscience, Utrecht, the Netherlands</p>
<p>Three approaches are discussed to study auditory verbal hallucinations (AVH) using EEG (electroencephalography) and MEG (magnetoencephalography). First, describe state (or symptom capture) studies where periods with and without hallucinations are compared, within a patient. Data point to frontal and temporal lobe activity, the latter resulting in competition with external sounds for auditory resources. Second, discuss trait studies where EEG and MEG responses to external sounds of hallucinators are compared to non-hallucinators. A tendency to hallucinate is associated with competition for auditory processing resources. Third, discuss mechanistic studies, including aberrant spontaneous neural activity, self-monitoring, and interregional communication. Most studies show differences in between patients and controls, but far fewer show symptom relationships. Efforts to understand the pathophysiology of AVH using EEG and MEG have been hindered by poor anatomical resolution of the EEG and MEG, poor assessment of symptoms, poor understanding of the phenomenon, poor models of the phenomenon, decoupling of the symptoms from the neurophysiology due to medications and comorbidities, and the possibility that the schizophrenia diagnosis breeds truer than the symptoms it comprises. These problems are common to studies of other psychiatric symptoms and should be considered when attempting to understand the basic neural mechanisms responsible for them.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1550059412471275">
<title>Symptom Oriented Approach in Psychiatric Research: Contributions from Brain Imaging and Electrophysiology</title>
<sec id="section12-1550059412471275">
<title>Silvana Galderisi<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Department of Psychiatry, University of Naples SUN, Naples, Italy</p>
<p>In spite of good evidence of reliability and clinical utility, scientists and clinicians are increasingly aware that several shortcomings hinder the validity of current psychiatric classifications. Even the Kraepelinian dichotomy has been called into question, and it has been suggested that it may be hindering the progress of neurobiological research in major psychiatric disorders. As a matter of fact, decades of neurobiological research based on current nosography provided limited contribution to both diagnosis and treatment that, in the absence of valid biological markers, are still largely based on the identification of clinical symptoms. The symptom-oriented approach adopted by brain imaging and electrophysiological studies was initially aimed to improve knowledge on pathophysiology of signs and symptoms of mental disorders by identifying the dysfunctional brain regions underlying each psychopathological phenomenon. However, most studies converged to demonstrate that psychopathological phenomena, as well as many cognitive dysfunctions, result from the failure to integrate the activity of different brain areas, thus highlighting the importance of focusing on networks, instead of individual regions, and on interactions and dynamics, instead of static abnormalities. Brain imaging and electrophysiological studies have also highlighted the need of an in-depth re-thinking of psychopathological constructs.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1550059412471275">
<title>Brain-Computer Interface Design for Widespread Use</title>
<sec id="section14-1550059412471275">
<title>Jane E. Huggins<sup>1</sup>, David E. Thompson<sup>2</sup>, Stefanie Blain-Moraes<sup>3</sup>, Patricia A. Wren<sup>4</sup>, Kirsten L. Gruis<sup>5</sup>, and Riley Schaff<sup>6</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Departments of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation and Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA</p>
<p><sup>3</sup>Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA</p>
<p><sup>4</sup>School of Health Sciences, Oakland University, Rochester, MI, USA</p>
<p><sup>5</sup>Department of Neurology, State University of New York Upstate Medical University, Syracuse, NY, USA</p>
<p><sup>6</sup>Department of Biology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA</p>
<p>In-home studies of brain-computer interfaces (BCIs) with a few applications show promise. However, translation of BCIs to widespread use requires understanding the BCI design priorities of potential users and creating BCIs to meet them. Our survey of 61 people with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) revealed degrees of acceptance of non-invasive and implanted electrodes, minimum desired BCI performance, and widespread interest in BCIs for different tasks. While perceived importance of BCI features varied by degree of disability, there were few differences in desired performance standards. A BCI was created to operate as a plug-and-play keyboard replacement and tested in laboratory use by people with ALS. BCI performance was slightly lower for this group than for controls. The BCI was functional, however, for stand-alone use and as a keyboard replacement on a computer or communication device. Plug-and-play compatibility allows any keyboard-operated device to be BCI-operated without modification, expanding devices available to BCI users and allowing BCIs to smoothly replace physical interfaces as ALS progresses. In a focus group on how BCIs might fit into their daily lives, people with ALS and their caregivers voiced interest in BCIs as potential enabling devices and proposed design improvements in most aspects of BCI design. Current and potential BCI users must be involved in all aspects of BCI research and development if BCIs are to make the transition to widespread use.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1550059412471275">
<title>Use of Quantitative EEG and Nuclear Medicine in Assessment of Psychiatric Patients with Sharp Waves</title>
<sec id="section16-1550059412471275">
<title>Lukasz M. Konopka<sup>1</sup> and Elizabeth M. Zimmerman<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>The Chicago School of Professional Psychology and Department of Psychiatry, Loyola University, Chicago, IL, USA</p>
<p>Patients presenting to neuropsychiatric practices often seek out this specialty as a consequence of unsuccessful therapeutic interventions by other practitioners. Utilization of quantitative EEG (qEEG) as an objective tool, which provides description of electrophysiological brain features, shows significant promise. Based on an outpatient clinical population evaluated with qEEG, we identified 71 patients out of a total of 250 who showed sub-epileptic brain activity. These patients are often treated for other behaviorally defined conditions that may exacerbate brain dysregulation. Furthermore, these patients are often referred for further neurodiagnostic evaluation that includes nuclear medicine studies. A combined qEEG and nuclear medicine approach provides for a better understanding of brain pathology and involvement of brain regions and appropriate networks. In all case studies presented, multi-imaging studies resulted in alteration of diagnoses and led to modification of therapeutic intervention, ultimately resulting in improvement of clinical outcome.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1550059412471275">
<title>Unlocking the Locked-In Detection of Consciousness and Communication in Non-responsive Patients</title>
<sec id="section18-1550059412471275">
<title>Andrea Kubler<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>University of Wurzburg, Wurzburg, Germany</p>
<p>Injury or disease may damage the brain and lead to the so-called locked-in state in which no communication is possible. This non-responsive state may be due to a loss of consciousness such as seen in the vegetative state or complete motor paralysis as in the locked-in syndrome after stroke or as a consequence of a neurodegenerative disease. Phenomenologically, these patients look alike, however, their level of consciousness is quite different. Diagnosis in non-responsive patients relies mainly on overt motor behavior and is thus error-prone if patients are consciously aware, but unable to move. New paradigms on the basis of evoked potentials as measured with EEG and imagery and executive functioning as measured with fMRI provide the possibility to better determine the level of consciousness. Passive paradigms which require passive listening only may elucidate basic and higher cognitive function. Active paradigms which elicit a brain response only when subjects follow the respective task relevant command allow us to unequivocally conclude whether a patient is consciously aware. Brain-computer interface (BCI) provides the possibility to use the active brain response for simple yes-no communication. The challenge for detecting consciousness and communication with BCI is to deal with the altered brain responses in non-responsive patients and the possibly short attention span, which necessitates short trial time and few repetitive stimulations within the mostly auditory paradigms. New developments in BCI that facilitate its use in daily life and improve reliability may facilitate communication when consciousness is detected.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1550059412471275">
<title>Future Imaging Modalities: Detecting Activity-Evoked pH Changes in Human Brain</title>
<sec id="section20-1550059412471275">
<title>Vincent A. Magnotta<sup>1</sup>, Hye Young Heo<sup>1</sup>, Casey P. Johnson<sup>1</sup>, and John A. Wemmie<sup>2</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Department of Radiology, The University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA, USA</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>Department of Psychiatry, The University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA, USA</p>
<p>While pH changes have been suggested to occur with brain function, a limited number of tools exist to measure pH dynamics with sufficient temporal and spatial resolution. We have recently evaluated a magnetic resonance imaging technique, T1 relaxation in the rotating frame (T1rho) as a tool that is sensitive to detecting pH changes evoked by changing the concentration of inhaled CO2. This work was also extended to evaluate pH changes associated with a visual activation task. Other functional imaging techniques employing BOLD, 1H, and 31P were obtained using the same task. The results showed that the T1rho; imaging was sufficiently sensitive to detect widespread acidosis associated with CO2 inhalation. In addition, the imaging sequence showed an increase in the estimated T1rho time associated with visual checkerboard suggesting a local acidosis. 31P spectroscopy showed a corresponding acidosis within the visual cortex, and 1H showed an increased lactate concentration. In a blood phantom, the T1rho sequence was not sensitive to blood oxygenation. This study suggests that a local acidosis occurs with brain function that can be potentially measured using MRI techniques. It also suggests that T1rho imaging can serve as a novel functional imaging technique that is able to access pH dynamics in vivo. A number of psychiatric disorders may have abnormalities in pH regulation, and this imaging technique may provide novel insight into the neurobiology of these disorders.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-1550059412471275">
<title>Independent Home Use of a P300-Based Brain-Computer Interface System by People Severely Disabled by Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</title>
<sec id="section22-1550059412471275">
<title>L.M. McCane<sup>1</sup>, J.R. Wolpaw<sup>1</sup>, S.M. Heckman<sup>1,2</sup>, D.J. McFarland<sup>1,</sup>, C.S. Carmack<sup>1,</sup>, S. Winden<sup>1,</sup>, E.W. Sellers<sup>2</sup>, D.E. Corda<sup>1,3</sup>, D. Zeitlin<sup>3</sup>, L.M. Tenteromano<sup>3</sup>, and T.M. Vaughan<sup>1,3</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Wadsworth Center, Albany, NY, USA</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>East Tennessee State University, Johnson City, TN, USA</p>
<p><sup>3</sup>Helen Hayes Rehabilitation Hospital-New York State Department of Health, West Haverstraw, NY, USA</p>
<p>Wadsworth Center personnel have been conducting Brain-Computer Interface (BCI) research since the late 1980s, with the objective of restoring communication and control to those with severe neuromuscular disabilities. As part of this work, we have begun over the past 7 years to translate a basic P300-based BCI system (BCIHome) into home use by people severely disabled by ALS. In the course of this work, we have developed and deployed: protocols for evaluating prospective users, their caregivers, and their living environments for BCI use; training procedures and manuals for users and caregivers; a suite of useful BCI applications; and Internet-based routines for remote oversight, parameter-updating, and data collection. To date, over 50 prospective home users have been evaluated for BCI use; ten BCIHome systems have been installed; and these systems have been used for as long as six years to date. The results indicate that the Wadsworth BCIHome system can function reliably for independent home use, and that it can provide useful communication to those whose severe neuromuscular disabilities make it difficult or impossible for them to benefit from conventional (i.e., muscle-based) assistive communication technology. Areas for continued study and further improvement include: methods for increasing system reliability; more convenient electrode application; methods for increasing communication rate; and auditory (or other non-visual) BCI operation for those with impaired vision.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-1550059412471275">
<title>Event-Related Indices of Hyperarousal and Impulsivity in Subjects with Bulimia Nervosa</title>
<sec id="section24-1550059412471275">
<title>Armida Mucci<sup>1</sup>, Silvana Galderisi<sup>1</sup>, Eleonora Merlotti<sup>1</sup>, Valentina Montefusco<sup>1</sup>, Annarita Vignapiano<sup>1</sup>, and Mario Maj<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Department of Psychiatry, University of Naples SUN, Naples, Italy</p>
<p>Bulimia nervosa [BN] is associated with a deficit of self-regulatory control and impulsivity. The present study was aimed to clarify whether impulsivity in BN subjects is related to hyperarousal, which impairs inhibitory control. Event-related potentials were recorded in 17 female patients with BN and 17 healthy controls, during a three-tone oddball task. ERP components related to response inhibition, effortful and automatic processing were analyzed. ERP topography and tomography were analyzed by means of the microstate and LORETA techniques. BN patients, with respect to healthy controls, showed reduced amplitude and shorter latency of the N200; increased amplitude and shorter latency of the target SW; higher activity of the distracter P300 generators in left fronto-parietal-temporal cortex and bilateral cingulate; lower activity of the target SW generators in right frontal gyrus, left parieto-temporal regions, and bilateral cingulate. The reduction of N2 latency was associated with the Barratt scores for impulsiveness. The observed electrophysiological abnormalities suggest a condition of hyperarousal, with impaired suppression of irrelevant stimuli due to abnormal cortical activation, with reduced signal-to-noise ratio. Our tomographic findings point to functional abnormalities within a neural system that subserves self-regulatory control, which may contribute to binge-eating and other impulsive behaviors in BN.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-1550059412471275">
<title>Molecular Imaging and Neurophysiology in Psychiatry: Clinical Relevance for Diagnosis and Treatment</title>
<sec id="section26-1550059412471275">
<title>Oliver Pogarell<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Department of Psychiatry, University of Munich, Germany</p>
<p>The neurobiological characterization of psychiatric disorders is a major issue in psychiatry. Pathophysiological hypotheses with respect to brain activity or brain neurochemistry provide the scientific background for the development of differential treatment strategies and the evaluation of the course of the disorder under treatment. The assessment of both brain electric and neurochemical activity using neurophysiology or neuroimaging tools can help to characterize distinct psychiatric disorders and consequently to monitor neurobiological effects of treatments. The combination of different methods provides complementary information, contributing to the validation of pathophysiological concepts relevant for diagnostic and treatment decisions. Both neurophysiological and functional neuroimaging techniques have been used to discriminate diagnostic and therapeutic subgroups of neuropsychiatric patients and have been assessed regarding prognostic and predictive properties. Studies in patients with depression, obsessive compulsive disorder, addiction or emotional instability provide evidence of different pathophysiological mechanisms between both categories and symptom dimensions, which may be relevant regarding the course of the disorders under treatment.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-1550059412471275">
<title>Auditory Cortical Stimulus Processing and Molecular Imaging in Psychiatry: Monitoring Pharmacotherapy in Patients with Major Depression</title>
<sec id="section28-1550059412471275">
<title>Oliver Pogarell<sup>1</sup>, Susanne Karch<sup>1</sup>, and Felix Segmiller<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Department of Psychiatry, University of Munich, Germany</p>
<p>The neurobiological characterization of psychiatric disorders may improve diagnostic and therapeutic decisions. Neurophysiology and molecular imaging techniques can be used to indirectly assess central monoaminergic functions providing a neurochemical characterization of patients with psychiatric disorders. Loudness dependence of auditory evoked potentials and Beta-CIT-SPECT were used to investigate patients with major depression before and under treatment with selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors. Patients with major depression were included in a four week treatment study with escitalopram. Neurophysiology and imaging studies were performed at baseline and under treatment. While the loudness dependence of auditory evoked potentials remained comparatively stable under the course of treatment, molecular imaging with Beta-CIT showed a decrease in serotonin transporter availability and an increase in dopamine transporter availability. In terms of dopamine transporter availability, there were differences between responders and non-responders. Antidepressive medication and change in clinical symptoms did not appear to significantly modify auditory cortical stimulus processing in major depression. However, the combination with molecular imaging techniques might lead to clinically and therapeutically relevant results.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-1550059412471275">
<title>N400 and Thought Disorder in Schizophrenia</title>
<sec id="section30-1550059412471275">
<title>Dean F. Salisbury<sup>1</sup> and Maya Libben<sup>2</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Western Psychiatric Institute and Clinic, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, PA, USA</p>
<p><sup>2 </sup>McLean Hospital, Department of Psychiatry, Belmont, MA, USA</p>
<p>A primary symptom of schizophrenia is thought disorder. Formal thought disorder includes deficits in speech production and language processing. These defects in thinking are reflected in abnormal speech; not only in what is said, but how it is said. The N400 event-related potential is especially sensitive to language processing, particularly in how current information is activated in semantic memory and integrated with contextual memory. Thus, N400 may serve as an index of dysfunction in the mechanisms underlying thought disorder. Our activation-maintenance model of thought disorder posits hyperactivation in semantic memory and increased decay and underutilization of contextual representations. Our work has shown that N400 is increased in schizophrenia to weak associates that depend on context for disambiguation, and that patients appear to underutilize right hemisphere contextual mechanisms. Using masked stimuli, we demonstrate that semantic memory show hyperpriming, that in turn correlates with the degree of thought disorder. Finally, we show that N400 is reduced in first hospitalized subjects, suggesting it may be a useful tool for detection of the schizophrenia prodrome before first hospitalization.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section31-1550059412471275">
<title>Brain-Computer Interface: A Longitudinal Investigation</title>
<sec id="section32-1550059412471275">
<title>E.W. Sellers<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>East Tennessee State University, Johnson City TN, USA</p>
<p>Brain-computer interface (BCI) provides an alternative method of communication that does not depend on traditional neuromuscular pathways (e.g., speech). People with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) can eventually become locked-in to their bodies. Thus, normal output channels are no longer available for communication. The P300 BCI extracts event-related potentials (ERPs) from the ongoing EEG and uses the ERPs to classify characters as desired or non-desired choices. As such, the BCI emulates a “virtual keyboard,” using EEG as the control signal. Using a longitudinal design, the relationships between power spectra for a resting state and a mental arithmetic task, the canonical Oddball response, BCI performance, and the ALSFRS-r (i.e., an instrument used to track disease progression) are examined. Nine patients are enrolled in the study and data are collected in intervals of eight weeks. Alpha power is higher in the resting state, P300 responses have remained stable, mean BCI copy spelling accuracy is 94.4%, and ALSFRS-r scores have decreased by 2.8 points. Overall, the results suggest that BCI performance remains stable as disease progression continues. Additional data is needed to determine whether the measures remain stable over time. Ideally BCI performance and other measures will not change as ALSFRS-r continues to decrease.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section33-1550059412471275">
<title>Biological Psychopathology: An Attempt to Match Psychiatric Symptoms in Brain Systems</title>
<sec id="section34-1550059412471275">
<title>Werner Strik<sup>1</sup> and Thomas Dierks<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>University Hospital of Psychiatry, University of Bern, Switzerland</p>
<p>In auditory hallucinations, thought and motor disorders, characteristical psychotic symptoms were linked to disorders of specific brain systems. To substantiate an empirically falsifiable neurobiological concept of psychotic symptom domains, a clinical rating scale (Bern Psychopathology Scale for Psychoses, BPS; Strik et al, 2010) was developed and validated. Each symptom was referred to the language, the limbic and the motor system, and to the respective normal psychic function in terms of a positive or negative deviation. The symptom distribution assessed with the BPS supported the presence of three symptom dimensions. Furthermore, we found hyperperfusion and reduced grey matter in Wernicke’s area linked to formal thought between volume and fractional anisotropy of the right SMA with motor retardation. The results of our clinical and imaging studies support the presence of clusters of psychotic symptoms which are related to structural and metabolic abnormalities of specific brain systems, relevant for human behavior and communication. Providing a new, systematic perspective on Bleuler’s dissociation, these symptom domains are unequally affected in different patients, but not mutually exclusive. Recent studies based on this systematic approach show that new, meaningful results can be obtained building subgroups according to systems-specific symptom domains.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section35-1550059412471275">
<title>Single and Multiple Epileptiform Foci in Psychiatric Patients: Implications for Clinical Symptom Severity</title>
<sec id="section36-1550059412471275">
<title>Elizabeth M. Zimmerman<sup>1</sup> and Lukasz M. Konopka<sup>1,2</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>The Chicago School of Professional Psychology, Chicago, IL, USA</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>Loyola University, Chicago, IL, USA</p>
<p>Patients with focal epileptiform abnormalities may present with different clinical symptomatology based on how this activity is distributed throughout the brain. The involvement of homologous electrode pairs may indicate a neuroprotective function of sharp wave activity in the recruitment of resources along neuronal networks. At the same time, isolated, single-focus epileptiform activity may suggest disconnection or desynchronization from neuronal networks and manifest in more problematic clinical behaviors. This presentation reviews EEG data and clinical symptoms in a sample of psychiatric patients at a community-based clinic. Findings suggest that patients with single-focus epileptiform abnormalities are much more likely than patients with homologous foci to present with greater emotional deregulation and to endorse severe symptoms such as suicidal and homicidal ideation, self-injurious behaviors, dissociation and/or psychosis, history of psychiatric hospitalization and history of previous suicidal attempt(s). These results provide implications for diagnosis and treatment of psychiatric patients with epileptiform activities.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section37-1550059412471275">
<title>Plenary Lecture</title>
<sec id="section38-1550059412471275">
<title>Topography of ERPs Elicited During Stroop Tasks Reveals Differences Between Males and Females</title>
<sec id="section39-1550059412471275">
<title>W. Skrandies<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Institute of Physiology, Justus-Liebig University, Giessen, Germany</p>
<p>Earlier reports show that stimulus compatibility is reflected in ERPs at early latencies originating from primary visual areas. We investigated the topography of ERPS recorded from 20 adult females and 20 adult males who processed compatible and non-compatible color words. Stimuli were presented in random order on a computer monitor. For control a conventional checkerboard reversal VEP was measured. EEG was recorded from 30 channels between Oz and 5% anterior to Fz. After artifact removal, ERPs were computed for different experimental conditions. Components were identified by maxima of global field power, and were compared between experimental conditions (compatible/incompatible stimuli) and between females and males an ANOVA with repeated-measurements. We observed statistically significant effects with early components (occurring between 80 and 140 ms and between 150 and 250 ms. Later, components displayed no significant effects. Gender differences were evident mainly with field strength and in the amount of lateralization of evoked components: in male subjects a stronger lateralization was observed. Such effects were not present in the control condition. Our results show that stimulus compatibility is reflected in electrophysiological measurements at latencies of about 100 ms. With this component, differences between males and females suggest rapid information processing in primary visual areas during Stroop tasks that are affected by gender.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section40-1550059412471275">
<title>Oral Sessions</title>
<sec id="section41-1550059412471275">
<title>Single-Trial Classification of Error Potentials (ErrP(s)) Increases P300 Brain-Computer Interface (BCI) Information Transfer Rate (ITR)</title>
<sec id="section42-1550059412471275">
<title>Daniel Berry<sup>1</sup>, Ken Colwell<sup>2</sup>, and Eric Sellers<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>East Tennessee State University, Johnson City, TN, USA</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</p>
<p>Classification of ErrPs can improve P300 BCI performance by detecting and deleting spelling errors. We compare a standard set of EEG channels to a channel set that is dynamically selected. In addition, an algorithm that optimizes ErrP classification thresholds by balancing hits and false alarms is presented. The data show that automatic error correction increases ITR, which may make BCI use a more palatable communication option for some people. Fifteen subjects completed a P300 BCI spelling task. Stimuli were arranged in an 8x9 matrix of alphanumeric items on a computer monitor. During each trial, subjects were instructed to attend to a predefined target item and note each time the item ‘flashed’. Every matrix item flashed two times per trial; the duration of each trial was 3 s. After each trial, sham feedback (20% error rate) was provided. Each subject completed 300 trials. A stepwise linear discriminant analysis (SWLDA) derived classification coefficients from a set of 8 typical BCI electrodes. An active selection method, Jumpwise Selection determined an optimal 8-channel set from the 32 channel montage. The threshold optimization algorithm was then applied to both channel sets and compared to fixed false alarm rates of 2% and 0%. ErrP cross-validation showed that the accuracy of the Jumpwise set was higher (90.4%) than the standard set (87.4%; p&lt;.001). Optimized ErrP classification saved 59 selections; the predefined thresholds of 2% and 0% saved 49 and 3 (p&lt;.001).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section43-1550059412471275">
<title>Delta Oscillations Indicate Gender Differences, Which May Explain Interindividual Differences in Brain Computer Interface (BCI) Performance</title>
<sec id="section44-1550059412471275">
<title>Timur Cetin<sup>1</sup>, Birgit Mathes<sup>1</sup>, Christina Schmied-Fehr<sup>1</sup>, and Canan Basar-Eroglu<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Institute of Psychology and Cognitive Research, University of Bremen, Bremen, Germany</p>
<p>Gender differences in slow frequency EEG have been reported in several studies, indicating that P300 amplitudes [1,2] and delta responses [3] in men are reduced towards women. The P300 is an ERP component on which the commonly used BCI P300 Speller is based. The speller’s algorithm, a stepwise linear discriminant analysis, bases its classification on the P300 s amplitude (Krusienski, et al., 2006). This study investigated if gender differences in delta amplitudes may be related to performance accuracy in the P300 speller. Men and women under 30 years as well as over 55 years of age were examined (total 44 subjects) respective to their P300 speller performance and their delta responses in a visual oddball paradigm. All participants were able to use the speller, but elder men showed less accurate performance (p&lt;0.001). Moreover, elder men showed lower delta responses in the oddball task at parietal and occipital electrodes (P&lt;0.05). No significant difference in the young group was found. We conclude that the P300 speller works sufficiently, but individual differences play a role in the quality of its outcome and this should be considered especially for elder men.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section45-1550059412471275">
<title>Neurophysiologic Aspects of Cannabis Induced Psychosis</title>
<sec id="section46-1550059412471275">
<title>Pierre Flor-Henry<sup>1</sup>, John C. Lind<sup>1</sup>, and Zoltan J. Koles<sup>2</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Alberta Hospital Edmonton and University of Alberta, Canada</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>Department of Engineering, University of Alberta, Canada</p>
<p>Fifteen male subjects hospitalized with cannabis induced psychosis: schizomanic, schizodepressive, bipolar mixed (average age 29) were compared to 68 healthy male controls (average age 27) and investigated with a 48 channel EEG system: R/L alpha power ratio and BEAMFORMER source localization carried out. The R/L alpha power ratio (right – left)/(right + left) is significantly smaller in the cannabis group at FC5/FC6 (p &lt; 0.03) and at C1/C2 (p &lt;0.006) indicating a greater degree of right hemisphere activation in the cannabis group. The BEAMFORMER source analysis showed that the cannabis group has increased sources in the left fronto-temporal region (14-20 Hz) and in the left temporo-parietal region (21-50 Hz) in the Eyes Open condition. In 8-13 Hz the controls have increased power over the whole of the left hemisphere, and to a lesser degree increased power in the right hemisphere (Eyes Closed) and increased power in the frontal regions (Eyes Open).These findings suggest that psychotic symptoms following cannabis are the consequence of increased right brain activation, leading through contralateral disinhibition to left hemisphere disorganization. Andreasson et al. (1987) found in a 15 year follow up of 45570 Swedish conscripts the relative risk for schizophrenia was six times greater in those who had smoked cannabis 50 times or more than in non-users. Further, the rate of schizophrenia increased with increasing consumption.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section47-1550059412471275">
<title>Altered Connectivity Patterns During Seizures with Different types of Consciousness Impairment</title>
<sec id="section48-1550059412471275">
<title>Montserrat Gerez-Malo<sup>1</sup> and Armando Tello-Valdés<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p>Hospital Español de Mexico, Granada, Mexico</p>
<p>Consciousness is a central concept in epilepsy: a loss characterizes generalized seizures and different impairments occur in partial seizures. Before EEG studies, Jackson postulated electrical discharges in hierarchical networks causing “consciousness dissociation.” Further, evidence of psychic phenomena in focal epilepsies raised several physiopathogenic hypotheses. Despite EEG and stimulation studies the mechanisms remain elusive. Experiential variability defies focalized interpretation. Dynamical non-linear interaction models are promising frameworks. The objective is to identify network connectivity alterations in different psychic seizures. LORETA current density correlations (CSDC) were calculated among Regions Of Interest (ROI) during psychic seizures in 10 patients. ANOVA analysis of: level (ICI-L) and content (ICI-C) from Ictal Consciousness Inventory, psychotic features from Positive Negative Symptom Scale (PANSS-P).</p>
<p>EEG and CSDC patterns differed among patients. Decreased CSDC in Default Mode Network (DMN) ROIs correlated with ICI-L. CSDC increases at limbic and midfrontal ROIs related to ICI-C and PANSS-P scores. In conclusion: (1) different types of consciousness impairment can be ictal correlates, (2) ICI-L, ICI-C and PANSS-P variations relate to different connectivity patterns, (3) DMN modulates ICI-L, (4) ICI-C and PANSS-P relate to integrative and monitoring networks.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section49-1550059412471275">
<title>Alpha as the Observer, Gamma as the Observed: Implications for Etiology and Treatment of Clinical Disorders</title>
<sec id="section50-1550059412471275">
<title>Russell Hebert<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup> Department of Physiology and Health, Maharishi University of Management, Fairfield, IA, USA</p>
<p>Current EEG models of consciousness have successfully characterized the “observed” or “content” aspects of experience through phase synchrony analysis of gamma EEG (above 40 Hz). However, both the observed and the “observer” should be necessary components within a complete theory of consciousness. Earlier, we isolated the observer aspect of the EEG as phase synchronized alpha (8-12 Hz). Recent studies by others support the idea that alpha is necessary for conscious experience. A “phase synchrony model of consciousness” is formulated which proposes alpha sub-serves the observer (attention) mechanism and gamma EEG depicts the observed (object). The model proposes that a disturbance of alpha attention mechanisms distorts the phase reset and ongoing phase-locking of alpha resulting in loss of resonant interaction with other frequencies. Clinical EEG investigations focusing on a diverse array of disorders support this thesis. We describe how disrupted alpha phase synchrony is being linked to Autism, schizophrenia, Alzheimer’s, mild TBI, mild cognitive impairment, premature birth syndrome and alcoholism. For the first time, we provide an evidence-based description of the joint observer/observed dimensions of consciousness that together show promise for further understanding and treatment of clinical disorders.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section51-1550059412471275">
<title>Event-Related Potential Studies of Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder: A Critical Review and Synthesis</title>
<sec id="section52-1550059412471275">
<title>Arash Javanbakht<sup>1</sup>, Israel Liberzon<sup>1</sup>, Alireza Amirsadri<sup>2</sup>, Klevest Gjini<sup>2</sup>, and Nash N. Boutros<sup>2</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Department of Psychiatry, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, UDA</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Neurosciences, Wayne State University, Detroit, MI USA</p>
<p>In this paper, we sought to critically review the ERP evidence of information processing abnormalities in patients with PTSD. An extensive Medline search included keywords of: PTSD or post-traumatic stress disorder, electrophysiology or EEG, electrophysiology, P50, P100, N100, P2, P200, P3, P300, sensory gating, CNV (contingent negative variation) and MMN (mismatch negativity). We limited the review to ERP adult human studies with control groups which were reported in the English language, and 36 studies were included. Subjects exposed to wide ranges of military and civilian traumas were studied in these reports. Presented stimuli were both auditory and visual. The most widely studied components included P300, P50 gating, N100 and P200. Most of the studies reported increased P300 response to trauma-related stimuli in PTSD patients. P50 studies were strongly suggestive of impaired gating in patients with PTSD. In conclusion, the majority of reports suggest presence of mid-latency and late ERP components differences in PTSD patients in comparison to healthy controls. We suggest that future ERP-PTSD studies utilize standardized assessment scales that provide detailed information regarding the symptom clusters and the degree of symptom severity. This would allow assessment of electrophysiological indices-clinical symptoms relationships. If supported by future research, ERP studies may be used for both initial assessment and treatment follow-up.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section53-1550059412471275">
<title>Randomization Based ERP Microstate Statistics for the Topographic Assessment of Latency Effects</title>
<sec id="section54-1550059412471275">
<title>M. Thomas Koenig<sup>1</sup>, Maria Stein<sup>1</sup>, Matthias Grieder<sup>1</sup>, and Mara Kottlow<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Department of Psychiatric Neurophysiology, University Hospital of Psychiatry, University of Bern, Switzerland.</p>
<p>ERP microstate analysis is a particularly sensitive tool to assess the dynamics of neurocognitive networks. For statistics, so far, microstate maps obtained from grand mean data were fitted back to individual data. Therefore, the goodness of fit is typically reduced by individual noise. Our aim was to improve statistical power of microstate statistics using procedures based on grand-mean data. In addition, we propose a new criterion to select the optimal number of microstate prototypes based on cross-validation. The procedure employs randomization: The effect of interest, e.g. the on- of a particular microstate, is quantified in the grand mean data of the groups and/or conditions. Next, the group / condition assignments of the individual ERPs are randomized, the grand means are recomputed, and the effect of interest is re-extracted. Sufficient repetitions of this procedure then yield the random distribution of the effect, against which the real data can be tested.</p>
<p>In a sample analysis, the newly developed microstate statistics yielded robust easily interpretable statistical results with very few assumptions and a-priori choices. Compared to previous procedures, the new method was more sensitive, especially for more subtle effects. The proposed microstate analysis is a=sensitive tool to assess differences in multichannel ERP dynamics. The increased statistical power allows identifying more subtle effects, which is particularly important in difficult patient populations.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section55-1550059412471275">
<title>Changes of Gray Matter Volume in Remitted First-Episode and Medication-Naïve Panic Disorder Patients</title>
<sec id="section56-1550059412471275">
<title>Chien-Han Lai<sup>1</sup> and Yu-Te Wu<sup>2</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Department of Psychiatry and Brain Image Research Unit, Buddhist Tzu-Chi General Hospital, Taipei Branch, Taipei, Taiwan</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>Institute of Brain Science, National Yang Ming University, Taipei, Taiwan</p>
<p>This study was aimed to investigate changes of gray matter volume (GMV) in first-episode drug-naïve patients with panic disorder (PD) with remission within 6 weeks under escitalopram treatment. We also studied whether there were any persistent deficits of GMV after remission to find “state-dependent brain changes” and “trait-like brain changes” for PD. Structural scans of 3-Tesla magnetic resonance imaging were performed on 21 patients at baseline and remitted status (sixth week). For the exclusion of inter-scanning bias, 21 healthy controls were also scanned twice within 6 weeks. We utilized optimized voxel-based morphometry with global brain volume, age and gender as covariates. Rating scales of panic symptoms improved with statistical significance (corrected p &lt; 0.001). Remitted patients had increased GMV in left superior frontal gyrus (corrected p &lt; 0.05) after therapy of escitalopram. There were significant deficits of GMV in right precentral gyrus (corrected p &lt; 0.05) after remission of PD symptoms. Improvements of panic symptoms were well correlated with changes of GMV after remission. In conclusion, left superior frontal gyrus (state-dependent brain changes) and right precentral gyrus (trait-like brain changes) might represent treatment characteristics of PD.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section57-1550059412471275">
<title>Imaginative Resonance Training (IRT) Achieves Elimination of Amputeeś Phantom Pain (PLP) Couples with a Spontaneous In-Depth Proprioception of a Restored Limb as a Marker for Permanence and Supported by Pre-Post-Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI)</title>
<sec id="section58-1550059412471275">
<title>Paul Meyer<sup>1</sup>, Christoph Matthes<sup>2</sup>, Karl Erwin Kusche<sup>2</sup>, and Konrad Maurer<sup>2</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>GfGW e. Wiesbaden, Germany</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>University of Frankfurt, Frankfurt, Germany</p>
<p>Non-pharmacological approaches such as mirror therapy and graded motor imagery often provide amelioration of amputee’s phantom limb pain (PLP), but elimination has proved difficult to achieve. Proprioception of the amputated limb has been noted in studies to be (PLP) defective and/or distorted in the presence of PLP, but has not, apparently, been researched for various stages of amelioration up to the absence of PLP. Previous studies using fMRI suggested that pathological cortical reorganisation after amputation may be the underlying neurobiological correlate of PLP. We report two cases of permanent elimination of PLP after application of I R T. The patients, 69 years and 84 years old, reported freedom from PLP for 3.5 years to date and 5 years to death respectively, together with in-depth achievement of proprioception of a restored limb at the end of the treatment, which may thus be taken as an indication of permanence. Pre/post fMRI for the first case show clearly a reversal of the pathological reorganisation in the sensorimotor cortex against a group of healthy controls.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section59-1550059412471275">
<title>Differences in Positive Attitude from Mere Exposure Effect and Other Likability Effect Reflected in Posterior Gamma Activity Strength</title>
<sec id="section60-1550059412471275">
<title>Kongthong Nutchakan<sup>1</sup>, Minami Tetsuto<sup>1</sup>, and Nakauchi Shigeki<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Toyohashi University of Technology, Japan</p>
<p>Mere exposure effect (MEE) has the potential to influence humans’ decision and social interaction. Since positive attitude towards stimuli caused by MEE and other factors such as personal preference are difficult to distinguish using behavioral effect alone, this study employed the EEG approach. Normalized Japanese faces matched in likability used as experimental stimuli were divided into exposed and unexposed groups. MEE was induced during a dummy task, and then participant’s EEG was recorded during likability evaluating session performed after the induction session. Each participant performed an additional likability session a month later in order to verify MEE without EEG recording. Participants were divided into 2 groups according to their behavioral data with and without MEE trend. In participants with MEE trend, gamma activity (40-60[Hz]) for exposed faces was significantly weaker than unexposed faces, indicating repetition suppression effect in posterior parietal area. Comparing exposed faces with high likability on the first day with declined likability (MEE) and preserved likability (non-MEE) a month later, MEE trials elicited significantly lower gamma activity in posterior parietal area. From ERP analysis, neither N170 amplitude nor latency was modulated. These results suggest that posterior gamma activity might be a potential indicator to distinguish MEE and other likability effect, at least in case of human face stimuli.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section61-1550059412471275">
<title>Polysomnographic and Psychometric Studies on the Effects of the Novel Anxiolytic Drug ABIO 08/01 on Sleep and Awakening Quality in Generalized Anxiety Disorder</title>
<sec id="section62-1550059412471275">
<title>Sergio Rosales-Rodríguez<sup>1</sup>, Gerda Maria Saletu-Zyhlarz<sup>1</sup>, Peter Anderer<sup>1</sup>, and Bernd Saletu<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, Medical University of Vienna, Austria.</p>
<p>ABIO 08/01 is a new anxiolytic isoxazoline with dose-dependent activating and sedative/relaxant properties in the qEEG<sup>1</sup> of healthy subjects. ERP<sup>2</sup> and psychometry<sup>1</sup> showed improved P300 latency and mental performance, suggesting nootropic effects. A decrease in well-being reflects sedative effects.In this phase-IIa study, the acute and chronic effects (8 weeks) of ABIO 08/01 on sleep and awakening of 18 drug-free generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) (F41.1, 300.02) patients investigated compared with age- and sex-matched normal controls. After a placebo run-in, they were split into 2 groups and received 5 or 10 mg of ABIO 08/01. If there was no clinical improvement after 2 weeks, the dose could be up-titrated to a maximum of 20 or 40 mg. Evaluations included polysomnography and psychometry. GAD patients showed reduced sleep efficiency due to increased wake after sleep onset and number of awakenings. S1 and the duration of sleep cycles due to longer NREM periods tended to increase. PLM indices were increased. ABIO 08/01 tended to improve sleep efficiency, reduced awakenings, S1, stage shifts and sleep cycle duration by shortening NREM periods. Thus, it normalized the above-described aberrations from the norm (key-lock principle). Respiration and PLM remained unchanged. Psychometry showed a significantly improved awakening quality, morning well-being, fine motor activity and attention, which reflects cognition-enhancing properties of the drug in addition to good tolerability.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section63-1550059412471275">
<title>Clinical and qEEG Studies with the Novel Anxiolytic Drug ABIO 08/01 in Generalized Anxiety Disorder</title>
<sec id="section64-1550059412471275">
<title>Bernd Saletu<sup>1</sup>, Peter Anderer<sup>1</sup>, Sergio Rosales-Rodriguez<sup>1</sup>, and Gerda M. Saletu-Zyhlarz<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, Medical University of Vienna, Austria</p>
<p>Double-blind, placebo-controlled phase-I studies with the new isoxazoline ABIO 08/01 by means of EEG mapping, LORETA and psychometry demonstrated good tolerability and significant CNS effects of the drug, depending on recording conditions and doses. The present phase-IIa, single-blind, randomized, increasing-dose, clinical and neurophysiological proof-of-concept study focused on the efficacy and tolerability of ABIO 08/01 administered to 18 drug-free generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) (F41.1, 300.02) patients as compared with age- and sex-matched normal controls. The study comprised three phases: a placebo run-in, active treatment and a placebo run-out period. Clinical assessments included the Clinical Global Impression Scale as well as observer- and self-ratings of depression and anxiety. GAD patients showed increased depression and anxiety, which significantly improved under ABIO 08/01, reaching normative values. EEG mapping of drug-free patients revealed reduced absolute power in delta and fast beta bands, increased relative power in slow beta and an accelerated total centroid, which reflects CNS activation. ABIO 08/01 induced significant CNS effects at all times in all recording conditions, characterized by increased absolute power in all frequency bands, increased relative theta and decreased relative alpha power (relaxation). Discontinuation of treatment did not lead to a rebound or reoccurrence of GAD symptoms, but interestingly showed optimal findings.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section65-1550059412471275">
<title>Pre- and Post- rTMS EEG Cordance in Treatment Resistant Depression</title>
<sec id="section66-1550059412471275">
<title>N. Tarhan<sup>1</sup> and G. Hizli Sayar<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Uskudar University, Istanbul, Turkey</p>
<p>rTMS is not efficacious in all major depression patients, and different application methods of the technique are still discussed. Current trends of personalized medicine necessitate the use of reliable biomarkers of treatment response. In this present study, we aimed to explore changes on QEEG cordance with rTMS in treatment resistant depression. Seventy-one patients with a diagnosis of treatment resistant depression were assessed pre- and post-rTMS by Hamilton depression scale and QEEG. Patients had taken part in a 3 week, 20 sessions, 25 HZ trial of rTMS adjunctive to their monotherapy SSRI regimen. The subjects were examined in three groups: remission, responder, non-responder groups. Response was defined as a 50% reduction of the HAMD score. Patients with HAMD scores of less than 8 were considered to be in remission. Higher theta cordance on the left frontal area on post- rTMS EEG was found to be associated with non-reponse to treatment. Higher right frontal delta cordance on post-rTMS QEEG was found to be associated with remission. A reduction of prefrontal QEEG theta cordance value after 20 sessions of rTMS was associated with response and remission. The cordance values have state marker values for rTMS treatment in depression. There is a need to continue to search for objective biomarkers and a combination of markers in order to proceed to a faster and more efficacious treatment of depression.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section67-1550059412471275">
<title>A Statistical Approach to Improving Accuracy and Communication Rates in BCIs</title>
<sec id="section68-1550059412471275">
<title>Sandy Throckmorton<sup>1</sup>, Kenneth Colwell<sup>1</sup>, Boyla Mainsah<sup>1</sup>, Kenneth Morton<sup>1</sup>, David Ryan<sup>1</sup>, Eric W. Sellers<sup>2</sup>, and Leslie Collins<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>East Tennessee State University, Johnson City, TN, USA</p>
<p>The goal of the research described in this talk is to improve P300-based Brain Computer Interface (BCI) speller speed and accuracy. In most modern BCI speller systems, the user is presented with a series of ‘flashes’ or illuminations of items while attending to the desired letter. Typically the number of times the letters in the grid are flashed is predetermined and fixed. Determining when to stop flashing automatically, sometimes called dynamic stopping, is a potential means of improving communication rate and accuracy. Several studies have considered dynamic stopping, but all used users’ past performance to determine when to stop. In this study, we compared speller performance in 26 non-diseased subjects using Bayesian updating in order to statistically determine when it is no longer necessary to collect additional data, and we compared performance with traditional ‘static stopping’. Accuracy and communication rate were statistically significantly improved across subjects, and for some subjects, communication rate doubled. We also incorporated a language model where the Carnegie Mellon dictionary was used to update the prior probabilities associated with each speller option as opposed to always assuming a uniform prior. Using data measured from the 26 non-diseased subjects and simulating the speller performance with and without the language model, the average number of flashes was reduced for all subjects with the language model incorporated, and the greatest reduction was seen for those subjects who had the lowest speller accuracy. Similar results were observed on an actual experiment involving fourteen subjects spelling with and without the language model. These results suggest that both dynamic stopping and language models can be used to improve speller performance.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section69-1550059412471275">
<title>Poster Session</title>
<sec id="section70-1550059412471275">
<title>The P300-Certainty Algorithm: Improving Accuracy by Withholding Erroneous Selections</title>
<sec id="section71-1550059412471275">
<title>Abdulrahman W. Aref<sup>1</sup> and Jane E. Huggins<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>The University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA</p>
<p>Non-invasive brain-computer interfaces (BCIs) are an emerging means of communication for people with severe motor impairments. The P300 response, which occurs in reaction to an unpredictable event induced by external yet relevant stimuli, is commonly used to control BCIs. The P300 speller identifies the user’s P300 response to determine which selection they are trying to choose. However, the P300 speller ranks the selections and chooses the top selection, which is not always correct, thus lowering the percentage of correct selections (accuracy). The P300-certainty algorithm was developed to reduce such errors and increase accuracy. This is achieved by assigning a certainty value to the P300 speller’s top selection and evaluating it against a specific threshold. If the selection’s certainty does not pass this threshold, it is blocked and not chosen. Alternatively, if the selection’s certainty passes the threshold, it is typed. To set the certainty threshold, a receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve showing the trade-offs between true positives and false positives was generated. The certainty threshold was set as 95% true positive rate. P300-certainty was tested on recorded copy-spelling data from 15 subjects. A paired t-test showed the accuracy increased from a mean of 82.30± 19.79% to 84.87±15.52% (p-value=0.042) with an average increase of 2.53±4.91%. The next steps are to optimize the certainty threshold, test using more data, and test the algorithm online.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section72-1550059412471275">
<title>Sensorimotor Activity in Speech Perception Measured Via Changes in Mu Rhythm Activity</title>
<sec id="section73-1550059412471275">
<title>Andrew Bowers<sup>1</sup>, Tim Saltuklaroglu<sup>2</sup>, Ashley Harkrider<sup>2</sup>, and Megan Cuellar<sup>2</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, AR, USA</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN, USA</p>
<p>The role of the motor system in speech perception is still debated because there are little data delineating the time course of its activity. To this end, this study employed a time-frequency analysis of the electroencephalography (EEG) mu (µ) rhythm, which was identified via independent component analysis (ICA). Sixteen participants passively listened to or actively identified syllables (e.g., /ba/ vs /da/) and rapid pitch changes in two-forced choice discrimination tasks at high and low signal-to-noise ratios. Independent components were clustered using measure product methods, including spectra, scalp distribution, and equivalent current dipole estimation (ECD). Topographic scalp-maps were examined using sLORETA. Random effects analysis of left and right lateralized sensorimotor µ component clusters revealed significant (pFDR&lt;.05) suppression in the traditional beta frequency range (13-30 Hz; indicative of motor activity) prior to, during, and following stimulus onset. For both left and right lateralized µ clusters, suppression prior to stimulus onset was found in the syllable discrimination task only. Suppression following stimulus offset in the left hemisphere was stronger for discriminations made correctly versus those made at a chance level. The findings are consistent with the generation of internal models in difficult speech discrimination tasks. These models generate predictions about likely phonetic units that are then processed with incoming acoustic cues.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section74-1550059412471275">
<title>A Longitudinal Investigation of Non-invasive P300 Based Brain-Computer Interface</title>
<sec id="section75-1550059412471275">
<title>Kelly E. Brown<sup>1</sup>, David B. Ryan<sup>1</sup>, Juliane A. Armstrong<sup>1</sup>, and Eric W. Sellers<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>East Tennessee State University, Johnson City, TN, USA</p>
<p>Brain-Computer Interface is an alternative method of communication. Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) patients can derive benefit from BCI use, as ALS can result in locked-in syndrome. The present BCI operates via event- related potentials (ERPs) extracted from the EEG. Items (i.e., alphanumeric characters and keyboard commands) attended to by the subject should produce a P300 ERP; unattended items should not. Stepwise linear discriminant analysis is used to classify the items as attended or unattended. Many studies show that ALS patients can communicate using the P300 BCI; however, no study has systematically examined BCI performance longitudinally. This study examines the relationship between disease progression, BCI performance, and several other factors. Nine patients are enrolled in the study and data are collected in intervals of eight weeks. In each session, the ALSFRS-r is administered to track disease progression, followed by four EEG tasks: resting EEG, a cognitive task, an oddball task, and a copy spelling task. The oddball task generated a P300 for attended stimuli, and not for unattended stimuli. ALSFRS-r scores have decreased by 2.8 points on average, mean BCI copy spelling accuracy is 94.4%. Overall, the results suggest that BCI performance remains stable as disease progression continues.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section76-1550059412471275">
<title>Mismatch Negativity (Mmn) and Sensory Auditory Processing In Children Aged 9-12 Years Presenting with Putative Antecedents of Schizophrenia</title>
<sec id="section77-1550059412471275">
<title>Jason M. Bruggemann<sup>1</sup>, Helen V. Stockill<sup>2</sup>, Glenn L. Mould<sup>2</sup>, Sheilagh Hodgins<sup>2</sup>, Rhoshel K. Lenroot<sup>1</sup>, Eric A. Taylor<sup>2</sup>, Robin M. Murray<sup>2</sup>, and Kristin R. Laurens<sup>1,2,3</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia &amp; Neuroscience Research Australia, Randwick, Australia</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>Institute of Psychiatry, King’s College London, London, UK</p>
<p><sup>3</sup>Schizophrenia Research Institute, Sydney, Australia</p>
<p>Identification of markers of abnormal brain function in children at-risk of schizophrenia may inform early intervention and prevention programs. Individuals with schizophrenia are characterized by attenuation of MMN amplitude, which indexes automatic auditory sensory processing. The current aim was to examine whether children who may be at increased risk of schizophrenia due to their presenting multiple putative antecedents of schizophrenia (ASz) are similarly characterized by MMN abnormalities, relative to typically developing (TD) children. EEG was recorded from 22 ASz and 24 TD children aged 9 to 12 years (matched on age, sex, and IQ) during a passive auditory oddball task (15% duration deviant). ASz children were those presenting: (1) speech and/or motor development lags/problems; (2) internalizing, externalizing, and/or peer-relationship problems in the clinical range; and (3) psychotic-like experiences. TD children presented no antecedents. MMN amplitude, but not latency, was significantly greater frontally in the ASz group than in the TD group. While MMN abnormalities were present in children at risk of schizophrenia, the nature of this abnormality differed from that observed in adults with schizophrenia. This may reflect developmental and disease effects in a pre-prodromal phase of psychosis onset. Longitudinal follow-up is necessary to establish the developmental trajectory of MMN in at-risk children.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section78-1550059412471275">
<title>Sparse Structured Probit Regression (SSPR) for Channel Selection and Classification for the P300 Speller</title>
<sec id="section79-1550059412471275">
<title>Kenneth Colwell<sup>1</sup>, Leslie Collins<sup>1</sup>, and Kenneth Morton<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</p>
<p>The P300 Speller uses real-time EEG measurements to allow a user to control a computer without requiring neuromuscular control. It provides an option for communication to populations with severe physical limitations. Home and clinical use of the Speller may be better facilitated by improving spelling accuracy, EEG ease-of-use, and robustness to installation. We address each of these aims by introducing SSPR, a method for training a linear classifier that generalizes the RVM classifier [Bishop 2000] to perform channel selection and classification concurrently. The resulting classifier is sparse in both spatiotemporal features and channels, performing a de facto channel selection that allows the system to determine which channels are not informative and may be removed. Further, the ability to select channels protects against time-dependent problems such as changes in brain response over time or cap installation errors. Future development of the SSPR method could allow for an online training method that ends when sufficient training data is collected. We apply SSPR to 18 subjects’ P300 Speller training and testing data, using the row/column paradigm with an 8-by-9 character grid. SSPR finds linear classifiers that provide a statistically significant increase in spelling accuracy compared to a standard classification method (Stepwise Linear Discriminant Analysis and the eight-channel subset described in Krusienski 2008), using small subsets of the available 32 channels.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section80-1550059412471275">
<title>Mu Wave Suppression During Speech and Non-speech Acoustic Processing Tasks</title>
<sec id="section81-1550059412471275">
<title>Megan Cuellar<sup>1</sup>, Andrew Bowers<sup>1</sup>, Ashley Harkrider<sup>1</sup>, Matt Wilson<sup>1</sup>, and Tim Saltuklaroglu<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>University of Tennessee Health Science Center, Knoxville, TN, USA</p>
<p>Two studies investigate whether mu suppression is sensitive to differences in acoustic processing tasks. Participants listened to various 90 second acoustic-only stimuli clips with their eyes closed and identified predetermined targets. Mu suppression was measured continuously across central electrodes (C3, Cz, and C4). In the first study, ten adult females listened to target pseudowords presented in three conditions (identification, discrimination, discrimination in noise). In the second study, thirteen adult females listened to speech and non-speech acoustic stimuli with segmentation versus non-segmentation requirements. The results of the first study found that mu suppression reached significance relative to baseline only in the most difficult discrimination in noise task at the C3 electrode site (indicative of left hemisphere sensorimotor activity) when measured in a 10-12 Hz bandwidth. The results of the second study found significantly greater overall suppression to speech relative as compared with non-speech tasks, and mu suppression relative to baseline was significant only at C3 during the speech segmentation task. Together, the results indicate that mu suppression is a sensitive measurement that is capable of reflecting acoustic processing differences during tasks with varying levels of linguistic content and cognitive complexity.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section82-1550059412471275">
<title>Predicting Trauma and Stress Reactions in Military Cadets using ERNs and Novelty P300s</title>
<sec id="section83-1550059412471275">
<title>Kevin K. Fleming<sup>1</sup>, Carole L. Bandy<sup>1</sup>, and John Dulmage<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Norwich University, Northfield, VT, USA</p>
<p>The anterior cingulate cortex (ACC) has been implicated as the source of both the novelty P300 waveform and the error-related negativity waveform (ERN). A study by Araki and colleagues (2005) found both decreased novelty P300s and decreased MRI voxel density for the ACC in Tokyo subway attack victims who reported symptoms of PTSD. Smaller ACC volume was associated with greater PTSD symptomology in these victims. We measured both the novelty P300 amplitude and the ERN negative deflection in a sample of 27 military cadets at Norwich University. The novelty P300 was obtained in an auditory oddball task with attended, unattended, and novel tones. The maximal positive peak at 300 ms was recorded from electrode Cz for each participant. The ERN was obtained in a weapon identification task in which participants pressed a mouse key to indicate a “shoot” response to briefly presented guns and tools. The ERN was recorded for each participant as the minimum negative deflection recorded in the Fz electrode 80 ms following false positive responses. We found a significant negative correlation between the P300 amplitude for attended tones and the ERN negative deflection in the weapon identification task, <italic>r</italic> (25) = -.393, <italic>p </italic>= .043. Higher amplitude P300s were associated with deeper ERN deflections. This result suggests that the novelty P300 and the ERN originate from the same frontal midline source, possibly the ACC. However, the connection between ERN and pathology are less clear. The ERN did not correlate significantly with measures of PTSD, trauma, hypervigilance, dissociative experiences, and depression, while the novelty P300 correlated significantly only with trauma reactions, <italic>r</italic> (25) = -.388, <italic>p</italic> = .046. More research is needed to examine both the ERN and the novelty P300 as predictors of trauma and stress reactions in military cadets as well as combat veterans.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section84-1550059412471275">
<title>Associations Between TMS-Based Single and Paired-Pulse Measures of Cortical Excitability and EP Measures of Sensory Gating in Healthy Individuals</title>
<sec id="section85-1550059412471275">
<title>Klevest Gjini<sup>1</sup>, Ravinder Sandhu<sup>1</sup>, Aisha Qazi<sup>1</sup>, and Nash Boutros<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup> Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Neurosciences, Wayne State University, Detroit, MI, USA</p>
<p>Cortical and subcortical inhibitory/excitatory processes are not well-characterized in a number of neuropsychiatric disorders. Transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) and Evoked Potentials (EPs) are valuable noninvasive techniques that can be used for an assessment of inhibitory neurotransmission in the human brain. In the current study, we examined motor cortical excitability using single and paired-pulse TMS-based measures, as well as global (cortical-subcortical) inhibitory processes using EP measures of sensory gating in a relatively large sample of healthy subjects (N=42). Relationships between TMS-based measures of motor cortical excitability and EP measures of sensory gating were assessed using Pearson’s correlation tests. Several significant associations were found, among which a significant positive correlation between TMS-based cortical silent period (CSP) duration at intensity of 150%-of-motor threshold and P50 sensory gating (i.e., longer CSP duration correlated with stronger gating; ratio gating measure: r=-0.426, p=0.01; and difference gating measure: r=0.478, p=0.006). Additionally, strong correlations between same TMS-based measures obtained by left and right motor cortex stimulations were observed. In conclusion, overall, current results are important in establishing normative control data that can be potentially utilized when evaluating cortical and subcortical inhibitory/excitatory mechanisms in neuropsychiatric disorders.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section86-1550059412471275">
<title>Accelerating Dynamic Data Collection in P300 Spellers with Language Modeling</title>
<sec id="section87-1550059412471275">
<title>B Mainsah<sup>1</sup>, L M Collins<sup>1</sup>, K Colwell<sup>1</sup>, and C S Throckmorton<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</p>
<p>P300 spellers rely on event-related potentials (ERPs) that occur in scalp-measured electroencephalography (EEG) to determine the character that the brain-computer interface (BCI) user intends to spell. The speller operates by evaluating the user’s EEG response as character subsets are flashed on a screen; when the flashed subset contains the desired character, an ERP occurs. However, because single ERPs tend to have low signal-to-noise ratios (SNR), each character is flashed multiple times and the responses averaged to increase SNR and classification performance. Adaptive selection of the number of flashes per character improves spelling speed and accuracy. The Dynamic Stopping algorithm used in this study accomplishes the adaptive selection by maintaining a probability distribution over characters, integrating each classified flash response into the model via a Bayesian update [Colwell et al., 2011]. Data collection is stopped when a character probability reaches a threshold and that character is selected as the intended target. In this study, the algorithm is expanded to include a Language Model which is implemented by initializing each character probability prior to data collection based on the previously spelled character. The Dynamic Stopping and Dynamic Stopping plus Language Model algorithms were tested online in 14 non-diseased subjects. The addition of the Language Model significantly reduced the mean number of flashes prior to character selection across all subjects.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section88-1550059412471275">
<title>Using Quantitative Electroencephalography (qEEG) to Compare Electrophysiological Markers and Clinical Presentation in Monozygotic Twins and Their Biological Mother</title>
<sec id="section89-1550059412471275">
<title>Allison D. O'Mara<sup>1</sup>, Corina Harwood<sup>1</sup>, Heather Tahler<sup>1</sup>, Elizabeth M. Zimmerman<sup>1</sup>, Phillip S. Epstein<sup>2</sup>, and Lukasz M. Konopka<sup>2</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>The Chicago School of Professional Psychology, Chicago, IL, USA</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>Advanced Neurodiagnostics, Wheeling, IL, USA</p>
<p>This study was designed to compare qEEG data of twins and their biological mother, each with different clinical presentations ranging from OCD to major depression. We compared qEEG data to explore genetic influences on electrophysiology and to identify potential biomarkers of clinical symptoms. We analyzed qEEG data for a set of male monozygotic twins and their mother. Each patient was diagnosed according to DSM-IV criteria and studied with qEEG. TBI was identified using qEEG Multivariate Discriminant Analysis. Results showed subjects exhibited similar types of brain wave irregularities. Each subject demonstrated epileptiform activity in the central region, with both twins exhibiting sharp waves at leads C3 and C4. Each subject showed poorly developed visual evoked potentials in comparison to auditory with corresponding abnormalities in occipital regions. Both twins had occipital asymmetry. Despite similarities, the twin suffering from anxiety demonstrated excess in high frequencies while the twin with major depression showed deficit slow frequencies in different regions. Data supports the hypothesis that similarities exist amongst twins and their biological mother in qEEG abnormalities and yet they have crucial differences consistent with their unique pathology. Findings of these subjects' qEEG in relation to pathology are consistent with previous research. Data provides support for qEEG as a useful tool in identifying clinical disorders as well as heritable overlaps.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section90-1550059412471275">
<title>Evaluation of Behavioral Measures of Frontal Lobe Dysfunction and Their Relationship with Electrophysiology in Cocaine-Dependent Patients</title>
<sec id="section91-1550059412471275">
<title>Aisha N. Qazi<sup>1</sup>, Klevest Gjini<sup>1</sup>, Ravinder Sandhu<sup>1</sup>, Diane Gooding<sup>2</sup>, and Nash Boutros<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Neurosciences, Wayne State University, Detroit, MI, USA</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>University of Wisconsin, Madison, Department of Psychology, Madison, WI, USA</p>
<p>There is fairly significant evidence that frontal lobe functioning is affected in cocaine-dependent subjects. However, the relationships between behavioral measures of frontal lobe dysfunction and electrophysiological measures of inhibition in cocaine use are unclear. Using the Frontal System Behavioral Scale (FrSBe), frontal lobe dysfunction was compared between a group of abstinent cocaine-dependent subjects (N=49) and healthy controls (N=32). Furthermore, by obtaining transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) and evoked potential (EP)-based measures of inhibition, we assessed the differential associations between these measures with FrSBE-based estimates of frontal lobe dysfunction. Patients had significantly higher average scores for disinhibition (p= .0001) and executive dysfunction (p=.0003). Stronger inhibitory function from P200 EP sensory gating measure was significantly associated with lower executive dysfunction in healthy controls (r= 0.491, p=0.007), but not in cocaine abusers (r= -0.178, p=0.261). Weaker inhibitory function from N100 EP sensory gating measure was significantly associated with apathy scores in cocaine patients (p=0.039), but not in healthy controls (p=0.358). Cocaine-dependent patients have disinhibition and executive dysfunction alteration according to FrSBe. Relationships between FrSBe scores and TMS- and EP-based measures, point to potential neurophysiological mechanisms underlying the frontal lobe dysfunction in cocaine-dependent patients.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section92-1550059412471275">
<title>Prevalence of Chronic Pain Among Individuals with Alcohol Dependence Syndrome</title>
<sec id="section93-1550059412471275">
<title>Jitendra Rohilla<sup>1</sup>, Geetha Desai<sup>1</sup>, and Prabhat Chand<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1 </sup>Department of Psychiatry, NIMHANS, Bangalore, India</p>
<p>Prevalence of chronic pain is reported to be more common in substance dependent population. There are studies on chronic pain in opioid dependent population, but the literature on alcohol and chronic pain is limited. Our objective is to assess the prevalence and correlates of chronic pain in alcohol dependence. The sample was chosen from patients attending outpatient services of Center for Addiction Medicine in National Institute of Mental Health and Neurosciences, Bangalore, India. Individuals who had chronic pain were evaluated in detail by a semi-structured proforma and Brief pain inventory. Chronic pain was prevalent in 18.3%(118) of subjects (646) with alcohol dependence syndrome, with 53.8% of them reporting pain to be of severe intensity, and mean duration of pain was 26.2 in months (SD=33.7).Chronic pain was significantly more common among older patients [t:2.46(95%CI 0.2 to 4.17) p:0.03]. Use of other substances (nicotine, benzodiazepines, opioids and inhalants) were found in 97.8%, with nicotine use being most common. Use of alcohol to manage pain in the last month was reported by 73.7% of patients, while 61.5% reported pain as a reason to continue to use alcohol. In conclusion, use of alcohol to manage pain is common among subjects with alcohol dependence syndrome, with the fact that chronic pain itself is common among this population. This study explains the need for assessing and addressing pain problems in effective ways among subjects with alcohol dependence.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section94-1550059412471275">
<title>Visual Attention’s Past Shapes the Future of BCI</title>
<sec id="section95-1550059412471275">
<title>David Ryan<sup>1</sup> and Eric Sellers<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><bold>
<sup>1</sup>
</bold>East Tennessee State University, Johnson City, TN, USA</p>
<p>A Brain-Computer Interface (BCI) offers a communication option to those who suffer from amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) and other motor disabilities. The majority of BCIs use a visual interface. Visual paradigms offer the highest communication rates when compared to other modalities such as auditory or tactile. One of the greatest challenges in BCI is signal-to-noise ratio (SNR). There is substantial research in signal processing to improve classification techniques and SNR. However, past research in visual attention has been largely overlooked and could improve SNR and usability. This work will review the present BCI paradigms and examine them under visual attention principles. The original visual paradigm, Row/Column (RC), was developed as a fast and simple method to present all of the items of a matrix rapidly. The RC paradigm design did not consider visual attention research topics such as; Gestalt grouping, attentional blink, flanker effects, and space based attention. Attentional principles can explain errors in BCI paradigms (adjacency error, attentional blink, non-target distraction) and how other paradigms have improved performance over RC. In addition, researchers use event-related potential components associated with different types of perception such as motion onset, covert attention, and color processing in an attempt to improve classification. By combining visual attention and signal processing research, a more effective BCI that is easier to use can be brought to those to need it most.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section96-1550059412471275">
<title>Comparison of P50 Sensory Gating in Schizophrenia Patients, Abstinent Cocaine-Dependent Subjects and Healthy Controls</title>
<sec id="section97-1550059412471275">
<title>Ravinder Sandhu<sup>1</sup>, Klevest Gjini<sup>1</sup>, and Nash Boutros<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Wayne State University, Detroit, MI, USA</p>
<p>Sensory gating during early P50 phase of auditory information processing has been shown to be impaired in schizophrenia and cocaine-dependent patients. Common assessment of sensory gating in schizophrenics, cocaine users and healthy subjects is needed to further understand the significance of mid-latency auditory evoked responses (MLAER) and gating in relation to clinical condition of subjects. The present study was conducted to obtain and compare latencies and amplitudes of P50 MLAER between schizophrenics, abstinent cocaine-dependent subjects without psychosis and healthy controls, with 12 subjects in each group. The paired-click (S1=S2) auditory evoked potential paradigm was used to obtain P50 responses from scalp electrodes. The Cz channel was selected for analysis. Peak-to-peak amplitudes and latencies of S1 and S2 responses, and gating measures (ratio, difference) were computed. The statistical analysis was performed using one-tailed t-tests for three pairs of groups. As expected, the schizophrenia patient group showed statistically significant decreased P50 sensory gating compared to the healthy control group (t19=2.9, p=0.009). Also, the mean P50 ratio was significantly higher for cocaine users group as compared to healthy controls group (t19=2.37, p=0.028), indicating decreased sensory gating in cocaine users as opposed to healthy controls. In conclusion, both cocaine users and schizophrenia subjects groups had worse sensory gating compared to the healthy controls group.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section98-1550059412471275">
<title>Pre-rTMS EEG Cordance as a Treatment Response Predictor in Depression</title>
<sec id="section99-1550059412471275">
<title>Gökben Hızlı Sayar<sup>1</sup>, Barış Önen Ünsalver<sup>1</sup>, Ali Bayram<sup>1</sup>, Eylem Özten<sup>1</sup>, and Nevzat Tarhan<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Uskudar University, Istanbul, Turkey</p>
<p>rTMS is a non-invasive brain stimulation technique that has proven to be associated with significant improvements in clinical symptoms of major depressive disorder either as monotherapy or combination therapy. This raises the interest of both patients and clinicians turning the current of clinical decision towards extensive consideration of rTMS as a treatment option in major depression treatment. Cordance is a QEEG method which gives values that strongly correlates with regional brain perfusion by combining information from absolute and relative power of the EEG spectra. Cordance measurement has been used to predict response to treatment with antidepressant drugs. In the present study we aimed to explore changes on QEEG cordance with rTMS treatment in treatment resistant depression. A total of 71 subjects completed the protocol. Choice of SSRI antidepressant drug treatment was decided by their own treating physician, who remained responsible for dosing and any changes in medication during the study. Patients had taken part in a 3 week, 20 sessions, trial of 25 Hz, left prefrontal cortex rTMS adjunctive to their medication regime. The subjects were examined in three groups: remission, responder, nonresponder groups. Response was defined as a 50% reduction of the HAMD score. Patients with HAMD scores of less than 8 were considered to be in remission. In pretreatment QEEG, the remission group had lower delta and theta cordance in the left prefrontal regions as compared to non-responders. The delta and theta cordance of responders were also lower than the theta cordance of nonresponse group in the prefrontal regions. rTMS could be proposed to use as an adjunctive treatment at patients having lower delta and theta cordance at frontal regions. The pretreatment QEEG appears to contain information regarding brain functioning that is relevant to, and predictive of, the therapeutic effect of the rTMS combined with SSRI antidepressant medication.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section100-1550059412471275">
<title>Visual Hallucinations in Psychiatric Disorders: What Do We Currently Know?</title>
<sec id="section101-1550059412471275">
<title>Manisha Shenava<sup>1</sup>, Klevest Gjini<sup>1</sup>, Matcheri Keshavan<sup>1</sup>, and Nash Boutros<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Department of Psychiatry, Wayne State University, Detroit, MI, USA</p>
<p>It is generally held, though with little systematic evidence, that visual hallucinations (VH) are more characteristic of psychoses secondary to medical or neurological illness but are relatively less frequent in primary psychotic disorders. Our goal was to evaluate the current state of knowledge regarding VH in psychiatric disorders. We searched PubMed, Google Scholar, and reference lists of included articles. Search terms included VH, psychiatry, schizophrenia, and psychosis. Forty articles of VH due to neurological disorders were included in this review for comparison. We found a total of 20 Articles pertaining to VH in psychiatric disorders. Evidence shows a large range of patients with various psychiatric disorders experience VH (from 17-70% in different studies). Formed VH seem to be present more often in psychiatric disorders while unformed VH seem more likely linked to neurological conditions. Patients with childhood onset schizophrenia (COS) are also reported to have a more likely chance of having VH than their adult counterparts. Finally, some articles report a link between lower socioeconomic status or lower IQ of psychiatric patients and a higher chance of developing visual hallucinations. Contrary to standard teaching, many primary psychiatric patients have VH, in particular with a formed content. Their higher prevalence in COS and their association with low IQ may suggest a neurodevelopmental basis for these hallucinations.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section102-1550059412471275">
<title>Disinhibition and Poor Error Monitoring Associated with Alcohol and Cannabis Exposure in Young Adults</title>
<sec id="section103-1550059412471275">
<title>Janette L. Smith<sup>1</sup> and Richard P. Mattick<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre, University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia</p>
<p>Current knowledge concerning the effects of alcohol and cannabis on cognitive function is based on older, more established/dependent users, and principally focuses on memory dysfunction alone. Our research examines a younger cohort with less exposure, but who are potentially at more risk of damage to their still-developing brains. Secondly, we combine assessment of not only memory but also executive function processes, which are increasingly important in models of the development and maintenance of substance abuse. Sixty participants aged 18-21 will undergo interviews assessing prior use of alcohol and cannabis, before completing experimental tasks assessing memory and executive functions while ERPs are recorded. Preliminary results (from ~30 participants) suggest increased alcohol use is associated with impaired inhibitory control, and impaired performance monitoring following inappropriate responses. However, memory function, attentional capture by alcohol and cannabis related words, and decision making appear unaffected by prior exposure to alcohol or cannabis. ERP data analysis is still in progress, but error-related negativity appears to be reduced in heavier drinkers. If the current results are upheld in the full sample, it suggests that a reduced ability to exert control over behavior, followed by a failure to adaptively adjust behavior after such errors, is apparent even in young adults with a shorter history of alcohol use than previously considered.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section104-1550059412471275">
<title>An Analysis of Overlapping Nontarget Responses for the P300 Speller</title>
<sec id="section105-1550059412471275">
<title>George Townsend<sup>1</sup> and Dean Krusienski<sup>2</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Algoma University, Sault Ste. Marie, Ontario, Canada</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>Old Dominion University, Norfolk, VA, USA</p>
<p>Brain-computer interfaces (BCIs) enable devices to be controlled via thought. One BCI based on scalp EEG that detects event-related potentials (ERPs) is the popular P300 Speller. The user is presented with a matrix of flashing symbols (stimuli) and attends to the desired symbol (target) as it flashes. All other stimuli are considered nontargets. To increase the speed and accuracy of this BCI the stimuli are presented as rapidly as possible. Since there is a nontarget stimulus in every epoch, and since the responses have a time course much longer than the time between the start of each epoch, this results in overlapping epochs. We show theoretically and empirically that customary averaging of the non-target responses produces erroneous results because of this overlap. An alternative approach to nontarget response averaging is proposed that reveals the proper response. Data was collected from ten volunteers where no nontarget stimuli where flashed, then every second nontarget, then every third. For all three conditions customary averaging shows the same traditional sinusoidal ripple with a period equal to the flash period of the BCI erroneously indicating a response in every epoch. When the alternative average method is employed, the correct responses are shown in accordance with the actual non-targets flashed. The proliferation of the incorrect approach in conference papers and posters suggests that this is a widely misunderstood issue that the BCI community needs to be made aware of.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section106-1550059412471275">
<title>Gamma-band Synchrony; Role of Music Perception in the Brain</title>
<sec id="section107-1550059412471275">
<title>Yuko Urakami<sup>1</sup>, Yoshikazu Washizawa<sup>2,3</sup>, Koki Kawamura<sup>3,4</sup>, Kazuko Hiyoshi<sup>3,5,</sup> and Andrzej Cichocki<sup>3</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Hospital and Research Institute, National Rehabilitation Center for Persons with Disabilities, Tokorozawa, Japan.</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>Department of Communication Engineering and Informatics, The University of Electro-Communications, Tokyo, Japan.</p>
<p><sup>3</sup>Laboratory for Advanced Brain Signal Processing, RIKEN Brain Science Institute, Wako-shi, Japan.</p>
<p><sup>4</sup>Department of Anatomy, School of Medicine, Keio University, Tokyo, Japan.</p>
<p><sup>5</sup>Department of Functional Brain Imaging, Human Brain Research Center, Graduate School of Medicine, Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan.</p>
<p>Music perception involves acoustic and auditory scene analysis, processing of interval relations, of musical syntax and semantics, and activation of premotor representations of actions. This study aimed to clarify the neural networks during music perception of musicians and non-musicians using 60-ch electroencephalography (EEG). We collected spontaneous brain activity in five musicians (four musical-trained students and one singer), five non-musical trained students while listening to “From the new world (Dvorak)” and “Requiem (Mozart)” for three minutes, being compared with resting state. During listening to the music, compared with the resting state, gamma activity was significantly decreased, especially in the prefrontal cortex. Likewise, alpha activity was significantly decreased during listening to the music, also decreased during imaging the music as seen in the left frontal, central and parietal lobes. The rate of decrease of gamma activity in the frontal midline was greater in the anterior part (Fp1, Fp2, Fpz) compared with posterior part (F1, F2, Fz), and central part(C1, C2, Cz). During music listening, the musicians’ gamma activity was significantly decreased in the temporal, parietal and occipital lobes compared with the non musicians’. During imaging the music, the musicians’ gamma activity was significantly decreased in the temporal, parietal and occipital lobes, whereas the non musicians’ gamma activity increased in the frontal lobe. Discussion: A gamma-activity decreases during music perception especially in the anterior part of the frontal lobe; it is strongly related to the integration of recognition and emotion which reflect the processing of music in a highly integrated level. Musicians’ gamma activity significantly decreases during listening to the music in the temporal, parietal and occipital lobes compared with non musicians, which may indicate the difference of auditory-processing mechanism as concerns tones or harmony, high or low tones, forte or piano, as well as pitch and melody. The gamma synchronization shows that musicians can image the music in the same or similar condition as they are listening to the music, that is, they do image and replay the music in the recollection of acoustic memory in the listening-to-the music state. The differences in brain activities during music perception between musicians and non-musicians may reflect the different quality of their musical training experiences and expert skills.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section108-1550059412471275">
<title>Pre-Attentive Auditory Evoked Potentials in Schizophrenia and Their Relationship to Psychopathology</title>
<sec id="section109-1550059412471275">
<title>Andrei Vedeniapin<sup>1</sup>, Cynthia L. Arfken<sup>2</sup>, Klevest Gjini<sup>2</sup>, and Nash N. Boutros<sup>2</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Medical University, Charleston, SC, USA</p>
<p><sup>2</sup>Wayne State University, Detroit, MI, USA</p>
<p>Relationship among gating ratios in standard and modified gating paradigms and PANSS Scales was examined in 37 schizophrenia subjects (age: M=45.4 years). Gating parameters were also measured in 41 control subjects (age: M=39.7 years). In addition to P50, N100, and P200 potentials in gating paradigms, MMN to frequency change was measured in 17 schizophrenia subjects and 25 control subjects. Two gating paradigms (one employed two identical 1000 Hz 4mSec stimuli and the other employed two different [1000 Hz and 1500 Hz] 4mSec stimuli) and a MMN frequency deviation paradigm (the standard 1000 Hz 4mSec and the deviant 15% of time 500 Hz 4mSec stimuli) were implemented. MMN latency was significantly shorter in schizophrenia subjects. MMN latency or amplitude did not correlate with the PANSS Scales. Sensory gating was decreased in schizophrenia subjects in both sensory gating paradigms. General Psychopathology Scale was negatively correlated with N100 and P200 gating in the modified gating (MG) paradigm only. Linear regression model showed that gating ratios in the MG paradigm predicted General Psychopathology Scale (P200 ratio) and Positive and Negative Scales (P50 ratio). This is the first study that demonstrated shorter latency of frequency MMN in schizophrenia. Although schizophrenia subjects had similar gating deficit in both standard and modified gating paradigms, only gating ratios in the gating paradigm that employed non-identical stimuli were related to PANSS Scales.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section110-1550059412471275">
<title>Dynamic of Spontaneous Blink Amplitude During the First rTMS Treatment Session Predicts Clinical Response in Depressed Patients</title>
<sec id="section111-1550059412471275">
<title>Andrei Vedeniapin<sup>1</sup>, Xingbao Li<sup>1</sup>, and Mark George<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Medical University, Charleston, NC, USA</p>
<p>The EEG and spontaneous blink measures were studied as possible predictors of clinical response to rTMS treatment in depressed patients. The data from 7 responders and 6 non-responders participants in the OPT-TMS study (the MUSC site) were examined. Five EEG segments in the beginning and 5 EEG segments at the end of the first rTMS session were selected. Each EEG segment was about 10 sec. duration and was selected right after the end of the rTMS train. The EEG data were spectrally analyzed and traditional delta (1-3 Hz), theta (4-6 Hz), alpha (7-13 Hz) and beta (14-24 Hz) spectral bands were calculated. An amplitude of the largest blink in each EEG segment was measured and averaged across first and last five EEG segments. No difference in the spectral power dynamic during the first rTMS session was found between clinical responders and non-responders. The results, however, showed statistically significant habituation of spontaneous blink amplitude in non-responders (paired two tails t-test =3.29, p=0.022). In responders, habituation was non-significant. A ratio of the averaged blink amplitude calculated as: (last/first)*100 was larger (p=0.056)in responders. This is the first report of the high frequency rTMS effect on the blink amplitude habituation in depressed patients. There is a possible relationship of such findings to the dopaminergic system.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section112-1550059412471275">
<title>The Tracing of Neural Processing on Perceptual Rivalry Using Steady-State Visual Evoked Potential</title>
<sec id="section113-1550059412471275">
<title>Yusuke Yokota<sup>1</sup>, Tetsuto Minami<sup>1</sup>, and Shigeki Nakauchi<sup>1</sup>
</title>
<p><sup>1</sup>Toyohashi University of Technology, Japan</p>
<p>Understanding of the neural processing for perceptual rivalry is one of the important topics in neurosciences. We employed bistable Necker lattice to investigate neural network during perceptual rivalry. In addition to using the Necker lattice, we focused on steady-state visual evoked potential (SSVEP) that is a powerful tool to study cognitive function. In this study, we presented flickering Necker lattice with 8 Hz and 12 Hz. It shows the different perception with different oscillatory activities. Therefore, if a participant’s perception changes from one perception to another perception, the corresponding activity changes. Our aim is to investigate the neural activities that are relevant to perceptual switching from the SSVEP. Two experiments were performed. In the one paradigm, the participants observed the flickering Necker lattice continuously and responded by pressing a button to any perceived reversal. In the other paradigm, the participants observed the flickering stable figure with one specific frequency. In this paradigm, stimulus changes from one stable figure to another stable figure with specific frequency for every specific term. We compared ambiguous reversals activity of ambiguous Necker lattice with physical reversals of stable lattice. Thirteen healthy volunteers participated in our experiments. The EEG was recorded from 64 active electrodes amplifier. Time–frequency analysis was performed by convolving the data with a complex Morlet wavelet. The differences between ambiguous and control activity were tested for statistical significance (p &lt; 0.01) using a non-parametric permutation test (Monte Carlo randomization) repeated 1000 times. As a result, the oscillatory activity before perceptual switching showed a significant difference between ambiguous Necker lattice and stable figure at frontal region (p &lt; 0.01). Moreover, SSVEP amplitude enhanced at occipital regions in stable figure tagging. On the other hand, it enhanced at occipito-temporal regions in ambiguous Necker tagging. These results suggested that SSVEP reflects neural different processing between ambiguous perceptual rivalry and stable physical reversal.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
</article>