<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ISC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spisc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Intervention in School and Clinic</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1053-4512</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1538-4810</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1053451212454168</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1053451212454168</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Departments</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Diversity Dispatches</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Strategies for Addressing the Disproportionate Representation of Diverse Students With Autism Spectrum Disorder</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>Juliet E.</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1053451212454168">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>More</surname><given-names>Cori</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1053451212454168">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1053451212454168"><label>1</label>Division of Teacher Preparation, Arizona State University, Phoenix, AZ, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1053451212454168"><label>2</label>Division of Educational Leadership and Technology, Arizona State University, Phoenix, AZ, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1053451212454168">Juliet E. Hart, Division of Teacher Preparation, Mary Lou Fulton Teachers College, Arizona State University, P.O. Box 37100, Phoenix, AZ 85069, USA Email: <email>Juliet.Hart@asu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>48</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>167</fpage>
<lpage>173</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Hammill Institute on Disabilities 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Hammill Institute on Disabilities</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>diversity(ies)</kwd>
<kwd>autism</kwd>
<kwd>strategy(ies)</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1053451212454168-img1.tif"/>
<p>Formerly considered a low-prevalence disorder, autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is the most rapidly growing developmental disability, ranked as the sixth most commonly classified disability in the United States, and is estimated to currently affect 1 in 110 children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1053451212454168">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 2011</xref>). Autism spectrum disorder is a neuro-developmental disorder and typically refers to autism, Asperger syndrome, and pervasive developmental disorder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1053451212454168">Klin, McPartland, &amp; Volkmar, 2005</xref>). To receive a diagnosis of autism based on the criteria outlined in the fourth edition of the <italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</italic> (<italic>DSM-IV</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1053451212454168">American Psychiatric Association [APA], 2000</xref>), a child must demonstrate limitations in the areas of social interaction and communication, and stereotypical patterns of behavior, interests, and/or activities. The proposed language of the <italic>DSM-V</italic> refers to autism as a spectrum disorder, and collapses autism, Asperger syndrome, child disintegrative disorder, and pervasive developmental disorder under the classification of ASD. The suggested definition emphasizes the difficulty individuals with ASD experience acquiring social communication skills (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dsm5.org">www.dsm5.org</ext-link> for the projected definition).</p>
<p>Although the prevalence of ASD was not previously thought to be disproportionally represented across ethnic, racial, or socioeconomic groups, recent investigations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1053451212454168">Mandell, Listerud, Levy, &amp; Pinto-Martin, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1053451212454168">Mandell, Novak, &amp; Zubritsky, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1053451212454168">Mandell et al., 2009</xref>) have indicated sobering racial disparities in the early detection and treatment of ASD, with children from minority groups often diagnosed at later ages than their White counterparts. The presence of cognitive delay appears to exacerbate this trend. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1053451212454168">Mandell et al. (2002)</xref> further asserted that disparities may result from differences in help-seeking by families, advocacy and support, and clinician behaviors. Correspondingly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1053451212454168">Travers, Tincani, and Krezmien’s (in press)</xref> multiyear (1998–2006) national profile examining the degree of disproportionate representation of students with ASD in special education suggested a systematic and decreasing shift in the proportion of African American students and Asian/Pacific Islander students identified with ASD, whereas Hispanic and American Indian/Alaskan Native students were consistently underrepresented each year of their analysis. Travers et al. confirmed previous, medically based research indicating that racially diverse students are being identified with ASD at later ages or are potentially being misidentified entirely (e.g., in the intellectual disability category).</p>
<p>Although decades of research confirmed the critical importance of intervening early for children across all disability categories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1053451212454168">Gallagher, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1053451212454168">Guralnick, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1053451212454168">Trohanis, 2008</xref>), results of recent research studies have underscored the importance of early detection of and targeted early intervention in ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1053451212454168">Dawson et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1053451212454168">Reichow &amp; Wolery, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1053451212454168">Schertz, Baker, Hurwitz, &amp; Benner, 2011</xref>). This growing body of research suggests that comprehensive developmental behavioral intervention for young children with ASD can significantly improve cognitive ability, adaptive behavior, and communication skills, thereby reducing the severity of ASD diagnosis. Consequently, diverse students may not be receiving the intensive, early interventions during the critical time period in which the greatest likelihood for positive impact exists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1053451212454168">Travers et al., in press</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section1-1053451212454168">
<title>Culturally Responsive Strategies for Practitioners</title>
<p>Whereas future research should seek to disentangle the variables and specific factors contributing to disproportionate representation of diverse students with ASD, school professionals can begin to address this issue within their classrooms and diagnostic settings. Although it is highly probable that both general and special educators will encounter students with ASD, consistent with the findings of the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1053451212454168">National Research Council (2001)</xref>, most teacher graduates receive minimal to no preparation in evidence-based practices for students diagnosed with ASD. With both general and sometimes even special educators often feeling unprepared to meet the needs of students with ASD due to lack of specialized training, teaching strategies to enhance the academic engagement, social communication, and behavior of ASD students are particularly useful and well-timed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1053451212454168">Hart &amp; Whalon, 2008</xref>). In this article we present culturally responsive practices that demonstrate how teachers can (a) increase their knowledge of ASD in the context of students’ diverse languages and cultures; (b) partner with families to share understanding of ASD symptomatology and assist diverse families in accessing needed services and resources; and (c) implement best-practices multicultural teaching and assessment strategies in the classroom for all students, with particular implications for diverse students with ASD. These “how to” strategies can assist professionals in lessening the negative impact of disproportionate representation for diverse populations, specifically, for diverse students with ASD.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1053451212454168">
<title>Strategies to Increase Teacher Knowledge</title>
<p>Increasing knowledge through awareness and understanding of ASD in the context of students’ language and culture are first steps in finding solutions to potential misclassification of students with ASD. As noted previously, teachers and teams need to recognize that the ASD label is applied variably across cultural groups. Next, it is important to understand that this disproportionate application of the ASD diagnosis may result from untrained educators and teams interpreting a child’s display of mild symptoms as a result of cultural differences rather than as indicators of disabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1053451212454168">Mandell et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1053451212454168">Noland &amp; Gabriel, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1053451212454168">Shattuck, 2006</xref>), thereby classifying students with ASD under other labels (e.g., developmental delay, mental retardation) or not classifying them at all (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053451212454168">Dyches, 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1053451212454168">Wilder, Dyches, Obiakor, and Algozzine (2004)</xref> described how some ASD characteristics such as tantrums, lack of eye contact, aggressive behavior, poor social and communication skills, and inappropriate emotional expression displayed by students with ASD may also have a cultural basis. For example, a student’s avoidance of eye contact coupled with lack of verbal response to adults is more common among Asian American children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1053451212454168">Lian, 1996</xref>) but, if frequently displayed, could be interpreted as indicative of delay in spoken language development, a primary feature of ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1053451212454168">Wilder et al., 2004</xref>). Therefore, educational professionals must be knowledgeable not only about the characteristics of students with ASD but also how the added dimensions of culture and language may impact identification of students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053451212454168">Dyches, 2011</xref>). How can teachers begin to increase their understanding of these interrelated components?</p>
<p>First, teachers can learn how to recognize the early indicators of ASD (e.g., language delay, lack of joint attention, limited shared interests and play with others, repetitive behaviors, etc.). The Centers for Disease Control (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/ncbddd/autism/educator.html">http://www.cdc.gov/ncbddd/autism/educator.html</ext-link>) offers easily accessible information for teachers, including videos about autism, benchmarks and early indicators of autism, information on planning in the classroom, as well as key developmental milestones to which teachers can refer. The ability to recognize the early signs of ASD will allow teachers to more readily recognize underrepresented groups of students with autism in their classrooms. Second, in an effort to maximize collaborative efforts, school psychologists, diagnosticians, and related service professionals can assist by providing training about autism for teachers and the community. Continued professional development related to the heterogeneity of the presentation of ASD should become a priority in all school settings, but especially those that serve diverse populations.</p>
<p>However, having awareness of the defining features and nuances of ASD is only one part of increasing knowledge about the disorder. School professionals need to keep informed of current trends in special education. To do this teachers should become members of and participate in local, state, and national professional organizations; read current research in educational journals; and attend conferences. Participating in these activities can ensure that school professionals stay abreast of information in special education and its related best practices. Educators can take advantage of preconference workshops specializing in areas such as diversity or ASD. Another way for educational professionals to stay on top of current information is to subscribe to free update services found on the Internet provided via email and news feeds. These online resources can reduce the amount of time school professionals spend searching for the most up-to-date and valid information to assist their students (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1053451212454168">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1053451212454168" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Free online resources.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1053451212454168-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>Although it is important that school professionals seek to increase their knowledge of ASD, they also must develop their understanding of the different cultures represented by students in their classrooms. Familiarity with culture helps teachers to enhance their instructional methods while it also assists them in recognizing cultural patterns of behavior that might overlap with ASD diagnosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1053451212454168">Wilder et al., 2004</xref>). Some strategies teachers can use to increase their knowledge of culture include participating in community activities, diversity training, and workshops offered by ethnic community-based organizations. The Educational Alliance at Brown University (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.alliance.brown.edu/tdl/index.shtml">http://www.alliance.brown.edu/tdl/index.shtml</ext-link>) offers additional, practical suggestions for school professionals in their efforts to increase their cultural understanding. For example, school personnel can invite members of different cultural groups to the school to help inform teachers about the generalized views of education and communication styles of members of that culture. Moreover, school professionals can collaborate with community members who are knowledgeable about students’ cultures, including chamber of commerce members, local businesspersons, and community spiritual leaders. Learning from cultural informants, colleagues, parents, and community leaders can help to access diverse students’ and families’ funds of knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1053451212454168">Moll, Amanti, Neff, &amp; Gonzalez, 1992</xref>), thereby identifying resources within students’ neighborhoods and increasing teachers’ overall knowledge of and connection to the families and cultures of their students.</p>
<p>Parents play an important role in identifying their children’s strengths and needs and are crucial members of multidisciplinary teams (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1053451212454168">Turnbull, Turnbull, Erwin, Soodak, &amp; Shogren, 2010</xref>). Forging relationships between families and teachers is critical to facilitating accurate identification of culturally and linguistically diverse students for ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1053451212454168">American Speech-Language-Hearing Association, 2006</xref>). Therefore, we turn next to strategies and resources that educators of diverse learners with ASD can utilize to effectively partner with parents and families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1053451212454168">Morrier, Hess, &amp; Heflin, 2008</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1053451212454168">
<title>Strategies to Build Family-School Connections</title>
<p>Research studies on diverse families and ASD have suggested that parents from different cultures vary in their views regarding ASD symptoms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1053451212454168">Coonrod &amp; Stone, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1053451212454168">Daley, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1053451212454168">2004</xref>) and possibly view the ASD diagnostic categories of difficulty with social interaction, communication, and repetitive behaviors through a cultural lens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053451212454168">Dyches, 2011</xref>), which may delay referral for an evaluation. For example, delays in language development may be viewed by families as related to the importance of watching and listening over speaking, silence/think time during conversations, and morés on appropriate children’s roles in conversations with adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053451212454168">Dyches, 2011</xref>). To facilitate dialogue with parents on the ways in which the diagnostic criteria for ASD in the areas of social interaction, communication, and stereotypic behaviors may be interpreted through a cultural lens, teachers can pose thoughtful questions to parents and families regarding these characteristics and the ways they may mirror ASD indicators (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1053451212454168">Table 1</xref> for examples).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1053451212454168" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Questions Related to Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) and Culture That Teachers Can Pose to Families</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1053451212454168" xlink:href="10.1177_1053451212454168-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Communication</th>
<th align="center">Socialization</th>
<th align="center">Behavior</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>How do people in your family use their voices to express themselves?</td>
<td>Is it important to you that your child has friends outside of the family?</td>
<td>Are there behaviors that your child engages in that get in the way of your home routines?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Do people speak loudly, softly, wait their turn? Are there interruptions?</td>
<td>Which do you value more in your child’s education—social skills or academic skills?</td>
<td>Are there any behaviors that your child displays in public that seem inappropriate to you? How do you expect children to behave when you go out in the community?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>How do you feel about children asking questions of adults?</td>
<td>Do you expect your child to follow directions from parents or adults right away or is it acceptable if he or she is sometimes distracted?</td>
<td>How would you describe your child’s activity level?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Do people in your family use a lot of gestures when they are speaking?</td>
<td>How are children expected to interact with adults? Other children?</td>
<td>How do you think your child’s activity level compares to that of siblings or other children?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>What language do you speak most frequently at home?</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>When you are talking with your children, do you want them to at look you in the eye or is that considered disrespectful?</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Do people in your family overlap when speaking with each other, speaking at the same time (e.g., simultaneous talk)?</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>How do people in your family show they are listening?</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Last, it is important that teachers understand that many families from culturally diverse backgrounds underuse school-based services (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1053451212454168">Sontag &amp; Schacht, 1993</xref>). For example, African American families frequently rely on the support of family, friends, and religious groups before seeking out professional assistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1053451212454168">Rogers-Dunlan &amp; Blancher, 1995</xref>) and then subsequently access those services less often than European Americans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1053451212454168">Pruncho, Patrick, &amp; Burant, 1997</xref>). Therefore, with the knowledge that parents may either be unaware of ASD symptoms, may view those symptoms differently (i.e., through their own cultural lens), or may underutilize services, school professionals must work vigorously to build family-school connections so that parents can become more knowledgeable about possible ASD symptoms in their children. Proactively collaborating with families as integral members of school teams becomes a critically important way to ensure children with ASD (diagnosed or undiagnosed) receive support at home as well as at school. When teachers take time connect with the family, appreciate the family’s communication style, and build cultural understanding, areas of need can be identified across settings.</p>
<p>What does facilitating communication with families look like? In practical terms, teachers can increase methods of communication by offering multiple means and multiple times for communication. These efforts can include directly connecting with families through traditional methods (e.g., face to face, phone calls, conferences, visits to the home) or technological methods (e.g., email, Skype) as well as during extended hours. Offering multiple means of communication to families sends the message that teachers are interested in incorporating the families’ preferences, honoring cultural differences, and respecting the challenges families might experience as a result of limited resources, thus validating the importance of the families’ input in the education of their children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1053451212454168">American Speech-Language-Hearing Association, 2006</xref>). School professionals should also be prepared to communicate during a variety of times throughout the day to meet the diverse needs of families. During these meeting times, school personnel can build family-school connections by conveying information about organizations that assist with home and community-based services as well as strategies that have been successful at school. Families can share progress at home, describe services that they have accessed, as well as relay their current needs.</p>
<p>Multidisciplinary and individualized education program (IEP) meetings are also opportunities that school personnel can take advantage of when seeking to connect with families. Information shared during these times can be used to make eligibility determinations as well as to develop educational plans. School personnel can collaborate with families in ongoing and informal ways by reviewing previous assessment data and information provided by the family to the multidisciplinary team, focusing specifically on the areas of socialization, communication, and behavior. The review of these data can help school personnel examine concerns and considerations of previous multidisciplinary teams and look for patterns that may be related to ASD diagnosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1053451212454168">Morrier et al., 2008</xref>). This communication can assist in linking services and strategies across settings, thereby promoting generalization of service delivery. With the rate of ASD prevalence amongst siblings at 20% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1053451212454168">Ozonoff et al., 2011</xref>), increasing communication with families has the potential to help younger siblings be identified with ASD earlier than may have been the case with the older sibling, thus helping the family to access services at an earlier age. Positive home-school connections increase family engagement in the educational process. A summary of strategies to partner with diverse families in order to facilitate their knowledge of ASD is provided in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1053451212454168">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1053451212454168" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Strategies to facilitate family school connections.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1053451212454168-fig2.tif"/></fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1053451212454168">
<title>Strategies to Facilitate Culturally Responsive Practices</title>
<p>School personnel can use a variety of instructional and assessment strategies to reduce the impact of disproportionate representation of children with ASD. These strategies include validating students’ cultural identity in classroom practices and instructional materials, implementing culturally responsive assessment practices, and engaging in self-reflection about one’s own personal biases. First, teachers can validate students’ cultures by ensuring a representative curriculum, making certain that materials reflect the culture of their students, thereby promoting a sense of belonging among them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1053451212454168">Winzer &amp; Mazurek, 1998</xref>). Specifically, teachers can select textbooks, design bulletin boards, and present lessons that are culturally supportive of their students by utilizing familiar images and adequately representing diverse groups, which can capitalize on the strengths students bring to the classroom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1053451212454168">Richards, Brown, &amp; Forde, 2006</xref>). Additionally, teachers can align instruction with students’ preferred communication and learning styles. For example, teachers can permit students to use multiple modes of response or allow students with ASD to communicate through visual rather than auditory receptive modes.</p>
<p>Next, implementing culturally responsive assessment practices is crucial as part of the comprehensive evaluation process to determine the presence of ASD in diverse students as well to document their progress. These practices begin with teachers keeping accurate data about students’ progress in academic and nonacademic areas (e.g., social, behavioral, self-help) areas. Within these data, teachers should pay particular attention to areas typically impacted by ASD (communication, behavioral, and social data) to ensure the students are progressing in all areas. Furthermore, as teachers analyze classroom-based data, they should consider how culture impacts any data collected. When progress is not being made in the areas typically impacted by ASD, school professionals can more closely examine the student’s services and disability eligibility.</p>
<p>Because an accurate classification of ASD is frequently the vehicle for securing appropriate educational services, multidisciplinary teams should seek to diminish barriers related to cultural or language differences for diverse students. For example, if team members are not proficient in the student’s native language, a trained bilingual evaluator should conduct the assessment, including observations of the student across settings as well appropriate instruments to determine the presence of ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053451212454168">Dyches, 2011</xref>). Furthermore, school psychologists, clinicians, and teachers need to be aware that presence of an intellectual disability can impact evaluation of ASD in children; that is, presence of intellectual disabilities may affect professionals’ further assessment of developmental delay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1053451212454168">Travers et al., in press</xref>). As part of implementing culturally responsive practices throughout the assessment process, school psychologists and clinicians must also consider how a student’s culture can affect verbal and nonverbal communication, how to select and adapt ASD screening/assessment tools, and the relationship between ASD characteristics and culturally based nonverbal behavior (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1053451212454168">American Speech-Language-Hearing Association, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1053451212454168">Dyches, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Last, all school professionals, but especially school psychologists, clinicians, and teachers, can engage in self-reflection, examining trends in their local population and adjusting their assessment practices accordingly. Identifying and attending to trends of disproportional representation at the local level will assist in addressing the issue at the national level. Similarly, teachers need to ensure that any anecdotal academic or behavioral data they collect and interpret is objective and free from bias. To accomplish this, teachers must engage in self-reflection, giving careful consideration to any personal biases they hold that may be influencing their interpretation of data they collect on their students. For example, some teachers may struggle with their own biases against students with ASD who display disruptive or unorthodox behaviors, who lack the normative social skills of the mainstream group, or who come from cultural backgrounds with which the teacher is unfamiliar or uncomfortable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1053451212454168">Wilder et al., 2004</xref>). Teachers must examine the personal motivations that govern their own behavior and determine whether these could be interfering with their effective teaching and accurate evaluation of diverse students with ASD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1053451212454168">Obiakor, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1053451212454168">Wilder &amp; Obiakor, 2003</xref>). This process can be facilitated with autobiographical and reflective journal writing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1053451212454168">Richards et al., 2006</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1053451212454168">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Researchers are beginning to examine disproportionate representation of diverse students within the ASD category more closely, with attention to the potential underservice of ethnic and linguistic minority populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1053451212454168">Hess, Morrier, Heflin, &amp; Ivey, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1053451212454168">Mandell et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1053451212454168">Travers et al., in press</xref>). This body of research points to the need for improved early screening and detection practices targeting racially and linguistically diverse groups, as children from minority groups may be less likely to receive timely clinical diagnosis of ASD outside of the school setting, their parents potentially relying on special education screening and assessment for ASD identification. In the meantime, school personnel can increase their knowledge of ASD and diverse cultures, build strong connections with families that value and honor their preferences and cultural differences, and implement evidence-based strategies to ensure all students have access to an accurate diagnosis and effective service delivery to address the growing number of students and families impacted by ASD.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab>. (<year>2000</year>). <source>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders</source> (<edition>4th ed.</edition>, Text Revision). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>American Speech-Language-Hearing Association</collab>. (<year>2006</year>). <source>Principles for speech-language pathologists in diagnosis, assessment, and treatment of autism spectrum across the life span</source> [Technical report]. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.asha.org/docs/html/TR2006-00143.html">http://www.asha.org/docs/html/TR2006-00143.html</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Prevalence of autism spectrum disorders: Autism and Developmental Disabilities Monitoring Network, United States, 2011</article-title>. <source>MMWR Surveillance Summaries</source>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coonrod</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Early concerns of parents of children with autistic and nonautistic disorders</article-title>. <source>Infants and Young Children</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Daley</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The need for cross-cultural research on the pervasive developmental disorders</article-title>. <source>Transcultural Psychiatry</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>550</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Daley</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>From symptom recognition to diagnosis: Children with autism in urban India</article-title>. <source>Social Science Medicine</source>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1323</fpage>–<lpage>1335</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Munson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . .Varley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Randomized, controlled trial of an intervention for toddlers with autism: The Early Start Denver Model</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>125</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2009-0958</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dyches</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>, <month>January</month> <day>18</day>). <article-title>Assessing diverse students with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>The ASHA Leader</source>. Retrieved from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.asha.org/Publications/leader/2011/110118/Assessing-Diverse-Students-With-Autism-Spectrum-Disorders.htm#2">http://www.asha.org/Publications/leader/2011/110118/Assessing-Diverse-Students-With-Autism-Spectrum-Disorders.htm#2</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The beginnings of federal help for young children with disabilities</article-title>. <source>Topics in Early Childhood Special Education</source>, <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guralnick</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>International perspectives on early intervention: A search for common ground</article-title>. <source>Journal of Early Intervention</source>, <volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whalon</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>20 ways to promote academic engagement and communication of children with autism spectrum disorder in inclusive settings</article-title>. <source>Intervention in School and Clinic</source>, <volume>44</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1053451207310346</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrier</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heflin</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ivey</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Autism treatment survey: Services received by children with autism spectrum disorders in public school classrooms</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>961</fpage>–<lpage>971</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McPartland</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Volkmar</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Asperger syndrome</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Volkmar</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of autism and pervasive developmental disorders</source> (pp. <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Teaching Asian American children</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Teaching students with moderate/severe disabilities, including autism: Strategies for second language learners in inclusive settings</source> (pp. <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Springfield, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Charles C Thomas</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mandell</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Listerud</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pinto-Martin</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Race differences in the age at diagnosis among Medicaid-eligible children with autism</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>1447</fpage>–<lpage>1453</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mandell</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zubritsky</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Factors associated with age of diagnosis among children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>116</volume>, <fpage>1480</fpage>–<lpage>1486</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mandell</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wiggins</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DiGuiseppi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Durkin</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Racial/ethnic disparities in the identification of children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source>, <volume>99</volume>, <fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>498</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amanti</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neff</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Funds of knowledge for teaching: Using a qualitative approach to connect homes and classrooms</article-title>. <source>Theory Into Practice</source>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morrier</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heflin</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Ethnic disproportionality in students with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Multicultural Education</source>, <volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Research Council</collab>. (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Educating children with autism. Committee on Educational Interventions for Children with Autism</article-title>. <source>Division of Behavioral and Social Sciences and Education</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academy Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Noland</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Screening and identifying children with autism spectrum disorders in the public school system: The development of a model process</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Obiakor</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>The eight-step multicultural approach: Learning and teaching with a smile</source>. <publisher-loc>Dubuque, IA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kendall/Hunt</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ozonoff</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Messinger</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yirmiya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zwaigenbaum</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>…Stone</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Recurrence risk for autism spectrum disorders: A baby siblings research consortium study</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>128</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>e1</fpage>–<lpage>e8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pruncho</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burant</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>African American and White mothers with chronic disabilities: Care giving burden and satisfaction</article-title>. <source>Family Relations</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>346</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reichow</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolery</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Comprehensive synthesis of early intensive behavioral interventions for young children with autism based on the UCLA Young Autism Project model</article-title>. <source>Journal of Autism and Other Developmental Disorders</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>H. V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forde</surname><given-names>T. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Addressing diversity in schools: Culturally responsive pedagogy</source>. Retrieved from the National Center for Culturally Responsive Educational Systems website: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nccrest.org/index.html">http://www.nccrest.org/index.html</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rogers-Dunlan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blancher</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>African-American families, religion, and disability: A conceptual framework</article-title>. <source>Mental Retardation</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>226</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schertz</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hurwitz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benner</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Principles of early intervention reflected in toddler research in autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Topics in Early Childhood Special Education</source>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0271121410382460</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shattuck</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The contribution of diagnostic substitution to the growing administrative prevalence of autism in U.S. special education</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>117</volume>, <fpage>1028</fpage>–<lpage>1037</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sontag</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schacht</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Family diversity and patterns of service utilization in early intervention</article-title>. <source>Journal of Early Intervention</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>444</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Travers</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tincani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krezmien</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>in press</year>). <article-title>A multiyear national profile of racial disparity in autism identification</article-title>. <source>Journal of Special Education</source> [Advance online publication]. <access-date>Retrieved September 22, 2011</access-date>, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sed.sagepub.com/content/early/2011/07/28/0022466911416247">http://sed.sagepub.com/content/early/2011/07/28/0022466911416247</ext-link>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022466911416247</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trohanis</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Progress in providing services to young children with special needs and their families: An overview to and update on the implementation of the Individuals With Disabilities Education Act (IDEA)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Early Intervention</source>, <volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>140</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soodak</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shogren</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Families, professionals, and exceptionality: Positive outcomes through partnerships and trust</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilder</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dyches</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Obiakor</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Algozzine</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Multicultural perspectives on teaching students with autism</article-title>. <source>Focus on Autism and Other Developmental Disabilities</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilder</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Obiakor</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The myth of socioeconomic dissonance: Working with homeless students in special education contexts</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Utley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rotatori</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Obiakor</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Advances in special education: Psychology of effective education for learners with exceptionalities</source> (pp. <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>415</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Stamford, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>JAI</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1053451212454168">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Winzer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mazurek</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Special education in multicultural contexts</source>. <publisher-loc>Upper Saddle River, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice-Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>