<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjcx</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Correctional Health Care</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1078-3458</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1940-5200</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1078345812458245</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1078345812458245</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Commentary</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Treatment of Older and Elderly Inmates Within Prisons</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Stal</surname>
<given-names>Marina</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MA</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1078345812458245">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1078345812458245"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1078345812458245">
<label>1</label>Teachers College at Columbia University, New York, NY, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1078345812458245">Marina Stal, MA, 7522 19th Ave., Brooklyn, NY 11214 USA Email: <email>mstal3965@gmail.com</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>69</fpage>
<lpage>73</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">NCCHC</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>An increase in the number of older and elderly inmates in the prison system has sparked controversy regarding current procedures and programs as well as possible solutions. Preservation of human and constitutional rights while maintaining appropriate punishment under the same Constitution and increased fiscal expenditures has called into question whether the correctional system is the correct setting for older and elderly inmates. The changing population in prisons has led to an increase in medical care expenses, causing some states to implement early release programs or to build separate facilities for the geriatric population. Statistics from the U.S. Department of Justice and the Federal Bureau of Prisons in conjunction with empirical studies create a foundation that allows for a comprehensive survey of the problems, current protocols, and prospective practices.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>older inmates</kwd>
<kwd>prisoners</kwd>
<kwd>correctional health care</kwd>
<kwd>Eighth Amendment</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In an article published by CNN in November 2009, Rich Hallworth, chief executive officer at Prison Health Services, Inc., was quoted as saying, “I would argue that the health care that is rendered behind bars is better than what is received in the general population” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1078345812458245">Chen, 2009</xref>, para.15, line 1). That statement may seem unusual, but the opinion Hallworth puts forth is a reality that can be traced back to the U.S. Constitution’s Bill of Rights. The rights granted by the Constitution have created a highly revered society that is largely balanced and harmonious. Individuals who choose to act outside the boundaries of acceptable behavior, which may involve infringing on another’s rights, are apt to face appropriate consequences; this is particularly true in regard to criminal behavior. Criminals who have been convicted and must complete a prison sentence are no longer seen as members of society, which results in the loss of certain rights. The creators of the Constitution recognized that a just approach to criminals may be problematic and consequently included provisions as a safeguard.</p>
<p>Although the Bill of Rights has numerous applicable amendments, in reference to prisoners, this article focuses on a particular clause of the Eighth Amendment: “. . . nor cruel and unusual punishments inflicted” (U.S. Constitution, Amendment VIII, § 1). This is an obvious preventive measure against actions meant to cause suffering and humiliation, regardless of the severity of the crime. In prisons, this is applicable to not only actions that may be taken but also those that are not. In accordance with the Eighth Amendment, in the case of <italic>Estelle v.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1078345812458245">
<italic>Gamble</italic> (1976</xref>, para.10), the Supreme Court ruled that “deliberate indifference to serious medical needs of prisoners constitutes the unnecessary and wanton infliction of pain.” More recently, the Supreme Court expanded on this ruling in the case of <italic>Helling v.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1078345812458245">
<italic>McKinney</italic> (1993)</xref> by stating that prison administrators cannot “ignore a condition…that is sure or very likely to cause serious illness and needless suffering.”</p>
<p>Going back to Hallworth’s comment, it seems appropriate that health care for inmates is at least adequate, as neglect of medical care is in clear violation of the Eighth Amendment. Court rulings referenced by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1078345812458245">Meyer and Weaver (2006</xref>; e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1078345812458245">
<italic>Knecht v. Gilman</italic>, 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1078345812458245">
<italic>Washington v. Harper</italic>, 1990</xref>) show an awareness of mental health in prisons, further expanding the concept of satisfactory health care in prisons to include mental health.</p>
<p>According to a Bureau of Justice Statistics report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1078345812458245">Stephan, 2004</xref>), in 2001 the annual operating cost per inmate in state facilities was $22,650; in facilities under the jurisdiction of the Federal Bureau of Prisons, the annual operating cost per inmate was $22,632. Undoubtedly, inmates requiring supplementary medical assistance result in an increase in state and federal expenditures. In 2001, spending on medical care alone for state prisoners amounted to $3.3 billion, and the Federal Bureau of Prisons disclosed a $210.57 million increase for total health care costs between 2000 and 2004 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1078345812458245">U.S. Department of Justice, 2005</xref>). While the growing prison population is an understandable factor in the increasing prison expenses, it is the increase in the older population of inmates that is an underestimated yet considerable contributor.</p>
<sec id="section1-1078345812458245">
<title>Numbers and Health Concerns of Older Inmates</title>
<p>Studies involving older inmates inadvertently formed a standard that labels inmates aged 50+ or 55+ as “older” (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1078345812458245">Aday, 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1078345812458245">2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1078345812458245">Gallagher, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1078345812458245">Zimbardo, 1994</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1078345812458245">Uzoaba (1998</xref>) produced a definition for “elderly” as individuals of age 65 and older. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1078345812458245">Aday (2006</xref>) describes older inmates as belonging to one of three categories: those incarcerated after age 50, those incarcerated prior to 50 but serving a long sentence, and those who are “career criminals” and are consistently imprisoned. According to the Bureau of Justice Statistics, as of June 2008, the estimated number of inmates aged 50 and above, both male and female, held in state or federal prisons or in local jails was 199,700, or approximately 8.6% of the total; elderly inmates accounted for 0.79% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1078345812458245">West &amp; Sabol, 2009</xref>). In contrast, in 2001, only 2.5% of the inmate population was over age 55 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1078345812458245">Beck, Harrison, &amp; Karberg, 2002</xref>). It is well documented that baby boomers are reaching the ranks of the older and elderly, thereby increasing the general older population. It may be shocking to learn that approximately 42.6% of older inmates, compared to 28.5% of those aged 45 to 54, are imprisoned for violent felonies such as sexual crimes, homicide, and aggravated assault (Aday, 2004).</p>
<p>The inclusion of inmates in jails may skew the estimates; however, there are two general conclusions that can be drawn from these statistics: (a) The number of older inmates is clearly increasing and (b) a considerable number of them are incarcerated for appalling crimes. These conclusions help explain why so much concern exists about this particular population, and why some propose rather extreme measures as possible ways to alleviate the fiscal problems. Bureau of Justice Statistics findings regarding inmates’ medical problems show that 68.5% of state inmates and 60% of federal inmates age 45 and older were experiencing medical problems at the time the data were collected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1078345812458245">Maruschak, 2008</xref>). Furthermore, 21.7% of the older inmates in state prisons and 22.9% in federal prisons underwent surgery after they were incarcerated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1078345812458245">Maruschak, 2008</xref>). In addition, older inmates are more likely to present with chronic health problems such as hypertension, diabetes, arthritis, cancer, emphysema, and kidney and heart problems (Aday, 2004). Considering that these are individuals incarcerated for a slew of felonies, these are staggering numbers. At the same time, it is evident that the corrections system is doing all it can to comply with the Eighth Amendment and preserve the rights of inmates to be free from cruel and unusual punishment by way of medical neglect (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1078345812458245">
<italic>Helling v. McKinney</italic>, 1993</xref>).</p>
<p>Mental health issues are another cause of concern in the prison system. In 1999, prisoners between the ages of 45 and 54 accounted for 20% of state and 10% of federal prisoners identified as mentally ill; findings for prisoners 55 and older were similar: 15.6% and 8.9% in state and federal prisons, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1078345812458245">Ditton, 1999</xref>). The following year it was found that 39.6% of state inmates and 36.1% of federal inmates were categorized as having a mental health problem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1078345812458245">Beck &amp; Maruschak, 2001</xref>). These numbers may not amount to much by themselves, but taking into account that 33.8% of state inmates and 24% of federal inmates received treatment following admission (e.g., overnight hospital stay, prescribed medications, professional therapy), it becomes clearer that inmates’ medical problems receive considerable attention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1078345812458245">Beck &amp; Maruschak, 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1078345812458245">Vito and Wilson (1985</xref>) call attention to other difficulties faced by older inmates. Although adjustment to imprisonment can be difficult regardless of age, older inmates may have difficulty adjusting to the new and complex environment. As prisons were not designed for comfort, the physical environment itself, with its minimal space, lack of privacy, and generally uncomfortable conditions, creates a challenging setting for older inmates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1078345812458245">Vito &amp; Wilson, 1985</xref>). Florence Caesar, a 64-year-old inmate at the Pennsylvania State Correctional Institution at Graterford, describes how younger inmates “have absolutely no respect for people with age. . . They stampede through us and knock us down—they don’t care you got a cane or a walker” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1078345812458245">DiFilippo, 2006</xref>). Although there is no empirical data regarding the prevalence of these issues using the three categories of older inmates proposed by Aday (2004), it seems a logical hypothesis that those incarcerated for the first time would have greater struggles.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1078345812458245">
<title>Policies and Perspectives on Incarceration of Older Inmates</title>
<p>Evidently, the increase in the number of older inmates creates a multifaceted predicament that must be addressed. A study in the <italic>Journal of the American Geriatrics Society</italic> conveys a position that has been highly ignored, that “the incarceration of the elderly poses fundamental questions of how we as a society treat our elders” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1078345812458245">Williams et al., 2006</xref>). The moral implications of the incarceration and care of older inmates resound beyond prisons, as members of society are inadvertently involved whether by relation, taxpayer responsibilities, or altruistic desires to help. Policies that have been proposed as potential solutions include early release or release into hospice care. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1078345812458245">Williams and colleagues (2006</xref>) call attention to an important question: “What do we want to do with a prisoner who is so demented he doesn’t remember his name, or who has had a stroke and is completely paralyzed?” Confining such individuals creates a pseudo-nursing home environment, which creates considerable changes in the prison dynamics.</p>
<p>States are attempting to assuage the conflict by various policies with the goal of maintaining the Eighth Amendment rights of the older prisoners while retaining the necessary purpose of the corrections system. A bill proposed in California would allow “nonviolent elderly prisoners to be released into hospice care or monitored with ankle bracelets” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1078345812458245">Chen, 2009</xref>). Officials from Georgia, New York, and Virginia are following similar strategies, granting early release to ailing and dying older inmates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1078345812458245">Chen, 2009</xref>, para. 16, lines 1–3). Carol McAdoo of the National Hospice and Palliative Care Organization points out that older inmates can be placed in separate facilities in the prison complex as a measure to consolidate costs. McAdoo cites Virginia and Pennsylvania as examples of states that have built geriatric prison facilities as a “minihospital” model as a way to confine yet care for the older inmates.</p>
<p>There are numerous opponents to the potential solutions regarding older inmates. One of the primary valid arguments is that regardless of age, the individual is incarcerated and serving a sentence because he or she has committed a crime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1078345812458245">DiFilippo, 2006</xref>). Jeffrey Beard, former director of the Pennsylvania Department of Corrections, concurs and emphasizes that a large percentage of older inmates are murderers and rapists, which questions whether age is a valid reason to truncate a potential life sentence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1078345812458245">DiFilippo, 2006</xref>). People who have been victims at the hands of the inmates, along with Will Marling, executive director of the National Organization for Victim Assistance in Virginia, believe that “A life sentence should mean life” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1078345812458245">Chen, 2009</xref>, para. 18, line 1). Speaking on behalf of victims, Marling said they believe that if released, the offender will continue to commit crimes; sadly, there is truth to their fears. George David Smith, 79, is considered a career criminal who was able to commute his life sentence but is back in prison due to numerous parole violations; nonetheless, he remains unrepentant for his crimes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1078345812458245">DiFilippo, 2006</xref>). A more recent example is that of Theodore Sypnier, 100, who was released from prison after serving a sentence for child molestation; district attorney Frank Sedita says, “He is an unrepentant child molester who has been doing this…for 60 years” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1078345812458245">Michel, 2009</xref>, para. 10, line 4).</p>
<p>Attempting to resolve issues resulting from the increase in older and elderly prisoners seems to lead to an impasse. It seems that the answers to this predicament are caught in an intricate balance of preserving rights, maintaining humane morals, financial considerations, and a muddle of differing opinions. In the end, it is unknown whether keeping an inmate imprisoned or granting release will prevent a future crime. Inadequate provision of care may result in a violation of the Eighth Amendment; yet release from prison may provide an opportunity for the inmate to commit another crime. This issue affects everyone, either directly or indirectly, so it would seem that a priority would be a comprehensive examination of the current state in prisons, not only from a federal and state perspective but also from the dissenters’ standpoint. The first step to solving this problem has been done: The problem has been identified.</p>
<p>A recent decision made by the Supreme Court inadvertently, or perhaps intentionally, affects the pervasiveness of this problem. On May 17, 2010, the Supreme Court ruled that “federal law allows…the civil confinement of a mentally ill, sexually dangerous federal prisoner beyond the date he would otherwise be released” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1078345812458245">
<italic>United States v. Comstock</italic> et al., 2010</xref>). Rationale for this decision included the use of the Eighth Amendment, as such prisoners are believed to be of harm to society as well as their fellow prisoners. Theoretically, this could mean that an individual deemed a sexual predator or mentally ill could remain in prison endlessly. Adhering to the constitutionality of the Supreme Court, it is understandable how such a decision was reached. The question becomes what will happen to the older inmates as funding is further allotted to other prisoners, remaining imprisoned only for their crime. As this ruling is enacted, it will be a challenge for the government to decide on an appropriate and satisfactory way to balance the needs of all involved. As always, it is much preferred that regardless of criminality, respect and care for the elderly remains a priority.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-1078345812458245">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author disclosed no conflicts of interest with respect to the authorship and/or publication of this article. For information about <italic>JCHC</italic>’s disclosure policy, please see the Self-Study Exam.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1078345812458245">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aday</surname>
<given-names>R. H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Aging in prison: A case study of new elderly offenders</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Offender Therapy and Comparative Criminology</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1177/0306624X9403800108</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aday</surname>
<given-names>R. H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Aging prisoners: Crisis in American corrections</source>. <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Praeger</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aday</surname>
<given-names>R. H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Aging prisoners</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Berkman</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Oxford handbook of social work and aging</source> (pp. <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harrison</surname>
<given-names>P. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Karberg</surname>
<given-names>J. C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Prison and jail inmates at midyear 2001</source> <comment>(BJS Bulletin NCJ 191702)</comment>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bureau of Justice Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maruschak</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Mental health treatment in state prisons, 2000</source> <comment>(BJS Special Report NCJ 188215)</comment>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bureau of Justice Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009, November</year>). <source>Prison health-care costs rise as inmates grow older and sicker</source>. <publisher-name>CNN Justice</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cnn.com/2009/CRIME/11/13/aging.inmates/index.html">http://www.cnn.com/2009/CRIME/11/13/aging.inmates/index.html</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>DiFilippo</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006, May</year>). <article-title>Growing old behind bars: Aging inmates raise questions from health care to whether they should be sprung</article-title>. <source>Philadelphia Daily News</source>. <comment>Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sentencing.nj.gov/downloads/pdf/articles/2006/May2006/story15.pdf">http://sentencing.nj.gov/downloads/pdf/articles/2006/May2006/story15.pdf</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ditton</surname>
<given-names>P. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Mental health and treatment of inmates and probationers</source> <comment>(BJS Special Report NCJ 174463)</comment>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bureau of Justice Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Estelle</surname>
<given-names>v.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <comment>Gamble, 429 U.S. 97</comment> (<year>1976</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gallagher</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Elders in prison: Health and well-being of older inmates</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Law and Psychiatry</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>333</lpage>.<bold> </bold>
<comment>doi:10.1016/S0160-2527(00)00080-7.2</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Helling</surname>
<given-names>v.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <comment>McKinney, (91-1958), 509 U.S. 25</comment> (<year>1993</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Knecht</surname>
<given-names>v.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <comment>Gilman, 488 F.2d 1136 (8th Cir</comment>. <year>1973</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Maruschak</surname>
<given-names>L. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Medical problems of prisoners</source> <comment>(BJS Report NCJ 221740). Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bjs.gov/index.cfm?ty=pbdetail&amp;iid=1097">http://www.bjs.gov/index.cfm?ty=pbdetail&amp;iid=1097</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weaver</surname>
<given-names>C. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Law and mental health: A case-based approach</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Michel</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009, December 8</year>). <article-title>Oldest sex offender about to be freed here</article-title>. <source>The Buffalo News</source>, p. A1.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stephan</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>State prison expenditures, 2001</source> <comment>(BJS Special Report NCJ 202949)</comment>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bureau of Justice Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="other">
<comment>United States v. Comstock et al.</comment>, <year>2010</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="other">
<comment>U.S. Constitution, Amendment VIII, § 1</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">U.S. Department of Justice, Office of the Inspector General</collab>. (<year>2005</year>). <source>Audit of the Federal Bureau of Prisons pharmacy services</source> <comment>(Audit Report 06-03). Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.justice.gov/oig/reports/BOP/a0603/final.pdf">http://www.justice.gov/oig/reports/BOP/a0603/final.pdf</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Uzoaba</surname>
<given-names>J. H. E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Managing older offenders: Where do we stand?</source> <comment>(Research report)</comment>. Ottawa, US: <publisher-name>Research Branch Correctional Service of Canada</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vito</surname>
<given-names>G. F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>D. G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Forgotten people: Elderly inmates</article-title>. <source>Federal Probation</source>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="other">
<collab collab-type="author">Washington v. Harper, 494 US 210</collab> (<year>1990</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>West</surname>
<given-names>H. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sabol</surname>
<given-names>W. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Prison inmates at midyear 2008—Statistical tables</source> <comment>(BJS Report NCJ 225619)</comment>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bureau of Justice Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>B. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lindquist</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sudore</surname>
<given-names>R. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Strupp</surname>
<given-names>H. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Willmott</surname>
<given-names>D. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walter</surname>
<given-names>L. C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Being old and doing time: Functional impairment and adverse experiences of geriatric female prisoners</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Geriatrics Society</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>702</fpage>–<lpage>707</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1078345812458245">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zimbardo</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>Transforming California’s prisons into expensive old age homes for felons: Enormous hidden costs and consequences for California’s taxpayers</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Center on Juvenile and Criminal Justice</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>