<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CPJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcpj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Pediatr (Phila)</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical Pediatrics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0009-9228</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-2707</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0009922812471714</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0009922812471714</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Resident Rounds</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Newborn With Hair Loss</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Fyall</surname><given-names>Katherine Marie</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812471714">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>Catherine A.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MS, CGC</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812471714">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Morrell</surname><given-names>Dean S.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812471714">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0009922812471714"><label>1</label>University of North Carolina Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0009922812471714">Dean S. Morrell, Department of Dermatology, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 410 Market Street Suite 400, Chapel Hill, NC 27516, USA Email: <email>morrell@med.unc.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>Unique cases written by pediatric residents with a faculty member.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>52</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>187</fpage>
<lpage>189</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0009922812471714" sec-type="cases">
<title>Case Presentation</title>
<p>An 8-month-old boy was referred to the pediatric dermatology clinic from his primary care physician for hair loss. According to his mother, the boy was born with a full head of hair but without eyebrows or eyelashes. At around 2 to 3 weeks old, he began losing his hair circumferentially around the sides and back of his head. At his first clinic evaluation, the areas on his head as well as his eyebrows were completely hairless, but he had sparse small eyelashes. His mother reported no pruritus or any indication of irritation or tenderness. He received clobetasol scalp solution for presumed alopecia areata with ophiasis presentation and was asked to follow up in a few weeks. On return 1 month later, he had no new hair growth or loss. Additionally, his mother reported that he had developed asymptomatic “bumpy” skin around his nose and on his extremities. He was otherwise healthy and was developing normally after an uncomplicated pregnancy and delivery. He had appropriate teeth and nail development for his age and had no known sweating or hearing abnormalities. There was also no known family history of skin disease, hair loss, or autoimmune conditions. Further questioning by genetics revealed consanguinity.</p>
<p>Clinical examination revealed a well-demarcated nonscarring alopecia involving the occipitoparietal region in an ophiasis pattern as well as the temporal regions in an androgenic pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0009922812471714">Figure 1</xref>). A hair pull test around the vertex and frontal areas was negative. Eyebrows were completely absent and there were small eyelashes noted. He had tiny milia-like follicular papules on the upper outer arms, thighs, knees, and facial cheeks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0009922812471714">Figure 2</xref>). A biopsy was not performed.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0009922812471714" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Well-demarcated, nonscarring alopecia involving the occipitoparietal and temporal regions. There is also an absence of eyebrows and minimal eyelash growth</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812471714-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-0009922812471714" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>On the cheeks, upper outer arms, thighs, and knees are tiny milia-like follicular papules</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812471714-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0009922812471714">
<title>Clinical Diagnosis</title>
<p>Atrichia with papular lesions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0009922812471714">
<title>Hospital Course</title>
<p>After receiving a clinical diagnosis of atrichia with papular lesions (APL), the steroid scalp solution was discontinued and ammonium lactate cream was prescribed for the papular lesions. The family was counseled about genetic testing to look for a causative mutation in the associated gene, human homolog of the mouse “hairless” (<italic>HR</italic>) gene, which was available on a research basis. They met with a genetic counselor and agreed to send blood for genotyping to Columbia University. Almost a year and a half later, his scalp, eyelash, and eyebrow alopecia was unchanged. DNA sequencing analysis at Columbia identified a homozygous mutation within exon 2 of the <italic>HR</italic> gene, called R33X, confirming the diagnosis of APL.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0009922812471714" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="section5-0009922812471714">
<title>Clinical Findings in APL</title>
<p>Atrichia with papular lesions (papular atrichia, OMIM 209500) is a rare, autosomal recessive genodermatosis characterized by irreversible loss of head and body hair and the development of keratin-filled cysts on the body. Affected individuals are typically born with normal appearing neonatal hair, which is gradually lost and never replaced by adult terminal hair. Hair is typically absent from the scalp, axillae, and body although some small eyebrows or eyelashes may be present. The papular lesions usually develop around 1 to 2 years of age but can arise at any time within the first decade of life.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922812471714">1</xref></sup> They most commonly involve the face, scalp, and extremities, particularly the elbows and knees, and they tend to increase in number as the individual ages.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0009922812471714">2</xref></sup> Individuals with APL have otherwise normal development, including teeth, hair, sweating, and hearing, which importantly distinguishes the disease from ectodermal dysplasia with associated atrichia. Histopathologic examination reveals empty infundibulae with irregular epithelial structures or cysts replacing the lower two thirds of hair follicles and various sizes of keratinizing epithelial cysts at all levels of the dermis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0009922812471714">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>The diagnostic criteria for APL were updated in 2008 by Yip et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0009922812471714">4</xref></sup> based on a literature review and personal observations. The authors recommend that 4 of 5 major criteria to be present for diagnosis and also provide 5 supplementary minor criteria. The major criteria include infantile atrichia, development of characteristic papular lesions, histological scalp findings, <italic>HR</italic> gene mutation, and clinical and/or molecular exclusion of vitamin D–dependent rickets (VDDR), specifically type II. VDDR-II is caused by a mutation in the vitamin D receptor, which renders it resistant to vitamin D3. Some patients with VDDR-II have alopecia that is clinically and microscopically similar to APL in addition to their findings of vitamin D deficiency such as early-onset rickets, hypocalcemia, and secondary hyperparathyroidism. The diseases likely share a common pathogenic pathway with regard to follicular development.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0009922812471714">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0009922812471714">5</xref></sup> The minor criteria that support the diagnosis include a family history of consanguinity, absence of other body hair, whitish hypopigmented streaks on the scalp, normal growth and development, and lack of response to any treatment modality. It is important to note that a scalp biopsy is not required for a diagnosis when clinical and genetic findings support APL.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0009922812471714">
<title>Molecular Basis of APL</title>
<p>Mutations in the human homolog of the mouse “hairless” (<italic>HR</italic>) gene have been implicated in the development of APL. Mutations in the <italic>HR</italic> gene are also responsible for another genetic cause of hair loss, alopecia universalis congenital, which is clinically distinguished by the <italic>absence</italic> of papular lesions. The <italic>HR</italic> gene is found on chromosome 8p21.2 and encodes a single zinc-finger transcription factor, which is highly expressed in the brain and skin.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0009922812471714">6</xref></sup> The <italic>HR</italic> protein functions as a co-repressor of multiple nuclear receptors, including the vitamin-D receptor (VDR). It has been hypothesized that VDR-HR suppresses gene expression during specific phases of the hair cycle. With loss of this repressive activity, there is inappropriate expression of genes that disrupt the normal hair cycle process.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0009922812471714">7</xref></sup> Histologically, the process is seen as a disintegration of the lower two thirds of the hair follicle which results in failure to enter anagen phase. Remnant structures are likely responsible for producing the characteristic epithelial outgrowths and dermal cysts.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0009922812471714">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>The database of allelic series continues to expand as more than 30 different nonsense, missense, insertion, and deletion mutations have been reported in the <italic>HR</italic> gene.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0009922812471714">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0009922812471714">8</xref></sup> Although the majority of cases of APL involve homozygous mutations, sporadic cases of compound heterozygous mutations in nonconsanguineous families have been identified over the past decade.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922812471714">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0009922812471714">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0009922812471714">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0009922812471714"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0009922812471714"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0009922812471714">12</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0009922812471714" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>It is important to consider APL when a newborn or infant presents with hair loss. Although alopecia totalis caused by autoimmune destruction of the follicle is a more common cause of hair loss, APL should not be overlooked in the differential diagnosis. Prompt diagnosis will prevent the child from undergoing invasive diagnostic procedures and unnecessary treatments for autoimmune alopecia. Genetic counseling is also beneficial for patient understanding of inheritance patterns and disease etiology.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0009922812471714">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Michailidis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Theos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zlotogorski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinez-Mir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christiano</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Atrichia with papular lesions resulting from novel compound heterozygous mutations in the human hairless gene</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Dermatol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>E79</fpage>-<lpage>E82</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0009922812471714">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zlotogorski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Panteleyev</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aita</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christiano</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical and molecular diagnostic criteria of congenital atrichia with papular lesions</article-title>. <source>J Invest Dermatol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>887</fpage>-<lpage>890</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0009922812471714">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schein-Goldshmid</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ben-Izhak</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sprecher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The alopecias associated with vitamin D-dependent rickets type IIA and with hairless gene mutations: a comparative clinical, histologic, and immunohistochemical study</article-title>. <source>Arch Dermatol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>141</volume>:<fpage>343</fpage>-<lpage>351</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0009922812471714">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horev</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zlotogorski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Atrichia with papular lesions: a report of three novel human hairless gene mutations and a revision of diagnostic criteria</article-title>. <source>Acta Derm Venereol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>346</fpage>-<lpage>349</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0009922812471714">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Djabali</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Atrichia caused by mutations in the vitamin D receptor gene is a phenocopy of generalized atrichia caused by mutations in the hairless gene</article-title>. <source>J Invest Dermatol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>612</fpage>-<lpage>617</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0009922812471714">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Atrichia congenita with papular lesions</article-title>. <source>Indian J Dermatol Venereol Leprol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>70</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0009922812471714">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malloy</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Interactions of the vitamin D receptor with the corepressor hairless: analysis of hairless mutants in atrichia with papular lesions</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>282</volume>:<fpage>25231</fpage>-<lpage>25239</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0009922812471714">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wajid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shimomura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christiano</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mutations in the hairless gene underlie APL in three families of Pakistani origin</article-title>. <source>J Dermatol Sci</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0009922812471714">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Henn</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zlotogorski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinez-Mir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christiano</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Atrichia with papular lesions resulting from compound heterozygous mutations in the hairless gene: a lesson for differential diagnosis of alopecia universalis</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>519</fpage>-<lpage>523</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0009922812471714">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ashoor</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenstein</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinez-Mir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zlotogorski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christiano</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Novel compound heterozygous nonsense mutations in the hairless gene causing atrichia with papular lesions</article-title>. <source>J Dermatol Sci</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0009922812471714">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Indelman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lestringant</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sprecher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Compound heterozygosity for mutations in the hairless gene causes atrichia with papular lesions</article-title>. <source>Br J Dermatol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>148</volume>:<fpage>553</fpage>-<lpage>557</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0009922812471714">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Paller</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Varigos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Metzker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Compound heterozygous mutations in the hairless gene in atrichia with papular lesions</article-title>. <source>J Invest Dermatol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>430</fpage>-<lpage>432</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>