<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sprsh</journal-id>
<journal-title>Perspectives in Public Health</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1757-9139</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1757-9147</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1757913912457315c</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1757913912457315c</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Mastering Public Health: Essential Skills for Effective Practice</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>132</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>254</fpage>
<lpage>254</lpage>
<product>
<source>Mastering Public Health: Essential Skills for Effective Practice</source>. Edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>Barry S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gaufin</surname><given-names>Joyce R.</given-names></name>
</person-group>. Published by <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>USA</publisher-loc>. Paperback, pp.<page-count count="353"/>. Price <price>£38.50</price>. ISBN:<isbn>978-0199753970</isbn></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Royal Society for Public Health 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Royal Society for Public Health</copyright-holder>
</permissions></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<graphic id="img4-1757913912457315" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1757913912457315-img4.tif"/>
<p>There are a lot of books on management and leadership out there, as anyone who has killed time wandering around an airport branch of WH Smith will know. Indeed, search for ‘leadership’ on Amazon and you will be rewarded with a choice of 60,000 books. The authors of ‘Mastering Public Health: essential skills for effective practice’ are brave to try for a niche in this crowded market, aiming to: <italic>“improve your performance and productivity within your organization</italic> (<italic>sic</italic>)”, but their courage pays off.</p>
<p>The book <italic>“focuses on the day-to-day practical skills and competencies”</italic> needed to actually get anything done. It comprises three sections: communication, administration and management, and leadership; each subdivided into topics. Communication, for example, includes communicating with the public, persuasion and advocacy, presentation skills, written communication and practicing cultural competence. Following each chapter, commentaries bring the advice to life through personal views and case studies. Topics are dealt with in a practical, down-to-earth style; abstract statements and theory are minimal. This is a how-to book, containing the sort of advice that you might hope to get from an attentive supervisor. Instead of starting with defining leadership, for example, we jump straight into ‘Creating a vision and inspiring others’. The content does occasionally stray into overly familiar territory (to be clear and concise in written communication, for example) but overall the wisdom and experience of the authors shines through.</p>
<p>The “practicing cultural competence” subsection title may give a clue to the main downside of the book for a UK audience: it has been written for US public health professionals. While this does not affect advice on communication or leadership, the treatment of certain topics (budgeting and quality improvement are two examples) is based within the US system and is therefore difficult to apply to UK practice.</p>
<p>This is a valuable addition to the shelf of those working in public health. Less a textbook than an opportunity to gain a better general understanding of how to practice effectively, it complements texts covering technical aspects of practice (such as, confusingly, another “Mastering Public Health”, used widely for Part A MFPH). Although there is some overlap with UK books – notably the Oxford Handbook – there is enough inspiration and fresh advice here to warrant its place on my bedside table.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig><bold>Dr Anne Swift MB ChB MFPH</bold><break/>
<italic>StR Public Health, East of England Public Health Training Scheme.</italic></sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>