<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MWC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmwc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Media, War &amp; Conflict</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1750-6352</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1750-6360</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1750635212461225c</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1750635212461225c</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Media &amp; Environment: Conflict, Politics and the News</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Maeseele</surname><given-names>Pieter</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1750635212461225">University of Antwerp, Belgium</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>290</fpage>
<lpage>292</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>Libby</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>Media &amp; Environment: Conflict, Politics and the News</source> <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>. <page-count count="205"/> pp., 9 illus. ISBN <isbn>13: 978-0-7456-4401-1</isbn> <price>£55</price> (hbk); ISBN <isbn>13: 978-0-7456-4402-8</isbn> <price>£15.99</price> (pbk).</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Libby Lester’s <italic>Media &amp; Environment: Conflict, Politics and the News</italic> has recently been published amidst a wave of books on media and environmental issues, most notably Anders Hansen’s <italic>Environment, Media and Communication</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1750635212461225">2010</xref>) and Julie Doyle’s <italic>Mediating Climate Change</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1750635212461225">2011</xref>). This illustrates how the ‘issue attention cycle’ concept for environmental issues not only accounts for ‘ups and downs’ in public and media discourses, such as the well-described peaks in the late 1960s, 1980s and mid-2000s, but also for academia in general, and the academic publishing market in particular. Working as a journalist for 15 years for Australian press outlets before entering academia in 2002, the author was an environmental journalist with an Australian broadsheet in the late 1980s, enabling her to experience firsthand many of the phenomena described. She is currently Associate Professor of Journalism, Media and Communications at the University of Tasmania, specializing in environmental conflict, and previously published her PhD on environmental conflicts in Tasmania as <italic>Giving Ground: Media and Environmental Conflict in Tasmania</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1750635212461225">2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Starting from a constructionist perspective, <italic>Media &amp; Environment</italic> puts forward the dual aim of revealing the dynamics and practices behind environmental issues in the news while reflecting on how public understandings, meanings, debates and action regarding the environment are shaped and influenced. To avoid the presumption of a potentially non-existent level of professional, institutional or social cohesion, the volume explicitly starts from an analytical approach that details what news media, sources and audiences are actually <italic>doing</italic> in the context of mediated environmental debates. The author argues that this approach allows us to grasp the complexities, contingencies, contradictions and contestation in mediated processes and practices, leading to a nuanced understanding of the relationship between news media and the environment. Furthermore, by foregrounding politics, conflict and power as key analytical terms, media-centeredness is avoided in favor of the mechanisms and actors shaping the environment as a public issue. This fundamentally media–sociological approach is reflected in the structure of the book which consists of seven chapters, with four chapters focusing on the different levels of the reflexive circuit between: (i) source strategies and news access – focusing on industry and government public relation practitioners, and scientists and lay people (chapter four), with a specific chapter on the environmental movement, its relationship(s) with news media, and the role of protest (chapter five); (ii) journalistic norms, values and practices and their impact on environmental news (chapter three); and (iii) the relationship between media consumption and audience engagement (chapter seven). Three additional chapters focus on the history of media and environmental communication until the birth of modern environmentalism (chapter one), important theoretical discussions, such as Habermas’s public sphere-concept, Thompson’s mediated visibility, the dynamics of issue attention cycles, Herman and Chomsky’s propaganda-model, Wolfsfeld’s and Cottle’s mediated conflict-approaches, and Beck’s risk society (chapter two), and the importance of images, symbols and celebrities in media strategies (chapter six).</p>
<p><italic>Media &amp; Environment</italic> represents a welcome introductory volume on the current state of the field, by carefully tying together known theories, critiques and studies. The most interesting parts of the book are the short case studies from the Tasmanian front, especially in chapters one, five (impact of the internet on movement politics), and six (the discovery and demise of the Tasmanian ‘El Grande’-tree). It must be noted however that the last chapter on audience engagement focuses on how environmental images, words and symbols in television news ‘might’ engage their audiences, not on results from audience research itself.</p>
<p>On a final note, the author’s earlier career in journalism is somehow tangible throughout the book, since the described vulnerability of environmental journalists to accusations of ‘advocacy’ and ‘lacking objectivity’ shines through in her persistence to adopt an ‘objective’ position towards fundamental theoretical (and normative) debates. This is remarkable as ‘conflict’, ‘politics’ and ‘power’ constitute key concepts of the author’s framework, but no distinction is made between the liberal–pluralist and critical tradition in media studies, nor any in-depth analysis of the meaning of these concepts. This affects the explanatory power of the arguments as well as precluding an evaluation of public and media discourses on the extent to which they contribute to democratic debate and citizenship. For example, the high level of media attention and the concomitant framing of climate change as an urgent public problem in the months leading up to the Copenhagen summit would be explained by the author as a clear indication of the permeability of the patterns and barriers in news practices and routines otherwise responsible for reproducing power imbalances. However, we would find no resources on how to understand the standstill and repeated failures, such as structural and cumulative inequalities or the hegemony of neo-liberal discourses and processes of depoliticization. In general, lacking in-depth analyses of existing theoretical, methodological or empirical debates, <italic>Media &amp; Environment</italic> is foremost a useful volume for students looking for an introduction to the field.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1750635212461225">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Mediating Climate Change</source>. <publisher-loc>Farnham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1750635212461225">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Environment, Media and Communication</source> (Routledge Introductions to Environment: Environment and Society Texts). <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1750635212461225">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Giving Ground: Media and Environmental Conflict in Tasmania</source>. <publisher-loc>Hobart</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Quintus Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>