<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjsr</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Service Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1094-6705</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7379</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1094670511426897</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1094670511426897</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Characterizing Value as an Experience</article-title>
<subtitle>Implications for Service Researchers and Managers</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Helkkula</surname>
<given-names>Anu</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1094670511426897">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1094670511426897">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1094670511426897"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kelleher</surname>
<given-names>Carol</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1094670511426897">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1094670511426897">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pihlström</surname>
<given-names>Minna</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1094670511426897">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1094670511426897">
<label>1</label>Hanken School of Economics, Helsinki, Finland</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1094670511426897">
<label>2</label>Espoo University School of Science, Aalto, Finland</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1094670511426897">
<label>3</label>Cranfield School of Management, Bedfordshire, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff4-1094670511426897">
<label>4</label>University College Cork, Cork, Ireland</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1094670511426897">Anu Helkkula, Hanken School of Economics, Arkadiankatu 22, Helsinki 00100, Finland. Email: <email>anu.helkkula@hanken.fi</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>59</fpage>
<lpage>75</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Within contemporary discourse around service-dominant logic, phenomenologically (experientially) determined value has been placed at the center of value discussion. However, a systematic characterization of value in the experience has not been presented to date. In this article, the authors outline four theoretical propositions that describe what value in the experience is, which are then illustrated using a narrative data set. The propositions consider both lived and imaginary value experiences and posit that current service experiences are influenced by previous and anticipated service experiences. The article contributes to the service literature by characterizing value in the experience as an ongoing, iterative circular process of individual, and collective customer sense making, as opposed to a linear, cognitive process restricted to isolated service encounters. The authors recommend that service researchers should consider the use of interpretive methodologies based on the four theoretical propositions outlined in order to better understand the many ways that service customers experience value in their lifeworld contexts, which extend well beyond the service organization’s zone of influence. Service managers should also consider how a richer understanding of past, current, and imaginary value in the context in service customers’ individual lifeworld contexts might generate novel insights for service innovations.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>experience</kwd>
<kwd>phenomenology</kwd>
<kwd>value</kwd>
<kwd>service</kwd>
<kwd>narrative</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1094670511426897">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Customer value has long been considered the next source of competitive advantage for service organizations (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-1094670511426897">Woodruff 1997</xref>). However, service researchers have yet to respond to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-1094670511426897">Woodruff’s (1997)</xref> exhortation to develop “… <italic>richer customer value theory that delves deeply into the customer’s world of product use in their situations</italic>…” (p. 150). While numerous methods and measures have been developed to research customer value, such as customer-perceived value, value-in-use, and value-in-context, value in the experience in the broader context of service customers’ lifeworlds has received limited interest among service researchers. <italic>Lifeworld</italic> (Lebenswelt) refers to a world that is grounded in an individual’s everyday lived experience in which meaning is prioritized in the individual’s social contexts (Husserl [1936] 1970; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1094670511426897">Langdridge 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1094670511426897">Merleau-Ponty [1945] 1962</xref>).</p>
<p>In the 10th foundational premise of service-dominant (S-D) logic, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr88-1094670511426897">Vargo and Lusch (2008)</xref> assert that “… value is always uniquely and phenomenologically determined by the beneficiary …” (p. 7). However, the nature of phenomenological value has not been elaborated or characterized to date. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr95-1094670511426897">Woodruff Smith (2007)</xref> defines phenomenology as the study of phenomena as they appear in an individual’s experiences and identifies different types of experience, for example, perception, imagination, thought, emotion, desire, volition, and action. In this article, we adopt a phenomenological perspective and conceptualize “value in the experience” as individual service customers’ lived experiences of value that extend beyond the current context of service use to also include past and future experiences and service customers’ broader lifeworld contexts. Within this view, “value resides not in the object of consumption, but in the experience of consumption” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1094670511426897">Frow and Payne 2007</xref>, p. 91). Similar to other conceptualizations, value in the experience is a subjective phenomenon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1094670511426897">Holbrook and Hirschman 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1094670511426897">Goulding 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Individual sense making of value in the experience can mean, in a hairstyling context, for example, that a person may choose to go to a new hairdresser simply to try something new even though his or her current hairdresser provides good service at a reasonable price. In addition to the current actual service experience (e.g., servicescape, atmospherics, etc.), the value in the experience of the new hair salon may also be influenced by such factors as previous experiences of hair salons, friends’ stories about their experiences and possible recommendations, the presence of other customers, or the type of day that the customer has had, for example, enjoying a day’s vacation or rushing to the salon after a busy day at the office prior to attending an important evening business function. At first, the service customer may feel awkward with the new hairstyle and doubt if the service was worth paying so much for. However, after receiving positive feedback from others, the value in the experience may cause the service customer to dismiss her concerns about the price, and reflect on how trendy the end result is, and to become more aware of the other types of clients of the same hair salon rather than the price.</p>
<p>Despite this recent interest in value in the experience in current academic discourse within and outside S-D logic, it is apparent that the epistemological and ontological foundations of value in the experience have not been previously characterized in a systematic way in the value literature to date. This article seeks to address this deficit by presenting a conceptual characterization of value in the experience. In doing so, we draw on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1094670511426897">Hart’s (2005)</xref> typology of how concepts can be characterized. To paraphrase Hart, the questions to be addressed in the characterization of value in the experience are as follows: (a) What is value in the experience? (an ontological question); (b) What can be accepted as evidence regarding value in the experience? (an epistemological question); and (c) What methods and techniques should be adopted for collecting data about value in the experience? (a methodological question).</p>
<p>The remainder of the article is organized as follows: First, we examine how customer (perceived) value has been characterized and measured in the literature to date. This is followed by four theoretical propositions that characterize what value in the experience is and a description of each using the hermeneutic spiral (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1094670511426897">Gummesson 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1094670511426897">Heidegger [1927] 1962</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1094670511426897">Husserl [1931] 1967</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1094670511426897">[1936] 1970</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1094670511426897">Jacoby and Braun 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-1094670511426897">Tuomi and Sarajärvi 2003</xref>). Next, we present a range of methods and techniques that are suitable for understanding value in the experience. One such method and technique, namely, the event-based narrative inquiry technique (EBNIT; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1094670511426897">Helkkula and Pihlström 2010</xref>), is subsequently illustrated using a narrative data set that shows how service customers individually and collectively make sense of lived and imaginary value experiences. The article concludes with a discussion of the implications of the propositions characterizing value in the experience for researchers and practitioners and suggests future research directions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1094670511426897">
<title>Value in the Experience and Applicable Evidence</title>
<sec id="section3-1094670511426897">
<title>Existing Characterizations of Customer (Perceived) Value</title>
<p>A review of the extant customer (perceived) value literature reveals that “… <italic>marketing thought is (still) seriously deficient in its understanding of customer value-related phenomena</italic> …” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr93-1094670511426897">Woodruff and Flint 2006</xref>, p. 184). Despite the vast literature on customer (perceived) value, several authors continue to argue that the customer value construct requires further refinement and development (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1094670511426897">Sanchez-Fernandez and Iniesta-Bonillo 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1094670511426897">Sanchez-Fernandez, Iniesta-Bonillo, and Holbrook 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1094670511426897">Smith and Colgate 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-1094670511426897">Woodruff 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-1094670511426897">Zeithaml et al. 2006</xref>). Within the literature, however, there seems to be consensus that value and value creation can be studied either as single universal concepts or from the vantage and contingency perspective of a particular source of value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1094670511426897">Lepak, Smith, and Taylor 2007</xref>). It is therefore possible to consider value from a number of perspectives, including those of the service customer and service provider (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1094670511426897">Payne, Storbacka, and Frow 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1094670511426897">Smith and Colgate 2007</xref>). In this article, we adopt the perspective of individual service customers who experience value, which we term value in the experience.</p>
<p>Many previous studies on customer (perceived) value have assumed that service organizations and their customers perform different predefined roles in relation to value cocreation. The role of the service organization has been viewed as that of predetermining the sources of value in the service offering and delivery, while service customers are primarily viewed as passive buyers and users of a particular service (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1094670511426897">Graf and Maas 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1094670511426897">Shah et al. 2006</xref>). Within this view, value is seen to derive from the characteristics of the firm’s service offering or to stem from the activities of the service organization, as opposed to resulting from the service customers’ activities or efforts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1094670511426897">Clulow, Barry, and Gerstman 2007</xref>). While this is a laudable and notable improvement of a “product-centric” company orientation, this view still seems to promote the belief that value or the benefits to be derived from the consumption of a particular service offering can somehow be largely predetermined by, controlled by, and communicated to customers before or during the service encounter itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1094670511426897">Kelleher and Peppard 2010</xref>). Such perspectives conceptualize customer (perceived) value as a rather objective construct at the expense of a more holistic appreciation of the multidimensional aspects of customer (perceived) value including affective and experiential aspects.</p>
<p>However, more recent definitions of customer (perceived) value emphasize the notion that value stems from service customers’ learned perceptions and preferences based on evaluations of the probable and resulting consequences in certain situations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-1094670511426897">Woodruff 1997</xref>). In contemporary service marketing and management discourse, customer value is no longer “objectified” and reduced to that which is produced or processed for customers; rather, customer value is now considered a phenomenon that relates to customer experience and value-in-use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1094670511426897">Heinonen 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1094670511426897">Heinonen et al. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1094670511426897">Kelleher and Peppard 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1094670511426897">Sandström et al. 2008</xref>;). For example, Sanchez-Fernandez, Iniesta-Bonillo, and Holbrook’s (2009) conceptual framework describes customer value in terms of economic, social, hedonic, and altruistic categories in an effort to capture the intrinsic, extrinsic, affective, and cognitive aspects of customer value in the context of service.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1094670511426897">
<title>Characterizing Value in the Experience</title>
<p>As previously stated, the current discourse around S-D logic has refocused the attention of service scholars and managers on the phenomenological nature of value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1094670511426897">Edvardsson, Tronvoll, and Gruber 2010</xref>). The phenomenological epistemology legitimizes the primacy of individuals’ or, in this case, service customers’ views and subjective experiences as data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1094670511426897">Goulding 2005</xref>). Meaning emerges from individuals’ everyday lived experiences and is prioritized in some form by those individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1094670511426897">Langdridge 2007</xref>; Woodruff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1094670511426897">Smith 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Within the contemporary discourse pertaining to S-D logic, Vargo (2008) uses (but does not thoroughly characterize) the term “value-in-context” as part of the continuing move from the more “goods-dominant” (G-D) logic-focused term “value-in-use.” The use of the term value-in-context emphasizes the notion that it is possible for service customers to experience value even if they do not use or have not had direct experience of the service or the service provider in question. Service customers can, for example, construct future or potential service experiences from their imagination or from other indirect sources, such as the stories and narratives of other people (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1094670511426897">Meyer and Schwager 2007</xref>), or the shared value-in-context experiences of other actors or beneficiaries (Vargo 2008).</p>
<p>In order to define “value in the experience,” we draw on the phenomenological approach and ontologically focus on subjective experience in a social context. Specifically, we consider value in the experience to be the value that is directly or indirectly experienced by service customers within their phenomenological lifeworld contexts. This article proposes that service customers make sense of and experience value in an iterative way, based on their previous experiences or understanding (i.e., preunderstanding). The ontological recognition of the subjective nature of experience predetermines what evidence can be accepted in relation to value in the experience. To outline the authors’ understanding of what can be accepted as data on value in the experience, the latter will be characterized through the presentation and discussion of four theoretical propositions, which are collectively referred to as the VALEX (value in the experience) propositions.</p>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 1:</italic> Value in the experience is individually intrasubjective and socially intersubjective.</p>
<p>Phenomenologically (experientially) determined value is uniquely determined by the beneficiary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-1094670511426897">Vargo and Lusch 2008</xref>), in this case, the service customer and is therefore subjective. According to the phenomenological approach, the intersubjective nature of value in the experience acknowledges service customers’ individual and collective relational engagement with the world and how they seek to make sense of this both at an individual and at a collective level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1094670511426897">Smith, Flowers, and Larkin 2009</xref>). Value in the experience is, therefore, also interactional within the context of service customers’ phenomenologically determined social networks (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1094670511426897">Finsterwalder and Tuzovic 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1094670511426897">Grove and Fisk 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1094670511426897">Palmer and Koenig-Lewis 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-1094670511426897">Vargo and Lusch 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>In addition to value being cocreated through service customers’ integration of the various physical resources provided by service organizations, value also emerges from service customers’ integration of other cultural and social resources, including other service customers, within their lifeworlds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1094670511426897">Arnould, Price, and Malshe 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1094670511426897">Baron and Harris 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1094670511426897">Chronis 2008</xref>). Service customers experience value and infer credibility from other customers based on the shared experiences of value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1094670511426897">Hennig-Thurau et al. 2004</xref>). Therefore, it appears that even if service customers individually experience value, they also tend to share certain type\types of experience\experiences with other service customers, that is, the data are intrasubjective and intersubjective (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1094670511426897">Schutz 1967</xref>). Furthermore, individual customers, as well as groups of customers, may hold common, “generalized” perceptions of phenomena and events within the various social groups to which they belong (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1094670511426897">Johns and Tyas 1997</xref>).</p>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 2:</italic> Value in the experience can be both lived and imaginary.</p>
<p>The interaction between service customer/customers and service provider/providers does not always need to be practically lived. Within the phenomenological perspective, service customers have direct experience of a particular service when they are actually participating in the service encounter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1094670511426897">Meyer and Schwager 2007</xref>). Service customers may also experience value and service as a result of indirect interactions with the service phenomenon, for example, through word-of-mouth recommendations, reviews, or advertisements (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1094670511426897">Meyer and Schwager 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1094670511426897">Miller, Fabian, and Lin 2009</xref>). In addition, value in the experience may incorporate imaginary experiences without any actual contact with the service provider (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1094670511426897">Helkkula 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 3:</italic> Value in the experience is constructed based on previous, current, and imaginary future experiences and is temporal in nature.</p>
<p>As postulated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1094670511426897">Belk (1975)</xref>, “… time may also be measured relative to some past or future event for the situational participant …” (p. 159). Human experience is a dynamic construct that is subject to continuous change as individuals engage with others in their lifeworlds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1094670511426897">Pollio, Henley, and Thompson 1997</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1094670511426897">Pollio, Henley, and Thompson (1997)</xref> further elaborate on the nature of human experience, stating that experience “… is always intensely personal and only infrequently transparent to itself; the meaning of one’s experience frequently changes as it is described and/or reflected upon …” (p. 29). Accordingly, service customers’ experiences of value may iteratively flow back and forth between current, future, and past experiences within a hermeneutic spiral of sense making. Service customers’ imaginary experiences of value, as outlined in the second proposition, may include nostalgic reinterpretations of previous experiences of value that represent service customers’ interpretations or reinterpretations of what might have been or anticipated experiences of what might be in the future (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1094670511426897">Arnould, Price, and Zinkhan 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-1094670511426897">Thompson, Locander, and Pollio 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-1094670511426897">Tynan and McKechnie 2009</xref>). Thus, current value in the experience can affect how a customer makes sense of past and future experiences.</p>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 4:</italic> Value in the experience emerges from individually determined social contexts.</p>
<p>Within the S-D logic discourse, customer value is viewed as being “… <italic>idiosyncratic, experiential, contextual, and meaning<bold>-</bold>laden</italic>…” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-1094670511426897">Vargo and Lusch 2008</xref>, p. 7). Service customers are always, consciously and unconsciously, accessing and modifying, to use <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1094670511426897">Schutz’s (1967)</xref> term, their “stock of knowledge” of their individual and collective “<italic>lifeworlds</italic>.” Value in the experience is determined by the individual service customer’s context and is constantly changing and will very much depend on the particular service customer’s specific interest and personal lifeworld context. The contexts in which service customers experience value do not necessarily equate with the service contexts offered or proposed by the service organization. Indeed, within the service customer’s lifeworld, the service contexts proposed by different service providers may or may not be integrated into the customer-to-customer (C2C) network context. Even if the service context proposed by service organizations is experienced by the service customer, such experiences will not be identical for each service customer (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1094670511426897">Chronis 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>When considering these four propositions in relation to researching value in the experience from the service customer’s perspective, it is important to acknowledge that “pure” experience will never be fully accessible to the researcher, or to the pertaining individual service customers, using phenomenological or indeed any other research methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1094670511426897">Smith, Flowers, and Larkin 2009</xref>). The ontological focus of phenomenology is subjective experience and how the individual service customer makes sense of it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1094670511426897">Goulding 2005</xref>; Woodruff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1094670511426897">Smith 2007</xref>). Therefore, inner thoughts and explicit speech are an essential part of sense making that illuminate but do not and cannot fully reveal lived experience. Although lived experience is emphasized in phenomenology, it does not need to denote externally observable actions but rather represents an individual mental construction. Thus, evidence in relation to experience is never an objective record of what really happened but rather represents respondents’, researchers’, and readers’ sense making in relation to particular phenomena. In addition, service customers’ iterative sense making is not a linear process, as current value in the experience is constructed based on previous and imaginary future experiences (e.g., Gummesson 2000; Heidegger [1927] 1962). Accordingly, and in acknowledgment of the caveats above, the individual service customer’s view is taken as a “fact.” <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511426897">Figure 1</xref>
 presents a holistic summary of the four VALEX propositions that can be applied when researching how individual service customers iteratively seek to make sense of value in the experience in different social contexts and lifeworld situations.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1094670511426897" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The hermeneutic spiral of individual and collective sense making of value in the experience.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1094670511426897-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1094670511426897">
<title>Method and Techniques for Understanding Value in the Experience</title>
<sec id="section6-1094670511426897">
<title>Established Customer (Perceived) Value Measurements</title>
<p>Many traditional customer (perceived) value measures are best suited for analyzing the experiences of current customers, and they tend to focus on a specific perspective rather than a holistic view of customer value. Established customer value measures, such as the Customer-Perceived Value Measurement scale (PERVAL), introduced by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-1094670511426897">Sweeney and Soutar (2001)</xref>, conceptualize customer value and its associated measurement as a linear process involving presevice, inservice, and postservice consumption phases (Sweeney and Soutar 2001), or merely as a value judgment based on in-use experience. Value judgments and evaluations of the perceived benefits and sacrifices of using a particular service are based on perceptions of some type of customer trade-off, for example, between price and quality. Other alternative approaches to measuring customer (perceived) value focus on predefined value categories in the context of a particular type or category of service and fail to incorporate a more longitudinal perspective (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1094670511426897">Flint, Woodruff, and Gardial 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1094670511426897">Holbrook 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1094670511426897">Rescher 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-1094670511426897">Zeithaml 1988</xref>). Typically, deductive measures that require consumers to evaluate their experience of using a service do not adequately capture the perceptions of noncustomers or prospective customers of the particular service or its competitors (Zeithaml et al. 2006).</p>
<p>Alternative customer value measures, which are primarily economic in nature, for example, customer assets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1094670511426897">Gupta and Lehmann 2003</xref>), customer equity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1094670511426897">Blattberg and Deighton 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1094670511426897">Hogan, Lemon, and Rust 2002</xref>), customer lifetime value (Berger and Nasr 2002), and customer profitability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1094670511426897">Reinartz and Kumar 2003</xref>), do recognize the longitudinal aspects of value. However, such measures are unable to capture the total customer experience in a holistic way over time. Many traditional customer (perceived) value measures focus on postuse evaluations of a particular service without explicitly taking into account how the use of other services or imagined experiences may affect customer (perceived) value judgments. Indeed, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-1094670511426897">Sweeney (2002)</xref> states that some factors used to evaluate or anticipate customer-perceived value prior to the service encounter are no longer important in postpurchase evaluation, for example, the inconvenience of using the service. They fail to acknowledge how past and future experiences of service customers and noncustomers are intersubjectively and intrasubjectively related when new and existing service customers seek to make sense of and evaluate perceived value within their idiosyncratic and socially constructed frames of reference.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1094670511426897">
<title>Interpreting Value in the Experience</title>
<p>Due to the limitations of current conceptualizations of customer (perceived) value and associated measurement scales that have been previously outlined, further academic research is required to better understand the customer value construct (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1094670511426897">Sanchez-Fernandez and Iniesta-Bonillo 2007</xref>). In line with the phenomenological epistemology, interpretive research methods that endeavor to illuminate how service customers make sense of subjective experience can be used to achieve this research objective. In contrast, research methods that aim at objective approximations and generalized outcomes are not applicable.</p>
<p>Narrative methods offer one illustration of a category of research approaches that interpret and make sense of human experience by listening to, collecting, and analyzing stories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-1094670511426897">Webster and Mertova 2007</xref>). Stories can be used to explore the VALEX propositions in different contexts. Narratives reveal the individual’s retrospective sense making of human experiences and enable the phenomenological researcher to illuminate the implicit—as well as explicit—meaning of a particular phenomenon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1094670511426897">Atkinson and Delamont 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1094670511426897">Smith, Flowers, and Larkin 2009</xref>). While narratives reveal service customers’ retrospective sense making of their experiences, they do not simply impart a passive mirroring of experience; rather, they reveal how service customers iteratively construct and reconstruct past, present, and anticipated future experiences using systems of signs, numbers, words, or pictures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1094670511426897">Czarniawska 2004</xref>). While temporal order is often present within service customers’ narratives, the latter do not necessarily, need to flow in a linear way as events; their importance and structural connections to each other make the temporal, spatial, and character details of the story explicit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1094670511426897">Riessman and Speedy 2007</xref>, p. 430). This is in line with the phenomenological approach, as sense making moves backward and forward between specific events and experiences to illuminate such experiences from the perspective of the individual storyteller (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1094670511426897">Crossley 2006</xref>) or, in this case, the service customer.</p>
<p>Narrative data collection methods, such as phenomenological or lifeworld interviews, can be used to explore how respondents make sense of their value experiences in a particular event and social context (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1094670511426897">Kvale and Brinkmann 2009</xref>). Such “interviews” are dialogical, intersubjective, social constructions (or coconstructions) of respondents’ sense making of their experiences, as opposed to knowledge discovery of “objective” facts by an omnipotent interviewer or researcher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1094670511426897">Kvale and Brinkmann 2009</xref>). Projective techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1094670511426897">Boddy 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1094670511426897">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr90-1094670511426897">Webb 1992</xref>) can also be introduced during phenomenological interviews in order to uncover or illuminate those experiences that respondents may be reluctant or unable to express directly.</p>
<p>Other methods that can be used to elicit service customer narratives include personal introspection, which requires service customers to analyze and record their own individual value experiences. Researchers then study service customers’ self-recollection of their life stories in the form of personal diaries or autobiographical accounts, which in turn illuminate such experiences for others, including the researcher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1094670511426897">Baron and Harris 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1094670511426897">Brown 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1094670511426897">Holbrook 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1094670511426897">Patterson, Hodgson, and Shi 2008</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1094670511426897">
<title>Illustration of Researching Value in the Experience Using Narrative Methods</title>
<p>The EBNIT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1094670511426897">Helkkula and Pihlström 2010</xref>) was used to analyze a data set of service customer narratives obtained from personal interviews, which illustrate the four VALEX propositions previously outlined. EBNIT combines narrative analysis and critical events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1094670511426897">Czarniawska 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-1094670511426897">Webster and Mertova 2007</xref>) with projective techniques in the form of metaphors. In EBNIT, the storyteller, in this case, the service customer, spontaneously, and in an unsolicited naturalistic fashion, indicates which value experiences are lived and which are imaginary. By focusing on service customers’ narratives of experienced critical and imaginary events, the respondent is invited to reflect on the possible meaning of the experiences and to coconstruct meaning together with the interviewer. In addition, respondents are triggered to reveal their imaginary value experiences through the use of metaphors, such as a magic wand, genie servant, or an ideal world, where everything is possible and there are no financial, technical, or other restrictions to their ideal stories.</p>
<p>The structure of EBNIT analysis mirrors the typical structure of a narrative, identifying actors, key events, and their sequence and settings that are context-specific. Within the EBNIT framework, the interdependence of events, their importance, and their structure make the temporal, spatial, and character details of the story explicit to the service customers concerned, as well as to the researcher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1094670511426897">McKee 1997</xref>). EBNIT recognizes that multiple perspectives, divergent viewpoints, and customer voices may exist at various points in time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1094670511426897">Helkkula and Pihlström 2010</xref>). Narratives of individual service customers’ experiences in their specific social context are therefore considered to represent dynamic, subjective—as opposed to objective, static—realities that reveal how service customers iteratively make sense of value in the experience. The latter is cocreated between the storyteller (service customer), the interviewer, and the reader or within the service customers’ social network (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1094670511426897">Schutz 1967</xref>). As part of the empirical EBNIT study, 25 service customers were individually interviewed regarding their experiences of using social forums in connection with various types of events, including cultural, sports, and family events (specifically a musical event, an orienteering event, a football tournament, and a bachelorette party). All 25 respondents had direct experience of the specific phenomenon being explored (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1094670511426897">Table 1</xref>
).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1094670511426897" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Summary of the Data Collection</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1094670511426897" xlink:href="10.1177_1094670511426897-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Source of Data</td>
<td>25 Narrative Interviews</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Service category</td>
<td>Web 2.0 service used (music, pictures, videos, and social networking sites)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Study conducted</td>
<td>2008</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">Preliminary questions</td>
<td>What Web 2.0 services have you used? (A list of the most popular Web 2.0 networking services was provided to respondents), For example, Facebook, LinkedIn, Second Life, MySpace, IRC Gallery (a social website for young people), photo sharing (Flickr, Picasa Web), and video sharing (YouTube, Google video)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>How many times have you attended or participated in the event/social networking site in question?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">Data collection methodology</td>
<td>Research questions:</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1. Describe how you use online social forums relating to this event?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
2. Describe other similar events
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
3. Tell me an imaginary story of how you would have acted if anything were possible? Forget technical restrictions; anything is possible. In the future, there will be a magic wand to help you do whatever you want
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Metaphors used</td>
<td>A magic wand, an online genie servant, or avatar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Search criteria</td>
<td>Event-based need, which spontaneously emerged during the interviews</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Time series</td>
<td>Interviews were conducted in June, July, and August of 2008</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lived versus imaginary experiences</td>
<td>25 storytellers expressed lived value experiences and 23 storytellers expressed imaginary value experiences based on their lived value experiences</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Final sample</td>
<td>25 service customer interviews</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Analysis of cases</td>
<td>The interviews were transcribed, saved as separate Microsoft Word documents and analyzed both as separate cases and in relation to each other, based on lived and imaginary value experiences using the QSR International product, NVivo</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Each service customer narrative (story) relating to various value experiences was transcribed and saved as a separate word document. Each narrative, together with related narratives, was then read in full in order to gain a holistic picture of the intrasubjective and intersubjective value experiences of the service customers involved. A minimum of two researchers reviewed each service customer narrative at least three times. Subsequent readings of the service customer narratives followed using the EBNIT technique. Using NVivo, themes were categorized as either lived critical experience or as imaginary experience based on the criticality of the event. Critical events, that is, those events that were remembered by respondents as being especially valuable, positive service-use situations, were coded as lived experiences. Other lived events, that is, more incidental events that were not reported by respondents as being critical, were also identified and coded in the analysis, which in turn facilitated a more holistic understanding of how service customers connect events when making sense of their experiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1094670511426897">Gough 1997</xref>). Events, which the storytellers presented as imaginary events and which often revealed customers’ imaginary, idealized experiences, were also coded; for example, situations where a new service would be valuable to the respondents, but one that does not yet exist. Differences in coding were discussed and mutually agreed upon.</p>
<p>Next, we illustrate the four VALEX propositions using the narratives that emerged from the EBNIT analysis. While each of the narratives analyzed was unique and tended to focus on particular themes, all four propositions relating to the characterization of value in the experience were identified in the narratives.</p>
<p>VALEX Proposition 1 (<italic>Value in the experience is individually intrasubjective and socially intersubjective</italic>) is the first proposition illustrated by the customer narratives. The intrasubjective nature of value in the experience reflects individual service customers’ sense making of value in the experience, which takes place as inner thoughts and which may or may not be externalized in the form of words or gestures. When individual service customers seek to make sense of their experiences in a social context, they interact with each other and discuss value in the experience. Such experiences may be shared directly with other customers or through online social networking sites. For example, an individual who attended a jazz festival made sense of value in the experience of attending the musical event. In addition, he wanted to know what his friends had experienced and wanted to share his experiences with them.<disp-quote>
<p>I decided to attend this jazz festival, as the weather was so nice and many concerts were outdoor concerts. Even if I was told that this was a good festival, I just did not like it. Don’t even know why, but I just did not. Afterwards, I followed other people’s status updates and uploaded pictures. I wanted to know where they have been, what they had done, and with whom. But I didn’t want them to know that I’ve been looking at their profile and pictures. (19-year-old male who attended a jazz festival)</p>
</disp-quote>It is clear that social networking forums are important for the social construction and sense making of different types of phenomena, such as value in the experience (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1094670511426897">Cova, Kozinets and Shankar 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1094670511426897">Kelleher and Helkkula 2010</xref>). While the first customer narrative refers to “lurking” behavior on social networks, that is, nonparticipant observation and reading of Facebook posts in order to understand the value in the experience of others, the second example illustrates how an individual service customer, by creating and sharing content on Facebook, seeks to assist her friends.</p>
<p>
<disp-quote>
<p>When I tag pictures that I’ve taken at this event, I don’t tag them for my own benefit. When other people, who attended this event, check Facebook, it’s nice that they understand that they get information from the pictures below by using this file tag. (26-year-old female who attended an orienteering event)</p>
</disp-quote>VALEX Proposition 2 (<italic>Value in the experience can be both lived and imaginary</italic>) demonstrates that value in the experience does not have to be based on an external event that has an external replica (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-1094670511426897">Valberg 1992</xref>); rather, value in the experience can also be based on an imaginary event or thought. The narratives of the service customers interviewed reveal how service customers make sense of their previous lived experiences and illustrate how such experiences could become more valuable to them. Some of the imaginary value in the (future) experiences revealed in the following customer narratives included adding sunshine, wind, and sound to photos and the provision of the precise location and position of friends at a festival or football tournament.</p>
<p>
<disp-quote>
<p>I think it is useful to see the date and time in the photo. I imagined I would automatically get the location where the picture was taken as well. […] If it were possible, I’d like my friends to sense the sunshine, rain, and wind in the pictures too. (26-year-old female who attended a football tournament)</p>
<p>I took a nice short video with my cell phone at the party. But I also imagine that pictures could include voice to express the atmosphere. (25-year-old female who attended a bachelorette (hen) party)</p>
</disp-quote>The following narrative shows that people may relate their imaginary value experiences to actual events in their lifeworld. In the next example, a young male revealed that he would like to be able to locate his friends at an event; however, he would not like others to be able to locate him.</p>
<p>
<disp-quote>
<p>[At this music festival] I would like to be able to use my cell phone to locate my friends, but I would not like to be located by them. (18-year-old male who attended a musical event)</p>
</disp-quote>It is important that service organizations recognize that future service innovations and development ideas can originate from such imaginary experiences. For instance, in the illustration quoted above, the imaginary experiences of incorporating sound into pictures or including a voluntary location-based option within a cell phone application provide interesting and novel insights for service innovation and development for companies in the mobile and web services sectors.</p>
<p>VALEX Proposition 3 (<italic>Value in the experience is constructed based on previous, current, and future experiences and is temporal in nature</italic>) refers to the ongoing reconstruction of value experiences based on previous, current, or imaginary future contexts, that is, the hermeneutic circle. Previous and anticipated future experiences of value will also, both subconsciously and consciously, become figural and brought to bear on current value in the experience. In the next illustration, one service customer made sense of current and future value in the experience based on past value in the experience of sharing photos with her friends.<disp-quote>
<p>In the past, I downloaded photos when we refurnished our apartment and then invited our friends to check them out. [Her friends told me they appreciated her downloading the photos.] I am planning to download some pictures I just took [of the event, which she attended with her friends]. It will be nice to see the pictures and create memories of past events. (29-year-old female who attended a bachelorette (hen) party)</p>
</disp-quote>Other service customer narratives revealed the multidimensional and temporal nature of value in the experience. For example, the following quotation demonstrates how one service customer made sense of her value in the experience before, during, and after a football tournament. She decided to attend the event on the recommendation of the friend and received an information package from the organizer of the event prior to attending. Prior to the event, she also started to think about her previous experiences in relation to playing football with her friends. She also continued to make sense of her value in the experience during and after the tournament had taken place, reflecting also on whether she would attend such an event again.</p>
<p>
<disp-quote>
<p>[First recommendation of her friend] First, I heard from Mary [names changed] that this event would be interesting.” … [Second recommendation from another friend] Susan told me the same. I have enjoyed jogging with them … [She looked for information in the Internet] I read about this on the Internet. … [imaginary/experience] I imagined it would be nice to attend. … [She decided to take part in the event] Then, I decided to attend and registered for the event on the Internet. … [The event arranger contacted her by mail] I received an information package by mail. There was a lot of useful information. … [She made sense of the value in the experience after the event and considered whether she would attend again.] I thought the tournament was fun. I might attend in the future as well. (49-year-old female who attended an orienteering event)</p>
</disp-quote>These service customers are making sense of their current, and imaginary future, value in the experience based on their past experiences. Sense making is related to different events and points in time, which makes it temporally contextual. Current temporal contexts and experiences may cause service customers to revise, revisit, and reinterpret past experiences. For example, even if a person might feel stressed during a sports competition or if a sports event is scheduled during bad weather, the value in the experience, considered retrospectively, may be reinterpreted in a more positive light. For example, an individual may fondly remember the friends with whom they shared an event, or may consider that a previous negative experience was indeed a positive and formative experience.</p>
<p>VALEX Proposition 4 (<italic>Value in the experience emerges from individually determined social contexts</italic>) indicates that the context of the value in the experience is individually determined in a social context and cannot be determined by the service provider. Sense making in relation to value experiences moves backward and forward: the customer’s lifeworld experiences act as the foundation for service customers’ understanding of value in the experience and other phenomena. For example, one young male indicated that value in the experience is affected by other individual/individuals who belong to the same social context.<disp-quote>
<p>I spend many hours a day on IRC [an online social networking website called IRC Gallery]. In my network of friends [an individually determined social context] are people that I know. I like most of the people, but some of them I dislike very much. I am updated about where people go, and I also share my experiences. If I get to know that a person I very much dislike will attend an event, I may not go there just because he will be there. Just meeting him there would destroy my good experience. (18-year-old male who attended a football event)</p>
</disp-quote>Other narratives indicated that individually determined social contexts are not stable and may affect value in the experience. For example, one service customer recounted that while she initially took up orienteering after meeting her husband, she now personally enjoys attending orienteering competitions and enjoys sharing this experience with her extended family.</p>
<p>
<disp-quote>
<p>Previously, I did not go orienteering at all. I was interested in other sports. But since I met my husband, orienteering has become a family thing. It was not just my husband who went orienteering, but his brother, sister, and parents used to go with as well. So, I actually just more or less had to start orienteering. That is why I go orienteering nowadays and decided to attend this ladies’ orienteering competition. Even though I went orienteering because it’s just a family thing, I enjoyed myself and the orienteering event was good. (41-year-old female who attended an orienteering event)</p>
</disp-quote>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1094670511426897">Table 2</xref>
 summarizes the four VALEX propositions. Value in the experience is not an objective measure of customer (perceived) value but is based on individual sense making in a social context. In addition, value in the experience may be based on an event or thought that has previously taken place, on stories of other people, or on an imaginary idea. The four propositions are not mutually exclusive; rather, they overlap and are interrelated with each other. For example, when the respondents determine the social context of the value in the experience (Proposition 4), it is often based on previous experience (Proposition 3). Thus, value in the experience cannot solely be restricted to the current service context proposed by the service organization.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1094670511426897" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Interpreting Value in the Experience</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1094670511426897" xlink:href="10.1177_1094670511426897-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Propositions Relating to the Characterization of Value in the Experience</th>
<th>Individual Value in the Experience Relates to the Social Context</th>
<th>Relationship to Previous Literature</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Proposition 1: Value in the experience is individually intrasubjective and socially intersubjective.</td>
<td>People make sense of value in the experience with subjective inner thoughts that reflect personal preferences or what is socially beneficial. The experiences are discussed and shared with others face-to-face, on the phone, and increasingly through online social networks such as Facebook.</td>
<td>Individual customer social networks were an important forum for the social construction and sense making of different types of phenomena, such as value (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1094670511426897">Cova, Kozinets, and Shankar 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1094670511426897">Kelleher and Helkkula 2010</xref>).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Proposition 2</td>
<td>Value in the experience can be based on individuals’ previous lived experiences of service-use situations or events where services could have been useful but were not used. Imaginary value experiences may also be based on other peoples’ experiences, on stories communicated through various media, or on individually imagined thoughts and beliefs.</td>
<td>Individuals socially and contextually construct what reality is for himself or herself (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1094670511426897">Shankar and Patterson 2001</xref> refer to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1094670511426897">Hudson and Ozanne 1988</xref>).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Value in the experience can be both lived and imaginary.</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Proposition 3 Value in the experience is constructed based on previous, current, and imaginary future experiences and is temporal in nature.</td>
<td>Current and future experiences are based on previous experiences and as such incorporate a temporal dimension. As people make sense of previous value in the experience at different points in time, they may see the past experience in a new light. Therefore, value in the experience is temporal in nature and subject to change.</td>
<td>The reconstructive or cumulative nature of experiences has been recognized in the hermeneutic spiral, which indicates that sense making and understanding is based on previous understanding (i.e., preunderstanding, cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1094670511426897">Husserl [1931] 1967</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1094670511426897">[1936] 1970</xref>; Gummesson 2000; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-1094670511426897">Tuomi and Sarajärvi 2003</xref>).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Proposition 4 Value in the experience emerges from individually determined social contexts</td>
<td>The context for value in the experience is not determined by the service provider, but rather by the individual’s lifeworld. Individuals make sense of value in the experience in relation to that context.</td>
<td>Sense making in relation to value experiences moves backward and forward: the customer’s lifeworld experiences act as the foundation of the customers’ understanding and experience of value and other phenomena, that is, phenomenological and experiential nature of value creation (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1094670511426897">Crossley 2006</xref>, p. 429; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1094670511426897">Helkkula and Kelleher 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-1094670511426897">Vargo and Lusch 2008</xref>).</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1094670511426897">
<title>Implications for Service Researchers</title>
<p>This study has characterized value in the experience and presented four VALEX propositions that conceptually broaden the perspective of value. The central premise of this characterization is that value in the experience is an intrasubjective, socially intersubjective, context- and situation-specific phenomenon that is both lived and imaginary, constructed based on previous, current, and imaginary future experiences and is temporal. In addition, it was illustrated, using the event-based inquiry technique, how the VALEX propositions can be used to analyze a data set of service customer narratives. Characterizing value in the experience has a direct impact on the ontological, epistemological, and methodological choices of a specific study or project.</p>
<sec id="section10-1094670511426897">
<title>Implications of Characterizing Value in the Experience and Acceptable Evidence of It</title>
<p>Clearly, it is possible to view value from a number of perspectives, including those of the service customer and service provider (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1094670511426897">Payne, Storbacka, and Frow 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1094670511426897">Smith and Colgate 2007</xref>). For service researchers, this implies that, while service organizations have certain perspectives relating to their value propositions, service customers possess their own approach to value, which does not always correspond with the value proposed by the company (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1094670511426897">Grönroos and Helle 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1094670511426897">Heinonen 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The application of the VALEX propositions to the narrative data set analyzed illustrate that value is indeed uniquely and phenomenologically determined by the service customer. This finding would seem to align with Vargo and Lusch’s (2008) and S-D logic’s tenth foundational premise: value is phenomenologically (experientially) determined by beneficiaries or actors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-1094670511426897">Vargo and Lusch 2008</xref>). Characterizing value in the experience using the VALEX propositions, therefore, reveals individual service customers’ dynamic, subjective, and event-specific interpretations of value in the experience (Woodruff <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1094670511426897">Smith 2007</xref>, p. 209).</p>
<p>The insights derived from this study also have implications for service researchers who are interested in examining C2C value cocreation and different perspectives of value. The nature of C2C value cocreation and social value experiences has been considered only to a limited degree in extant research in the form of social value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1094670511426897">Sheth, Newman, and Gross 1991</xref>), social esteem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1094670511426897">Konanam and Balasubramanian 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1094670511426897">Laukkanen and Lauronen 2005</xref>), social pressure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1094670511426897">Kleijnen, Wetzels and de Ruyter 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr89-1094670511426897">Venkatesh, Morris, and Davis 2003</xref>), and the social context of service-use situations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1094670511426897">Pura and Heinonen 2008</xref>). To date, much of the extant research on customer (perceived) value has considered individual customer value independently of other customers and has ignored the effects of the latter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1094670511426897">Graf and Maas 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1094670511426897">Kelleher and Peppard 2010</xref>), with some notable exceptions, including the Nordic School of Marketing, S-D logic, and the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1094670511426897">Schau, Muniz, and Arnould (2009)</xref>. The VALEX propositions and related service customer narratives indicate that value in the experience cannot solely be restricted to a single dyadic relationship between an individual service customer and a service organization, but rather occurs within a value constellation of multiple firms, customers, and other actors with a service system or network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1094670511426897">Gummesson 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-1094670511426897">Vargo and Lusch 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>We summarize what value in the experience is and what evidence is acceptable with regard to it in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1094670511426897">Table 3</xref>
. In addition, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1094670511426897">Table 3</xref> compares the characteristics of the various interpretive research approaches compatible with the VALEX propositions to alternative deductive measurement scales, such as PERVAL (Sweeney and Soutar 2001), that were developed to measure customer-perceived value of different types of services. When compared to linear measurement scales, such as PERVAL, a number of ontological and epistemological differences are evident. PERVAL has a predefined measurement scale as a starting point, and it aims to present objective and generalizable findings in preservice, inservice, and postservice phases of a specific service or context, as defined by the service provider. While PERVAL focuses on perceived value, the VALEX propositions center on lived and imaginary value in the experience. Applying the VALEX propositions, service customers define event-specific contexts by describing the current service experience in relation to previous and imaginary future events.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1094670511426897" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Comparison of Individual and Collective Sense Making of Value in the Experience (VALEX) to the Customer-Perceived Value Measurement (PERVAL) Scale</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1094670511426897" xlink:href="10.1177_1094670511426897-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Characterization</th>
<th>Inductive Value Measurement Techniques, such as VALEX Propositions</th>
<th>Deductive Value Measurement Models, such as PERVAL</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Philosophical perspective</td>
<td>Phenomenological (experiential)</td>
<td>Realist or critical realist</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Evidence about value in the experience</td>
<td>Interpretive: individuals’ (service customers’) subjective experiences are justified as data</td>
<td>Aims to present objective, generalizable results that are based on subjective self-reported data</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Form of knowing</td>
<td>Sense making that is based on an iterative and cumulative process of previous and current understanding (the hermeneutic spiral)</td>
<td>Based on theoretically justified hypothesis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3">Individual versus social value perspective</td>
<td rowspan="3">Experiences of value are both individually (intrasubjective) and socially (intersubjective) constructed</td>
<td>Service provider’s perspective on how individual service customers perceive value</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Analyzes the effects of customer-perceived value on other constructs</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Aims to generalize findings on a population</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lived and imaginary perspective</td>
<td>Includes lived and imaginary value experiences. Incorporates both direct and indirect value experiences, that is, the individual service customer can imagine the experience of service in the inner world without ever having experienced the service in the external world</td>
<td>Focuses on customer-perceived value. Does not discuss imaginary customer-perceived value; therefore, necessitates direct experience or use of a particular service</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Temporal nature</td>
<td>Value experiences are based on current, previous, and imagined future experiences within and outside the context of the specific service</td>
<td>Value is perceived in preservice, inservice, and postservice consumption phases</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Context</td>
<td>Event-specific and justified by the individual service customer in the individual’s lifeworld, which is socially constructed. Identifies the world as lived, in comparison to the world as construed by an external entity, for example, a service provider</td>
<td>Defined by the service provider</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Theoretical contribution</td>
<td>Suggestive propositions may act as an invitation for further work on the phenomenon or set of issues revealed by the study</td>
<td>A measurement scale that enables analysis of relationships between constructs; may add specificity, new mechanisms, or boundaries to existing theories</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The comparison elucidated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1094670511426897">Table 3</xref> indicates that the application of the VALEX propositions is suitable for analyzing how service customers dynamically intertwine their lived and imaginary value experiences in a hermeneutic spiral of nonlinear, cyclical sense making.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1094670511426897">
<title>Implications Relating to the Possible Methods and Techniques That Could be Used for Collecting Data About Value in the Experience</title>
<p>While certain aspects of subjective meanings of everyday lived experiences might be evident or figural to individual service customers in certain contexts, sometimes value in the experience may be hidden from service customers and researchers within the “natural attitude” and may need to be uncovered using phenomenological research methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1094670511426897">Langdridge 2007</xref>). As illustrated, studies conceptualizing value in the experience can be operationalized using methods and techniques that understand sense making as a form of knowing and that focus on individual subjective experience in a social context. In this article, a narrative technique to collect data was employed, but any research method or technique that is interpretive and focuses on the subjective experience and how individuals make sense of it can be used to collect data in relation to value in the experience. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1094670511426897">Table 4</xref>
 presents a summary of the characteristics of such methodologies.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1094670511426897" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Methodological Approach for Collecting Evidence About Value in the Experience</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1094670511426897" xlink:href="10.1177_1094670511426897-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Characterization</th>
<th>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Research approaches</td>
<td>Interpretive</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constructs and measures</td>
<td>The phenomenon of value in the experience is the starting point of the research as opposed to existing constructs, measures, and scales</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Research question</td>
<td>Open-ended inquiry about lived and imagined value in the experience in service customers’ lifeworlds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3">Methodologies</td>
<td>Do not aim to use linear measures, but rather use first-person illustrations of customer sense making in relation to value in the experience</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Seek to examine the dynamic and complex phenomenon of value in the experience before, during, and after actual or imaginary service consumption</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Also, consider the effect of and interrelationships between other types of actual or imaginary service consumption within an individual’s lifeworld context</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Goal of data analysis</td>
<td>Possible pattern identification</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Data analysis method</td>
<td>Thematic content; aims to interpret and make sense of value in the experience</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="5">Examples of possible techniques</td>
<td>Narrative inquiry, protocol writing, and phenomenological interviews (service customer lifeworld descriptions and sense making of what happened)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Personal introspection (e.g., using diaries, journals, and blogs)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Critical incident technique (interviews or written stories of specific events)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Projective techniques including metaphors</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ethnographic techniques including autoethnography, netnography, participant and nonparticipant observation</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>It is important to note that it is not our intention to suggest that interpretive methodologies are the only methods applicable for studying customer value or that they should serve as a replacement for other alternative methods, such as linear measurement scales. We consider that the VALEX propositions offer a useful characterization of value in the experience that complements other predefined customer (perceived) value measurement scales, for example, using phenomenological research methods and techniques as a prestudy. The VALEX propositions, therefore, are an example of “nascent theory” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1094670511426897">Edmondson and McManus 2007</xref>), which holds that “… <italic>researchers do not know what issues may emerge from the data and so avoid hypothesizing specific relationships between variables</italic>…” (p. 1162). Predefined scales, such as PERVAL, can be used in conjunction with phenomenological research methods and techniques, as both approaches can provide complementary insights regarding the nature and experience of customer (perceived) value.</p>
<p>Analyzing value in the experience using the VALEX propositions does not aim to generate generalizable findings from large samples, but rather seeks to learn something new from examining value in the experience within service customers’ lifeworld contexts. In addition, the phenomenological approach provides a longitudinal perspective of customer value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1094670511426897">Kumar, Lemon, and Parasuraman 2006</xref>), as service customers reconstruct current value in the experience based on their past and imaginary value in the experience.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1094670511426897">
<title>Implications for Managers</title>
<p>From the service organization’s perspective, relatively little is known about customer value-related phenomena (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1094670511426897">Flint, Woodruff, and Gardial 2002</xref>; Woodruff and Flint 2006). While <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1094670511426897">Priem (2007)</xref> acknowledges the pivotal role of customers as the arbiters of value, he notes that customer value is primarily conceptualized as something that is embedded or transferred in market offerings and value chains to customers. In this context, the service organization’s overarching objective is to develop and provide services and service experiences containing some type of embedded value to customers, at a profit, in order to generate a return for shareholders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1094670511426897">Priem 2007</xref>). The notion of exchange value (or value-in-exchange), which pertains to the actual price paid by the customer to the firm for the service purchased, becomes the predominant consideration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1094670511426897">Bowman and Ambrosini 2000</xref>). In that vein, strategic business decisions are typically based on the company perspective including, for example, market potential, competitors, the price customers are expected to be willing to pay, and short-term and long-term profitability calculations. However, a broader perspective from the customer’s point of view is needed. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1094670511426897">Frow and Payne (2011)</xref>, for example, note that few organizations actively consider how they might better engage with stakeholders to develop more relevant value propositions.</p>
<p>Based on the characterization of value in the experience, we provide managerial implications that enable service managers to better understand what value in the experience is, what can be accepted as evidence about it, and how to collect data on it.</p>
<sec id="section13-1094670511426897">
<title>Implications to Understanding What Value in the Experience is and Acceptable Evidence of It</title>
<p>According to the VALEX propositions, value in the experience is based on previous experiences, related to service customers’ lived and imaginary value in the experience in specific, contextual settings. The VALEX propositions indicate that value in the experience goes well beyond the interaction between service customer/customers and the service provider. It is therefore imperative that service managers broaden their perspective in order to analyze service customers’ lifeworld contexts and social networks, to observe both existing and imaginary customer practices, and to explore expectations based on the past as well as the future. We recommend that service organizations not only research and identify the core values and lived experience of service customers but also extend observations to include socially constructed experiences in order to successfully cocreate relevant value propositions.</p>
<p>For a service organization, characterizing value in the experience complements more traditional customer-perceived approaches and enables a deeper understanding of (perceived) value in service customers’ lifeworld contexts. The changing conditions in different contextual settings are difficult to anticipate but should be included in strategic decision making in the quest for estimating service customers’ willingness to cocreate value in the experience. When aiming to cocreate value with potential or existing customers, service organizations are faced with questions about how, when, and the degree to which current and prospective service customers are willing to financially support or pay for current or imaginary future value experiences. For development purposes, as the narratives suggest, it is important that service organizations recognize that future service innovations and development ideas can originate from service customers’ imaginary experiences. This is particularly important, for example, in contexts where service innovations are so new that service customers or organizations do not have access to service customers’ prior perceptions or expectations in order to form a basis for their value judgments. Any value propositions that plan to incorporate new technology into the service offering in ways that have not been available before rely on imaginary future experiences of how value can be experienced before the first service offerings are available for trial and use. Examples of such technologies in the past included, for example, text messaging, location-based services and augmented reality, to name but a few.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1094670511426897">
<title>Implications Relating to the Possible Methods and Techniques That Could be Used for Collecting Data About Value in the Experience</title>
<p>Currently, interpretive approaches using customer narratives are to some extent used by service organizations to illustrate customer practices in their everyday lives.</p>
<p>We suggest that using interpretive methodologies and analyzing value in the experience using the VALEX propositions provides new insights on how value is constructed in the service customers’ lived contexts. Managers would benefit from collecting evidence on lived and future customer experiences, identifying possible patterns as to why, when, and what customers are willing to purchase in the future, as well as which parties should be involved in the holistic value experience. Interpretive methods, such as diaries, journals, blogs, interviews, or written stories of specific events and observations, are recommended for collecting data about value in the experience.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1094670511426897">
<title>Future Research Directions</title>
<p>As the implications of this article highlight, value in the experience is a meaningful research topic for service marketing scholars with direct implications for practitioners. The leading service marketing and management scholars in the world have ranked value among the top 10 research priorities, and in particular, the requirements to measure and optimize the value of service and to enhance the service experience through cocreation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1094670511426897">Ostrom et al. 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>This is primarily a conceptual article with limited empirical illustration using interpretive research methods. In this article, we have endeavored to contribute to the topical discussion and research priority of value by characterizing value in the experience (VALEX) as a complementary, phenomenological perspective for examining customers’ value experiences and to present some future research directions in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1094670511426897">Table 5</xref>
 to deepen the understanding of this phenomenon.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-1094670511426897" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Future Research Directions for Value in the Experience</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1094670511426897" xlink:href="10.1177_1094670511426897-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Implications</th>
<th>Topics and Propositions</th>
<th>Current Insights</th>
<th>Important Research Questions</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Implications for understanding what value in the experience is</td>
<td>Individual social (P1) Social context (P4)</td>
<td>Researchers should make explicit the perspective from which value is being analyzed and in which context.</td>
<td>How does customer context affect customer value in the experience?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Researchers should also consider and acknowledge the social networks and lifeworld contexts of respondents.</td>
<td>Does individually constructed perceived value differ from socially constructed value in the experience?</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Both individual and collective value experiences should be considered and include sharing with others and nonmonetary service exchanges.</td>
<td>How is value in the experience shared with others?</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Implications as to what can be accepted as evidence about value in the experience</td>
<td>Lived imaginary (P2)</td>
<td>The epistemological, phenomenological understanding focuses on subjective experience, which relates to past current and future events.</td>
<td>How do past and future lived value in the experience affect current value in the experience?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Past future (P3)</td>
<td>Further research should also incorporate imaginary experiences in connection with lived experiences. This is particularly relevant in relation to new service innovations.</td>
<td>How can value be optimized in future experiences?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>How can service organizations innovate by combining customers’ lived and imaginary experiences?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Implications as to what methods and techniques should be adopted for collecting data about value in the experience</td>
<td>Interpretive methods and techniques</td>
<td>When focusing on value in the experience, researchers should use interpretive research approaches and methods that are flexible enough to include events that service customers see as relevant, despite the fact that events are related to the specific service, provider, or use situation at hand.</td>
<td>What methods can be used to illuminate and interpret subjective and context specific value in the experience?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Alternative research methods and techniques need to be developed to further explore subjective experiences in a social context.</td>
<td>How do interpretive methods and techniques complement objective research methods?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Could other types of data, for example symbols, art, drama, or videos, be used to illuminate customers’ sense making of their experiences?</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Like all studies, the present investigation has certain acknowledged limitations. The illustrations used in this article are from a single service category, namely, Web 2.0 services, which potentially limits the generalizability of the findings to other contexts. We believe that the propositions apply regardless of the service field, although the social context may be easier to identify in digital than traditional retailing contexts. Therefore, we encourage researchers to collect additional examples of service customer narratives and experiences in other service categories using, for example, blogs, customer diaries, customer feedback, personal customer service situations, and interviews. This would facilitate deeper contextual insights in different service fields, such as retailing, travel, and financial services. In such fields, customer communities or online forums are often used to elicit future value proposition ideas from a panel of current customers. Insights relating to imaginary future experiences can also be extracted from these types of forums using appropriate methods. Nevertheless, it should be noted that the subjective meaning of customers’ consumption contexts may change over time. Thus, interpretive research approaches that adopt a longitudinal perspective and acknowledge the dynamic and iterative nature of value in the experience from the individual service consumer perspective are needed.</p>
<p>We encourage empirical studies that characterize value in the experience and reflect the epistemological and ontological position that knowledge is dynamic, intersubjective and intrasubjective, and socially constructed. While studies on customers’ subjective value experiences in a specific lifeworld context will not provide generalizable findings for researchers and practitioners, they capture subjective value experiences in the social context. Thereby, they will facilitate a deeper understanding of how service customers make sense of their lived and imaginary value experiences in specific social contexts. Alternative research methods and techniques need to be developed to further explore subjective experiences in a social context. Future research on value in the experience would enable service organizations to make sense of how current and prospective customers make sense of their event-specific value in the experience in their own lifeworld. With increased understanding, companies may be better prepared to facilitate value in the experience and offer meaningful value propositions.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The authors would like to thank the editor and anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments, and the following professors at Hanken School of Economics for their feedback on the previous versions of the article: Tore Strandvik and Maria Holmlund-Rytkönen.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn4-1094670511426897">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn5-1094670511426897">
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: The illustrative quotes have been selected from a research project financed by Tekes, the Finnish Funding Agency for Technology and Innovation. The authors would like to thank Tekes and the Foundation for Economic Education, Finland for financing that enabled the article to be finalized. The authors received no financial support for authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arnould</surname>
<given-names>Eric J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Price</surname>
<given-names>Linda L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Malshe</surname>
<given-names>Avinash A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <article-title>“Toward a Cultural Resource-Based Theory of the Customer”</article-title> in <source>The Service-Dominant Logic of Marketing: Dialog, Debate and Directions</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Lusch</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vargo</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds., <publisher-loc>Armonk, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>M.E. Sharpe</publisher-name>, <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arnould</surname>
<given-names>Eric J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Price</surname>
<given-names>Linda L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zinkhan</surname>
<given-names>George M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>), <source>Consumers</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Atkinson</surname>
<given-names>Paul</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Delamont</surname>
<given-names>Sara</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Analytic Perspectives”</article-title> in <source>Collecting and Interpreting Qualitative Materials</source>, <edition>3rd ed</edition>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Denzin</surname>
<given-names>N. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lincoln</surname>
<given-names>Y. S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds., <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>, <fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Baron</surname>
<given-names>Steve</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>Kim</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Consumers as Resource Integrators,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing Management</source>, <volume>24</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Belk</surname>
<given-names>Russell W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>), <article-title>“Situational Variables and Consumer Behavior,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source>, <volume>2</volume> (<month>December</month>), <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Berger</surname>
<given-names>Paul D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nasr</surname>
<given-names>Nada I.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>), <article-title>“Customer Lifetime Value: Marketing Models and Applications,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Interactive Marketing</source>, <volume>12</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Blattberg</surname>
<given-names>Robert C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Deighton</surname>
<given-names>John</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>), <article-title>“Customer Equity,”</article-title> <source>Harvard Business Review</source>, <volume>74</volume> (<month>July-August</month>), <fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Boddy</surname>
<given-names>Clive</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>), <article-title>“Projective Techniques in Market Research: Valueless Subjectivity or Insightful Reality?”</article-title> <source>International Journal of Market Research</source>, <volume>47</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Boddy</surname>
<given-names>Clive</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>), <article-title>“From Brand Image Research to Teaching Assessment: Using a Projective Technique Borrowed From Marketing Research to Aid an Understanding of Teaching Effectiveness,”</article-title> <source>Quality Assurance in Education</source>, <volume>12</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>Stephen W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>“Autobiography,”</article-title> in <source>Handbook of Qualitative Methods in Marketing</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Belk</surname>
<given-names>R. B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>Cheltenham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Edward Elgar</publisher-name>, <fpage>440</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bowman</surname>
<given-names>Cliff</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ambrosini</surname>
<given-names>Véronique</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>), <article-title>“Value Creation Versus Value Capture: Towards a Coherent Definition of Value in Strategy,”</article-title> <source>British Journal of Management</source>, <volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chronis</surname>
<given-names>Athinodoros</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Co-Constructing the Narrative Experience: Staging and Consuming the American Civil War at Gettysburg,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing Management</source>, <volume>24</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), 1, <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Clulow</surname>
<given-names>Val</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barry</surname>
<given-names>Carol</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gerstman</surname>
<given-names>Julie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“The Resource-Based View and Value: the Customer- Based View of the Firm,”</article-title> <source>Journal of European Industrial Training</source>, <volume>31</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cova</surname>
<given-names>Bernard</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kozinets</surname>
<given-names>Robert</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shankar</surname>
<given-names>Avi</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds.) (<year>2007</year>), <source>Consumer Tribes</source>, <publisher-loc>Great Britain</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Crossley</surname>
<given-names>Nick</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <article-title>“Phenomenology,”</article-title> in <source>Encyclopedia of Social Theory</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Harrington</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marshall</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Muller</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds., <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Czarniawska</surname>
<given-names>Barbara</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>), <source>Narratives in Social Science Research</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Edmondson</surname>
<given-names>Amy C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McManus</surname>
<given-names>Stacy E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Methodological Fit in Management Field Research,”</article-title> <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>32</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1155</fpage>–<lpage>1179</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Edvardsson</surname>
<given-names>Bo</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tronvoll</surname>
<given-names>Bard</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gruber</surname>
<given-names>Thorsten</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>), <article-title>“Expanding Understanding of Service Exchange and Value Co-Creation: A Social Construction Approach,”</article-title> <source>Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science</source>, <volume>2</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>509</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Finsterwalder</surname>
<given-names>Jorg</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tuzovic</surname>
<given-names>Sven</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>), <article-title>“Quality in Group Service Encounters—A Theoretical Exploration of the Concept of a Simultaneous Multi-Customer Co-creation Process,”</article-title> <source>Managing Service Quality</source>, <volume>20</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Flint</surname>
<given-names>Daniel J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Woodruff</surname>
<given-names>Robert</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gardial</surname>
<given-names>Sarah F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>), <article-title>“Exploring the Phenomenon of Customers’ Desired Value Change in a Business-to-Business Context,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing</source>, <volume>66</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frow</surname>
<given-names>Pennie</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Payne</surname>
<given-names>Adrian</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>), <article-title>“A Stakeholder Perspective of the Value Proposition Concept,”</article-title> <source>European Journal of Marketing</source>, <volume>45</volume> (<issue>1/2</issue>), <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frow</surname>
<given-names>Pennie</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Payne</surname>
<given-names>Adrian</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Towards the ‘Perfect’ Customer Experience,”</article-title> <source>Brand Management</source>, <volume>15</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gough</surname>
<given-names>Noel</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>), <source>Horizons, Images and Experiences: The Research Stories Collection</source>. <publisher-loc>Geelong, Victoria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Deakin University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goulding</surname>
<given-names>Cristina</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>), <article-title>“Grounded Theory, Ethnography and Phenomenology: A Comparative Analysis of Three Qualitative Strategies for Marketing Research,”</article-title> <source>European Journal of Marketing</source>, <volume>39</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>294</fpage>–<lpage>308</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sunil</surname>
<given-names>Gupta</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lehmann</surname>
<given-names>Donald R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>), <article-title>“Customers as Assets,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Interactive Marketing</source>, <volume>17</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Graf</surname>
<given-names>Albert</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maas</surname>
<given-names>Peter</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Customer Value from a Customer Perspective: A Comprehensive Review,”</article-title> <source>Journal für Betriebswirtschaft</source>, <volume>58</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grönroos</surname>
<given-names>Christian</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Helle</surname>
<given-names>Pekka</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>), <article-title>“Adopting a Service Logic in Manufacturing,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Service Management</source>, <volume>21</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grove</surname>
<given-names>Steve J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fisk</surname>
<given-names>Ray P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>), <article-title>“The Impact of Other Customers on Service Exchanges: A Critical Incident Examination of ‘Getting Along,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Retailing</source>, <volume>73</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gummesson</surname>
<given-names>Evert</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Extending the Service-Dominant Logic: From Customer Centricity to Balanced Centricity”</article-title>, <source>Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science</source>, <volume>36</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gummesson</surname>
<given-names>Evert</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>), <source>Qualitative Methods in Management Research</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, California</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hart</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>), <source>Doing a Literature Review. Releasing the Social Science Research Imagination</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Heidegger</surname>
<given-names>Martin</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>[1927]1962</year>), <source>Being and Time</source> [trans. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Macquarrie</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Robinson</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>]. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Heinonen</surname>
<given-names>Kristina</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>), <article-title>“The Influence of Customer Activity on e-Service Value-in-use,”</article-title> <source>International Journal of Electronic Business</source>, <volume>7</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Heinonen</surname>
<given-names>Kristina</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Strandvik</surname>
<given-names>Tore</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mickelsson</surname>
<given-names>Karl-Jacob</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bo</surname>
<given-names>Edvardsson</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sundstrom</surname>
<given-names>Eric</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Andersson</surname>
<given-names>Per</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>), <article-title>“A Customer-Dominant Logic of Service”</article-title>, <source>Journal of Service Management</source>, <volume>21</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>548</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hennig-Thurau</surname>
<given-names>Thorsten</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kevin</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gwinner</surname>
<given-names>Gianfranco Walsh</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gremler</surname>
<given-names>Dayne D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>), <article-title>“Electronic Word-of-Mouth Via Consumer-Opinion Platforms: What Motivates Consumers to Articulate Themselves on the Internet?”</article-title> <source>Journal of Direct Marketing</source>, <volume>18</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Helkkula</surname>
<given-names>Anu</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>), <article-title>“Characterising the Concept of Service Experience,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Service Management</source>, <volume>22</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Helkkula</surname>
<given-names>Anu</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kelleher</surname>
<given-names>Carol</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>), <article-title>“Circularity of Customer Service Experience and Customer Perceived Value,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Customer Behaviour</source>, <volume>9</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Helkkula</surname>
<given-names>Anu</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pihlström</surname>
<given-names>Minna</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>), <article-title>“Narratives and Metaphors in Service Development,”</article-title> <source>Qualitative Market Research</source>, <volume>13</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>354</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hogan</surname>
<given-names>John E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lemon</surname>
<given-names>Katherine N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rust</surname>
<given-names>Roland T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>), <article-title>“Customer Equity Management: Charting New Directions for the Future of Marketing,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Service Research</source>, <volume>5</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holbrook</surname>
<given-names>Morris B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>“Customer Value and Autoethnography: Subjective Personal Introspection and the Meanings of a Photograph Collection,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Business Research</source>, <volume>58</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holbrook</surname>
<given-names>Morris B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>), <article-title>“The Nature of Customer Value, An Axiology of Services in the Consumption Experience”</article-title> in <source>Service Quality. New Directions in Theory and Practice</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Rust</surname>
<given-names>R. W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Richard</surname>
<given-names>L. O.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds., <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>, <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holbrook</surname>
<given-names>Morris B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hirschman</surname>
<given-names>Elizabeth C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>), <article-title>“The Experiential Aspects of Consumption: Consumer Fantasies, Feelings, and Fun,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source>, <volume>9</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hudson</surname>
<given-names>Laurel A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ozanne</surname>
<given-names>Julie L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>), <article-title>“Alternative Ways of Seeking Knowledge in Consumer Research,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source>, <volume>14</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>508</fpage>–<lpage>552</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Husserl</surname>
<given-names>Edmund</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>[1936] 1970</year>), <source>The Crisis of European Sciences and Transcendental Phenomenology</source> [trans. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Carr</surname>
<given-names>David</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>]. <publisher-loc>Evanston, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Northwestern University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Husserl</surname>
<given-names>Edmund</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>[1931] 1967</year>), <source>Cartesian Meditations</source> [trans. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Cairns</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>]. <publisher-loc>The Hague, The Netherlands</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Martinus Nijoff</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jacoby</surname>
<given-names>Edmund</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Braun</surname>
<given-names>Ulrike U.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <source>50 Klassiker Philosopher. Denker von der Antike bis Heute</source>. <publisher-loc>Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Gerstenberg</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Johns</surname>
<given-names>Nick</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tyas</surname>
<given-names>Phil</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>), <article-title>“Customer Perceptions of Service Operations: Gestalt, Incident or Mythology?”</article-title> <source>The Service Industries Journal</source>, <volume>17</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>474</fpage>–<lpage>488</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kelleher</surname>
<given-names>Carol</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Helkkula</surname>
<given-names>Anu</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>), <article-title>“Virtually Speaking—Customer to Customer Communication in Virtual Communities,”</article-title> <source>The Journal of Applied Management and Entrepreneurship</source>, <volume>15</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kelleher</surname>
<given-names>Carol</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>Joe</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>), <article-title>“Consumer Experience of Value Creation: A Phenomenological Perspective,”</article-title> <source>European Advances in Consumer Research</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kleijnen</surname>
<given-names>Mirella</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wetzels</surname>
<given-names>Martin</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ko</surname>
<given-names>de Ruyter</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>), <article-title>“Consumer Acceptance of Wireless Finance,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Financial Services Marketing</source>, <volume>8</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>206</fpage>–<lpage>217</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Konanam</surname>
<given-names>Prabhudev</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Balasubramanian</surname>
<given-names>Sridhar</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>), <article-title>“The Social-Economic-Psychological Model of Technology Adoption and Usage: An Application to Online Investing,”</article-title> <source>Decision Support Systems</source>, <volume>39</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>524</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lemon</surname>
<given-names>Katherine N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Parasuraman</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <article-title>“Managing Customers for Value. An Overview and Research Agenda,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Service Research</source>, <volume>9</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kvale</surname>
<given-names>Steinar</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brinkmann</surname>
<given-names>Svend</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>), <source>InterViews: Learning the Craft of Qualitative Research Interviewing</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Langdridge</surname>
<given-names>Darren</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <source>Phenomenological Psychology Theory, Research and Method</source>, <publisher-loc>Essex</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson Education Limited</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Laukkanen</surname>
<given-names>Tommi</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lauronen</surname>
<given-names>Jari</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>), <article-title>“Consumer Value Creation in Mobile Banking Services,”</article-title> <source>International Journal of Mobile Communications</source>, <volume>3</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lepak</surname>
<given-names>David P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>Ken G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>Susan M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Value Creation and Value Capture a Multilevel Perspective,”</article-title> <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>32</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>180</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McKee</surname>
<given-names>Robert</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>), <source>Story: Substance, Structure, Style</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Regan Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Merleau-Ponty</surname>
<given-names>Maurice</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>[1945] 1962</year>), <source>Phenomenology of Perception</source> [trans. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>]. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>Christopher</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schwager</surname>
<given-names>Andre</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Understanding Customer Experience,”</article-title> <source>Harvard Business Review</source>, <volume>85</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>Kent D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fabian</surname>
<given-names>Frances</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Shu-Jou</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>), <article-title>“Strategies for Online Communities,”</article-title> <source>Strategic Management Journal</source>, <volume>30</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ostrom</surname>
<given-names>Amy L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bitner</surname>
<given-names>Mary Jo</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>Stephen W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burkhard</surname>
<given-names>Kevin A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goul</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smith-Daniels</surname>
<given-names>Vicki</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Demirkan</surname>
<given-names>Haluk</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rabinovich</surname>
<given-names>Elliot S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>), <article-title>“Moving Forward and Making a Difference: Research Priorities for the Science of Service,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Service Research</source>, <volume>13</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Palmer</surname>
<given-names>Adrian</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Koenig-Lewis</surname>
<given-names>Nicole</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>), <article-title>“Editorial Essay: An Extended, Community Focused, Experiential Framework for Relationship Marketing,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Customer Behaviour</source>, <volume>8</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Patterson</surname>
<given-names>Anthony</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hodgson Julia</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>Jiwei</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Chronicles of ‘Customer Experience’: The Downfall of Lewis’s Foretold,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing Management</source>, <volume>24</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Payne</surname>
<given-names>Adrian</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Storbacka</surname>
<given-names>Kai</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Frow</surname>
<given-names>Pennie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Managing the Co-Creation of Value,”</article-title> <source>Academy of Marketing Science Journal</source>, <volume>36</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pollio</surname>
<given-names>Howard R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Henley</surname>
<given-names>Tracy B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>Craig J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>), <source>The Phenomenology of Everyday Life</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Priem</surname>
<given-names>Richard L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“A Consumer Perspective on Value Creation,”</article-title> <source>The Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>32</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pura</surname>
<given-names>Minna</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Heinonen</surname>
<given-names>Kristina</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>“Exploring Mobile Service Business Opportunities from a Customer-Centric Perspective”</article-title>, in <source>Global Mobile Commerce: Strategies, Implementation and Case Studies</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> ed., <publisher-loc>Idea Group Inc. London</publisher-loc>, <fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reinartz</surname>
<given-names>Werner</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>“The Impact of Customer Relationship Characteristics on Profitable Lifetime Duration,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing</source>, <volume>67</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rescher</surname>
<given-names>Nicholas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1969</year>), <source>Introduction to Value Theory</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Riessman</surname>
<given-names>Catherine Kohler</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Speedy</surname>
<given-names>Jane</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Narrative Inquiry in the Psychotherapy Professions”</article-title> in <source>Handbook of Narrative Inquiry. Mapping a Methodology</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Clandinin</surname>
<given-names>D. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> ed., <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, California</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>, <fpage>426</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sanchez-Fernandez</surname>
<given-names>Raquel</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Angeles</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name>
<surname>Iniesta-Bonillo</surname>
<given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“The Concept of Perceived Value: A Systematic Review of the Research,”</article-title> <source>Marketing Theory</source>, <volume>7</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sanchez-Fernandez</surname>
<given-names>Raquel</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Angeles</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name>
<surname>Holbrook</surname>
<given-names>Morris B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>), <article-title>“The Conceptualization and Measurement of Customer Value in Services,”</article-title> <source>International Journal of Marketing Research</source>, <volume>15</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sandström</surname>
<given-names>Sara</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bo</surname>
<given-names>Edvardsson</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kristensson</surname>
<given-names>Per</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Magnusson</surname>
<given-names>Peter</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Value in Use through Service Experience,”</article-title> <source>Managing Service Quality</source>, <volume>18</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schau</surname>
<given-names>Hope Jensen</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Muniz</surname>
<given-names>Albert M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arnould</surname>
<given-names>Eric J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>), <article-title>“How Brand Community Practices Create Value,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing</source>, <volume>73</volume> (<month>September</month>), <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schutz</surname>
<given-names>Alfred</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>), <source>The Phenomenology of the Social World</source>. <publisher-loc>Evanston, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Northwestern University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>Denish</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rust</surname>
<given-names>Roland T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Parasuraman</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Staelin</surname>
<given-names>Richard</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Day</surname>
<given-names>George S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <article-title>“The Path to Customer Centricity,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Service Research</source>, <volume>9</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shankar</surname>
<given-names>Avi</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Patterson</surname>
<given-names>Maurice P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>), <article-title>“Interpreting the Past, Writing the Future,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing Management</source>, <volume>17</volume> (<issue>5/6</issue>), <fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>501</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sheth</surname>
<given-names>Jagdish N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Newman</surname>
<given-names>Bruce N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gross</surname>
<given-names>Barbara L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>), <source>Consumption Values and Market Choices: Theory and Applications</source>. <publisher-loc>Cincinnati, OH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>South-Western</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>J. Brock</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Colgate</surname>
<given-names>Mark</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Customer Value Creation: A Practical Framework,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing Theory and Practice</source>, <volume>15</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>Jonathan A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Flowers</surname>
<given-names>Paul</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Larkin</surname>
<given-names>Michael M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>), <source>Interpretative Phenomenological Analysis Theory, Method and Research</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sweeney</surname>
<given-names>Jillian C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>), <article-title>“Customer-Perceived Value”</article-title> in <source>Services Marketing: A Managerial Approach</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>McColl-Kennedy</surname>
<given-names>J. R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> ed., <publisher-loc>Milton, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley</publisher-name>, <fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sweeney</surname>
<given-names>Jillian C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Soutar</surname>
<given-names>Geoffrey N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>), <article-title>“Consumer Perceived Value: The Development of a Multiple Item Scale,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Retailing</source>, <volume>77</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>Craig J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Locander</surname>
<given-names>William B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pollio</surname>
<given-names>Howard R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>), <article-title>“Putting Consumer Experience back into Consumer Research: The Philosophy and Method of Existential-Phenomenology,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source>, <volume>16</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr84-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tuomi</surname>
<given-names>Jouni</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sarajärvi</surname>
<given-names>Anneli</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>), <source>Laadullinen Tutkimus Ja Sisällönanalyysi</source>, <publisher-loc>Jyväskylä. Finland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Gummerus Kirjapaino Oy</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr85-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tynan</surname>
<given-names>Caroline</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McKechnie</surname>
<given-names>Sally A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>), <article-title>“Experience Marketing: A Review and Reassessment,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing Management</source>, <volume>25</volume> (<issue>5/6</issue>), <fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>517</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr86-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Valberg</surname>
<given-names>Jerry J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>), <source>The Puzzle of Experience</source>, <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Clarendon Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr87-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vargo</surname>
<given-names>Stephen L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Customer Integration and Value Creation: Paradigmatic Traps and Perspectives,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Service Research</source>, <volume>11</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr88-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vargo</surname>
<given-names>Stephen L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lusch</surname>
<given-names>Robert</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Service-Dominant Logic: Continuing the Evolution,”</article-title> <source>Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science</source>, <volume>36</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr89-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Venkatesh</surname>
<given-names>Viswanath</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morris</surname>
<given-names>Michael G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>Fred D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>), <article-title>“User Acceptance of Information Technology: Toward a Unified View,”</article-title> <source>MIS Quarterly</source>, <volume>27</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>478</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr90-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Webb</surname>
<given-names>John R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>), <source>Understanding and Designing Marketing Research</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr91-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Webster</surname>
<given-names>Leonard</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mertova</surname>
<given-names>Patricie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <source>Using Narrative Inquiry as a Research Method, Introduction to Using Critical Event Narrative Analysis in Research on Learning and Teaching</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr92-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Woodruff</surname>
<given-names>Robert B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>), <article-title>“Customer Value: The Next Source for Competitive Advantage,”</article-title> <source>Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science</source>, <volume>25</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr93-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Woodruff</surname>
<given-names>Robert B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Flint</surname>
<given-names>Daniel</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <article-title>“Marketing’s Service-dominant Logic and Customer Value”</article-title> in <source>The Service-Dominant Logic of Marketing: Dialog, Debate, and Directions</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Vargo</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lusch</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds., <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>M.E. Sharpe</publisher-name>, <fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr94-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Smith Woodruff</surname>
<given-names>David</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <source>“Phenomenology [Homepage of Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy],”</source> <comment>(accessed September 25, 2010), [available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/phenomenology">http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/phenomenology</ext-link>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr95-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Smith Woodruff</surname>
<given-names>David</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <source>Husserl</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr96-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zeithaml</surname>
<given-names>Valerie A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>), <article-title>“Consumer Perceptions of Price, Quality, and Value: A Means-End Model and Synthesis of Evidence,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing</source>, <volume>52</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr97-1094670511426897">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zeithaml</surname>
<given-names>Valerie A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bolton</surname>
<given-names>Ruth N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Deighton</surname>
<given-names>John</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Keiningham</surname>
<given-names>Timothy L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lemon</surname>
<given-names>Katherine N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Andrew Petersen</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <article-title>“Forward-looking Focus: Can Firms have Adaptive Foresight?”</article-title> <source>Journal of Service Research</source>, <volume>9</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1094670511426897">
<p>
<bold>Anu Helkkula</bold> (anu.helkkula@hanken.fi) is a senior researcher at the Centre for Relationship Marketing and Service Management (CERS) at Hanken School of Economics in Helsinki, Finland, where she received her PhD in 2010. Her primary research interests include service experience, the co-creation of value, and the development of innovation practices. For 20 years, she has worked in service management and development positions. Her research has appeared in the Journal of Service Management, Qualitative Market Research, the International Journal of Pharmaceutical and Health Care Marketing, the Journal of Customer Behaviour, and the Journal of Applied Management &amp; Entrepreneurship. She is also a senior researcher at Aalto University School of Science, Finland (anu.helkkula@aalto.fi).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1094670511426897">
<p>
<bold>Carol Kelleher</bold> (carol.kelleher@ucc.ie) is a lecturer in marketing at University College Cork, Ireland and a PhD candidate (part-time programme) at Cranfield School of Management, United Kingdom (carol.kelleher@cranfield.ac.uk). Carol’s research focuses on the consumer experience and practice of value co-creation in collaborative consumption contexts. Her research has appeared in the Journal of Customer Behaviour, the International Journal of Electronic Government Research, the Journal of Applied Management and Entrepreneurship, and the Irish Management Journal.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1094670511426897">
<p>
<bold>Minna Pihlström</bold> (minna.pihlstrom@hanken.fi) is a senior researcher at the Centre for Relationship Marketing and Service Management (CERS) at Hanken School of Economics in Helsinki, Finland, where she received her PhD in 2008. Her primary research interests include mobile and e-commerce, customer perceived value, customer equity and loyalty, and strategic customer segmentation. Her research has appeared in Psychology and Marketing, the Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services, Qualitative Market Research, the Journal of Services Marketing, Managing Service Quality, and the Journal of Information Technology, Theory and Applications. She also acts as a senior consultant at Segmento Oy.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>