<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EHP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spehp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eval Health Prof</journal-id>
<journal-title>Evaluation &amp; the Health Professions</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0163-2787</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3918</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0163278711423937</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0163278711423937</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Professional Competence</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Defining Physicians’ Readiness to Screen and Manage Intimate Partner Violence in Greek Primary Care Settings</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Papadakaki</surname>
<given-names>Maria</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0163278711423937">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0163278711423937"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Prokopiadou</surname>
<given-names>Dimitra</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0163278711423937">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Petridou</surname>
<given-names>Eleni</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0163278711423937">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kogevinas</surname>
<given-names>Manolis</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0163278711423937">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lionis</surname>
<given-names>Christos</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0163278711423937">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0163278711423937"><label>1</label>Clinic of Social and Family Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Crete, Heraklion, Greece</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0163278711423937"><label>2</label>Department of Hygiene, Epidemiology and Medical Statistics, Athens University Medical School, Goudi, Athens, Greece</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0163278711423937"><label>3</label>National School of Public Health, Athens, Greece</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0163278711423937">Maria Papadakaki, Voiotias 13, PC 71303, Heraklion, Greece Email: <email>mpapadakaki@yahoo.gr</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>35</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>199</fpage>
<lpage>220</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The current article aims to translate the PREMIS (Physician Readiness to Manage Intimate Partner Violence) survey into the Greek language and test its validity and reliability in a sample of primary care physicians. The validation study was conducted in 2010 and involved all the general practitioners serving two adjacent prefectures of Greece (<italic>n</italic> = 80). Maximum-likelihood factor analysis (MLF) was used to extract key survey factors. The instrument was further assessed for the following psychometric properties: (a) scale reliability, (b) item-specific reliability, (c) test–retest reliability, (d) scale construct validity, and (e) internal predictive validity. The MLF analysis of 23 opinion items revealed a seven-factor solution (<italic>preparation, constraint, workplace issues, screening, self-efficacy, alcohol/drugs, victim understanding</italic>), which was statistically sound (<italic>p</italic> = .293). Most of the newly derived scales displayed satisfactory internal consistency (α ≥ .60), high item-specific reliability, strong construct, and internal predictive validity (<italic>F</italic> = 2.82; <italic>p</italic> = .004), and high repeatability when retested with 20 individuals (intraclass correlation coefficient [ICC] &gt; .70). The tool was found appropriate to facilitate the identification of competence deficits and the evaluation of training initiatives.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>intimate partner violence</kwd>
<kwd>primary health care</kwd>
<kwd>screening</kwd>
<kwd>validation</kwd>
<kwd>PREMIS</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0163278711423937">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>A large body of evidence documents the often severe and long-lasting impact of intimate partner violence (IPV) on human health including, fatal outcomes, acute and chronic physical injuries, mental health problems and behavioral problems, gynecological disorders and obstetric complications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0163278711423937">Coker, Smith, Bethea, King, &amp; McKeown, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0163278711423937">Feder et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0163278711423937">Hathaway et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0163278711423937">Jasinski, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0163278711423937">Plichta &amp; Falik, 2001</xref>). As with other diagnostic challenges, the primary care physician, who has developed a trusting relationship with the patient, is in an ideal position to take a thorough history, assess mental and physical health, including the psychosocial context, and link physical symptoms with the underlying abuse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0163278711423937">Naumann, Langford, Torres, Campbell, &amp; Glass, 1999</xref>). Nevertheless, primary care providers have been criticized for not assessing routinely their patients’ exposure to IPV and rarely documenting the cases in medical records (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0163278711423937">Lapidus et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0163278711423937">Waalen, Goodwin, Spitz, Petersen, &amp; Saltzman, 2000</xref>). They are criticized generally for providing suboptimal care to women exposed to IPV (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0163278711423937">Alpert, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0163278711423937">Gadomski, Wolff, Tripp, Lewis, &amp; Short, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0163278711423937">Sugg, Thompson, Thompson, Maurio, &amp; Rivara, 1999</xref>). A number of studies of primary care physicians have documented high levels of misperceptions and prejudicial attitudes about IPV along with a knowledge gap, lack of awareness, and poor clinical skills and practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0163278711423937">Gutmanis, Beynon, Tutty, Wathen, &amp; MacMillan, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0163278711423937">Miller &amp; Jaye, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0163278711423937">Rodriguez, McLoughlin, Nah, &amp; Campbell, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0163278711423937">Sugg et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0163278711423937">Weinreb, Fletcher, Candib, &amp; Bacigalupe, 2007</xref>). It has also been noted that family physicians remain uncertain about their role with respect to assessment for IPV (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0163278711423937">Janssen, Dascal-Weichhendler, &amp; McGregor, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>A critical challenge is thus to increase the numbers of primary care physicians working with IPV victims while simultaneously preparing them to meet the specialized needs of an abused population. Most importantly, there is a need to define competencies for primary care physicians and foster training opportunities in the field. Although certain efforts were undertaken in the past decades to define competencies for primary care physicians, questions remain about the core attitude, knowledge, and skill competencies required to serve IPV victims competently as well as about the core aspects of training needed to develop such competence. The lack of convenient and well-defined outcome measures of actual changes in clinical practices, knowledge and skills, remains a pressing gap (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0163278711423937">Cohn, Salmon, &amp; Stobo, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0163278711423937">Garcia-Moreno, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0163278711423937">Nicolaidis, Curry, &amp; Gerrity, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0163278711423937">Short, Alpert, Harris, &amp; Surprenant, 2006</xref>). In that respect, not many tools exist to assess the effectiveness of educational interventions on health care providers’ knowledge, attitudes, beliefs, and self-reported behaviors (KABB; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0163278711423937">Short, Cotton, &amp; Hodgson, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0163278711423937">Short, Surprenant, &amp; Harris, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0163278711423937">Sugg et al., 1999</xref>) and when these tools were applied to different populations, they presented various limitations related to their sample size and generalizability as well as their construct validity and repeatability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0163278711423937">Gadomski et al., 2001</xref>; Harris, Salasche, &amp; Harris, 2002; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0163278711423937">Thompson et al., 2000</xref>). In the absence of common evaluation standards and tools, it is difficult to draw firm conclusions about the effectiveness of current interventions and their applicability in other settings.</p>
<p>As the training programmes addressing the needs of health care professionals are likely to have similar objectives, it would be helpful to standardize the process and content of training as well as the evaluation tools and measures. Among the few existing tools, the PREMIS (Physician Readiness to Manage Intimate Partner Violence) survey incorporated all KABB aspects and has further been shown to be reliable, valid, and sensitive to change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0163278711423937">Short, Alpert, et al., 2006</xref>). PREMIS is a 67-item tool, originally designed to assess physicians’ readiness to manage IPV by gathering information on four broad areas related to the physicians’ preparation, knowledge, opinion, and practice. In contrast to the rest of the tools, the PREMIS survey collected more detailed information on physicians’ self-reported behaviors and measured physicians’ actual knowledge based on up-to-date knowledge evidenced in current literature. As the PREMIS survey presents good psychometric properties and is most easily accessible, there are several initiatives in progress worldwide toward the adaptation and validation of the tool in various languages.</p>
<p>Certain circumstances mentioned below, underline the importance of this study for the Greek primary health care. Most importantly, IPV in Greece has been found to be very prevalent in the general population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0163278711423937">Papadakaki, Tzamalouka, Chatzifotiou, &amp; Chliaoutakis, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0163278711423937">Tzamalouka, Parlalis, Soultatou, Papadakaki, &amp; Chliaoutakis, 2007</xref>), but underrecognized and insufficiently documented in hospital records (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0163278711423937">Petridou et al., 2002</xref>). Surprisingly, although IPV has been shown to be more prevalent in rural than urban areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0163278711423937">Petridou et al., 2002</xref>), no actions have ever been commenced to improve identification of IPV in primary care settings. In order to effectively identify and address physicians’ competence deficits serving as barriers to early IPV identification, certain tools are needed and the current article reports on the results of the validation study of the PREMIS survey with Greek primary care physicians.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0163278711423937">
<title>Materials and Method</title>
<sec id="section3-0163278711423937">
<title>Instrument Adaptation</title>
<sec id="section4-0163278711423937">
<title>Translation</title>
<p>Written permission from the copyright holder of the PREMIS was obtained to produce a Greek version of the questionnaire, conceptually equivalent with the original and relevant to the new target culture. The instrument was translated into Greek using the standard forward–backward translation process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0163278711423937">Wild et al., 2005</xref>). A special form was developed to facilitate the translation process. Four individual translators were involved in the process as well as the instrument developer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0163278711423937">Short, Alpert, et.al., 2006</xref>). Initially, the original version was translated into Greek by two independent bilinguals, having certified knowledge in both the English and the Greek language. A third individual translator performed the reconciliation between the two initial English–Greek translations and all inconsistencies while merging the two versions were corrected in agreement with the two translators. The reconciled version was then back translated into English by a native speaker. All translations were included in the special form and were sent to the instrument developer for comments. The instrument developer was asked to compare the back-translated items with the original items and report on items that were not consistent due to cross-cultural differences. Discrepancies were resolved through subsequent refinement.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0163278711423937">
<title>Face validity</title>
<p>Five general practitioners serving rural health centers in Crete were conveniently drawn from the target population to be cognitively debriefed with respect to comprehensibility, ambiguity of the items, and relevance to social context (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0163278711423937">Wild et al., 2005</xref>). A special form was developed to facilitate the cognitive debriefing process as a measure of face validity, asking participants to evaluate three different aspects of each PREMIS item with a 5-point Likert-type scale: (a) appropriateness of the application of the PREMIS items to the primary care context and the general practitioners duties; (b) clarity of the questions; (c) rephrasing alternatives for potentially ambiguous items. A cognitive debriefing report was produced on points of uncertainty and actions taken. Final adjustments were made as necessary.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0163278711423937">
<title>Validation Study</title>
<sec id="section8-0163278711423937">
<title>Study population</title>
<p>All general practitioners (<italic>n</italic> = 108) serving rural health centers in two of the four prefectures of Crete region in Greece (Heraklion, Rethymno) were invited to participate in the study. A list of practicing physicians was obtained from the Regional Health Administration to facilitate the sample selection process, following an official request. A total of 80 general practitioners completed the PREMIS survey, achieving a response rate of 74%.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0163278711423937">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>The current study is part of a broader research project carried out at Crete region in Greece, aiming to explore issues of identification and management of IPV in primary health care. The project was partly funded by the Research Committee of the University of Crete and received approval by two governmental bioethical bodies, operating at local and national level; the Bioethical Committee of the University Hospital in Heraklion, Crete (Ref. No 953/13-02-2009) and the National Centre for Health Research, EKEPI (Ref. No 6455/10-06-2009). The study was conducted between March and May 2010 in two adjacent prefectures of Heraklion and Rethymno in Greece. Test–retest reliability was assessed over a 3- to 4-week period and was based on a sample of 20 general practitioners recruited via a practice based research network in primary care operating in Crete, Greece (mean age = 40.7; SD = 1.3; range = 39–43; female, 60.0%; mean clinical experience = 7.6; SD = 1.4; range = 6–11). The questionnaire was self-administered and was completed during face-to-face contacts with the study participants, at their working practice. The questionnaire was delivered by a professional social worker (MP) with postgraduate studies in public health and previous experience with IPV research and the mean duration of its completion was 35 min. Participants were provided oral and written information on study goals and objectives and promised anonymity and confidentiality. Their informed consent was obtained before completing the questionnaire.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0163278711423937">
<title>Survey instrument</title>
<p>The study employed the PREMIS survey, a tool developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0163278711423937">Short, Alpert, et al. (2006)</xref> comprising 67 items. An outline of the tool is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0163278711423937">Table 1</xref>
. The final version of the questionnaire involves a number of individual scales exploring physician’s perceived and actual preparedness to identify and manage IPV as follows (a) perceived preparation, (b) perceived knowledge, (c) actual knowledge, (d) opinions, and (e) practice issues through self-reported behaviors. The perceived preparation scale includes 12 items asking respondents how prepared they feel to assist IPV victims with responses ranging from 1 (not prepared) to 7 (quite well prepared). The perceived knowledge scale contains 16 items asking how much respondents feel they know about IPV with responses ranging from 1 (nothing) to 5 (very much). The actual knowledge scale represents a total score of correct items deriving from 8 multiple choice items and 11 true/false items on IPV causes, manifestations, victim’s behavioral patterns, and physician’s professional practices. The opinion scale includes 32 items exploring participants’ beliefs on the causes of IPV, victims’ condition, and physicians’ role in IPV management with responses ranging from 1 (strongly disagree) to 7 (strongly agree). The practice issues scale includes 13 items investigating self-reported behaviors on IPV management with various responding options.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0163278711423937" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Outline of the Original PREMIS Survey</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0163278711423937" xlink:href="10.1177_0163278711423937-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Sections</th>
<th>Scales</th>
<th>Number of Items</th>
<th>Sample Item</th>
<th>Response Options</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Respondent profile</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>Age, gender</td>
<td>Various response options</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">Background</td>
<td>Perceived preparation</td>
<td rowspan="2">4</td>
<td>How prepared do you feel to identify IPV indicators based on patient history and physical examination</td>
<td>Likert-type scale (1 = <italic>not prepared</italic>, 7 = <italic>quite well prepared</italic>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Perceived knowledge</td>
<td>How much do you feel you now know about what questions to ask to identify IPV</td>
<td>Likert-type scale (1 = <italic>nothing</italic>, 5 = <italic>very much</italic>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Knowledge</td>
<td>Actual knowledge</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>Which of the following are warning signs that a patient may have been abused by his or her partner?</td>
<td>8 multiple choice and 11 true/false items</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Opinions</td>
<td>Opinion scale</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>I do not have sufficient training to assist individuals in addressing situations of IPV</td>
<td>Likert-type scale (1 = <italic>strongly disagree</italic>, 7 = <italic>strongly agree</italic>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Practice issues</td>
<td>Practice issues</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>Is there a protocol for dealing with adult IPV at your clinic/practice?</td>
<td>Various response options</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0163278711423937">
<p>
<italic>Note</italic>. IPV = intimate partner violence.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0163278711423937">
<p>
<italic>Source</italic>. Short, Alpert, et al. (2006).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0163278711423937">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>All data analyses were carried out with the Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS, Windows version 17.0; SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL). Analysis was based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0163278711423937">Short, Alpert, et al.’s (2006)</xref> codebook and SPSS syntax (available online at ajpm-online.net). Negative-worded items were reverse coded for the needs of the analysis. Descriptive analysis was performed whenever appropriate.</p>
<sec id="section13-0163278711423937">
<title>Factor analysis</title>
<p>Exploratory factor analysis (EFA) was used for the 32 items of the opinion scale of the original instrument because our primary aim was to explore and refine the underlying structure of the items. The individual item suitability (skew range = −0.91 to 0.93; kurtosis range = −1.30 to 1.45) confirmed the suitability of the maximum-likelihood factor (MLF) extraction procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0163278711423937">Fabrigar, Wegener, Maccallum, &amp; Strahan, 1999</xref>). The MLF analysis was used to extract key survey factors and verify how well survey items fit the constructs that they were designed to measure. A Bartlett’s test of sphericity with p &lt; .05 and a Kaiser–Meyer–Olkin (KMO) measure of sampling adequacy of 0.6 were used to perform the analysis. Factor loadings were estimated for exploratory purposes, using a lower item loading level of 0.32 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0163278711423937">Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 2001</xref>) cited as a good rule of thumb, equating to approximately 10% overlapping variance with the other items in that factor. Only factor loadings greater than 0.20 were displayed in the analysis. The dimensional structure was based on Eigenvalues &gt; 1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0163278711423937">Hakstian, Rogers, &amp; Cattell, 1982</xref>). The highest loadings were considered for scale assignment. Items were considered for deletion if they loaded on two or more factors or had a correlation of less than 0.32 with their own factor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0163278711423937">Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 2001</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0163278711423937">
<title>Reliability and validity</title>
<p>The PREMIS survey was then assessed for the following psychometric properties (a) scale reliability, (b) item-specific reliability, (c) test–retest reliability (repeatability), (d) construct validity, and (e) internal predictive validity. The Cronbach’s coefficient α was used to test the internal consistency reliability of identified scales, for which ≥.7 was considered satisfactory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0163278711423937">Cormack, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0163278711423937">Polit &amp; Hunglar, 1999</xref>). Assessment of the item-specific reliability of newly derived factors was made by correlating each item with its own scale and by testing each scale’s internal consistency with the item removed. Poor items were defined as those that when deleted, increased the Cronbach’s α coefficient by .1 or more (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0163278711423937">Ferketich, 1991</xref>). The test–retest reliability addressed the overall stability rate of items through measuring 20 participants’ response shift on the items between test and retest. Test–retest reliability was estimated by the single measure of intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC), using a one-way random model with an absolute agreement type, with 95% confidence interval (CI) and with ratings 0 to 0.2 considered as poor, 0.2 to 0.4 fair, 0.4 to 0.6 moderate, 0.6 to 0.8 substantial, and 0.8 to 1.0 almost perfect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0163278711423937">Landis &amp; Koch, 1977</xref>). Between-scale correlations were used as a measure of construct validity, for which r &gt; .70 was considered as strong. A linear regression model was calculated to test the internal predictive validity of key survey constructs, employing the cumulative score of Practice issues as the dependent variable and the Background and Opinion scales as independent variables. The model tested whether self-reported professional practices could be predicted by the key survey constructs such as the actual and perceived knowledge scales as well as by the newly derived opinion scales.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0163278711423937">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section17-0163278711423937">
<title>Cultural Adaptation</title>
<p>A number of modifications were introduced in the Greek version of the questionnaire as a result of the translation and cognitive debriefing process. In particular, 4 items were omitted from the <italic>Opinion Section</italic> due to being irrelevant to the Greek context. The first 3 items (12a, 12b, and 12c) referred to mandatory reporting laws on IPV, child, and elder abuse and the 4th item (17) referred to an accrediting organization <italic>Joint Commission</italic>, not applying in Greece. Another 2 items were omitted from the list of referral resources under the <italic>Practice Issues</italic> section. These items referred to IPV support services are not available in Greece such as the lesbian, gay, transvestite, bisexual support, and the batterers treatment program. Besides the exclusion of certain items not applying in the Greek context, a number of items were modified to better reflect the local situation. For example, some categories of referral resources were included in the list of resources of the Greek questionnaire with their full local name instead of the general category name they represented, so as to be more realistic and familiar to the survey participants. Furthermore, items reflecting the U.S. situation were adapted to the Greek context. For example, all reference to <italic>the states</italic>, where substituted by the term <italic>countrywide</italic> to represent the Greek country. Finally, some words, when translated in Greek deviated from the original meaning and thus were not translated word-to-word (e.g., the word “witnessing”).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0163278711423937">
<title>Sample Characteristics</title>
<p>Participants were almost evenly split by gender (men; <italic>n</italic> = 43, 53.8%). Their mean age was 42.2 years (<italic>SD</italic> = 5.3) and their mean clinical experience was 20.4 years (<italic>SD</italic> = 3.1). The majority of the primary care physicians were practicing in the prefecture of Heraklion (<italic>n</italic> = 66, 82.5%) and the vast majority had no previous training on IPV (<italic>n</italic> = 76, 95.0%).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0163278711423937">
<title>Psychometric Characteristics</title>
<sec id="section20-0163278711423937">
<title>Factor Structure</title>
<p>Initial factor analysis of the 32 opinion items (4 items were excluded during the cognitive debriefing process) revealed a nine-factor solution (MLF analysis), which rejected the null hypothesis of good fit (χ<sup>2</sup> = 348.349, <italic>df</italic> = 244, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .000). However, the KMO measure of sampling adequacy was 0.613 indicating suitability of the data for factor analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0163278711423937">Kaiser &amp; Rice, 1974</xref>). Bartlett’s test of sphericity was significant (χ<sup>2</sup> = 1272.66, <italic>df</italic> = 496, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .0001) showing significant correlation between items and therefore suitability of the data for structure detection. The model explained 61.5% of the variability in the original 32 variables. Two factors displayed 2 items with high loadings and one factor displayed just 1 item. This model seemed to lack a good theoretical solution and thus a new MLF model was recomputed after discarding 9 items that met the criteria initially set for item deletion. These items cross-loaded highly on two or more factors or poorly contributed to the factor they loaded on (Items 3, 4, 5, 8, 9, 22, 27, 30, and 32). All the items currently discarded can be located in the original instrument (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0163278711423937">Short, Alpert, et al., 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>The new MLF model revealed a seven-factor solution, which was statistically sound with a <italic>p</italic> value greater than the threshold of .05 (<italic>p</italic> = .293). This model explained 57.5% of the total variance and generated a comprehensible factor structure, similar to the factor structure demonstrated by the instrument developer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0163278711423937">Short, Alpert, et al., 2006</xref>). Below there is a detailed description of the structure and the characteristics of the new factors in comparison with the original opinion scales demonstrated by the instrument developers.</p>
<p>The <italic>first factor</italic>, which accounted for 15.47% of the variance, comprised 4 items (10a, 10b, 10c, and 28) such as <italic>I don’t have the necessary skills to discuss abuse with an IPV victim who is female</italic> and was labeled “Preparation.” All the items of the new scale loaded in their original factor and the factor loadings ranged between .417 and .931. The <italic>second factor</italic> accounted for 6.40% of the variance and comprised 3 items (13, 23, and 24) such as <italic>Health care providers do not have the time to assist patients in addressing IPV</italic>. This factor was labeled “Constraints” and had 2 items in common with the original 2-item scale (Items 13 and 23). The factor loadings ranged between .381 and .950. The <italic>third factor</italic> was labeled “Workplace issues” and accounted for 15.62% of the total variance. It comprised 5 items (6, 19, 20, 25, and 29) such as <italic>My practice setting allows me adequate time to respond to victims of IPV</italic> and the factor loadings ranged between .325 and .759. The new factor had 3 items in common with the original 6-item scale (Items 19, 20, and 25). The <italic>fourth factor</italic> did not replicate any of the original opinion scales. It accounted for 6.33% of the total variance and was labelled Screening. It incorporated 2 items (2 and 18) both referring to the physicians’ screening practices in IPV situations such as <italic>I ask all new patients about abuse in their relationships</italic>. These items derived from two different factors in the original opinion scale (“Victim Autonomy” and “Victim Understanding”) and the factor loadings were .638 and .821. The <italic>fifth factor</italic> was labeled “Self-efficacy,” comprised 3 items (14, 26, and 31) such as <italic>I am able to gather the necessary information to identify IPV as the underlying cause of patient illnesses (e.g., depression, migraines)</italic>, and accounted for 6.21% of the variance. The new scale had only 1 item in common with the original scale (Item 14) and the factor loadings ranged between −.537 and −.793. The <italic>sixth factor</italic> accounted for 3.83% of the variance. It was labeled <italic>Alcohol/Drugs</italic> and comprised 2 items (7, 21) such as <italic>Patients who abuse alcohol or other drugs are likely to have a history of IPV</italic>. Both items loaded in their original factor and their loadings were −.520 and .617. The <italic>seventh factor</italic> was labeled <italic>Victim Understanding</italic> and accounted for 3.63% of the variance. It comprised 4 items (1, 11, 15, and 16) such as <italic>If victims of abuse remain in the relationship after repeated episodes of violence, they must accept responsibility for that violence</italic>. All items loaded in their original factor and the factor loadings ranged between .454 and .645.</p>
<p>Two opinion scales of the original instrument did not emerge in the current model. The first scale was the <italic>Legal requirements</italic>, whose items were excluded during the cognitive debriefing process as they did not apply in our country (Items 12a, 12b, 12c, and 17). The second scale was the <italic>Victim autonomy</italic>, whose items were discarded during the recalculation of the model of factor analysis (Items 8, 22, and 30).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0163278711423937">
<title>Scale Reliability</title>
<sec id="section22-0163278711423937">
<title>Background scales</title>
<p>Descriptive data on the mean scores and Cronbach’s α coefficients from the responses in the three background scales are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0163278711423937">Table 2</xref>
. The mean score in the <italic>Perceived Preparation</italic> scale was 4.09 (<italic>SD</italic> = 1.17) across all 11 items and its internal consistency was high (α = .932). Scores in the <italic>Perceived Knowledge</italic> scale had a mean of 3.36 (<italic>SD</italic> = 1.22) across the 16 items and its internal consistency was high as well (α = .960). The mean score in the <italic>Actual Knowledge</italic> scale was 18.52 (<italic>SD</italic> = 4.58) across correct items from 8 multiple choice items and 11 true/false items; however, the Cronbach’s coefficient estimation was not appropriate.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0163278711423937" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Summary of Scale Characteristics</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0163278711423937" xlink:href="10.1177_0163278711423937-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Scales</th>
<th align="center">Total Items</th>
<th align="center">Cronbach’s α</th>
<th align="center">Mean (<italic>SD</italic>)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Background</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Perceived preparation</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>.932</td>
<td>4.09 (1.17)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Perceived knowledge</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>.960</td>
<td>3.36 (1.22)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Actual knowledge</td>
<td>18</td>
<td align="center">N/A</td>
<td>18.52 (4.58)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Opinions</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Preparation</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>.784</td>
<td>3.70 (1.24)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Constraints</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>.613</td>
<td>4.33 (1.38)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Workplace issues</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>.775</td>
<td>3.09 (1.13)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Screening</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>.582</td>
<td>3.45 (1.40)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Self-efficacy</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>.752</td>
<td>4.78 (1.22)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Victim understanding</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>.633</td>
<td>4.10 (1.24)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Alcohol/drugs</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>&lt;.50</td>
<td>4.05 (0.80)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Practice issues</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Practice issues</td>
<td>13</td>
<td align="center">N/A</td>
<td>17.82 (5.93)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0163278711423937">
<p>
<italic>Note</italic>. N/A = not available; <italic>SD</italic> = standard deviation.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0163278711423937">
<title>Opinion scales</title>
<p>Seven factors were derived from the factor analysis. Although two factors contained just 2 items, all seven factors were tested for internal consistency. Five of the seven factors displayed satisfactory or acceptable internal consistency (α ≥ .60), one factor moderate (α = .582) and one factor low (α = &lt; .50). The factor mean scores and α coefficients are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0163278711423937">Table 2</xref>. <italic>Preparation</italic>, <italic>Workplace issues,</italic> and <italic>Self-efficacy</italic> displayed a satisfactory internal consistency (α = .784, α = .775, and α = .752, respectively), comparable to those of the three original scales (α = .850, α = .790, and α = .690, respectively). <italic>Constraints</italic> displayed an acceptable internal consistency (α = .613), higher than the one of the original scale (α = .470). <italic>Alcohol/Drugs</italic> displayed a low internal consistency (α &lt; .50) comparing with the satisfactory one of the original 3-item scale (α = .70). <italic>Victim Understanding</italic> displayed an acceptable internal consistency (α = .633), slightly lower than that of the original 6-item scale (α = .690). The newly derived scale <italic>Screening</italic> displayed a moderate internal consistency (α = .582).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0163278711423937">
<title>Item-Specific Reliability</title>
<p>Item-specific analysis showed that in all cases, the scale α coefficient would have either stayed the same or decreased if the item had been removed and all item-total correlations were greater than .30 suggesting that each scale measured a single construct (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0163278711423937">Table 3</xref>
).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0163278711423937" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Item Analysis for Each Study Scale</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0163278711423937" xlink:href="10.1177_0163278711423937-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Scale</th>
<th>Item No.</th>
<th align="center">Item-Total Correlation</th>
<th align="center">Cronbach’s α (Item Removed)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">Preparation (α = .784)</td>
<td>10a</td>
<td>.612</td>
<td>.719</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10b</td>
<td>.769</td>
<td>.632</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10c</td>
<td>.644</td>
<td>.702</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>28</td>
<td>.358</td>
<td>.779</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3">Constraints (α = .613)</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>.546</td>
<td>.316</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>23</td>
<td>.308</td>
<td>.609</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>24</td>
<td>.425</td>
<td>.508</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="5">Workplace issues (α = .775)</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>.316</td>
<td>.774</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>19</td>
<td>.584</td>
<td>.725</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td>.603</td>
<td>.720</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25</td>
<td>.649</td>
<td>.700</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>29</td>
<td>.631</td>
<td>.708</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">Screening (α = .582)</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>.412</td>
<td align="center">N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18</td>
<td>.412</td>
<td align="center">N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="3">Self-efficacy (α = .752)</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>.547</td>
<td>.712</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>26</td>
<td>.585</td>
<td>.665</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>31</td>
<td>.614</td>
<td>.632</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">Alcohol/drugs (α &lt; .50)</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>−.430</td>
<td align="center">N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>21</td>
<td>−.430</td>
<td align="center">N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="4">Victim understanding (α = .633)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>.306</td>
<td>.633</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>.434</td>
<td>.551</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>.528</td>
<td>.486</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td>.400</td>
<td>.573</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0163278711423937">
<p>
<italic>Note</italic>. N/A = not available.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-0163278711423937">
<title>Test–Retest Reliability</title>
<p>Differences between test and retest scores in all the PREMIS scales were explored (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0163278711423937">Table 4</xref>
). Overall, the values of ICC of the selected scales were substantial or high (ICC &gt; .70), with the exception of <italic>Screening</italic> and <italic>Constraints</italic>, which displayed fair-to-moderate ICC values (ICC = .370 and .571, respectively).</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0163278711423937" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Test–Retest Evaluation of the Greek PREMIS Survey Within a 3- to 4-Week Interval</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0163278711423937" xlink:href="10.1177_0163278711423937-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Scales</th>
<th align="center">ICC</th>
<th align="center">CI 95%</th>
<th>
<italic>p</italic> Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Background</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Perceived preparation</td>
<td>.844</td>
<td>[.56, .95]</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Perceived knowledge</td>
<td>.784</td>
<td>[.42, .93]</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Actual knowledge</td>
<td>.679</td>
<td>[.22, .89]</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Opinions</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Preparation</td>
<td>.830</td>
<td>[.52, .94]</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Constraints</td>
<td>.571</td>
<td>[.04, 85]</td>
<td>&lt;.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Workplace issues</td>
<td>.933</td>
<td>[.79, .98]</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Screening</td>
<td>.370</td>
<td>[−.20, −.76]</td>
<td>&lt;.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Self-efficacy</td>
<td>.778</td>
<td>[.41, .93]</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Victim understanding</td>
<td>.807</td>
<td>[.47, .94]</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Alcohol/Drugs</td>
<td>.790</td>
<td>[.43, .93]</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Practice issues</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Practice issues</td>
<td>.798</td>
<td>[.45, .93]</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-0163278711423937">
<p>
<italic>Note</italic>. CI = confidence interval; ICC = intraclass correlation coefficient.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-0163278711423937">
<title>Between-Scale Correlations</title>
<p>Correlations between the instrument scales were tested following the developers’ example. As regards to the background scales (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0163278711423937">Table 5</xref>
), a substantial correlation was demonstrated between <italic>Perceived preparation</italic> and <italic>Perceived knowledge</italic> (<italic>r</italic> = .744, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01), replicating the correlation found in the developers’ study (<italic>r</italic> = .789, <italic>p</italic> = .000).</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-0163278711423937" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Correlations Between the Questionnaire Scales</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0163278711423937" xlink:href="10.1177_0163278711423937-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>
</th>
<th align="center">Perceived Knowledge</th>
<th>
</th>
<th align="center">Perceived Preparation</th>
<th>Constraints</th>
<th align="center">Workplace Issues</th>
<th>Screening</th>
<th align="center">Self- Efficacy</th>
<th align="center">Alcohol/ Drugs</th>
<th align="center">Victim Understanding</th>
<th align="center">Practice Issues</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Perceived preparation</td>
<td align="center">I</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Perceived knowledge</td>
<td>.744<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">**</xref></sup></td>
<td align="center">I</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Actual knowledge</td>
<td>.152</td>
<td>.178</td>
<td align="center">I</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Preparation</td>
<td>.200</td>
<td>.276<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>−.115</td>
<td align="center">I</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constraints</td>
<td>−.079</td>
<td>.092</td>
<td>−.116</td>
<td>.401<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">**</xref></sup></td>
<td align="center">I</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Workplace issues</td>
<td>.540<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>.569<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>.175</td>
<td>.179</td>
<td>−.162</td>
<td align="center">I</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Screening</td>
<td>.120</td>
<td>.228<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>.008</td>
<td>−.002</td>
<td>.069</td>
<td>.265<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">*</xref></sup></td>
<td align="center">I</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Self-efficacy</td>
<td>.621<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>.608<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>−.011</td>
<td>−.186</td>
<td>−.155</td>
<td>.494<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>.142</td>
<td align="center">I</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Alcohol/Drugs</td>
<td>.034</td>
<td>.101</td>
<td>−.154</td>
<td>.075</td>
<td>.159</td>
<td>.162</td>
<td>.261<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>−.028</td>
<td align="center">I</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Victim Understanding</td>
<td>−.193</td>
<td>−.242<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>.332<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>.102</td>
<td>.415<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>−.295<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>−.052</td>
<td>−.361<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>−.026</td>
<td align="center">I</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Practice issues</td>
<td>.169</td>
<td>.255<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>−.076</td>
<td>.231<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>.287<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>.235<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">*</xref></sup></td>
<td>.327<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0163278711423937">**</xref></sup></td>
<td>.099</td>
<td>−.092</td>
<td>.052</td>
<td align="center">I</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-0163278711423937">
<p>
<italic>Note</italic>. <sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 (two-tailed). <sup>**</sup><italic>p</italic> &lt; .01 (two-tailed).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>In respect to the seven opinion scales (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0163278711423937">Table 5</xref>), <italic>Workplace issues</italic> and <italic>Victim understanding</italic> displayed moderate-to-low correlations with three other opinion scales (<italic>Self-efficacy,</italic>
<italic>Constraints</italic>, and <italic>Screening</italic>), with correlations ranging between .261 and .494. On the other hand, <italic>Preparation</italic> was correlated only with <italic>Constraints</italic> (<italic>r</italic> = .401, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) and similarly <italic>Alcohol/Drugs</italic> was correlated only with <italic>Screening</italic> (<italic>r</italic> = .261, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01).</p>
<p>As regards to correlations between the background and the opinion scales (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0163278711423937">Table 5</xref>), <italic>Perceived Knowledge</italic> was found to correlate with most of the opinion scales (<italic>r</italic> = −.242 to .608) except from <italic>Constraints</italic> and <italic>Alcohol/Drugs.</italic>
<italic>Perceived preparation</italic> was correlated with two opinion scales, <italic>Workplace issues and “Self-efficacy</italic>” (<italic>r</italic> = .540, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01 and <italic>r</italic> = .621, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01, respectively). <italic>Actual knowledge</italic> was only correlated with <italic>Victim understanding</italic> (<italic>r</italic> = .332, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01).</p>
<p>In respect to correlations between the <italic>Practice Issues</italic> scale and the rest of the questionnaire’s scales (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0163278711423937">Table 5</xref>), a low but significant correlation was displayed between the <italic>Perceived knowledge</italic> and the <italic>Practice issues</italic> (<italic>r</italic> = .255, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05). In addition, low-to-moderate correlations were demonstrated between most of the opinion scales <italic>(Preparation, Workplace issues, Constraints,</italic> and <italic>Screening</italic>) and the <italic>Practice issues</italic> (<italic>r</italic> = .231 to .327).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-0163278711423937">
<title>Internal Predictive Validity</title>
<p>Multiple regression analysis revealed strong internal predictive validity of the new scales with four of the seven opinion scales found to be significantly correlated with the <italic>Practice issues</italic> scores (<italic>F</italic> = 4.315; <italic>p</italic> = .000; <italic>R</italic> = .618; <italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup> Adj = .293). In particular, after controlling for the amount of previous training, the three background scales and all the newly derived opinion scales, the multiple regression model revealed that increasing scores of <italic>Workplace issues</italic> (<italic>B</italic> = 1.589; <italic>p</italic> = .016; CI = [0.299, 2.880]), <italic>Constraints</italic> (<italic>B</italic> = 1.275; <italic>p</italic> = .016; CI = [0.243, 2.308]), and <italic>Screening</italic> (<italic>B</italic> = 1.257; <italic>p</italic> = .004; CI = [0.413, 2.101]) as well as decreasing scores of <italic>Alcohol/Drugs</italic> (<italic>B</italic> = −1.834; <italic>p</italic> = .018; CI = [−3.349, −0.319]) increased the likelihood of high score in the <italic>Practice issues</italic> scale. Furthermore, increasing hours of previous training on IPV were found to increase the likelihood of <italic>Practice issues</italic> (<italic>B</italic> = 0.893; <italic>p</italic> = .013; CI = [0.190, 1.596]).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section28-0163278711423937">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our goal was to validate an instrument that would prove an effective measure of outcome in response to an educational intervention or series of interventions on IPV identification and management. The current article describes the translation and cultural adaptation of the PREMIS survey into the Greek language. The translation was an important part of this research as it assisted in developing a culturally, contextually, linguistically, and socially congruent instrument. Involvement of bilingual and bicultural individuals in the translation process as well as cognitive debriefing with individuals representing the target population assisted in arriving at a culturally appropriate tool facilitating understanding of the respondents’ contextual circumstances and the context-specific meaning of research constructs. As a result of this process, certain language and cultural differences were managed successfully and high face validity was found. Most importantly, the latest methodological standards used in the cultural adaptation process ensured the appropriateness and applicability of the instrument in the target population and made it feasible to increase the scientific accuracy of the research by achieving cultural equivalence and avoiding instrumentation artifacts.</p>
<p>As regards to the validation study, the PREMIS opinion scale was successfully refined from a 36-item, an eight-factor structure to a 23-item, seven-factor structure. The factor analysis was found to explain 57.5% of the variance, meaning that the complexity of the data set could be considerably reduced with a 42.5% loss of information. Factor loadings were high, suggesting strong theoretical cohesion among the scale items. Although a different factor structure emerged from the initial rotation, the seven-factor solution was preferable due to its excellent goodness of fit and due to being more theoretically meaningful and consistent with the original structure of the PREMIS survey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0163278711423937">Short, Alpert, et al., 2006</xref>) as well as with other validation studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0163278711423937">Connor, Nouer, Mackey, Tipton, &amp; Lloyd, 2010</xref>). Following item reduction, scaling assumptions were met satisfactorily for the 6 multi-item scales. In particular, although some items did not load particularly on their original factor, they are interesting and should be maintained in the next version of the tool as the factorial structure of the items was acceptable with six of the seven factors corresponding to the theoretical model. A new factor (Screening) already identified in a previous validation study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0163278711423937">Connor et al., 2010</xref>), emerged from the analysis and incorporated items from two previous factors (<italic>Self-efficacy</italic> and <italic>Victim understanding</italic>) from the preliminary eight-factor structure. This scale focuses on a highly debated issue, which is not yet a common practice in health care settings. Under these circumstances, many practice dilemmas arise concerning the feasibility and ethics of screening, when this is expected to be implemented in a country with limited resources for IPV victims, such as in Greece.</p>
<p>Six of the seven scales demonstrated increased internal consistency among their items and consequently high reliability. As expected, the 2-item scales provided the lowest reliability partly due to the number of items involved. Further testing of the scales is needed and the introduction of new items could enhance the scales’ reliability.</p>
<p>All items satisfied the requirements for item specific-internal reliability with the Cronbach’s α coefficient of the five scales comprising more than 2 items, being lower when the item was removed.</p>
<p>As regards to test–retest reliability following the questionnaire recompletion after a 3- to 4-week interval, the results showed moderate to almost perfect agreement for most of the scales, except for the scale of <italic>Screening</italic>, which should be further tested.</p>
<p>In respect to the construct validity, most correlations between the questionnaire scales replicated research findings evident in international literature and were easily interpreted: <italic>Alcohol/Drugs</italic> displayed fewer correlations with the other opinion scales, replicating the findings of previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0163278711423937">Connor et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0163278711423937">Feder et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0163278711423937">Gutmanis et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0163278711423937">Short, Alpert, et al., 2006</xref>). Most of the background and opinion scales were correlated with <italic>Practice issues</italic> indicating a link between the various scales and self-reported practices. Many of the new scales demonstrated strong predictive validity as they were found to best predict variations in the <italic>Practice Issues</italic> scores.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-0163278711423937">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Overall, the results provide evidence on the psychometric integrity of the Greek tool, which is based upon the PREMIS survey. Application of the tool in the study population supports its use with general practitioners serving primary care settings. The translated version of the tool has demonstrated evidence of validity and reliability and could be used as a measure of educational outcome. The measure taps most domains of physicians’ KABB and at the same time it is brief and easily administered. It allows the evaluation of training progress and physicians’ self-evaluation of training needs in IPV management and can be used across levels of training and professional development. The Greek version of the tool is available upon request and will be used in programs of continuing education in the near future.</p>
<p>Certain limitations have been identified and need to be addressed in future research. The sample, although statistically appropriate for factor analysis, was drawn from two adjacent prefectures of Greece and this limits the generalization of the results. It should be stated however, that there is no published evidence indicating variations among general practice settings in the various health regions of Greece. In addition, 9 items were discarded from the original opinion scale of the instrument as a result of the factor analysis and this could potentially affect the factor solution as well as the number of factors finally retained. We however managed to extract a factor structure similar to the one of the original instrument by retaining all meaningful items early in the process and when the factor solution was clear. Furthermore, convergent validity was not assessed in the current study due to the lack of available validated instruments to serve for comparative purposes. Nevertheless, most of the new scales were correlated and highly predicted variations in self-reported behaviors, which could provide an insight regarding the scale’s high construct validity. Further validation studies with larger and representative samples are warranted to strengthen the current results.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section30-0163278711423937">
<title>Implications</title>
<p>To our knowledge, this is the first validated tool available in Greek-speaking countries to assess physicians’ knowledge, attitudes, and skills on IPV issues. The refined and shortened version of the PREMIS will confer benefits from a research perspective, in terms of ease of administration, scoring, and completion, which is desired and necessitated in the busy health care environments. Most importantly, this language-specific tool will facilitate the understanding of physicians’ competency-related barriers to IPV identification and management and will elicit important information for developing culture-specific interventions. Training programs will benefit from this tool as it can provide an operationalized structure to define and evaluate competencies in the field. With this instrument, Greek general practitioners who have been interested yet reticent about working with IPV victims due to competency concerns now may be able to understand their training challenges and how to overcome them in order to bridge the practice gap. Defining and evaluating competencies for professional practice is a strategy to encourage training of general practitioners and improve service provision for IPV victims in primary care. As the survey is currently being validated in Europe and Australia, the Greek version of the PREMIS survey is expected to enable international comparisons among training interventions around the world and, hopefully, initiatives in Greece will be linked with international efforts so that primary care professionals’ training on IPV will be cross-fertilized with novel conceptual frameworks and cutting-edge methodologies.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The authors would like to express their appreciation to all the study participants for their kind contribution and collaboration.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-0163278711423937">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-0163278711423937">
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: The study was granted by the Research Committee of the University of Crete, Greece.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Alpert</surname>
<given-names>E. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Addressing domestic violence: The (long) road ahead</article-title>. <source>Annals of Internal Medicine</source>, <volume>147</volume>, <fpage>666</fpage>–<lpage>667</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cohn</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Salmon</surname>
<given-names>M. E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stobo</surname>
<given-names>J. D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<comment>(on behalf of the Committee on the Training Needs of Health Professionals to Respond to Family Violence Board on Children, Youth and Families)</comment>. (<year>2002</year>). <source>Confronting chronic neglect: The education and training of health professionals on family violence</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academy Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Coker</surname>
<given-names>A. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>P. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bethea</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>King</surname>
<given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McKeown</surname>
<given-names>R. E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Physical health consequences of physical and psychological intimate partner violence</article-title>. <source>Archives Family Medicine</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>451</fpage>–<lpage>457</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Connor</surname>
<given-names>P. D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nouer</surname>
<given-names>S. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mackey</surname>
<given-names>T. N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tipton</surname>
<given-names>N. G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lloyd</surname>
<given-names>A. K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Psychometric properties of an intimate partner violence tool for health care students</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>1012</fpage>–<lpage>1035</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1177/0886260510365872</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cormack</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>The research process in nursing</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell Science</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fabrigar</surname>
<given-names>I. W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wegener</surname>
<given-names>D. T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maccallum</surname>
<given-names>R. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Strahan</surname>
<given-names>E. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Evaluating the use of exploratory factor analysis in psychological research</article-title>. <source>Psychological Methods</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Feder</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ramsay</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dunne</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rose</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arsene</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Norman</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Taket</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>How far does screening women for domestic (partner) violence in different health-care settings meet criteria for a screening programme? Systematic reviews of nine UK National Screening Committee criteria</article-title>. <source>Health Technology Assessment, <italic>13</italic>, iii–iv, xi–xiii</source>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>, <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>347</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ferketich</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Focus on psychometrics aspects of item analysis</article-title>. <source>Research in Nursing &amp; Health</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gadomski</surname>
<given-names>A. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wolff</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tripp</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Short</surname>
<given-names>L. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Changes in health care providers' knowledge, attitudes, beliefs, and behaviors regarding domestic violence, following a multifaceted intervention</article-title>. <source>Academic Medicine</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>1045</fpage>–<lpage>1052</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Garcia-Moreno</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Dilemmas and opportunities for an appropriate health-service response to violence against women</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>, <volume>359</volume>, <fpage>1509</fpage>–<lpage>1514</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gutmanis</surname>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beynon</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tutty</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wathen</surname>
<given-names>C. N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>MacMillan</surname>
<given-names>H. L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Factors influencing identification of and response to intimate partner violence: A survey of physicians and nurses</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>12</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hakstian</surname>
<given-names>A. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>W. T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cattell</surname>
<given-names>R. B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>The behavior of number-of-factors rules with simulated data</article-title>. <source>Multivariate Behaviour Research and Therapy</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>J. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Salasche</surname>
<given-names>S. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>R. B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Can internet-based continuing medical education improve physicians' skin cancer knowledge and skills?</article-title>
<source>Journal of General Internal Medicine</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hathaway</surname>
<given-names>J. E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mucci</surname>
<given-names>L. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Silverman</surname>
<given-names>J. G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>D. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mathews</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pavlos</surname>
<given-names>C. A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Health status and health care use of Massachusetts women reporting partner abuse</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>302</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Janssen</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dascal-Weichhendler</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McGregor</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Assessment for intimate partner violence: Where do we stand?</article-title>
<source>Journal of the American Board of Family Medicine</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>415</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jasinski</surname>
<given-names>J. L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Pregnancy and domestic violence. A review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Trauma, Violence &amp; Abuse</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kaiser</surname>
<given-names>H. F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rice</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>). <article-title>Little Jiffy, mark IV</article-title>. <source>Educational and Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>111</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Landis</surname>
<given-names>J. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Koch</surname>
<given-names>G. G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <article-title>The measurement of observer agreement for categorical data</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lapidus</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cooke</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gelven</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Duncan</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Banco</surname>
<given-names>L. A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Statewide survey of domestic violence screening behaviors among pediatricians and family physicians</article-title>. <source>Archives of Pediatrics &amp; Adolescent Medicine</source>, <volume>156</volume>, <fpage>332</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jaye</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>GPs' perception of their role in the identification and management of family violence</article-title>. <source>Family Practice</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Naumann</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Langford</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Torres</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Glass</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Women battering in primary care practice</article-title>. <source>Family Practice</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nicolaidis</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Curry</surname>
<given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gerrity</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Health care workers' expectations and empathy toward patients in abusive relationships</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Board of Family Practice</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Papadakaki</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tzamalouka</surname>
<given-names>G. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chatzifotiou</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chliaoutakis</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Seeking for risk factors of intimate partner violence (IPV) in a Greek national sample: The role of self-esteem</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>732</fpage>–<lpage>750</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Petridou</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Browne</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lichter</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dedoukou</surname>
<given-names>X.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alexe</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dessypris</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>What distinguishes unintentional injuries from injuries due to intimate partner violence: A study in Greek ambulatory care settings</article-title>. <source>Injury Prevention</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Plichta</surname>
<given-names>S. B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Falik</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Prevalence of violence and its implications for women’s health</article-title>. <source>Women’s Health Issues</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>244</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Polit</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hunglar</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Nursing research: Principles and methods</source> (<edition>6th ed</edition>.). <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McLoughlin</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nah</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>J. C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Mandatory reporting of domestic violence injuries to the police: What do emergency department patients think?</article-title>
<source>Journal of the Medical Association</source>, <volume>286</volume>, <fpage>580</fpage>–<lpage>583</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Short</surname>
<given-names>L. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alpert</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>J. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Surprenant</surname>
<given-names>Z. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>A tool for measuring physician readiness to manage intimate partner violence</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>. <italic>Tool</italic>: <volume>180</volume>.<fpage>e1</fpage>–<lpage>e7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Short</surname>
<given-names>L. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cotton</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hodgson</surname>
<given-names>C. S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of the module on domestic violence at the UCLA school of medicine</article-title>. <source>Academic Medicine</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>S75</fpage>–<lpage>S91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Short</surname>
<given-names>L. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Surprenant</surname>
<given-names>Z. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>J. M.</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>A community-based trial of online intimate partner violence CME</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sugg</surname>
<given-names>N. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>R. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>D. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maurio</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rivara</surname>
<given-names>F. P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Domestic violence and primary care: Attitudes, practices, and beliefs</article-title>. <source>Archive Family Medicine</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tabachnick</surname>
<given-names>B. G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fidell</surname>
<given-names>L. S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Using multivariate statistics</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Allyn &amp; Bacon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>R. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rivara</surname>
<given-names>F. P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>D. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barlow</surname>
<given-names>W. E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sugg</surname>
<given-names>N. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maiuro</surname>
<given-names>R. D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rubanowice</surname>
<given-names>D. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Identification and management of domestic violence—A randomized trial</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tzamalouka</surname>
<given-names>G. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Parlalis</surname>
<given-names>S. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Soultatou</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Papadakaki</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chliaoutakis</surname>
<given-names>J. E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Applying the concept of lifestyle in association with aggression and violence in Greek cohabitating couples</article-title>. <source>Aggressive Behavior</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Waalen</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goodwin</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spitz</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Petersen</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Saltzman</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Screening for intimate partner violence by health care providers</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>230</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weinreb</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fletcher</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Candib</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bacigalupe</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Physicians' perceptions of adult patients' history of child abuse in family medicine settings</article-title>. <source>The Journal of the American Board of Family Medicine</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>419</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0163278711423937">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wild</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grove</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eremenco</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McElroy</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Verjee-Lorenz</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Erikson</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Principles of good practice for the translation and cultural adaptation process for patient-reported outcomes (PRO) measures: Report of the ISPOR task force for translation and cultural adaptation</article-title>. <source>Value Health</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>