<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IRS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spirs</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1012-6902</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7218</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1012690210395526</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1012690210395526</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Sport and social development: Promise and caution from an incipient Cambodian football league</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>Chiaki</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1012690210395526">Osaka University, Japan</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-1012690210395526">University of Calgary, Canada</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1012690210395526">Kevin Young, Department of Sociology, University of Calgary, 2500 University Drive NW, Calgary, Alberta, Canada T2N 1N4. E-mail: <email>kyoung@ucalgary.ca</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>5</fpage>
<lpage>26</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© International Sociology of Sport Association and SAGE Publications 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">International Sociology of Sport Association and SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>One of the enduring controversies found in the literature on the role that sport plays in social development is whether this assumed relationship is weak or robust. Despite evidence both for and against the ‘sport-enhances-social-development’ model, a rapidly expanding cluster of case studies and a growing literature in a number of disciplines, there remain entire countries which have not been systematically explored and where almost no sociological research is available in English. Cambodia is one such case. Based upon qualitative methods (specifically interviews and observation) and as part of an ongoing study, this article reports on an incipient sport initiative (the Siem Reap Hotel Football League) in northern Cambodia. Emphasizing that sport is ‘contested terrain’ and may simultaneously improve and exacerbate existing social relations in any setting, our data show that any promise sport offers communities in either a micro or macro sense should be viewed through the lens of caution and circumspection.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Cambodia</kwd>
<kwd>competition</kwd>
<kwd>friendship</kwd>
<kwd>poverty</kwd>
<kwd>sport-for-development</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1012690210395526" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Over the past 20 years, social movements dedicated to and scholarly debates based upon the potential role of sport in social development have grown considerably. Organizations geared towards social development and peace, such as the United Nations, governmental agencies as well as international non-governmental organizations (NGOs) began regarding sport as a tool for resolving local, national and global problems. Multiple forms of sport-related development programs have been implemented, although the actual advantages of sport in development sectors have not been fully determined, or convincingly replicated across settings. Some geographical settings remain almost completely unexplored.</p>
<p>Why is so much expected of sport these days? What are the proven advantages of sport as a development tool? To answer these questions, we should first consider some impressions generally held about sport, especially regarding its allegedly peaceful character, its ‘squeaky clean’ image, and its advocacy of fair play codes. It has become de rigueur for donor agencies to showcase their campaigns by using, for example, emotionally wrenching images of sad (or smiling) children from impoverished areas of developing countries holding rustic soccer balls to emphasize the purity, promise, and moral philanthropy of sport. Second, sport in recent years has attracted significant attention and garnered massive support as an effective means of combating social problems such as poverty, ethnic and religious strife, HIV/AIDS, and other forms of civil and political conflict.</p>
<p>In order to clarify the ‘promise’ of sport in the development sectors and to add to a growing literature on the potential strengths and weaknesses of using sport to achieve social goals, this article will first re-assess the relationship between sport and social development, and then offer an empirically based case study of the ‘Siem Reap Hotel Football League’ (SHFL) in northwestern Cambodia. The primary goal of the article is to examine the role of sport in general development contexts and the specific contribution the SHFL has made to the daily lives of its participants. This research is significant because it examines the assumed and expected role of sport in a developing Asian country in which there has, to this point, been limited research on the place of sport in the respective literatures of the sociology of sport and international development. Very little of the research that does exist is available for English-speaking audiences.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1012690210395526">
<title>Sport in the development sectors</title>
<sec id="section3-1012690210395526">
<title>‘Development through sport’ initiatives</title>
<p>The notion of <italic>sport as a human right</italic> has increasingly been applied to the development sectors. Many declarations and charters such as the Olympic Charter (IOC 1925), European Sport for All Charter (European Sport Ministers 1975), International Charter of Physical Education and Sport (UNESCO 1978), Declaration of Pun Del Este (MINEPS 1999), and Building a Peaceful and Better World through Sport (UN General Assembly Resolution 1993, 1995, 1997, 2000, 2002) emphasized human rights through games and play for all people. Sport as a fundamental right of children, vulnerable persons and marginalized groups was given recognition by the Declaration of the Rights of the Child (1959), the Convention on the Rights of the Child (1989), Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women (1979), and the Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples (2007).</p>
<p>The status of sport as a right brings with it an obligation on the part of governments, multilateral institutions, and other agents in civil society to ensure that opportunities exist for everyone to participate in sport and physical activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1012690210395526">SDPIWG, 2006</xref>). UNESCO, which has taken part in these declarations from an early stage, has spoken austerely on this matter: ‘we can ask ourselves whether it might not be appropriate to move towards a right to sport’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1012690210395526">UNESCO, 2004</xref>: 12). The reasons for this directive include the fact that the various clauses have not been formally binding on states and may consequently be regarded as recommendations only, and that, with regard to obligations, covenants acknowledge sport as a right indirectly through the right to education, the right to participate in recreational activities, and the right to participate in a spectrum of cultural pursuits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1012690210395526">UNESCO, 2004</xref>). A UN inter-agency task force recognized that ‘the right to sport and play is often denied. In many cases this is because of discrimination, particularly by gender and ability. It is also frequently due to political neglect of the importance of sport in society’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1012690210395526">UN Inter-agency Task Force, 2005</xref>: 4). It thus seems important that in developing countries with rudimentary social infrastructures, including fully established laws and regulations, the effectiveness of sport should be examined concretely rather than by focusing on the right to sport as an ideal.</p>
<p>In the 1990s a large paradigm shift took place in the development sectors and new coordinates toward poverty reduction (which had previously been seen as an individual and personal issue) came to be regarded as a critical global issue. The United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) proposed a new way forward – <italic>Human Development</italic> – putting individuals at the center of development work, and prioritizing the expansion of choice and opportunity in each person’s life as the ultimate goal of international development. In this respect, sport was now expected to provide an arena for individuals and communities, which are, after all, the basic subjects of human development, to make known and realize their potentials. Importantly, sport was viewed as adding ‘tremendous positive value to international development and cooperation work for the benefit of women, men, girls and boys, irrespective of the developing degree of a continent’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1012690210395526">Meire, 2005</xref>: 4).</p>
<p>In 2001, the UN Secretary-General appointed the first special advisor on sport for development and peace. The necessity of creating a policy frame for actual development work through sport had increased, and the UN task force was established in 2003 and international conferences on sport and development were held in 2003 and 2005. The international working group (SDPIWG) was formed with representatives from 15 countries, and the International Year of Sport and Physical Education (IYSPE) was proclaimed by the UN in 2005. Ministers and high-ranking officials from 43 countries adopted the Accra Call for Action on sport for development and peace in 2007 and a second special advisor was appointed in 2008. All of these initiatives were based on the assumption that sport contributed directly and positively to human development, and thus the cooperation of a multitude of sport-friendly groups in the development sectors was viewed as essential. Our point is not to completely dismiss the fact that sport might contribute to social development in all of these desired ways. However, our position is that it is both important and fair to constantly remind (i.e. caution) ourselves that the contribution of sport to social development in any setting is far more a <italic>possibility</italic> than an <italic>inevitability</italic>, and that the actual advantages of sport as a tool in any community depends on a multitude of often very complex factors that differ from context to context.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1012690210395526">
<title>Learning lessons: What we know from the research so far</title>
<p>Reports on sport in the development sectors increased rapidly at the turn of the millennium. SDPIWG published <italic>Literature Reviews of Sport for Development and Peace</italic> in 2007, reviewing over 280 studies in related areas of sport for development. The report looked into the use of sport in five sectors: education, health, gender, persons with disabilities, and peace focusing on <italic>human development</italic>. Its extensive review contains case examples both in developing and developed countries in each sector, and concludes, perhaps predictably: ‘while the literature review identified areas where further research is needed … sport has the potential to contribute to development and social issues’ (SDPIWG, 2007: 5). From SDPIWG’s challenge in several sectors, we recognize and appreciate the difficulty of convincingly summarizing the advantages of sport even after such massive literature review efforts. The final conclusion seemed suitably cautious: ‘the evident benefits appear to be an indirect outcome of the context and social interaction that is possible in sport rather than a direct outcome of participating in sport’ (SDPIWG, 2007: 4).</p>
<p>In addition to research which considers using sport in certain development sectors, ongoing attempts for evaluation of concrete field experiences may also be found in, for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1012690210395526">Coalter (2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1012690210395526">Burnett (2006)</xref>. Working from the perspectives of social impact assessment, the anthropology of development, and strategic management, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1012690210395526">Burnett (2006)</xref> in particular has created an evaluative scheme which could help measuring the meaning and outcomes of sport using cross-sectional perspectives.</p>
<p>Closely related to the field of sport and development research is sport and peace research. This area has recently also expanded and already there are some notable contributions. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1012690210395526">Ben-Porat (1998)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1012690210395526">Gasser and Levinsen (2004)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1012690210395526">Keim (2003)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1012690210395526">Sugden (2006)</xref> have all contributed detailed field studies concerning peace or conflict resolution, mainly based on qualitative methods. Although the complexities of carrying out interpretive work in ‘foreign’ settings has long been acknowledged in the methodological literature, qualitative work and field-oriented approaches also contain real ‘learning lessons’ forthe development sectors which clearly need to consider and respond to ‘insider voices’ regarding how sport may be ‘adding’ to the community.</p>
<p>Overall, however, the number of empirical sociological case studies on sport in developing countries is still relatively modest. Further and ongoing field research is essential in order to collect data directly and to observe and hear the voices and accounts of participants, allowing them to speak in their own terms and categories. Possible research endeavors have been and are undermined by the difficulty of establishing rapport and cooperative relationships in given settings – contacts, trust, researcher safety, and practical organizational issues often represent real hurdles. Fortunately however, some valuable work has been successfully undertaken, especially in African settings. Notable studies include Clignet and Stark (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1012690210395526">1974</xref>, Cameroon), Baker and Mangan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1012690210395526">1987</xref>, numerous African countries), Corlett and Mokgwathi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1012690210395526">1989</xref>, Botswana), Godia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1012690210395526">1989</xref>, Kenya), Ojeme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1012690210395526">1989</xref>, Nigeria), Lema (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1012690210395526">1989</xref>, Zaire), Bale and Sanb (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1012690210395526">1996</xref>, Kenya), Stuart (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1012690210395526">1996</xref>, Zimbabwe), Armstrong and Giulianotti (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1012690210395526">1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1012690210395526">2004</xref>, numerous African countries), Amusa and Toriola (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1012690210395526">1999</xref>, numerous African countries), Armstrong (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1012690210395526">2002</xref>, Liberia), Keimbou (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1012690210395526">2005</xref>, Cameroon), and Chappell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1012690210395526">2005</xref>, Namibia). Unsurprisingly, research on South African sport is deep and rich (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1012690210395526">Burnett, 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1012690210395526">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1012690210395526">Keim, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1012690210395526">Nauright, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1012690210395526">Pelak, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Compared to such African research, the breadth and depth of empirical research in the other developing regions remains inadequate. Sport development studies in Latin American settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1012690210395526">Arbena, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1012690210395526">1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1012690210395526">1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1012690210395526">1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1012690210395526">2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1012690210395526">Carter, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1012690210395526">Trotz, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1012690210395526">Wagner, 1982</xref>), and South Asian and Islamic settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1012690210395526">Anderson, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1012690210395526">Beran, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1012690210395526">Douglas, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1012690210395526">Hay, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1012690210395526">Hirai, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1012690210395526">Stevenson, 1989</xref>) are rare. Among other reasons, language, geographical, cultural and access barriers constitute the usual array of prohibitive factors, but these are all relative notions and the fact of the matter is that the possible role of sport in social development in Asian countries, and especially southern Asian countries, has hardly been broached. As Wagner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1012690210395526">1989</xref>: 3) noted regarding the historical trends of modern research: ‘we do not have enough comparative descriptive data about sport in non-western contexts to develop good general theories of sport’. Tellingly, regarding sport in Asia, he went on to note: ‘… it is interesting that the areas of the world that maintained strong historical traditions even during long occupation by European colonial powers as well as the countries that did not suffer long European colonialism still have strong traditional sport’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1012690210395526">1989</xref>: 5-6).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1012690210395526">
<title>Sport in Cambodian society</title>
<p>Bordered by Thailand, Laos and Vietnam, the Southeast Asian Kingdom of Cambodia (formerly Kampuchea) has a population of 13.4 million (Cambodian 2008 general population census). Most Cambodians are Buddhist and make their living agriculturally. The level of social indicators such as GDP (2727 PPPUS$), literacy rate (73.6%) and school enrolment rate (60.0%) is still low even compared to the other countries in this area, although there is a remarkable annual national economic growth (UNDP, 2008). In the mid-late 1970s, under the Pol Pot/Khmer Rouge administration, extensive genocidal ‘cleansing’ occurred and a period of civil and social chaos ensued. Approximately one third of Cambodians were killed (the population decreased from 10 million to 7 million), although the exact number of victims varies depending on the source one uses.</p>
<p>According to informal reports, professionals such as lawyers, doctors, and teachers, as well as artists <italic>and</italic> athletes were especially targeted because of their power to influence the masses and popular culture. Although the Pol Pot regime ended in 1978, civil war and political uncertainty continued through the 1980s. The Paris Agreement was concluded in 1991 and the long road toward Cambodian revival began. While the lifestyles of ordinary Cambodians today continue to be modest and arduous by Western standards, economic growth has been widely regarded to hover at an impressive eight percent per year. The garment and tourism sectors lead this high speed growth and Siem Reap, the target area of this research, accounts for 70 percent of the national tourism income. However, even though the famous and tourist-drawing ruins of Angkor Wat are located here, poverty in this rural area is still much more severe than in other provinces in the country (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1012690210395526">Figure 1</xref>), and living conditions can be harsh. About 53.7 percent of residents in Siem Reap live below the poverty line of $0.32US (for urban areas) and $0.27US (for rural areas) per capita per day consumption as set by the Cambodian government.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1012690210395526" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Poverty rate in Cambodia. <italic>Source</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1012690210395526">Danida (2006)</xref>.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1012690210395526-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Sport in Cambodia operates under the control of the Ministry of Education, Youthand Sport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1012690210395526">MoEYS, 2005</xref>). Focusing on youth who, using a local phrase, are viewed as workhorses leading the country into the future, education is a high priority, and the importance of sport-related education is also emphasized in the Cambodian constitution. However, the actual implementation of sport-related activities has been beset with difficulties because of the chronic lack of human and material resources, including budgets. Persons playing roles such as administrative officers, teachers and coaches after the Pol Pot regime are scarce, and the few sport-interested individuals and groups that do exist have been struggling without educational materials, training opportunities, and basic resources. Although there are close to 400 primary and secondary schools, approximately 40,000 students, and 670 teachers in Siem Reap province, the total number of Physical Education teachers is, at the time of writing, 15. Since generous governmental support for sport could not realistically be expected in a difficult economy, sport in the school system has gradually taken off as a private enterprise. Despite extreme poverty throughout much of the country, and reflecting broader globalizing trends, television has come to be regarded as an important element of daily life, and thus Cambodians are able to consume world sport, including that played at the highest level or professionally, such as European football, the FIFA World Cup and the Olympic Games. In turn, these seem to have influenced and encouraged widespread interest in sport. Until the early 2000s, there were few leisure time options in this mostly agrarian culture and sport activity was rarely seen due to lack of opportunity and, equally importantly, its lack of cultural relevance. However, there have been significant changes concerning sport and, most encouragingly, consistent and <italic>patterned</italic> systems of sport have expanded in recent years in Cambodia. Today, while the sporting environment and sports opportunities and resources remain basic and crude, Cambodians throughout the country are involved in constellations of sporting initiatives and activities, often without the level of instruction, facilities or financial aid that are simply taken-for-granted in more developed countries. Today it is fair to note that many Cambodians have come to recognize sport as a preferred aspect of their cultural lives, but hardly an essential component in a country still recovering from a turbulent, and often violent, past.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1012690210395526">
<title>The Siem Reap Hotel Football League: A case study</title>
<sec id="section7-1012690210395526">
<title>The SHFL</title>
<p>The Siem Reap Hotel Football League (SHFL) was established as an amateur entity in 2004 with eight teams. By 2008, the league had expanded to 11 teams (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1012690210395526">Table 1</xref>).1 Motivated by both athletic and social interests, five principal goals initially helped shape the league: i) to improve technical skill in the sport of football; ii) to promote collegiality and harmony among hotel staff; iii) to improve the physical and mental health of hotel staff members; iv) to encourage friendship and respect between the staff members of ‘rival’ hotels; and, v) to contribute to the development of the quality and standard of Cambodian football in general. The SHFL mandate requires that each team: i) comprises a maximum of 22 players, all of whom must have worked in their respective hotels for at least three months; ii) is able to pay a registration fee of $250 US; iii) registers all players, thus providing standardization across the league and basic demographic data for the league; and, iv) volunteers one representative and four ‘deputies’ to act as SHFL committee members. In these ways, the SHFL committee comprises representatives from each participating team, with the SHFL President, Vice President, accountant and Secretary General to be selected every year by a vote of committee members. The SHFL sets all the rules concerned, including the schedule of matches and the budget, adhering to the aforementioned five targets in their annually reviewed regulations.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1012690210395526" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>2008 SHFL teams</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1012690210395526" xlink:href="10.1177_1012690210395526-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="9">Hotel league team data 2008</th>
<th align="left" colspan="4">Hotel data</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Employee data</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Team</th>
<th align="left">Affiliation</th>
<th align="left">Participation</th>
<th align="left">Rank2007</th>
<th align="left">Num. of coach (playing coach)</th>
<th align="left">Practiceper week</th>
<th align="left">Practice venue</th>
<th align="left">Annualbudget(US$)</th>
<th align="left">Budgetsource</th>
<th align="left">Support bycompany</th>
<th align="left">Hotelopen</th>
<th align="left">Hotel rank (stars)</th>
<th align="left">Num. of rooms</th>
<th align="left">Priceper room (US$)</th>
<th align="left">Num. of employees</th>
<th align="left">Day off</th>
<th align="left">Average salary</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>A</td>
<td>2005</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>School Ground</td>
<td>-</td>
<td>General Manager(GM), Sponsor</td>
<td>Bus,Holidays, Time shift</td>
<td>1997</td>
<td>*****</td>
<td>131</td>
<td>260–375</td>
<td>350</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>120</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>B</td>
<td>2007</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>Sandlotin town</td>
<td>300</td>
<td>GM. Sponsor</td>
<td>Bus,Equipment, Uniform</td>
<td>2003</td>
<td>****</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>90–165</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>80–150</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>C</td>
<td>2005</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>Sandlotin hotel</td>
<td>200</td>
<td>Union,Sponsor</td>
<td>Bus</td>
<td>2003</td>
<td>*****</td>
<td>130</td>
<td>110–332</td>
<td>260</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>60–65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>D</td>
<td>2005</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>0(1)</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>Sandlotin hotel</td>
<td>1000</td>
<td>Budget for publicity</td>
<td>Budget, Bus, Equipment</td>
<td>2004</td>
<td>*****</td>
<td>259</td>
<td>160–900</td>
<td>300</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>E</td>
<td>2007</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>0(1)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>1000</td>
<td>Company, Sponsor</td>
<td>Bus,Equipment</td>
<td>2007</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>80</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>150</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>F</td>
<td>2005</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>School Ground</td>
<td>400</td>
<td>Company, Sponsor</td>
<td>All exceptfor water</td>
<td>2002</td>
<td>****</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>130–150</td>
<td>155</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>G</td>
<td>2004</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0(2)</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>Sandlotin hotel</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>Company, Sponsor,Managers</td>
<td>Bus, Water, Holidays</td>
<td>2004</td>
<td>*****</td>
<td>223</td>
<td>170–300</td>
<td>250</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>110</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>H</td>
<td>2005</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>Sandlotin hotel</td>
<td>800</td>
<td>Company, Sponsor,Sections</td>
<td>Bus, Drink, Holidays</td>
<td>2003</td>
<td>****</td>
<td>142</td>
<td>110–200</td>
<td>150</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>150</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>I</td>
<td>2007</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Rental (30$/Day)</td>
<td>Ondemand</td>
<td>Company</td>
<td>Water</td>
<td>2005</td>
<td>*****</td>
<td>107</td>
<td>184–425</td>
<td>80</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>J</td>
<td>2008</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0(1)</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>Rental (30$/Day)</td>
<td>Ondemand</td>
<td>Company</td>
<td>Budget, Bus, Equipment</td>
<td>1998</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>1–2</td>
<td>70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>K</td>
<td>2004</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>Rental (20$/Day)</td>
<td>1000</td>
<td>Company, Players</td>
<td>Budget, Bus</td>
<td>2004</td>
<td>****</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>175–305</td>
<td>120</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>80</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>All players in the SHFL are male, and the age range is 15–40 years, with the average age being 26 years. Rather than a conventional ‘season’ format, the SHFL is essentially organized along the lines of a spring/summer ‘knock-out’ competition. A qualifying round of two pools is held between May and July every year with two winners from each pool reaching the semi-finals. Winners of the two semi-finals compete for the overall championship played at the Siem Reap Provincial Stadium located approximately 6 kilometers outside the city of Siem Reap. Although early round games are played under informal circumstances, sometimes on school grounds, with modest crowds of 200–300 people, the opening and closing ceremonies of the tournament are much grander in scale, and are attended by the Provincial Governor, the players, staff and managers of all teams, and crowds of approximately 1000 people. The 2008 closing ceremony was broadcast nationally in Cambodia at peak television-watching time. The champion team wins a prize of $300US, with $200US going to the runner-up, $100US to third place, and $50US to fourth place.</p>
<p>In brief, the SHFL is an increasingly recognized aspect of popular culture in Cambodia. Although relatively lighthearted targets (such as fun and intra-industry collegiality) were at the centre of its original goal structure, the league continues to grow and galvanize its place in ‘serious’ amateur Cambodian sport. While a national professional football league organized by the Ministry of Education exists, at the time of writing, the SHFL is the only league organized ‘by the people’ of Cambodia. Other sports have been proposed for similar amateur leagues in Cambodia (such as volleyball for women), but no such ventures currently exist. In this way and, we contend, of real significance for an internationally sensitive sociology of sport, the SHFL represents a critical and stand-alone exemplar of amateur sport organized within a work industry (the hotel and tourist trade) in this still developing south-east Asian nation.2</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1012690210395526">
<title>A note on method</title>
<p>Two fieldwork strategies – in-depth interviewing and observation – underpin this ongoing (2007 to present) study of sport in the Siem Reap region of Cambodia. During that period, approximately 43 days were spent gathering data in the field. A cluster of individuals related to the SHFL were observed and interviewed. These included: 17 SHFL committee members including all representatives of the 2007 SHFL participant team and SHFL founders, nine persons occupying management roles of one kind or another such as human resource managers, four sport officers in the Ministry of Education, six coaches and physical education school teachers, and four personsworking in the tourism sector. Each person was interviewed two or three times for an average of approximately 45 minutes, mainly in English, although on two occasions a translator was required. In order to maximize respondent comfort, convenience and data yield, all interviews were held in a location chosen by the interviewee such as their office or football fields where practices or matches took place. A semi-structured interview guide allowed us to probe issues such as the history of the league, its goals and parameters, its support among local private and public institutions (such as the hotels themselves and the Provincial Office of Education, Youth and Sport – see<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1012690210395526">Figure 2</xref>), its problem-solving mechanisms, its experiences on both individual and organizational levels, and its desired outcomes (for ‘outcomes’ we used previous social ecological work to help frame our questions – e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1012690210395526">Bronfenbrenner, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1012690210395526">Leslie, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1012690210395526">Owen, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1012690210395526">Salis, 1989</xref>). Each respondent was offered a pseudonym to protect their anonymity (although none chose one) and informed that they could withdraw from the study at any time. As an indication of the existing goodwill in the SHFL,no-one we contacted was unwilling to be interviewed. Indeed, several echoed thefeelings of one central ‘key informant’ and showed a genuine interest in participating in the research by openly sharing their experiences – ‘we are waiting for this opportunity to talk about our sport environment’. We experienced no problems ‘getting in’ or gaining access to possible respondents representing any of the multiple layers ofparticipation and organization involved, or indeed to any of the SHFL events. Observational settings ranged from group meetings, to opening and closing ceremonies, to the football events themselves.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1012690210395526" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>The SHFL and other local institutions: Relationships aimed at ‘development’</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1012690210395526-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1012690210395526">
<title>Friendship, competition and struggle in the SHFL</title>
<p>Our data clearly suggest that the SHFL directly contributed toward developing relationships among individuals, hotel staff members, and hotels themselves. Especially in a retrenched economic climate where hotels and other businesses routinely face closure and bankruptcy, SHFL participants seemed particularly grateful for the opportunity to coalesce around common purposes and goals, as well as to share knowledge with colleagues experiencing similar levels of work-related stress. Unanimously, our respondents emphasized emerging friendships as the crowning achievement of the league, and expressed pride in the fact that several of the SHFL’s principal targets (as outlined above) had been successfully met in this regard. In the words of Rachana (27 years, player, team leader, executive house keeper) and Som (31 years, player, team leader, chief concierge) respectively:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Before, the cooperation between the eight departments is not so close. Here now cooperation is smoother between the staff and between the managers. We have good relationships. When I need a truck, although I do not know how to get a truck [as a housekeeping manager], I will ask to the cook [department]. They can find a truck for me by one of the suppliers. People here come to get closer and closer so we have good cooperation. There is [now] more effective operation in our hotel. (Rachana)</p>
<p>We are playing football especially for the friendship. We can say that the [prize] money is not a main thing, and championship is, too, although being a champion is good if we can get it. It will be a reputation of our hotel, so this is also a main goal for our hotel. But the most [important] thing, we think, is relationship. We have a chance to see all the people from the other hotels, which are not only players but also staff members. When we play a game, many staff members go to support the team, so they can see each other. (Som)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Perhaps unsurprisingly given the social context, there was concrete evidence of how the SHFL contributed to the forging of new relationships among participants. SHFL matches offered regular and, significantly, casual and relaxed opportunities to initiate relationships among the players, supporters and administrators, as was evidenced during the 2009 Cup Final where we observed several of the managers from numerous hotels greeting one another and chatting in the bleachers, even though they were not from the hotel teams on the field of play. Further, and also significantly given the work that has been done on sport as a vehicle for social development, there was evidence from Moeng and Sophy that casual acquaintanceship revolving around the SHFL carried real potential for ‘carry-over’ improvements in the workplace:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>There are many [SHFL] committee meetings, sometimes too many. Before we start the league, we need to decide our policy, rule, prize and budget, etc. That’s why we need to have a lot of meeting. We have coffee breaks in the meeting, and after the tournament, we also have a small party for team leaders [committee members]. So, we know each other very well. (Moeng, 35 years, non-player, Vice President of the SHFL, assistant purchasing manager)</p>
<p>We don’t have much budget but [it] costs much for water, medicine and uniform etc. [for playing football]. We need cooperation with Ministry of Education, government and sponsors. During my studying in a high school and a faculty, I did not spend much money at that time. [As a] student, I could get a lot of support by my government. But here, for us, we should spend for everything by ourselves. In Siem Reap, we have good system, hotel league. We can combine our resource to create one league and the others can’t do like this. In Phnom Penh, besides government, they have just only friendly matches but not like us. (Sophy, 34 years, former-player, team-leader, assistant Food &amp; Beverage manager)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In these ways, it was clear that several of the SHFL’s stated principals (promoting friendship and collegiality, etc.) were being met and that, moreover, participants expressed a level of pride in the success of their league achieving its core goals.</p>
<p>Although we clearly observed the importance of developing friendships at the inter-personal and organizational level, we were also exposed to forms of friendship development as an outgrowth of the SHFL in the community more broadly – on this matter, it is important to recall the emphasis placed on the initiation and strengthening of relationships in the social development literature and policy mandates reviewed earlier in this article. In this respect, we regard the word ‘social’ encapsulated by the admittedly over-used phrase ‘social development’ to refer to advancements at both micro- and macro-levels, and this is certainly a process at work in the SHFL and its affiliated communities. Our respondents spoke openly and consistently about improved relationships, not in the sense that the SHFL was viewed naively as some sort of panacea for all of Siem Reap’s or indeed Cambodia’s economic problems but, rather, in the way in which the league had become a talking and reference point for both participants and for the surrounding communities as whole. For instance, our respondents spoke of taking news and experiences with the SHFL, and its members, back to their homes, families and neighborhoods, and reported growing intrigue in the league among locals who, for instance, would never play, such as children and older persons in less firm health. But there was further concrete evidence of achieving fundamental SHFL goals and reaching Siem Reap society more generally.</p>
<p>For example, and as indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1012690210395526">Figure 2</xref>, the SHFL regularly holds football matches, and at those times, they invite select primary and secondary students from the surrounding schools. The choice of particular schools is made by the provincial sport office under the auspices of the provincial education office and selected students are encouraged by their principals to take in and enjoy SHFL games. Often, students receive gifts such as notebooks, pens, and school bags from the SHFL committee embossed with an SHFL message encouraging students to take school seriously and consider the role of sport in the future development of Siem Reap. In this respect, the SHFL, in turn, expects a simultaneous positive impact on student motivation both with regard to education and sport. As the President of SHFL observed, inadvertently underscoring the strongly gendered character of the league which clearly operates largely as a male domain:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>We decide our rule strictly. If you [students] want to play in our hotel league, you have to work at least three month in a hotel. If you want to be a hotel man, you should study first. (Sambo, 37 years, former-player, SHFL President, chief concierge)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>It was evident from our interviews that most SHFL players had experienced domestic conflict and often abject poverty in their childhood, especially if they were slightly older and grew up in the troubled 1970s and 1980s. Some players were raised in orphanages having lost parents and siblings. Indeed, this is common enough that most of the SHFL hotels operate staff dormitories providing daily meals and other basic resources. Facing such hardships and severe circumstances, it is not hard to understand why SHFL players may view the league as a rare and concrete opportunity and thus study, work and train with real commitment – a fact that seems to resonate and be recognized throughout the whole Siem Reap community. For instance, several respondents noted how working in hotels and enjoying the access to the SHFL meant for them not having to rely on their parents for subsistence or basic agricultural work opportunities.</p>
<p>There are other articulations of local level cooperation that is vital for the SHFL to exist and indeed for sport in Siem Reap more broadly to prosper. One illustration may be found in budgetary matters. The SHFL pays $35US per match in stadium and referee fees, totaling approximately $1000US per year – this constitutes nearly one fifth of the annual budget of the entire Siem Reap provincial sport office and (for instance) one third of the 2008 SHFL budget. In many regions in other developing countries as well as in Cambodia itself, the commitment of the central government to education and sport development is weak due to a chronic lack of economic resources as well as sport being viewed as a low-priority area. The Cambodian regional organizations for education and sport are required to have their own financial resources for implementing programs and activities, which predictably prevents otherwise well-intended sport initiatives from blooming, or even being considered. In this particular case, the SHFL views education and sport development in Cambodian society as one of the main objectives of their activities and maintains close relations with the provincial sport office. The President of the SHFL underlined the developing symbiosis between his league and the broader governance of regional sport in Cambodia in the following way:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>When we want to have SHFL-related events such as [a] tournament or [a] conference, we send [an] application to the provincial sport office to get permission from them. The permission has meaning – <italic>they</italic> [i.e. the provincial sport office] are also involved in our activities. We always work with them for sport development and our SHFL activities are also important for the sport office. (Sambo)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Needless to say, finance is at the center of whether the SHFL can operate, even as a completely voluntary and non-profit entity, as again suggested by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1012690210395526">Figure 2</xref>. The donation of things like space for meetings, stationery for communication, and fees for renting playing fields and game officials flows from the SHFL to the provincial education office. In other words, cash flow and infrastructural support moves from the private industrial sector to the governmental sector. What is important to note is that ownership of many of the SHFL member hotels is ‘foreign’, and in this way monies such as entry fees and resources such as players and spectators are inevitably intertwined with overseas investment as well as uniquely Cambodian objectives and goals, a fact that obviously emphasizes the marriage of convenience between this micro League, Cambodian regional support, and layers of international cooperation.</p>
<p>However, moving from evidence that appears to support a consensual functionalist approach to sport and social development to evidence that is far more suggestive of sport as a galvanizer of difference and hub of social fragmentation, as with other sport-related settings, the relations between the hotel teams and their members are not always smooth, and we found evidence of struggle on several levels. Lack of cooperation, or competitive rivalry, articulated itself in a number of ways, none clearer than on-field physical confrontation and fighting between players. Timmy (33 years, former player, team-leader, sales manager) spoke directly of the problem for the need to avoid potential violence in the league:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>In our team, we have little problems. Some players in our team play very strong. It’s like attacking, very tough, very bad football. But after discussion after the match we [made] sure with a team leader not do like this, very hard, very terrible play, so we should respect each other, because this is a hotel league which is not a champion’s league such as premium league and world cup. This is a friendship league between hotel and hotel. (Timmy)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Most of SHFL committee members regarded this problem as an important guiding principle not only for the SHFL but also for their hotel itself:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>We need more ethics, otherwise they broke their legs and they cannot work for a month. People [customers] are not happy in such a hotel, if staffs went playing football and [became] injured. (Timmy)</p>
<p>Some of my players used to have these experiences [injury]. Our league used to have these experiences also, and our fans, our manager and our GM, they all see the fighting in the field. They want to solve this problem not to bring it into the hotel. (Rachana)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>As with all social settings where incipient sport is introduced and at all levels of play, whether action on the field of play remains ‘within the rules’ and respectful, or emotions ‘run-over’ and competition becomes hostile and aggressive seems to depend at least in part on the model of sport being used. A democratic model targeting motives of friendship and collegiality is obviously a very different option than an elite ‘result-oriented’ model where winning at all costs is key, and we observed some manifest ‘growing pains’ in Cambodia as to what exactly the SHFL wanted to be and become. It is unsurprising that many SHFL players prized winning over other goals, but the SHFL committee made clear and evident efforts to strike a balance between the competition that inevitably arises in all sport and a level of friendship that they centrally sought out, as noted in the words of committee members:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I always tell to our members, ‘during your playing, don’t pursue to win too much. Win is win. Everyone wants to win, but you have to know the way to play respecting each other.’ (Sophy)</p>
<p>We need to be more friendly, we don’t want to play badly and we don’t want to relate to any problem. Now all the manager always try to tell them [players], whichever they lose or win, they need to be happy … all the manager … have responsible to control their staffs [players] not to make any problem. We can do it without any difficulty because we can get the cooperation from the other department, staff members and fans who all respect to our players. (Rachana)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The familiar need for balance between healthy and risky competition was not lost on our respondents, as Som observed: ‘If there was … fighting, the team should be brought out and expelled. They must understand the risk they made their hotel name bad. I talk to the players in the meeting to play a more professional game.’ Once again, pursuing this balance is not easy, at any level of sport. As Sugden has put it: ‘Of course if sport becomes ‘‘too competitive’’ – when the quest for victory at all costs overrides the desire to take part in a balanced and equitable struggle for achievement – then any attempt to use sport to enhance positive social goals can be undone’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1012690210395526">2006</xref>: 234). It is fascinating to us that the constant struggle between results-oriented sport and participation-oriented sport may be articulated by one researcher (Sugden) speaking of his experiences with ‘sport-as-peace-development-tool’ in a Middle Eastern setting (Israel), but at the same time reflect just as accurately and poignantly on a new sport initiative in an Asian setting thousands of miles away (Cambodia) replete with a very different social structure and culture.</p>
<p>Regarding the possibility of realizing its stated principal goals, the SHFL experienced a further problem around the issue of registration; a problem that had indeed shown itself from the inception of the league – the familiar problem of ‘unregistered’ individuals being encouraged or allowed to compete. As so many other sport settings have uncovered, an extremely common form of cheating in sport is to allow skilled but unregistered persons to play (this has been such a common problem in North American collegiate sport that complicated rules and often stiff penalties have been devised to prevent it). This was a recurring, if declining, problem in the SHFL. In our time in Siem Reap, we found that such persons might start matches, or they may be introduced as ‘substitutes’ later in games (when it is less easy to ascertain their legitimacy). Culturally, bribery and corruption are not uncommon in Cambodia (in a 2009 speech, a US Ambassador argued that Cambodia lost $500 million US to corruption annually),3 and it would be naïve to expect that it would not surface in a sport context such as an incipient football league. Corruption proved to be a problem of deep concern to the organizers of the SHFL, especially because it can also involve the role of officials. As Moeng put it:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>In this year, problems came from referee. Although they are not professional, they sometimes took one side and the other team got upset. They use their relationships in the game. For example, some members in a group are his [a referee’s] relative or old student. That’s why his feeling was little bit on one side to judge unfairly.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Currently, there are five referees in Siem Reap province and, together, they judge the SHFL matches. They are not professional referees but staff members from the Siem Reap sport office in the Ministry of Education and, by trade, physical education teachers in the primary and secondary school system. They have all had informal technical training by an official referee of the Football Federation of Cambodia (FFC), but this training has not been officially recognized or vetted by the federation. The average age of the five referees is 28 years, and not all of them were trained under the renewed educational system started in 1993 after the Pol Pot regime. Several reported experiencing few sport opportunities during their formative school years and, overall, their experience was limited, which may account for the difficulty they experienced maintaining a balance between friendship and competitiveness on the field of play. Our respondents described officiating problems in the following ways:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>During playing in this year, some players could not accept the judgment by referee because, they said, referee was not correct. Even though they [players] are young, they play a lot. They also watch many matches on T.V. and they know well about football. (Sophy, 34 years, former player, team-leader, assistant Food &amp; Beverage manager)</p>
<p>Honestly, I don’t trust on the referee. Sometimes they use their personal relationships. They don’t even know how to play football. Some players in my team used to play in Phnom Penh and in the other province for the provincial team, so they know very well how to play disciplinary and what is the rule so far. (Rachana)</p>
<p>Referees have some lack points actually, but not really like peoples think they are bad. If we are player, we just play, but referee have to know all the rules. People may think that referring is an easy job but it’s not, no, no really … I feel very sorry for them. (Moeng, 31 years, player, team leader, chief concierge)</p>
<p>The audience, when they see something [e.g. a referee’s decision], they shout ‘oh, it’s not fair!’, ‘referee, don’t do like this!’ whatever. Then, players hearing it in the field think it’s not good judge. (Sambo, 37 years, former-player, SHFL President, chief concierge)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Again, neither officiating ineptitude nor corruption represent new problems in sport; both have been widely reported in a range of national and cultural settings. Both are also experienced where sport is in the throes of development and of establishing norms and policies. In some ways, the speed with which football is entering the social and cultural landscape of Cambodian life, such as in the case of the SHFL, is such that rules and norms remain ambiguous and unclear, and certainly exploitable, at this time. As Vamplew noted, ‘rules are not set in a vacuum but are affected by a variety of factors often reflecting the social, economic or even political environment of the time’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1012690210395526">2007</xref>: 23). In the SHFL case, Sophy’s comments underscore the fact that the values characterizing the SHFL are far from homogeneous for everyone involved:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>We have our level. Our hotel league is small part of our government which has competitors, professionals … our league is for fun, friendship and our relationship only. But some hotel, they don’t think like that. Some says ‘I do what I want to get a champion’. So, sometimes the operation cannot run smooth because of them. Anyway, we try to control everything. During this year, we have some complaints between hotel [team] and hotel, and between hotel and referees. I hope next year, we set very very strict policy to control on that. Even this year, our policy was strict, but some hotel, they didn’t respect it well. (Sophy)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The SHFL committee tried to resolve the problems we have identified (such as physical violence, registration violations, and corruption involving players or officials) in an informal and democratic way, introducing a new mechanism for negotiation and resolution. This included the adoption of a system of so-called ‘double regulation’ – a mix of the Cambodian Football Association and FIFA regulations on the field, as well as SHFL-specific regulations for resolving their issues both on and off the field.</p>
<p>By adopting this ‘double regulation’ code, the committee felt more robustly equipped to deal with and resolve problems. On the one hand, they set clear and detailed rules regarding certain issues (discussed above) that trouble SHFL management. At the same time, and wanting to avoid draconian interventions and sanctions, they omitted overly strict rules in SHFL regulations that have the possibility of excluding some teams and players or applying harsh penalties:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>We don’t want to chase any SHFL members which have already joined in SHFL. If we are too strict in our policy, the one who made a mistake will be out. Although it depends on the mistake, we should explain not to repeat it to continue joining instead of [throwing] them out. Because our most important purpose is friendship, so we need let participants understand about our members, about another teams not only about themselves. (Sophy, 2009)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In their meetings and discussions, the SHFL committee members confirmed their original policy and purposes several times among themselves, and sought out the best way to resolve problems emerging in their fledgling league. Repeatedly, they showed every effort to galvanize and stand by their originally stated principals, but were more than willing to acknowledge that, to this point at least, their commitment to sport as a tool of social development and specifically their push towards friendship and collegiality had at times been tempered by corruption, excessive competitiveness and violence, as well as other matters over which they continue to struggle.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1012690210395526" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion: Sport and social development and the need for circumspection</title>
<p>As our data show, establishing friendship, cultivating respect and collegiality on and at several levels are core values of the SHFL. To many readers, these may appear as simple, predictable, and even naïve motives. However, of real relevance for a culturally sensitive sociology of sport, Cambodia <italic>and</italic> the SHFL are beset with their own unique experiences and problems where the uses (and abuses) of sport are concerned. In our view, the SHFL is a notable and eminently studyable cultural phenomenon in modern Cambodia where there remain very few opportunities for people to experience social integration except for concrete work-related activities in the daily pursuit of making a living in a continuingly destitute country.</p>
<p>Reminding us of a familiar theme in sport advocacy which is clearly not without its critics, the focal point of the discussions of the organizers of the SHFL was consistently about striking a balance of <italic>competitiveness</italic> and <italic>friendship</italic> in Cambodian society, which always seemed to be at the basis of their problems, in and out of sport. Importantly and as several of our respondents noted, creating friendship in the SHFL community as well as in the community more broadly carries the possibility to enhance further values such as safety, security and local hospitality at, for instance, the World Heritage Angkor Wat site, which might in turn attract more foreign tourists in the future. The invitations of students and local residents to SHFL matches show the SHFL’s goal of encouraging comprehensive personal friendships among hotel staff members, between hotels, and among local residents living within proximity of the hotels. As several SHFL representatives argued, when rival hotels enjoy close relationships and exchange information and experience in such an informal and collegial way, the effectiveness of the tourism sector more broadly is enhanced, even though that efficacy is expressed in terms other than annual revenues and is difficult to quantify.</p>
<p>In his research on tourism in the Mekong area, Polladach observed: ‘An issue … that needs to be confronted is how income created by the tourism industry can be shared fairly to reduce poverty and make a healthier community’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1012690210395526">2010</xref>: 207). In many of the developing countries, tourism development is typically pursued (i.e. owned, controlled and operated) via foreign investment, and it is often the case that benefits to local residents are intangible, or worse. Although, as described here, we certainly found evidence of conflict and struggle between elements of the Cambodian tourism industry and the local residents of Siem Reap, the SHFL, to this point at least, shows genuine care in and diligence toward loftier motives aimed not at profit but at forms of development in the local region and beyond along the lines identified in this article, and ably summed up in the words of a former player and executive housekeeper of one of the SHFL hotels: ‘We want to explain people in Siem Reap that we (the hotels) don’t mean we want to earn by ourselves. We would like to contribute on the development of whole Siem Reap’ (Sithen, 34 years).</p>
<p>At the time of writing and on the basis of the evidence to date, it seems reasonable to acknowledge that SHFL activities, representing an alliance between the hotels and established social organizations such as the provincial education office, underscore the possibility and potential of sport in strongly positive ways. There are obvious limitations to any successes so far – the SHFL, like much of Cambodian society more generally, opens up far more doors to males than females and remains patriarchal in this respect, like sport anywhere it is amenable to exploitation and abuse, and we are very aware that in time its still rather simple and so-far laudable goals might be impacted by the vicissitudes of power, finance and corruption. But for the time being at least this modest Asian initiative, embedded in both its own micro-cultural setting and connected to the far broader spirit of ‘social development through sport’, remains at an embryonic and innocent stage of its own life-course. When the committee members air their uncertainties about competitiveness and friendship, they genuinely feel that they are creating an arena for the healthy co-existence of these two factors. The conflicts and continuous struggles for these possibilities allow Cambodian people to interact and explore forms of cooperation, while coalescing around a form and type of sport undergoing its own kind of definition and shaping to best fit local circumstances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1012690210395526">Donnelly and Young, 1985</xref>). Stated differently, and as Coalter has remarked, ‘developing sport in the community, it may also be possible to contribute to the development of communities through sport’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1012690210395526">2005: 4</xref>).</p>
<p>The sociology of sport literature contains an entire early generation of largely functionalist sport studies taking for granted the positive functions of sport, and more recently and more critically, several notable studies regarding the possibility of friendship and integration through sporting activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1012690210395526">Coalter, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1012690210395526">Coleman and Iso-Ahola, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1012690210395526">Iso-Ahola, 1996</xref>), and about cultivating morals and value systems to allow communities to ‘work’ more efficiently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1012690210395526">Coalter, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1012690210395526">Ebbeck and Gibbons, 2003</xref>). As with others, our fieldwork leads us to acknowledge the potentially positive and integrative possibilities of sport as a tool of social development, but does not suggest that sport is so autonomous that it can make social problems magically disappear or new and better communities magically come to life. This was not the case with the SHFL, or indeed with Cambodian society more generally, where phenomena such as poverty, social conflict and violence endure, despite the introduction of well-intended sport-related initiatives.</p>
<p>Generally speaking, it is difficult to evaluate the outcomes of sport in developmentsectors, especially when the targets are based on abstract characteristics, since these outcomes are often intangible and take a long time to become evident and measure robustly and with accuracy. However, through our research in Cambodia we found such ‘outcomes’ include personal and social friendship and cooperation, and the sprouting of spontaneous efforts for social development by members in the private sector. As the basic values of sports – such as teamwork, effort, and achievement – reflect those of the wider society (Sport for Development and Peace International Working Group, 2007), SHFL members regard ‘sport’ as a powerful tool to enhance local living conditions and circumstances via one of its key industries – tourism. Our Cambodian case study does not necessarily mean that sport can be used as a ‘development tool’ successfully in all settings, such as other developing countries. Indeed, our case study does not allow us to say with certainty that sport ‘solves’ social problems or, in fact, does anything more than ‘lives along side’ social problems as they continue to be struggled over by the locals involved.</p>
<p>However, on the other hand, our study did allow us to confirm that, as an organization and an idea, the SHFL at the very least operates as a context in which social problems may be acknowledged, considered and addressed, as well as bringing otherwise diverse and differentiated groups together in potentially respectful and healthy ways. For these reasons, we believe that exploring a fledgling sport initiative in a developing culture such as Cambodia carries merit and value both in and of itself as well as for the wider implications it may have for the community around it.</p>
<p>During this research venture into the possibility of using sport in developing contexts, some keywords such as ‘spontaneousness’, ‘voluntariness’, ‘autonomy’ and ‘grassroots’ emerged as important elements of social development through sport. These words are not only poignant because they speak to the possibility of sport being used for developing communities in a macro sense, but also because they hint at the roles of individuals in these communities in a micro sense; and, specifically, they hint at how sport initiatives might provide venues for personal growth. For all its negatives and flaws, sport is clearly a social institution with ‘promise’ on both community and individual levels, and the introduction of the SHFL is evidence of how otherwise relatively unempowered individuals can operate spontaneously, voluntarily and relatively autonomously at the grassroots level through sport to improve their social circumstances. This, however, is not to deny the possibility of clashing value and power systems of one kind or another entering the picture so as to color that sport initiative as it evolves, as we discovered in the local struggles over forms of cheating and violence, as well as in emerging dialogues of participants regarding what football in the local community could and should be, and for whom. Emphasizing the familiar point that sport is ‘contested terrain’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1012690210395526">Donnelly and Young, 1985</xref>) even more strongly, very few local Cambodians are even asking questions about whether the SHFL should open up its doors to females – at this moment the league remains staunchly masculinist. In these respects, and notwithstanding the genuine human spirit of optimism and hope, it seems reasonable to conclude that making a case for an unfettered ‘sport-equates-to-social-development’ argument is uncompelling, and that any promise sport offers communitiesin either a micro or macro sense should be viewed through the lens of caution and circumspection, especially in situations where sport initiatives are embryonic and experimental.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1012690210395526"><label>1.</label><p>The SHFL 2008 teams were: Angkor Palace Resort &amp; Spa, FCC Angkor, Hotel De La Paix, La Résidence d’Angkor, Le Meridian Angkor Hotel, Preah Khan Hotel, Raffles Grand Hotel d’Angkor, Royal Angkor International Hospital, Shinta Mani, Siem Reap Airways Catering, and Victoria Angkor Resort and Spa.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1012690210395526"><label>2.</label><p>The tourism sector continues to lead the national Cambodian economy and it may be argued that the younger generations express a certain pride in it, viewing tourism as a vehicle administered by middle-class people to assist regional and national development.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1012690210395526"><label>3.</label><p>Cited in <italic>The Cambodian Daily</italic> (May 2009). International Volunteer Center of Yamagata, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ivyivy.org/blog/">http://www.ivyivy.org/blog/</ext-link>, accessed 5 October 2010.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Amusa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toriola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Physical Education and Sport in Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>Ibadan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>LAP Publications</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Sport in Thailand</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Sport in Asia and Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arbena</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>An Annotated Bibliography of Latin American Sport: Pre-Conquest to thePresent</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arbena</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Sport in Latin America and the Caribbean</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Colier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>The Cambridge Encyclopedia of Latin America and the Caribbean</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arbena</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Dimensions of international talent migration in Latin American sports</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bale</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Global Sports Arena: Athletic Talent Migration in an Interdependent World</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Frank Cass</publisher-name>, <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arbena</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Dimensions of Latin American soccer on and off the field</article-title>. <source>Studies in Latin American Popular Culture</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arbena</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Meaning and joy in Latin American sports</article-title>. <source>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Talking up the game: Football and the reconstruction of Liberia, West Africa</article-title>. <source>Global Studies in Culture and Power</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>494</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Giulianotti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Entering the Field</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Berg</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Giulianotti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Football in Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mangan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <source>Sport in Africa: Essays in Social History</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Holmes &amp; Meier Publishers Inc</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bale</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Kenyan Running</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Frank Cass &amp; Co. Ltd</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ben-Porat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The commodification of football in Israel</article-title>. <source>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Physical education and sport in the Philippines</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Sport in Asia and Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bronfenbrenner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <source>The Ecology of Human Development: Experiments by Nature and Design</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Social impact assessment and sport development: Social spin-offs of the Australia-South Africa junior sport programme</article-title>. <source>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Building social capital through an ‘active community club’</article-title>. <source>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>New rules to the old game: Cuban sport and state legitimacy in the post-Soviet era</article-title>. <source>Identities, Global Studies in Culture and Power</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chappell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Sport in Namibia: Conflicts, negotiations and struggles since independence</article-title>. <source>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clignet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Modernization and the game of soccer in Cameroun</article-title>. <source>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coalter</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Sport and Community Development: A Manual</source>. <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sport Scotland</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coalter</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>The Social Benefit of Sport: An Overview to Inform the Community Planning Process</source>. <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sport Scotland</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iso-Ahola</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Leisure and health: The role of social support and self-determination</article-title>. <source>Journal of Leisure Research</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Corlett</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mokgwathi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Sport in Botswana</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Sport in Asia and Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="other">
<collab>Danida</collab> (<year>2006</year>) <source>The Atlas of Cambodia: National Poverty and Environment Maps</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Reproduction and transformation of cultural forms in sport: A contextual analysis of rugby</article-title>. <source>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</source> <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Sport in Malaysia</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Sport in Asia and Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ebbeck</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Explaining the self-conception of perceived conduct using indicators of moral functioning in physical education</article-title>. <source>Research Quarterly for Exercise and Sport</source> <volume>74</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>284</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gasser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levinsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Breaking post-war ice: Open fun football schools in Bosnia and Herzegovina</article-title>. <source>Sport in Society</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>457</fpage>–<lpage>472</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Godia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Sport in Kenya</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Sport in Asia and Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Soccer in South Asia: Empire, nation, diaspora</article-title>. <source>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</source> <volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Globalizing sports: Culture and rugby imports from Oceania in Japan</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Alomes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Islands in the Stream</source>. <publisher-loc>Melbourne</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Maribyrnong Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Iso-Ahola</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Leisure-related social support and self-determination as buffers of stress-illness relationship</article-title>. <source>Journal of Leisure Research</source> <volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Keim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Nation Building at Play Vol. 4</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Meyer &amp; Meyer Sport Ltd</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Keimbou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Physical education in Cameroon (1920–60) games, body and culture</article-title>. <source>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lema</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Sport in Zaire</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Sport in Asia and Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Insufficiently active Australian college students: Perceived personal, social, and environmental influences</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Gender Equality, Sport and Development</source>. <publisher-loc>Bienne</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Swiss Academy for Development</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Ministry of Education, Youth and Sport, Kingdom of Cambodia</collab> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Education Strategic Plan 2006–2010</source>. <publisher-loc>Phnom Penh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ministry of Education, Youth and Sport</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nauright</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Sport, Cultures and Identities in South Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Manchester University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ojeme</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Sport in Nigeria</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Sport in Asia and Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>266</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Humpel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Understanding environmental influences on walking: Review and research agenda</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pelak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Negotiating gender/race/class constraints in the new South Africa</article-title>. <source>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Polladach</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Pro-poor ethnic tourism in the Mekong: A study of three approaches in northern Thailand</article-title>. <source>Asia Pacific Journal of Tourism Research</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sallis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hovell</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>A multivariate study of determinants of vigorous exercise in acommunity sample</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Sport for Development and Peace International Working Group</collab> (<year>2006</year>) <source>From Practice to Policy</source>. <publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sport for Development and Peace International Working Group</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Sport for Development and Peace International Working Group</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Harnessing the Power of Sport for Development and Peace: Recommendations to Governments</source>. <publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sport for Development and Peace International Working Group</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Sport in the Yemen Arab Republic</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Sport in Asia and Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Players, workers, protestors: Social change and soccer in colonial Zimbabwe</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>MacClancy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Sport, Identity and Ethnicity</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Berg</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sugden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Teaching and playing sport for conflict resolution and co-existence in Israel</article-title>. <source>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trotz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Rethinking Caribbean transnational connections: Conceptual itineraries</article-title>. <source>Global Networks</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<collab>United Nations Educational Scientific and Cultural Organization</collab> (<year>2004</year>) <conf-name>4th International Conference of Ministers and Senior Officials Responsible for Physical Education and Sport (MINEPS3), working document</conf-name>, <conf-loc>United Nations Educational Scientific and Cultural Organization, Athens</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>UN Inter-agency Task Force on Sport for Development and Peace</collab> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Sport as a Tool for Development and Peace</source>. <publisher-loc>California</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UN Inter-agency Task Force on Sport for Development and Peace</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vamplew</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Playing with the rules: Influences on the development of regulation in sport</article-title>. <source>International Journal of the History of Sport</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>871</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Sport participation in Latin America</article-title>. <source>International Review for the Sociology of Sport</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1012690210395526">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>Sport in Asia and Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>