<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CHI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spchi</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chronic Illn</journal-id>
<journal-title>Chronic Illness</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1742-3953</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1745-9206</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1742395311422613</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1742395311422613</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>‘Getting back to normal’: the added value of an art-based programme in promoting ‘recovery’ for common but chronic mental health problems</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Makin</surname><given-names>Sally</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1742395311422613">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Gask</surname><given-names>Linda</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1742395311422613">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1742395311422613"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1742395311422613"><label>1</label>Old Age Psychiatry, Manchester Mental Health and Social Care Trust, Manchester Royal Infirmary, Manchester, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1742395311422613"><label>2</label>Primary Care Psychiatry, Health Services Research Group, Manchester Academic Health Sciences Centre, University of Manchester, Manchester, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1742395311422613">Linda Gask, Primary Care Psychiatry, Health Services Research Group, Manchester Academic Health Sciences Centre, University of Manchester, Manchester, M13 9PL, UK Email: <email>linda.gask@manchester.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>64</fpage>
<lpage>75</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Objectives. The aim of this project was to explore the <italic>added value</italic> of participation in an <italic>Arts on Prescription</italic> (AoP) programme to aid the process of <italic>recovery</italic> in people with common but chronic mental health problems that have already undergone a psychological ‘talking’-based therapy. Methods. The study utilized qualitative in-depth interviews with 15 clients with persistent anxiety and depression who had attended an ‘AoP’ service and had previously received psychological therapy. Results and discussion. Attending AoP aided the process of recovery, which was perceived by participants as ‘returning to normality’ through enjoying life again, returning to previous activities, setting goals and stopping dwelling on the past. Most were positive about the benefits they had previously gained from talking therapies. However, these alone were not perceived as having been sufficient to achieve recovery. The AoP offered some specific opportunities in this regard, mediated by the therapeutic and effect of absorption in an activity, the specific creative potential of art, and the social aspects of attending the programme. Conclusions. For some people who experience persistent or relapsing common mental health problems, participation in an arts-based programme provides ‘added value’ in aiding recovery in ways not facilitated by talking therapies alone.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Anxiety</kwd>
<kwd>depression</kwd>
<kwd>creative therapies</kwd>
<kwd>social inclusion</kwd>
<kwd>recovery</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1742395311422613"><title>Background</title>
<p>There is a developing evidence base for the impact of creative arts in healthcare.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1742395311422613">1</xref></sup> <italic>Arts in health</italic> have been described as:<disp-quote>
<p>‘<italic>creative activities that aim to improve individual/community health and healthcare delivery using arts-based approaches, and that seek to enhance the healthcare environment through the provision of artworks or performances’</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1742395311422613">2</xref></sup> (p. 11)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>This includes literature and writing, theatre and drama, dance, music and visual arts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1742395311422613">3</xref></sup> and is therefore a broad umbrella covering active participation in creative activities (such as drawing and painting) and more passive audience or viewer activities (such as paintings hung on clinic and hospital walls).The relationship between art and health has a rich and complex history<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1742395311422613">2</xref></sup> and a broad scope incorporating two key dimensions, whether the focus is primarily on engagement with the arts (with an assumption that this carries benefits for well-being) or more specifically on health improvement (with the assumption that the arts can help to achieve health outcomes).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1742395311422613">3</xref></sup> The intervention evaluated in this article is concerned with the latter dimension.</p>
<sec id="sec2-1742395311422613"><title>Arts, health and mental health</title>
<p>In 2006, the Review of Arts and Health Working Group<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1742395311422613">3</xref></sup> concluded that:<disp-quote>
<p>‘<italic>Arts and health are and should be firmly recognised as being, integral to health, healthcare provision and healthcare environments’</italic> (p. 16).</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>The last decade saw a rapid development of arts and health projects across the United Kingdom, supported by policy developments.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1742395311422613">4</xref></sup> However, this was not without its critics citing inadequate evidence and exaggerated claims for the benefits of art.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1742395311422613">5</xref></sup> There have been calls for a more systematic approach to evaluation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1742395311422613">6</xref></sup> in an arena in which there has been only limited peer-reviewed and published research.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1742395311422613">7</xref></sup> Commentators on the evidence base for arts in health have also noted that ‘<italic>there is a pressure for quantitative positivist evaluation</italic>’ in the healthcare field,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1742395311422613">8</xref></sup> particularly in the evaluation of newer focused psychological interventions, which may particularly clash with the ideological stance of those involved in creative therapies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1742395311422613">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>The practice of an art, such as painting, has the potential for therapeutic power, enabling the expression of cognitive, emotional and spiritual ideas to which people may otherwise have no access. The arts can be soothing and calming, distract from pain and anxiety, and increase self-confidence and motivation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1742395311422613">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1742395311422613">10</xref></sup> Particularly promoted for people with mental health problems are community-based ‘arts for health’ projects. These differ from more traditional forms of art therapy, which requires therapists with specialist training, in that they are focused on process—actually ‘doing’ and experiencing the creation of art. There is some evidence that they may have a positive impact on sense of well-being, psychological symptoms, quality of life and recovery from illness.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1742395311422613">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1742395311422613">11</xref></sup> Arts may be especially helpful for those who find it hard to express their feelings verbally,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1742395311422613">8</xref></sup> and can offer ways of dealing with social exclusion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1742395311422613">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1742395311422613">13</xref></sup></p>
<p><italic>Arts on Prescription</italic> (AoP) is a type of social prescribing in which there is a referral process, whereby health or social care providers refer people to a service or source of support.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1742395311422613">14</xref></sup> The first AoP scheme was founded in Stockport in North West England in 1994. In AoP settings, working artists, rather than trained art therapists, engage groups of people in a community setting. There is limited published empirical research specifically on AoP,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1742395311422613">15</xref></sup> but Bungay and Clift have reviewed the available evidence, much of which, they note, is qualitative, indicating that participation raises self-esteem, provides a sense of purpose, helps people engage in social relationships and increases sense of empowerment and social inclusion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1742395311422613">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1742395311422613">16</xref></sup> A large, multi-project evaluation <italic>Invest to Save</italic>, which included evaluation of AoP projects, utilizing both qualitative and quantitative methods and conducted in the North West of England has also reported its findings.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1742395311422613">17</xref></sup></p></sec>
<sec id="sec3-1742395311422613"><title>Promoting recovery</title>
<p>There is also growing interest in the link between <italic>recovery</italic> and involvement in creative activities. Recovery is understood to mean something different from sustained remission of symptoms or cure and has been defined by Anthony as a way of <italic>living a satisfying</italic>, <italic>hopeful and contributing life</italic>, <italic>even with the limitations caused by illness</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1742395311422613">18</xref></sup> There has been only limited exploration of the utility of the ‘recovery model’ for people with common mental health problems (though there is increasing evidence of the chronic nature of some common mental health problems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1742395311422613">19</xref></sup>); and little work has been done to fully characterize the process of recovery from these problems, despite the success of this concept in changing the culture in the field of severe and enduring mental illness (which does not generally include within its definition anxiety and depression), particularly schizophrenia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1742395311422613">20</xref></sup> In recent years, ‘recovery’ has been redefined from the traditional sense of ‘cure’ or ‘absence of symptoms’<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1742395311422613">21</xref></sup> to something less quantifiable and more attainable for those with persistent mental health problems, encapsulating the return of the ability to function effectively to some degree and the return to activities that would normally be taken for granted.</p>
<p>Although some qualitative work has been carried out to characterize the process of recovery from depression,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1742395311422613">22</xref></sup> in the field of common mental health problems notions of ‘recovery’ remain remarkably biomedical. In pharmacological trials, recovery is defined interms of reduction in symptoms rather than improvement in social functioning.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1742395311422613">23</xref></sup> Allied to this is the view that recovery, although defined in social terms but from the rather narrow economic perspective only of ability to work, can be achieved with a ‘quick fix’ of psychological therapy alone.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1742395311422613">24</xref></sup></p></sec>
<sec id="sec4-1742395311422613"><title>The present study</title>
<p>The call for ‘evidence’ to inform the quality and cost-effectiveness of services funded from a diminishing healthcare budget is strident. Indeed it seems likely that, in a period of more limited funding in mental health, with a more specific focus on ‘outcomes’ (usually measured quantitatively),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1742395311422613">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1742395311422613">25</xref></sup> there will be tight competition for funding between community-based services utilising an artistic medium and healthcare services utilising psychological therapies in the non-pharmacological treatment of common mental health problems.</p>
<p>The art-based and psychological therapy literatures have developed in parallel. In practice, some clients will have been in receipt of both of these approaches. How do these differ and potentially complement each other? The aim of this project was to explore the <italic>added value</italic> of participation in an <italic>AoP</italic> programme to aid the process of <italic>recovery</italic> in people with common but chronic mental health problems who have already undergone a psychological ‘talking’-based therapy. In order to answer this question, we need to understand how recovery might be conceptualized by those attending the programme. What part did attending the sessions play in the process of recovery? And, how did this process differ from the client's previous experience of treatment—specifically, in this case, psychological or talking therapies?</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec5-1742395311422613" sec-type="methods"><title>Method</title>
<p>Qualitative in-depth interviews with 15 clients who attended the ‘Time Out’ AoPservice run by START in Salford. Permission to carry out this study was obtained from the University of Manchester Research Ethics Committee.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec6-1742395311422613"><title>Setting</title>
<p>The START in Salford project (a charitable organisation that provides arts training andopportunities for people of all ages experiencing mental ill health or social exclusion) is based in Pendleton, Salford, Greater Manchester, and was set up in 1993, where it primarily worked with people with severe mental health problems and psychosis. For the last 5 years, it has been providing a service for people with mild to moderate anxiety and depression, referred (as a form of social prescribing) by their general practitioner (see <xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="boxed-text1-1742395311422613">Box 1</xref>)
<boxed-text id="boxed-text1-1742395311422613" position="float"><title>Box 1</title>
<p>The <bold>‘Time Out’ project at START in SALFORD</bold></p>
<p>Start ‘Time Out’ Arts on Prescription service offers up to two sessions weekly, each lasting 2 hours with all materials and equipment provided. Professional artists are there to help as much as members need and will guide them through a series of activities which could include: drawing and painting, pottery, gardening, photography and more. They can try a variety of activities and choose what they like best. Beginners are especially welcome.</p>
<p>The project is flexible and can last up to 6 months. Members can explore opportunities in volunteering, leisure interests, employment and education. Or, having enjoyed their 6 months of art sessions they may then decide to join the member-led art group.</p>
<p>A mental health worker carries out the initial assessment, and is available for one-to-one counselling when needed. She also runs workshops to promote mental well-being such as relaxation sessions.</p>
<p>Additional out-reach art sessions are also organized in local primary care settings, which have also welcomed exhibitions of members’ work.</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.startinsalford.org.uk">http://www.startinsalford.org.uk</ext-link></p></boxed-text></p></sec>
<sec id="sec7-1742395311422613"><title>Recruitment of sample</title>
<p>A list of 28 clients of the project who had recently completed (or almost completed) the 6-month AoP programme, and whom had also been in receipt of some form of psychological therapy within the previous 5years (and thus were experiencing or hadexperienced either persistent or recurrent symptoms anxiety and/or depression during that period), was compiled by the mental health worker attached to the project. A total of 16 potential interviewees were approached from this list by the researchers, based upon their gender (in order to achieve a balance of male and female interviewees) andthe type of psychological treatment received—cognitive-behaviour therapy,counselling, guided self-help and/or brief psychological input from a Graduate Mental Health Worker or psychodynamic psychotherapy (or a combination of these)—in order to include as wide a range as possible of different experiences of talking therapies. Further, interviewees were approached from the remaining clients when two of the original 16 who had initially expressed interest in the study were not willing to participate and one person withdrew permission after the interview, leaving a total of 15 (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1742395311422613">Table 1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table1-1742395311422613" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics of participants and experiences of talking therapies</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1742395311422613" xlink:href="10.1177_1742395311422613-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Interview number</th>
<th>Gender</th>
<th>Age</th>
<th>Ethnicity</th>
<th>Type of previous treatment</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>01</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Cognitive–behaviour therapy</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>02</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Cognitive–behaviour therapy</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>03</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Cognitive–behaviour therapy</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>04</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Graduate mental health worker<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1742395311422613">*</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td>05</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Perinatal service-counselling</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>06</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Graduate mental health worker<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1742395311422613">*</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td>07</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Counselling</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>09</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Counselling</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Graduate mental health worker<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1742395311422613">*</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Psychodynamic psychotherapy</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Graduate mental health worker<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1742395311422613">*</xref> alcohol team</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>13</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Graduate mental health worker<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1742395311422613">*</xref></td></tr>
<tr>
<td>14</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Cognitive-behaviour therapy, inpatient care</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>M</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Counselling, inpatient care</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td>F</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>White British</td>
<td>Counselling</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1742395311422613"><label>*</label><p>Graduate mental health worker is trained in and provides brief psychological therapy utilising guided self-help.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>The interviewees were between the ages of 22 and 62 and all were of White British ethnicity. START gets few ethnic minority referrals, which reflect the ethnic mix of Salford (predominantly White British). Generally, they were no longer in receipt of any form of psychological therapy although in a minority of cases contact with the psychological therapist was ongoing. All those interviewed described experience of persistent mental health problems, which hadonly partially, if at all, responded to earlier therapy. All participants provided written consent to be interviewed and every effort was made to ensure that intervieweesdid not feel coerced in any way to participate.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec8-1742395311422613"><title>Data collection</title>
<p>Interviews were carried out during the period of May to July 2008 by a medical student researcher trained and supervised by the second author. Interviews were specifically concerned with the following topics: the nature of the problems that resulted in referral to the project, views about the project, how the process helped with specific symptoms of anxiety and depression and with the process of ‘recovery’—including how that was understood by the participants, and how this approach differed from their experience in talking therapies. The interviews lasted between half an hour and an hour and a half and were all audio-recorded and transcribed. The topic guide can be found in <xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="boxed-text2-1742395311422613">Box 2</xref>.
<boxed-text id="boxed-text2-1742395311422613" position="float"><title>Box 2</title>
<p>
<list list-type="order">
<list-item><p><bold>Nature of problem that resulted in attending the project?</bold> (<italic>prompts</italic>)
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Nature of problem</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Duration</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>How affects everyday life</p></list-item>
</list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Other types of treatment that he/she has received for this?</bold> Who from? (<italic>prompts</italic>)
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>GP</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>From Primary Care Mental Health Team</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mental Health Services</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Other?</p></list-item>
</list>What type of treatment? (<italic>prompts</italic>)
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Talking treatment- psychotherapy, counselling, cognitive-behaviour therapy</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Medication?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Other?</p></list-item>
</list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Views about Arts on Prescription?</bold>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>What have you been doing on programme?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>How has this helped- if at all- with symptoms?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>How has this helped- if at all- with functioning in everyday life?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>How has it helped- if at all- with getting back into work?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What else is involved in recovery?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>How else has it helped or definitely not helped?</p></list-item>
</list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><bold>Comparison with previous experience of talking treatments?</bold>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>How does this approach differ from talking treatment?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What is different? What is Arts on Prescription better for? What is talking treatment better for?</p></list-item>
</list></p></list-item>
</list></p></boxed-text></p></sec>
<sec id="sec9-1742395311422613"><title>Analysis</title>
<p>All participants were sent copies of their interview transcripts for editing and correction so they could be sure that their anonymity had not been compromised in any way. Data was analysed thematically.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1742395311422613">26</xref></sup> The lead author began coding each interview as it was carried out, with the assistance of MAXQDA2 qualitative software to assist in data handling. Emergent themes were discussed and developing hypotheses explored in subsequent interviews with modification of the interview schedule. All interviews were repeatedly read by both authors. As the project progressed, they met regularly to clarify meaning and to characterize the nature of the experiences that were described by participants, in order to develop a conceptual understanding of emergent themes.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec10-1742395311422613" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title>
<p>The findings are presented here, in accordance with the key themes that emerged from the analysis. Through an understanding of how participants conceptualized ‘recovery,’ it was possible to develop an understanding of how attendance at AoP had contributed to this, and then to discern how this experience differed from and/or complimented their previous experience of psychological therapy.</p>
<sec id="sec11-1742395311422613"><title>Returning to normality</title>
<p>It was particularly striking how many participants described persistent problems with social functioning, in terms of an inability to ‘go out’ and re-engage with everyday life prior to beginning to attend the programme. Many described long-standing difficulties with making relationships and coming to terms with loss, particularly through bereavement. The concept of ‘recovery’ as used in the literature referred to above was not at all familiar to any of the participants in the early interviews, so it was necessary to translate this in subsequent interviews into an equivalent concept; to this end ‘getting better’ was found to be the simplest explanation of the term.</p>
<p>Some participants said that ‘getting better’ for them meant getting on with life; to stop dwelling on past experiences and to move forward, enabling them to do things for themselves:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘What does “getting better” mean? Getting back to what we used to be like. Getting back to what we used to do. I mean, when I was</italic> [depressed] <italic>I didn’t watch TV, DVDs, play computer games, read … I never did anything, I didn’t even date … I lost all them and that’s all the stuff I used to do’</italic> (participant 4).</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>For others, it was important to be able to set goals and to be able to reach them, with a sense of moving forward:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘looking as though I can go out and I can set goals and I can make them goals … me being happy rather than just stuck in a rut’</italic> (participant 5).</p></disp-quote>And it was quite simply feeling ‘normal’:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘I know it sounds daft, but feeling normal … it’s not feeling tired, achy, sad … . So feeling normal is getting up in the morning going, “Oh, right, yes, new day.” Get ready, have a shower, brush your teeth, clean up quick so you can get out’</italic> (participant 16).</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Thus, there was a sense of wanting to get back to a life where it was possible to achieve things that had previously been taken for granted, but which was also enjoyable, hopeful and productive. For some, but not all, this also meant being hopeful about returning to work but this was only one aspect of ‘normality’ and seen as an ultimate rather than a more immediate goal, which was unsurprising given the chronicity of some problems that were described.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec12-1742395311422613"><title>The specific benefits of talking therapy</title>
<p>Most of the participants were positive about the benefits they had previously gained from talking therapies. Some particularly like the non-judgemental stance taken by the therapist and the reassurance received from them. Cognitive approaches were helpful for enabling them to understand their own thoughts and to change the way they were thinking about things:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘It was good for making me focus on things I was doing that were negative, and how to focus on things that were positive and how to maintain a consistent routine as well. I mean just to see where I was going wrong with things, see how I was looking at things in negative ways’</italic> (participant 2—cognitive-behaviour therapy).</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>A sense of achieving insight from talking about the past was perceived as an important benefit from counselling and more insight-oriented therapies:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘There was a lot of things that I discovered about myself, masses of things that I discovered about myself which I should have learned when I was younger’</italic> (participant 11—dynamic psychotherapy).</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>The confidentiality of the one-to-one therapeutic relationship was particularly valued:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘It’s good because you’re speaking one to one, and it’s confidential. When there’s other people it can be, you know if they are going to say anything outside, or if you bump into them again and they hold it against you and things like that’</italic> (participant 15—counselling, also inpatient care).</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>However, these alone were not perceived as having being sufficient to always help participants to achieve what they considered to be ‘returning to normality’.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec13-1742395311422613"><title>The contribution of AoP to ‘returning to normality’</title>
<p>Three themes emerged from the data in relation to how attending AoP specifically contributed to a sense of being able to return to a sense of ‘normality’: the therapeutic and effect of absorption in an activity, the specific creative potential of art and the social aspects of attending the programme.</p>
<sec id="sec14-1742395311422613"><title>Absorption in activity</title>
<p>Most participants talked about how the arts helped to keep their mind busy. This helped people by keeping them occupied and preventing boredom and by ‘taking their mind off things’ and ‘getting you doing things’. Participating in the classes gave them something to focus on, giving them a way of dealing with distress and helping to stop ruminating on negative thoughts and also to relax:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘Well it’s a few hours where your mind is occupied and absorbed by what you’re doing at the Arts centre, so it takes your mind off reality for a while’</italic> (participant 14).</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>This feeling might carry over into everyday life:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘it takes you away from yourself, you’re thinking about something else … There’s many a morning after I’ve left here when it’s finished, at 12.30 … you’re going home with a buzz, that was alright, that felt good, that lasted all day’</italic> (participant 13).</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>In addition to providing distraction to them and allowing relaxation, doing something also gave participants a purpose, a structure for their day and a reason to get up in the morning and leave their home, helping to increase their motivation.<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘Well it’s something to get up for, isn’t it? “Oh yes, I’m going to go there and do that today”’</italic> (participant 1).</p>
<p><italic>‘It made me more focused on what I was doing. I started to organise myself better. Create a routine, rather than just drifting through the day’</italic> (participant 2).</p></disp-quote></p></sec>
<sec id="sec15-1742395311422613"><title>Creativity</title>
<p>Creating art was seen to be therapeutic and relaxing, providing some participants with a way of expressing themselves and reflecting their state of mind:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘How does it feel to paint a nice picture?’Cause I’m doing something that’s nice and it’s beautiful. I’m not doing something that’s sad and depressing. I mean, if Idrew you a picture now of a dark castle on a stormy night, what does that tell you about my state of mind? It means I’m depressed. If Idraw something like a nice, sunny landscape with sheep and cows and that … you know, that’s basically what it is’</italic> (participant 4).</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>But for most, it was important in terms of its contribution to a sense of tangible achievement, producing a ‘product’ of a piece of art and thus resulted in increase in confidence and self-esteem.</p>
<p>Many participants reported how participation in the arts sessions had increased theirconfidence. Achievement played an important part—participants oftensurprised themselves with what they were able to achieve artistically, creating and producing something tangible, which led to increased confidence in their own abilities and self-worth.<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘it started out just doing a little bit of art but the confidence spreads to other areas in your life, like I say, doing things, talking to people, not being frightened to have a go. Like I say it’s affected quite a wide range, Ithink’</italic> (participant 16).</p></disp-quote></p></sec>
<sec id="sec16-1742395311422613"><title>Company and support</title>
<p>The social aspect of the programme appears to be very important for all of the participants. Almost everyone said they had made friends, and highlighted this as an important part of the programme. A number of these people saw the friends they had made in the classes outside of START.</p>
<p>Meeting other people was a very important aspect of the sessions, allowing participants to have someone to talk to and someone to listen to their problems, which was seen as being very helpful. These people might be the mental health worker, others who were experiencing similar problems:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘I think being able to come here and speak to people who obviously have probably been through the same thing as what I’ve been through … And I think if you make friends with people and you chat to them and you listen to them and they listen to you, I think you’re helping each other along, you know’</italic> (participant 6).</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>A number of participants talked about how being in the classes allowed them to ‘be themselves’. Sessions provided a non-threatening and non-competitive environment where people felt they were accepted and could relax, something which may notbe possible at home. It seemed important, however, that ‘talking’ was something that participants did not feel obliged to do:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘I come in here and if I choose to talk to somebody I can’</italic> (participant 11).</p>
<p><italic>‘Unless you wanted to speak to her,</italic> [mental health worker] <italic>she wouldn’t dig’</italic> (participant 12)<italic>.</italic></p></disp-quote></p>
<p>So, being able to relax and enjoy life again, a sense of achievement resulting in increased confidence and self-esteem, and an opportunity to re-engage with the social world again can be seen as the mediating factors by which attending AoP contributed to a sense of ‘getting back to normal’.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec17-1742395311422613"><title>Doing not talking: Added value of attending AoP</title>
<p>A recurring theme was the need to build on what had been gained in psychological therapy, by having an opportunity to (and being motivated to) re-engage with life.<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘My psychologist referred me, because I was stuck in the house really for quite long’</italic> (participant 15).</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>However, talking therapy did not specifically facilitate social interaction or necessarily focus on the future:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘it was just like “Right sit here and spill your life out”, really. It’s like; I don’t want to do that. … I just wanted the more social side and nobody to sit there and say “You need to think about your past” or anything like that. I just wanted more to focus more on whatwas coming rather than what’s been’</italic> (participant 5—perinatal service and counselling).</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Participants commented on how they liked that the programme was practical and constructive providing participants with new interests and skills and aiding them to return to activities. This made them feel that they were doing something worthwhile that was actively helping them move forward in their lives, thus restoring more sense of hope:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘I think also with talking therapies, particularly with counselling—you could talk about the man in the moon if you wanted to … it’s something to get up for, isn’t it?. “Oh yes, I’m going to go there and do that today” and “Yes I want to finish that painting so I’ll do a bit now”’</italic> (participant 1).</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Indeed, an important aspect of the programme appeared to be its role as a ‘stepping stone’ to other activities. Most participants discussed how it had helped them to get back into education, voluntary work or even, for a few, eventually paid work, giving them a greater sense of meaning and direction in their lives. Thus, talking therapy and attending AoP could be seen as complementary, playing a different role. Indeed, AoP did not seem to be seen as ‘therapy’ in quite the same way as psychological treatment. It was perceived as ‘action’ or ‘doing’ rather than ‘talking’:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>‘discussing and talking about your condition, gives you a bit more understanding. And as I said she [psychologist] came up with suggestions that helped and the Arts on Prescription isn’t to do with your illness, it’s to do with an activity. So as long as you’ve got the ability to do the activity that’s all the tutors are interested in, they’re not interested in what your condition is, whereas you’re talking about yourself and your condition with psychotherapy … they’re both valuable in their own rights, and there’s not one better than the other’</italic> (participant 14).</p></disp-quote></p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec18-1742395311422613" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="sec19-1742395311422613"><title>Summary of key findings</title>
<p>For people with common and chronic mental health problems of depression and anxiety, an arts-based therapeutic programme aided the process of recovery, characterized as ‘returning to normality’, through enjoying life again, returning to previous activities, setting goals and stopping dwelling on the past. Most of the participants were positive about the benefits they had previously gained from talking therapies. However, these alone were insufficient to help them to achieve recovery. Attendance at the AoP Programme was seen as offering some specific opportunities in this regard, mediated by the therapeutic and effect of absorption in an activity, the specific creative potential of art and the social aspects of attending the programme.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec20-1742395311422613"><title>Relevance to the published literature</title>
<sec id="sec21-1742395311422613"><title>The meaning of ‘recovery’ in this context</title>
<p>As we discussed earlier, the meaning of ‘recovery’ remains unclear in relation to people with common mental health problems given that the literature has thus far focused on the experience of people with more chronic and severe mental health problems.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1742395311422613">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1742395311422613">21</xref></sup> Our findings clearly echo those of Ridge and Ziebland<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1742395311422613">22</xref></sup> who found that some of the people with depression who they interviewed wanted to ‘<italic>feel “normal” or “human” again and enjoy life … ’.</italic> They also noted, however, that others wanted more than this, and grappled with narratives about their longer term prognosis. They describe a process of insight into <italic>unknown qualities of self that potentially lie beyond depression</italic> which is echoed in the discoveries that our participants described in their achievement in acquiring or developing artistic skills that they had never known they might possess, leading them to imagine a different narrative for their future lives. However, it is interesting that several of our participants also emphasized their goal as being a return to employment, echoing the narrower way in which recovery has been viewed in recent policy on psychological therapy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1742395311422613">24</xref></sup></p></sec>
<sec id="sec22-1742395311422613"><title>The contribution of art to the recovery process</title>
<p>The role of arts in enhancing self-esteem has been recognised in many areas of mental healthcare<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1742395311422613">8</xref></sup>: by creating something individuals can boost their own self-esteem, which may in turn help to <italic>improve</italic> their mood. Additionally, being able to express one's state of feeling in paintings may not only be calming and relaxing but also help an individual to understand themselves and their state of mind—a finding also supported by previous research in this field.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1742395311422613">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1742395311422613">10</xref></sup> Our themes are very similar to those of Spandler and her colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1742395311422613">11</xref></sup> and those benefits described for other evaluations of AoP programmes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1742395311422613">15</xref></sup></p>
<p>The perceived importance of social interaction also raises the question of whether it was the art classes that participants were involved in, the engagement with a class regardless of the ‘art’ content or just the opportunity to have ‘time out’ from their everyday lives and meeting with others in a similar situation that were the primary factors in bringing about a positive experience. Could this have been achieved in a ‘day centre’ environment without specific engagement in creative work? There are indications that the art played an important role in terms of supporting people. Firstly, the importance of the ‘end products' that were produced in the sessions, the visible art works, was emphasized in terms of the feelings of pride in their achievements—which is also supported by a recent study of the meaning of art to people who use mental health services.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1742395311422613">10</xref></sup> Learning new skills and the achievement of producing something appeared to be important steps towards rebuilding confidence and belief in participants’ own abilities.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec23-1742395311422613"><title>The ‘added value’ of an arts programme</title>
<p>Our study adds to the published literature by delineating the specific ways in which an AoP can ‘add value’ by aiding recovery for people with chronic common mental health problems who have previously experienced psychological therapies. This has not, to our knowledge, been previously explored and was not considered by Spandler et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1742395311422613">11</xref></sup> Previous research specifically evaluating AoP programmes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1742395311422613">15</xref></sup> has also not considered this question, yet, as we have noted earlier, it seems important to ask questions about the specific role of such programmes in the light of the current emphasis on targeting psychological therapy for funding through the Improving Access to Psychological Therapies initiative<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1742395311422613">27</xref></sup> and the changing policy context in the United Kingdom, with the potential risk to funding for both Arts and Social Prescribing initiatives.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1742395311422613">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1742395311422613">28</xref></sup> Many participants were continuing to struggle with social isolation and exclusion. They described a sense of building on what had been gained in psychological therapy, by having an opportunity to (and being motivated to) re-engage with life. Part of the social aspect of attending the programme was having someone to talk to—but this was very much under the control of the participant with no sense of any obligation to talk, either to fellow attendees or the mental health worker. Making friends and creating a social network is clearly impossible to directly achieve from a one-to-one intervention (although it may be a goal of the therapy)—and is not generally encouraged in group psychotherapy. Talking therapy and attending AoP could be seen as complementary, and for many, AoP did not seem to be seen as ‘therapy’ in quite the same way as psychological treatment. There was no relationship with a specific therapist. The emphasis was on activity and enjoyment, with opportunity for improving social interaction. It was perceived quite simply as ‘action’ or ‘doing’ rather than ‘talking’.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec24-1742395311422613"><title>Limitations of the study</title>
<p>Due to time constraints, the sample size was relatively small. It was only possible to interview participants who found the project helpful in some way—people who do not find the AoP useful did not continue to attend the sessions and could therefore not be interviewed. The sample from which the interviewees were selected was drawn up by the project mental health worker and those people who were approached and were willing to talk may have particularly positive experiences. This may have led to an under-representation of the negative aspects of AoP.</p>
<p>We were also unable to specifically report in detail here on other treatment received as this was not the focus of our study, but it does seem likely from our interviews that additional treatments such as medication also played a part, for some participants, inachieving recovery.</p>
<p>It is also possible that people who did not attend the arts programme had recovered as a result of talking therapy alone, such that they did not need to attend an additional treatment programme such as this one; but for those who attended there did appear to be an added benefit in terms of recovery. Completing 15 interviews was enough to reach a saturation of themes in relation to the arts programme but not for the very varied experiences of talking therapy (which we did not report in detail here) as there are many different types of talking treatments available.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec25-1742395311422613" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>For some people who experience persistent or relapsing common mental health problems, participation in an arts-based programme may provide ‘added value’ in aiding recovery in ways not facilitated by talking therapies alone.</p></sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec26-1742395311422613"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1742395311422613"><label>1.</label><citation citation-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staricoff</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <source><italic>Arts in health: a review of the medical literature</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Arts Council, 2004</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1742395311422613"><label>2.</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Determined to dialogue: a survey of arts in health in the North and Yorkshire</source>, <publisher-loc>Durham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Centre for Arts and Humanities in Health Care and Medicine</publisher-name>, <year>2002</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1742395311422613"><label>3.</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Department of Health</collab>. <source>Report of the review of arts and health working group</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Health</publisher-name>, <year>2006</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1742395311422613"><label>6.</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Arts Council England</collab>. <source>A prospectus for arts and health</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Arts Council</publisher-name>, <year>2007</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1742395311422613"><label>7.</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The arts as painkiller</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Mirza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source>Culture vultures: is UK arts policy damaging the arts?</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Policy Exchange</publisher-name>, <year>2006</year>, <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1742395311422613"><label>8.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Argyle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Art in the community for potentially vulnerable mental health groups</article-title>. <source>Health Educ</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1742395311422613"><label>4.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Clift S, Camic PM, Chapman B, Clayton G, Daykin N, Eades G, et al. The state of arts and health in England. <italic>Arts and Health</italic> 2009; 1: 6–35</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1742395311422613"><label>9.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staricoff</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Arts in health: the value of evaluation</article-title>. <source>J R Soc Promot Health</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1742395311422613"><label>10.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lathom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sixsmith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interrogating power: the case of arts and mental health in community projects</article-title>. <source>J Community Appl Soc Psychol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>268</fpage>–<lpage>279</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1742395311422613"><label>11.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stacey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stickley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The meaning of art to people who use mental health services</article-title>. <source>Perspect Publ Health</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1742395311422613"><label>12.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spandler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Secker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Catching life: the contribution of arts initiatives to recovery approaches in mental health</article-title>. <source>J Psychiatr Mental Health Nurs</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>791</fpage>–<lpage>799</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1742395311422613"><label>13.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>South</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Community arts for health: an evaluation of a district programme</article-title>. <source>Health Educ</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1742395311422613"><label>14.</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>ODPM</collab>. <source>Mental health and social exclusion. Social Exclusion Report Summary</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Office of the Deputy Prime Minister</publisher-name>, <year>2004</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1742395311422613"><label>15.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>South</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Can social prescribing provide the missing link?</article-title> <source>Prim Health Care Res Dev</source> <year>1008</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1742395311422613"><label>16.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bungay</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Clift</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Arts on prescription: a review of practice in the UK</article-title>. <source>Perspect Publ Health</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>2767</fpage>–<lpage>2281</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1742395311422613"><label>17.</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Secker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hacking</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Spandler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shenton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Mental health, social inclusion and arts: developing the evidence base</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Health</publisher-name>, <year>2007</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1742395311422613"><label>18.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kilroy</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Senior</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Invest to save: arts in health evaluation, exploring the impact of creativity, culture and the arts, on health and well being</source>. <comment>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.miriad.mmu.ac.uk/investtosave/reports/Summary%20Report%20ISP.pdf">http://www.miriad.mmu.ac.uk/investtosave/reports/Summary%20Report%20ISP.pdf</ext-link> (2007) (accessed 10th September 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1742395311422613"><label>19.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recovery from mental illness: the guiding vision of the mental health system in the 1990's</article-title>. <source>Psychosoc Rehabil J</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1742395311422613"><label>20.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gask</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Is depression a chronic Illness?</article-title> <source>Chron Illness</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1742395311422613"><label>21.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recovery from schizophrenia and the recovery model</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Psychiatr</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>374</fpage>–<lpage>390</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1742395311422613"><label>22.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The rediscovery of recovery: open to all</article-title>. <source>Adv Psychiatr Treat</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1742395311422613"><label>23.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ridge</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziebland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>“The old me could never have done that”: how people give meaning to recovery following depression</article-title>. <source>Qual Health Res</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1038</fpage>–<lpage>1053</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1742395311422613"><label>24.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>McMonagle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The enhancement of social functioning as a therapeutic principle in the management of depression</article-title>. <source>J Psychopharmacol</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>S25</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1742395311422613"><label>25.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Layard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The case for psychological treatment centres</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>332</volume>: <fpage>1030</fpage>–<lpage>1032</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1742395311422613"><label>26.</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Department of Health</collab>. <source>No health without mental health: a cross-government mental health outcomes strategy for people of all ages</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Health</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1742395311422613"><label>27.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Using thematic analysis in psychology</article-title>. <source>Qual Res Psychol</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1742395311422613"><label>28.</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Department of Health. ‘Improving Access to Psychological Therapies’, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iapt.nhs.uk">http://www.iapt.nhs.uk</ext-link> (accessed 10th September 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1742395311422613"><label>29.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><collab>Department of Health</collab>. <source>‘Equity and Excellence: Liberating the NHS’</source>. <comment>http://www.dh.gov.uk/en/Publicationsandstatistics/Publications/PublicationsPolicyAndGuidance/DH_117353 (accessed 10th September 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>