<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CJP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcjp</journal-id>
<journal-title>Criminal Justice Policy Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0887-4034</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3586</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0887403412447809</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0887403412447809</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Sword or Shield? A Systematic Review of the Roles FASD Evidence Plays in Judicial Proceedings</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Douds</surname><given-names>Anne S.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0887403412447809">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>Holly R.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0887403412447809">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sumner</surname><given-names>William E.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0887403412447809">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0887403412447809"><label>1</label>Penn State- Harrisburg, Harrisburg, PA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0887403412447809"><label>2</label>Children’s Law Center, Washington, DC</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0887403412447809"><label>3</label>Redemption After Prison, Atlanta, GA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0887403412447809">Anne S. Douds, 160 Olmstead Building, Department of Public Affairs, PSU, Harrisburg, 777 West Harrisburg Pike, Middletown, PA 17057, USA. Email: <email>anne@federalhasson.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>492</fpage>
<lpage>509</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In this first-ever systematic review of fetal alcohol spectrum disorders in all federal court cases arising prior to 2011, the authors identified 1713 cases, with 131 cases substantively relevant to mental capacity, criminal intent, sentencing, and attorney malpractice. The majority of cases arose after <italic>Atkins v. Virginia</italic>, the pivotal Supreme Court case that prohibits the death penalty for mentally disabled persons. Among other things, this study reveals that FASD evidence usually defeats a death penalty sentence, but the lower courts reflect inconsistencies in how courts receive and handle mental health evidence.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>crimal justice policy</kwd>
<kwd>criminal trial</kwd>
<kwd>justice</kwd>
<kwd>juvenile justice</kwd>
<kwd>sentencing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>“Fetal alcohol spectrum disorders” (FASDs) arise when mothers consume alcohol during pregnancy, causing the developing fetus to be neuro-developmentally impaired (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0887403412447809">Burd, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0887403412447809">Kodituwakku, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0887403412447809">Weinberg et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0887403412447809">Riley et al., 2004</xref>). Although it is not clear what levels of prenatal alcohol exposure cause disabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0887403412447809">Abel, 2006</xref>), it has been established that both chronic alcohol use and intermittent binge drinking during pregnancy can cause profound disabilities along a spectrum of disorders, collectively known as FASDs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0887403412447809">Burd et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0887403412447809">Abel, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0887403412447809">Adams et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0887403412447809">Streissguth et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0887403412447809">Mattson et al., 2007</xref>). According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, FASDs are the leading cause of preventable birth defects and developmental disabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0887403412447809">CDC, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Moreover, FASDs are significantly correlated with criminal justice involvement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0887403412447809">Koren et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0887403412447809">Streissguth et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0887403412447809">Boland et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0887403412447809">Fast &amp; Conry, 2004</xref>; <italic>but see</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0887403412447809">Lynch et al., 2003</xref>). The effects of FASDs plague people throughout their lives, causing them to be at increased risk for delinquent and criminal behavior and for contact with criminal justice systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0887403412447809">Sayal, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0887403412447809">Boland et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0887403412447809">Burd et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0887403412447809">Conry &amp; Lane, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0887403412447809">Ishikawa et al., 2003</xref>). Persons with FASDs are at increased risk for antisocial behavior from birth by virtue of their <italic>in utero</italic> exposure to alcohol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0887403412447809">Roebuck et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0887403412447809">Bailey et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0887403412447809">Coles et al., 1991</xref>), and they frequently suffer from a broad constellation of secondary disabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0887403412447809">Howell et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412447809">Goldschmidt et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0887403412447809">Nanson &amp; Hiscock, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0887403412447809">Charmichael Olson et al., 1997</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0887403412447809">1</xref></sup> In severe cases, FASD sufferers exhibit profound antisocial, delinquent, or aggressive behaviors, and they lack the ability to foresee the consequences of their actions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0887403412447809">Streissguth et al., 2004</xref>). In a recent publication, Fast and Conry provide a useful mnemonic device “ALARM” to summarize the myriad disorders frequently arising from FASDs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0887403412447809">2009</xref>): Poor <italic>Adaptive</italic> functioning; <italic>Language</italic> deficits; Attention problems; deficiencies in <italic>Reasoning</italic> skills; and poor <italic>Memory</italic>. Each of these five disabilities has profound implications for criminal justice practitioners and criminal defendants.</p>
<p>Advocates and researchers maintain that FASD diagnoses are critical at every stage of the criminal justice process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0887403412447809">Streissguth et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0887403412447809">Steinhausen et al. 1993</xref>). However, there is almost no empirical data that explores how FASD diagnoses operate within actual legal systems. In order to explore these issues, this study systematically reviews all relevant United States federal case law to determine how federal courts receive FASD evidence and what role that evidence plays in the disposition of claims for mental incapacity, competency, sentence mitigation, and ineffective assistance of counsel. This article provides the first comprehensive analysis of the roles that FASD evidence plays in federal criminal justice proceedings and explores emerging judicial trends in relation to FASDs.</p>
<sec id="section1-0887403412447809">
<title>Background Literature</title>
<p>FASD is an umbrella term used to describe a constellation of disabilities that may result from prenatal exposure to alcohol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0887403412447809">Chudley et al., 2005</xref>). There is no consensus within the clinical community on the precise diagnostic criteria for FASDs. The more narrowly defined disorder known as “Fetal Alcohol Syndrome” (FAS) is recognized in the latest Diagnostics and Statistical Manual of Mental Health Disorders (<italic>DSM IV</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0887403412447809">Astley et al., 2004</xref>), but the broader spectrum of related disorders, encompassed by the term FASD, are subject to interpretations, depending upon which of several diagnostic criteria clinicians may use. Because this spectrum often includes conditions that can be diagnosed independently of FASDs, the term eludes clinical diagnostic definition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0887403412447809">Boland et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0887403412447809">Stratton et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0887403412447809">Streissguth et al., 1996</xref>).</p>
<p>Nevertheless, FASD is a recognized medical condition with significant, attendant disabilities that implicate sufferers’ legal rights (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0887403412447809">Douglas, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0887403412447809">Moore &amp; Greene, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0887403412447809">Fast &amp; Conry, 2009</xref>), ranging from their rights against self-incrimination and their right to effective assistance of counsel to their right to introduce mental health in mitigation at sentencing. Moreover, because persons with FASDs may meet the standard for “mental retardation,” the courts may be prohibited from imposing the death penalty on such persons under <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0887403412447809"><italic>Atkins v. Virginia</italic> (2002)</xref>. Persons suffering from FASDs, and related secondary disabilities, often do not have the cognitive ability to form criminal intent, to confess or testify meaningfully, or to benefit from traditional sentencing structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0887403412447809">SAMHSA, 2006</xref>). Many FASD sufferers exhibit impaired adaptive functioning; research demonstrate that many FASD sufferers they essentially lack the level of social responsibility, or personal autonomy, generally expected from people in society (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0887403412447809">Conry &amp; Fast, 2009</xref>). Other studies reveal that many FASD sufferers cannot translate socially learned lessons from one situation to another, and that they often have problems with externalization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0887403412447809">D’Onofrio et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0887403412447809">Thomas et al., 1998</xref>). Streissguth and colleagues found that persons with FASDs score significantly lower on tests that measure for adaptive functioning, suggesting that FASD sufferers are likely to have difficulties with interpersonal boundaries and with identifying positive and negative peer influences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0887403412447809">Streissguth et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0887403412447809">Sood et al., 2001</xref>). FASD sufferers have normal tested IQs, but they often exhibit inferior social and adaptive skills. They may be eager to please, and they may befriend people who will take advantage of them. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0887403412447809">Thomas et al., 1998</xref>). Research further demonstrates that many FASD sufferers are highly suggestible (Kassin et al., 2010; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0887403412447809">Perske, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0887403412447809">Fast &amp; Conry, 2004</xref>). They often are unlikely to consider the long-term consequences of their statements or actions, which can have profound criminal justice implications. For example, because they are socialized to respect authority figures such as police officers and court officials, they may “confess” or testify to an untruth if they think it is what someone “wants to hear” (Kassin et al., 2010; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0887403412447809">Perske, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0887403412447809">Fast &amp; Conry, 2004</xref>). Similarly, in an effort to escape the discomfort inherent in an arrest or in court testimony, they will recount what they think someone “wants to hear” rather than the truth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0887403412447809">Moore &amp; Greene, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0887403412447809">Clare &amp; Gudjonnson, 1993</xref>).</p>
<p>Language problems compound FASD sufferers’ adaptive and cognitive immaturity and contribute to their difficulties with meaningful participation in criminal justice systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0887403412447809">Church &amp; Kaltenbach, 1997</xref>). In their efforts to please the authority figure posing questions, FASD sufferers may say they understand something when they do not. Because their disabilities may be “hidden” by superficial verbal skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0887403412447809">Chartrand &amp;Forbes-Chilbeck, 2003</xref>), they may appear to understand their rights, but cognitively they are lost. Accordingly, they may unwittingly abdicate their constitutional rights against unreasonable searches and seizures, against self-incrimination, and to assistance of counsel (Kassin et al., 2010).</p>
<p>Similarly, persons with FASDs have attention problems, which commonly are associated with impulse control and, thus, delinquent behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0887403412447809">Peadon &amp; Elliott, 2010</xref>). They have trouble delaying gratification. Like all people, they wish to avoid discomfort. However, their disabilities may lead them to consent to a search, confess to a crime, or provide false testimony simply to escape the immediate discomfort of the police interrogation or court appearance. They do not understand the need to be truthful. The complexity of trials is vexing to persons of normal intellect; they can be overwhelming to persons of inferior cognitive ability, which may cause them to say or do things adverse to their interests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0887403412447809">LaDue &amp; Dunne, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0887403412447809">Moore &amp; Greene, 2004</xref>). As an example from outside the United States, one young man, suffering from FASDs, confessed to a double murder that he could not have committed because he was incarcerated at the time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0887403412447809">Conry &amp; Fast, 2000</xref>). He later explained that he thought that the attorney who was questioning him would be “happy” if he told him what he “wanted to hear.” He also added that he just wanted for the questioning to end, and he thought that confession was the most expeditious solution.</p>
<p>Exhibition of such a lack of impulse control belies underlying problems with cognitive reasoning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0887403412447809">Willford et al., 2006</xref>). People with FASDs often lack the ability to comprehend abstract thought or to understand their legal rights (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0887403412447809">Bracken, 2008</xref>). At the most fundamental level, clinical experience has established that persons with FASDs often lack the requisite capacity to form criminal intent such that they should be subjected to criminal laws and stand trial, clearly suggesting that FASDs are relevant to insanity defenses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0887403412447809">LaDue &amp; Dunne, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0887403412447809">Capron, 1992</xref>).</p>
<p>Persons with FASDs frequently lack the intellect necessary to understand the judicial proceedings of which they are a part (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0887403412447809">Clare &amp; Gudjonnson, 1993</xref>). They are unlikely to comprehend the implications of consenting to a search, plea negotiations, or sworn testimony (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0887403412447809">Bracken, 2008</xref>). For example, they may lack the requisite mental capacity for their consent to a search to be “voluntary” under the law (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0887403412447809">Conry &amp; Fast, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0887403412447809">Fast &amp; Conry, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Finally, memory problems plague FASD sufferers, causing gaps in recall and poor recollection in general (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0887403412447809">Douglas, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0887403412447809">Rasmussen, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0887403412447809">Mattson et al., 1996</xref>). They may not be competent to participate in their own defense or serve as a witness. Again, because of their impulsive desire to please and to avoid uncomfortable situations, compounded by their inferior reasoning abilities, they may testify falsely or confabulate during interrogation. Therefore, their reliability as witnesses should be scrutinized carefully (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0887403412447809">Fast &amp; Conry, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>These issues have taken on greater legal significance in the wake of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0887403412447809"><italic>Atkins v. Virginia</italic> (2002)</xref>, in which the United States Supreme Court determined that a “mentally retarded” defendant cannot be subjected to the death penalty. However, not all disorders arising from FASDs constitute “mental retardation.” The broad spectrum of conditions implicated by an FASD diagnosis makes the applicability of <italic>Atkins</italic> problematic and highly case-specific.</p>
<p>Perhaps most significantly, failure to identify or properly present FASD evidence may support a claim for ineffective assistance of counsel (IAC). In these claims, a defendant seeks a new trial or hearing on the basis that the attorney did not represent him/her effectively. The standard for effectiveness is defined in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0887403412447809"><italic>Strickland v. Washington</italic> (1984)</xref>. Under the two-prong <italic>Strickland</italic> standard, a moving party must demonstrate that the attorney’s performance was deficient <italic>and</italic> that the deficiency resulted in prejudice to the defense. Theoretically, an attorney could be found to have failed to provide adequate counsel if he/she fails to raise the FASD issue; fails to investigate the FASD issue; fails to produce adequate medical evidence or expert testimony regarding FASD; fails to elicit proper testimony from an expert; or fails to secure an opposing expert. No prior studies have analyzed the law that governs claims for ineffective assistance of counsel (IAC) in relation to FASDs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0887403412447809" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>This study provides the first systematic review of all federal case law available through Lexis Nexis for any and all cases from any and all dates in the “All Federal Cases” database that contained the terms “alcohol” and either “fetal,” “prenatal,” “perinatal,” “pregnant,” “in utero,” “ARND” (alcohol related neurodevelopmental disorder), “ARBD” (alcohol related birth defect), “FAS,” “FAE” (fetal alcohol effects) or “FASD” with the search term for “pregnant,” truncated to capture “pregnancy” also. This search identified 1,713 cases, 131 of these cases referenced evidence relating to any party or witness’s prenatal exposure to alcohol. These cases were retained for analysis. The authors coded these cases for (a) date; (b) jurisdiction; (c) level of court; (d) whether the FASD evidence related to a defendant or a witness; (e) the substantive claims implicated in relation to the FASD evidence; (f) whether the FASD evidence was admitted into evidence by the court; (g) whether the FASD evidence was found to be persuasive; and (h) whether the party seeking relief in reliance on FASD evidence prevailed in the underlying claim(s). Although all 131 cases were coded, only 108 included substantive analysis of legal issues involving FASD evidence. Those 108 cases provide the bulk of data that are the subject of this study.</p>
<sec id="section3-0887403412447809">
<title>Findings</title>
<p>The majority of the 131 identified cases arose within the past five years, with only 23 cases identified prior to the 2000s and 81 cases arising after 2005 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0887403412447809">Figure 1</xref>). It is speculated that this trend is explained by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0887403412447809"><italic>Atkins v. Virginia</italic> (2002)</xref>. The Supreme Court ruled on the implications of mental health issues in death penalty proceedings in 2002. It would have taken several years for attorneys and courts to incorporate the <italic>Atkins</italic> ruling into their practices, and it is logical to assume that the full effect of <italic>Atkins</italic> manifested itself in this uptick in cases citing FASDs in post-2005 cases.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0887403412447809" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Cases referencing FASDs by year.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0887403412447809-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>Among the 108 substantive cases, slightly less than one-half (<italic>n</italic> = 50) of the cases appeared at the federal appellate level. Of those, one-half arose in the Eighth (<italic>n</italic> = 12) and Ninth (<italic>n</italic> = 13) United States Circuit Courts of Appeals. The United States District Court in Texas district courts received evidence of FASDs more often than any other state (<italic>n</italic> = 17), followed by Arizona (<italic>n</italic> = 11), South Dakota (<italic>n</italic> = 10), California (<italic>n</italic> = 9), Florida (<italic>n</italic> = 8), and Washington (<italic>n</italic> = 7). Overall, the United States Circuit Court for the Ninth Circuit entertained the most cases involving FASDs, with a total of 37 combined cases from the district and appellate levels. No FASD cases that met the search criteria arose at the federal appellate level in the United States Courts of Appeals for the First, Second, or Sixth Circuits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0887403412447809">Figure 2</xref>). The most thorough, and arguably the most punitive analysis of FASD evidence can be found in Texas jurisprudence. Overall, defendants who claimed that they had FASDs were successful in 32% of their claims for related relief. Defendants were not successful in excluding any victim/witness testimony on the basis that the victim/witness lacked competency to testify, but that the credibility, or relative value, of victim/witnesses’ testimony was questioned in three of the nine cases.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0887403412447809" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Division of cases among federal courts.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0887403412447809-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In light of the confusion within the clinical community, it is not surprising that there is no consensus among the federal courts on the meaning or significance of an FASD diagnosis (SAMHSA, 2001).However, all courts in this study accepted FASD evidence as relevant. No court identified through this research excluded evidence of FASD on the grounds that it was not probative of the matter raised. The courts received every offer of FASD evidence; they disagreed on the persuasive value and effect of such evidence, but they all entertained the evidence at some level.</p>
<p>None of the courts in this study excluded FASD evidence outright for any reason, but the courts are trending towards weightier consideration of FASD evidence. The shift towards more comprehensive analysis of FASD evidence appears to begin in 2002, the same year that the United States Supreme Court’s decided <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0887403412447809"><italic>Atkins v. Virginia</italic> (2002)</xref>. There is no evidence of a direct, causal relationship between the <italic>Atkins</italic> decision and the handling of FASD evidence among lower courts, but the date it notable and worthy of consideration for future research, Additionally, in more recent years, the courts seemed to afford counsel a great deal of latitude to develop FASD evidence, with one court allowing defense counsel to subpoena otherwise sealed adoption records to establish that defendant’s birth mother drank alcohol during her pregnancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0887403412447809"><italic>Keen v. Hancock County Job and Family Services</italic>, 2008</xref>). However, in the most recent cases, the courts appear to be trending once again towards stricter interpretations of FASD evidence with respect to both culpability and sentencing.</p>
<p>Very few courts analyzed FASD evidence directly or independently of other evidence. Instead, the majority of the courts considered FASD evidence in conjunction with evidence of other mental health issues. Thus, the discrete significance of FASD diagnoses was difficult to parse from the accompanying evidence. Most courts lumped the diagnoses with a myriad other issues and diagnoses, finding that the aggregated mental health evidence was relevant to a defendant’s mental state. Nonetheless, no court excluded evidence of FASDs as irrelevant, and no court dismissed claims that were brought in partial reliance on FASD for lack of admissibility.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section4-0887403412447809">
<title>Arrest and Confession</title>
<p>As described above, a great deal of literature suggests that FASD evidence should play a significant role in matters relating to arrest and confession; nevertheless, only seven of the federal cases address FASDs in the context of arrest, confession and related procedures. Instead, most of the courts spoke more broadly of “mental capacity” or “diminished capacity.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0887403412447809">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>In the four older cases that addressed arrest or confession directly, the courts deemed FASD sufferers’ confessions knowing and voluntary, and thus admissible, even though the defense provided evidence that the defendant had one or more mental impairments related to prenatal alcohol exposure. However, the expert testimony in those early cases lacked clinical support. In one case, the expert witness called by the defense equated FASD impairments to the impairments that may arise from “a high fever” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0887403412447809"><italic>United Sates v. Aripa</italic>, 1997</xref>). Obviously, the court did not find such testimony compelling.</p>
<p>Similar results were found among older cases in which the defense requested competency hearings for purposes of determining whether the defendant was competent at the time he/she was arrested and/or confessed. In those cases, the courts refused to hold competency hearings because prenatal toxic exposure and possible FASDs were not adequate grounds for questioning the defendant’s competency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0887403412447809">Castro, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412447809"><italic>Dunn v. Johnson</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0887403412447809"><italic>Mooring v. Lewis</italic>, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>The courts in the three more recent cases considered FASD evidence more fully but, nevertheless, found confessions by FASD sufferers to be voluntary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0887403412447809"><italic>Heynard v. Alabama</italic>, 2006</xref>; the <italic>Heynard</italic> court found that the FASD sufferer was intelligent enough to understand his <italic>Miranda</italic> rights and that he had passed all required intelligence tests). These courts looked to the totality of the mental health evidence, not just the FASD, to assess voluntariness of confessions or knowing waiver of <italic>Miranda</italic> rights. In these cases, FASD was one of many mental health issues presented to the court, and it appears that FASD was one of the many factors on which the courts relied to find possible diminished capacity (<italic>Jacobs v. Horn</italic>, 2005; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0887403412447809"><italic>Schriro v. Landrigan</italic>, 2007</xref>, dissenting opinion, “it is clearly possible—even likely—that evidence of his neurological disorder, fetal alcohol syndrome, and abusive upbringing would have influenced the sentencing judge’s assessment of his moral blameworthiness”). In this case, the defendant’s motion was denied, but the FASD evidence was given much fuller analysis than in prior cases.</p>
<p>With that said, it should be noted that only a handful of the federal cases in this study spoke to <italic>Miranda</italic> or other Fourth Amendment issues. The authors’ preliminary investigation suggests that there is more data on judicial treatment of these issues in state judicial opinions (<italic>see, for example</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0887403412447809"><italic>Louisiana v. Holmes</italic>, 2008</xref>). Those cases are beyond the scope of this study, but they warrant further exploration in order to garner a fuller understanding the interactions among FASDs and events surrounding arrest and confession.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0887403412447809">
<title>Mental Capacity</title>
<p>Almost all of the cases studied considered FASD in relation to broader claims for mental incapacity or diminished capacity. The takeaway lessons from the cases are not encouraging for those advocating for special treatment of FASD under theories of diminished capacity. Generally, the federal case law indicates that, while FASD evidence may be relevant to capacity claims, it usually is not adequate to be successful in asserting the claim. For example, the FASD diagnosis, without more, will not negate criminal intent. The majority of courts reached this conclusion, but the rationales articulated by the courts were quite diverse. The arguments may be classified into three categories: the “it is so common that it cannot be sufficient evidence” school; the “propensity is not enough” school; and “the threshold IQ” school.</p>
<p>The first group of cases appears to say that, because FASDs are prevalent among criminal defendants, FASDs are not adequate evidence of mental incapacity. None of the courts explained their rationale for drawing an inferential relationship between prevalence of FASDs and whether the disabilities cause sufferers to be insane or to have diminished capacity. For example, in the Eighth Circuit, the standard insanity jury instruction provides that “[a] defendant was insane if, at the time of the alleged criminal conduct, as a result of a severe mental disease or defect, [he] . . . was unable to appreciate the nature and quality of the wrongfulness of [his] acts.” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0887403412447809"><italic>Elk v. United States</italic>, 2010</xref>). This jury instruction is not unusual, and no one contested its applicability in <italic>Elk</italic>. What is odd, however, is that the court appears to find that, because FASDs are prevalent among criminal defendants, FASDs are not enough to satisfy the standards for giving the insanity jury instruction. “The mental disease and/or defects which defendant alleges that he suffers from are, unfortunately, not uncommon among defendants who appear before this Court. The Court would not have given this instruction. As a result, the Court finds that petitioner was not prejudiced by any lack of investigation into his alleged mental defects” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0887403412447809"><italic>Elk</italic>, 2010</xref>). The court devalues the FASD evidence using an aberrant logical syllogism. A similar argument about a different mental health condition would be absurd: If schizophrenia were prevalent within a jurisdiction, would that prevalence diminish the medical fact that schizophrenia causes diminished capacity?</p>
<p>Another vein of case law indicates that propensity evidence may not be sufficient to establish mental incapacity or diminished capacity (but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0887403412447809"><italic>Bond v. Beard</italic>, 2008</xref>). In other words, it is usually not enough to show that the defendant has an FASD and therefore is unlikely to understand the impact of his conduct. Advocates maintain that a person who does not have the cognitive capacity to govern their own behavior should be presumed to lack the requisite mental capacity to be held accountable for their actions. However, the majority of the courts have not adopted this perspective. Instead, they appear to follow a stricter construction of the insanity/diminished capacity defenses to require that the defendants show that they lacked impulse control, or exhibited aberrant rashness, at the time of the commission of the crime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0887403412447809"><italic>Poyson v. Ryan</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0887403412447809"><italic>Twitty v. United States</italic>, 2010</xref>). At least one recent case bucks this trend and finds that evidence of FASDs and other problems were sufficient to establish that the defendant most likely lacked the ability to form criminal intent at the time he committed murder. In that case, the burden was on the prosecution to show that, despite general mental incapacity, the defendant possessed adequate criminal intent at the time he murdered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0887403412447809"><italic>Bond v. Beard</italic> (2008)</xref>, finding that “the record contains nothing suggesting that he did not suffer from these problems at the time he shot [the victim] . . . [his] capacity to appreciate the criminal nature of his conduct and to conform it to the requirements of the law was substantially impaired at the time he shot [the victim]”).</p>
<p>Applying statutorily established standards for defining mental retardation, several of the courts found that defendants did not carry their burden of proof to establish mental retardation if they did not establish that the defendant’s tested intelligence was below a statutorily established threshold and/or that the defendant had sufficiently poor adaptive functioning. Regardless of the degree to which the defendant’s functioning fell below accepted standards of behavior, the defendants did not prevail unless they met the statutory standard (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0887403412447809"><italic>Carroll v. Secretary</italic>, 2009</xref>). In summary, these courts found that <italic>functional</italic> mental retardation is not <italic>actual</italic> mental retardation. This position should not be surprising in light of court’s general admonition to follow state law as articulated by legislatures, but it does suggest that the emerging clinical definition for FASDs and the existing statutory definitions of mental retardation are not compatible.</p>
<p>A fourth category of cases found that proffers of FASD evidence, in combination with other evidence, would have been sufficient to support claims for diminished capacity, if it had been presented properly. In other words, the courts did not find that FASDs caused persons to have diminished capacity, but they did find that the attorneys’ failure to pursue evidence of FASDs was a sufficient oversight to warrant a new hearing on diminished capacity claims. This group of courts came close to finding that FASDs are sufficient foundation for establishing diminished capacity, but no court made this express ruling on the basis of FASD alone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0887403412447809"><italic>Lambert v. Blodgett</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0887403412447809"><italic>Bond v. Beard</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0887403412447809"><italic>United States v. Keeler</italic>, 2007</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0887403412447809">
<title><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0887403412447809"><italic>Atkins v. Virginia</italic> (2002)</xref> and the Death Penalty</title>
<p>Several arguments founded in FASD evidence were successful in setting aside a death sentence under <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0887403412447809"><italic>Atkins v. Virginia</italic> (2002)</xref>. While most claims for mental incapacity failed to defeat the element of criminal intent, a plurality of efforts to set aside the death penalty due to FASD-related claims for diminished capacity have succeeded. Prior to <italic>Atkins</italic>, relatively little attention was paid to FASD evidence in relation to claims for death penalty mitigation, with only 2 cases arising prior to 2006. Shortly after <italic>Atkins</italic> was decided, the federal courts began to entertain more evidence of FASDs in relation to death penalty issues (<italic>n</italic> = 17), and several found that FASD evidence, in conjunction with other mental health evidence, was persuasive and sufficient to escape the death penalty (<italic>n</italic> = 6).</p>
<p>Expert testimony that FASDs caused the defendant to be mentally impaired often were sufficient under the “significant limitations in intellectual functioning” element of the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0887403412447809"><italic>Atkins v. Virginia</italic> (2002)</xref> definition of mental retardation. One line of cases appears to open the door to an expansion of the definition of mental retardation under <italic>Atkins</italic> for any condition that substantially impedes intellectual function, regardless of the petitioners’ tested intelligence (Hearn, 2008). On the other hand, another line of cases, best exemplified by the opinion from the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0887403412447809"><italic>Trevino v. Thaler</italic> (2010)</xref> court, indicates that FASD evidence sometimes may be more prejudicial than beneficial at sentencing.</p>
<p>Many courts have considered FASD as one factor among many when assessing mitigation or death penalty eligibility, but the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0887403412447809"><italic>Trevino v. Thaler</italic> (2010)</xref> court is the only one captured in this study that isolates FASD and defines its relative evidentiary value:<disp-quote>
<p>Petitioner has presented this Court with no fact-specific allegations, much less any evidence, showing either (1) there is a developing national consensus among legislative bodies rejecting the efficacy of execution for capital murderers who suffer from fetal alcohol syndrome; (2) offenders who suffer from fetal alcohol syndrome, as a group, necessarily possess diminished capacities to understand and process information, communicate, abstract from mistakes and learn from experience, engage in logical reasoning, control their impulses, and understand the reactions of others; or (3) offenders who suffer from fetal alcohol syndrome necessarily face the same or similar increased risk of death penalty will be imposed in spite of factors that may have called for less severe penalties as do mentally retarded offenders. In short, petitioner has not presented this Court with any evidence establishing an individual suffering from fetal alcohol syndrome or fetal alcohol effects necessarily suffers the same type of debilitating and mitigation effects as an individual who suffers from mental retardation. While fetal alcohol syndrome is often associated with mental retardation, there is no evidence before this Court establishing an equivalency between fetal alcohol syndrome and mental retardation in terms of the inability of an individual suffering fetal alcohol syndrome to recognize the “wrongness” of his or her own conduct, learn from his or her mistakes, or confirm his or her conduct to societal norms. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0887403412447809"><italic>Trevino v. Thaler</italic>, 2010</xref>)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>While <italic>Trevino</italic> is the only court to articulate this position so comprehensively, the language is consistent with the general approach and attitude of other cases from the past two years.</p>
<p>FASD evidence received mixed treatment in relation to sentence mitigation overall. Defendants initially were successful in claims for mitigation, but the courts appear to be trending towards less favorable treatment of FASD evidence. In fact, a few courts ruled that evidence that a defendant suffered from FASDs was an aggravating circumstance, warranting a stiffer sentence than someone without FASDs would have received (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0887403412447809"><italic>United States v. McQuade</italic>, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Given this trend among the courts, it is clear that FASD evidence should be deployed with caution, lest it contribute to the opposite result of that sought by the moving party. Evidence of FASDS and related disabilities traditionally were offered into evidence to mitigate a sentence or argue for therapeutic intervention over incarceration. The more recent decisions in this study indicate that the courts are trending towards a different interpretation of FASD evidence offered at sentencing. It is being received, not as mitigation, but as an aggravating circumstance, warranting increased sentence lengths or more restrictive placement.</p>
<p>The courts showed consensus with regard to how to treat victim/witnesses who suffer from FASDs. All victims who suffered from FASDs were found to be “vulnerable victims” under the standards for aggravating circumstances that allow juries to deviate from sentencing guidelines in order to impose harsher sentences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0887403412447809"><italic>United States v. Janis</italic>, 1995</xref>). The courts also were unanimous in the manner in which they handled motions to disqualify victim/witnesses who suffered from FASDs (<italic>n</italic> = 11). All of the courts that considered this issue allowed FASD sufferers’ to testify despite defense objections that they were incompetent due to their disabilities (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0887403412447809"><italic>Ault v. Waid</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>In the victim/witness cases, generally the courts found that FASD evidence was relevant to credibility, not competency (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0887403412447809"><italic>United States v. Butterfly</italic>, 1999</xref>). It should be noted that in all of these cases, the defense was attacking the competency of the victim/witness to testify concerning violence committed against him/her. The decision-makers’ desire to have the victim heard may have outweighed competency concerns. These victims were permitted to testify as fully competent witnesses despite their youth and FASD-related disabilities. Moreover, the courts found that they should be given wide latitude in the format of their testimony and should receive procedural protections such as remote testimony via closed circuit television (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0887403412447809"><italic>Devereaux v. Perez</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0887403412447809"><italic>Devereaux v. Abbey</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0887403412447809"><italic>United States v. One Star</italic>, 2006</xref>). Interestingly, the two courts that considered rape allegations by victims who suffered from FASDs found that the victims were not competent to consent to sexual relations in part due to their disabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0887403412447809"><italic>Schuler v. Hudson</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0887403412447809"><italic>Turner v. Rapelje</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0887403412447809">
<title>Ineffective Assistance of Counsel</title>
<p>Claims for ineffective assistance of counsel (IAC) permeated many of the cases in this study. Of the 39 cases in which FASD evidence was a material component to an IAC claim, only 13 defendants prevailed (33%). In an additional ten cases, the courts found that the attorneys’ failure to develop FASD evidence may have been ineffective, but that defendants did not suffer prejudice as a result of that ineffective assistance (26%). In other words, the attorney’s errors were harmless. Notably, all of the successful IAC claims, and six of the 10 “harmless error “ cases arose in the 2000s, suggesting an increasing tendency among the courts to find that attorneys must pursue FASD evidence.</p>
<p>With that said, the dicta surrounding the “harmless error” findings are illuminating. In finding that failure to develop FASD evidence was not prejudicial, several recent courts went further. These courts determined that attorneys’ failure to develop FASD evidence was a smart strategic choice because of the “double-edged” nature of the FASD evidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0887403412447809"><italic>Vasquez v. Thaler</italic>, 2010</xref>). Beginning in the late 2000s, the courts tended to find that “[e]vidence of such neurological conditions, even if supported, is double-edged. Evidence of brain abnormalities can just as easily show that the defendant is a future threat to others because he has poor impulse control and an inability to learn from his mistakes” (<italic>Manning v. Epps</italic>, 2009).</p>
<p>In perhaps the starkest case studied, the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0887403412447809"><italic>Trevino v. Thaler</italic> (2010)</xref> court found that the attorney’s failure to introduce FASD actually was a strategic success because “evidence showing petitioner’s virtually lifelong criminal history, Fetal Alcohol Syndrome, long history of alcohol and narcotics abuse, as well as petitioner’s abused and neglected childhood, would likely have solidified the jury’s affirmative answer to the first capital sentencing special issue, i.e., the future dangerousness special issue” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0887403412447809"><italic>Trevino v. Thaler</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0887403412447809" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>No firm conclusions can yet be drawn on the role FASD diagnoses play in judicial proceedings. In light of the lack of diagnostic consensus in the clinical community and the federal court system’s inconsistent treatment of FASD evidence, practitioners and advocates must continue to navigate their way dimly through the morass of laws and standards. On the one hand, the evidence shows that awareness has increased over the past two decades and that courts consistently and increasingly are accepting evidence of FASDs as relevant to several elements of civil and criminal claims. On the other hand, it appears that the courts recently are trending towards drawing adverse inferences from FASD evidence and towards considering that evidence as enhancement evidence during sentencing.</p>
<p>To move forward, more must be done. An initial solution is two-fold. The clinical community must move the research on FASDs forward rapidly and with consensus on the appropriate diagnostic standards. Thus far, there has been much disagreement and discourse within the diagnostic community on how to diagnose FASDs. Better science is a necessary prerequisite to better policy, so criminal justice practitioners and advocates should call upon the research community to do more to develop diagnostic consistency. Next, the legal system must move from its inconsistent treatment of FASDs in the courtroom. In this regard, there is a significant need for education and awareness training amongst justice. In the end, advancing the understanding of FASD-related evidence in the courtroom serves all interested communities. The medical community remains true to its Hippocratic Oath, serving both the patient and the community writ large. The legal community moves towards its ideal of fair and equal treatment for all under the law. Sufferers of FASDs benefit from more appropriate treatment, under the law, at sentencing, and in rehabilitation programming. Finally, at a different level of abstraction, society benefits from a more carefully tailored and responsive justice system.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label><p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><label>Funding</label><p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<notes><fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0887403412447809">
<label>1.</label>
<p>These disabilities include, but are not limited to attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), conduct disorders, memory problems, difficulties with abstract thought.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0887403412447809">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Please see below for the broader discussion of capacity issues.</p></fn>
</fn-group></notes>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Anne S. Douds</bold> is Lecturer in Criminal Justice for the Department of Public Affairs at Penn State- Harrisburg, and she serves as Special Litigation Counsel for constitutional and civil rights issues for Federal &amp; Hasson, LLP.</p>
<p><bold>Holly R. Stevens</bold> recently joined the Children’s Law Center in Washington, DC as their Evaluation and Strategic Learning Specialist. Previously, she has served as a consultant at Justice Systems Innovation and as an assistant research professor at George Mason University. She is also a doctoral candidate in George Mason University’s Criminology, Law and Society program.</p>
<p><bold>William E. Sumner</bold> earned his law degree from Duke University, with honors. He now serves as the Chief Executive Officer of Redemption After Prison, a Georgia non-profit organization that provides reintegration training and education for adult men who have served time in federal and state prisons.</p></bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Fetal alcohol syndrome: A cautionary note</article-title>. <source>Current Pharmaceutical Design</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1521</fpage>-<lpage>1529</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bittner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buttar</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daston</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname> . . . Ploifkam</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Statement of the Public Affairs Committee of the Teratology Society on the Fetal Alcohol Syndrome</article-title>. <source>Teratology</source>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>344</fpage>-<lpage>347</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Astley</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Diagnostic guide for fetal alcohol spectrum disorders: The 4-digit diagnostic code</source>. <publisher-loc>Seattle</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Washington</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>Atkins v. Virginia</collab>, 536 U.S. 304 (<year>2002</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<source>Ault v. Waid</source>, 654 F.Supp. 2d 465 (<year>2009</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Delaney-Black</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Covington</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ager</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>James</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hannigan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sokol</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Prenatal exposure to binge drinking and cognitive and behavioral outcomes at age 7 years</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology</source>, <volume>191</volume>, <fpage>1037</fpage>-<lpage>1043</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chudley</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The challenge of Fetal Alcohol Syndrome in adult offender populations</article-title>. <source>Forum on Corrections Research</source>, <volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burrill</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duwyn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Fetal alcohol syndrome: Implications for correctional service</article-title>. <source>Report to Research Branch, Correctional Services Canada</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<source>Bond v. Beard</source>, 539 F.3d 256 (<year>2008</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bracken</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Canada’s aboriginal people, fetal alcohol syndrome, and the criminal justice system</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.olc.edu/~jolson/Socialwork/OnlineLibrary/Bracken%20(2008)%20Canada’s%20aboriginal%20people,%20fetal%20alcohol%20syndrome%20and%20the%20criminal%20justice%20system.pdf">http://www.olc.edu/~jolson/Socialwork/OnlineLibrary/Bracken%20(2008)%20Canada’s%20aboriginal%20people,%20fetal%20alcohol%20syndrome%20and%20the%20criminal%20justice%20system.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burd</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Selfridge</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klug</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bakko</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Fetal alcohol syndrome in the United States Corrections System</article-title>. <source>Addiction Biology</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>169</fpage>-<lpage>176</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burd</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Odendaal</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Ethanol and the placenta: A review</article-title>. <source>Journal of Maternal-Fetal &amp; Neonatal Medicine</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>361</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burd</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klug</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kerbeshian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martsolf</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Diagnosis of fetal alcohol spectrum disorders: a validity study of the fetal alcohol syndrome checklist</article-title>. <source>Alcohol</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>605</fpage>-<lpage>614</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Capron</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>At law: Fetal alcohol and felony</article-title>. <source>The Hastings Center Report</source>, <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>28</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carmichael Olson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Streissguth</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bookstein</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Theide</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Association of prenatal alcohol exposure with behavioral and learning problems in early adolescence</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>1187</fpage>-<lpage>1194</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Carroll v. Secretary</source>, et al., 574 F.3d 1354 (<year>2009</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Castro v. Oklahoma</source>, 71 F.3d 1502 (<year>1998</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>Fetal alcohol spectrum disorders</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/Features/FASD/?s_cid=tw_cdc828">http://www.cdc.gov/Features/FASD/?s_cid=tw_cdc828</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chartrand</surname><given-names>L.N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forbes-Chilbeck</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The sentencing of offenders with fetal alcohol syndrome</article-title>. <source>Health Law Journal</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chudley</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conry</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loock</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosales</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Fetal alcohol spectrum disorder: Canadian guidelines for diagnosis</article-title>. <source>Canadian Medical Association Journal</source>, <volume>172</volume>(<supplement>Suppl. 5</supplement>), <fpage>S1</fpage>-<lpage>S22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Church</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaltenbach</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Hearing, speech, language, vestibular disorders in the fetal alcohol syndrome: A literature review</article-title>. <source>Alcoholism, Clinical and Experimental Research</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>495</fpage>-<lpage>412</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clare</surname><given-names>I. C. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gudjonsson</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Interrogative suggestibility, confabulation, and acquiescence in people with mild learning disabilities (mental handicap): implications for reliability during police interrogation</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>-<lpage>301</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>I. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Platzman</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Falek</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Effects of prenatal alcohol exposure at school age: Physical and cognitive development</article-title>. <source>Neurotoxicology and Teratology</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>357</fpage>-<lpage>367</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Conry</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fast</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Fetal alcohol syndrome and the criminal justice system</source>. <publisher-loc>Vancouver, BC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fetal Alcohol Syndrome Resource Society</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Conry</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Characteristics of youth with FASD on adjudicated probation orders</source>. Final report to the Department of Justice Canada and British Columbia Ministry of Children and Family Development.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Devereaux v. Abbey</source>, 263 F.3d 1070 (<year>2001</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Devereaux v. Perez</source>, 218 F.3d 1045 (<year>2000</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>D’Onofrio</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Hulle</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waldman</surname><given-names>I. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rathouz</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lahey</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Causal inferences regarding prenatal alcohol exposure and childhood externalizing problems</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>1296</fpage>-<lpage>1304</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The sentencing response to defendants with foetal alcohol spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source>Criminal Law Journal</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>239</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Dunn v. Johnson</source>, 162 F.3d 302 (<year>1998</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Elk v. United States</source>, 2010 U.S. Dist . LEXIS 12672 (<year>2010</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fast</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conry</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The challenge of fetal alcohol syndrome in the criminal legal system</article-title>. <source>Addiction Biology</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>161</fpage>-<lpage>166</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fast</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conry</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Fetal alcohol spectrum disorders and the criminal justice system</article-title>. <source>Developmental Disabilities Research Reviews</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>250</fpage>-<lpage>257</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldschmidt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stoffwer</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Geva</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Prenatal alcohol exposure and academic achievement at age six:</article-title> <source>A nonlinear fit. Alcoholism: Clinical and Experimental Research</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>763</fpage>-<lpage>770</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Heynard v. McDonough</source>, 459 F.3d 1217 (<year>2006</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Platzman</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Prenatal alcohol exposure and ability, academic achievement, and school functioning in adolescence: A longitudinal follow-up</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pediatric Psychology</source>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>116</fpage>-<lpage>126</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raine</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Obstetric complications and aggression</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Encyclopedia on early childhood development</source> [online]. <publisher-loc>Montreal, Quebec, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Centre of Excellence for Early Childhood Development. Retrieved from</publisher-name>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.child-encyclopedia.com/documents/Ishikawa-RaineANGxp.pdf">http://www.child-encyclopedia.com/documents/Ishikawa-RaineANGxp.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Jacobs v. Horn</source>, 129 F.Supp. 390 (<year>2001</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<source>Keen v. Hancock County Job and Family Svcs.</source>, 581 F.Supp. 893 (<year>2008</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Streissguth</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Effects of prenatal alcohol exposure on social behavior in humans and other species</article-title>. <source>Neurotoxicology and Teratology</source>, <volume>22</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>143</fpage>-<lpage>149</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kodituwakku</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Defining the behavioral phenotype in children with fetal alcohol spectrum disorders: A review</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>192</fpage>-<lpage>201</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koren</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roifman</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nulman</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Hypothetical framework: FASD and criminality—Causation or association? The limits of evidence-based knowledge</article-title>. <source>Journal of Fetal Alcohol Syndrome International</source>, <volume>2</volume>(<issue>e6</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.motherisk.org/JFAS_documents/FASD_Criminality.pdf">http://www.motherisk.org/JFAS_documents/FASD_Criminality.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>LaDue</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Legal issues and FAS</article-title>. <source>The challenge of fetal alcohol syndrome: Overcoming secondary disabilities</source>. <publisher-loc>Seattle</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Washington Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Lambert v. Blodgett</source>, 248 F.Supp. 2d 988 (<year>2003</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<source>Louisiana v. Holmes</source>, <year>2008</year></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Corley</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Examining delinquency in adolescents differentially prenatally exposed to alcohol: the role of proximal and distal risk factors</article-title>. <source>Journal of Studies on Alcohol and Drugs</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>678</fpage>-<lpage>686</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schonfeld</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Teratogenic effects of alcohol on brain and behavior</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Institute on Alcohol and Alcoholism, National Institutes of Health</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Delis</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Verbal learning and memory in children with fetal alcohol syndrome</article-title>. <source>Alcoholism: Clinical and Experimental Research</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>810</fpage>-<lpage>816</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Fetal alcohol spectrum disorder (FASD): a need for closer examination by the criminal justice system</article-title>. <source>Criminal Reports</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Mooring v. Lewis</source>, 2003 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 4827 (<year>2003</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nanson</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hiscock</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Attention deficits in children exposed to alcohol prenatally</article-title>. <source>Canadian Medical Association Journal</source>, <volume>152</volume>, <fpage>1071</fpage>-<lpage>1076</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peadon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Distinguishing between attention-deficit hyperactivity and fetal alcohol spectrum disorders in children: clinical guidelines</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>-<lpage>515</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Perske</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Thoughts on the police interrogation of individuals with mental retardation</article-title>. <source>Mental Retardation</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>377</fpage>-<lpage>380</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Poyson v. Ryan</source>, 683 F.Supp. 2d 956 (<year>2010</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Executive Functioning and Working Memory in Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorder</article-title>. <source>Alcoholism: Clinical and Experimental Research</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1359</fpage>-<lpage>1367</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sowell</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Teratogenic effect of alcohol: a decade of brain imaging</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Medical Genetics</source>, <volume>127C</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roebuck</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Prenatal alcohol exposure again linked to delinquency, psychiatric woes</article-title>. <source>Alcoholism: Clinical and Experimental Research</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1070</fpage>-<lpage>1076</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Sayal</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heron</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alati</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edmond</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Binge pattern of alcohol consumption during pregnancy and childhood mental health outcomes: Longitudinal population-based study</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>123</volume>, <fpage>e289</fpage>-<lpage>e296</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Schriro v. Landrigan</source>, 550 U.S. 465 (<year>2007</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Schuler v. Hudson</source>, 2009 U.S. LEXIS 102737 (<year>2009</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sood</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Delaney-Black</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Covington</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nordstrom-Klee</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ager</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Templin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname> . . . Sokol</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Prenatal alcohol exposure and childhood behavior at age 6 to 7 years: I. Dose-response effect</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>108</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>e34</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steinhausen</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spohr</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Long-term psychopathological and cognitive outcome of children with fetal alcohol syndrome</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>990</fpage>-<lpage>994</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Stratton</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Battaglia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>1996</year>). <source>Fetal alcohol syndrome: Diagnosis, epidemiology, prevention, and treatment</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>. <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Streissguth</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koganm</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Understanding the occurrence of secondary disabilities in clients with fetal alcohol syndrome (FAS) and Fetal alcohol effects (FAE), Final Report to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)</source> (Tech. Rep. No. 96 06). <publisher-loc>Seattle</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Washington, Fetal Alcohol and Drug Unit</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Streissguth</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bookstein</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Malley</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Risk factors for adverse life outcomes in fetal alcohol syndrome and fetal alcohol effects</article-title>. <source>Journal of Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>228</fpage>-<lpage>238</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>Strickland v. Washington</collab>, 466 U.S. 688 (<year>1984</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>The Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration (SAMHSA)</collab>. (<year>2006</year>). <source>Fetal alcohol spectrum disorders and the criminal justice system</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAMHSA, United States Department of Health and Human Services</publisher-name>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fasdcenter.samhsa.gov/documents/WYNK_Criminal_Justice5.pdf">http://www.fasdcenter.samhsa.gov/documents/WYNK_Criminal_Justice5.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Comparison of social abilities of children with fetal alcohol syndrome to those of children with similar IQ scores and normal controls</article-title>. <source>Alcoholism: Clinical and Experimental Research</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>528</fpage>-<lpage>533</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Trevino v. Thaler</source>, 678 F.Supp. 2d 445 (<year>2010</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Turner v. Rapelje</source>, 2010 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 2631 (<year>2010</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Twitty v. United States</source>, 2010 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 138648 (<year>2010</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>United Sates v. Aripa</source>, 132 F.3d 40 (<year>1997</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>United States v. Butterfly</source>, 1999 U.S. App. LEXIS 9784 (<year>1999</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<source>United States v. Janis</source>, 71 F.3d 308 (<year>1995</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>United States v. Keeler</source>, <year>2007</year> U.S. Dist LESXIS <year>1739</year> (<year>2007</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<source>United States v. McQuade</source>, 403 F.3d 717 (<year>2005</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<source>United States v. One Star</source>, 4654 F.3d 828 (<year>2006</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal"><source>Vasquez v. Thaler</source>, 2010 U.S. App. LEXIS 16824 (<year>2010</year>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sliwowska</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hellemans</surname><given-names>K. C. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Prenatal alcohol exposure: foetal programming, the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis and sex differences in outcome</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroendocrinology</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>470</fpage>-<lpage>488</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-0887403412447809">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Willford</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leech</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Moderate prenatal alcohol exposure and cognitive status of children at age 10</article-title>. <source>Alcoholism: Clinical and Experimental Research</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>1051</fpage>-<lpage>1059</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>