<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RCB</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sprcb</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rehabil Couns Bull</journal-id>
<journal-title>Rehabilitation Counseling Bulletin</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0034-3552</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1538-4853</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0034355213478928</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0034355213478928</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Continuing Education</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Continuing Education Questions</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>56</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>193</fpage>
<lpage>195</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Hammill Institute on Disabilities 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Hammill Institute on Disabilities</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0034355213478928">
<title>Questions relating to Marini (2013)</title>
<list id="list1-0034355213478928" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The majority of previous research regarding attitudes toward having a relationship with someone with a disability has typically shown that:<list id="list2-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Persons without a disability would rather be friends or coworkers as opposed to date or marry someone with a disability</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Persons without a disability generally have the same attitudes regarding dating someone with a disability as they do being a coworker</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Persons without a disability prefer to date or marry someone with a psychiatric disability over someone with a physical disability</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Persons without a disability do not have favorable attitudes for any type of relationship (e.g., acquaintance, friendship) with someone with a disability</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The authors of the present study found that the majority of previous research regarding having a relationship with someone with a disability is flawed because:<list id="list3-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Of the stranger affect</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The disability is made the salient and single identifying feature of the individual</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The studies are not realistic or resemble how people make partner decisions in real life</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>All of the above</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>None of the above</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Present study findings mirrored similar findings from previous studies in that:<list id="list4-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Males most often have more favorable attitudes toward dating or marrying someone with a disability</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Females most often have more favorable attitudes toward dating or marrying someone with a disability</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Males and females equally share similar attitudes toward dating or marrying someone with a disability</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Hispanic students have more favorable attitudes toward dating or marrying a wheelchair user</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>In the present study, the authors found that for those participants who were not interested in having a dating or marrying relationship with a wheelchair user, the primary reasons were:<list id="list5-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>The partner with a disability would be sick often, he or she would be depressed often, and would likely be unemployed</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>It would be socially awkward to be seen with a partner with a disability, he or she would not be able to do anything for, and he or she would be unable to perform sexually</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The partner with a disability would be sick often, would be unable to perform or satisfy a partner sexually, and would usually be angry over their situation</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The partner with a disability would be sick often, it would be socially awkward to be with him or her, and he or she would likely be unable to perform sexually</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The findings in the present study suggest that:<list id="list6-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Knowing or having a past relationship with someone with a disability often leads to having a more favorable attitude toward dating or marrying someone with a disability</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Knowing or having a past relationship with someone with a disability often leads to less favorable attitudes toward dating or marrying someone with a disability</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Knowing someone with a disability makes no difference in attitudes toward dating or marriage compared with those who do not have a past relationship</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Rehabilitation counselors often commit ethical violations because of having a sexual relationship with a client with a disability</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0034355213478928">
<title>Questions relating to Fleming et al. (2013)</title>
<list id="list7-0034355213478928" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Evidence-based practice can serve to assist rehabilitation counselors and practitioners in:<list id="list8-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Serving more clients, because they will not need to develop individual approaches with each person</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Always providing the right service, because they know it will be effective</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Not having to spend as much money</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Providing validated interventions to ensure clients are getting the best possible services</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Which of the following was NOT discussed as a barrier to adopting evidence-based practice in rehabilitation counseling?<list id="list9-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Ethical issues</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Complex and individualized nature of rehabilitation services</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lack of interest</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Varied practice settings</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The research team reviewed published studies and categorized them according to theme. Which of the following was not included?<list id="list10-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Interagency collaboration</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Empowerment and customer self-concept</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Essential elements of service delivery</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Training needs of rehabilitation counselors</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>In the article’s discussion of counselor preparation, initial evidence was presented in support of which of the following statements?<list id="list11-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Master’s-level rehabilitation counselors achieved better outcomes with clients with severe disabilities than other counselors within the first 6 years of practice</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Master’s-level counselors (rehabilitation or related) achieved better outcomes with clients with severe disabilities within the first 6 years of practice</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Clients working with master’s-level rehabilitation counselors reported higher levels of satisfaction than clients working with other counselors</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Clients working with master’s-level counselors (rehabilitation or related field) reported higher levels of satisfaction than clients working with counselors with less training</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Which of the following was not recommended as a future research direction for rehabilitation?<list id="list12-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Increase the utilization of secondary data to answer questions about service efficacy</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Replicate and expand upon initial findings of service effectiveness</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Proposing and then testing theoretical models as they relate to different topics within disability and rehabilitation services</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Applying both qualitative and quantitative methods to different levels of service provision to analyze current methods of service provision</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0034355213478928">
<title>Questions relating to Barros-Bailey and Saunders (2013)</title>
<list id="list13-0034355213478928" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>In the vocational exploration phase of rehabilitation counseling, the information collected from a labor market survey is typically used to develop a(n):<list id="list14-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Plan</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Placement</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Evaluation</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Assessment</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Labor market survey competencies are required in rehabilitation counseling:<list id="list15-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Job analyses</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Policies and procedures</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Literature</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Credentialing standards</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Labor market survey data are a component of Neulicht et al.’s:<list id="list16-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Labor market analysis</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Transferable skills analysis</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Behavioral search</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Labor market search</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Rehabilitation counselors rate the importance of labor market analysis as:<list id="list17-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Not important to somewhat important</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Not important to extremely important</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Important to extremely important</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Important to somewhat important</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Labor market survey is most commonly used in rehabilitation counseling by those holding the following job title:<list id="list18-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Case Manager</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Rehabilitation Counselor</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Forensic/Expert Witness</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Rehabilitation Consultant</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0034355213478928">
<title>Questions relating to Ipsen et al. (2013)</title>
<list id="list19-0034355213478928" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>What percentage of the clients reported using email to communicate with their counselors?<list id="list20-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>26%</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>39%</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>51%</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>63%</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What percentage of clients felt that email would be an acceptable way to communicate with their counselor?<list id="list21-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>26%</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>39%</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>51%</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>63%</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Which factor(s) were associated with significantly different rates of telecommunication use?<list id="list22-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Age</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Education</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Disability type</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>b and c</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Fifty six clients reported negative experiences using technology to communicate with their counselors. What was the primary or most often described reason for negative experiences?<list id="list23-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Technical difficulties such as dropped calls, lost messages, or poor Internet connections</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Difficulty understanding written instructions</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Counselor not returning phone calls or emails</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lack of access to necessary technology or assistive technology</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What percentage of rural clients was served through an itinerant counseling relationship, where the counselor traveled to a nearby town to deliver face-to-face services to the client?<list id="list24-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>25%</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>36%</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>47%</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>61%</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0034355213478928">
<title>Questions relating to Dong et al. (2013)</title>
<list id="list25-0034355213478928" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The cost of accommodations, urgency of the request, and timing of the request were three differences found related to the nature of accommodation requests. Which of the following is true regarding these differences?<list id="list26-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>In all cases, the employers’ ratings of importance of the items were higher than ratings of employees with disabilities</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>All cases had confidence intervals that were overlapping, so there was no evidence of a difference in ratings</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>In all cases, employers’ ratings on these items were lower than employees with disabilities or service providers’ ratings</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>In all cases, service providers rated these items lower than employees with disabilities and employers</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>All three stakeholder groups believe/agree that:<list id="list27-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>The extent to which accommodations are matched to job requirements is very important</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Employer’s understanding of disabilities and Americans With Disabilities Act (ADA) eligibility is important</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Supportiveness of the employee’s direct supervisor is very important</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>All of the above</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>An emerging pattern of the perception of the importance of the accommodation items among the three stakeholder groups is:<list id="list28-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>A convergence of the perception of the importance of accommodation items between service providers and employers</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>A convergence of the perception of the importance of accommodation items between employees with disabilities and employers</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>A convergence of the perception of the importance of accommodation items among the three groups</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>A convergence of the perception of the importance of accommodation items between service providers and employees with disabilities</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Some employers are more likely to approve reasonable accommodation (RA) requests than others. For employers who are less likely to provide accommodations, they tend to believe:<list id="list29-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>The extent to which the accommodations are matched to job requirements is an extremely important RA consideration</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>An employee’s knowledge of the employers’ RA procedures is less important as a factor in the RA decision-making process</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Coworkers’ perceived fairness of the accommodation is less important as a factor in deciding whether to approve or deny an RA request</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>All of the above</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Which of the following statements is correct in describing employees who are less likely to request accommodations?<list id="list30-0034355213478928" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>They believe “ease of use of accommodation” is less important than employees who were more likely to request</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>They believe “extent to which the accommodations are matched to job requirements” is as important as employees who were more likely to request</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>They believe “employee’s communication skills in requesting accommodations” is less important than employees who were more likely to request.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>None of them is correct</p></list-item></list></p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</body>
</article>