<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spajh</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Hosp Palliat Care</journal-id>
<journal-title>American Journal of Hospice and Palliative Medicine®</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1049-9091</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-2715</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049909111420701</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1049909111420701</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Extinction of Care-Induced Vocalizations by a Desensitization Routine on a Palliative Care Unit</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>RPN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909111420701">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>RN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909111420701">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Deonarain</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>RPN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909111420701">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frank</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>RN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909111420701">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mayers</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>RPN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909111420701">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>Beverley Jean</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909111420701">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1049909111420701"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yuen</surname>
<given-names>Harold</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909111420701">1</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1049909111420701"><label>1</label>The Salvation Army Toronto Grace Health Centre, Toronto, Ontario, Canada</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1049909111420701">Beverley Jean Smith, 650 Church St., Toronto, ON M4Y 2G5, Canada Email: <email>bsmith@torontograce.org</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>29</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>318</fpage>
<lpage>320</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Vocalizations during care occur frequently in patients with dementia, and are not uncommon in the palliative setting. Underlying trigger factors may include pain during movement, fear of being turned, startle reflex, attempts at verbal communication, environmental factors such as cold water, and other possible etiologies. A case of a 92 year old female who screamed and called out during bathing is presented. This patient with comorbid dementia and brain lesions did not respond to pre-event pain medication, and became somnolent due to opioid administration for presumed incident pain. A non-pharmacological approach, with a patient-centered focus rather than task orientation, succeeded in extinguishing the vocalizations after a period of six weeks.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>dementia</kwd>
<kwd>vocalizations</kwd>
<kwd>nursing</kwd>
<kwd>personal care</kwd>
<kwd>fentanyl</kwd>
<kwd>palliative</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<disp-quote>
<p>Granny objected to being bathed, saying that she had bathed the day before and at her time of life she did not see why she had to be pestered with soap and water the way she was. Argument was useless, so she began to fight with the nurses, clawing at them and screaming… Around a large bare spot on her head she had a thin fringe of hair which stood up like a field of ferns. “She has been crying for her wig since she came in”, the other nurse said. She had sympathy and understanding and realized that the little old lady needed more than soap and water and clean bed linen. She needed more than to be loved. She wanted to be respected as a person, and for that she needed to have her wishes respected. She needed such appurtenances as her wig. Dorothy Day, <italic>The Long Loneliness</italic>
</p>
</disp-quote>
<sec id="section1-1049909111420701">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Vocalizations (shouting, crying, and calling out) during routine personal care and bathing are a common occurrence in patients with dementia. Patients in a palliative setting may also exhibit similar vocalizations during care. Underlying trigger factors may include pain during movement, startle reflex, attempts at verbal communication, environmental stressors (such as cold water, bright lighting or loud noise), and other possible etiologies. This form of verbal agitation during care is often difficult to manage and disturbing to family, caregivers, and the surrounding patients. In the past, on our palliative care unit, management of this distress during care has focused on pain relief, as pain appears to be a frequent contributing factor. However, in this case, invasion of privacy or even possible post-traumatic stress appeared to be a significant correlate. Graded desensitization to the care process by nonpharmacological means leads to an extinction of the behavior within weeks.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1049909111420701">
<title>Case Presentation</title>
<p>A 92-year-old female with a history of dementia and a high attenuation mass effect in the frontal horn of the left lateral ventricle was admitted to our palliative care unit from an acute care hospital after being found on the floor of her residence at a local retirement home. There were no other cognitive or mental health correlates noted in the admission assessment other than a history of hoarding in the past. Further magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the head showed bilateral brain lesions of an enhancing multilobulated type. These lesions were asymmetrical in size and located within the heads of the caudate nuclei. She had a prognosis of days to weeks when admitted to our unit.</p>
<p>Nurses found giving any type of care including bathing and diaper changes for incontinence extremely difficult as she would cry or scream with touch, particularly when washing the perineal area. Coincident with the vocalizations, she would become combative and try to prevent care from occurring. Her brother had been designated power of attorney for personal care as a result of her progressive dementia and resultant loss of capacity. He reported that the patient had always been a very private person but was unable to elucidate further etiological or chronological information.</p>
<p>There was an initial question of whether she was in pain, experiencing some form of neuropathic or referred pain, or even whether an opiate hypersensitivity syndrome had developed. However, the use of narcotics was so occasional to rule out the latter.</p>
<p>The possibility of abuse during previous experiences of care was considered a possible etiological factor leading to stress and vocalizations during care. Although difficult to prove when patients have impaired cognition, this possibility is part of the differential diagnosis when considering environmental contributors to vocalizations and resistance to caregivers. However, her care appeared to be exemplary prior to her admission to our facility. There was no evidence of mistreatment at the previous health facilities in which she had lived to suggest abuse.</p>
<p>A putative diagnosis of post-traumatic stress disorder contributing to the vocalization during care was put forward, particularly with respect to her sensitivity to perineal bathing. However, due to the patient’s impaired cognition, a diagnosis of post-traumatic stress disorder, requiring a strict adherence to the <italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</italic> (Fourth Edition [<italic>DSM-IV</italic>]) criteria, could not be made.</p>
<p>Fentanyl sublingually (parenteral formulation), initially 12.5 to 25 mcg and then 50 to 100 mcg, was prescribed 20 minutes prior to care to assist with presumed pain and to allow the daily physical requirements of care. Occasionally, 2.5 mg of midazolam was also used subcutaneously to supplement the fentanyl and reduce anxiety. This ameliorated the vocalizations somewhat but did not remove them.</p>
<p>Nurses then adjusted their interventions with the use of bed baths and the dripping of warm water on the genital area rather than washing the genitalia. Patting the patient dry rather than rubbing was instituted. Nurses gave care in pairs rather than individually. Whenever care was given, a patient-centered approach was used. The patient was kept covered at all times. Talking to the patient in a gentle tone was part of the routine. Prewarnings and explanations of what was to happen next were regularly used. During each episode of care, the nurses used verbal assurances to the patient that she would be safe and requested that the patient open her eyes so she could anticipate and see where she was going when being turned.</p>
<p>Gradually, over the course of 4 to 6 weeks, the need for sublingual fentanyl was reduced and the scheduled fentanyl prior to care was switched to pro re nata (prn). The calling out during care became softer and less frequent. After 9 weeks at our facility, the vocalizations during care ceased entirely. The patient became more responsive to staff, expressing her needs and wants with 1 word answers. She was also able to assist with care by attempting to turn her body toward the bedrails when asked to do so by the nurse.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1049909111420701">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Vocalizations during care are common in both community settings (65%) and nursing homes (range up to 86%).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1049909111420701">1</xref></sup> Bathing appears to be the personal care event most likely to engender behavioral symptoms such as these in cognitively impaired patients. Medications are not likely to help and may impair cognition, locomotion, and behavior.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049909111420701">2</xref></sup> Nonpharmacological approaches to reducing agitation or vocalizations during care are contextually relevant as contributing factors have a high probability of being environmental, involving the touch of the caregiver, noise, cold, and potentially painful stimuli.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1049909111420701">1</xref></sup>
</p>
<p>Although fewer studies involving patients in palliative care have been conducted, vocalizations during personal care do occur on our palliative unit, less frequently than in nursing home or community settings but still on a regular basis. Trial and error is sometimes required to find a suitable intervention to ameliorate these distressing symptoms. In some instances, no extinguishing factor can be found and the vocalizations continue.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1049909111420701" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Timeline—Chart Notes on Patient’s Response to Personal Care</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1049909111420701" xlink:href="10.1177_1049909111420701-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Day 1</td>
<td>Disorientation. Agitated but easily redirected</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Day 2</td>
<td>Nurses note patient frightened with care, resistive to care, screams with care</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Day 3</td>
<td>Possible pain with care. Fentanyl sublingual (parenteral formulation) prior to care</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Day 8</td>
<td>Cries during perineal care. Scheduled morphine prior to care for incident pain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Days 9 and 10</td>
<td>Slept most of day shift × 2 days. Thought to be medication effect</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Day 11</td>
<td>Morphine prior to care discontinued. Nurses begin patient-focused routine</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Day 30</td>
<td>Fentanyl prior to care changed to pro re nata (prn). Asked whether benzodiazepine would benefit</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Day 31</td>
<td>Request for benzodiazepine during care denied. Patient-focused care only</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Day 43</td>
<td>First charting of no vocalizations during care</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Day 60</td>
<td>No vocalizations during care on regular basis</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The patient in this case demonstrated that nonpharmacological measures can be instituted on a first-line basis or concurrently with pharmacological approaches. Time is required to acclimatize the patient to the new, patient-centered regime and minimize or extinguish distressing verbalizations. Studies in nursing homes have shown that a substantial reduction in behavioral symptoms can often be achieved within a 6-week period.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1049909111420701">1</xref></sup> Although some patients who are in palliative settings may not have a length of stay long enough to establish efficacy, nevertheless, the institution of bathing with an approach focused on patient’s experience over task orientation may be beneficial from the first day.</p>
<p>Counterconditioning, changing the association between 2 events to create an association with a new event through repetitive process, could have contributed to extinction of vocalizations during care. However, some patients with dementia or brain lesions may have anxious thoughts and fearful emotions that could be ameliorated by a higher order process than reflex response such as is involved in counterconditioning. Respect for the patient, such a basic concept, is difficult to quantify and more difficult to propagate. As in this case, explanations of what the caregiver is doing and simple kindness and consideration in the process of personal care gave opportunity for the patient’s emotions to change with time as trust was developed in the caregivers. This requires customized attention to the patient’s responses and may not involve strictly defined counterconditioning techniques.</p>
<p>The other factor which may have played a significant role in this patient’s distress was her underlying condition. Her brain lesions were in the frontal lobe and caudate nucleus, with the caudate lesions lying alongside the amygdala. The amygdalae are the nuclei in the temporal lobes of the brain, which are involved with the processing of memory and emotion. Neuroregulatory dysfunction in the frontal cortex and amygdalae may cause disinhibition and alter the affect and could theoretically have been a factor in her agitated calling out during care.</p>
<p>A beneficial resolution to this case was achieved with the persistent efforts of the nursing staff. The daily routines of the nursing team proved more effective than pharmacological approaches and assisted the patient to adjust successfully to the unit. Evidence of improvement of function in other domains also occurred during the same time frame that the agitated vocalizations during bathing were extinguished.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-1049909111420701">
<p>The authors declared no conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1049909111420701">
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1049909111420701">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sloane</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hoeffer</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mitchell</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Effect of person-centered showering and the towel bath on bathing-associated aggression, agitation, and discomfort in nursing home residents with dementia: a randomized, controlled trial</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1795</fpage>–<lpage>1804</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1049909111420701">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grigsby</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kaye</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Robbins</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Behavioral disturbance and impairment of executive functions among the elderly</article-title>. <source>Arch Gerontol Geriatr</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>