<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MSS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmss</journal-id>
<journal-title>Memory Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1750-6980</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1750-6999</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1750698012455738</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1750698012455738</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book review: Human Rights and Memory</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Savelsberg</surname><given-names>Joachim J</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1750698012455738">University of Minnesota, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>506</fpage>
<lpage>508</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sznaider</surname><given-names>Natan</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>Human Rights and Memory</source>. <publisher-loc>University Park, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>. <page-count count="192"/> pp. <price>$59.95</price>. ISBN <isbn>9780271037387</isbn></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Weaving together philosophical discourse, sociological reasoning, and historical information, Levy and Sznaider suggest that memories and the human rights movement are intimately linked. They carefully lay out central concepts and theses in the first 3 of 10 chapters. Chapters 4–7 seek to support these theses by reviewing four different historical stages, from the interwar period to the post–Cold War era. Final chapters address the politics of forgiveness, European issues, and effects of the era of terrorism.</p>
<p>The authors argue that today human rights have globally moved center stage. As a new principle of political legitimacy, they have come to challenge the notion of national sovereignty. The book is most relevant for readers of this journal though because of a second claim: “… historical memories of past failures to prevent human rights abuses have become a primary mechanism through which the institutionalization of human rights idioms and their legal inscription during the past two decades have transformed sovereignty. The global proliferation of human rights norms is driven by the public and frequently ritualistic attention to memories of their persistent violations” (p. 4). In other words, memories thus drive human rights discourses, and these discourses have become a major cultural and political force. In fact, the legitimacy of states now hinges on memory politics of human rights. What then is the nature of such memories, and what are their conditions?</p>
<p>Current day memories are no longer national but cosmopolitan memories, in which national and global concerns are closely interwoven, an argument developed in Levy and Sznaider’s (2005) <italic>The Holocaust and Memory in the Global Age</italic>. This turn toward cosmopolitan memories resulted first from the weakening capacity of nation states in shaping the past and the related fragmentation of memory, in which diverse local groups and competing affiliations gain the upper hand. They resulted secondly from a shift from communicative memories, based on group-specific carriers, to cultural memories, reproduced through media and communicative institutions.</p>
<p>Yet, cosmopolitan concerns, and the memories supporting them, are not only distinct from national memories (at one end of the continuum) but also distinct from abstract principles of universalism (at the other). In cosmopolitanism, the particularities of others remain relevant, while only a “universalistic minimum” is postulated; the contradiction between particularism (and associated “feeling”) versus universalism (with its abstract Kantian principles) thus arrives at a new synthesis. Global human rights concerns become historicized, that is, incorporated into political–cultural scripts of nations. What emerges is recognition of the “dignity of man” not as an eternal truth but as a construct with strong social underpinnings.</p>
<p>Communicative mechanisms and institutions that produce cosmopolitan memories include the globalization of media images and communication technologies through which distant events create local resonance and identifications. They also include the law: “Our analysis shows how recent trials related to human rights abuses are an important locus for the production of cosmopolitan ideals and their criticism … Trials are transformative opportunities, where memories of grave injustices are addressed in rituals of restitution and renewal … Justice itself becomes a form of remembrance” (p. 19). More broadly, the juridification of global politics is central to the cosmopolitanization of sovereignty, and the enforcement of rights is increasingly guaranteed by the cultural and legal recognition of humanity as a category of membership.</p>
<p>Levy and Sznaider review twentieth century history to support their claims: They note how the nation state, a product of the French Revolution, and how identifying the people with the state, became radicalized by the outcome of World War I. The postwar order gave 60 million people states of their own, but it also turned 25 million into minorities, and sought to protect them via <italic>minority rights</italic>, established by the League of Nations. This attempt had to fail, the authors argue, in light of the strong notion of national sovereignty, on which the new international order was based—with catastrophic consequences. Recognition and memory of this failure motivated a shift from minority rights toward <italic>human rights</italic> after the end of World War II. Universal declarations and principles generated by war crime trials document this shift. Examples are the notion of crimes against humanity and of citizens’ moral responsibility even against their own states. Jews, no longer the focus of the new philosophy, despite the Judeocide of the Nazis, became representatives of humanity as such. The widely accepted, and massive, forced transfer of minority populations at the end of World War II (which today would be named “ethnic cleansing”) further reflected the demise of minority protection. Legal language after World War II underscored the new focus on human rights and its mnemonic roots. The UN Charter, the London Agreement and the Nuremberg Trial, and the Universal Declaration of Human Rights are cited for illustration. The Genocide Convention, however, stressing the protection of <italic>specific groups</italic>, while not returning to the old model of minority protection, abandons abstract universalism and indicates the new cosmopolitan understanding of human rights.</p>
<p>Even the Cold War era advanced human rights ideas, propagated against the fear (and memory) of totalitarianism, and institutionalized in numerous conventions, the Helsinki accords and in the rise of an unprecedented international nongovernmental organization (INGO) movement. Finally, according to Levy and Sznaider, the post–Cold War era further advanced the cosmopolitanization of human rights regimes, as illustrated by the substantial number of <italic>domestic</italic> human rights trials, the incorporation of international law into <italic>domestic</italic> jurisdictions (internalization of human rights norms by states), and the creation of the International Criminal Court with its <italic>complementarity</italic> principle. This principle privileges states’ rights to prosecute human rights perpetrators as long as they are willing and capable to do so. Universal jurisdiction and humanitarian intervention, on the other hand, steeped in a strong sense of universalism, faced increasing challenges.</p>
<p>In short, this impressive little book by Levy and Sznaider, while a challenging read, offers an important sign post. It tells us much about the shape memories of atrocities take, about conditions of such memories, and about their potential effects on national sovereignty and human rights regimes. Such signposts are important for orientation in a confusing world, but they come with risks. We have too little systematic evidence to date about the conditions and effects of memories, the human rights interventions they motivate and through which they are created. Questions remain. Are universal jurisdiction and humanitarian intervention (as expressions of an abstract, universalist notion of human rights) actually on the decline—and for good? The West’s 2011 intervention in Libya speaks a different language. Do countries, especially powerful ones, actually incorporate international human rights concerns into their legitimacy basis? The United States, for example, has refrained from signing and ratifying important international conventions, and it has resisted the attribution of criminal liability to its leaders. We have elsewhere demonstrated the problematic effects of this reluctance on the country’s commitment to protect human rights against transgressions by its own government and military. Moreover, while I agree that legal interventions produce historic memories, these memories are filtered through a particular judicial logic and colored by political constraints under which law operates, especially international law. Finally, while I am sympathetic to the notion of cosmopolitanism, is its rise not a question of degree? May not national memories as well as universal standards remain central players in the making of memories and critical in the establishment (and rejection) of human rights doctrines?</p>
<p>Like all good books, <italic>Human Rights and Memory</italic> thus provides rich fodder for thought. It raises new questions and should motivate rich lines of future empirical inquiry. I highly recommend it to scholars and graduate students in sociology, philosophy, law, political science, and history, to all who share an interest in memory and human rights.</p>
</body>
</article>