<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CJP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcjp</journal-id>
<journal-title>Criminal Justice Policy Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0887-4034</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3586</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0887403412446993</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0887403412446993</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>When the Mayor Speaks . . . Mayoral Crime Control Rhetoric in the Top U.S. Cities</article-title>
<subtitle>Symbolic or Tangible?</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>Nancy E.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0887403412446993">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>Willard M.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0887403412446993">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0887403412446993"><label>1</label>University of Akron, Akron, OH, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0887403412446993"><label>2</label>Sam Houston State University, Huntsville, TX, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0887403412446993">Nancy E. Marion, University of Akron, Department of Political Science, 302 Buchtel Common, Akron, OH 44325-1904, USA. Email: <email>nmarion@uakron.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>473</fpage>
<lpage>491</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Past research on presidential and gubernatorial rhetoric related to crime shows that both presidents and governors use symbolic statements in their crime rhetoric. To date, no research has analyzed how mayors employ political language related to crime. As mayors are politically closer to the people and have a greater impact on local crime policy, it is important to understand the nature of how mayors use symbolic language about crime. The current study draws on hypotheses derived from research related to presidents and governors and applies them to the top 50 city executives. A content analysis of 6 years (2005-2010) of mayors’ State of the City speeches was conducted to assess how mayors employ the issue of crime in their political communication. Overall, the results suggest that mayors employ crime rhetoric in a different manner from other executives when speaking to their constituents about crime.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>criminal justice policy</kwd>
<kwd>crime control policy</kwd>
<kwd>symbolic politics</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I’m the one who gets called up about a problem. I’m the one who gets called up about the street lighting and the abandoned car. I’m the one who gets blamed if the police don’t arrive. I’m the one they blame if a city truck is broken down.</p>
<attrib>Chicago Mayor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0887403412446993">Richard M. Daley</xref></attrib>
</disp-quote></p>
<sec id="section1-0887403412446993" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Crime is an issue that receives sizeable attention from executives at all levels, including presidents, governors, and mayors. These executives often mention crime issues in their speeches as they respond to citizen concerns about the safety of their communities. Many times, executive rhetoric about crime is tangible and describes specific anticrime policies or ideas designed to address a particular concern. These tangible policies will be implemented, typically through some program, aimed at creating change. Other times, speeches on crime by executives contain largely symbolic language. This is a communication that is designed to satisfy the public’s need for action or to reassure them that something is being done about the problem, although not providing any specific program that will result in substantive changes to existing policy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0887403412446993">Edelman, 1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0887403412446993">1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0887403412446993">1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0887403412446993">Elder &amp; Cobb, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0887403412446993">Oliver, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0887403412446993">2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0887403412446993">Stolz, 1983</xref>). By using symbolic language, the speaker is appearing to address a problem when in fact they are not.</p>
<p>Previous studies show that executives often rely on symbolic language rather than tangible language when discussing crime and violence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0887403412446993">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0887403412446993">Marion &amp; Farmer, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0887403412446993">Oliver, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0887403412446993">2003</xref>). Some of these studies focus on presidents, and find that although different presidents speak about different crime related issues over time, or have different policy approaches to solving a particular problem, they each have a significant amount of symbolic rhetoric included in their public communications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0887403412446993">1994b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0887403412446993">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0887403412446993">Marion &amp; Farmer, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0887403412446993">Oliver, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0887403412446993">2003</xref>). Other work focuses on gubernatorial rhetoric on crime, and shows that governors also rely on symbolic rhetoric to portray their concern about crime to voters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Another executive official that must address crime issues are mayors. These elected officials are considered to be closer to the people, and therefore often the ones that citizens turn to when a problem arises, as exampled by the epigraph quoting Chicago Mayor Richard Dailey. Often, presidents and governors are “out of reach” for most citizens, but a mayor appears to be more approachable to the average person (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0887403412446993">Scheingold, 1991</xref>). In that regard, mayors are thought to give voice to underrepresented interests among voters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0887403412446993">Schragger, 2006</xref>). This makes their responses to crime and violence even more meaningful to voters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0887403412446993">Waller, 2008</xref>). To date, there has been no research on the use of symbolic language by mayors with regard to crime issues. The current study seeks to fill the void in the literature and analyze the use of symbolic language by the mayors of the largest cities across the United States to determine the patterns and trends of rhetoric on crime control. The study applies the findings on presidential and gubernatorial language to mayoral speeches to ascertain if similar patterns hold true. In sum, this study attempts to determine whether mayors use symbolic rhetoric in ways similar to presidents and governors, or if they rely on different methods to communicate to their constituents.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0887403412446993">
<title>Literature Review</title>
<p>One primary method for assessing political communication is through the use of symbolic politics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0887403412446993">Edelman, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0887403412446993">Scheingold, 1995</xref>). Symbolic language was originally described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0887403412446993">Murray Edelman (1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0887403412446993">1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0887403412446993">1988</xref>) who made the distinction between tangible actions and symbolic actions. He described tangible actions as those speeches and policies that make significant modification or adjustments and have a direct effect on a problem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0887403412446993">Gusfield, 1967</xref>). These are the policies that create policy variation and produce new results.</p>
<p>However, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0887403412446993">Edelman (1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0887403412446993">1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0887403412446993">1988</xref>), many actions and speeches can be considered to be symbolic. Symbolic proposals are those that give the appearance of change, when in reality, no serious or significant adjustments are ever made. By using symbolic rhetoric, elected officials can appease public concerns without directly or substantively addressing the underlying problem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0887403412446993">Oliver &amp; Marion, 2006</xref>). Executives rely on symbolic language to reach out to the public in an effort to incite an emotion or reaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0887403412446993">Stolz, 1999</xref>), and make people feel good about the government’s response to a public concern. Through symbolic language, executives try to reassure and persuade the public that they are doing something (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0887403412446993">Elder &amp; Cobb, 1983</xref>). The end result of symbolic policies and rhetoric, however, is not new policies but simply an appearance of action (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0887403412446993">Marion &amp; Farmer, 2003</xref>). In fact, symbolic laws are often not fully funded nor enforced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0887403412446993">Gusfield, 1967</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0887403412446993">1986</xref>).</p>
<p>Speeches laced with symbolic language are used by executives because they are an effective way to appeal to the public, show their concern, and appear to act on a problem. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0887403412446993">Thompson (2005)</xref> argues that the mayor of New York used symbolic language to manage the citizens’ fear of crime in their districts. He writes that in this case, “the appearance of controlling crime was at least as important to them as reducing the crime rate” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0887403412446993">Thompson, 2005</xref>, p. 301).</p>
<p>In some cases, because the political process is so complicated and abstract to most citizens, executives sometimes rely on symbolic language as a means to simplify the process. The same holds true for complex issues such as crime control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0887403412446993">Shull, 1989</xref>). As a means to simplify the political process and the complexities of controlling crime, voters tend to listen to political speeches and assume that what an official describes will eventually be enacted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0887403412446993">Edelman, 1988</xref>). In many cases, the public is more concerned with the leader’s attention to the problem rather than if crime is actually reduced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0887403412446993">Lorinskas, Kalinich, &amp; Banas, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0887403412446993">Oliver, 1998</xref>).</p>
<p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0887403412446993">Stolz (2007)</xref>, there are five functions of symbolic policies and rhetoric (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0887403412446993">Stolz, 2007</xref>). The first is to serve a reassurance function. This is a way to indicate to the public that officials are aware of a concern and that some action is being taken to resolve it. Second, symbolic policies serve an educative role because they seek to educate the public on an issue. Third, policies also have a moral educative role because they codify the public’s mores about what is right and wrong. The fourth role of symbolic policies is simplification, to help officials discuss complicated issues more easily with the public. This is especially true for crime issues, which are very complicated but yet demand attention by the public. Finally, symbolic policies can sometimes act as models for state and local government action. This means that the federal government may propose a plan that appears to be a new approach to halt crime, but it is serving an underlying purpose of relaying a message to states about the need for action. The federal legislation may also be an example of the type of legislation that the states could pass if they did not want to spend a great amount of time and money to develop their own.</p>
<p>Past research has clearly demonstrated the presidents often rely on symbolic language when discussing crime issues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0887403412446993">Calder, 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0887403412446993">1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0887403412446993">Oliver, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0887403412446993">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0887403412446993">Stolz, 2007</xref>). One of the first presidents to discuss crime control issues was Johnson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0887403412446993">Caplan, 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0887403412446993">Cronin, Cronin, &amp; Milakovich, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0887403412446993">Dilulio, Smith, &amp; Saiger, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0887403412446993">Felkenes, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0887403412446993">Finckenauer, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0887403412446993">Potter, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0887403412446993">Scheingold, 1995</xref>). Since that administration, crime has been on the presidential agenda of every administration in some way (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0887403412446993">Stolz, 1999</xref>). Because of the growth of crime as a federal issue, a trend termed the “federalization of crime” (see for example <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0887403412446993">Dilulio, Smith, &amp; Saiger, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0887403412446993">Kaminer, 1994</xref>), modern presidents have given more speeches about crime as a way to show their concern to voters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0887403412446993">Oliver, 1998</xref>, 2003a). When they talk about crime, presidents are acknowledging that many people have a concern about their safety and the safety of their families and friends. Presidents use symbolic language to convey their concerns to the public, in turn hoping that it will enhance their popularity, increase their public support and their approval within their constituency base, and increase their electability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0887403412446993">Edwards &amp; Wayne, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0887403412446993">Fairchild &amp; Webb, 1985</xref>).</p>
<p>Past research also shows that state executives (i.e., governors) also rely on symbolic language when discussing crime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>). Constitutionally, crime control is a state concern. It is a power reserved to the states (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0887403412446993">Jacob et al., 1982</xref>), and until recently, state officials were the primary policy makers in this area. Even today, the majority of anticrime legislation is passed and implemented on the state level. Because of that, governors must discuss different policy options for controlling crime in their state.</p>
<p>Mayors are another executive that often discuss crime issues in response to the public’s concern about violence. As the primary leader in city government, they are responsible for the safety of the people who live and work there. Mayors have the most power in local government, and therefore have the biggest capacity to shape the agenda and find solutions to the community’s problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0887403412446993">Kuo, 1973</xref>). In fact, it has been argued that most Americans assume that mayors are the central political leaders and policy makers in their communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0887403412446993">Berman &amp; Merrill, 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0887403412446993">Gertson, 2010</xref>). By examining the yearly State of the City speech given by mayors, the patterns of symbolic rhetoric by these executives can be analyzed to determine if they follow the same patterns as those found in presidential and gubernatorial speeches.</p>
<p>There are five findings from past research on presidential and gubernatorial rhetoric on crime that can be applied to mayors. First, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">Marion’s (1994a)</xref> analysis of presidential speeches found that presidents increased the number of speeches on crime they gave each year they were in office. Similar findings were not discovered in analyses of gubernatorial speeches. It was found that state leaders, as a whole, did not devote more time to crime issues in their speeches with each consecutive year in office (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>). Put simply, governors did not talk about crime more each year they were in office. This is a plausible finding because crime has typically been recognized as a state concern, and governors have traditionally placed the issue higher on their agendas than other issues. The same pattern is proposed when mayoral speeches on crime are analyzed. It is hypothesized that the frequency with which mayors discuss crime control will stay relatively the same over time because the issue remains a primary concern of local government officials.</p>
<p>A second hypothesis relates to political party differences in the number of times crime is discussed. Previous work on federal executive rhetoric indicates that Republican presidents did not put crime on their agendas more frequently than democratic presidents. This is somewhat contradictory to what one might expect, given the “law and order” perspective held by Republican Party members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0887403412446993">Marion, 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">1994</xref>). However, the research on governors also showed that state-level Republican executives also did not devote more time in their speeches to crime control than Democratic executives. Instead, these findings suggest that governors of both parties talk about crime issues with equal frequency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>). Thus, based on these findings, the second hypothesis for this study is there will be no difference in the number of speeches given by Republican and Democratic mayors.</p>
<p>The third finding from past studies shows that the issues discussed by presidents differ over time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994b</xref>). This is simply because the issues important to the public change and officials must alter their behavior as they respond to those differences. In addition, new crimes sometimes emerge that previously did not exist, such as computer crimes or identity theft. These new opportunities for criminal behavior cannot be ignored by executives. However, the same pattern did not hold true with governors. In fact, the specific crime issues discussed by governors remained consistent over time. This was explained by the fact that governors are less likely to respond to the political “whims” of the day (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>). As it is the case that mayors and governors are considered to be “closer” or more approachable to the people than presidents, it is thought that the findings from the research on governors’ will also apply to mayors. Thus, it is hypothesized that the crime issues discussed by mayors will remain the same over time.</p>
<p>Fourth, past research on executives and crime control rhetoric demonstrates that federal executives provided policy statements (tangible statements) in about 51% of their speeches, thus relying on symbolic statements about 49% of the time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994a</xref>). Interestingly, governors had symbolic language in about 54% of their speeches. Thus, governors relied on symbolic statements about the same amount of time as presidents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>). On the basis of these findings, it is proposed that mayors will rely on symbolic statements in about half of their speeches.</p>
<p>Finally, research shows that crime control statements by Democratic presidents contain less symbolic statements than Republican presidents. In other words, Democrats make more specific proposals about crime policies than do Republicans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994a</xref>; Oliver, 2003a; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0887403412446993">Scheingold, 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0887403412446993">1995</xref>). The same research on governors shows that there was no difference in the symbolism found in governors’ speeches between those from the Republican or Democratic parties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>). Thus, it is proposed in the current research that there will be no difference between Republicans and Democrats in the amount of symbolic versus tangible language about crime during the study period.</p>
<sec id="section3-0887403412446993">
<title>Hypotheses</title>
<p>In light of these observations regarding the crime agenda of presidents and governors, five hypotheses can be derived from these previous studies to apply them to the mayoral rhetoric on crime control. The hypotheses tested in this study are therefore based on the findings from prior academic research on presidential and gubernatorial crime rhetoric. They include the following:</p>
<list id="list1-0887403412446993" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1</italic>: The frequency with which crime is discussed by mayors will remain the same over the years of the study.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 2</italic>: Republican and Democratic mayors will devote the same number of speeches to the issue of crime.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 3</italic>: There will be few changes in the specific topics mentioned by mayors over the years.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 4</italic>: About half of all mayoral speech concerning crime will be symbolic.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 5</italic>: There will be equal amounts of symbolic language from Republican and Democratic mayors.</p></list-item></list>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section4-0887403412446993" sec-type="methods">
<title>Data and Method</title>
<p>Previous studies on presidential and governors’ agendas on crime have used content analysis of speeches to determine patterns and trends (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0887403412446993">Baumgartner &amp; Jones, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0887403412446993">Cohen, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0887403412446993">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0887403412446993">Heck &amp; Shull, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0887403412446993">Kessel, 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0887403412446993">Light, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0887403412446993">Marion, 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0887403412446993">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0887403412446993">Shull &amp; Ringelstein, 1989</xref>). The present study adopts the same techniques and applies it to the behavior of mayors in the 50 largest cities in the United States as identified by the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0887403412446993">U.S. Census Bureau (2010)</xref>. To complete the content analysis, each State of the City address given by the 50 largest city mayors from 2005 through 2010 was collected, read, and coded. It is in these speeches that mayors communicate their agenda to the public, similar to a presidential State of the Union address (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0887403412446993">Oliver, 2002</xref>) or a governors’ State of the State address (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>). By examining the content of this yearly speech, the patterns of the individual mayors’ agendas toward crime control can be analyzed and a comparison of mayors over time can be traced.</p>
<p>The State of the City speeches were obtained from the Pew Center on the States (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://stateline.org">stateline.org</ext-link>), the websites of the Mayors, the major city newspapers, and in some cases, directly from the Mayors’ office. In the collection of speeches for each year, there were a number of speeches that appeared to be “missing” from the database. On further inspection, it was determined that in many cities, the State of the City speech is only given “from time to time,” thus often there was no definitive patterns for speech delivery (e.g., Austin, Texas &amp; Raleigh, North Carolina). In other cases, the State of the City speech is given every year except for the last year the mayor is in office (which is also an election year) or it is not given by a Mayor in his or her first year in office. Within the context of the present study 33 speeches were not given during the total of 6 years of speeches given in the 50 largest cities in the United States. This is opposed to the four cases of bona fide missing speeches. The first derived from Arlington, Texas, where for 2 years the Mayor (Dr. Cluck) decided that rather than delivering a speech, he would deliver a PowerPoint© presentation. As a result, there was no speech to code in the database and trying to code the PowerPoint created inconsistencies in the data collection. Finally, one city (Oakland) could not verify whether a speech was actually given during the years 2005 and 2006, and no method of follow up employed could verify the status. So, although there were a total of 300 “years” in the study (2005-2010), the final database consisted of 263 mayoral State of the City addresses.</p>
<p>The 263 speeches were downloaded into electronic files and were searched both manually and electronically using the code word search parameters found in previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0887403412446993">Oliver, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0887403412446993">Oliver &amp; Barlow, 2005</xref>). The speeches were then coded and categorized in a variety of ways. First, each speech was read (manually) and searched (electronically) to determine if crime was mentioned in the speech. This could range from a whole section on crime control offset by a specific heading or a few words denoting a concern for crime in the city. Any mention of crime or a related topic found in a State of the City speech was then coded for the purposes of this study. The length of each statement was recorded by the total number of words related to crime, and further calculated as a percentage of the entire speech. Not all State of the City addresses were found to have crime related content, but that number was small, consisting of only 13 speeches or 4.9% of the total database.</p>
<p>The total number of speeches was also analyzed by the party affiliation of the Mayors, as either Democrat or Republican. In the case of the database, two individuals were listed as Independents, Miami Mayor Diaz and New York Mayor Bloomberg. In the case of Mayor Diaz, rather than coding him as an independent, he was coded as a Democrat, as that was his prior party before running as an Independent and for the fact he spoke at the Democratic National Convention for Democratic nominee Senator Barack Obama. Mayor Bloomberg was coded as a Republican for that was his party affiliation before declaring himself an Independent (despite having originally declared himself a Democrat).</p>
<p>The crime mentions were next categorized based on the topic discussed by the mayor which included such topics as guns, domestic violence, and gangs. Those statements that did not focus on a particular issue were coded as “general” statements about crime. An example is Albuquerque Mayor Martin Chavez, who in his 2006 State of the City Address made the statement, “My number one priority has always been public safety.” This statement does not focus on a particular type of crime or issue, but instead provides a broad general statement.</p>
<p>The crime statements were further analyzed to determine if they were either symbolic or tangible. A symbolic statement is vague, lacks detail, and is said primarily to satisfy voters’ concerns. They are statements in which a mayor acknowledges the seriousness of crime and the importance of “doing something” but does not make any serious policy proposals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0887403412446993">Edelman, 1964</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0887403412446993">1994b</xref>). An example of a mayoral symbolic statement from the database was Jacksonville (FL) Mayor John Peyton, who rhetorically argued in his 2006 speech,<disp-quote>
<p>The evidence is clear. Violent crime is infecting every section and every neighborhood of Jacksonville. These killers, rapists and robbers recognize no boundaries, show no mercy, and have no remorse. They have the ability and the opportunity to violate every part of Jacksonville and every person who lives here. Children should not have to live their lives watching for stray bullets. Mothers should not have to worry about their safety on the next trip to the grocery store. Business owners should not worry about smash and grabs in their store fronts. Let’s be very clear. What I am proposing today is not an initiative. This is not a campaign. This is a WAR to take back our town. And in a war, people have to choose sides. There are good guys and there are bad guys. Everyone has to choose a side. The good guys are the law abiding, tax-paying citizens who work hard every day to make live better for their families, friends and neighbors. The good guys are police officers and rescue workers that put themselves in harms way to keep us safe.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Symbolic statements like this present little detail and do not directly address the problem of crime in the city. Statements that were also considered symbolic, consisted of speeches where mayors discussed previous years’ crime issues such as crime rates, arrests, or improvements in corrections. In addition, anecdotes or short stories related to a crime issue were also coded as symbolic statements.</p>
<p>Tangible statements, conversely, are detailed and directly address crime problems (Edelman, 1967; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0887403412446993">1994b</xref>). It is a policy statement that provides direction, advocates a particular program or course of action to be taken by the administration to address the problem or perceived problem. An example of a tangible statement from the mayoral database comes from Honolulu (HI) Mayor Mufi Hannemann, who in his 2007 State of the City speech put forth that
<disp-quote>
<p>The Waikiki and East Honolulu burglary-and-theft detectives and other HPD units will be opening an office at Fort Ruger this year, giving the police a permanent and visible operation in East Honolulu. We’re also moving forward with the expansion of the crime laboratory and plans for a replacement for the Waianae substation with a full station to serve the Leeward Coast.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This statement clearly spelled out very tangible initiatives for addressing the problems of crime: opening an office at Fort Ruger, expanding a crime lab, and replacing a substation with a full police station. Tangible statements, as demonstrated here, are real programs, physical construction, and programs aimed at addressing crime problems, rather than simply consisting of rhetorical statements.</p>
<p>Additional demographic data were collected from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0887403412446993">U.S. Census Bureau (2010)</xref> data regarding the 50 largest cities as well as the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0887403412446993">U. S. Conference of Mayors (2010)</xref> website, including such things as the political affiliation of each mayor.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0887403412446993">
<title>Findings</title>
<p>The findings of the analysis present some interesting trends. First, it should be noted that unlike governorships, where a slight majority of the seats are held by Republicans, when it comes to mayors, the vast majority are Democrats. There were a total of 74 individual mayors represented in this study. Of those, 55 were Democratic mayors making up 74.3% of the total, leaving only 25.6% (<italic>n</italic> = 19) of the top 50 cities in the United States having Republican mayors.</p>
<p>To determine how often these mayors spoke about crime in their State of the City speeches, the number of words devoted to crime in their speeches was compiled, as was the percentage of words devoted to crime as compared to the total number of words in the speech. As previously noted, the sample included 263 State of the City speeches from 2005 through 2010. The greatest number of speeches a mayor (or mayors) could give in the time frame was six, which was in fact the mode, although five was the mean. Several cities in the 6 year time frame only delivered one State of the City speech (e.g., Austin, TX; Las Vegas, NV; Oakland, CA). The number of words in these speeches ranged from 803 (Phoenix, AZ, 2010) to 15,727 (San Francisco, CA, 2007) with the mean being 4,205 words (<italic>SD</italic> = 1,845). The number of words related to crime within the 263 State of the City speeches ranged from 0 (e.g., Nashville, TN, 2005; San Antonio, TX, 2007; Seattle, WA, 2005) to 3,907 (Washington, D.C., 2008). The mean number of words related to crime for the sample was 432 (<italic>SD</italic> = 491). It should be noted that there were 13 speeches with no mention of crime whatsoever consisting of 4.92% of the sample. When further assessing the number of words related to crime against the entire speech, the percentages ranged from 0 to 57% (Jacksonville, FL, 2008). The mean for the percentage of the speeches related to crime was 9.7% with a standard deviation of 8.9%.</p>
<p>Turning to the number and average number of speeches by political party, the results are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0887403412446993">Table 1</xref>. What is most interesting is that of the 263 speeches in the sample, 76.9% of the words were spoken by a Democratic mayor, whereas 22.6% were spoken by a Republican mayor. These findings are, however, consistent with the number of Democratic/Republican mayors in the sample. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0887403412446993">Table 1</xref> also shows that the frequency for which State of the City speeches are given appears to remain fairly steady for mayors of both parties over the time period of 2005 to 2010. The number of speeches incorporating crime rhetoric for Republican mayors ranged from 7 to 13, whereas the range for Democratic mayors was 30 to 37 speeches a year. This means that crime rhetoric in mayoral State of the City speeches remained fairly constant suggesting further support for the first hypothesis.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0887403412446993" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Crime in Mayoral State of the City Speeches by Party with Average Number of Words Per Speech and Percentage of Total Speech.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0887403412446993" xlink:href="10.1177_0887403412446993-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Republican<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Democrats<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Total<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Year</th>
<th align="center">No. of speeches</th>
<th align="center">Average no. of words</th>
<th align="center">% of total speech</th>
<th align="center">No. of speeches</th>
<th align="center">Average no. of words</th>
<th align="center">% of total speech</th>
<th align="center">No. of speeches</th>
<th align="center">Average no. of words</th>
<th align="center">% of total speech</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>2005</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>280</td>
<td>3.4</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>398</td>
<td>12.5</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>339</td>
<td>15.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2006</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>475</td>
<td>3.8</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>407</td>
<td>12.9</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>441</td>
<td>16.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2007</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>386</td>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>609</td>
<td>14.0</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>498</td>
<td>16.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2008</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>439</td>
<td>4.1</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>622</td>
<td>13.6</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>531</td>
<td>17.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2009</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>244</td>
<td>3.8</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>357</td>
<td>11.4</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>301</td>
<td>15.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2010</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>330</td>
<td>4.9</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>289</td>
<td>12.5</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>310</td>
<td>17.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>359</td>
<td>22.6</td>
<td>203</td>
<td>447</td>
<td>76.9</td>
<td>263</td>
<td>403</td>
<td>99.5<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0887403412446993">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0887403412446993">
<label>a</label>
<p>Does not equal 100% due to rounding.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>In terms of the hypothesis that crime rhetoric is likely to come equally from Republican and Democratic mayors, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0887403412446993">Table 1</xref> shows that although Republicans address the problems of crime in their State of the City addresses, Democratic mayors are far more verbose about the issue. Looking at the actual number of words devoted to crime in their speeches, in 2005, 2007, 2008, and 2009, Democrats spoke above the average number of words in a speech, whereas that was only the case for the Republicans in 2006 and 2009. Turning to the percentage of speeches dedicated to the topic of crime, it would also appear that Democrats devoted far more words on the subject matter than their Republican counterparts in every year of the sample. Statistically speaking, (χ<sup>2</sup>(276, <italic>N</italic> = 263) = 404.16, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001), this assertion is supported, thus indicating no support for the hypothesis that crime rhetoric would be equal for Republican and Democratic mayors, but rather suggesting that for the top 50 U.S. city mayors, crime is a Democratic issue.</p>
<p>To test the hypothesis that the issues mayors discuss in their State of the City speech would remain the same each year, each mention of crime was coded by subject matter. The findings are reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0887403412446993">Table 2</xref>. It was hypothesized that there would be little variation among the issues mayors’ address, and that topics would not change based upon the latest crime issues. The findings suggest support for the hypothesis. The topics that mayors spoke about from 2005 through 2010 remained fairly constant from year to year with little variation in the frequency of mentions. What appears to be the most important issue for mayors, as denoted by the higher number of mentions in their State of the City speeches, is the police with 188 mentions. Mayors also made a number of general statements regarding crime (100 total), such as the need to decrease crime to keep citizens safe. Other issues of concern for the mayors were youth crimes (55), gangs (52), funding (50), guns (38), and neighborhoods (36). The results of <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0887403412446993">Table 2</xref> would suggest that the issues placed on the mayors’ agenda regarding crime did not change or vary much from year to year, thus supporting the hypothesis that there would be little shift in the crimes that mayors would address each year. It should be noted that there were some issues that appeared in certain years and did change, such as homeland security was prevalent in the years 2005 and 2006, but soon all but disappeared. Another issue that came onto some mayors’ agenda was the issue of copper wire theft, showing mainly in 2009 and 2010, but none of these ever rose to more than ten mentions in any given year in the study.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0887403412446993" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Top Crime Issues Mentioned by Top 50 City Mayors, 2005-2010.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0887403412446993" xlink:href="10.1177_0887403412446993-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Topic</th>
<th align="center">2005</th>
<th align="center">2006</th>
<th align="center">2007</th>
<th align="center">2008</th>
<th align="center">2009</th>
<th align="center">2010</th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Police</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>188</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>General</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Youth</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>55</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gangs</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Funding</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Guns</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>38</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Neighborhoods</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Drugs</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9-1-1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Domestic violence</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>12</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0887403412446993">
<p>Note: Top crime issues based on total number of mentions (&gt;10) by Republican and Democratic Mayors.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Turning to the analysis of how mayors employ political rhetoric of crime, whether that rhetoric is symbolic or tangible, there were a number of interesting findings. The mayors use of symbolic crime speech in their State of the City addresses ranged from 0 to 1,865 words (Albuquerque, NM 2007) with a mean of 303 words (<italic>SD</italic> = 324) on crime per speech. The mean percentage of the symbolic crime rhetoric was 73.6% (<italic>SD</italic> = 30.1%), meaning that approximately three-quarters of all State of the City speeches that have crime as a topic, mayors employ symbolic rhetoric to address the problem. This would appear to at least partially support the hypothesis that half of all mayoral speech concerning crime would be symbolic, because at least half of the speeches were symbolic. However, the magnitude of the percentage of speeches being symbolic was not anticipated when compared to previous research assessing presidential and gubernatorial speeches on crime.</p>
<p>Further analysis of the 263 speeches regarding their use of symbolic and tangible rhetoric found that 36.8% (<italic>n</italic> = 97) of the crime speeches were composed entirely of symbolic language, although only 1.89% (<italic>n</italic> = 5) of the speeches fully employed tangible rhetoric. Another way of looking at this is that 6.8% (<italic>n</italic> = 18) of the speeches employed no symbolic rhetoric, whereas 41.6% (<italic>n</italic> = 110) of the speeches employed no tangible rhetoric. This clearly suggests that mayors were more likely to employ symbolic rhetoric when it came to the issue of crime than to offer more tangible proposals to the citizens of their city.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0887403412446993">Table 3</xref> demonstrates how the symbolic and tangible speeches were used by the different parties from 2005 through 2010. In this sample of mayoral State of the City speeches, the Democrats by far spoke more often about the issue of crime with 77% (<italic>n</italic> = 203) of their speeches employing crime rhetoric. Twenty-three percent (<italic>n</italic> = 61) of the speeches by the Democratic mayors were entirely symbolic when it came to crime, and when they employed both symbolic and tangible rhetoric in their speeches, the majority of the political language remained symbolic (75%). Republican mayor speeches employing the issue of crime consistent of 22.8% (<italic>n</italic> = 60) of the sample and 23% (<italic>n</italic> = 36) of these speeches engaged in symbolic rhetoric. When analyzing the mixed rhetoric speeches by the Republican mayors, 94.5% of these 21 speeches were symbolic, meaning only 5.5% of the Republican rhetoric, when the speech was mixed, employed tangible rhetoric. Statistically speaking, it can be said that there was a significant difference between the two parties use of symbolic rhetoric in their State of the City speeches χ<sup>2</sup>(238, <italic>N</italic> = 263) = 355.24, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. Although there were more Democratic mayors employing more symbolic speeches, Republicans were more likely to engage in symbolic rhetoric when it came to the subject matter of crime, thus rejecting the fifth hypothesis.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0887403412446993" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mayoral Statements Related to Crime: Symbolic Versus Tangible.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0887403412446993" xlink:href="10.1177_0887403412446993-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Year/party</th>
<th align="center">Symbolic</th>
<th align="center">Tangible</th>
<th align="center">Mixed (% symbolic)</th>
<th align="center">None</th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>2005</td>
<td>Democratic</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>19 (63)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Republican</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (100)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2006</td>
<td>Democratic</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>25 (68)</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Republican</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>6 (67)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2007</td>
<td>Democratic</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>27 (81)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>37</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Republican</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3 (100)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2008</td>
<td>Democratic</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>25 (68)</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Republican</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>5 (100)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2009</td>
<td>Democratic</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>17 (70)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Republican</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (100)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2010</td>
<td>Democratic</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>14 (100)</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Republican</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (100)</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>Democratic</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>127 (75)</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>203</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Republican</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>21 (94.5)</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>60</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0887403412446993" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The research on presidential and gubernatorial rhetoric on crime control issues clearly shows that many of their speeches are comprised of symbolic statements. Although the crime policies that these two executives make will have an impact upon such things as funding and the passage of criminal laws, no one can dispute that where the funding and laws are executed occurs at the local level. Like former Speaker of the House Tip O’Neil’s famous saying “All Politics is local,” so too is crime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0887403412446993">O’Neil, 1995</xref>). Mayors sit at the lowest level of the executive branch which is responsible for carrying out the duties and obligations of the criminal justice system, and ensuring the community is safe, through the deployment of the city police, courts, and jails. When there is a spike in crime or a unique crime problem arises, the mayor becomes the focal point for local citizens, either to demand change or to look for local leadership on the issue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0887403412446993">Miller, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0887403412446993">Waller, 2008</xref>). As the mayor has such influence over how criminal justice is carried out, it is important to understand how mayors, especially mayors in the largest cities in the United States, carry out this function. It is, therefore, crucial to understand mayoral rhetoric on crime control to determine if mayoral speeches are symbolic or tangible. In other words, are city mayors relying on symbolic statements that make citizens feel good, or are their speeches comprised of tangible speeches that make legitimate proposals with real benefits?</p>
<p>It was hypothesized that city mayors would exhibit similar patterns of behavior as found in presidents and governors when it came to their rhetoric on crime control. All three of these political offices have very similar responsibilities, and all three play a role in crime control. As such, presidents, governors, and mayors all mention crime control in their key annual speeches. Despite the similarities, mayors face different challenges from presidents and governors, for they are not only policy makers, but are executives who must directly implement policy decisions. The results of this analysis on the city executives’ rhetoric reveal that mayors are very different from the other two executives and do not necessarily follow either the presidents’ or governors’ lead.</p>
<p>First, it was hypothesized that mayoral rhetoric on crime control issues would remain consistent each year. This would have been more reflective of the governors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>) who spoke consistently about crime from year to year, rather than the office of the presidency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0887403412446993">Marion, 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">1994a</xref>) which has increasingly dedicated more time to crime control rhetoric. For the most part, it was found that mayors neither devoted more words to crime control issues nor devoted a higher percentage of their speeches to crime over the years, as hypothesized. This means that mayors simply did not talk more about crime with each consecutive year. Thus, this hypothesis was supported by the results of the study. At the same time, this is a plausible finding because mayors, unlike presidents, needed to put crime high on their agendas and discuss crime concerns consistently over the years like governors. Crime was never a new policy arena for mayors (and governors), as it was for presidents, beginning in the early 1960s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994a</xref>). As mayors have always been responsible for the crime issue, it has remained a consistent part of their agenda; hence, the space devoted to the topic in the State of the City speeches did not increase.</p>
<p>Second, it was hypothesized that Republican and Democratic mayors would devote equal amount of their speeches on the issue of crime. Although crime is often considered to be a Republican issue, one that tends to be dominated by “get-tough” rhetoric and crime control policies, past research has demonstrated that for presidents or governors, neither party dominates the issue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0887403412446993">Oliver, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0887403412446993">2003</xref>). Republicans and Democrats talk equally on the topic, both attempting to address the problems of crime, although through very different policy proposals. In the case of mayors, however, the issue of crime was largely a Democratic topic. Although there were in fact far more Democratic mayors among the top 50 cities in the United States between 2005 and 2010, the difference in space allocated to the crime issue in their speeches by Democratic mayors was statistically significant. This may be the result of a counter by Democrats to the long held conventional wisdom, in order not to be undercut by the Republican Party on the issue of crime. Overall then, the hypothesis that crime would be equally divided was not supported by the findings.</p>
<p>The third hypothesis was that specific crime topics mentioned by mayors over the years would not change. Overall, the data did support this hypothesis. The primary issues appeared to focus first and foremost on the police, one of the largest concerns (and biggest budgetary expenditure) for a city mayor. The second topic consistently centered on general statements about crime. In nearly every case, the number of mentions from year to year on these and other subjects did not fluctuate across the time series. This is in keeping with the findings from a study on governors that found the topics they discussed changed little from year to year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>). Although it does differ from research on the presidency which finds the issues addressed were constantly changing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0887403412446993">1994b</xref>). So, although presidents perhaps chase what is popular or on the minds of the electorate, governors and mayors, closer to the realities of having to deal with crime, are more focused on issues of concern amongst their constituents.</p>
<p>The fourth hypothesis was that mayors would rely on symbolic rhetoric about crime in about half of their speeches. Presidents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0887403412446993">1994b</xref>) and governors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>) employ symbolic language in about half of their speeches, thus it was argued that mayors would be no different. The results of the current study show about 75% of the time when mayors discussed crime issues, they used symbolic language, far greater than their gubernatorial or presidential counterparts. Interestingly, at the lowest level where crime policy is executed, mayors rely more on symbolic rhetoric to convince their constituents that they are addressing the problems of crime. Perhaps this is because of the constraints (budgetary and others) and limitations in dealing with the problems of crime they face, thus necessitating mayors to direct action toward the crime problem through rhetoric, rather than actually committing to tangible policies that will require additional funding.</p>
<p>The fifth and final hypothesis, closely related to the last, is that Republican and Democratic mayors would employ symbolic language equally. Previous research finds that Republican presidents employ more symbolic language in their speeches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0887403412446993">1994b</xref>), although there was no difference amongst governors by political affiliation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>). The results of this study suggest that like presidents, Republican mayors dedicated more of their speeches to symbolic rhetoric. When combined with the fact that there were more Democratic mayors speaking more about crime, this statistically significant finding becomes even more interesting to note that it was still Republican mayors that resorted to symbolic rhetoric over Democratic mayors.</p>
<p>Overall, it is clear that mayors do not follow the same pattern as either presidents or governors when it comes to discussing the issue of crime in their State of the City speeches. In sum, two out of the five hypotheses suggested at the outset were supported by the analysis. The frequency of crime rhetoric remained the same over time and there was no change in their crime topics across time. The three hypotheses that were not supported were Republicans and Democrats speak equally (Democrats mention crime more often), half of the mayoral speeches would be symbolic (it was a full three-quarters), and that Republicans and Democrats would rely equally on symbolic rhetoric (Republicans relied more often on this type of rhetoric).</p>
<p>In terms of crime policy, it seems that mayors rely more on symbolism about crime to appease the public than either presidents or governors. These findings may be indicative of the fact that mayors, unlike the other two executives, have to deal more directly with the issue of crime. For large city mayors, crime is a daily occurrence, a daily problem, and a daily issue they must respond to, politically, economically, and organizationally. Mayors do not have the luxury of hiding behind policy debates regarding crime control policy, but are rather at the forefront of the criminal justice system, politically speaking. Recognizing the constraints they face, mayors may resort more to symbolic rhetoric as a way to show their citizens that they are doing something about crime without adding new programs or increasing the size of the city police, local courts, or jails. It may also be a reflection of the fact that presidents and governors create the new laws and policies that city mayors have to implement, thus tying their hands in regard to the laws that must be enforced and the policies implemented. This leaves mayors little room to be innovative in their own right. Thus, to get elected (or reelected), they must rely more heavily on political language that appeals to the citizenry, than proposing new tangible benefits.</p>
<p>These results may also indicate that citizens (or voters) understand that crime control is an area where governors have limited control, and presidents even less so. The “real work” on addressing crime is done at the city level. They may understand that governors have a much greater potential of having a serious impact on the enforcement of laws and execution of the policies created by the legislatures. In the end, city residents may be more accepting of symbolic language from the city mayors because of the vagaries of crime and the economic constraints of the city. Thus, when confronted with these realities they are not so much looking for an increased criminal justice presence or higher taxes to pay for that presence, but are looking for leadership to address the problems of crime.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0887403412446993" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The results of this study show that mayors do not use crime rhetoric in the exact same fashion as presidents or governors. This could be because crime control is an issue that has only recently surfaced as a presidential agenda item, although it has always been an issue for city mayors. In addition, mayors serve at the local level, a level where criminal justice is carried out, more so at least than either national or state. Although it has been said that citizens have come to look more to presidents to address the problems of crime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887403412446993">Marion, 1994a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0887403412446993">Oliver, 2003</xref>), and that they expect more from governors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887403412446993">Marion, Smith, &amp; Oliver, 2009</xref>), they may be more forgiving of the city mayors in their employment of symbolic language to demonstrate their leadership on the crime issue. Faced with the realities of crime and the limitations of both budgets and the criminal justice system, citizens may have less expectation from city leaders than they do from governors and presidents. Although citizens may expect governors to provide more tangible support, they may simply look to the mayor for leadership on the crime issue.</p>
<p>Future research into city level crime control and the context in which these symbolic speeches are given will provide a better understanding of the relationship between the electorate and mayors, thus providing a better understanding of crime as a political issue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0887403412446993">Miller, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0887403412446993">Scheingold, 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0887403412446993">1995</xref>). Additional studies on how crime is used by mayors in different types of speeches, such as inaugural addresses, may help to better define how crime is not only addressed by city mayors, but how they use it for political means. The contextual variables in which these speeches are given would also help clarify why mayors rely upon symbolic rhetoric in their state of the city speeches. Furthermore, studies that encompass a greater time frame may also uncover more patterns of mayoral rhetoric about crime over time. This study was focused on a time period after 9/11 and further removed, a study focused on 2000 to 2004, may emphasize homeland security issues more, and a pre-9/11 study may provide additional insight and demonstrate distinct differences than those found in this post-9/11 study. Of course, similar research on another local level, that of county commissioner, may also help to illuminate how, or if, symbolic rhetoric is used to reach out to citizens and voters in a similar manner as mayors.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label><p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><label>Funding</label><p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Nancy E. Marion</bold> is a professor of Political Science at the University of Akron in Akron, Ohio. She has written many books and articles that help to define the relationship between political actors and criminal justice.</p>
<p><bold>Willard M. Oliver</bold> is professor of Criminal Justice in the College of Criminal Justice at Sam Houston State University in Huntsville, Texas. He has written numerous articles and books regarding the intersection of the executive branch and crime policy, to include the Law &amp; Order Presidency (Prentice Hall, 2003).</p></bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>Agendas and instability in American politics</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Merrill</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <article-title>Citizen attitudes toward municipal reform institutions: A testing of some assumptions</article-title>. <source>Western Political Quarterly</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>274</fpage>-<lpage>283</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Calder</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Presidents and crime control: Kennedy, Johnson and Nixon and the influences of ideology</article-title>. <source>Presidential Studies Quarterly</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>574</fpage>-<lpage>589</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Calder</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>The origins and development of federal crime control policy: Herbert Hoover’s initiatives</source>. <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Praeger</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Caplan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <article-title>Reflections on the nationalization of crime, 1964-1968</article-title>. <source>Law and the Social Order</source>, <volume>1973</volume>, <fpage>583</fpage>-<lpage>635</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Presidential rhetoric and the public agenda</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Politics</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>107</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Presidential responsiveness and public policy-making: The public and the policies that presidents choose</source>. <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor, MI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>T. Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Milakovich</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <source>U.S. v. crime in the streets</source>. <publisher-loc>Bloomington, IN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Daley</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>n.d.</year>). <source>Biography for Richard M. Daley</source>. IMDB Database. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0197881/bio">http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0197881/bio</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dilulio</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saiger</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The federal role in crime control</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>J. Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petersilia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Crime</source> (pp. <fpage>445</fpage>-<lpage>462</lpage>). <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ICS</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1964</year>). <source>The symbolic uses of politics</source>. <publisher-loc>Champaign, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Illinois Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1971</year>). <source>Politics as symbolic actions: Mass arousal and acquiescence</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Markham</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>Constructing the political spectacle</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Wayne</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <source>Presidential leadership: Politics and policy making</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>St. Martin’s</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elder</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <source>Political Use of Symbols</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Longman</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fairchild</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Crime, justice and politics in the United States today</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fairchild</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>V. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The politics of crime and criminal justice</source> (pp. <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Beverly Hills, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Felkenes</surname><given-names>G. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Liberty, restraint, and criminal justice: Gerald Ford’s presidential concerns</article-title>. <source>Journal of Criminal Justice</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>-<lpage>160</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Finckenauer</surname><given-names>J. O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Crime as a national political issue: 1964-76</article-title>. <source>Crime and Delinquency</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gertson</surname><given-names>L. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Public policy making: Process and principles</source> (<edition>3rd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Armonk, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>M. E. Sharpe</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gusfield</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>). <article-title>Moral passage: The symbolic process in public designations of deviance</article-title>. <source>Social Problems</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gusfield</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <source>Symbolic crusade: Status politics and the American temperance movement</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Urbana, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Illinois Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>E. V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shull</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Policy preferences of justice and presidents</article-title>. <source>Law and Policy Quarterly</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>327</fpage>-<lpage>338</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lineberry</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heinz</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beecher</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swank</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <source>Governmental responses to crime: Crime on urban agendas</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Justice, National Institute of Justice</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaminer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Federal offense</article-title>. <source>The Atlantic Monthly</source>, <volume>273</volume>, <fpage>102</fpage>-<lpage>114</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kessel</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>). <article-title>Parameters of presidential politics</article-title>. <source>Social Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <article-title>Mayoral influence in urban policymaking</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>620</fpage>-<lpage>638</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Light</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>The president’s agenda: Domestic policy choices from Kennedy to Clinton</source> (<edition>3rd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lorinskas</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalinich</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banas</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Symbolism and rhetoric: The guardians of status quo in the criminal justice system</article-title>. <source>Criminal Justice Review</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Presidential agenda setting in crime control</article-title>. <source>Criminal Justice Policy Review</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>159</fpage>-<lpage>184</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994a</year>). <source>A history of federal crime control initiatives, 1960-1993</source>. <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Praeger</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994b</year>). <article-title>Symbolism and federal crime control legislation, 1960-1990</article-title>. <source>Journal of Crime and Justice</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Symbolic policies in Clinton’s crime control agenda</article-title>. <source>Buffalo Criminal Law Review</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Crime control in the 2000 presidential election: A symbolic issue</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Criminal Justice</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>129</fpage>-<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Gubernatorial crime control rhetoric: A study in symbolic politics</article-title>. <source>Criminal Justice Policy Review</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>457</fpage>-<lpage>474</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>The perils of federalism: Race, poverty, and the politics of crime control</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Neil</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>All politics is local: And other rules of the game</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Adams Media</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Presidential rhetoric on crime and public opinion</article-title>. <source>Criminal Justice Review</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>139</fpage>-<lpage>160</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Executive Orders: Symbolic Politics, Criminal Justice Policy and the American Presidency. American Journal of Criminal Justice</article-title>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Executive orders: Symbolic politics, criminal justice policy, and the American presidency</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Criminal Justice</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>The law and order presidency</source>. <publisher-loc>Upper Saddle River, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Following the leader? Presidential influence over Congress in the passage of federal crime control policy</article-title>. <source>Criminal Justice Policy Review</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>-<lpage>286</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Budgets, institutions and change: Criminal justice policy in America revisited</article-title>. <source>Criminal Justice Policy Review</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>451</fpage>-<lpage>467</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>War on crime: Bandits, g-men, and the politics of mass culture</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rutgers University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scheingold</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>The politics of street crime: Criminal process and cultural obsession</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scheingold</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Politics, public policy and street crime</article-title>. <source>Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science</source>, <volume>539</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>-<lpage>154</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schragger</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Can strong mayors empower weak cities? On the power of local executive in a federal system</article-title>. <source>Yale Law Journal</source>, <volume>115</volume>, <fpage>2542</fpage>-<lpage>2578</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shull</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <source>The president and civil rights policy: Leadership and change</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shull</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ringelstein</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Presidential attention, support and symbolism in civil rights, 1953-1984</article-title>. <source>Social Science Journal</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stolz</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Congress and capital punishment: An exercise in symbolic politics</article-title>. <source>Law and Policy Quarterly</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>157</fpage>-<lpage>180</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stolz</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Congress, symbolic politics and the evolution of the 1994 “Violence Against Women Act.”</article-title> <source>Criminal Justice Policy Review</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>401</fpage>-<lpage>428</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stolz</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Interpreting the U.S. human trafficking debate through the lens of symbolic politics</article-title>. <source>Law and Policy</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>311</fpage>-<lpage>338</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Seeking effective power: Why mayors need community Organizations</article-title>. <source>Perspectives on Politics</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>301</fpage>-<lpage>308</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>U.S. Census Bureau</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Retrieved from at</article-title> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.census.gov/">http://www.census.gov/</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>U.S. Conference of Mayors</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.usmayors.org/">http://www.usmayors.org/</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0887403412446993">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Less law, more order</source>. <publisher-loc>Ancaster, Ontario, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Manor House Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>