<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppia</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part A: Journal of Power and Energy</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0957-6509</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-2967</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0957650912470081</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0957650912470081</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Tidal energy resource characterization: methodology and field study in Admiralty Inlet, Puget Sound, WA (USA)</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Polagye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0957650912470081">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0957650912470081"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0957650912470081">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0957650912470081"><label>1</label>Department of Mechanical Engineering, Northwest National Marine Renewable Energy Center, University of Washington, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0957650912470081"><label>2</label>Applied Physics Laboratory, Northwest National Marine Renewable Energy Center, University of Washington, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0957650912470081">B Polagye, Department of Mechanical Engineering, Northwest National Marine Renewable Energy Center, University of Washington, Seattle, WA 98115, USA. Email: <email>bpolagye@u.washington.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>227</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>352</fpage>
<lpage>367</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Tidal energy resource characteristics are presented from a multi-year field study in northern Admiralty Inlet, Puget Sound, WA (USA). Measurements were conducted as part of a broader effort to characterize the physical and biological environment at this location ahead of a proposed tidal energy project. The resource is conceptually partitioned into deterministic, meteorological, and turbulent components. Metrics with implications for device performance are used to describe spatial variations in the tidal resource. The performance differences between passive and fixed yaw turbines are evaluated at these locations. Results show operationally significant variations in the tidal resource over length scales less than 100 m, likely driven by large eddies shed from a nearby headland. Finite-record length observations of tidal currents are shown to be acceptable for estimating device performance, but unsuitable for direct investigation of design loads.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Tidal energy</kwd>
<kwd>hydrokinetic</kwd>
<kwd>resource characterization</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0957650912470081" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>The need for sustainable energy sources has driven an interest in all types of renewable energy, including tidal hydrokinetic energy, whereby the kinetic energy of strong (&gt;1 m/s) tidal currents is converted to electricity. The devices used to achieve this are superficially similar to wind turbines and share common physical and mechanical principles. The global tidal energy resource is relatively modest at 3.7 TW and the practically extractable resource will be several orders of magnitude lower.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957650912470081">1</xref></sup> Typically, economically attractive tidal energy sites are located at relative geographic constrictions (narrows or sills) and the resource is localized over length scales on the order of kilometers. In comparison, economically viable wind and wave resources are distributed over hundreds of kilometers. These limitations are offset by the first-order predictability of the tidal resource, high average resource intensity (&gt;1 kW/m<sup>2</sup>), and the ability to leverage over 40 years of experience from wind energy and offshore oil and gas exploration.</p>
<p>Resource characterization is an early stage project development activity. One objective is to evaluate the power generation potential for a turbine at a particular location. Another is to establish design loads. A number of tidal first-generation turbine failures are ascribed to improper characterization of design loads.</p>
<p>Acoustic Doppler current profilers (ADCPs) are a standard instrument used to measure three-dimensional currents throughout the water column. ADCPs measure currents indirectly through the time dilation of backscattered acoustic pulses.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957650912470081">2</xref></sup> Pulses along three or four divergent beams return the velocity projection along each beam. The velocity projections are then used to reconstruct the full three-dimensional velocity field, and a coordinate transformation based on instrument orientation (heading, pitch, and roll) converts these measurements to a geographic reference frame
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0957650912470081"><label>(1)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math1-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>∧</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>∧</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>∧</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>u</italic>, <italic>v</italic>, and <italic>w</italic> are the north, east, and upward components of measured velocity. Because of the finite pulse length, each of these velocities includes a degree of measurement uncertainty or ‘Doppler noise.’<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957650912470081">3</xref></sup> Averaging the results from multiple pulses reduces this uncertainty, providing a more accurate estimate of the mean velocity over a sampling interval. Doppler noise has a zero mean value and known standard deviation, <italic>n</italic><sub>sample</sub>. Doppler velocimeters and electromagnetic current meters, both of which measure velocity at a point, have also been used to lesser extent in resource characterization studies.</p>
<p>Measured currents (<bold><italic>U</italic><sub>sample</sub></bold>) are conceptually partitioned into deterministic (<bold><italic>U</italic><sub>det</sub></bold>), meteorological (<bold><italic>U</italic><sub>met</sub></bold>), and turbulent (<bold><italic>U</italic><sub>turb</sub></bold>) components
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0957650912470081"><label>(2)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math2-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">U</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">sample</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">U</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">det</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">U</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">met</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">U</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">turb</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">±</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>sample</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
each of which are further subdivided. The deterministic currents include harmonic currents, described by harmonic constituents,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650912470081">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957650912470081">5</xref></sup> as well as the aharmonic response to these currents induced by local topography and bathymetry. Aharmonic currents are not described by tidal constituents, but are repeatable, site-specific flow features.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0957650912470081">6</xref></sup> Meteorological currents include wave- and wind-induced motion,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0957650912470081">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0957650912470081">8</xref></sup> residual currents associated with estuarine stratification,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0957650912470081">9</xref></sup> and storm surges.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0957650912470081">10</xref></sup> Turbulent currents include large-scale, horizontal eddies and small-scale, isotropic turbulence.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0957650912470081">11</xref></sup> The relative contribution of these elements to measured currents is site-specific.</p>
<p>This article presents results from a multi-year tidal energy resource characterization field study in northern Admiralty Inlet, Puget Sound, WA (USA) at the site of a proposed tidal energy project. Characterization metrics are used to quantify variations in the tidal resource over a range of spatial and temporal scales. Variations in the deterministic and meteorological currents are emphasized; turbulence characteristics are described elsewhere.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0957650912470081">11</xref></sup> The number and duration of stationary ADCP deployments at this location is more intensive than typical for site development. Consequently, these data provide insight into the variability that may be undersampled by common tidal energy siting practices. In combination with a simple turbine model, the operational significance of resource variability is evaluated and the performance of passive and fixed yaw turbines compared. This article extends the resource metrics described in Gooch et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0957650912470081">12</xref></sup> by quantifying the error associated with their calculation from finite-length records.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0957650912470081" sec-type="methods"><title>Methodology</title>
<sec id="sec3-0957650912470081"><title>Field measurements</title>
<p>Admiralty Inlet is a major sill at the mouth of Puget Sound. Excepting the relatively small exchange through Deception Pass, the entirety of the Puget Sound tidal prism passes through this constriction. Between Point Wilson and Admiralty Head, the channel cross section is at a minimum and current amplitude at a maximum. ADCPs were deployed repeatedly in an upward looking configuration on ballasted fiberglass tripods (Oceanscience Sea Spiders) for periods of up to three months each. The instrument head is approximately 0.7 m above the seabed and the blanking distances varied between 0.4 and1.0 m, depending on the operating frequency of the profiler. Sea Spiders were lowered to the seabed and as-deployed locations recorded by DGPS. Wire angles were minimized by drifting during deployments and recovery positions were typically within 5 m of as-deployed locations (i.e. within DGPS error). Details of each deployment are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0957650912470081">Table 1</xref> and locations shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0957650912470081">Figure 1</xref>. Site 1 is a composite record consisting of four deployments, each approximately three months in duration and located within a 20 m radius. Doppler noise in each sample (<italic>n</italic><sub>sample</sub>) is calculated by the manufacturer’s software.
<fig id="fig1-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Acoustic Doppler current profiler (ADCP) deployment locations superimposed on bathymetry: (a) reference site (1: 48.1530 N, 122.6880 W) and macro-scale comparison sites (2 and 3) and (b) reference site (2) and meso- and micro-scale comparison sites (4–8).</p>
<p>All distances are referenced to site 1. Admiralty Head is directly to the east of the site.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Doppler profiler configuration for deployments in northern Admiralty Inlet, Puget Sound, WA.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Site</th>
<th>Platform</th>
<th>Instrument</th>
<th>Deployment dates (dd/mm/yy)</th>
<th>Duration (days)</th>
<th>Mean depth (m)</th>
<th>Bin size (m)</th>
<th>Sample interval (s)</th>
<th><italic>n</italic><sub>sample</sub> (m/s)</th>
<th><italic>n</italic><sub>ensemble</sub> (m/s)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>SS #02</td>
<td>Nortek Continental 470 kHz</td>
<td>18/08/10–09/08/11</td>
<td>356</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>SS #01</td>
<td>RDI Workhorse 300 kHz</td>
<td>10/11/10–10/02/11</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>0.04</td>
<td>0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>SS #01</td>
<td>RDI Workhorse 300 kHz</td>
<td>13/02/11–09/05/11</td>
<td>85</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>0.05</td>
<td>0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>SS #03</td>
<td>Nortek AWAC 600 kHz</td>
<td>11/02/10–04/05/10</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>0.04</td>
<td>0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>SS #03</td>
<td>Nortek AWAC 600 kHz</td>
<td>20/05/09–03/08/09</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>0.05</td>
<td>0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>SS #04</td>
<td>Nortek AWAC 1 MHz</td>
<td>09/05/11–08/06/11</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>SS #03</td>
<td>Nortek AWAC 600 kHz</td>
<td>11/05/11–09/08/11</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>0.04</td>
<td>0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>SS #04</td>
<td>Nortek AWAC 1 MHz</td>
<td>05/07/11–11/08/11</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>0.01</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Velocity measurements were a component of studies to broadly characterize the physical and biological environment at this location prior to tidal turbine installation. Locations were selected based on shipboard ADCP surveys, power cable routing considerations for the proposed project, vessel traffic patterns, and biological characterization studies. Spatial variability in the tidal resource is assessed at three decadal length scales defined by the distance from the reference deployment at site 1:
<list id="list1-0957650912470081" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>macro-scale: distance greater than 1000 m (sites 2 and 3),</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>meso-scale: distance between 100 and 1000 m (sites 4–6), and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>micro-scale: distance less than 100 m (sites 7 and 8).</p></list-item>
</list>In an energetic environment, such as northern Admiralty Inlet, macro-scale variations are expected, but the magnitude of micro-scale gradients is difficult to predict a priori. For example, shipboard ADCP surveys of this site are able to identify meso-scale gradients, but cannot resolve micro-scale gradients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0957650912470081">13</xref></sup></p>
<p>Four models of Doppler profilers were used over the course of the project: RDI Workhorse (300 kHz), Nortek Continental (470 kHz), and Nortek AWAC (600 kHz and 1 MHz). All units performed well, with near-100% data return for all deployments. The instrumented Sea Spider platforms are almost neutrally buoyant (−20 kg wet weight) and are ballasted by 360 kg of lead. This was sufficient to maintain instrument stability on the cobbled seabed. During a typical deployment, each tripod generally rotated by 25–50° on the seabed during the first spring tide, but once established, did not experience further rotation (One deployment with SS #01 (300 kg of lead ballast) appears to have translated approximately 100 m from the as-deployed location, based on heading and pressure sensor logs and estimated as-recovered position. This deployment is not included in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0957650912470081">Table 1</xref> or subsequent analysis, but serves to demonstrate the marginal stability of even low-drag platforms deployed in these types of energetic environments).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0957650912470081"><title>Data preparation</title>
<p>Measured currents are evaluated to exclude low quality data from results. First, measurements in the region shadowed by the water surface are excluded. Per Brown et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0957650912470081">14</xref></sup> this region is approximately given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0957650912470081"><label>(3)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math3-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>H</italic> is the water depth and <inline-formula id="ilm1-0957650912470081"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math1-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the angle between the ADCP transducer surface and vertical (20° for RDI and 25° for Nortek). For the deployments in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0957650912470081">Table 1</xref>, the observed shadow region varies between 4 and 6 m, consistent with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-0957650912470081">equation (3)</xref> for water depths on the order of 60 m. Second, for measurements obtained with an RDI ADCP, bins with average correlation counts less than 60 are excluded. Nortek firmware automatically excludes measurements with comparably low correlation counts.</p>
<p>The sampling interval (i.e. the time between the start of each sample) varied by deployment, ranging from 1 to 60 s. During most deployments with 60 s sampling intervals, the profilers collected information for 50–75% of the interval. In post-processing, all sampled velocities are converted to 5 min ensembles (<bold><italic>U</italic><sub>ensemble</sub></bold>), filtering the majority of turbulent scale motion from the signal,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0957650912470081">11</xref></sup> while preserving the deterministic and meteorological components
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0957650912470081"><label>(4)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math4-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">U</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">ensemble</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">U</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">sample</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">U</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">det</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">U</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">met</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">U</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">turb</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">±</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>sample</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">   </mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">≈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">U</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">det</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">U</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">met</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">±</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ensemble</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula4-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
where the overbar denotes a temporal mean. This also reduces ensemble Doppler noise (<italic>n</italic><sub>ensemble</sub>) by a factor of <italic>N</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957650912470081">1</xref>/<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957650912470081">2</xref></sup> relative the original Doppler noise (<italic>n</italic><sub>sample</sub>), where <italic>N</italic> is the number of samples in the ensemble. Consequently, all ensembles underpinning this analysis have a standard error less than 0.03 m/s. This is at least an order of magnitude smaller than the sum of the deterministic and meteorological components over all stages of the tide.</p>
<p>When the vertical velocity is small, it is convenient to describe the flow field in terms of horizontal velocity (<italic>U<sub>h</sub></italic>)
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0957650912470081"><label>(5)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math5-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>±</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">u</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">v</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula5-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
where, by convention, flood is signed positive and ebb is signed negative. This reduces the three-dimensional flow field to a one-dimensional time series at each depth. Principal component analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957650912470081">15</xref></sup> is used to determine the principal axes for ebb and flood.</p>
<p>Surface-gravity waves, including swell from the Strait of Juan de Fuca and locally generated wind-waves, have orbital velocities that decay with depth from the water surface. Here, wave-orbital velocities are not expected to affect sub-surface current resource metrics or turbine performance, because the depths of interests are more than half a wavelength beneath the surface. Moreover, the wave orbital velocities are obscured in calculating the 5 min ensembles used for resource metrics, because the orbital velocities (nominally 2–12 s period) have a zero Eulerian average on time scales longer than several wave periods (e.g. 5 min). At shallower sites, wave orbital velocities may contribute significant variance to the sub-surface velocity field, but zero mean is still expected for all but the shallowest sites. To confirm these assertions, site-specific wave measurements were made from August to November 2010 using a 600 kHz AWAC deployed within several hundred meters of site 1. The AWAC recorded 1 Hz bursts of surface elevation and velocity for 10 min at the top of each hour, from which the orbital velocities at depth are calculated using the wave frequency-directional spectra and linear finite-depth theory.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0957650912470081">8</xref></sup></p>
<p>Tidal estuarine systems such as Puget Sound have sub-tidal exchange flows resulting from stratification. Here, these residual currents are evaluated using a low pass filter (PL66).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957650912470081">16</xref></sup> A half-amplitude period of 40 h is used; the tidal signal is not removed by shorter half-amplitude periods.</p>
<p>Storm surges that appreciably alter currents are uncommon in Puget Sound and none occurred during the data collection period. Similarly, given the expected deployment depth for hydrokinetic devices (e.g. &gt;5 m below the surface) and prevailing water depth (60 m), the signal from wind-driven currents is negligible at this location.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0957650912470081"><title>Resource characterization metrics</title>
<p>A representative fortnight of ADCP data is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0957650912470081">Figure 2</xref>. The magnitude and direction of the horizontal currents vary with time and vertical position. The tidal regime in northern Admiralty Inlet is characterized as mixed, mainly semidiurnal with two ebb and flood currents of unequal magnitude each lunar day.
<fig id="fig2-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Representative acoustic Doppler current profiler (ADCP) data (days 0–15 from site 5): (a) horizontal velocity magnitude and (b) horizontal velocity direction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Resource characterization metrics are used to compare locations. Only those characteristics with clear device performance or design implications are described here; a broader set are presented in Gooch et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0957650912470081">12</xref></sup></p>
<p>Four time-averaged metrics are used to describe spatial variability.
<list id="list2-0957650912470081" list-type="order">
<list-item><p><italic>Mean kinetic power density</italic> (kW/m<sup>2</sup>) – the time average of kinetic power density (<italic>K</italic>)
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-0957650912470081"><label>(6)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math6-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow/><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1 2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo/></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">ρ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathvariant="bold"/><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">U</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">h</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathvariant="bold"/><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula6-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
   where <italic>ρ</italic> is the density of seawater (nominally 1024 kg/m<sup>3</sup>). The mean kinetic power density is equivalent to the mean flux of kinetic energy through a vertical plane, and this quantity is the first-order predictor of project economics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957650912470081">17</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Mean kinetic power asymmetry</italic> (dimensionless) – the ratio of mean kinetic power density over all ebb currents to all flood currents, <inline-formula id="ilm2-0957650912470081"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math2-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ebb</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>flood</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This indicates whether power generation will be skewed toward one stage of the tide. Asymmetries may result from interactions between reflected tidal wavelengths (in an idealized embayment subjected to a single constituent harmonic forcing, peak ebb currents are slightly more intense than flood currents) or by local distortions to the harmonic currents caused by bathymetry and/or topography.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Peak velocity</italic> (m/s) – the maximum horizontal velocity observed, <inline-formula id="ilm3-0957650912470081"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math3-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>max</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Maximum currents are of interest for determining design loads. Here, the peak velocity associated with deterministic and meteorological currents are evaluated. Assessing the turbulent contribution to peak currents from ADCP data is problematic, even at high temporal resolution (e.g. 1 Hz), because Doppler uncertainty broadens the distribution of observed turbulence intensities, even for uniquely valued intensities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0957650912470081">18</xref></sup> In Thomson et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0957650912470081">11</xref></sup> a characteristic turbulent velocity fluctuation is defined, following the IEC standard for wind, however this is a statistical quantity and not equivalent to a peak turbulent velocity fluctuation.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Direction asymmetry</italic> (°) – the asymmetry between the mean direction (<inline-formula id="ilm4-0957650912470081"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math4-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) of ebb and flood, relative to bidirectional currents
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-0957650912470081"><label>(7)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math7-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>flood</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ebb</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>180</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula7-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
   The performance of a fixed yaw turbine is degraded if the current direction and rotor plane are misaligned.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Direction standard deviation</italic> (°) – the standard deviation of current direction relative to the principal axes (<italic>σ<sub>θ</sub></italic>). Around slack water, when turbines are idle, the reversing currents give rise to large, but irrelevant, direction deviations. The direction standard deviation is calculated only when the currents have fully set to ebb or flood, nominally <inline-formula id="ilm5-0957650912470081"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math5-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ≥ 0.5 m/s. As for direction asymmetry, the performance of fixed yaw turbine is degraded if the current direction is misaligned with the rotor plane.</p></list-item>
</list>The <italic>MATLAB</italic> code to calculate these, and other metrics, is available for download at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://depts.washington.edu/nnmrec/characterization">http://depts.washington.edu/nnmrec/characterization</ext-link>. All measurement time series are available for download at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://depts.washington.edu/nnmrec/project_meas.html">http://depts.washington.edu/nnmrec/project_meas.html</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0957650912470081"><title>Turbine model</title>
<p>A simple model for the performance of a hydrokinetic turbine is used to assess the operational significance of variations in the tidal resource. The properties of an unshrouded horizontal axis tidal turbine representative of commercial prototypes are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0957650912470081">Table 2</xref>. Inflow conditions over the turbine rotor are approximated by hub-height values and the device power output (<italic>P</italic>) is described as a function of horizontal velocity by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8-0957650912470081"><label>(8)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math8-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="center"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>      </mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cos</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cut</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>in</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="center" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1 2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo/></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cos</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>      </mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cut</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>in</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cos</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rated</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="center" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1 2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo/></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rated</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>   </mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rated</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula8-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-eq8.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>γ</italic> is the angle between the current and rotor plane (<italic>γ</italic> = 0 when flow is aligned with the rotor plane), <italic>D</italic> the turbine diameter (and thus <italic>π D</italic><sup>2</sup>/4 is the swept area of the turbine), <italic>η</italic><sub>p</sub> the performance coefficient of the rotor, <italic>η</italic><sub>e</sub> the efficiency of the power train (gearbox, generator, and power electronics), <italic>U</italic><sub>cut-in</sub> the speed at which the turbine begins to rotate, and <italic>U</italic><sub>rated</sub> the speed at which maximum power is generated (beyond this point, power extraction is curtailed through active pitch control, dynamic stall, or electrical control). For simplicity, the performance coefficient and power train efficiency are idealized as constant over the full range of operating conditions.
<table-wrap id="table2-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Horizontal axis turbine parameters.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Parameter</th>
<th>Value</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Rotor diameter, <italic>D</italic></td>
<td>25 m</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hub height</td>
<td>Mid-water depth  (∼30 m above seabed)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Performance coefficient, <italic>η</italic><sub>p</sub></td>
<td>50%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Power train efficiency, <italic>η</italic><sub>e</sub></td>
<td>90%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cut-in speed, <italic>U</italic><sub>cut-in</sub></td>
<td>0.7 m/s</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rated speed, <italic>U</italic><sub>rated</sub></td>
<td>2.25 m/s</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rated power</td>
<td>1.3 MW</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>A number of commercial prototype tidal turbines are fixed yaw devices (Polagye et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0957650912470081">19</xref></sup> Section 2) and cannot respond to directional fluctuations. The effect of rotor misalignment is captured, to the first order, as a cos<sup>2</sup><italic>γ</italic> reduction in power generated.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957650912470081">20</xref></sup><bold><sup>,</sup></bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0957650912470081">21</xref></sup> This is a combination of decreases in the apparent turbine swept area and in the relative inflow velocity, as reflected by the cos<sup>1/3</sup> terms in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8-0957650912470081">equation (8)</xref>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957650912470081">20</xref></sup> For a passively yawed turbine, it is assumed that <italic>γ</italic> is always equal to zero. For a fixed yaw turbine, the alignment angle that maximizes average power generation is determined iteratively. The rated speed is chosen to yield economically viable capacity factors (e.g. 30%) in a mixed, mainly semidiurnal tidal regime.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957650912470081">17</xref></sup> It is assumed that energy removal will not appreciably alter inflow conditions (e.g. average power extracted by a single device is much less than the theoretical resource limit<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0957650912470081">22</xref></sup>) and that blockage effects are negligible<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0957650912470081">23</xref></sup> given the dissimilar magnitudes of turbine swept area (∼10<sup>2</sup> m<sup>2</sup>) to channel cross-sectional area (∼10<sup>5</sup> m<sup>2</sup>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0957650912470081"><title>Performance characterization metrics</title>
<p>Performance metrics used for this analysis include:
<list id="list3-0957650912470081" list-type="order">
<list-item><p><italic>Mean power</italic> (MW) – the time average of power output (<italic>P</italic>). This is proportional, conceptually, to project revenue.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Capacity factor</italic> (%) – the ratio of average power to rated power. This is an indicator of the degree of capital utilization for a project.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Percentage of time operating</italic> (%) – the percentage of time the turbine is operating (sometimes referred to as exceedance). This is helpful to understanding the persistence of environmental stressors such as dynamic effects (i.e. rotating blade), noise, and electromagnetic fields.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0957650912470081">24</xref></sup></p></list-item>
</list>As is standard in the wind industry, rather than directly calculating power generation from an underlying time series, the data are reduced to a joint probability distribution of horizontal velocity (<italic>U<sub>h</sub></italic>) with direction (<italic>θ</italic>). Note that the joint probability distribution retains the relationship between velocity and direction, as opposed to independent probabilities distributions of each, and this is essential to correctly evaluate power output (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8-0957650912470081">equation (8)</xref>). Horizontal velocity magnitude and direction discretization to 0.1 m/s and 1° result in biases of less than 1% for mean power generation estimates relative to direct calculation from the underlying time series (not shown).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0957650912470081"><title>Metric uncertainty</title>
<p>Metrics calculated from finite-length observations may diverge from their true values (defined as the average over an infinite observation). Generically, the convergence of a metric to its true value is given by
<disp-formula id="disp-formula9-0957650912470081"><label>(9)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math9-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula9-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-eq9.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>M</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) is the time varying metric and <italic>T</italic> the length of observation. In shorthand, the averaging time for a metric is represented with a superscript and posited to have converged when <inline-formula id="ilm6-0957650912470081"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math6-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Since <italic>M<sup>∞</sup></italic> is not known a priori, this convergence can only be investigated in a proximate manner for a measured velocity consisting of deterministic, meteorological, and turbulent components. However, for the harmonic component, the value of a metric calculated over the tidal epoch (18.6 years) is likely to approach its true value (i.e. <inline-formula id="ilm7-0957650912470081"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math7-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>epoch</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). Because the aharmonic component is a non-linear response to the harmonic component, the deterministic currents should converge at a similar rate to the harmonic component. Further, if the meteorological currents are weak, convergence of the harmonic component may be a reasonable proxy for convergence of measured currents.</p>
<p>The <italic>MATLAB T_TIDE</italic> routine<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0957650912470081">25</xref></sup> is used to extract harmonic constituents from the horizontal velocity observations at mid-water from site 1. The Rayleigh criterion is slightly relaxed to 0.97, resulting in 60 constituents that are significant at 95% confidence level. A predicted time series over the tidal epoch is generated. Over longer time scales (days to years), the beating between constituents gives rise to decaying oscillations in the calculated metrics with periodicity
<disp-formula id="disp-formula10-0957650912470081"><label>(10)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math10-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>beat</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula10-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-eq10.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>For example, the beating between the principal lunar semidiurnal constituent (M2) and principal solar semidiurnal constituent (S2) gives rise to the well-known 14.8 day neap-spring cycle. Because the modulation amplitude depends on the relative amplitude of the beating constituents, the results presented here may only be applicable to mixed, mainly semidiurnal tidal regimes.</p>
<p>From the epoch prediction for horizontal velocity, 185-day records are extracted at a time resolution of 15 min, each offset by 20 days (no constituent beating at this period). This yields 336 realizations of harmonic currents over the epoch. For each realization, the rate of convergence for three metrics is evaluated:
<list id="list4-0957650912470081" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>mean kinetic power density: <inline-formula id="ilm8-0957650912470081"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math8-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>harmonic</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>harmonic</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>epoch</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>maximum velocity: <inline-formula id="ilm9-0957650912470081"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math9-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>max</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>harmonic</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo>max</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>harmonic</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>epoch</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>mean power generation: <inline-formula id="ilm10-0957650912470081"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math10-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>harmonic</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>harmonic</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>epoch</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item>
</list><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0957650912470081">Figure 3</xref> shows the convergence of mean power density, calculated from harmonic currents, to its epoch value. Given that the neap-spring cycle is the dominant beating between constituents at this location, it is unsurprising that the standard error decreases to 5% after two complete cycles (30 days). The standard error then continues a gradual, oscillatory decay, declining to 2% after 160 days. For the purpose of characterizing mean power density, a record length of 30 days, or longer than 70 days, provides 5% accuracy. When the temporal mean contains less than an integer number of beat periods (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula10-0957650912470081">equation (10)</xref>), the calculated metric will deviate from its true value. While all finite-length records, by definition, contain a non-integer number of constituent beat periods, as the record length increases the associated bias declines. For example, the local maximum in standard error at 38 days corresponds to a record length of 2.5 neap-spring cycles, where the relative position in the cycle is likely to bias the metric high or low. By 180 days, the neap-spring oscillations are less pronounced, as a consequence of the record encompassing more than a dozen beat periods. A synthetic tidal series containing only the M2 and S2 constituent (and, therefore, only a neap-spring beating) would have zero standard error for record lengths containing an integer number of beat frequencies.
<fig id="fig3-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>(a) Convergence of mean power density (calculated from harmonic currents) to its epoch value (thin lines denote individual realizations over the epoch and dashed lines denote standard error) and (b) standard error normalized by running mean power density as a function of observation time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-fig3.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0957650912470081">Figure 4</xref>, the probability of observing the maximum harmonic currents over the tidal epoch within a finite observation period is low, even for observations exceeding half a year. For example, after six months, the probability of having observed the 95th percentile harmonic currents is less than 0.8, which is insufficient to directly inform device design. For the more typical site characterization, field study lasting 30 days, the probability of having observed the 95th percentile harmonic currents is less than 0.25. This motivates statistical projections of peak velocity for device design, since direct observation is difficult.
<fig id="fig4-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>(a) Convergence of the maximum harmonic current to its epoch value (thin lines denote individual realizations over the epoch) and (b) probability of observing the <italic>N</italic>th percentile harmonic currents over a given observation time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-fig4.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0957650912470081">Figure 5</xref> shows the convergence of mean power generation, calculated from harmonic currents, to its epoch value. Convergence is qualitatively similar to mean power density, but mean power generation converges more rapidly to its epoch value than the mean power density because of the non-linear damping caused by power shed above rated speed (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8-0957650912470081">equation (8)</xref>). The standard error decreases to within 3% of its epoch value at 30 days and to within 2% after 160 days.
<fig id="fig5-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>(a) Convergence of average power generation (calculated from harmonic currents) to its epoch value (thin lines denote individual realizations over the epoch and dashed lines denote standard error) and (b) standard error normalized by running mean of power generation as a function of observation time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-fig5.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0957650912470081" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec10-0957650912470081"><title>Contribution of meteorological currents</title>
<p>Analysis of AWAC wave data (August to November 2010) indicates that surface-gravity waves in the vicinity of Admiralty Head are typically local wind-waves, with significant wave heights &lt;1 m and dominant periods &lt;4 s. According to linear finite-depth theory,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0957650912470081">8</xref></sup> the associated wave orbital velocities will decay to 0.1 m/s at depths of 5 m below the surface. Under the maximum observed wave conditions of 2.3 m significant wave height and 6.7 s dominant period, the wave orbital velocities are 0.4 m/s at a depth of 5 m below the surface and 0.1 m/s at depth of 20 below the surface. Again, these velocities are obscured (zero mean) in the 5 min ensembles, similar to the turbulent fluctuations.</p>
<p>Residual currents at site 1 are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0957650912470081">Figure 6</xref> and are representative of those over the study area. A classical circulation pattern is observed, with net outflow near the surface and net inflow near the seabed. There is also a seasonal variation, with relative maxima in the early summer (snow melt freshet) and the late fall (precipitation from strong storms). Because strong tidal exchanges over the Admiralty Inlet sill mix the water column, residual currents are strongest during neap tides and weakest during spring tides. At mid-water (30 m from seabed), residual currents are ubiquitously weak, with a maximum amplitude rarely exceeding 0.1 m/s. Closer to the seabed and surface, residual currents are more intense, approaching 0.4 m/s. Observations do not indicate measurable wind-driven currents or storm surge currents, consistent with expectations for this location.
<fig id="fig6-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Residual currents for site 1.</p>
<p>Gaps in the record correspond to recovery and redeployment of the instrumentation package.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-fig6.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The relative contribution of deterministic and meteorological currents to the measured currents, therefore, varies with depth. Over all depths, the peak deterministic (tidal) currents are nearly an order of magnitude more intense than the meteorological currents. Residual currents are significant near the surface and seabed, but not over the middle of the water column. Within 5 m of the surface, wave orbital velocities are of similar order to residual currents, but are insignificant over most of the water column.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0957650912470081"><title>Temporal and spatial variability in the tidal resource</title>
<p>Building on the analysis of metric uncertainty for the harmonic component of measured velocity, the temporal variability and, therefore, uncertainty, in all resource metrics is evaluated using mid-water data from site 1. While this is a finite-length observation, the dominant periodicities are well-represented in the year-long time series. Convergence is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0957650912470081">Figure 7</xref> for power density, direction, and maximum velocity. Mean power density and power density asymmetry converge in a manner consistent with the previous analysis of the harmonic component, providing support for the assumption that the deterministic (harmonic and aharmonic) and harmonic contributions to resource metrics converge at similar rates. Direction convergence (asymmetry and variation) appears to require longer observation times. This is counterintuitive, given that there should not be a fundamental periodicity to tidal direction. However, because a flux gate compass is only accurate to a few degrees, the variations shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0957650912470081">Figure 7</xref> are more likely attributable to sensor drift. The convergence of maximum velocity offers a cautionary example for resource characterization. While this metric appears to converge rapidly to its true value, analysis of harmonic currents suggests that it is unlikely for <inline-formula id="ilm11-0957650912470081"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math11-0957650912470081"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>max</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>l year</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mo>max</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Therefore, observed maximum velocity is likely to be lower than its true value and is reported only to demonstrate the strength of measured tidal currents at this site.
<fig id="fig7-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Convergence of resource metrics to annual average values (site 1): (a) power density, (b) mean direction, and (c) maximum velocity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-fig7.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Spatial variability is discussed in the context of three decadal length scales defined by the distance from the reference location (site 1): micro-scale for less than 100 m separation, meso-scale for 100 to 1000 m, and macro-scale for more than 1000 m. Resource characteristics for all locations are tabulated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0957650912470081">Table 3</xref> at mid-water depth. The observed macro-scale resource variations are expected given that site 2 is to the lee of the headland and site 3 is close to the channel center, away from the headland influence. Applying a 1 kW/m<sup>2</sup> threshold for an economically attractive mean power density,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957650912470081">17</xref></sup> sites 1 and 3 are candidates for tidal energy development, but site 2 is not, being close enough to the headland to be within the flood eddy (The objective of this deployment was to gather information about harbor porpoise response to passenger ferry operation. This location was never considered a likely candidate for tidal energy development and is included in this discussion to illustrate macro-scale variations in mean kinetic power density). Over meso-scale distances (sites 4–6) and micro-scale distances (sites 7–8), all sites have potential for development, but variations in power and direction metrics exceed metric uncertainty. The micro-scale variations are of particular interest for site development. For example, the mean power density at site 7 is more than 10% higher than at site 1, even though the two sites are separated by only 60 m and resource properties are evaluated at nearly the same absolute depth.
<table-wrap id="table3-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Resource characteristics at sites in northern Admiralty Inlet, Puget Sound, WA.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Site</th>
<th>Distance to site 1 (km)</th>
<th>Distance from seabed (m)</th>
<th>Mean kinetic power density<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0957650912470081">a</xref></sup> (kW/m<sup>2</sup>)</th>
<th>Mean kinetic power asymmetry</th>
<th>Directional asymmetry (°)</th>
<th>Directional variation (°)</th>
<th>Maximum velocity<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0957650912470081">b</xref></sup> (m/s)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>1.8 ± 0.04</td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>3.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>1.10</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>0.6 ± 0.02</td>
<td>7.8</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>2.60</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>1.4 ± 0.06</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>3.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>0.35</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>1.7 ± 0.07</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>3.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>0.23</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>2.1 ± 0.09</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>3.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>0.19</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>2.0 ± 0.10</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>3.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>2.0 ± 0.08</td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>3.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 <sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0957650912470081">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>2.0 ± 0.10</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>3.1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0957650912470081"><label>a</label>
<p>Standard error based on analysis of harmonic velocity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0957650912470081">Figure 3</xref>).</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0957650912470081"><label>b</label>
<p>These are likely to be understated relative to their true values for all sites given the duration of observation.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0957650912470081"><label>c</label>
<p>series truncated to 30 days so that metric uncertainty is similar to other locations surveyed.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>The bias in current strength toward ebb at sites 1 and 4–8 is likely to result from flow acceleration around the nearby headland and the separation that occurs in its lee.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0957650912470081">26</xref></sup> Admiralty Head has a length (alongshore) of 5.5 km and width (offshore) of 2.5 km. The mean depth in the near-shore area is approximately 30 m. On a strong ebb, horizontal currents exceed 2.5 m/s and are dominantly semidiurnal. Per the scaling arguments presented in Signell and Geyer,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0957650912470081">27</xref></sup> these translate to length scales for frictional dissipation and the tidal excursion of 6 and 35 km, respectively. For these values, eddy propagation would be expected to be similar to steady flow, with a characteristic eddy size comparable to the characteristic size of the headland.</p>
<p>Variations with depth for a selection of sites representing macro-, meso-, and micro-scales relative to the reference site are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0957650912470081">Figure 8</xref>. The vertical coordinate is normalized by the total water depth (<italic>H</italic>). In general, mean power density increases toward the surface, as would be expected assuming a no-slip condition at the seabed and a classic bottom boundary layer. For sites near the headland, the ebb power density is nearly twice that of flood near the seabed, but ebb and flood approach parity near the surface. Conversely, the direction asymmetry increases with distance from the seabed, exceeding 20° for locations near the reference site. Direction variation uniformly reaches a minimum at mid-water. As for the mid-water results presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0957650912470081">Table 3</xref>, comparable variations are observed over micro- and meso-scales at all depths.
<fig id="fig8-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Vertical variations in resource characteristics at sites in northern Admiralty Inlet, Puget Sound, WA.</p>
<p>Acoustic interference over dashed portion of reference site profiles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-fig8.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0957650912470081"><title>Temporal and spatial variability in turbine performance</title>
<p>Spatial variability in turbine performance is evaluated using the previously described turbine model. The uncertainty in performance metrics is investigated in a similar manner to resource characterization metrics using the long-term data from site 1. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0957650912470081">Figure 9</xref> shows the convergence of performance metrics at this location to their one-year values. As with resource metrics, convergence is in general agreement with the analysis of the harmonic component. The damping in power resulting from the rated speed is apparent, with a more rapid convergence to long-term values than for the resource characteristics. Because the operating percentage is affected in a non-linear manner by the cut-in speed (rather than rated speed), this metric converges in a different manner than mean power generation.
<fig id="fig9-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Convergence of turbine performance metrics to long-term values (site 1, passive yaw).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-fig9.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0957650912470081">Table 4</xref> presents performance metrics at difference sites for devices with mid-water hub heights. Spatial variability mirrors the trends in resource characteristics. Variability on a macro-scale is pronounced, with mean power generation at sites 2 and 3 only 30% and 80% of the site 1 value. Over meso- and micro-scales, average power generation varies by 5–10% from the reference site. This exceeds measurement uncertainty and is operationally significant in terms of cost of energy, suggesting an economic benefit to micro-siting.
<table-wrap id="table4-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Turbine performance at sites in northern Admiralty Inlet, Puget Sound, WA.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0957650912470081" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-table4.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th colspan="3"/><th colspan="3">Passive yaw</th>
<th colspan="3">Fixed yaw</th>
</tr>
<tr><th>Site</th>
<th>Distance to site 1 (km)</th>
<th>Turbine depth (m)</th>
<th>Average power output (MW)</th>
<th>Capacity factor (%)</th>
<th>Time operating (%)</th>
<th>Average power output (MW)</th>
<th>Capacity factor (%)</th>
<th>Time operating (%)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>0.35</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>0.34</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>1.07</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>2.59</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>0.29</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>0.28</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>66</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>0.35</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>76</td>
<td>0.33</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>76</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>73</td>
<td>0.37</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>73</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>0.19</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>0.38</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>76</td>
<td>0.36</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>76</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>0.06</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>0.38</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>74</td>
<td>0.36</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>0.07</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>0.38</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>75</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Operating time for devices with economically attractive capacity factors exceeds 70% at most locations. From an ecological standpoint, the stressors associated with turbine operation would be present for the majority of time, but not continuous. The operating time is strongly dependent on the device cut-in speed.</p>
<p>Performance differences between passive yaw and fixed yaw turbines are also presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0957650912470081">Table 4</xref>. The effect of off-axis flow is a function of direction asymmetry, direction variation, and power density asymmetry (e.g. the effect of direction asymmetry is muted if there is also a large power density asymmetry between ebb and flood). For sites at mid-water near the headland, the mean power generation for a fixed yaw device is, at most, 5% lower than for a passive yaw device. This may be operationally significant, but economically offset by reduced device complexity for fixed yaw turbines. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0957650912470081">Figure 10</xref>, near the seabed, the penalty for a fixed yaw devices slightly increases, with higher direction variation (<italic>σ<sub>θ</sub></italic>) dominating over lower direction asymmetry.
<fig id="fig10-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Vertical profiles of average power generation for a turbine (site 7), contrasting performance between passive and fixed yaw devices over a range of depths.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-fig10.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-0957650912470081" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>Operationally significant variations in the tidal resource (5–10% variations in mean power generation) are identified over length scales less than 100 m (micro-scale variations). This has several consequences for resource characterization activities. First, variations on these length scales are unlikely to be resolved by shipboard surveys,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0957650912470081">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0957650912470081">28</xref></sup> though such approaches are useful for mapping larger-scale variability. Second, if numerical models are used to resolve micro-scale gradients, grid resolution should be <italic>O</italic> (10 m). The magnitude of the observed micro-scale gradients may be somewhat unique to this site given the proximity to a headland (Admiralty Head at less than &lt;1 km). Site developers will need to balance the beneficial resource intensification around headlands against micro-siting difficulties and ebb/flood asymmetries. Because of these asymmetries at headland sites, passive/active yaw turbines are expected to produce somewhat more power than fixed yaw turbines (at most 5% for this location).</p>
<p>The resource metrics presented here emphasize power density over velocity. Device performance varies with the power density (velocity cubed), so mean velocity is not an inherently useful metric for tidal resource characterization. The root mean cubed velocity can be directly converted to mean power density, but can cause confusion if not carefully defined by practitioners. For mixed, mainly semidiurnal tidal energy sites, the cumulative probability density functions (CPDFs) of velocity and power density are also illuminating. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0957650912470081">Figure 11</xref>, approximately 50% of the power density (and, therefore, possible power generation) occurs at velocities greater than 2 m/s. However, these velocities occur only 10% of the time.
<fig id="fig11-0957650912470081" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>Cumulative probability density functions (CPDFs) of velocity and power density (site 1, mid-water depth).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912470081-fig11.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>These results also provide insight into data collection strategies informing device siting decisions, estimate performance, and determine design loads. For all performance metrics (and resource metrics related to performance), reasonable accuracy (i.e. standard error of 5%) is obtained from 30-day observations. In fact, the beating of harmonic constituents increases uncertainty in metrics calculated from data collected over marginally longer periods (i.e. 30–50 days). For mixed, mainly semidiurnal sites, survey periods of less than 30 days are not recommended. When the dominant velocity components are deterministic and turbulent, sampling over 30 days at a rate of 1 Hz can provide useful information about resource characteristics, device performance, and turbulent motions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0957650912470081">11</xref></sup> This type of data collection is within the capabilities of the current generation of Doppler profilers when equipped with GB-capacity storage cards and lithium-ion batteries. However, if the meteorological component is appreciable, longer-term data collection may be necessary to estimate device performance.</p>
<p>The assessment of design loads is more problematic. Specifically, the probability of observing the 90th percentile tidal epoch velocity within a 30 day period is only slightly more than 50%. Since operational lifetimes for devices are on the same order as the tidal epoch (i.e. 20 years), maximum observed currents should not be taken as a proxy for maximum expected currents over the device design lifetime. How best then to estimate design loads without resorting to extreme factors of safety? One approach is to rely on harmonic analysis to predict the deterministic component and treat turbulent and meteorological currents statistically. This is, however, problematic for three reasons. First, if the deterministic currents contain a strong aharmonic component, this will not be captured by harmonic analysis and predicted velocities may substantially under- or over-predict maximum deterministic currents. Second, accurate prediction of currents over the tidal epoch requires at least a year of data, which may be an onerous cost burden for site developers. While inference from a reference station<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957650912470081">5</xref></sup> may overcome this difficulty, preliminary analysis of tidal elevation and current constituents from this site suggest that amplitude ratios and phase differences for currents should not be assumed, without verification, to be equivalent to those of the tidal elevation constituents. Third, conventional harmonic analysis is only suitable for predicting both magnitude and direction when currents progress through an ellipse,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957650912470081">5</xref></sup> which is not always the case at energetic sites. Given the number of prototype tidal turbine failures ascribed to under-estimation of design loads, there remains a clear need to develop rigorous techniques for determining maximum design velocities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-0957650912470081" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>This article presents multi-year observations of tidal currents at a proposed tidal energy site in Admiralty Inlet, Puget Sound, WA (USA). Both the spatial variability in the tidal resource and the implications for device performance are evaluated. Resource and performance metrics are proposed that intuitively reduce the observational data for decision making purposes. These metrics show that operationally significant variations in turbine performance are likely over length scales on the order of 100 m. This has important implications for the arrangement of turbines within an array, particularly at locations close to headlands.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec15-0957650912470081"><title>Funding</title>
<p>Funding for this study is provided by the US Department of Energy and Snohomish Public Utility District (DE-FG36-08GO18179). This report was prepared as an account of work sponsored by an agency of the US Government. Neither the US Government nor any agency thereof, nor any of their employees, makes any warranty, expressed or implied, or assumes any legal liability or responsibility for the accuracy, completeness, or usefulness of any information, apparatus, product, or process disclosed, or represents that is use would not infringe privately owned rights. Reference in this study to any specific commercial product, process, or service by trade name, trademark, manufacturer, or otherwise does not necessarily constitute or imply its endorsement, recommendation, or favoring by the US Government or any agency thereof. Their views and opinions of the authors expressed in this study do not necessarily state or reflect those of the US Government or any agency thereof.</p>
</sec>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The authors thank Joe Talbert, Jeff Epler, Chris Bassett, Sam Gooch, and Capt. Andy Reay-Ellers for their assistance in collecting these data. They also thank Bob Thresher at NREL for discussions around the appropriate treatment of off-axis flows for fixed and passive yaw turbines.</p></ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0957650912470081"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arbic</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A coupled oscillator model of shelf and ocean tides</article-title>. <source>Cont Shelf Res</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>30</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>574</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0957650912470081"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Teledyne RD Instruments. <italic>Acoustic Doppler current profiler principles of operation: a practical primer</italic>. Report no. RDI P/N 951-6069-00, 2006. Poway, CA: Teledyne</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0957650912470081"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brumley</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Deines</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Performance of a broad-band acoustic Doppler current profiler</article-title>. <source>IEEE J Oceanic Eng</source> <year>1991</year>; <volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0957650912470081"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On the predictability of currents</article-title>. <source>Int Hydrographic Rev</source> <year>1983</year>; <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0957650912470081"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foreman</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsden</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>De-tiding: theory and practice</article-title>. <source>Quantitative skill assessment for coastal ocean models, coastal and estuarine studies</source>, <volume>vol. 47</volume><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Geophysical Union</publisher-name>, <year>1995</year>, pp. <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0957650912470081"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polagye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Epler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Limits to the predictability of tidal current energy</article-title><conf-name>Proceedings of the MTS/IEEE oceans 2010</conf-name><conf-date>20–23 September 2010</conf-date>. <conf-loc>Seattle, WA</conf-loc>. <publisher-loc>Piscataway, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0957650912470081"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Wind-driven circulation in the Chesapeake Bay, Winter 1975</article-title>. <source>J Phys Oceanogr</source> <year>1979</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>572</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0957650912470081"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><source>The applied dynamics of ocean surface waves</source> , <publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Scientific</publisher-name>, <year>1989</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0957650912470081"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattray</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Gravitational circulation in straits and estuaries</article-title>. <source>J Mar Res</source> <year>1966</year>; <volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0957650912470081"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><source>Tides, surges, and mean sea-level</source> , <publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley</publisher-name>, <year>1987</year>, pp. <fpage>472</fpage>–<lpage>472</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0957650912470081"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Polagye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Durgesh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Measurements of turbulence at two tidal energy sites in Puget Sound, WA (USA)</article-title>. <source>IEEE J Ocean Eng</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0957650912470081"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gooch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Polagye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Site characterization for tidal power</article-title><conf-name>Proceedings of the MTS/IEEE oceans 2009</conf-name><conf-date>26–29 October 2009</conf-date>. <conf-loc>Biloxi, MI</conf-loc>. <publisher-loc>Piscataway, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0957650912470081"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Epler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Polagye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Shipboard acoustic Doppler current profiler surveys to assess tidal current resources</article-title><conf-name>Proceedings of the MTS/IEEE oceans 2010</conf-name><conf-date>20–23 September 2010</conf-date>. <conf-loc>Seattle, WA</conf-loc>. <publisher-loc>Piscataway, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0957650912470081"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Trasvina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Estimation of surface winds from upward looking acoustic Doppler current profilers</article-title>. <source>J Geophys Res</source> <year>1992</year>; <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>17925</fpage>–<lpage>17930</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0957650912470081"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><source>Data analysis methods in physical oceanography</source> , <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>, <year>2001</year>, pp. <fpage>638</fpage>–<lpage>638</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0957650912470081"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beardsley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Limeburner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><source>CODE-2: moored array and large-scale data report</source><comment>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute Technical report no. WHOI-85-35, 1985. Woods Hole, MA: Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute, p.21</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0957650912470081"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bedard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Previsic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Polagye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>North America tidal in-stream energy conversion technology feasibility study</source><comment>Report no. EPRI TP-008-NA, 2006. Palo Alto, CA: Electrical Power Research Institute, p.9</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0957650912470081"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polagye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Noise removal from Doppler profiler measurements of turbulence</article-title>. <source>IEEE J Ocean Eng</source><comment> under revision</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0957650912470081"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Polagye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Cleve</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Copping</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Environmental effects of tidal energy development</source><comment>Report no. NMFS F/SPO-116, 2011. Silver Spring, MD: U.S. Dept. Commerce, NOAA, p.186</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0957650912470081"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On wind turbine power performance measurements at inclined airflow</article-title>. <source>Wind Energy</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0957650912470081"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bahaj</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Molland</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaplin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Power and thrust measurements of marine current turbines under various hydrodynamic flow conditions in a cavitation tunnel and a towing tank</article-title>. <source>Renewable Energy</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>426</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0957650912470081"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The power potential of tidal currents in channels</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc London Ser A</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>461</volume>: <fpage>2563</fpage>–<lpage>2572</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0957650912470081"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The efficiency of a turbine in a tidal channel</article-title>. <source>J Fluid Mech</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>588</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0957650912470081"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boehlert</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Environmental and ecological effects of ocean renewable energy development: a current synthesis</article-title>. <source>Oceanography</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0957650912470081"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pawlowicz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Beardsley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lentz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Classical tidal harmonic analysis including error estimates in MATLAB using T_TIDE</article-title>. <source>Comput Geosci</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>28</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>929</fpage>–<lpage>937</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0957650912470081"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geyer</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Signell</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Measurements of tidal flow around a headland with a shipboard acoustic Doppler current profiler</article-title>. <source>J Geophys Res</source> <year>1990</year>; <volume>95</volume>(<issue>C3</issue>): <fpage>3189</fpage>–<lpage>3197</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0957650912470081"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Signell</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Geyer</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transient eddy formation around headlands</article-title>. <source>J Geophys Res</source> <year>1991</year>; <volume>96</volume>(<issue>C2</issue>): <fpage>2561</fpage>–<lpage>2575</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0957650912470081"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Palodichuk M, Polagye B and Thomson J. Resource mapping at tidal energy sites. <italic>IEEE J Ocean Eng</italic>, in press</comment>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<app-group><app id="app1-0957650912470081"><title/>
<sec id="sec16-0957650912470081"><title>Appendix</title>
<sec id="sec17-0957650912470081"><title>Notation</title>
<p><def-list id="list5-0957650912470081">
<def-item><term><italic>D</italic></term><def><p>turbine diameter (m)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>H</italic></term><def><p>water depth (m)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>K</italic></term><def><p>kinetic power density (kW/m<sup>2</sup>)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>M</italic></term><def><p>a time varying metric describing the tidal resource or device performance</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>n</italic><sub>ensemble</sub></term><def><p>Doppler uncertainty in ensemble average currents (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>n</italic><sub>sample</sub></term><def><p>Doppler uncertainty in measured currents (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>P</italic></term><def><p>device power output (kW)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>U</italic><sub>cut-in</sub></term><def><p>the speed at which a device begins to generate power (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><bold><italic>U</italic><sub>det</sub></bold></term><def><p>deterministic component of tidal currents (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><bold><italic>U</italic><sub>ensemble</sub></bold></term><def><p>ensemble average currents (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>U<sub>h</sub></italic></term><def><p>horizontal velocity, vector sum of north and east components (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><bold><italic>U</italic><sub>met</sub></bold></term><def><p>meteorological component of tidal currents (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>U</italic><sub>rated</sub></term><def><p>the speed at which maximum power is generated by a device (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><bold><italic>U</italic><sub>sample</sub></bold></term><def><p>measured currents (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><bold><italic>U</italic><sub>turb</sub></bold></term><def><p>turbulent component of tidal currents (m/s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>γ</italic></term><def><p>angle between the current and rotor plane (°)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>η</italic><sub>e</sub></term><def><p>power train efficiency</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>η</italic><sub>p</sub></term><def><p>rotor performance coefficient</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>θ</italic></term><def><p>direction of current (°)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>ρ</italic></term><def><p>seawater density (kg/m<sup>3</sup>)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>σ<sub>θ</sub></italic></term><def><p>standard deviation of current direction (°)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>ϕ</italic></term><def><p>angle between Doppler profiler transducer surface and vertical (°)</p></def></def-item></def-list></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec18-0957650912470081">
<title>Subscripts and superscripts</title><p><def-list id="list6-0957650912470081">
<def-item><term>ebb</term><def><p>ebb tidal currents (seaward direction)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>epoch</term><def><p>an observation over the tidal epoch (18.6 years)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>flood</term><def><p>flood tidal currents (landward direction)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>harmonic</term><def><p>the harmonic component of the deterministic tidal current</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>overbar</term><def><p>time average</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>T</italic></term><def><p>length of a finite observation</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term>∞</term><def><p>an infinite observation</p></def></def-item></def-list></p>
</sec>
</sec></app></app-group></back>
</article>