<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjcn</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Child Neurol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Child Neurology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0883-0738</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1708-8283</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0883073811428379</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0883073811428379</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Vincristine-Related Neuropathy Versus Acute Inflammatory Demyelinating Polyradiculoneuropathy in Children With Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Brigo</surname>
<given-names>Francesco</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0883073811428379">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0883073811428379"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Balter</surname>
<given-names>Rita</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0883073811428379">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Marradi</surname>
<given-names>Pierluigi</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0883073811428379">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ferlisi</surname>
<given-names>Monica</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0883073811428379">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zaccaron</surname>
<given-names>Ada</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0883073811428379">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fiaschi</surname>
<given-names>Antonio</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0883073811428379">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frasson</surname>
<given-names>Emma</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0883073811428379">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bertolasi</surname>
<given-names>Laura</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0883073811428379">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0883073811428379">
<label>1</label>Department of Neurological, Neuropsychological, Morphological and Movement Sciences, Section of Clinical Neurology, University of Verona, Italy</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0883073811428379">
<label>2</label>Department of Pediatrics, University of Verona, Italy</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0883073811428379">
<label>3</label>Department of Neurology, Cittadella Hospital, Padua, Italy</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0883073811428379">Francesco Brigo, MD, Department of Neurological, Neuropsychological, Morphological and Movement Sciences, Section of Clinical Neurology, University of Verona, Piazzale L.A. Scuro, 37134 Verona, Italy Email: <email>dr.francescobrigo@gmail.com</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>867</fpage>
<lpage>874</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>23</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>30</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>10</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The objective of this study was to evaluate whether electroneurography could help in differentiating between vincristine-induced neuropathy and acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy. We performed electroneurography in 7 children from September 2006 to March 2009 admitted to receive chemotherapy including vincristine for acute lymphoblastic leukemia, in whom severe acute limb weakness developed, suggesting vincristine-induced neuropathy. Three of 7 patients had electroneurography, suggesting acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy. They received intravenous immunoglobulins without discontinuing chemotherapy, and within 10 days their electroclinical conditions improved. Although electroneurography showed only absent <italic>F</italic> waves, preventing us from reaching a definitive neurophysiological diagnosis of acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy, children’s presenting clinical manifestations, their disease course, and rapid and complete recovery after intravenous immunoglobulins argued strongly in its favor. A prompt, correct differential diagnosis of vincristine neuropathy and acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy in patients with acute lymphoblastic leukemia receiving vincristine is essential to improve disease outcome and prolong life expectancy.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy</kwd>
<kwd>acute lymphoblastic leukemia</kwd>
<kwd>electroneurography</kwd>
<kwd>chemotherapy</kwd>
<kwd>intravenous immunoglobulin</kwd>
<kwd>neurophysiological studies</kwd>
<kwd>vincristine-induced neuropathy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy is an autoimmune disorder that normally follows respiratory or gastrointestinal infections. It has also been reported in association with various hematologic conditions, including Hodgkin disease, non-Hodgkin lymphoma, and bone marrow transplantation in adult patients. The estimated incidence of acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy ranges between 1.1 and 1.8 cases per 100 000 per year with lower rates reported in children (&lt;16 years) of around 0.6/100 000 per year.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073811428379">1</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Vincristine is a chemotherapeutic drug belonging to the vinca alkaloid family of anticancer agents usually used for treating acute lymphoblastic leukemia. A frequently reported vincristine-induced adverse effect is a length-dependent sensory-motor axonal polyneuropathy that manifests in 30% to 50% of treated patients and is sometimes severe enough to cause tetraplegia. A severe and acute vincristine-induced neuropathy may occur in patients with Charcot-Marie-Tooth hereditary neuropathy type IA, even if asymptomatic for the hereditary condition.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0883073811428379">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0883073811428379"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0883073811428379">4</xref>
</sup> Acute inflammatory polyradiculoneuropathies occurring during vincristine treatment are far less frequent and almost all cases refer to adults. Some anecdotal reports describe adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia in whom acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy manifests during vincristine treatment.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0883073811428379">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0883073811428379"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0883073811428379">7</xref>
</sup> Whereas vincristine-induced neuropathy is relatively common, only 2 published reports describe acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy in children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia receiving chemotherapy including vincristine.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0883073811428379">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0883073811428379">9</xref>
</sup> Because acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy can sometimes be difficult to differentiate from vincristine-induced neuropathy, the differential diagnosis relies also on other diagnostic procedures, especially neurophysiological testing. Reaching a proper differential diagnosis is essential because the 2 conditions necessitate distinctly different therapeutic approaches and differ in disease course and quality-of-life outcomes.</p>
<p>In this study, we evaluated whether neurophysiological testing could help in defining acute neuropathy in children receiving vincristine chemotherapy for acute lymphoblastic leukemia and in making the difficult though essential differential diagnosis between vincristine-induced neuropathy and acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy. We also tried to verify our clinical experience suggesting that acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy might be more common than expected in children receiving vincristine for acute lymphoblastic leukemia.</p>
<sec id="section1-0883073811428379" sec-type="methods">
<title>Patients and Methods</title>
<p>From September 2006 to March 2009, 17 consecutive children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia were admitted to our hospital’s pediatric unit to receive chemotherapy, according to Associazione Italiana Ematologia Oncologia Pediatrica, the Italian Association of Pediatric Hematology/Oncology protocols (2000 and 2006) that included vincristine among other chemotherapy drugs (intravenous methylprednisolone, dexamethasone, daunorubicin [Daunoblastina], asparaginases, and intrathecal methotrexate). During chemotherapy, 7 of the 17 patients (4 girls and 3 boys with a median age of 6 years; range 4-10.8 y/mo) suddenly (&lt;48 hours) began to experience severe progressive lower limb weakness leading to a clinical suspicion of fulminant vincristine-induced neuropathy. All 7 children underwent neurologic studies and neurophysiological testing, that is, nerve conduction velocity studies without sedation. Two patients also had a lumbar puncture for cerebrospinal fluid analysis to detect albuminocytologic dissociation. Informed consent was obtained from all children’s parents.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0883073811428379">
<title>Results</title>
<p>In all children, acute limb weakness developed during chemotherapy for acute lymphoblastic leukemia. In 4 of the 7 children, neurologic examination (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0883073811428379">Table 1</xref>) typically found loss of deep tendon reflexes and lower limb weakness, in the distal muscles first and then at more proximal sites. Cramps and paresthesias were reported. None of these patients had cranial nerve involvement and bladder or bowel symptoms. No infectious illness preceding the onset of neurologic deficits was reported. In these children, upper and lower limb motor and sensory nerve conduction studies obtained within 3 days after the neurologic deficits developed showed neurophysiological findings consistent with a vincristine-induced axonal neuropathy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0883073811428379">Figure 1A</xref>) consisting of reduced-amplitude compound muscle action potentials and/or preserved nerve conduction velocities; F waves had normal minimal latency (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0883073811428379">Table 3</xref>); electromyography showed neurogenic abnormalities in all these children. Given the clinical features and neurophysiological findings and because none of the other chemotherapy drugs used during protocols of the Italian Association of Pediatric Hematology/Oncology (corticosteroids, daunorubicin, asparaginases, and methotrexate) except vincristine causes neurotoxicity, it was reasonable to consider these 4 children as having vincristine-induced neuropathy. They all discontinued vincristine as recommended,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0883073811428379">10</xref>
</sup> and their neurologic status progressively ameliorated within 2 months.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0883073811428379" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Clinical Data<sup>a</sup>
</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0883073811428379" xlink:href="10.1177_0883073811428379-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Patient</th>
<th>Diagnosis</th>
<th>Age, y/mo; Sex</th>
<th>Time Since Diagnosis of Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia, wk</th>
<th>Type of Chemotherapy; Cumulative VCR Dose, mg</th>
<th>Physical Examination</th>
<th>CSF Values</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>Probable AIDP</td>
<td>4; M</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>Induction; 3.45</td>
<td>Severe LLW; mild ULW; absent patellar and ankle DTR; no SA</td>
<td>NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>Probable AIDP</td>
<td>5.5; M</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>Induction; 2.3</td>
<td>Severe LLW; absent patellar DTR; no SA</td>
<td>Clear and colorless; WBC count 1; RBC count 30; protein 11 mg/dL; glucose 71 mg/dL; culture negative</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Probable AIDP</td>
<td>4.7; F</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>Reinduction; 3.5</td>
<td>LLW; absent patellar DTR; normal ankle DTR; no SA</td>
<td>Clear and colorless; WBC count 0; RBC count 0; protein 90 mg/dL; glucose 101 mg/dL; culture negative</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>VCRN</td>
<td>10.8; F</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>Induction; 1</td>
<td>Severe LLW; mild ULW; absent patellar and ankle DTR; no SA</td>
<td>NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>VCRN</td>
<td>9.1; F</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>Reinduction</td>
<td>Severe LLW; absent patellar and ankle DTR; no SA</td>
<td>NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>VCRN</td>
<td>3.7; M</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>Induction; 3</td>
<td>Severe LLW; mild ULW; absent patellar and ankle DTR; no SA</td>
<td>NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>VCRN</td>
<td>4.5; F</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>Induction; 1.8</td>
<td>Severe LLW; absent patellar and ankle DTR; no SA</td>
<td>NP</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0883073811428379">
<p>Abbreviations: CSF, cerebrospinal fluid; DTR, deep tendon reflexes; LLW, lower limb weakness; NP, not performed; RBC, red blood cell; SA, objective sensory alterations; ULW, upper limbs weakness; VCR, vincristine; WBC, white blood cell.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0883073811428379">
<p>
<sup>a</sup>Normal cerebrospinal fluid values: white blood cell count &lt;5 mm<sup>3</sup>; red blood cell (RBC) count, 0-5; protein 15-45 mg/dL; glucose 50-80 mg/dL.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig1-0883073811428379" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>A, Left and right peroneal nerve (patient 6): reduced-amplitude compound muscle action potentials. B, Right median nerve (patient 1): normal motor conduction velocity, distal motor latency and amplitude (sensitivity = 5 mV/D; time = 5 ms/D; filters = 10 Hz, 5 kHz) C, Right median nerve (patient 1): absent F waves (phase-rectified signal; sensitivity = 2 mV/vertical bar on the left; 50 μV/vertical bar on the right; time = 5 ms/D; filters = 200 Hz, 10 kHz). EDB = extensor digitorum brevis.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0883073811428379-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In the remaining 3 patients, similar to other children, neurologic examination (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0883073811428379">Table 1</xref>) invariably showed severe lower limb weakness, with absent deep reflexes. None of the 3 patients had cranial nerve involvement, bladder or bowel symptoms, or sensory abnormalities. No infectious illness preceding the onset of neurologic deficits was reported. All the children’s weakness was severe enough to interfere with autonomous gait, so that they rapidly became unable to walk unaided within 2 days from the onset. Because their clinical features strongly resembled those of the other 4 children in whom acute limb weakness developed, we found it almost impossible to clinically differentiate between the 2 groups. In these 3 patients, nerve conduction velocity examination showed a proximal conduction abnormality with absent upper and lower limb F waves, and with normal distal nerve conduction velocity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0883073811428379">Figure 1B</xref> and C), allowing us to suspect probable acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy at a very early stage. Although in some nerves compound muscle action potentials amplitude was reduced (patient 3), such an amplitude reduction by itself could not explain the absence of F waves, which instead may be explained by an extremely proximal demyelination. None of the 3 patients had slowed motor conduction velocities or prolonged motor terminal latencies (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0883073811428379">Table 2</xref>). According to recent electrodiagnostic criteria,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0883073811428379">11</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0883073811428379"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0883073811428379">13</xref>
</sup> these 3 patients were diagnosed as having probable acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0883073811428379" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Electrophysiological Findings in Children With Probable Acute Inflammatory Demyelinating Polyradiculoneuropathy<sup>a</sup>
</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0883073811428379" xlink:href="10.1177_0883073811428379-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>
</th>
<th colspan="4">Nerve Tests Before IVIG</th>
<th colspan="4">Nerve Tests 1 wk After IVIG</th>
<th colspan="4">Nerve Tests Some Months<sup>b</sup> After IVIG</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">MCV/SCV, m/s</td>
<td align="center">DML/DSL, ms</td>
<td align="center">Amplitude, mV/μV</td>
<td align="center">F wave, ms</td>
<td align="center">MCV/SCV, m/s</td>
<td align="center">DML, ms</td>
<td align="center">Amplitude, mV</td>
<td align="center">F wave, ms</td>
<td align="center">MCV/SCV, m/s</td>
<td align="center">DML, ms</td>
<td align="center">Amplitude, mV/μV</td>
<td align="center">F wave, ms</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>R median (M)</td>
<td>
<bold>48.4</bold>
</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>6.4</td>
<td>
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>56.3</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>7.4</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>8.8</td>
<td>19.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L median (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>59.3</td>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>10.1</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>53.1</td>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>9.5</td>
<td>19.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>29.8</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>31.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>30.6</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>30.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R peroneal</td>
<td>44.1</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>47.5</td>
<td>3.1</td>
<td>2. 9</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>57.1</td>
<td>3.3</td>
<td>3.2</td>
<td>33.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L peroneal</td>
<td>54.5</td>
<td>5.0</td>
<td>
<bold>1.9</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>47.5</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>
<bold>1.9</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>59.1</td>
<td>3.0</td>
<td>4.4</td>
<td>33.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R sural</td>
<td>62.8</td>
<td>1.8</td>
<td align="center">28 μV</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>74.3</td>
<td>1.79</td>
<td align="center">11 μV</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L sural</td>
<td>61.4</td>
<td>1.76</td>
<td align="center">26 μV</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>78.8</td>
<td>1.62</td>
<td align="center">19 μV</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>R median (M)</td>
<td>56.2</td>
<td>2.9</td>
<td>5.4</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>51.7</td>
<td>2.9</td>
<td>4.0</td>
<td>19.6</td>
<td>58.3</td>
<td>3.0</td>
<td>12.2</td>
<td>22.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L median (M)</td>
<td>51.9</td>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>4.9</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>63.0</td>
<td>2.7</td>
<td>
<bold>3.6</bold>
</td>
<td>19.3</td>
<td>57.4</td>
<td>2.8</td>
<td>10.4</td>
<td>20.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R ulnar (M)</td>
<td>52.4</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>
<bold>5.3</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>53.1</td>
<td>1.67</td>
<td>
<bold>4.7</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>53.6</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>10.3</td>
<td>19.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L ulnar (M)</td>
<td>54.2</td>
<td>1.75</td>
<td>
<bold>5.5</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>50.3</td>
<td>1.42</td>
<td>
<bold>4.7</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>53.8</td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>12.1</td>
<td>20.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>31.3</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>33.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>30.0</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>31.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R peroneal </td>
<td>45.2</td>
<td>2.7</td>
<td>
<bold>1.0</bold>
</td>
<td>
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>
<bold>0.9</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>47.8</td>
<td>3.1</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>33.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L peroneal</td>
<td>42.0</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>
<bold>1.0</bold>
</td>
<td>
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>
<bold>1.3</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>49.0</td>
<td>2.8</td>
<td>4.3</td>
<td>32.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R sural</td>
<td>
<bold>39.1</bold>
</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td align="center">11 μV</td>
<td> </td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>57.1</td>
<td>1.75</td>
<td align="center">13 μV</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L sural </td>
<td>
<bold>39.1</bold>
</td>
<td>1.79</td>
<td align="center">14 μV</td>
<td> </td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>57.8</td>
<td>1.73</td>
<td align="center">13 μV</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>R median (M)</td>
<td>53.6</td>
<td>3.1</td>
<td>4.2</td>
<td>
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>58.0</td>
<td>2.7</td>
<td>6.1</td>
<td>18.5</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L median (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R ulnar (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L ulnar (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>33.0</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>36.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>33.5</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>36.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R peroneal</td>
<td>41.2</td>
<td>4.1</td>
<td>
<bold>0.5</bold>
</td>
<td>
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>48.8</td>
<td>3.2</td>
<td>
<bold>0.5</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>55.4</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>5.8</td>
<td>36.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L peroneal</td>
<td>42.9</td>
<td>4.1</td>
<td>
<bold>0.47</bold>
</td>
<td>
<bold>–</bold>
</td>
<td>43.8</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>
<bold>0.5</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">
<bold>–</bold>	</td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td>4.2</td>
<td>4.0</td>
<td>38.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R sural</td>
<td>40.7</td>
<td>1.72</td>
<td align="center">17 μV</td>
<td> </td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>51.0</td>
<td>1.96</td>
<td align="center">6 μV</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L sural </td>
<td>41.7</td>
<td>1.68</td>
<td align="center">16 μV</td>
<td> </td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>50.5</td>
<td>1.88</td>
<td>
<bold>5.9 </bold>μV</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0883073811428379">
<p>Abbreviations: –, absent; DML, distal motor latency (ms); DSL, distal sensory latency (ms); L, left; M, motor; MCV, motor conduction velocity (m/s); NP, not performed/data not available; R, right; S, sensory; SCV, sensory conduction velocity (m/s).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0883073811428379">
<p>
<sup>a</sup>Abnormal findings are in bold. Motor and sensory conduction velocity, normal values: median nerve, ≥50 m/s; ulnar nerve, ≥50 m/s; peroneal nerve, ≥ 40 m/s; sural nerve, ≥40 m/s. F waves, normal values: median nerve, ≤29 m/s; ulnar nerve, ≤32 m/s; peroneal nerve, ≤43 m/s; tibial nerve, ≤56 m/s. Distal motor latency, normal values: median nerve, ≤4.0 m/s; ulnar nerve, ≤3.3 m/s; peroneal nerve, ≤6.5 m/s. Compound muscle action potential normal amplitudes: abductor pollicis brevis (median nerve), ≥4.0 mV; abductor digiti minimi (ulnar nerve), ≥6.0 mV; extensor digitorum brevis (peroneal nerve), ≥2.0 mV. Sensory nerve amplitude (sural nerve), ≥6 μV.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0883073811428379">
<p>
<sup>b</sup>15 months for patient 1; 32 months for patient 2; 48 months for patient 3.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table3-0883073811428379" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Electrophysiological Findings in Children With Vincristine-Induced Neuropathy<sup>a</sup>
</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0883073811428379" xlink:href="10.1177_0883073811428379-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>
</th>
<th colspan="4">Nerve Tests</th>
<th colspan="4">Nerve Tests Some Months<sup>b</sup> After VCR Therapy</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">MCV/SCV, m/s</td>
<td align="center">DML, ms</td>
<td align="center">Amplitude, mV/μV</td>
<td align="center">F wave, ms</td>
<td align="center">MCV/SCV, m/s</td>
<td align="center">DML, ms</td>
<td align="center">Amplitude, mV/μV</td>
<td align="center">F wave, ms</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>R median (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L median (M)</td>
<td>53.8</td>
<td>3.5</td>
<td>7.9</td>
<td>22.5</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R ulnar (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L ulnar (M)</td>
<td>57.7</td>
<td>2.7</td>
<td>
<bold>5.1</bold>
</td>
<td>23.3</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>41.8</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>40.8</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R peroneal</td>
<td>45.6</td>
<td>3.5</td>
<td>
<bold>1.8</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L peroneal</td>
<td>43.5</td>
<td>3.3</td>
<td>
<bold>1.0</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L sural </td>
<td>50.8</td>
<td>1.77</td>
<td>7.0 μV</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>R median (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L median (M)</td>
<td>53.5</td>
<td>2.3</td>
<td>10.2</td>
<td>28.8</td>
<td>60.0</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>15.1</td>
<td>22.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R ulnar (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L ulnar (M)</td>
<td>54.2</td>
<td>1.92</td>
<td>6.8</td>
<td>30.0</td>
<td>61.0</td>
<td>1.92</td>
<td>11.2</td>
<td>22.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>45.2</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>41.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>43.3</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>40.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R peroneal</td>
<td>44.4</td>
<td>3.5</td>
<td>
<bold>1.6</bold>
</td>
<td>41.7</td>
<td>52.5</td>
<td>3.5</td>
<td>3.9</td>
<td>40.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L peroneal</td>
<td>44.3</td>
<td>4.2</td>
<td>
<bold>1.2</bold>
</td>
<td>43.0</td>
<td>53.2</td>
<td>3.1</td>
<td>5.8</td>
<td>40.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L sural </td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td>2.8</td>
<td>19 μV</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>R median (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L median (M)</td>
<td>57.1</td>
<td>2.4</td>
<td>4.3</td>
<td>20.3</td>
<td>55.9</td>
<td>2.8</td>
<td>14.3</td>
<td>20.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R ulnar (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L ulnar (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>33.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>35.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R peroneal</td>
<td>48.4</td>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>
<bold>0.2</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td>49.0</td>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>4.7</td>
<td>34.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L peroneal</td>
<td>45.6</td>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>
<bold>0.1</bold>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>44.0</td>
<td>3.2</td>
<td>3.3</td>
<td>35.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L sural </td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>58.0</td>
<td>1.81</td>
<td>13 μV</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>R median (M)</td>
<td>57.7</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>4.0</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>61.5</td>
<td>2.4</td>
<td>11.5</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L median (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R ulnar (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L ulnar (M)</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>29.0</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>32.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L tibial</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>30.2</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>30.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R peroneal</td>
<td>45.0</td>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>
<bold>0.5</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td>2.8</td>
<td>4.2</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L peroneal</td>
<td>54.5</td>
<td>3.2</td>
<td>
<bold>1.3</bold>
</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td>52.0</td>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>3.9</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>R sural</td>
<td>59.3</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>7.0 μV</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>67.0</td>
<td>1.94</td>
<td>22 μV</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>L sural </td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td align="center">NP</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>71.8</td>
<td>1.81</td>
<td>19 μV</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-0883073811428379">
<p>Abbreviations: –, absent; DML, distal motor latency (ms); DSL, distal sensory latency (ms); L, left; M, motor; MCV, motor conduction velocity (m/s); NP, not performed/data not available; R, right; S, sensory; SCV, sensory conduction velocity (m/s).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-0883073811428379">
<p>
<sup>a</sup>Abnormal findings are in bold. Motor and sensory conduction velocity, normal values: median nerve, ≥50 m/s; ulnar nerve, ≥50 m/s; peroneal nerve, ≥40 m/s; sural nerve, ≥40 m/s. F waves, normal values: median nerve, ≤29 m/s; ulnar nerve, ≤32 m/s; peroneal nerve, ≤43 m/s; tibial nerve, ≤56 m/s.  Distal motor latency, normal values: median nerve, ≤4.0 m/s; ulnar nerve, ≤3.3 m/s; peroneal nerve, ≤6.5 m/s. Compound muscle action potential normal amplitudes: abductor pollicis brevis (median nerve), ≥4.0 mV; abductor digiti minimi (ulnar nerve), ≥6.0 mV; extensor digitorum brevis (peroneal nerve), ≥2.0 mV. Sensory nerve amplitude (sural nerve), ≥6 μV.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn8-0883073811428379">
<p>
<sup>b</sup>24 months for patient 5; 12 months for patient 6; 45 months for patient 7. Data of patient 4 are not available because the patient died some months after our evaluation.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>In 2 patients (patients 1 and 2, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0883073811428379">Table 1</xref>), probable acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy manifested during induction therapy given according to the Italian Association of Pediatric Hematology/Oncology Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (2006) protocol, whereas in 1 patient (patient 3) it began during reinduction therapy according to the Italian Association of Pediatric Hematology/Oncology Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (2000) protocol.</p>
<p>The vincristine dose administered in patients diagnosed as having probable acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy varied in the 3 children: patient 2 began to experience acute weakness after receiving 1.75 mg/m<sup>2</sup> of vincristine, patient 1 after 2.62 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, and patient 3 after 1.58 mg/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p>In 2 patients (patients 2 and 3), a lumbar puncture obtained on the day after the neurologic deficits began gave normal findings in patient 2, whereas in patient 3 it showed albuminocytologic cerebrospinal fluid dissociation, the classic laboratory marker of acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy. In patient 1, we did not perform cerebrospinal fluid analysis because the parents declined to give consent. All 3 children received a 5-day course of intravenous immunoglobulins 0.4 g/kg/d. During the first week after intravenous immunoglobulins began, their clinical conditions improved and they had minimal or no residual neurologic deficits: at discharge each patient was able to walk unaided. Each child continued receiving vincristine, completing the course of chemotherapy. Nerve conduction velocity studies obtained 1 week after intravenous immunoglobulin treatment was begun showed that nerve conduction velocity findings in all cases had begun to improve and late responses had reappeared; nerve conduction velocity studies performed some months later yielded normal findings (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0883073811428379">Table 2</xref>); these patients were treated with intravenous immunoglobulins and did not discontinue vincristine therapy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0883073811428379">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>During chemotherapy, 7 of the 17 patients who consecutively received chemotherapy with vincristine for acute lymphoblastic leukemia, developed acute progressive limb weakness. Although clinical features pointed to a peripheral neuropathy, neurophysiological findings allowed us to identify 2 different groups. In the first one, consisting of 3 children, electroneurography showed a severe impairment of proximal motor conductions (F waves) with a relative sparing of distal conductions and sensory nerve action potentials. In the second group, on the contrary, limb weakness was accompanied by a severe reduction of distal compound muscle action potential amplitude and of distal, as well as proximal, nerve conduction velocity, with or without impairment of sensory nerve action potentials.</p>
<p>Our study shows how neurophysiological testing can help in defining acute neuropathy in children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia receiving chemotherapy with vincristine and in making the difficult though essential differential diagnosis between vincristine-induced neuropathy and acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy. Despite our small study sample, as our previous clinical experience suggested, neurophysiological testing indicated an unexpectedly high rate of probable acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy in children receiving vincristine for acute lymphoblastic leukemia (41%). As many as 3 of the 7 children we studied had neurophysiological findings suggesting acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0883073811428379">
<title>Patients With Vincristine-Induced Neuropathy</title>
<p>Our findings in this clinical neurophysiological study confirm and extend previous information on peripheral vincristine-induced neuropathy in children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia. From a clinical point of view, our patients showed typical clinical features of vincristine-induced neuropathy, although such an acute onset and severe neurologic involvement might have suggested a coexistence of a Charcot-Marie-Tooth hereditary neuropathy type IA, which was however easily ruled out because electroneurography studies showed axonal changes. None of the patients received other drugs acting on the CYP450 enzyme pathway, thus causing excessive vincristine toxicity. Neurophysiological testing in 4 children we studied disclosed a length-dependent sensory-motor axonal polyneuropathy that developed during vincristine chemotherapy. In these children, the reduced-amplitude sensory nerve action potentials and compound muscle action potentials but preserved nerve conduction velocity values reflect distal axonal degeneration. All the children with vincristine-induced neuropathy that we studied immediately discontinued vincristine therapy according to current recommendations.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0883073811428379">7</xref>
</sup> After vincristine discontinuation, there was progressive, relatively rapid recovery, and at 8 weeks’ follow-up all children were able to walk and neurologic examination normalized. Although a possible beneficial role of intravenous immunoglobulins in vincristine-induced neuropathy cannot be ruled out a priori, we decided not to treat these children with intravenous immunoglobulins, considering that vincristine-induced neuropathy is not an immune-mediated disorder (so that there might be no rationale for the use of an immunomodulant therapy) and that there are no published recommendations regarding the use of intravenous immunoglobulins in vincristine-induced neuropathy.</p>
<sec id="section5-0883073811428379">
<title>Patients With Clinical and Neurophysiological Findings Suggesting Acute Inflammatory Demyelinating Polyradiculoneuropathy</title>
<p>Our clinical data and electrophysiologic findings in 3 children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia in whom severe acute limb weakness developed and was diagnosed as acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy add to the 2 anecdotal case reports in children.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0883073811428379">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0883073811428379">9</xref> </sup>In this small study sample, we found no evident differences between the clinical presentations in children with vincristine-induced neuropathy and acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy nor a relationship between vincristine doses administered and severity of acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy. Neurophysiological studies in our patients with severe acute limb weakness therefore proved helpful in differentiating between vincristine-induced neuropathy and acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy, thus suggesting the appropriate therapeutic management. In our patients diagnosed as having acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy, a nerve conduction velocity examination done soon after the onset of neurologic symptoms showed absent F waves, allowing us to rule out acute vincristine-induced neuropathy and indicating a proximal nerve conduction block caused by an acute demyelinating process.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0883073811428379">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0883073811428379">13</xref>
</sup> Absent F-wave responses are a nonspecific finding suggesting, though not by itself diagnostic of, acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0883073811428379">8</xref>
</sup> Also, the absence of F waves in some nerves where compound muscle action potential amplitude was also reduced (patient 3) may be explained by an extremely distal demyelination, and it is further confirmed by the return of the amplitude to a normal level at a subsequent electroneurography study. Given these neurophysiological findings are not pathognomic yet suggest acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy, and because according to the current diagnostic criteria for acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0883073811428379">14</xref>
</sup> these 3 children showed all the clinical features required for diagnosis and no features casting doubt on or excluding the diagnosis, we decided to treat the patients with intravenous immunoglobulins, a classic therapy for acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy. This management decision allowed us to see how the clinical course of their disease progressed without discontinuing vincristine and the other chemotherapy drugs. In one of the 3 patients with suspected acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy (patient 3), a lumbar puncture yielded cerebrospinal fluid showing classic albuminocytologic dissociation, whereas in another (patient 2) it yielded normal cerebrospinal fluid findings, possibly because the sample was obtained too early after the onset of acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy (as known, an increase in the cerebrospinal fluid protein may not be seen in the first 48 hours of symptoms and occasionally the cerebrospinal fluid protein remains normal for as long as a week).<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0883073811428379">15</xref>
</sup> All 3 patients promptly received intravenous immunoglobulins at standard doses (0.4 g/kg/d for 5 days) and their clinical conditions immediately began to improve. This prompt intravenous immunoglobulin–induced clinical improvement was another important feature supporting probable acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy in these children given that a good clinical response to intravenous immunoglobulin therapy would have been unlikely in children with vincristine-induced neuropathy. The only abnormal finding was the absence of F waves suggesting early stage of acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy, so that we could not make a diagnosis of definite acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy. Although only the absence of F waves prevented us from reaching a definitive neurophysiological diagnosis of acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy, the children’s clinical manifestations, together with the disease course and the rapid improvement after intravenous immunoglobulin therapy, suggested acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy. A possible explanation why our patients had absent F waves as their only electrophysiologic abnormality could be that, because they were hospitalized during chemotherapy, they underwent neurophysiological testing almost immediately after their acute muscle weakness manifested, presumably when acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy was still at a very early stage.</p>
<p>Alternatively, absence of F waves might be due to lymphoblastic infiltration of the proximal roots, but the rapid and dramatic response to vincristine and intravenous immunoglobulins, as well as the lack of radicular pain or cerebrospinal fluid pleocytosis, allowed us to rule out such a hypothesis.</p>
<p>We found a far higher rate of acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy (41%) in the children hospitalized during vincristine treatment for acute lymphoblastic leukemia than published data imply. This new finding suggests that polyradiculoneuropathy may be underestimated, possibly because acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy may clinically resemble vincristine-induced neuropathy. Our findings therefore again underline the importance of neurophysiological diagnostic studies in differentiating vincristine-induced neuropathy from acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy. Differentiating acute vincristine-induced neuropathy and acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy on a clinical basis alone may be challenging for clinicians.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0883073811428379">5</xref>
</sup> Most studies attribute the fulminant development of progressive limb weakness to vincristine and not to acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy, probably because in the rare reported cases peripheral motor neuropathy caused by chemotherapy has heretofore been considered far more frequent than acute polyradiculoneuropathy. In our children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia, we were able to differentiate between vincristine neurotoxicity and acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy only by examining findings from nerve conduction velocity studies. Electrophysiological studies are therefore of paramount importance in differentiating the 2 conditions. The neurophysiological diagnosis of acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy allows prompt treatment and, as in our patients, does not necessarily imply discontinuing vincristine and other chemotherapeutic agents. This therapeutic option is of extreme importance in ensuring a good outcome for both acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy and acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy is a monophasic disease. After patients start intravenous immunoglobulin therapy, their neurologic conditions usually return to normal with no (or minimal) neurologic deficits. This therapeutic approach also improves the outcome and quality of life for patients with acute lymphoblastic leukemia, because continuing vincristine in patients with acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy and acute lymphoblastic leukemia needing chemotherapy keeps hematologic disease under better control. Conversely, without a prompt, correct diagnosis, acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy might be erroneously diagnosed as vincristine-induced neuropathy and thus vincristine treatment might be discontinued; in these patients, acute lymphoblastic leukemia could worsen and their life expectancy may shorten.</p>
<p>The pathophysiologic basis for acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy in children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia remains unclear. Some evidence suggests immunodepression secondary to intensive chemotherapy.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0883073811428379">8</xref>
</sup> Immune system neoplasms may also act to trigger acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy in a manner similar to some viral infections.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0883073811428379">6</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>In conclusion, although our data from a small study sample should be confirmed by further epidemiologic prevalence studies, acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy developing during treatment for acute lymphoblastic leukemia may be less rare than previous reports suggest. Because in some cases, acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy may be difficult to clinically differentiate from vincristine-induced neuropathy, the differential diagnosis inevitably relies on findings from neurophysiological testing. Making a prompt, correct differential diagnosis of vincristine-induced neuropathy and acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy in patients with acute lymphoblastic leukemia under vincristine treatment does much to improve outcome, including life expectancy. If children receiving acute lymphoblastic leukemia chemotherapy manifest acute progressive limb weakness and nerve conduction velocity testing discloses absent F waves, the clinician should suspect acute polyradiculoneuropathy and undertake other diagnostic procedures (such as lumbar puncture and gadolinium-enhanced spinal magnetic resonance imaging to look for nerve root enhancement) to reach the definitive diagnosis and meanwhile institute therapy with intravenous immunoglobulins to reverse the clinical symptoms.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgment</title>
<p>We thank Francesco Passarella for graphic support.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0883073811428379">
<label>Author Contributions</label>
<p>LB conceived and designed the study. LB, FB, RB, PM, AZ, and MF were responsible for acquisition of data, and LB, FB, and EF analyzed and interpreted the data. FB drafted the manuscript, and EF, LB, and AF critically revised the manuscript for important intellectual content. Finally, LB and EF supervised the study.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn2-0883073811428379">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-0883073811428379">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0883073811428379">
<label>Ethical Approval</label>
<p>Informed parental consent was given before the electroneurography in each patient.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0883073811428379">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McGrogan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Madle</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seaman</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>de Vries</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>. The epidemiology of Guillain-Barré syndrome worldwide. A systematic literature review</article-title>. <source>Neuroepidemiology</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>150</fpage>-<lpage>163</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0883073811428379">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hildebrandt</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holler</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Woenkhaus</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Acute deterioration of Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease IA (CMT IA) following 2 mg of vincristine chemotherapy</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>743</fpage>-<lpage>747</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0883073811428379">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chauvenet</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shashi</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Selsky</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kurtzberg</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bell</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>; <article-title>Pediatric Oncology Group Study. Vincristine-induced neuropathy as the initial presentation of Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease in acute lymphoblastic leukemia: a Pediatric Oncology Group study</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Hematol Oncol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>316</fpage>-<lpage>320</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0883073811428379">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weimer</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Podwall</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Medication-induced exacerbation of neuropathy in Charcot Marie Tooth disease</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Sci</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>242</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0883073811428379">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>González Pérez</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Serrano-Pozo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Franco-Macías</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mon</surname>
</name>
<name>
<surname>tes-Latorre</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gómez-Aranda</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Campos</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Vincristine-induced acute neurotoxicity versus Guillain-Barré syndrome: a diagnostic dilemma</article-title>. <source>Eur J Neurol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>826</fpage>-<lpage>828</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0883073811428379">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Moudgil</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Riggs</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Fulminant peripheral neuropathy with severe quadriparesis associated with vincristine therapy</article-title>. <source>Ann Pharmacother</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>1136</fpage>-<lpage>1138</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0883073811428379">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vembu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Al-Shubaili</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Al-Khuraibet</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kreze</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pandita</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>Guillain-Barré syndrome in a case of acute lymphoblastic leukaemia. A case report</article-title>. <source>Med Princ Pract</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>-<lpage>275</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0883073811428379">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aral</surname>
<given-names>YZ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gursel</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ozturk</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Serdaroglu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Guillain-Barré syndrome in a child with acute lymphoblastic leukemia</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Hematol Oncol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>343</fpage>-<lpage>346</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0883073811428379">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Norman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Elinder</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Finkel</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Vincristine neuropathy and a Guillain-Barré syndrome: a case with acute lymphatic leukemia and quadriparesis</article-title>. <source>Eur J Haematol</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0883073811428379">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McCune</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lindley</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Appropriateness of maximum-dose guidelines for vincristine</article-title>. <source>Am J Health Syst Pharm</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>1755</fpage>-<lpage>1758</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0883073811428379">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Al-Shekhlee</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hachwi</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Preston</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Katirji</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>New criteria for early electrodiagnosis of acute inflammatory demyelinating polyneuropathy</article-title>. <source>Muscle Nerve</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>66</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0883073811428379">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Van den Bergh</surname>
<given-names>PY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Piéret</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Electrodiagnostic criteria for acute and chronic inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy</article-title>. <source>Muscle Nerve</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>565</fpage>-<lpage>574</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0883073811428379">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vucic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cairns</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Black</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chong</surname>
<given-names>PS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cros</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Neurophysiologic findings in early acute inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy</article-title>. <source>Clin Neurophysiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>2329</fpage>-<lpage>2335</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0883073811428379">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Asbury</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cornblath</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of current diagnostic criteria for Guillain-Barré syndrome</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>suppl</issue>): <fpage>S21</fpage>-<lpage>S24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0883073811428379">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bradshaw</surname>
<given-names>DY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Guillain-Barré syndrome in children: clinical course, electrodiagnosis, and prognosis</article-title>. <source>Muscle Nerve</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>500</fpage>-<lpage>506</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>