<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JGM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjgm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Generic Medicines: The Business Journal for the Generic Medicines Sector</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1741-1343</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-7090</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1741134312436783</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1741134312436783</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>US Legal and Regulatory Update</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A brief summary of the America Invents Act</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Braier</surname><given-names>Paul A</given-names></name><degrees>PhD, Esq</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1741134312436783">Partner, Greenblum &amp; Bernstein, P.L.C.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>29</fpage>
<lpage>32</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1741134312436783"><title>Compiled and written by Greenblum &amp; Bernstein PLC</title>
<sec id="sec2-1741134312436783"><title>—a US intellectual property law firm which provides a full range of services in IP-related matters for biotech and pharmaceutical companies, including:</title>
<p>Drafting of patent applications</p>
<p>Patent prosecution</p>
<p>Patent and trademark litigation</p>
<p>Patent infringement and validity opinions</p>
<p>Patent interferences</p>
<p>Patent reexamination proceedings (<italic>inter partes</italic> and <italic>ex parte)</italic></p>
<p>Abbreviated new drug applications (ANDAs)</p>
<p>New drug strategies</p>
<p>Market entry strategies</p>
<p>Joint venture strategies</p>
<p>Licensing</p>
<p>This section is intended to be a synopsis of recent developments and is not intended to be exhaustive. If any issue is referred to in this section is to be relied upon, specific advice should be sought. Please contact:</p>
<p>Paul Braier</p>
<p>Greenblum &amp; Bernstein PLC</p>
<p>1950 Roland Clarke Place</p>
<p>Reston, VA 20191</p>
<p>USA</p>
<p>Tel: +1 703 716 1191</p>
<p>Fax: +1 703 716 1180</p>
<p>Email: <email>PBRAIER@gbpatent.com</email></p>
<p>Web: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.gbpatent.com">www.gbpatent.com</ext-link></p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec3-1741134312436783"><title/>
<p>The America Invents Act (the AIA), signed into law on September 16, 2011, implemented the most sweeping changes to the US patent law since the modern US patent law was enacted in 1952. The AIA made major changes in almost every aspect of patent law, from procedural prosecution changes, to post-grant changes, and on through to litigation.</p>
<p>As large an impact as the change in law will have for patent practitioners, the fact is that many of the changes will have much less direct impact on industry, including the pharmaceutical industry. The most significant change—a shift from first-to-invent to first-to-file—may encourage earlier filing dates, and revises the definition of “prior art,” but may not have such a profound effect on patent applicants as it does for patent attorneys.</p>
<p>This being said, there are several changes implemented by the AIA that those in the pharmaceutical area should become familiar with. The most important of these are briefly summarized below.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec4-1741134312436783"><title>Post-grant review</title>
<p>The new post-grant review is a public procedure that may be requested by any person who is not an owner of the patent. The petitioner can request that one or more claims be canceled on almost any basis, including anticipation, obviousness, insufficient written description, or lack of enablement, but not for failure to disclose the best mode. The request may be based on any evidence, including patents, printed publications, and declarations, and must identify with particularity the claims being challenged and the evidence that supports the challenge. The real party in interest must be identified. These documents must also be sent to the patent owner. The US PTO may not authorize a post-grant review unless it determines that the evidence submitted, if not rebutted, makes it more likely than not that at least one claim is not patentable.</p>
<p>A petition for post-grant review must be filed within 9 months from issue date (or re-issue date, if appropriate) of the patent. Post-grant review is not available if the petitioner previously filed a suit for declaratory judgment of invalidity of the patent. Moreover, if the petitioner files a litigation on the same date or after a post-grant review is requested, then the litigation may be stayed (depending on the circumstances) pending resolution of the post-grant review. The US PTO must resolve a post-grant review within 1 year from authorization of the review, with a single 6-month extension being possible.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1741134312436783">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>During post-grant review, the patent owner will have one opportunity to amend the challenged claims, either by cancelation, or with proposals for substitute claims.</p>
<p>In a later litigation, the petitioner is estopped from alleging invalidity of a claim on any basis that could have reasonably been raised during the post-grant review. This also applies to later proceedings before the US PTO, and before the International Trade Commission.</p>
<p>Although post-grant review is done by the same agency that issued the patent in the first place, in the appropriate cases, it may turn out to be a more rapid and cost-effective way of dealing with validity issues than by going to court. Moreover, the decision on the post-grant review is not itself a court decision that can contribute to a failure-to-market forfeiture event (though a district court might well adopt the holding of the post-grant review, possibly contributing to a forfeiture event).</p>
<p>Post-grant review is codified in 35 U.S.C. §§ 321–329. The amendments enacting the post-grant review become effective on September 16, 2012, and yet mysteriously only apply to patents that have effective filing dates on or after March 16, 2013.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec5-1741134312436783"><title><italic>Inter Partes</italic> review</title>
<p>The new <italic>inter partes</italic> review procedure has much in common with post-grant review, yet is complementary to it in the sense that <italic>inter partes</italic> review may only be filed after 9 months from the issue date (or re-issue date) of the patent, or after termination of a post-grant review. Like the post-grant review, the petitioner must identify all evidence and arguments of invalidity of all claims asserted to be not patentable, and the real party in interest must be identified. This information must also be sent to the patent owner. The patent owner then has the opportunity to file a “preliminary response” to the request. The US PTO may not authorize an <italic>inter partes</italic> review unless it determines that the evidence submitted by the petitioner, in view of any preliminary response filed by the patent owner, establishes a reasonable likelihood that the petitioner will prevail on at least one of the challenged claims.</p>
<p>The provisions relating to length of <italic>inter partes</italic> reviews, stays of litigation, and estoppel in later proceedings are similar to the corresponding post-grant review provisions.</p>
<p>Like post-grant review, in the appropriate cases, <italic>inter partes</italic> review may turn out to be a more rapid and cost-effective way of dealing with validity issues than by going to court.</p>
<p><italic>Inter partes</italic> review is codified in 35 U.S.C. §§ 311–319. The amendments enacting the post-grant review become effective on September 16, 2012, and apply to all US patents, regardless of issue date.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec6-1741134312436783"><title>Pre-issuance submissions by third parties</title>
<p>The AIA implements a procedure by which any third party may file prior art in a pending application (the application at interest) for consideration by the examiner. The art, which must be an issued patent, a published patent application, or other printed publication, must generally be filed by 6 months from the publication date of the application at interest, or the date of the first Official Action, whichever is later. A concise statement of the relevance of the submitted prior art is also required. The submitted documents will be considered by the examiner during prosecution of the application. There is no requirement to identify the real party in interest.</p>
<p>It is important to bear in mind that, as with all art considered by the examiner, any patent that issues from the application at interest will be presumed to have a heightened presumption of validity with respect to the art submitted by the third party. Therefore, it is important that a third party submitter of prior art prepare a statement of relevance that is both thorough and easily understood by the examiner (two priorities that may at times conflict with one another).</p>
<p>In cases where a branded pharmaceutical keeps a continuation application pending, or files new evergreening patent applications on questionable aspects, third party submission of prior art may be an efficient way of putting strong prior art before the examiner for consideration.</p>
<p>The provision enacting pre-issuance submissions is codified in 35 U.S.C. § 122 (e). The procedure becomes effectives on September 16, 2012, and applies to all pending US patent applications, regardless of filing date.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec7-1741134312436783"><title>Defense to infringement based on prior commercial use</title>
<p>The older law on the prior-inventor defense to infringement has been replaced by a considerably expanded defense to infringement based on prior commercial use. Under the new law, good faith commercial use of a method, machine, composition of matter, etc., at least 1 year before the earliest filing date of a patent (or date of public disclosure by the patentee) could constitute a defense to infringement.</p>
<p>The defense is not a general patent license, and only applies to the particular prior commercial use, which may be extended to variations in quantities or volumes of the claimed subject matter. The defense does not apply to additional subject matter (e.g., in dependent claims) that was not the subject of prior commercial use. Moreover, while the defense may be generally shared among affiliates, it is generally not transferable to a third party in the absence of a sale of the company or line of business to which the defense applies. Moreover, if the prior commercial use had been abandoned, then this might result in loss of the defense.</p>
<p>It is interesting to note that the statute addresses pre-marketing regulatory review. In particular, subject matter that is subject to pre-marketing regulatory review for evaluation of safety or efficacy is deemed to be commercially used throughout the regulatory review period. The law specifically mentions that regulatory review used in calculating a Hatch-Waxman patent term extension qualifies as commercial use (e.g., NDAs for new chemical entities). However, the language of the statute is broad, and arguably also includes other NDAs, as well as ANDAs and DMFs.</p>
<p>It is expected that this defense may be of special interest to suppliers of active pharmaceutical ingredients, especially those that do research and development in the US.</p>
<p>The provision enacting the defense is codified in 35 U.S.C. § 273. The defense may be asserted with respect to any patent that issues on or after September 16, 2011.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec8-1741134312436783"><title>Supplemental examinations</title>
<p>The AIA implemented a new “supplemental examination” procedure that permits a patent owner to clean up the prosecution history in order to remove possible issues of inequitable conduct. In particular, the patent owner may file a request for supplemental examination asking the USPTO to consider, reconsider, or correct information believed relevant to the patent. The USPTO then has 3 months in which to determine whether the submitted information raises a substantial new question of patentability. If a substantial new question of patentability is raised, then the USPTO will order re-examination of the patent.</p>
<p>The effect of emerging from supplemental examination is that the patent may not be held unenforceable based on the information that was submitted and considered in the supplemental examination request.</p>
<p>A supplemental examination may not be available in two situations. The first is where the allegation of inequitable conduct was properly pled in a litigation before the supplemental examination request is made. The second is where the allegation is properly made in a Notice Letter pursuant to a Paragraph IV certification before the supplemental examination request is made.</p>
<p>The provision enacting supplemental examinations is codified in 35 U.S.C. § 257. The procedure took effect on September 16, 2011, and may be requested for any US patent, regardless of filing or issue date.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec9-1741134312436783"><title>Elimination of best mode challenges</title>
<p>The United States has long required that the specification of a patent disclose the best mode (if any) of practicing the invention contemplated by the inventors at the time the application is filed. While serious challenges to patent validity based on withholding of best mode have been rare, the assertion has often been made in litigation with sometimes significant impact on the course of discovery and other aspects of the litigation.</p>
<p>The AIA has not removed the best mode requirement, which is codified in 35 U.S.C. § 112, first paragraph (now designated § 112 (a)). The AIA has, however, essentially gutted the requirement. An allegation of violating the best mode requirement may no longer serve to invalidate a patent claim, or to result in unenforceability of a patent. However, there appears to be a split among practitioners about whether disclosure of the best mode is still required in order to perfect domestic or foreign claims of priority.</p>
<p>The effect of this change will be felt across all technologies. It will perhaps be felt especially keenly in the biotechnology and biosimilars areas, because even small process changes can have profound impact of the production of the final product. Applicants for patents may now be encouraged to withhold important process information from the patent disclosures, such as optimal process parameters known by the inventors.</p>
<p>The amendments relating to best mode challenges apply to any litigation filed on or after September 16, 2011.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec10-1741134312436783" sec-type="discussion|conclusion"><title>Discussion and conclusion</title>
<p>The AIA made a large variety of major changes to the US patent law. Some of these changes may be helpful in certain cases for generic companies (e.g., post-grant and <italic>inter partes</italic> reviews), while other changes are certainly more to the benefit of branded pharmaceuticals (e.g., elimination of best mode; and supplemental examinations).</p>
<p>The above descriptions are just brief summaries of a law that is actually quite long and complicated. Moreover, because the AIA passed into law so recently, it may be many months, or even years, before courts of law begin interpreting any given portion of the law. Nevertheless, generic companies would do well to gain at least a passing knowledge of aspects of the law that are more likely to be of potential importance to the generic industry.</p></sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1-1741134312436783"><label>1</label><p>An appeal to the Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit (whether from a district court or the USPTO) would likely add another year to the process.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</back>
</article>