<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RAS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spras</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Review of Administrative Sciences</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0020-8523</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7226</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0020852311429756</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0020852311429756</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The effect of information on oversight: the European Parliament’s response to increasing information on comitology decision-making</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Brandsma</surname><given-names>Gijs Jan</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0020852311429756"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0020852311429756">Utrecht University, The Netherlands</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0020852311429756">Gijs Jan Brandsma, Utrecht University, Utrecht School of Governance, Bijlhouwerstraat 6, Utrecht 3511 ZC, The Netherlands Email: <email>g.j.brandsma@uu.nl</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>78</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<issue-title>Symposium on government transparency: creating clarity in a confusing conceptual debate</issue-title>
<issue-title>Guest Editor: Albert J. Meijer</issue-title>
<fpage>74</fpage>
<lpage>92</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">International Institute of Administrative Sciences</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The European Parliament, like any parliament, needs information for scrutinizing executive decision-making. But how does it process this information in practice? This article focuses on the European Parliament’s increasing grip on ‘comitology’ decision-making: committees composed of national civil servants, producing executive measures that are adopted by the European Commission. Two types of changes are addressed: organizational changes and changes in working methods of EP staff. The analysis shows that the European Parliament has effectively built up a system of decentralized police-patrol oversight, but not following more information rights as such but rather as a result of its increasing political powers. The article concludes that information only affects the behaviour of the European Parliament in combination with very specific as opposed to quite general or diffuse political rights.</p>
<sec><title>Points for practitioners</title>
<p>This article traces the effects of information on the functioning of the European Parliament as an accountability forum. It concludes that information only makes a difference when coupled with very specific as opposed to very general or diffuse political rights.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>accountability</kwd>
<kwd>administrative organization and structures</kwd>
<kwd>control</kwd>
<kwd>international administration</kwd>
<kwd>transparency</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0020852311429756" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>The European Parliament, like any other parliament, needs information in order to be able to function. For its legislative function, expert information is vital so that members of parliament are able to make sound decisions with respect to the effectiveness of a particular policy. For its function of overseeing the executive and holding it to account, members of parliament need information that makes them aware of the wheelings and dealings of the executive. Although generally information on executive decision-making is of paramount importance for parliaments, the relevance of different types of information depends on the type of control that is exercised. From a checks and balances perspective, for instance, information is required that reveals whether or not the executive has exceeded its discretionary powers that are specified in legislation. A popular control perspective, by contrast, would point to information on the input and output of executive decision-making processes, in order for the legislator to be able to judge what particular preferences have in fact been translated into policies and how, and what have not been. Finally, a learning perspective would mainly require evaluative information in order for the legislator to learn from past events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0020852311429756">Bovens et al., 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>In much of the literature on government transparency and accountability in general, an ‘automatic link’ is assumed from transparency, or rather, the availability of information, to accountability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0020852311429756">Naurin, 2007</xref>). It is assumed that the mere fact that a principal is informed of the behaviour of an agent makes the agent act more in line with the preferences of the principal – whether because the agent anticipates the response of the principal or because the principal in fact responds to the information he receives (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0020852311429756">Huber, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0020852311429756">Lane, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0020852311429756">Lupia, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0020852311429756">Strøm, 2000</xref>). Information, thus, seems something of which a parliament cannot have enough. Even though the availability of more information does not necessarily make government more accountable in itself, information does contain the cues to which parliaments respond. Thus, processing information is an important precondition for evaluating the performance of government, and setting the wheels of accountability in motion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0020852311429756">Bovens, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0020852311429756">Naurin, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>But in this respect only little is known about how the European Parliament processes information. Previous work mainly addresses this issue both in abstract terms as part of a broader concept of oversight<bold>,</bold> as well as with a focus on West-European and American national parliaments (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0020852311429756">McCubbins and Schwartz, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0020852311429756">Saalfeld, 2000</xref>). This is surprising given that accountability is an issue of major concern with respect to European Union policy-making (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0020852311429756">Bovens et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0020852311429756">Gustavsson et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0020852311429756">Papadopoulos, 2010</xref>). Over recent years the repertoire of instruments available to the European Parliament in order to hold the Commission accountable has increased (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0020852311429756">Bovens et al., 2010</xref>). Nevertheless such instruments can only work to their full potential when sufficient information comes in and when this information is actually processed.</p>
<p>In this regard it must also be remembered that the European Parliament cannot easily be compared to national parliaments in Europe. All Western democratic parliamentary systems have well-established systems of interacting with the executive that are mediated by political parties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0020852311429756">Saalfeld, 2000</xref>), making control of the executive to a great degree a party political matter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0020852311429756">Peters, 2009</xref>). But the European Union works differently from the standard model. Although the legislative powers of the European Union are shared between the European Parliament and the Council of Ministers, only the European Parliament has scrutiny powers. Also, it consists of parties and transnational party groups that do not support the Commission by means of a permanent coalition of parties. This means that majorities need to be built for accepting amendments to proposed legislation, but also for budget approval or for opposing executive measures adopted by the Commission.</p>
<p>This contribution focuses on the processing of information by the European Parliament. More specifically it homes in on information on comitology: an executive decision-making mode acting under the auspices of the Commission that deals with about 60 percent of all European executive measures, and for which the European Parliament has fought a long institutional battle in order to get information and control rights (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0020852311429756">Brandsma, 2010</xref>). This means that comitology is not ‘just’ another mode of governance, but actually the main decision-making process when it comes to adopting executive measures. How does the European Parliament process information on comitology in the context of holding the Commission to account? This is the question that is central to this contribution.</p>
<p>The analysis is split into two parts. After a brief introduction on comitology and the EP’s stance towards it, the first part of the analysis presents how the parliament’s scrutiny powers and its information rights regarding comitology have developed. The second part analyses on the basis of interviews with EP staff – to whom the task of processing information is delegated – how the EP internally manages the flow of information on comitology decision-making. The article concludes that, even though in the past the EP has strongly bargained for more information so as to facilitate it in taking political action, information hardly seems to have made a difference in practice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0020852311429756"><title>Comitology and the European Parliament</title>
<p>The EP has shown itself to be very interested in controlling the executive measures that are adopted by the Commission. Obviously, executive acts are less far-reaching than legislation, but executive acts contain all the specific provisions that will effectively be applied and have an impact on the lives of citizens and the prospects of businesses throughout the community.</p>
<p>Since the 1990s, several efforts have been made to increase the transparency of the Commission towards the general public (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0020852311429756">Brandsma et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0020852311429756">Hix, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0020852311429756">Lodge, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0020852311429756">Peterson, 1995</xref>). Simultaneously, the EP has fought a long battle regarding access to Commission documents and scrutiny powers of its executive activities as well. This battle was fought out especially visibly in the realm of comitology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0020852311429756">Bradley, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0020852311429756">Türk, 2003</xref>). Comitology refers to a set of about 250 committees that are chaired by the Commission and staffed by member state civil servants, who discuss and vote on executive measures. About half of all executive Decisions, Directives and Regulations are adopted via comitology, and in addition it also deals with many executive measures that take a different form, such as annual working programmes. In total, comitology produces between 2000 and 2500 executive measures per year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0020852311429756">Brandsma, 2010</xref>). This makes comitology the main executive governance tool within the European Union.</p>
<p>The practice of establishing comitology committees has existed ever since the first years of European integration because the member states feared they would lose control over policy implementation when delegating this to the Commission. Given the fact that only member state civil servants are represented in the committees, the power of the EP has long been a contested issue. Throughout its history, the EP has consistently objected to comitology, mainly for two reasons. The first is that the Parliament wishes to be on <italic>equal footing</italic> with the Council (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0020852311429756">Bergström, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0020852311429756">Bradley, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0020852311429756">Neuhold, 2008</xref>). The Council and the EP are co-legislators, but participation in comitology committees is kept exclusive to member state representatives only. This structure made the EP fear that the Commission and the member states were able to strike politically significant deals in implementation measures instead of in normal legislation, thereby bypassing the EP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0020852311429756">Bergström, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>The second reason is that, according to the EP, comitology undermines its prerogative of <italic>executive scrutiny</italic>. As any parliament, the EP has been endowed with the task of scrutinizing the executive. However, its formal ties to the executive are mainly with the Commission as an institution. The Parliament holds the view that it should be able to control the executive in full, including comitology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0020852311429756">Neuhold, 2008</xref>). The Commission, however, has long held the view that comitology decision-making should not be subject to parliamentary control because the committees consist of member state representatives and are only chaired by the Commission. Until the Court of Justice ruled otherwise in 1997, the Commission used this as an argument for not making committee proceedings available to the public and to the EP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0020852311429756">Brandsma et al., 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>These two reasons lie at the heart of over 40 years of inter-institutional quarrelling over the Parliament’s status vis-à-vis comitology. By means of strategically blocking the legislative process, limiting the validity of certain legislation – and hence also curtailing the possibility of implementing measures via comitology – to a fixed number of years (the so-called ‘sunset clauses’) and at times even freezing parts of the Commission’s budget, it managed to secure an increasing number of scrutiny powers and information rights over comitology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0020852311429756">Bradley, 2008</xref>). This shows that the EP has very strong feelings about this, and one may therefore expect that the strengthening of the Parliament’s information rights and scrutiny powers has brought about changes in its organization. But before going into this in more detail, it is important to underline first which specific rights the Parliament actually has, and which it gained in recent years.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-0020852311429756"><title>The European Parliament’s powers of scrutiny</title>
<p>If the EP wants to take action against a comitology issue, it can choose between several options. Two of these are special rights that the EP enjoys for comitology only, and two more are generic rights that have always been in the EP’s repertoire.</p>
<sec id="sec4-0020852311429756"><title>The ‘droit de regard’ or right of scrutiny (RoS)</title>
<p>This right was introduced in the 1999 Decision on the functioning of the comitology system, allowing the Parliament to oppose a draft measure when the proposed measure exceeds the implementing powers provided for in the basic instrument. The ‘droit de regard’ only applies when the draft measure is based on a co-decision act. The Parliament can express its opposition within one month of receiving the draft measure and does so by means of a non-binding resolution. Apart from very exceptional circumstances, such a resolution first has to be voted upon by the relevant parliamentary committee, and then in plenary by means of an absolute majority.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0020852311429756">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>Conditions for using this right are thus very restrictive. The ‘droit de regard’ includes only one possible reason for objection that is extremely restrictive; and because majorities in both the EP committee and in plenary are required, whereas the EP only has plenary meetings once a month.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0020852311429756"><title>The regulatory procedure with scrutiny (RPS) and opposition to delegated acts</title>
<p>The regulatory procedure with scrutiny was agreed upon in 2006, although it builds upon a special privilege that the EP has enjoyed since 2003 in the field of financial services. As with the ‘droit de regard’, the regulatory procedure with scrutiny allows the EP to oppose a draft measure. However, such opposition does have binding effects and it may be based on reasons other than power abuse. The Parliament may also object because a draft measure is not compatible with the aim or content of the original co-decision act, or because it does not respect the principles of subsidiarity or proportionality. As a result of the entry into force of the Lisbon Treaty, this procedure will gradually be replaced by the <italic>delegated act procedure</italic> provided for in the Treaty itself, which equips the EP with unlimited grounds for objections and also the possibility of revoking the delegation of powers to the Commission. Another change is that the comitology committees involved are turned into expert groups of national administrators, which means that they lose their voting power (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0020852311429756">Brandsma and Blom-Hansen, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>A resolution for objection has to follow the same route: first it has to be accepted by the relevant parliamentary committee before it can be voted upon in plenary. Under the RPS regime, the Parliament has three months to express its objection in plenary, as opposed to only one month under the ‘droit de regard’. Again, this right only applies when the draft measure is based on a co-decision act that specifies that the Parliament can make use of such powers.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0020852311429756">2</xref></sup> Under the newly established delegated acts procedure, time limits have changed to two months, extended by another two months if the Parliament has in the meantime announced that it considers adopting a resolution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0020852311429756">Brandsma and Blom-Hansen, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>As a general rule, the RPS procedure applies when the resulting implementing acts can modify or add to so-called ‘non-essential elements’ of the original co-decision acts (i.e. annexes). Since the Lisbon Treaty changes the legal basis of Commission executive decision-making, it is not yet fully clear to which additional cases the new delegated act scheme will apply.</p>
<p>The above two rights cannot be used in a generic sense. Which of the two special rights applies is a matter that has to be negotiated when the original legislative act is decided upon between the Council and the Parliament. But besides the ‘droit de regard’ and RPS, the EP can also resort to two further courses of action that it can always use at its own discretion, either separately from or in addition to the two courses of action already mentioned.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0020852311429756"><title>The right to make statements</title>
<p>The EP can always adopt resolutions in order to make political statements. These have to follow the procedure as the above-mentioned resolutions, from individual MEPs, via a committee, to plenary.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0020852311429756">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0020852311429756">4</xref></sup> The other institutions are not bound to such resolutions in any way, but nevertheless resolutions bear a strong political message that may still have an impact.</p>
<p>A telling example is the Commission decision to put body scanners on the list of allowed security measures at airports. The Transport committee of the EP decided not to formally object to the measure, but the Civil Liberties committee drafted a statement against the use of body scanners which was accepted as a resolution in plenary. The Commission took account of this message and decided to withdraw body scanners from the list (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0020852311429756">Hardacre and Damen, 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0020852311429756"><title>Bargaining</title>
<p>Given that parliamentary committees (primarily) deal with legislative proposals, they can express their discontent in legislative negotiations with the other institutions on related issues. Because many pieces of legislation have to be revised after a number of years, the other institutions can expect stronger future demands from the EP if it feels unhappy about the adopted implementing measures. Similarly, parliamentary committees can also threaten to draft a resolution and rally support under the RPS scheme unless certain other commitments are made by the Commission on related files.</p>
<p>All of these options have in common that control is effectively exercised at the level of the parliamentary committees. Although resolutions have to be routed via plenary, the actual initiative to take such measures normally follows from the committees, which as the following section will show in more detail are also the key actors in the parliament’s information regime on comitology.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0020852311429756"><title>The European Parliament’s information rights</title>
<p>The Parliament’s successes in obtaining more scrutiny rights from 1999 onwards also necessitated the conclusion of working agreements between the Parliament and the Commission on document forwarding. The 1999 Comitology Decision already pointed out which documents the EP was entitled to receive in order to enable it to perform its right of scrutiny, but it did not further specify the conditions and procedures under which those documents were to be forwarded.</p>
<p>For that reason, the Parliament and the Commission concluded a bilateral agreement in October 2000<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0020852311429756">5</xref></sup> – well over a year after the entry into force of the 1999 Comitology Decision. It repeats the 1999 Decision in mentioning that the Parliament is to receive draft agendas for meetings, the results of voting, a list of authorities to which the member state representatives belong, summary records of the committees’ discussions and draft implementing measures that were submitted to the committees, the latter only when these are based on a co-decision act. According to the bilateral agreement, the Parliament was to receive those documents at the same time and on the same conditions as the committee members. The elaborate versions of the committees’ minutes, however, were not to be forwarded to the EP. However, pursuant to a Court ruling a few years earlier, the Parliament may request access to those minutes as well as to draft implementing measures that are not based upon a co-decision act.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0020852311429756">6</xref></sup> Since the EP has no scrutiny rights in those fields concerned, such documents could only be requested for information only. The Commission also committed itself to forward such documents electronically once the technical arrangements for that had been made.</p>
<p>For measures that relate to the financial services sector, extra information arrangements were made between the EP and the Commission between the years 2001 and 2004 which also relate to the EP’s special scrutiny powers in that field (see above). By means of a letter from Commissioner Bolkestein, the Commission and the Parliament agreed to set up regular meetings between the two institutions: monthly meetings between the secretariat of the EP’s committee on Economic Affairs and the Commission services in DG Internal Market, and regular meetings between the Commissioner and the coordinators and rapporteurs within the Economic Affairs committee (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0020852311429756">European Commission, 2001</xref>). Also, it was agreed that Commission officials would inform the EP of the discussions in comitology committees and that they would be obliged to answer any questions from the EP on such discussions, either orally or in writing.</p>
<p>In 2008, a new bilateral agreement between the EP and the Commission was concluded.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0020852311429756">7</xref></sup> It includes the same provisions as the 2000 agreement and reiterates the extra agreements that were made for the financial services sector. The only difference from the previous arrangements is that minutes are now explicitly classified as confidential documents, so that penalties can be applied if such documents are leaked. On top of the pre-existing arrangements, the new agreement also mentions the establishment of a new document register, maintained by the Commission and to which the EP has direct access, which contains all documents forwarded from the Commission to the EP including the stage of the procedure of decision-making and timetable information. The agreement also states that the EP will continue to receive documents on an individual basis by e-mail.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0020852311429756">Table 1</xref> gives an overview of the EP’s information rights regarding comitology, including the restrictions under which these rights are applied.
<table-wrap id="table1-0020852311429756" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Overview of European Parliament’s information rights for comitology</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0020852311429756" xlink:href="10.1177_0020852311429756-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th colspan="2">2000<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">2008<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>Rights</th>
<th>Restrictions</th>
<th>Rights</th>
<th>Restrictions</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Agendas Vote results Attendance lists Summary records Draft measures Minutes</td>
<td>None Only results; not how each member state voted No names or contact details included None, but documents are less specific and complete than minutes Only if act is based on a co-decision act. If not, only for information and on special request On special request only; Commission decides</td>
<td>Same as in 2000, but also: Minutes Access to document database Information on committee discussions Q&amp;A with COM- staff about committee discussions Three-level discussions</td>
<td>Same as in 2000, but classified as confidential Maintained by Commission From 2003 and for financial services only From 2003 and for financial services only From 2001 and for financial services only</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>So far, we have seen that the European Parliament has generic as well as specific scrutiny powers over comitology decision-making at its disposal, and also that it has acquired information rights over the past decade. The sheer number of comitology meetings per year (about 1000), the number of measures discussed in them (about 2000 to 2500) and the short time the EP usually has to adopt resolutions when it is able to do so (one to three months) already are indicative of the time pressure under which the Parliament has to operate. It must also be pointed out here that the EP was not ‘drowned’ by the Commission sending it all sorts of information on comitology at its own discretion, but that the EP has in fact been very persistent in requesting to be sent all these specific documents for many years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0020852311429756">Bergström, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0020852311429756">Bradley, 2008</xref>). Given the many positive effects that the literature attributes to the availability of information, such as government effectiveness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0020852311429756">Drew and Nyerges, 2004</xref>), actual pursuit of the legislator’s preferences (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0020852311429756">Strøm, 2000</xref>) and popular control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0020852311429756">Bovens, 2007</xref>), and further given the very strong interest that the EP has traditionally had in gaining information rights for comitology, one would at the very least expect to see its organization adapt to the changing circumstances. Before the EP’s system of processing all this information is elaborated, the next section first explains the research design of the empirical part of this study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0020852311429756"><title>Data and methods</title>
<p>The empirical part of this study ‘follows’ the trail of documents sent by the Commission, and closes in on two distinct types of changes in the EP’s administration. The first are structural changes: were responsibilities re-allocated, and to whom? How was the organizational structure adapted to the new situation? The second type are changing working methods of EP support staff who work with comitology documents on a day-to-day basis. How do they handle the vast amount of comitology documents? And how do they make MEPs aware of comitology issues?</p>
<p>Data have been collected by means of interviews. Since the task of processing information on comitology has been delegated to the EP’s administrators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0020852311429756">Kaeding and Hardacre, 2010</xref>), eight staff members were interviewed. Six support parliamentary committees and are in charge of informing MEPs directly on comitology affairs. Two further staff members working on comitology coordination or providing practical support on comitology horizontally in Parliament have also been interviewed. All respondents were promised anonymity. The low number of interviewees is due to the fact that, as subsequent paragraphs will show, only a few of the EP’s 18 committees deal with comitology files on a regular basis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0020852311429756"><title>The Parliament’s response to increasing amounts of information</title>
<p>Previous research into the processing of information by parliaments has shown that they have different ways of dealing with information. The famous study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0020852311429756">McCubbins and Schwartz (1984)</xref>, for instance, distinguishes between police-patrol and fire-alarm type regimes, in which the former refers to a system in which parliaments place governments under active information requirements, whereas the latter refers to a system in which parliaments rely on third parties to monitor governments, implicitly or explicitly on their behalf, who only alert parliaments in cases where they feel parliamentary attention is necessary.</p>
<p>For comitology, the EP organized a police-patrol form of oversight for itself, but in a decentralized form (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0020852311429756">McCubbins and Schwartz, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0020852311429756">Ogul and Rockman, 1990</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0020852311429756">Figure 1</xref> shows a diagram of this procedure and shows that information on comitology committee proceedings follows a lengthy route from the Commission DGs that manage the comitology committees, via several Commission and Parliamentary services, to the responsible parliamentary committees.
<fig id="fig1-0020852311429756" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Information flow from comitology committee to MEP <italic>Sources</italic>: European Parliament and Commission 2008, European Parliament 2009, Rules of Procedure of the European Parliament: Rule 88, Respondents 3, 5 and 8.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0020852311429756-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Between the Commission and the members of the parliamentary committees, two possible levels of change can be identified: changes in the attribution of responsibilities and changes in the working methods of EP administrators, who in turn inform members of parliament. These will now be addressed in turn.</p>
<sec id="sec11-0020852311429756"><title>Organizational changes</title>
<p>The increasing flow of information and powers of the EP vis-à-vis comitology decision-making have brought about two changes in the EP’s organization. They concern the secretariats of the parliamentary committees as well as the Parliament’s Receptions and Referrals Office. The Receptions and Referrals Office is the place where all documents sent to Parliament, whether by mail or electronically, are received and forwarded to the relevant people in the EP. With respect to comitology documents, this means that all incoming documents are forwarded to the secretariats of the parliamentary committees that were involved in drafting the original co-decision act upon which the Commission’s implementing measures are based.</p>
<p>The first change is that the system of how to forward the vast number of comitology documents gradually changed. Initially, the Commission did not put in the subject line what the topic of the message was, and the Receptions and Referrals office just forwarded all the incoming documents without systematically organizing them (Respondent 2). But especially from 2006, when the Parliament received more scrutiny rights under the aforementioned RPS, the need for a more systematic document handling system arose (Respondent 5). In May 2009, the Receptions and Referrals Office started using a new database system called ‘EPGreffe’ in which the Commission’s secretariat-general uploads small packs of documents. The Receptions and Referrals Office then selects to whom these documents are to be forwarded, and also checks if, where necessary, all language versions are actually included in the document packages (Respondent 8). The appropriate parliamentary committee secretariat then receives the documents in an e-mail attachment (Respondents 1, 2, 4 through 8).</p>
<p>Additionally, the Commission has committed itself to making comitology information available in a more structured and user-friendly format, both in terms of information sent to the EP as well as information released to the general public (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0020852311429756">European Parliament and European Commission, 2008</xref>). Besides sending information to the EP via the Receptions and Referrals Office, the Commission also installed its own comitology register to which EP committee staff have access. This includes the same information, but it makes it easier to find related or additional documents in the same dossiers. In practice, most EP administrators use the information that they receive via the Receptions and Referrals Office and only use the Commission’s database – if at all – when they need additional information (Respondents 1, 2, 5, 6, 7). Only one respondent primarily makes use of the Commission’s register (Respondent 4), and some also mention receiving information directly from Commission staff (Respondents 1, 5).</p>
<p>The second change, which also took place in the EP’s committee secretariats, is that dedicated staff members were recruited as from 2006. Within the Receptions and Referrals Office, one person was made responsible for handling comitology information, and within all Parliamentary committee secretariats a comitology contact person was appointed (Respondents 1 through 8). Some committees that deal with a relatively large number or heavy comitology issues (Economic Affairs, Environment and Transport) were able to hire an extra secretary because of this (Respondents 3, 5, 7).</p>
<p>Although these changes took place in the aftermath of new information agreements between the Parliament and the Commission with respect to comitology, ‘more information’ has not been their unique driving force. With respect to the first change, it does seem plausible that the new document handling system – including the allocation of a dedicated member of staff to the Receptions and Referrals Office – does indeed follow from a practical need to handle a vast amount of documents in an efficient way. But also, this need only became pressing after 2006 when the EP received more scrutiny rights (Respondent 5). There seems no relation with the number of documents that the EP receives on a regular basis, since it has been receiving large volumes of comitology documents ever since the year 2000. The number of committee meetings, for instance, and therefore also the number of agendas and meeting summaries, has been around the 1000 mark over recent years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0020852311429756">European Commission, 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0020852311429756">2009</xref>). The same can be said with respect to the second change. The parliamentary committees that have the highest comitology workload indeed were able to recruit extra staff members, but only after the 2006 Comitology Decision gave the EP an extra right of scrutiny. This too does not follow logically from the information rights that were installed in the year 2000.</p>
<p>The above shows that more information alone did not bring about organizational changes in the EP. The most significant rise in the amount of information sent to the EP, as <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0020852311429756">Table 1</xref> shows, was in the year 2000, whereas the organizational changes happened from the year in which the EP gained an extra political right: from 2006. This suggests that the need to organize information flows in an accessible manner only arises when it is instrumental to a specific parliamentary right (in this case: the right to overturn committee opinions) as opposed to an addition to existing general rights such as controlling the executive by means of asking questions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0020852311429756"><title>Working methods of EP staff</title>
<p>Students of parliamentary oversight have occasionally addressed the role that parliamentary support staff play in stimulating members of parliament to act upon their inputs, thereby strengthening their own positions within the system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0020852311429756">Aberbach, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0020852311429756">Ogul and Rockman, 1990</xref>). Dedicated staff for comitology affairs have been absent from the EP’s committees for a long time. Only since 2006 have a small number of dedicated administrators been appointed in the parliamentary committee secretariats that are explicitly responsible for comitology matters. As a result of this, it is not possible to detect changes in their working styles as a result of more EP information rights that were put in place before their appointment.</p>
<p>What can be observed as a result of the 2006 changes and the appointment of dedicated staff members, however, is that an informal coordinating network (the ‘comitology network’) was set up by the Codecision and Conciliations Unit, a unit of the EP that on a horizontal level deals with inter-institutional decision-making. The comitology network meets several times a year and brings together the comitology contact persons of the parliamentary committee secretariats, as well as staff members of the political groups. The aim of the network is to share practical problems and find common solutions or best practices, both when it comes to drafting new legislation and when keeping track of implementing measures. With respect to the latter issue, topics that are discussed frequently are, for example, the changes introduced by the Lisbon Treaty, dealing with deadlines and, interestingly, how to make MEPs aware of the importance of comitology (Respondents 1, 3, 5, 6; see further below).</p>
<p>There are significant differences between parliamentary committees with respect to the workload that comitology brings within their policy domains. There are four committees that receive more dossiers than others under the right of scrutiny and the regulatory procedure with scrutiny: Transport, Development, Agriculture, and, especially, Environment (Respondents 3, 8). Those committees, thus, have more information to process than the other committees. Do their administrative staff, who deal with information processing, have working methods that are different from those of the staff who have to process much less information on comitology affairs?</p>
<p>Within the ‘lead group’ of four committees, three comitology administrators were interviewed. Upon receipt of information from the Reception and Referrals Office, one respondent forwards each and every package of information directly to all MEPs in the committee, including an abstract of the files attached and an internal deadline before which MEPs are to let the secretariat know they would like to discuss an objection within the committee (Respondent 2). In the Environment and Transport committees, which out of these four committees also work on the bulk of the RPS files, the packages of information are collected and forwarded together with a newsletter that includes a brief summary of the attached files (Respondents 5, 7, 8). In one committee, further background to the issues is also provided by means of the newsletter (Respondent 5). The newsletters are produced between twice a week and every fortnight. This does mean that some time is eaten up by this procedure from the one to three months that the EP has to adopt a resolution in the committee and in plenary, but this way it is easier for MEPs to digest the information. In one committee, some MEPs prefer not to receive all the e-mails, but the secretariat feels it is a political responsibility to select important files, not an administrative one, and therefore still forwards all individual measures (Respondent 7).</p>
<p>In the remainder of the committees, practices are varied as well. This partly has to do with the working culture within the committees. In one committee, all files are forwarded to all members of the committee (Respondent 4), whereas in another committee these are only forwarded to the coordinators of the political groups within the committee, together with a short background note (Respondent 6). In one exceptional case, the secretariat filters out important RPS measures and forwards these to the chairman of the committee and the rapporteur of the co-decision act upon which the comitology measure is based, together with an assessment of what course of action would be most appropriate (Respondent 1). In none of those committees, however, are newsletters produced.</p>
<p>Again, it appears that a higher information load in itself does not have an impact on how EP staff members handle the incoming information, as one of the committees that are responsible for handling relatively more comitology issues applies the same working methods as those who manage relatively few issues. The distribution of newsletters is limited to the two committees that both have a high information load <italic>and</italic> work on RPS measures relatively often, being the committees of Transport and Environment. This shows again that a higher level of information in itself does not affect work practices within a parliament, but that it only has an impact in combination with more extensive and specific parliamentary powers.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-0020852311429756"><title>Political implications</title>
<p>How, then, do these changes in the Parliament’s information system and its handling of the information therein relate to the activities of MEPs? After all, this is what the Parliament’s information system is meant to support. As mentioned before, the EP has four instruments at its disposal: a right of scrutiny resolution on the legality of a certain measure; more extended veto rights under the regulatory procedure with scrutiny; the ability to make political statements through other resolutions; and the ability to threaten with all of the above in the course of a bargaining process with other institutions.</p>
<p>Measured by the frequency by which the EP deploys any of these instruments, it does not seem likely that the changing information regime has greatly affected parliamentary behaviour simply because it only rarely takes action in the first place. Between the introduction of the ‘droit de regard’ in 1999, and 2010, the EP adopted only nine resolutions on the grounds of power abuse. This low number may not be surprising given the fact that the Parliament only has one month to adopt such resolutions in plenary, and that these resolutions are not binding. In fact, they only oblige the Commission to ‘reconsider’ its measures which in a political sense means giving further explanation on the contested measure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0020852311429756">Lintner and Vaccari, 2009</xref>). The final decision thus lies with the Commission, which adopted the acts in the first place and generally does not give way to parliamentary concerns about their legality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0020852311429756">Neuhold, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>But the other rights are also hardly used in practice. Until the summer of 2010, the regulatory procedure with scrutiny, which was introduced in 2006, had resulted in just three parliamentary vetoes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0020852311429756">Kaeding and Hardacre, 2010</xref>). Five further veto attempts failed in committee, and one final veto attempt was voted down in plenary by a very narrow margin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0020852311429756">Kaeding and Hardacre, 2010</xref>). Those numbers in relative terms are substantially higher than with the ordinary right of scrutiny, but remain quite low in absolute terms. Even lower figures can be seen for other courses of action, such as making political statements through resolutions. Besides Parliament’s success with respect to body scanners, mentioned earlier (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0020852311429756">Hardacre and Damen, 2009</xref>), only two further resolutions of this type were adopted between 1999 and 2005 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0020852311429756">Lintner and Vaccari, 2009</xref>). Only once has a veto threat alone made the Commission withdraw its measure, and twice was a veto threat used as a bargaining chip for future legislative processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0020852311429756">Kaeding and Hardacre, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Thus, all in all the harvest of ten years of parliamentary scrutiny rights is rather meagre when compared to the vast number of measures on which the EP receives information. Obviously failure to put forward objections, in whatever form, may be indicative of consent to the adopted measure, but it is observationally equivalent to parliamentary working structures hindering scrutiny or to a lack of awareness more generally. At the very least, one might have expected to see comitology affairs discussed more often during committee meetings. It has recently been put forward that the lack thereof may have to do with lack of political interest in technical matters for which tight deadlines apply (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0020852311429756">Kaeding and Hardacre, 2010</xref>), and this also corresponds to the reading of insiders. There are very few reactions to comitology documents, so that comitology issues are only rarely placed on the parliamentary committee’s agenda (Respondent 2). According to an experienced official who works on horizontal comitology issues, before 2007 neither MEPs nor EP officials cared about comitology at all (Respondent 3). But gradually, interest rose as a result of the new possibilities that the regulatory procedure with scrutiny brought to the EP, and because the aforementioned ‘comitology network’ helped the committee administrators in raising awareness.</p>
<p>This also brings us, again, to procedural incentives as an alternative but stronger explanation. The introduction of the regulatory procedure with scrutiny in 2006 led to changes in the EP’s document handling system, and EP committee support staff also disseminate information in a more accessible format when a committee handles a relatively large number of RPS measures. Despite its tight deadlines, the relative strength of the RPS procedure also stimulates interest in controlling decision-making because resolutions adopted pursuant to the weaker ‘right of scrutiny’ do not have binding effects (Respondents 1 through 5). The implication of this is that the EP’s information regime is partly disjointed from the control that it exercises in practice. Overall, selection is based on procedural incentives as opposed to content.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-0020852311429756" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In many policy documents as well as in many studies of governance, transparency is hailed as the panacea for confronting almost all the EU’s alleged legitimacy problems, from increasing its legitimacy in a more general sense (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0020852311429756">Corbett et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0020852311429756">Eriksen and Fossum, 2002</xref>) to, specifically, increasing popular trust (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0020852311429756">Majone, 2000</xref>), government effectiveness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0020852311429756">Drew and Nyerges, 2004</xref>) and control over the executive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0020852311429756">Héritier, 2003</xref>). Especially in the latter part of the literature, an ‘automatic link’ is assumed from transparency, or the availability of information, to accountability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0020852311429756">Naurin, 2007</xref>). It is assumed that the mere fact that principals are informed of the behaviour of an agent make it act more in line with the preferences of the principals (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0020852311429756">Huber, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0020852311429756">Lane, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0020852311429756">Lupia, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0020852311429756">Strøm, 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>This article has investigated how the EP processes information on comitology decision-making. Although it is not possible to find out empirically what the outputs of comitology decision-making would have been in the absence of parliamentary control, one would expect the EP to use information on comitology to a great degree. It has expressed interest in controlling comitology ever since the early 1960s, and started receiving more information on comitology at the turn of the century. This was expected to have a major impact on the degree to which the Parliament takes action with respect to comitology decision-making.</p>
<p>Even though information is seen as a necessary precondition of accountability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0020852311429756">Bovens, 2007</xref>), this article has shown that the increase in information on comitology seems to have hardly affected the way in which the EP controls it. Although the Parliament has always had means of controlling comitology at its disposal, it did not enjoy substantial ‘special’ scrutiny rights until 2006. From the interviews it appears as if the Parliament did not respond to increasing amounts of information per se, but rather it has been waiting for extra scrutiny rights before beginning to process incoming information systematically. Only then did changes take place in the EP’s organization and in the working methods of its administrative staff.</p>
<p>New changes in the EP’s scrutiny rights are under way. As was already briefly mentioned before, the Lisbon Treaty has introduced a split in the legal basis of comitology decision-making between ‘delegated acts’ (Article 290) and ‘implementing acts’ (Article 291). The delegated acts regime provides for parliamentary control rights which are slightly broader than the current regulatory procedure with scrutiny, as well as for an informal system of member state expert groups. The implementing acts regime is very closely modelled on the traditional comitology system, excluding the regulatory procedure with scrutiny (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0020852311429756">Brandsma and Blom-Hansen, 2011</xref>). If current practices of information processing continue, it seems likely that the EP will focus on controlling delegated acts since this comes with more procedural incentives, while leaving implementing measures barely attended.</p>
<p>As the above exploration shows, overseeing comitology measures on a day-to-day basis is a daunting task, and for many committees too much for MEPs to handle all on a structural basis. On this note, it seems plausible that MEPs in practice rely on fire alarms which by definition are of a more accidental nature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0020852311429756">Türk, 2003</xref>). But as previous research has shown, probably only true insiders can trigger fire alarms in a useful way. For that, the information on comitology that is publicly available on the internet reflects too little of the discussions in the comitology committees, both in terms of quantity and of quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0020852311429756">Brandsma et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>The assumed link from information to parliamentary behaviour, thus, is far from automatic. Transparency itself is not the magic cure that improves or even strengthens government accountability all by itself. But the case of comitology and the European Parliament does show that it is a necessary component together with other conditions in order to be able to make full use of the available repertoire of control instruments. Two lessons can be drawn in this respect. The first is that the volume and quality of information that recipients receive is not sufficient for producing effects. Rather, what it takes is the <italic>processing</italic> of the information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0020852311429756">Brandsma, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0020852311429756">Naurin, 2007</xref>). The crucial question for the exercise of control by parliaments, thus, seems not to be how much information it receives, but rather how the interest of members of parliament is distributed between issues and to what degree they actually make use of the available information. The second lesson is that procedural incentives seem to make actors in parliaments engage with the information provided. Information provided to a parliament only becomes relevant when members of parliament can see the link between the information they receive and specific as opposed to more diffuse political rights.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<title>Notes</title>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1-0020852311429756"><label>1</label><p>Rules of Procedure of the European Parliament, Rule 88.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn2-0020852311429756"><label>2</label><p>Rules of Procedure of the European Parliament, Rule 88.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn3-0020852311429756"><label>3</label><p>Rules of Procedure of the European Parliament, Rule 103.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn4-0020852311429756"><label>4</label><p>It is important to note that any parliamentary committee can vote on a ‘normal’ resolution, as opposed to the RoS and RPS resolutions that have to pass the committee that was in charge of drawing up the original co-decision act.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn5-0020852311429756"><label>5</label><p>Official Journal of the European Communities (2000), L 256/19.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn6-0020852311429756"><label>6</label><p>Rothmans case, Court of First Instance T-188/97.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn7-0020852311429756"><label>7</label><p>Official Journal of the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0020852311429756">European Communities (2008)</xref>, C 143/1.</p></fn></fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aberbach</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>Keeping a Watchful Eye: The Politics of Congressional Oversight</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Brookings Institution</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergström</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Comitology: Delegation of Powers in the European Union and the Committee System</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bovens</surname><given-names>MAP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Analysing and assessing accountability: A conceptual framework</article-title>. <source>European Law Journal</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>447</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bovens</surname><given-names>MAP</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>’t Hart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) (<year>2010</year>) <source>The Real World of EU Accountability</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bovens</surname><given-names>MAP</given-names></name><name><surname>’t Hart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schillemans</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Does public accountability work? An assessment tool</article-title>. <source>Public Administration</source> <volume>86</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Halfway house: The 2006 comitology reforms and the European Parliament</article-title>. <source>West European Politics</source> <volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>837</fpage>–<lpage>854</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandsma</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <publisher-loc>Backstage Europe</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Comitology, accountability and democracy in the European Union. PhD Thesis</publisher-name>, <publisher-name>Utrecht University</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandsma</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Blom-Hansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The post-Lisbon battle over comitology: Another round of the politics of structural choice</article-title>. <comment>EUI Working Paper 2011/3. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cadmus.eui.eu">http://cadmus.eui.eu</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandsma</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>How transparent are EU ‘Comitology’ committees in practice?</article-title>. <source>European Law Journal</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>819</fpage>–<lpage>838</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corbett</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Shackleton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>The European Parliament</source>, <edition>4th edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Harper</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyerges</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Transparency of environmental decision making: A case study of soil cleanup inside the Hanford 100 area</article-title>. <source>Journal of Risk Research</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eriksen</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name><surname>Fossum</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Democracy through strong publics in the European Union</article-title>. <source>Journal of Common Market Studies</source> <volume>40</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>424</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>European Commission</collab> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Letter from commissioner Bolkestein to Mrs Randzio-Plath</article-title>, <comment>MEP, 2 October</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>European Commission</collab> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Commission Staff Working Document: Annex to the report from the Commission on the working of committees during</article-title> <comment>2005 (COM(2006) 466 final)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>European Commission</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Report from the Commission on the working of committees during 2008 and Commission Staff Working Document ‘Presentation of committee activities in 2008 by policy sectors’ accompanying the report from the Commission on the working of committees during 2008</article-title> <comment>(COM(2009) 335 final)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>European Parliament and European Commission</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <comment>Agreement between the European Parliament and the Commission on procedures for implementing Council Decision 1999/468/EC laying down the procedures for exercise of implementing powers conferred on the Commission, as amended by Decision 2006/512/EC</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>European Parliament</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Comitology Handbook: The European Parliament’s work in the field of comitology</article-title>. <comment>Conference of Committee Chairs, PE 405.166rev</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gustavsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) (<year>2009</year>) <source>The Illusion of Accountability in the European Union</source>. <publisher-loc>Abingdon</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hardacre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Damen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The European Parliament and comitology: PRAC in practice</article-title>. <source>Eipascope</source> <volume>2009</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Héritier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Composite democracy in Europe: The role of transparency and access to information</article-title>. <source>Journal of European Public Policy</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>814</fpage>–<lpage>833</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hix</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The study of the European Union II: The ‘new governance’ agenda and its rival</article-title>. <source>Journal of European Public Policy</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Delegation to civil servants in parliamentary democracies</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Political Research</source> <volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaeding</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardacre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The execution of delegated powers after Lisbon: A timely analysis of the regulatory procedure with scrutiny and its lessons for delegated acts. EUI Working Paper 2010/85</article-title>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cadmus.eui.eu">http://cadmus.eui.eu</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Public Administration and Public Management: The Principal–Agent Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lintner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaccari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The European Parliament’s Right of Scrutiny under comitology: A legal ‘David’ but a political ‘Goliath’?</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oettel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaccari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>21st Century Comitology: The Role of Implementing Committees in the Enlarged European Union</source>. <publisher-loc>Maastricht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Eipa</publisher-name>, <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lodge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Transparency and democratic legitimacy</article-title>. <source>Journal of Common Market Studies</source> <volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>368</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lupia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Delegation and its perils</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Strøm</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Delegation and Accountability in Parliamentary Democracies</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCubbins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Congressional oversight overlooked: Police patrols versus fire alarms</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Political Science</source> <volume>28</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Majone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The credibility crisis of Community regulation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Common Market Studies</source> <volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naurin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Transparency, publicity, accountability – The missing links</article-title>. <source>Swiss Political Science Review</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neuhold</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Taming the ‘Trojan Horse’ of comitology? Accountability issues of comitology and the role of the European Parliament</article-title>. <source>European Integration Online Papers</source> <fpage>12</fpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogul</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rockman</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Overseeing oversight: New departures and old problems</article-title>. <source>Legislative Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Accountability and multi-level governance: More accountability, less democracy?</article-title>. <source>West European Politics</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>1030</fpage>–<lpage>1049</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The role of national parliaments: Checks and balances between the EU and the member states</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Verhey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiiver</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Loeffen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Political Accountability and European Integration</source>. <publisher-loc>Groningen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Europa Law Publishing</publisher-name>, <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Playing the transparency game: Consultation and policy-making in the European Commission</article-title>. <source>Public Administration</source> <volume>73</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>492</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saalfeld</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Members of parliament and governments in Western Europe: Agency relations and problems of oversight</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Political Research</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>376</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strøm</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Delegation and accountability in parliamentary democracies</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Political Research</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0020852311429756"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Türk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Transparency and comitology</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Demmke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Continuity and Change in the European Integration Process</source>. <publisher-loc>Maastricht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>EIPA</publisher-name>, <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<bio>
<p><bold>Gijs Jan Brandsma</bold> is a Post-Doctoral Research Fellow of Public Administration at Utrecht University in The Netherlands. His research focuses on transparency, accountability and openness of European Union governance.</p></bio>
</back>
</article>