<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JTC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjtc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Thermoplastic Composite Materials</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0892-7057</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1530-7980</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0892705711408988</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0892705711408988</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Characterization of Flexibly Linked Shape Memory Polyurethane Composite with Magnetic Property</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Yong-Chan</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0892705711408988">Department of Chemistry, The University of Suwon, Hwasung-shi, Kyonggi-do 445-743, Korea</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Jae Won</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Min Woo</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-0892705711408988">Department of Polymer Engineering, The University of Suwon, Hwasung-shi, Kyonggi-do 445-743, Korea</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>Byoung Chul</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0892705711408988">*</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff3-0892705711408988">School of Nano Engineering, Center for Nano Manufacturing, Inje University, Gimhae 621-749, Korea</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0892705711408988"><label>*</label>E-mail: <email>bcchun@inje.ac.kr</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>25</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>283</fpage>
<lpage>303</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>A flexibly cross-linked shape memory polyurethane (SMPU) was converted to a magnetic polymer by making a composite with a ferromagnetic particle (Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>). The flexibly cross-linked SMPU has already displayed excellent mechanical and shape memory properties; the design of a magnetically responsive material allowed for a unique and novel SMPU. Among the three different composite preparation methods (melt-mixing, solvent blending, and <italic>in situ</italic> reaction mixing), the melt-mixing method was the best and attained even distribution of magnetic particles and high mechanical and shape memory properties. Differential scanning calorimetric and infrared results showed that the polymer structure was not affected by melt-mixing. In tensile testing, the maximum stress of the composite reached 39 MPa, and the strain at break also increased to 2495%. Shape recovery exhibited maximums as high as 99% and displayed similar values after repetitive shape recovery test cycles. Finally, the magnetic property of SMPU was characterized by a superconducting quantum interference device magnetometer and demonstrated in the magnetic attraction test. The potential applications of the magnetic and flexible SMPU are discussed.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>magnetic</kwd>
<kwd>composite</kwd>
<kwd>grafting</kwd>
<kwd>shape memory</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0892705711408988"><title>INTRODUCTION</title>
<p>Shape memory polyurethanes (SMPUs) have been extensively studied due to their attractive properties, such as practical and adjustable phase transition temperature ranges, high and reproducible shape recovery, easy and simple processing, and chemical resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0892705711408988">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0892705711408988">9</xref>]. The characteristics of SMPU were explained by a phase-separated structure in which hard and soft domains are formed due to their differences in intermolecular attractions. A cross-linked structure was tested to improve the mechanical and shape memory properties of linear SMPU. An advanced flexible cross-linking method in which SMPU chains were connected by a flexible poly(ethylene glycol) (PEG) displayed high tensile stress and strain capabilities and reliable shape recovery under severe conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0892705711408988">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0892705711408988">15</xref>]. Other than improving the mechanical properties of the polymer, special effects such as electric or magnetic responsiveness, low-temperature shape recovery, temperature or pH sensing, and electric conductivity are actively researched as a mean to develop smart polymer; in such materials, the active functional molecule was chemically coupled to polymer chains to improve the uniform distribution and secure attachment of the functional group. For example, we have reported low-temperature shape recovery polymers that can sustain shape recovery at temperatures as low as −30°C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0892705711408988">16</xref>]. Electroactive shape memory polymer composites containing carbon nanotubes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0892705711408988">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0892705711408988">18</xref>], electromagnetic filler [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0892705711408988">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0892705711408988">20</xref>], Ni chain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0892705711408988">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0892705711408988">22</xref>], or hybrid fibers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0892705711408988">23</xref>] have been already reported and they demonstrate rapid shape recovery by applying an electric current or electromagnetic field. Magnetic polymer systems are also one of the areas of high research interest. Such materials are attractive for magnetic drug targeting in which a magnetic nanoparticle transports a drug to the area of interest by local application of a magnetic field [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0892705711408988">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0892705711408988">25</xref>]; they are also being investigated for magnetic separations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0892705711408988">26</xref>] and magnetic resonance imaging [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0892705711408988">27</xref>]. A magnetic and thermoresponsive shape memory polystyrene that responds to the heat generated from magnetic induction has also been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0892705711408988">28</xref>]. The combination of a flex-linked SMPU with magnetite (Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>) particles to form a magnetic SMPU composite is synergistic; the proven mechanical strength and shape recovery of the flex-linked SMPU and the well-known magnetic response of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> particles will demonstrate a different type of functional SMPU. In this investigation, a flex-linked SMPU composite that has uniform distribution of magnetic particles and can respond to a magnetic stimulus was studied.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0892705711408988"><title>EXPERIMENTAL</title>
<sec id="sec3-0892705711408988"><title>Materials</title>
<p>Poly(tetramethylene glycol) (PTMG, Aldrich, Mw = 2000 g/ mole), 4,4′-methylenebis (phenylisocyanate) (MDI, Tokyo Kasei), 1,4-butanediol (BD, Junsei Chemical), PEG (PEG-200, Duksan Chemical, Mw = 200 g/mole), and Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> (Aldrich) were dried under a high vacuum (0.1 torr) for 12 h before use. Dimethylformamide (DMF, Duksan Chemical, Korea) was distilled over CaH<sub>2</sub> before use.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0892705711408988"><title>Polymer Synthesis</title>
<p>A flex-linked SMPU was prepared by adopting a method described in literature, where the soft segment content was 68 wt% for M1 series and 72 wt% for M2 series, and hard segment content was 32 wt% for M1 series and 28 wt% for M2 series [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0892705711408988">29</xref>]. A mixture of MDI and PTMG in a ratio that is specified in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0892705711408988">Table 1</xref> was placed in a 500-mL four-necked beaker-type flask equipped with a mechanical stirrer, condenser, nitrogen purge, and oil bath. The mixture was allowed to react for 3 h at 50°C to prepare the prepolymer. BD, functioning as a chain extender, was dissolved in 100 mL of DMF and added to the prepolymer; the reaction continued for 1 h. Subsequently, a second quantity of MDI was added to the reaction mixture mentioned above, and the reaction continued for 1 h. PEG-200 was added to the mixture as a cross-linker, and the mixture was stirred for 2 h under the same conditions. After complete polymerization, the PU product was dried in a 60°C oven for 3 days to remove residual DMF. Schematics of the resulting SMPU structures are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0892705711408988">Figure 1</xref>. The flex-linked SMPU and Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> composites were prepared by a melt-mixing method with a co-rotating micro twin-screw extruder (Bau Tech BA-10, screw diameter = 19 mm, <italic>L</italic>/<italic>D</italic> = 40) at 160°C to 180°C, with a screw torque of 10–11 Nm and a screw speed of 200–250 rpm. The pelletized SMPU/Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> composite was transformed into 0.4 ± 0.01 mm thick film sheets by melt pressing (Carver 4122) at 185°C and quickly cooling. Specimens for mechanical and shape memory tests were made from the film sheets.
<fig id="fig1-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Structures of (a) linear SMPU and (b) SMPU with flexible cross-linking.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Composition of the magnetic SMPU.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0892705711408988" xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th/>
<th colspan="6">Reactant (mmol)<hr/></th></tr>
<tr>
<th>Sample code</th>
<th>MDI-1</th>
<th>PTMG</th>
<th>BD</th>
<th>MDI-2</th>
<th>PEG-200</th>
<th>Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub></th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>M1-1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4.3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-2</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>13</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-3</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>4.3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-4</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>13</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-5</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>4.3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-6</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>13</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-7</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>4.3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-8</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>13</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4.3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-2</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>13</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-3</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>4.3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-4</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>13</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-5</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>4.3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-6</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>13</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-7</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>4.3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-8</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>13</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0892705711408988"><title>Characterization</title>
<p>A Fourier-transform infrared (IR) spectrophotometer (JASCO 300 E) equipped with attenuated total reflectance capability was used to obtain IR spectra of the SMPU samples. For each sample, 25 scans were taken at resolution of 4 cm<sup>−1</sup> and a scan speed of 2 mm/ s. A differential scanning calorimeter (DSC 8000, Perkin Elmer) was used to take calorimetry data for both heating and cooling scans at a rate of 10°C/ min between −50°C and 250°C under N<sub>2</sub> flow. After melting at 250°C for 5 min and cooling quickly to −50°C, a 20-mg specimen was warmed to 250°C at 10°C/ min while monitoring the phase transitions. Tensile properties were measured with a Universal Testing Machine (UTM, LR50K, Lloyd Instrument, UK) according to the ASTM D638 standards of a 25-mm gage length, a 10-mm/ min crosshead speed, and a 2.5-kN load cell. The fractured surfaces of composites were imaged with a scanning electron microscope (SEM, JEOL JMS-6360 A).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0892705711408988"><title>Shape Memory Test</title>
<p>A UTM equipped with a temperature-controlled chamber was used for cyclic shape memory tests. A specimen with a length <italic>L</italic><sub>0</sub> was drawn 100% to 2<italic>L</italic><sub>0</sub> in a temperature-controlled chamber set at 45°C over the course of 2 min and kept at 45°C for 5 min. Afterwards, the specimen was cooled to −25°C in the chamber with liquid nitrogen for 10 min, and the upper grip was released. The shrunken length (<italic>L</italic><sub>1</sub>) was measured after the sample had remained at −25°C for 20 min. Percent shape retention (%) was calculated using Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0892705711408988">1</xref>). The specimen in the chamber was then heated to 45°C for 5 min, and the length (<italic>L</italic><sub>2</sub>) was measured after 10 min at 45°C. Percent shape recovery (%) was calculated using Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0892705711408988">2</xref>). The shape memory test was repeated three times for each specimen.
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0892705711408988"><label>(1)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0892705711408988"><label>(2)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0892705711408988"><title>Magnetic Activity Test</title>
<p>A superconducting quantum interference device (SQUID) magnetometer (Quantum Design MPMS5), housed in the Seoul branch of the Korea Basic Science Institute, was used to measure the magnetic field (B-field) of SMPU specimens under the condition of an external magnetizing field strength (H-field) from −2000 to 2000 Oe at room temperature (298 K). Magnetic levitation experiments were carried out with a specimen (5 × 100 mm<sup>2</sup>) that was fixed at one end and was free to move vertically at the other end. The maximum height of the free end that was raised by a permanent magnet hanging at the top was compared.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0892705711408988"><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title>
<sec id="sec9-0892705711408988"><title>Synthesis of Magnetic SMPU</title>
<p>An alternating arrangement of hard (MDI) and soft (PTMG) segments in the SMPU structure was critical for a high shape recovery. The advanced flex-linking of SMPU was different from the conventional cross-linking in that PEG, the flexible cross-linker, was laterally linked between PU chains to increase tensile mechanical stress without decreasing the strain and to attain a reproducible shape recovery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0892705711408988">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0892705711408988">15</xref>]. The grafting of functional groups to polymer chains is already well studied for electric conductivity, electro-active artificial muscles, antistatic coatings, low-temperature shape recovery, and ion sensing. The lateral cross-linking in the flex-linked SMPU is similar in that grafting of PEG to SMPU chains was made between SMPU chains. The flex-linked SMPU demonstrated superior mechanical and shape memory properties when compared to the linear SMPU and was selected as a polymer matrix for the composite. Magnetic particles selected in this study were Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, which have been frequently adopted in magnetic polymer research due to their nano-scale particle size, compatibility with SMPU, and ferromagnetic characteristic. Instead of grafting magnetic particles to SMPU chains, magnetic particles were melt-mixed with SMPU in a twin-screw compounder due to the absence of available sites for covalent bonding on the Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> particle. Other mixing methods were unsuccessfully attempted. Solvent mixing, in which magnetic particles were stirred with an SMPU solution in DMF, had the problem of magnetic particles aggregating around the stirrer. The addition of magnetic particles during SMPU synthesis also had a similar problem, where the magnetic particles attached to stirrer driving shaft. The success of melt-mixing in a compounder originated from the facts that magnetic particles were not attracted to the compounder screw and twin-screw compounding was better in distributing magnetic particles compared to single-screw compounding. Even distribution of magnetic particles in the SMPU matrix could be seen in SEM pictures of the fractured surfaces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0892705711408988">Figure 2</xref>). The structural differences between linear and flex-linked SMPU can be observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0892705711408988">Figure 1</xref>. In <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0892705711408988">Table 1</xref>, the amount of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> was fixed at either 4.3 or 13 mmol in both the M1 and M2 series while gradually increasing PEG-200 content, and the soft segment content in the M2 series (72 wt%) was larger than that of the M1 series (68 wt%). Therefore, the combination of magnetic responsiveness, very high strength, and high shape recovery was intended to produce a versatile flex-linked SMPU in this investigation.
<fig id="fig2-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>SEM photographs of (a) SMPU (M1 series control), (b) M1-6, (c) SMPU (M2 series control), and (d) M2-6. Note: The scattered white spots in images (b) and (d) are the Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> particles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0892705711408988"><title>IR and DSC Analysis</title>
<p>The stretching vibration mode of the hydrogen-bonded urethane carbonyl group appeared in the IR spectrum at 1699–1706 cm<sup>−1</sup>, which is slightly less than that of the free urethane carbonyl group (1731–1733 cm<sup>−1</sup>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0892705711408988">30</xref>]. The stretching vibration mode of the carbonyl group is also affected by dipole–dipole interactions between SMPU chains. The relative peak areas around both 1700 and 1730 cm<sup>−1</sup> did not change with increasing Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> content for either the M1 series (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0892705711408988">Figure 3(a)</xref>) or the M2 series (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0892705711408988">Figure 3(b)</xref>). Based on the IR results for both the M1 and M2 series, no shift were observed in the bonded carbonyl and free carbonyl as the Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> or PTMG content increased. Addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> into the SMPU did not seem to affect the molecular interactions such as hydrogen bonding and dipole–dipole interactions, and hard segment interactions were not disrupted. The glass transition temperature (<italic>T</italic><sub>g</sub>) of the soft segments of the SMPU were low (under −50°C) and difficult to detect by DSC; instead, the melting temperature (<italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub>) of this soft segment of the SMPU was obtained. The <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> of the soft segments of both the M1 and M2 series was observed around 20°C. The peak area, corresponding to the enthalpy of the transition, increased with Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> content; this behavior was presumably due to the interactions between Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> particles and the SMPU chains, which restricted movement of polymer chains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0892705711408988">Figure 4</xref>). The thermal analysis results showed that soft segment melting was affected a little by the presence of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> particles. Therefore, the soft segment melting temperature was used as the reference point for shape recovery tests.
<fig id="fig3-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>IR spectra of (a) M1 and (b) M2 series.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-fig3.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig4-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>DSC thermograms of (a) M1 and (b) M2 series.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-fig4.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0892705711408988"><title>Tensile Properties</title>
<p>The maximum stress in the M1 series with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> increased from 4 MPa for M1-1, to 14 MPa for M1-3, and to 24 MPa for M1-5, before decreasing to 15 MPa for M1-7. The maximum stress in the M1 series with 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> also increased from 4 MPa for M1-2, to 15 MPa for M1-4, and to 39 MPa for M1-6; this value slightly decreased to 19 MPa for M1-8. In the M1 series, the highest maximum stress increase was observed at M1-6 (345%) compared to the one without Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>. However, the maximum stress decreased with the addition of magnetic particles when 10 mmol of PEG-200 was used as the cross-linker, compared to the control without Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>. The addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> did not affect the maximum stress in the case of the linear SMPU, in which PEG-200 was not used. Therefore, proper addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> increased the maximum stress until a certain point, when further addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> decreased this value. The maximum stress in the M2 series with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> showed an increase, going from 3.8 MPa for M2-1, to 22 MPa for M2-3, to 28 MPa for M2-5, and to 26 MPa for M2-7. The maximum stress in the M2 series with 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> also showed an increase, going from 3.6 MPa for M2-2, to 19 MPa for M2-4, to 22 MPa for M2-6, and to 17 MPa for M2-8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0892705711408988">Figure 5</xref>). In the M2 series, the highest maximum stress increase was observed at M2-5 (170%) compared to the one without Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>. In the M2 series, a similar trend to that of the M1 series was observed: the maximum stress increased with the addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> at 5 mmol of PEG-200, but decreased at 10 mmol of PEG-200, compared to the control. Therefore, both M1 and M2 series showed a similar behavior if Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> particles were included. The effect of the addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> on the improvement of the maximum stress of both M1 and M2 series was obvious at 5 mmol of PEG-200, but inconsequential at 10 mmol of PEG-200. At 5 mmol of PEG-200, SMPU was less cross-linked, and Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> particles could have interacted with the polymer chains, resulting in higher maximum stress. When the SMPU was highly cross-linked and strengthened with a high PEG content like the one with 10 mmol of PEG-200, Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> particles may have hindered the molecular interaction between the polymer chains, reducing the maximum stress. The maximum stress generally decreased if the content of inorganic particles was increased in the composites. The gradual increase of the maximum stress of control samples, one without Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, in both the M1 and M2 series as the PEG content was increased was simply due to more flexible cross-linking by PEG. The strain at break in the M1 series with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> increased from 648% for M1-1, to 1237% for M1-3 and to 1718% for M1-5, before decreasing to 1577% for M1-7. Strain at break in the M1 series with 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> also increased from 700% for M1-2, to 1597% for M1-4, and to 2287% for M1-6; this value decreased to 1780% for M1-8. Unexpectedly, strain did not decrease as the Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> content increased. The strain of polymer composites generally decreased when the stress was improved due to increased rigidity. However, the flexible cross-linking made improvements of both stress and strain possible, and such characteristics were not hindered by the addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>. The strain at break in the M2 series with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> also showed a similar trend as the PEG content increased: 621% in M2-1, 2090% in M2-3, 2495% in M2-5, and 2154% in M2-7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0892705711408988">Figure 6</xref>). The strain at break in the M2 series with 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> increased from 543% in M2-2, to 2019% in M2-4, and to 2427% in M2-6; this value decreased to 1918% in M2-8. The strain at break of the SMPU of both M1 and M2 series was found to increase with the addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>; the synergistic effect between the SMPU and Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> particles originated from the flexible cross-linking. Results of tensile properties are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0892705711408988">Table 2</xref>. The combined improvement in stress and strain after the addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> can also be observed in the stress–strain curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0892705711408988">Figure 7</xref>(a) and (b) for the M1 series; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0892705711408988">Figure 7</xref>(c) and (d) for M2 series), in which values for both maximum stress and strain at break were increased relative to samples without Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>. In general, the simultaneous improvement of both the maximum stress and strain at break after the addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> was very intriguing and helpful in designing a strengthened polymer composite.
<fig id="fig5-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Maximum stress of (a) M1 and (b) M2 series.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-fig5.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig6-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Strain at break of (a) M1 and (b) M2 series.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-fig6.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig7-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Stress–strain curves of (a) M1 series with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, (b) M1 series with 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, (c) M2 series with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, and (d) M2 series with 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-fig7.tif"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table2-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Tensile mechanical properties.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0892705711408988" xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th>Sample code</th>
<th>Maximum stress (MPa)</th>
<th>Strain at break (%)</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>M1-1</td>
<td>4.0</td>
<td>648</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-2</td>
<td>4.0</td>
<td>699</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-3</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>1237</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-4</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>1597</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-5</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>1718</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-6</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>2287</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-7</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>1577</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-8</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>1779</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-1</td>
<td>3.8</td>
<td>621</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-2</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>543</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-3</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>2090</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-4</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>2019</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-5</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>2495</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-6</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>2427</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-7</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>2154</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-8</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>1918</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0892705711408988"><title>Shape Memory Effect</title>
<p>Shape recovery and retention of the SMPU were investigated by a cyclic shape memory test at <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> ± 20°C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0892705711408988">Figures 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0892705711408988">9</xref>). The <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> of the soft segment was selected for shape memory tests instead of the <italic>T</italic><sub>g</sub> which is too low for temperature control using our apparatus and is too low for practical applications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0892705711408988">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0892705711408988">12</xref>]. Shape recovery of the M1 series with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> was 96%, 96%, 99%, and 90% for M1-1, M1-3, M1-5, and M1-7, respectively, in the first test cycle and remained above 90% after four cyclic tests. Shape recovery of the M1 series with 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> was 96% for M1-2, 96% for M1-4, 93% for M1-6, and 92% for M1-8; these values gradually decreased after repeated test cycles. Shape recovery of the M2 series with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> was 99% for M2-1, 99% for M2-3, 92% for M2-5, and 90% for M2-7 in the first test cycle; these values remained around 90% after four cyclic tests. Shape recovery of the M2 series with 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> was 95%, 97%, 97%, and 91% for M2-2, M2-4, M2-6, and M2-8, respectively, and decreased as the cyclic tests continued. Shape recovery of both the M1 and M2 series was above 90% and slightly decreased as PEG content increased. Shape recovery of the SMPU was reproducible, as judged from the four cyclic tests. Finally, the addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> did not significantly alter the results of shape recovery. The shape retention experiments were conducted at a very low temperature (−20°C) and tested the tendency of an SMPU to retain its shape against a shape recovering force. Shape retention, in general, increased for all of the SMPUs with increasing PEG content up to 10 mmol of PEG. The addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> did not affect the shape retention. The M2 series was expected to have a better shape retention than M1 series because the M2 series contained a greater amount of soft segments (based on comparing the PTMG content of each series). However, the difference in shape retention between the M1 and M2 series was minimal. Cyclic shape retention tests also demonstrated that the shape retention of both the M1 and M2 series remained mostly constant after four cyclic tests; for example, the initial shape retention values of M1-6 (88%) and M2-6 (85%) were slightly reduced to 84% and 79%, respectively, after four cycles. Shape memory test results are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0892705711408988">Table 3</xref>. Considering shape recovery, shape retention, and tensile mechanical test results, both the M1 and M2 series performed excellently when compared to the previous SMPUs; M1-5 and M2-3, in particular, exhibited outstanding shape recovery for an SMPU. The addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> to the SMPU did not interfere with the molecular interactions necessary for their excellent performance in shape memory and mechanical properties.
<fig id="fig8-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Cyclic shape recovery tests of (a) M1 series with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, (b) M1 series with 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, (c) M2 series with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, and (d) M2 series with 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-fig8.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig9-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Cyclic shape retention tests of (a) M1 series with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, (b) M1 series with 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, (c) M2 series with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, and (d) M2 series with 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-fig9.tif"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table3-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Shape memory properties.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0892705711408988" xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th/>
<th colspan="2">Shape memory (%)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0892705711408988">a</xref></sup><hr/></th></tr>
<tr>
<th>Sample code</th>
<th>Recovery</th>
<th>Retention</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>M1-1</td>
<td>96</td>
<td>79</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-2</td>
<td>96</td>
<td>79</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-3</td>
<td>96</td>
<td>85</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-4</td>
<td>96</td>
<td>88</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-5</td>
<td>99</td>
<td>93</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-6</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>89</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-7</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>87</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M1-8</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>80</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-1</td>
<td>99</td>
<td>80</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-2</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>80</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-3</td>
<td>99</td>
<td>91</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-4</td>
<td>97</td>
<td>90</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-5</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>88</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-6</td>
<td>98</td>
<td>85</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-7</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>72</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>M2-8</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>82</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0892705711408988"><label>a</label><p>First cycle of shape memory results.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-0892705711408988"><title>Magnetic Property</title>
<p>The magnetization of SMPU specimens was tested by a SQUID magnetometer that measured the magnetized field (H-field) of a material by an external magnetic field (B-field). As seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0892705711408988">Figure 10</xref>, Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> alone did show a significant response to the external magnetic field, and the control, the SMPU without Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, did not respond to the external magnetic field. The M1 and M2 series showed an intermediate magnetic response depending on the amount of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> included in the specimen. The M2 series showed a slightly larger magnetic response than the M1 series at the same Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> content because the M2 series had a higher content of soft segments and better flexibility. Therefore, magnetization of the SMPU depended on the Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> content and the direction of the magnetic field. In line with the magnetization test, the maximum height that the SMPU could be raised by a permanent magnet was compared for M2 series, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0892705711408988">Figure 11</xref> and plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0892705711408988">Figure 12</xref>. For simplicity, only the M2 series was selected for comparison because it had a higher soft segment content and better flexibility for the levitation test. The M2 series with 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> (M2-2, M2-4 M2-6, and M2-8) had levitation values around 40 cm, while the M2 series with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> (M2-1, M2-3, M2-5, and M2-7) exhibited levitation of approximately 15 cm. The levitation height in the M2 series was affected more by the Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> content, as opposed to the PEG content. The SMPU with flexible cross-linking did not lose its pliability after cross-linking and was able to attain similar heights compared to the linear one. The magnetic response of an SMPU with flexible cross-linking was demonstrated in this investigation and will be useful in fields such as fibers, foams, elastomers, and insulating materials with magnetic property.
<fig id="fig10-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Magnetization of PUs measured by SQUID magnetometer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-fig10.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig11-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>Magnetic attraction of M2 series: (a) control, (b) M2-1, (c) M2-2, (d) M2-3, (e) M2-4, (f) M2-5, (g) M2-6, (h) M2-7, and (i) M2-8. Note: The inset number designates the raised height (mm).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-fig11.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig12-0892705711408988" position="float"><label>Figure 12.</label><caption><p>Comparison of the maximum magnetic attraction height of SMPUs with 4.3 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> and 13 mmol of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0892705711408988-fig12.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-0892705711408988"><title>CONCLUSION</title>
<p>The SMPU composite prepared by melt-mixing with Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> was investigated for magnetic activity. Characterizations of thermal transitions, tensile behavior, and shape memory properties supported the fact that the addition of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> did not affect the characteristics of a linear SMPU. Two series, M1 and M2, with different soft segment, PEG, and Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> content were compared. The shape recovery of both series was greater than 90% for all materials and reproducible through four cyclic tests. Shape retention of the entire series remained greater than 80%. The magnetic activity was demonstrated by vertically raising the SMPU specimens by a permanent magnet; the height was dependent on the amount of Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> included in the composite. These preliminary findings described a promising method for making magnetic SMPU composites with a uniform distribution of magnetic particles.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0892705711408988">Figure 11</xref> appear in color online <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jtc.sagepub.com">http://jtc.sagepub.com</ext-link></p></fn>
</fn-group>
<ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</title>
<p>This research was supported by Basic Science Research Program through the National Research Foundation funded by the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology (R11-2005-065).</p>
</ack>
<ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0892705711408988"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Study on Shape-Memory Behavior of Polyether-Based Polyurethanes. II. Influence of Soft-Segment Molecular Weight</article-title>, <source>J. Appl. Polym. Sci.</source>, <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>1575</fpage>–<lpage>1586</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0892705711408988"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Influence of Silica on Shape Memory Effect and Mechanical Properties of Polyurethane–Silica Hybrids</article-title>, <source>Eur. Polym. J.</source>, <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1343</fpage>–<lpage>1348</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0892705711408988"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabani</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luftmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraft</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Synthesis and Characterization of Two Shape-Memory Polymers Containing Short Aramid Hard Segments and Poly(ϵ-caprolactone) Soft Segments</article-title>, <source>Polymer</source>, <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>4251</fpage>–<lpage>4260</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0892705711408988"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ping</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Polylactide-Based Polyurethane and its Shape-Memory Behavior</article-title>, <source>Eur. Polym. J.</source>, <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1240</fpage>–<lpage>1249</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0892705711408988"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Synthesis and Shape Memory Effects of Si–O–Si Cross-Linked Hybrid Polyurethanes</article-title>, <source>Polymer</source>, <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>457</fpage>–<lpage>465</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0892705711408988"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>B.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Im</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Im</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Novel Copolyester-Based Ionomer for a Shape-Memory Biodegradable Material</article-title>, <source>Polymer</source>, <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>1830</fpage>–<lpage>1834</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0892705711408988"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Razzaq</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anhalt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frormann</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weidenfeller</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Mechanical Spectroscopy of Magnetite Filled Polyurethane Shape Memory Polymers</article-title>, <source>Mater. Sci. Eng. A</source>, <volume>471</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0892705711408988"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rousseau</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Facile Tailoring of Thermal Transition Temperatures of Epoxy Shape Memory Polymers</article-title>, <source>Polymer</source>, <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1852</fpage>–<lpage>1856</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0892705711408988"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Surprising Shape-Memory Effect of Polylactide Resulted from Toughening by Polyamide Elastomer</article-title>, <source>Polymer</source>, <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1311</fpage>–<lpage>1315</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0892705711408988"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>T.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Structure-Property Relationship and Shape Memory Effect of Polyurethane Copolymer Cross-Linked with Pentaerythritol</article-title>, <source>Fibers Polym.</source>, <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0892705711408988"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Crosslinked Polyurethanes with Shape Memory Properties</article-title>, <source>Polym. Int.</source>, <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>854</fpage>–<lpage>859</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0892705711408988"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The Study of Crosslinked Shape Memory Polyurethanes</article-title>, <source>Mater. Chem. Phys.</source>, <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>368</fpage>–<lpage>372</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0892705711408988"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Effect of Glycerol Cross-Linking and Hard Segment Content on the Shape Memory Property of Polyurethane Block Copolymer</article-title>, <source>J. Mater. Sci.</source>, <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>6524</fpage>–<lpage>6531</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0892705711408988"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>T.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Structure–Property Relationship of Shape Memory Polyurethane Cross-Linked by a Polyethyleneglycol Spacer between Polyurethane Chains</article-title>, <source>J. Mater. Sci.</source>, <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>9045</fpage>–<lpage>9056</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0892705711408988"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>T.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Flexible Cross-Linking by Both Pentaerythritol and Polyethyleneglycol Spacer and its Impact on the Mechanical Properties and the Shape Memory Effects of Polyurethane</article-title>, <source>J. Appl. Polym. Sci.</source>, <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>2800</fpage>–<lpage>2808</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0892705711408988"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Effects of the Pendant Naphthalene Group on the Mechanical Properties and Low Temperature Shape Memory Effect of Polyurethane Copolymer</article-title>, <source>J. Intell. Mater. Syst. Struct.</source>, <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1163</fpage>–<lpage>1170</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0892705711408988"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goo</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Electroactive Shape Memory Polyurethane Composites Incorporating Carbon Nanotubes</article-title>, <source>Macromol. Rapid Commun.</source>, <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>412</fpage>–<lpage>416</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0892705711408988"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>I.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goo</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Development and Application of Conducting Shape Memory Polyurethane Actuators</article-title>, <source>Smart Mater. Struct.</source>, <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1476</fpage>–<lpage>1482</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0892705711408988"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>H.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Study on the Activation of Styrene-Based Shape Memory Polymer by Medium-Infrared Laser Light</article-title>, <source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source>, <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>144105</fpage>–<lpage>144107</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0892705711408988"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Electromagnetic Activation of Shape Memory Polymer Networks Containing Magnetic Nanoparticles</article-title>, <source>Macromol. Rapid Commun.</source>, <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1168</fpage>–<lpage>1172</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0892705711408988"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phee</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Electrical Conductivity of Thermoresponsive Shape-Memory Polymer with Embedded Micron Sized Ni Powder Chains</article-title>, <source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source>, <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>014104</fpage>–<lpage>014107</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0892705711408988"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Significantly Reducing Electrical Resistivity by Forming Conductive Ni Chains in a Polyurethane Shape-Memory Polymer/Carbon-Black Composite</article-title>, <source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source>, <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>204101</fpage>–<lpage>204103</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0892705711408988"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>H.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Electro-Induced Shape-Memory Polymer Nanocomposite Containing Conductive Particles and Short Fibers</article-title>, In: <source>Proceedings of 15th International Symposia on Smart Structures and Materials</source>, <publisher-loc>San Diego</publisher-loc>, <comment>9–13 March, Vol. 6932</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0892705711408988"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wust</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hling</surname><given-names>H.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Magnetic Fluid Hyperthermia (MFH): Cancer Treatment with AC Magnetic Field Induced Excitation of Biocompatible Superparamagnetic Nanoparticles</article-title>, <source>J. Magn. Magn. Mater.</source>, <volume>201</volume>: <fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>419</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0892705711408988"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andreas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Regina</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klaus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Johannsen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wust</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadobny</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schirra</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loening</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanksch</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Presentation of a New Magnetic Field Therapy System for the Treatment of Human Solid Tumors with Magnetic Fluid Hyperthermia</article-title>, <source>J. Magn. Magn. Mater.</source>, <volume>225</volume>: <fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0892705711408988"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Španová</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rittich</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horák</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenfeld</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prodělalově</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suìiková</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Štrumcová</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Immunomagnetic Separation and Detection of <italic>Salmonella</italic> Sells Using Newly Designed Carriers</article-title>, <source>J. Chromatogr. A</source>, <volume>1009</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0892705711408988"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Methotrexate-Modified Superparamagnetic Nanoparticles and Their Intracellular Uptake into Human Cancer Cells</article-title>, <source>Langmuir</source>, <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>8858</fpage>–<lpage>8864</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0892705711408988"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monk</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisbrenner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Characterization of Shear Deformation and Strain Recovery Behavior in Shape Memory Polymers</article-title>, <source>Polymer Testing</source>, <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>498</fpage>–<lpage>503</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0892705711408988"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Lateral Flexible Linking of Polyurethane Copolymer and the Effect on Shape Recovery and Tensile Mechanical Properties</article-title>, <source>Polym. Eng. Sci.</source>, <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>2457</fpage>–<lpage>2466</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0892705711408988"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>A Study on the Characteristics of Network Structures of Crosslinked Polyurethanes</article-title>, <source>Polymer (Korea)</source>, <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>392</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>