<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HSX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphsx</journal-id>
<journal-title>Homicide Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1088-7679</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6720</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1088767912463216</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1088767912463216</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Margo Wilson’s Influence Continues</article-title>
<subtitle>A Research Note on the Sex Ratios of Killing (SROKs) in Texas’ Six Largest Cities</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Titterington</surname><given-names>Victoria B.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1088767912463216">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Subjack</surname><given-names>Jeanne</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1088767912463216">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1088767912463216"><label>1</label>Sam Houston State University, Huntsville, TX, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1088767912463216">Victoria Titterington, College of Criminal Justice, P.O. Box 2296, Sam Houston State University, Huntsville, TX 77341-2296, USA Email: <email>titterington@shsu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>16</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue in Honor of Margo Wilson</issue-title>
<fpage>380</fpage>
<lpage>392</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Drawing on Margo Wilson and Martin Daly’s cross-national research on the spousal “sex ratio of killing” (SROK), this study examines the overall, relationship-specific, and age-specific SROKs for Texas’ six largest cities. This analysis of <italic>Supplementary Homicide Reports</italic> for the cities of Austin, Dallas, El Paso, Fort Worth, Houston, and San Antonio indicates that overall sex ratios of killing in Texas were comparable to the United States, whereas four of the six cities had higher intimate partner sex ratios of killing than the state or nation. Wide variation of intimate partner SROKs based on offender age, race, and weapon was also found.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>femicide</kwd>
<kwd>gender</kwd>
<kwd>victimization</kwd>
<kwd>intimate partner</kwd>
<kwd>victim/offender relationship</kwd>
<kwd>evolutionary psychology</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1088767912463216">
<title>Background</title>
<p>The first author of this article originally met Margo Wilson in 1992 at the Second Annual Workshop of the Homicide Research Working Group on the FBI’s Quantico, Virginia campus. Margo presented a paper, “A Lifespan Perspective on Homicide Violence: The Young Male Syndrome,” coauthored with her life partner and collaborator, Martin Daly. As an early PhD student in sociology, this was my first exposure to Wilson and Daly’s seminal work on the evolutionary psychological perspective of violence. As fully elaborated on in their <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1088767912463216">1988</xref> book, <italic>Homicide</italic>, this explanation of lethal violence is compelling. From this first meeting, I considered it a privilege to be professionally acquainted with Margo.</p>
<p>I was particularly interested in the work that Margo Wilson and Martin Daly published on the elevated risk of uxoricide (wife-killing) in Hamilton-Wentworth, Ontario for women with coresiding minor children who were not the biological offspring of their current partners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1088767912463216">Daly, Wiseman, &amp; Wilson, 1997</xref>). Margo was extremely helpful to me with both substantive and editorial advice as I and my coauthor worked to replicate the Canadian analysis of uxoricide for the city of Houston, Texas. We were ultimately successful in doing so (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1088767912463216">Brewer &amp; Paulsen, 1999</xref>) and I felt quite indebted to Margo for her willingness to serve as an informal mentor for the project. She was always exceptional in her attentiveness to the “new-kids-on-the-block” as well as her seasoned colleagues.</p>
<sec id="section2-1088767912463216">
<title>Sex Ratios of Killing (SROKs)</title>
<p>Another important and provocative aspect of Margo Wilson and Martin Daly’s research is the concept they termed “the sex ratio of killing” (SROK). Among their many influential contributions was their analysis of the exceptional sex ratio of killing in spousal homicides in the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1088767912463216">Wilson &amp; Daly, 1992</xref>). This dynamic research duo observed that in the United States there were 75 women killing their registered or common-law spouses for every 100 men committing such acts. This SROK was not only very high in relation to women’s representation as homicide offenders in other relationship types, but was also two to four times greater than the spousal sex ratio of killing in Canada, Denmark, England/Wales, Scotland, and New South Wales, Australia.</p>
<p>Wilson and Daly’s inquiry into the exceptional SROK in U.S. spousal homicide was timely and influential. It illustrated how intimate dyads are unique among social relationships, including how they may become lethal. This initial research was conducted and published at a time when feminism was still quite controversial. At the same time, the serious social issue of domestic violence, especially as manifested in the United States, was gaining the attention of the legal, criminal justice, and social service arenas. In turn, their research prompted countless others to learn more about the phenomenon of nonlethal and lethal intimate partner violence.</p>
<p>Since the publication of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1088767912463216">Wilson and Daly’s 1992</xref> paper, at least three other published studies have focused on intimate partner homicide ratios in the United States. These studies include the 1997 analysis of 191 U.S. cities for the period of 1988 to 1992 by Gauthier and Bankston, who analyzed the influence of varying degrees of gendered economic equality on SROKs, within economic and regional cultural contexts. They found a significant negative influence of female economic equality on the intimate SROK, within the context of general economic well-being and more traditional cultural orientations to gender roles of the communities being studied. In other words, in communities where women gained economic parity with men, the sex ratios of killing intimate partners have a tendency to be biased in favor of males.</p>
<p>A descriptive study of intimate partner homicide ratios for Chicago and Houston was also inspired by Wilson and Daly’s work on this subject. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1088767912463216">Paulsen and Brewer’s (2000)</xref> comparison of the general characteristics of intimate partner killing in the third and fourth largest cities in the United States indicated that the relative proportions of women and men killing intimate partners were similar along three dimensions, but the high intimate partner SROKs were primarily a Black phenomenon. Analysis also indicated that the sex ratios of killing were high only for the killing of spouses or children and that men’s relative risk of intimate partner homicide victimization in both cities decreased dramatically when the two parties were estranged.</p>
<p>A more recent extension of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1088767912463216">Wilson and Daly’s (1992)</xref> study, also conducted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1088767912463216">Gauthier and Bankston (2004)</xref>, applied a self-help social control perspective and looked at sex-specific motives to explain the high U.S. sex ratio of intimate homicide as well as the variation of intimate partner SROKs across 157 U.S. cities. Their research revealed that the sociological variables that significantly changed the SROKs across communities (e.g., mandatory arrest laws and mean levels of public assistance) did so by lowering the rate of women offenders. Their analysis also showed that the proportion of city populations that are Hispanic and Black significantly affected the intimate partner SROK. The effect of a large Hispanic population was a lowering of the volume of women offending, thus lowering the SROK. By contrast, the SROK was significantly increased by a large Black population through an increase in the rate of women spouse or intimate partner killers. This was in keeping with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1088767912463216">Wilson and Daly’s (1992)</xref> interpretation of the findings within their original SROK study and the general distribution of intimate partner killings in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1088767912463216">Paulsen and Brewer’s (2000)</xref> investigation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1088767912463216">
<title>The Present Study</title>
<p>The research herein is yet another extension of Wilson and Daly’s work, describing the overall and intimate partner SROKs over a 31-year period for Texas’ six largest cities: Austin, Dallas, El Paso, Fort Worth, Houston, and San Antonio (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1088767912463216">Figure 1</xref>). During the 1976-2007 time period, 10.1% of all U.S. homicides occurred in Texas. In turn, these six cities are among the 20 most populous in the United States, with a combined 2010 population of more than 6.8 million. Since 1993, these cities have constituted the Executive Issues Major Cities Program of the Police Research Center (PRC) within the College of Criminal Justice of Sam Houston State University. The PRC generates research, consultation, and training with these six cities and their chiefs of police.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1088767912463216" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Texas Six Largest Cities and U.S. Rank by Population</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1088767912463216-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1088767912463216" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>The unit of analysis in this study is incidents of murder and nonnegligent homicide, utilizing available data from a composite Uniform Crime Reports: Supplementary Homicide Reports (SHR) File for the years 1976 to 2007 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1088767912463216">Fox &amp; Swatt, 2009</xref>). The file provides incident-level information on criminal homicides in the United States, including location, circumstances, and method of offense as well as demographic characteristics of victims and offenders and the relationship between the two. The data are based on monthly reports to the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) by local law enforcement agencies participating in the FBI’s Uniform Crime Reporting Program. To account for nonreported data (missing cases), a weighting scheme linked to FBI annual estimates of homicide counts by states and National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS) mortality data on decedent characteristics in coroners’ reports for deaths classified as homicide was adopted. For incomplete case data (e.g., missing characteristics on victims), a multiple imputation process based on a log-linear model for incomplete multivariate categorical data was implemented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1088767912463216">Fox &amp; Swatt, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>It should be noted that Wilson and Daly’s analysis of <italic>spousal</italic> SROKs used city-specific homicide files, including historical relationship data. Their classification of spousal relationships included couples who, at the time of the homicide or previously, had a shared residence and sexual intimacy. This included registered and de facto current or former marriages and those boyfriend–girlfriend relationships where there was explicit evidence of current or past coresidency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1088767912463216">Wilson &amp; Daly, 1992</xref>). In keeping with subsequent studies (Gauthier &amp; Bankston, 1997, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1088767912463216">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1088767912463216">Paulsen &amp; Brewer, 2000</xref>) the present analysis is of the broader concept of <italic>intimate partner</italic> SROKs. That said, our classification of intimate partner homicides includes offenders and victims who, at the time of the killing, were married, common-law or divorced couples, or who were reported by the police as boyfriend–girlfriend or in homosexual relationships. Despite the lack of historical information on coresidency or sexual intimacy of those victim–offender relationships reported as boyfriend–girlfriend or homosexual, we reason that those not thought to be intimate in nature would have been categorized by the police as friends.</p>
<p>In the SHR 1976 to 2007 file there were 32 victim–relationship categories, recoded into five for purposes of this analysis: Intimate, Family, Friend, Acquaintance, and Stranger. For the present analysis, those victim–offender relationships recorded by the police as current or former, registered or common-law spouses, boyfriends/girlfriends or homosexual partners were designated as <italic>Intimate</italic>; all other familial categories (including step- and in-law relationships) were coded as <italic>Family</italic>; the <italic>Friend</italic> category remained as such; coworkers and other known relationships were coded as <italic>Acquaintances</italic> and the remaining stranger or unknown categories were coded as <italic>Stranger</italic>. We recognize that combining these last two categories is somewhat arbitrary but do not believe it detracts from the primary question at hand related to homicides between intimate partners.</p>
<p>The composite SHR file used for this analysis does not contain a category for ethnicity; so that, we are compelled to limit our examination to offender and victim race, recorded by the police as White (including Hispanic White), Black, and Other. This 31-year file contained 17 original weapon categories, recoded into three for this study. All long-guns and handguns were classified as <italic>Guns</italic>, the SHR <italic>Knife</italic> category remained the same and the remaining categories were designated as <italic>Other</italic>. This Other category included poison, explosives, fire, drugs, drowning, and asphyxiation.</p>
<p>A final factor we take into consideration in this study is the ages of offenders and victims, with an interest in how this affects intimate partner SROKs. Although the composite SHR data file includes a category for victims age 65 and above, the level of aggregation for older offenders is age 50 and older. Therefore, we employed the 50+ age grouping for both Intimate partner homicide offenders and victims and compared this to all offenders and victims younger than age 50.</p>
<p>After determining frequencies for each of the variables included in this analysis, chi-square tests of significance were employed for within-city differences in offender and victim sex, race, and age, as well as weapon used.</p>
<p>While we recognize the limitations of the SHR, we believe it continues to be the best single source of homicide data that includes the victim–offender relationship for the six cities of interest in this study. What is gained by this exploratory analysis is a more complete estimate of victim–offender relationships, victim and offender sex, age and race, and weapon used. What is lost is the detail regarding intimate partner forms (e.g., registered versus de facto relationships), victim and offender ethnicity, and circumstantial details of the killing. Still, the SHR are useful in covering a longer time span and allowing the generation of city-specific SROK profiles for a specific state; information that has heretofore been unexplored.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1088767912463216" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section6-1088767912463216">
<title>The Role of Relationship Type in SROKs</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1088767912463216">Table 1</xref> displays the overall and relationship-specific sex ratios of killing (SROKs) for the United States, Texas, and Texas’ six largest cities for the period from 1976 through 2007. Based on the SHR imputation accounting for all reported homicide and nonnegligent manslaughter victims in the respective categories, it is first remarkable that the overall SROKs range from only 10 to 14 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1088767912463216">Table 1</xref>) for the United States, the state of Texas, and the six largest cities within this state. This means that for every 100 men who killed women, 10 to 14 women killed men. However, the picture changes considerably when the SROKs are disaggregated by victim–offender relationship. For the U.S. overall during this 30-plus year period, almost half as many women as men killed intimate partners, as indicated by the SROK of 48 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1088767912463216">Table 1</xref>). This ratio is lower than that reported in previous research for a shorter time period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1088767912463216">Wilson &amp; Daly, 1992</xref>), but is almost four times the overall SROK. Compared to this national figure, it is also the case that women’s representation as intimate partner homicide offenders is significantly higher for Texas, with a statewide intimate partner SROK of 62. However, the range of intimate partner SROKS varies widely across the cities in this analysis, from a low of 24 in El Paso to a high of 82 in Houston.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1088767912463216" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Overall and Relationship-Specific Sex Ratios of Killing (SROKs) for the United States, Texas, and Texas’ Six Largest Cities, 1976-2007</p>
<p>United States</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1088767912463216" xlink:href="10.1177_1088767912463216-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="4">United States<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="4">Texas<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Intimate</td>
<td>53,335</td>
<td>25,846</td>
<td><bold>48</bold></td>
<td>Intimate</td>
<td>5,264</td>
<td>3,242</td>
<td><bold>62</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Family</td>
<td>50,931</td>
<td>13,628</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>Family</td>
<td>5,316</td>
<td>1,313</td>
<td>25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Acquaintance</td>
<td>265,725</td>
<td>19,777</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>Acquaintance</td>
<td>26,207</td>
<td>2,066</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Stranger</td>
<td>133,145</td>
<td>5,739</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>Stranger</td>
<td>13,354</td>
<td>591</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Overall</td>
<td>503,136</td>
<td>64,990</td>
<td><bold>13</bold></td>
<td>Overall</td>
<td>50,141</td>
<td>7,212</td>
<td><bold>14</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="4">Austin<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="4">Dallas<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intimate</td>
<td>111</td>
<td>49</td>
<td><bold>44</bold></td>
<td>Intimate</td>
<td>550</td>
<td>433</td>
<td><bold>78</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Family</td>
<td>85</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>Family</td>
<td>691</td>
<td>176</td>
<td>25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Acquaintance</td>
<td>599</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>Acquaintance</td>
<td>4,011</td>
<td>378</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Stranger</td>
<td>240</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>Stranger</td>
<td>2,677</td>
<td>132</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Overall</td>
<td>1,035</td>
<td>135</td>
<td><bold>13</bold></td>
<td>Overall</td>
<td>7,929</td>
<td>1,119</td>
<td><bold>14</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="4">El Paso<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="4">Fort Worth<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intimate</td>
<td>111</td>
<td>27</td>
<td><bold>24</bold></td>
<td>Intimate</td>
<td>243</td>
<td>166</td>
<td><bold>68</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Family</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>Family</td>
<td>244</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Acquaintance</td>
<td>391</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>Acquaintance</td>
<td>1526</td>
<td>125</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Stranger</td>
<td>250</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>Stranger</td>
<td>765</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Overall</td>
<td>844</td>
<td>88</td>
<td><bold>10</bold></td>
<td>Overall</td>
<td>2778</td>
<td>384</td>
<td><bold>14</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="4">Houston<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="4">San Antonio<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intimate</td>
<td>801</td>
<td>659</td>
<td><bold>82</bold></td>
<td>Intimate</td>
<td>321</td>
<td>180</td>
<td><bold>56</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Family</td>
<td>805</td>
<td>209</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>Family</td>
<td>386</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Acquaintance</td>
<td>5,249</td>
<td>410</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>Acquaintance</td>
<td>2,273</td>
<td>142</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Stranger</td>
<td>3,724</td>
<td>146</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>Stranger</td>
<td>1,196</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Overall</td>
<td>10,579</td>
<td>1,424</td>
<td><bold>13</bold></td>
<td>Overall</td>
<td>4,176</td>
<td>474</td>
<td><bold>11</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1088767912463216">
<p>Note; (<italic>p</italic>&lt;.05)</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1088767912463216">
<title>Offender Race and Weapon in Intimate Partner SROKs</title>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1088767912463216">Table 2</xref>, a range of 86% to 97% of these intimate partner SROKs were classified as intraracial, though Hispanic and non-Hispanic Whites are not disaggregated in these data. As of 2000, approximately 60% of San Antonio’s population was of Hispanic or Latino origin, and this was the ethnic classification for more than 80% of El Paso’s residents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1088767912463216">U.S. Census Bureau, 2009</xref>). This is a likely explanation for the low White intimate partner SROK in El Paso, given the cultural tradition of male-dominated Latino households (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1088767912463216">Macionis, 2003</xref>, p. 347). This finding is also in keeping with previous studies of SROKs in the United States and Texas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1088767912463216">Gauthier &amp; Bankston, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1088767912463216">Paulsen &amp; Brewer, 2000</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1088767912463216" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>The Intimate Partner SROKs by Offender Race and Weapon for Texas’ Six Largest Cities, 1976-2007</p>
<p>Austin</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1088767912463216" xlink:href="10.1177_1088767912463216-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="4">Austin<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="4">Dallas<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Offender race</td>
<td colspan="4">Offender race</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> White</td>
<td>88</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>36</td>
<td> White</td>
<td>257</td>
<td>135</td>
<td>53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>17</td>
<td><bold>77</bold></td>
<td> Black</td>
<td>286</td>
<td>297</td>
<td><bold>104</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td> Other</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Weapon</td>
<td colspan="4">Weapon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gun</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>43</td>
<td> Gun</td>
<td>345</td>
<td>288</td>
<td><bold>83</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Knife</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>12</td>
<td><bold>86</bold></td>
<td> Knife</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>117</td>
<td><bold>143</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>24</td>
<td> Other</td>
<td>123</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="4">El Paso<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="4">Fort Worth<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Offender race</td>
<td colspan="4">Offender race</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> White</td>
<td>98</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>24</td>
<td> White</td>
<td>124</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>27</td>
<td> Black</td>
<td>119</td>
<td>102</td>
<td><bold>86</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td> Other</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Weapon</td>
<td colspan="4">Weapon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gun</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>21</td>
<td> Gun</td>
<td>154</td>
<td>118</td>
<td><bold>77</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Knife</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>10</td>
<td><bold>91</bold></td>
<td> Knife</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>32</td>
<td><bold>110</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>6</td>
<td> Other</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="4">Houston<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="4">San Antonio<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Offender<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
<th/>
<th align="center">Man<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Woman<hr/></th>
<th align="center">SROK<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Offender race</td>
<td colspan="4">Offender race</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> White</td>
<td>382</td>
<td>214</td>
<td>56</td>
<td> White</td>
<td>248</td>
<td>121</td>
<td>49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black</td>
<td>404</td>
<td>440</td>
<td><bold>109</bold></td>
<td> Black</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>59</td>
<td><bold>82</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>33</td>
<td> Other</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Weapon</td>
<td colspan="4">Weapon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gun</td>
<td>485</td>
<td>444</td>
<td><bold>92</bold></td>
<td> Gun</td>
<td>196</td>
<td>99</td>
<td>51</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Knife</td>
<td>148</td>
<td>187</td>
<td><bold>126</bold></td>
<td> Knife</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>59</td>
<td><bold>140</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>168</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>17</td>
<td> Other</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1088767912463216">
<p>Note: <italic>Intraracial</italic> incidents ranged from 86% of cases in Fort Worth to 97% in Austin. A range from 94% in Fort Worth and San Antonio to 98% in El Paso was <italic>heterosexual</italic> incidents. Available data in this SHR file did not include Ethnicity. Therefore <italic>Race</italic>, in this analysis, refers to White (both Hispanic and non-Hispanic), Black, and Other. p&lt;.05</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1088767912463216">Table 2</xref> provides a closer look at the distribution and characteristics of Intimate partner SROKs specifically for Texas’ six largest cities over this 31-year time period. As seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1088767912463216">Table 2</xref>, five of the six cities have significantly higher Intimate partner SROKS for Black offenders than Whites (including Hispanic Whites) or others. In Dallas and Houston, more Black women than Black men committed lethal violence against an intimate partner, with Black intimate partner SROKS of 104 and 109, respectively.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1088767912463216">Table 2</xref> also displays SROKs based on the weapon used to commit lethal violence against an intimate partner. In all six cities, SROKs were significantly (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) higher in cases in which a knife was the cause of death. There was actually an excess of female- over male-perpetrated Intimate partner homicides committed with a knife in Dallas, Fort Worth, Houston, and San Antonio. In comparison to knife homicides, intimate partner SROKS were lower when a gun was the cause of death, though the six cities varied. Firearm SROKs were near parity in Dallas (83), Fort Worth (77), and Houston (92). <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1088767912463216">Table 2</xref> also reveals that incidents in which a weapon other than a firearm or knife was used accounted for the smallest number of incidents perpetrated by women or men, and the lowest intimate partner SROKs across all six cities. Though firearms and knives were the most likely weapons used by either sex in all six cities, this latter finding indicates that men were much more likely than women to use a variety of other methods of committing criminal homicide. One possible explanation is that, with the exception of killing with poison or other drugs, the other methods reported (e.g., drowning or strangulation) require relatively greater physical strength, typically the case for a male partner.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1088767912463216">
<title>The Role of Age in Intimate Partner SROKs</title>
<p>One dimension of intimate partner SROKs as yet unexplored in previous research is their distribution based on the ages of victims and offenders. Specifically, we are interested in whether the likelihood of these relatively high levels of women intimate partner homicide offending continues into older age. As necessitated by the available data and earlier explained, we disaggregate the offender age into the categories of under age 50 and age 50 or older, to compute age-specific overall and intimate partner SROKs.</p>
<p>At least two notable findings are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1088767912463216">Table 3</xref>. One is that women’s representation among homicide offenders is much lower for homicide overall than for intimate partner homicide, regardless of offenders’ age (except for older offenders in El Paso, where both overall and intimate partner SROK’s were very low). The other is that there is much more variability among cities in the sex ratios of intimate partner homicide than in overall criminal homicide offending, regardless of the offender’s age.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1088767912463216" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>A Comparison of SROKs for Younger and Older (Age 50+) Offenders in Texas’ Six Largest Cities, 1976-2007</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1088767912463216" xlink:href="10.1177_1088767912463216-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Younger offenders (Age 15-49)<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Older (Age 50+) offenders<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">City</th>
<th align="center">Overall SROKs</th>
<th align="center">Intimate partner SROKs</th>
<th align="center">Overall SROKs</th>
<th align="center">Intimate partner SROKs</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Austin</td>
<td>13</td>
<td><bold>46</bold></td>
<td>9</td>
<td><bold>28</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dallas</td>
<td>14</td>
<td><bold>82</bold></td>
<td>18</td>
<td><bold>62</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>El Paso</td>
<td>10</td>
<td><bold>26</bold></td>
<td>20</td>
<td><bold>17</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fort Worth</td>
<td>13</td>
<td><bold>65</bold></td>
<td>20</td>
<td><bold>96</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Houston</td>
<td>13</td>
<td><bold>84</bold></td>
<td>17</td>
<td><bold>71</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>San Antonio</td>
<td>11</td>
<td><bold>58</bold></td>
<td>17</td>
<td><bold>46</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>When looking at the intimate partner SROKs in homicides with younger offenders, we see that they range from 26 in El Paso to 84 in Houston. If we treat El Paso as an outlier, intimate partner SROKs of offenders under age 50 range from 46 in Austin to a high of 84 in Houston. In comparison, overall SROKs in homicides with younger offenders ranged from 10 in El Paso to 14 in Dallas. Furthermore, intimate partner SROKs among older (age 50 and above) offenders range from a low of 17 in El Paso and 28 in Austin to highs of 71 in Houston and 96 in Fort Worth. Among older offenders, the overall SROKs ranged from 9 in Austin to 20 in El Paso and Fort Worth.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1088767912463216">
<title>SROKs Over Time</title>
<p>A reduction in national levels of intimate partner homicide since the 1990s has been well documented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1088767912463216">Dugan, Nagin, &amp; Rosenfeld, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1088767912463216">Wells &amp; DeLeon-Granadas, 2004</xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1088767912463216">Figure 2</xref>, this trend is borne out in the intimate partner SROKs for Texas and its six largest cities over the 31-year time frame of this investigation. The intimate partner SROK dropped by 48% for the U.S. overall and by more than 67% for the state of Texas. Across Texas’ six largest cities, the reduction in intimate partner SROKs was 34% to 82%, with the largest decreases in Fort Worth, Houston, and San Antonio. The reduction in SROKs reflects a decline in men’s versus women’s risk of intimate partner homicide victimization from the period 1976-1985, to the period 1986-1995, to the period 1996-2007, across all geographic units including El Paso (data not shown).</p>
<fig id="fig2-1088767912463216" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Intimate partner SROKs over time for the United States, Texas, and Texas’ six largest cities, 1976-2007</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1088767912463216-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1088767912463216" sec-type="discussion|conclusions">
<title>Discussion and Conclusions</title>
<p>The primary objective of this study was to describe sex ratios of killing and intimate partner sex ratios of killing in a state representing 10% of all U.S. homicides over the 1976-2007 time period. Texas’ six largest cities are among the 20 most populous nationally, with 2010 populations ranging from 649,121 for El Paso to 2,099,451 in Houston.</p>
<p>This exploratory study yielded a number of important findings. We found, for example, that women’s versus men’s representation among intimate partner homicide offenders was significantly higher for Texas than the United States over the course of these 30 years. However, the range of Intimate partner SROKs varied considerably, from a low of 24 in El Paso to a high of 82 in Houston.</p>
<p>As related to weapon use in the commission of these approximately 60,000 homicides in Texas’ six largest cities, firearms and knives were the most likely weapons used by either sex in all six cities. We also found that the lowest sex ratios of killing for both intimate partner and nonintimate partner homicides were those involving weapons other than guns or knives, indicating that a relatively larger number of men than women used means such as fire or strangulation to commit their lethal acts.</p>
<p>We found that intimate partner SROKs among older (age 50 and above) offenders ranged from a low of 17 in El Paso to a high of 96 in Fort Worth. This relatively greater representation of older women as intimate partner homicide offenders calls for further examination in later studies, using city-specific data that would include information about possible histories of domestic violence that finally culminated in homicide.</p>
<p>On examining the basic race classification available in the SHR data, we learned that five of the six largest Texas cities had significantly higher intimate partner SROKs for Black offenders than Whites (including Hispanic Whites) or others. In two cities, Dallas and Houston, there were more Black women than Black men committing lethal intimate partner violence. In four of the six cities, we also found an excess of female- over male-perpetrated intimate partner SROKs when the weapon used was a knife, whereas the intimate partner SROKs were near parity in gun-related incidents for half of the cities we studied.</p>
<p>Another important finding was that there was a much wider range of intimate partner SROKs than overall SROKs, in both the younger (less than age 50) and older offender age categories. Though overall SROKs ranged from 10 to 14 for younger offenders and 9 to 20 for older offenders; intimate partner SROKs ranged from 26 to 84 for younger offenders and 17 to 96 for older offenders.</p>
<p>Finally, we found a significant (<italic>p</italic> &lt;. 01) reduction in the intimate partner sex ratios of killing from the 1976-1985 to the 1996-2007 time period, statewide and for each of these cities. While the intimate partner SROK was reduced by 48% for the United States, it fell by more than 67% for the state of Texas and was reduced between 34% to 82% across Texas’ six largest cities.</p>
<p>Along with providing useful baseline data on overall and intimate partner sex ratios of killing over a 30-year time frame in urban areas of Texas, the present study also generates questions for future research. For example, while all six of these cities are governed by the same penal code related to homicide, there is likely to have been variation in city- or county-specific law enforcement responses to intimate partner nonlethal and lethal violence. Similarly, the present data offer no indication of the domestic violence resources available in each of these cities. In keeping with previous research showing that the availability of such resources may affect the saving of lives of women and of men in intimate relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1088767912463216">Dugan et al., 1999</xref>), it would be interesting to track individual cities over time by their SROKs and resources available to abused women. Equally important in future research would be a temporal analysis of race/ethnicity-specific intimate partner sex ratios of killing, allowing for a comparison of how each of these cities tracks with national data indicating a long-term trend of greater reductions in female- than male-perpetrated Intimate partner homicide, particularly among Black couples.</p>
<p>In conclusion, Margo Wilson’s innate curiosity was borne out in part by the question of how homicide in intimate dyads is different from homicide generally. One answer to this question is found in her work with collaborator Martin Daly and others on the intimate partner sex ratios of killing. Study of this phenomenon has continued to the present day. The business of protecting women and men in intimate partner relationships, as well as the business of continued research in this critical aspect of human relationships, has been well served by Margo’s remarkable questions and insights. The present study has been particularly motivated by the extensive evidence that she and her collaborators provided to our understanding of differences between women and men in the volume, types, and motives for lethal violence.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Bios</title>
<p><bold>Victoria B. Titterington</bold> is a Professor in the College of Criminal Justice at Sam Houston State University. Her research interests are in the areas of aging and crime victimization, as well as lethal family violence. Her work has appeared in such journals as <italic>Homicide Studies, Violence &amp; Victims and The International Journal of Offender Therapy &amp; Comparative Criminology</italic>.</p>
<p><bold>Jeanne Subjack</bold> is a Doctoral Teaching Fellow in the College of Criminal Justice at Sam Houston State University. Her research interests include policy issues related to specialized populations and corrections.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1088767912463216">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>V. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>A comparison of U.S. and Canadian findings on uxoricide risk for women with children sired by previous partners</article-title>. <source>Homicide Studies</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>317</fpage>-<lpage>332</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1088767912463216">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>Homicide</source>. <publisher-loc>Hawthorne, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aldine de Gruyter</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1088767912463216">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wiseman</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Women with children sired by previous partners incur excess risk of uxoricide</article-title>. <source>Homicide Studies</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1088767912463216">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dugan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagin</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Explaining the decline in intimate partner homicide; the effects of changing domesticity, women’s status, and domestic violence resources</article-title>. <source>Homicide Studies</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>214</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1088767912463216">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swatt</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Uniform crime reports [United States]: Supplementary homicide reports with multiple imputation, cumulative files 1976-2007</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icpsr.umich.edu/icpsrweb/NACJD/series/57/studies/24801">http://www.icpsr.umich.edu/icpsrweb/NACJD/series/57/studies/24801</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1088767912463216">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bankston</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>“Who kills whom” revisited: A sociological study of variation in the sex ratio of spouse killings</article-title>. <source>Homicide Studies</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>96</fpage>-<lpage>122</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1088767912463216">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Macionis</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Sociology</source>. <publisher-loc>Upper Saddle River, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson Education</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1088767912463216">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>V. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The Intimate partner sex ratio of killing revisited: A comparison of Houston and Chicago homicide</article-title>. <source>Gender Issues</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>88</fpage>-<lpage>100</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1088767912463216">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>U.S. Census Bureau</collab>. (<year>2009</year>). <source>Top 50 states in the U.S. by population and rank</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0763098">http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0763098</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1088767912463216">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeLeon-Granadas</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The homicide decline: Disaggregated trends, theoretical explanations, and policy implications</article-title>. <source>Criminal Justice Policy Review</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>246</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1088767912463216">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Who kills whom in spouse killings? On the exceptional sex ratio of Intimate partner homicides in the United States</article-title>. <source>Criminology</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>189</fpage>-<lpage>215</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>