<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">THE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spthe</journal-id>
<journal-title>Thesis Eleven</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0725-5136</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7455</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0725513612453422</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0725513612453422</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Adorno’s view of psychoanalysis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Dahmer</surname>
<given-names>Helmut</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0725513612453422"/>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0725513612453422"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0725513612453422">Technical University of Darmstadt, Germany</aff>
<bio>
<title>Biographical note</title>
<p>
<bold>Helmut</bold> <bold>Dahmer</bold> studied with Helmuth Plessner, Max Horkheimer, Theodor Adorno and Jürgen Habermas. He edited the psychoanalytic monthly <italic>Psyche</italic> from 1968 to 1992, belonged to the advisory council of the Hamburg Institute of Social Research between 1984 and 1987 and was Professor of Sociology at the Technical University of Darmstadt from 1974 to 2002. He is currently a freelance scholar and writer in Vienna. His publications include <italic>Libido und Gesellschaft </italic>(1973, 1982), <italic>Pseudonatur und Kritik </italic>(1994), <italic>Soziologie nach einem barbarischen Jahrhundert </italic>(2001), <italic>Divergenzen </italic>(2009) <italic>Die unnatürliche Wissenschaft </italic>(2012) and <italic>Interventionen </italic>(2012).</p>
</bio>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0725513612453422">Helmut Dahmer, Technical University of Darmstadt, Germany Email: <email>prof.helmut.dahmer@gmail.com</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>111</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>97</fpage>
<lpage>109</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Thesis Eleven Pty, Ltd., SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Psychoanalysis sets out to solve the riddles and enigmas of the psyche. For Adorno, however, psychoanalysis itself is an enigma. Why, he asks, have both the theory and its therapeutic applications become entangled in insoluble contradictions? Adorno identifies to a certain extent with the great psychoanalytic riddle-solvers, Freud and Ferenczi, as he probes these contradictions. He hopes, however, to move beyond the limits of a theory that reduces all phenomena to psychological factors, so he also approaches the problem as a sociologist. This perspective enables him to describe the static and dynamic aspects of the social structure within which psychoanalysis developed in the first half of the 20th century. And it frees him, furthermore, from the misconception that Freud passed on to most of his followers: the belief that they were pursuing a natural science of the soul, which would generate its own rigorously scientific psychological technique.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>autonomy-ideal</kwd>
<kwd>Critical Theory</kwd>
<kwd>ego weakness</kwd>
<kwd>mass psychology</kwd>
<kwd>partial drives</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A comprehensive study of psychoanalysis in the ‘Frankfurt School’ is still to come (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0725513612453422">Bonss 1982</xref>). On the one hand, it would have to bring out common elements and differences in the interpretation of Freudian theory and therapy in the writings of Horkheimer, Benjamin, Adorno and Marcuse – as well as in the later works of Habermas, Apel and Sonnemann. On the other hand, it would have to place the use made of psychoanalysis by these authors in the framework of their own philosophical and political projects.</p>
<p>Adorno’s first philosophical works – on Husserl and Freud – were indebted to ‘pure empiricism’, a variety of the Kantian transcendental philosophy conceived by the Frankfurt philosopher Hans Cornelius, the academic teacher of Horkheimer and Adorno. ‘The pure empirical worldview … is identical in essence with that of the theory that Kant put forward and justified as <italic>transcendental idealism</italic> in the Critique of Pure Reason’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23a-0725513612453422">Cornelius 1919</xref> [1911]: 342).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0725513612453422">1</xref>
</sup> His 1924 dissertation, for example, sought to elucidate and rectify ‘the contradiction between the transcendental<italic>-</italic>idealist and the transcendent<italic>-</italic>realist components in Husserl’s theory of objects’. Husserl’s ‘distinction between being as consciousness and being as reality’ (or ‘the world of objects independent of consciousness’) is dismissed brusquely: objects are not causes <italic>of</italic> experiences but ‘rules <italic>for </italic>experiences and are therefore strictly inherent in consciousness’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973a [1924]</xref>: 73; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973b</xref> [1927]: 233). He then undertook a comprehensive study of the ‘concept of the unconscious in transcendental psychology’. Worked out between 1926 and 1927, this was planned as a PhD thesis, but withdrawn at the beginning of 1928.</p>
<p>Adorno’s critique of the premise of ‘realia’ that transcend consciousness, originally elaborated in his discussion of Husserl, was then directed at the metaphysics of the unconscious, as this was usually viewed in post-Kantian philosophy, particularly after Schopenhauer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0725513612453422">Heinz and Dahmer 1978</xref>: 127–67). For this purpose, the procedure and the concepts of psychoanalysis were changed or ‘translated’ into those of the philosophy of immanence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973b</xref> [1927]: 105 ff.). The philosophy of consciousness receives welcome confirmation through the demonstration of its (far-reaching) agreement with Freud’s empirical psychology, while psychoanalysis receives its ‘transcendental justification as science’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973b</xref> [1927]: 304; cf. 248 and 310 ff.).</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>The concepts that lie at the heart of our investigation either do not appear in psychoanalysis at all, or they appear as <italic>subsidiary</italic> <italic>hypotheses</italic> that are weighed up solely in pragmatic terms. Their philosophic legitimacy is a matter of indifference to the psychoanalyst and they are loaded often enough with all kinds of obscurities, dogmatic presuppositions and naturalisms. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973b</xref> [1927]: 238)</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>In the framework of transcendental philosophy, the unconscious (neglected by Kant) is conceptualized as an indirectly given fact (independent of present experiences, that is, of phenomena). Yet ‘everything unconscious is always and without exception proven in what is conscious’, namely in what is produced as clear memory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973b</xref> [1927]: 313 ff).</p>
<p>At first, Adorno’s argument in his treatise stays within the frame of the history of philosophy. He maintains that the philosophy of the 19th and early 20th century treated the unconscious as an ontological substance in order to rectify a difficulty (or a deficit) in Kantian philosophy. The construction of a transcendental (instead of a transcendent) concept of the unconscious is only achieved with the help of the conceptual apparatus that Cornelius had developed. The latter’s <italic>Transcendental Systematics </italic>of 1916 and its leading ideas – from the ‘immediately given’ to the ‘immanence of consciousness’ – are not questioned (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0725513612453422">Tiedemann 1973</xref>: 381f.).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0725513612453422">2</xref>
</sup> Finally, however, after renewed elucidation of the ‘aim’ of his undertaking, Adorno suddenly leaves the labyrinth of neo-Kantianism behind, as well as the mere history of ideas. He now argues that the existing ‘social conditions’ gave rise to the confused but popular concept of a (transcendent) unconscious by historical necessity and, following Freud, he contrasts it to a ‘scientifically reduced theory of the unconscious’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973b</xref> [1927]: 316–22).</p>
<p>The essentialist view of human nature and the life-metaphysics closely related to it, together with the ‘ideology of fascism’, fulfilled a dangerous function by distracting attention altogether from ‘the existing economic system and the dominance of economics’. Indeed these views defended the exploitation of the many, the luxury of the few and the predatory habits of imperialism (by naturalizing them). Those who can afford it are offered an imaginary refuge, a kind of ‘summer holiday of consciousness’. Psychoanalysis is, however, ‘a sharp weapon … against any and every metaphysics of the drives and the idolization of mere mindless organic life’; that is why it has been condemned as ‘destructive’.</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>We realize that psychoanalysis is not unambiguously dedicated to the elucidation of the unconscious; we had to criticize certain arguments of psychoanalytic theory that seem to implicate a concept of the unconscious as a natural or transcendent object. … However, it cannot be overlooked that in its deepest intentions psychoanalysis is able and willing to establish the primacy of knowledge about the unconscious. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973b</xref> [1927]: 321)</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>This criticism of ideology is then followed by the main historical-materialist point:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>After everything that we have argued about the transcendental idealist possibility of a law-governed connection between the material and psychic worlds, we should not be astounded if not merely the recognition of the unconscious matters of fact, but also their constitution is dependent on the material world, that means: on society. … A precondition for uncovering many more decisive unconscious contents is therefore a change of the present social system.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>This sets:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>a limit on all elucidation and thereby also on our investigation. Nevertheless, we do not believe … we have begun anything futile. The practical consequences of false teachings cannot be overcome by merely theoretical means; this requires insight into the falseness of those doctrines and their replacement by more correct teachings. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973b</xref> [1927]: 321)</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>In the first volume of the <italic>Collected Writings of Adorno</italic> this ‘disenchantment of the unconscious’ is followed by three lectures and theses from the years 1931–2, which – in the form of a ‘dreamlike anticipation’<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0725513612453422">3</xref>
</sup> – outline the program of his further development of the ‘young Hegelian enlightenment’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0725513612453422">Horkheimer 1987a</xref> [1926]: 157). In the inaugural lecture, held in May 1931 in Frankfurt, Adorno linked his ideas to those of Walter Benjamin. He exposed the weaknesses of the main contemporary philosophies (neo-Kantianism, life-philosophy, phenomenology and logical empiricism). His diagnosis: traditional philosophy is undergoing a process of self-dissolution. Spirit is no longer able to create out of itself the totality of what is real, or to comprehend it, and the exact sciences avoid reflection on their presuppositions and findings. The task of a new kind of materialistic philosophy is that of interpretation (of findings or facts), or more precisely: the solving of riddles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973d [1951a]</xref>: 141ff., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0725513612453422">1974</xref>: 125–8).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0725513612453422">4</xref>
</sup> What is puzzling is the ‘residue of the phenomenal world’, namely that which escapes interest in self-preservation or utilization, because it does not seem immediately usable – the crumbs that fall from the lord’s table, what remains when hunger is appeased or what is rejected as unappetizing refuse and banished into the unconscious (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973b</xref> [1927]: 232ff., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0725513612453422">1973d [1951a]</xref>: 169ff., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0725513612453422">1974</xref>: 150).</p>
<p>When Adorno comes to speak here about the ‘amazing and repellent affinity’ between interpretative philosophy and materialism, he calls first on Freud, then on Marx:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>The turn to the ‘residue of the phenomenal world’, which Freud proclaimed is valid beyond the realm of psychoanalysis, just as the turn of progressive social philosophy to the economy does not arise merely from the empirical predominance of the economy, but equally from the inherent requirements of philosophical interpretation. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973c</xref> [1931]: 336)</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>Materialistic interpretation is valid for what is unintended, what can be broken down into its smallest elements, out of whose experimental arrangement an unexpected solution arises fortuitously. This is the Freudian process of dream analysis: a reading that decodes signs, or the transformation of codes into text.</p>
<p>In the context of discussion of a ‘complication’ with which the dream interpreter deals in the case of the so-called confirmatory or compliant dreams in analytical therapy, Freud writes that the task (here) is comparable to solving one of the children’s games called ‘puzzles’:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>A ‘puzzle’ (Rätsel) is created by cutting: … a coloured picture fitting exactly into a wooden frame into a large number of pieces of the most irregular and crooked shapes. If one succeeds in arranging the crooked heap of fragments, <italic>each</italic> <italic>of</italic> <italic>which</italic> <italic>bears</italic> <italic>upon</italic> <italic>it</italic> <italic>an</italic> <italic>unintelligible</italic> <italic>piece</italic> <italic>of</italic> <italic>drawing</italic>, so that the picture acquires a meaning, and there is no gap anywhere in the design and so that the whole fits into the frame – if all these conditions are fulfilled, then one knows that one has solved the puzzle and there is no alternative solution. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0725513612453422">Freud 1963b</xref> [1923]: 308ff., emphasis added)</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>The riddle does not encode a hidden reality that forms the basis of it (or is hidden behind it) and which must be uncovered; rather it calls for a solution that illuminates and dissolves ‘the enigma in a flash’. Thus the riddle disappears with its solution.</p>
<p>In this context a variant of the old story of Oedipus, the riddle-solver, is instructive; it says that in no way had he solved the riddle of the sphinx assigned to him or uttered the solution, but had only laid his hand thoughtfully on his forehead. The sphinx, however, had misunderstood this gesture, wrongly believing that the wanderer wanted to demonstrate that he had understood in a flash what the riddle pointed towards: that is, Oedipus himself, or ‘humankind’.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0725513612453422">5</xref>
</sup> Aghast and desperate, the man-eating monster is said to have thrown itself into the chasm, upon which the Thebans were freed from this plague.</p>
<p>The Husserl criticism of 1924 was taken up and continued ten years later during Adorno’s exile in Oxford.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0725513612453422">6</xref>
</sup> The defence of psychoanalysis as science through demystification of the concept of the unconscious that was devised in 1927 was thus not followed by any critical essay on Freud, or by any later lecture or seminar dedicated to psychoanalysis. There is no Freud monograph by Adorno, nor one about Marx or Nietzsche, despite the fact that the significance of both for the elaboration of a negative dialectic can scarcely be overestimated. Nevertheless, Adorno had adopted the psychoanalytic mode of thinking early on; so his philosophical and sociological writings, as well as his theories on music and literature, are interwoven with Freudian concepts and theses. In a report on his work written in November 1934 for Horkheimer, he stated that he was ‘constantly engaged’ with the ‘psychoanalytic complex’ and ‘would like to say something … fundamental’ about it (in the <italic>Journal for Social Research</italic>) – in the form of ‘ideas for a dialectical psychology’. The ‘problem of mediating between society and psychology’ or that of ‘psychic reification’ may well be ‘the central thing’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0725513612453422">Adorno and Horkheimer 2003</xref>: 39–42).</p>
<p>Such ideas are developed later in various essays and aphorisms of Adorno. The Freud critique was made in the aphorisms of <italic>Minima Moralia</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973d [1951a]</xref>: 65–77; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0725513612453422">1974</xref>, Aph. 36–42). These were formulated between 1937 and 1944 and emphasized the ‘repressive aspects’<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0725513612453422">7</xref>
</sup> of ‘unenlightened enlightenment’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973d [1951a]</xref>: 67ff.). It was followed two years later by a lecture for the Psychoanalytic Society of San Francisco, which was published in 1952 under the title: ‘On the Relation between Psychoanalysis and Social Theory’. In this paper Adorno developed his critique of the ‘neo-Freudian revisionism’ of Karen Horney, that soon developed into a school. He argued that the ‘neo-Adlerians’ had taken up the conformist tendencies in Freud’s writings on the technique of treatment, disregarded his radical theory of the drives and oriented therapy determinedly towards the patients’ proper adjustment to the realities of their social ‘milieu’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0725513612453422">Adorno 1972a [1946a]</xref>: 20–41).</p>
<p>In the chapter of <italic>Dialectic of Enlightenment </italic>entitled ‘Limits of Enlightenment’, Horkheimer and Adorno trace anti-Semitism back to ‘false projection’ (in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0725513612453422">Horkheimer 1987b [1944, 1947]</xref>: 217–38). There it is stated that ‘in a certain sense all perception is projection’ and that ‘the morbid element in anti-Semitism is not the projective relation as such, but rather the loss of reflection in it’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0725513612453422">Horkheimer 1987b</xref>: 217–19). In 1951, after completing his studies on the authoritarian character (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0725513612453422">Adorno 1972c</xref> [1950]) and on the demagogic tricks of fascist agitators in the USA,<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0725513612453422">8</xref>
</sup> Adorno published an interpretation of Freud’s work, <italic>Group Psychology and the Analysis of the Ego</italic> (Freud 1967 [1921]). It had been a clairvoyant anticipation of fascist manipulation of the masses and of the psychosocial structure of the ‘national community’ (<italic>Volksgemeinschaft</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0725513612453422">Adorno 1972d [1951b]</xref>: 408–33).</p>
<p>The great essay, ‘On the Relation between Psychology and Sociology’, with which Adorno opened the 1955 Festschrift for Horkheimer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0725513612453422">Adorno 1972e [1955]</xref>: 64–69), corresponds most directly to the project for a ‘dialectical psychology’ formulated in his letter to Horkheimer in 1934. However, he perceived the work as unsatisfactory, or even as a failure, and attached a short addendum to it ten years later (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0725513612453422">Adorno 1972f [1966b]</xref>: 86–92). One of the ‘Critical Models’ from the collection <italic>Interventions</italic> (dedicated to the memory of Fritz Bauer) reverted to Freud’s libido theory in order to offer proof that even where the laws on sexual offences are highly liberal, sexuality continues to be subject to disapproval (as a negation of the ego principle). Whatever deviates from the socially accepted form of sexual satisfaction (whether it be pleasure in the component instincts, homosexuality or relations with prostitutes) is, as ever, subject to discrimination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0725513612453422">Adorno 1977 [1963]</xref>: 533–54). In the major work published in 1966, the dialectics of psychic terms introduced by Freud (id, ego and superego) was pursued further, above all in the chapters dedicated to Kant and Hegel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973f [1966a]</xref>: 211–99, 300–60). Finally, in the first chapter of <italic>Aesthetic Theory,</italic> Freud’s exclusively psychological interpretation of art as wish fulfilment was criticized and set against the Kantian doctrine of art as ‘disinterested appreciation’ of beauty.</p>
<p>Since sociology and psychology have established themselves as independent sciences, they avoid one another. Although they have a common object, that of socialized individuals, an object that is actually a subject, the different concerns of the two disciplines – with, for example, the psychological achievements of individuals or with the social relations in which they are entangled – led to theories about social relations and social development that deviate greatly from each other (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0725513612453422">Adorno 2003b [1940sb]</xref>: 86ff.). Attempts to integrate ‘pure’ sociology and ‘pure’ psychology within the framework of an encompassing general theory could only succeed at the cost of relinquishing those insights that are indebted to the one-sidedness of either discipline. Such forcible attempts at harmonization produced a substitute form of sociologism or psychologism. The solution of psychological and social enigmas requires an utraquistic procedure, in which the experiences and insights specific to the disciplines of sociology and psychology are played out against one another.</p>
<p>Sociology and psychology are different sciences for bringing social history to public awareness. In social history, institutionalized power relations shape the matrix of individual life-courses. Sociology knows this, psychology ignores it. Isolated individuals (social atoms or ‘monads’) owe their status as relatively independent individuals to the relations of production and distribution, from which they imagine themselves to be independent. But even their psychology is shaped by these relations and is thus not a constituent of society, but rather a <italic>constitutum</italic> or social product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973f [1966a]</xref>: 342–4). In keeping with this idea, sociology only has a right to the pre-eminence it gained with the elucidation of the Sphinx’s riddle of social history, to the extent that it is aware of the historically specific character of its own concepts.</p>
<p>The divergent viewpoints of sociology and psychology (that is to say, of social theory and psychoanalysis) derive from the inherent ambiguity, the protean character of their common object, that is of the socialized individuals, whose inner structure and relations to one another both sciences seek to fathom. The forms of societal association adapted to the relations of dominance and exploitation in a society vary historically and the relations of individuals to groups, tribes, ranks and classes change with them, as does the structure of their drives. Modern European society is the result of the dissolution of feudal allegiances, of the growing independence of individuals from the groups in which they originated and from the territories occupied by them. Isolated individuals only had a chance of survival in the western cities, that is, in the craft and industry centres of an international network of trade relations. Individual producers (entrepreneurs and free wage-earners), acting as private people, provided for the production of social goods, and their relations to one another were no longer those of direct but rather of indirect domination, mediated by exchange.</p>
<p>Individuals who can maintain themselves under favourable market conditions by placing themselves at the disposal of others (in work determined by them), or by having their capital at their own disposal (and with it the work of others) – and in this sense realize a kind of ‘autonomy’– are also the product of specific social relations and – like these – have a history. Anyone who only has himself at his disposal, and is therefore dependent on the sale of his labour-power, is immediately at a disadvantage in relation to those who possess the means of production and thus also have control over him. The proportion of self-employed people in the economically active population has dramatically decreased in the last two hundred years. The vast majority of those who are economically active consist of dependent employees. The autonomy of isolated individuals has always been only a relative one, and therefore a kind of illusion; and in a society in which giant international concerns stand opposite hosts of wage dependants and recipients of charity, not only do cultural values change but also the power relation between the inner, psychic agencies of the members of society, or their psychological structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0725513612453422">Horkheimer 1987b [1944, 1947]</xref>: 233 ff.; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0725513612453422">1973</xref>: 168 ff.)</p>
<p>Sociology and psychology are competing to monopolize explanation of the history of the social world. By striving for self-sufficiency these disciplines are reacting specifically to the antagonism of individual and culture. Individuals are (along with their psychic structure) the product of their respective societies and thus part of the ‘superstructure’ (or of what is ‘constituted’); they are conditioned to reproduce the existing institutions, but do not cease to resist them because they are inexhaustible pleasure seekers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0725513612453422">Freud 1969</xref> [1905]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0725513612453422">1966</xref>: 126). (That is the only reason why individual and social histories exist.) In the economy of the psyche the antagonism between individual and culture appears as conflict between the ego and the id.</p>
<p>Psychology in the modern sense, as Freud explored and presented it, is one modelled on the apparently independent individuals of the liberal era.</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>The pre-bourgeois world did not know psychology yet and the totally socialized world doesn’t know it any longer. Psycho-analytical revisionism corresponds to the latter; it reflects the displacement of forces between society and the individual. Social power no longer needs the mediating agencies of ego and individuality. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0725513612453422">Adorno 1972e [1955]</xref>: 83)</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>At the end of this era, when the sphere of circulation or mediation is being relativized or abolished, psychoanalysis appears, just at the moment when the individualistic type of psychology, to which Freud subscribed, is already in the process of dissolution. Those who are materially independent, who are keen on autonomy, have developed a kind of virtual, market-shaped internal space for their psychic ‘apparatus’, whose function is to cope with internal and external irritations. In this psychic space, opposing forces struggle in a way that is analogous to struggles in the market: that is, antagonistic strivings – between sexual and destructive desires and internalized social forces – are mediated and compromises are negotiated in the interest of self-preservation.</p>
<p>Like Freud, Adorno grasps the antagonism of ego and id: the conflict of sexuality and the drive for happiness with the reality-oriented pleasure-unpleasure calculus of the ‘agencies for controlling the drives in the psychic economy’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0725513612453422">Adorno 1984</xref> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0725513612453422">1970</xref>]: 186–9). ‘He alone who could situate utopia in blind somatic pleasure, which, satisfying the ultimate intention, and in itself without any intention, has a stable and valid idea of truth’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973d [1951a]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0725513612453422">1974</xref>: 61). He apprehends it, if that is possible, even more sharply than Freud,<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0725513612453422">9</xref>
</sup> who wrote that individuals who are bound to repressive culture by violence and morality are sworn enemies of culture, although they owe their survival to it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0725513612453422">Freud 1962 [1921]</xref>: Ch.1). The relative independence of a considerable part of the population which was attained at the height of the bourgeois era, and which led to the formation of the cultural ideal of autonomy, is lost thanks to the concentration of capital – the dispossession of the middle classes. In the ‘age of regression’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0725513612453422">Adorno 1977</xref> [1963]: 533), discerning members of the bourgeoisie and self-conscious workers are replaced by demagogues, peddlers of hatred and the masses who have been goaded on by them, and who trample on everything that is not like them. Under mounting social pressure people turn themselves into machines for self-preservation, increasingly experiencing themselves psychologically as tools or instruments. No longer individual subjects, they have become mere extensions of their economic functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973d [1951a]</xref>: ‘Novissimum Organum’; 1974: 228). The consequent ego weakness, the ‘depersonalization of the self’, leads to an externalization of the superego and to a renunciation of individualized, ‘personal’ morality. Mobs of obedient followers, massacres and extermination camps teach us what has become of the autonomy of the individual today.</p>
<p>What made individuation possible in the liberal era and led to the formation of an ideal of free individuality is in the process of dissolving:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>The new anthropology, that is, the theory of a new human type formed under the conditions of monopoly and state capitalism, contrasts expressly with psychology. The individual is the central concept in psychology … Those who represent the new type are no longer individuals, that is the unity, continuity and substantiality of the individual is dissolved … Whenever collective subjects are formed, the whole economy of the drives, together with the mechanism of desire, is nullified [or set out of function …]. Freud grasped this intuitively in his most advanced works, above all in <italic>Beyond the Pleasure Principle</italic>, though he did not draw the consequences from it. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0725513612453422">Adorno 2003a [1940sa]</xref>: 69ff.)</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>A new arrangement of society, which could make novel forms of autonomy and spontaneity possible, still lies below the horizon. At the same time, even in the era of cannibalistic totalitarianism, Adorno believed it was inevitable that totalitarianism would collapse. The fascist regime in Germany seemed untenable to him, because its terrors were not the result of a relapse into archaic barbarity but rather the product of ‘artificial regression’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0725513612453422">Adorno 1972d [1951b]</xref>: 430; cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0725513612453422">Adorno 1973f</xref>: 90). He saw fascism as a theatrical presentation of barbarity on the stage of modern exchange society:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>Freud made a distinction between hypnosis and group psychology by defining the former as taking place between two people only. However, the leaders’ appropriation of mass psychology, the streamlining of their technique, has enabled them to collectivize the hypnotic spell. The Nazi battle cry of ‘Germany awake!’ hides its very opposite. The collectivization and institutionalization of the spell … have made the transference more and more indirect and precarious, so that the aspect of performance, the ‘phoniness’ of enthusiastic identification … has been tremendously increased. This increase may well terminate in sudden awareness of the untruth of the spell, and eventually in its collapse. Socialized hypnosis breeds within itself the forces which will do away with the spook of regression through remote control and in the end awaken those who keep their eyes shut though they are no longer asleep. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0725513612453422">Adorno 1972d [1951b]</xref>: 433)</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>Adorno seizes on ‘the hackneyed phrase about mass-hypnosis under fascism’ that Freud uses and defines it specifically:</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>Even those stages of collective enthusiasm to which the term ‘mass hypnosis’ refers have an element of conscious manipulation, by the leader and even by the individual subject himself, which can hardly be regarded as a result of mere passive contagion. … There is always something self-styled, self-ordained, and spurious about fascist hysteria.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>Incidentally, ‘cynical soberness is probably more characteristic of the fascist mentality than psychological intoxication’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0725513612453422">Adorno 1972b [1946b]</xref>: 397–401).</p>
<p>Adorno’s history of the modern soul and its agencies extends this far. Yet in view of the fall of the totalitarian regimes and the example they have left behind, there is still a postscript to be added. As early as 1927, Freud wrote that the soft ‘voice of the intellect’ was seeking incessantly to penetrate us, but did not gain a hearing until the end, ‘after a countless succession of rebuffs’ (Freud 1962 [1927]: Ch. X: 49). In our experience, politically induced mass-hypnoses, enforced by terror, persist – and this is also true of the generations brought up under Hitler and Stalin, despite the subsequent changes of these regimes.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-0725513612453422">10</xref>
</sup> They outlive their founders<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-0725513612453422">11</xref>
</sup> and their propagandists, and repeated powerful attacks from outside are necessary to rouse at least some of the daydreamers who keep their secrets all too gladly to themselves. The hypnosis of the German ‘folk-community’– the nightmare of Europe – lasted till its military defeat, and no small number of ‘national comrades’ remained under its spell for life. Yet for a long time the rudely awoken post-war generation did not dare to open its eyes and face up to the cruel deeds of its predecessors, those horrific sleepwalkers.</p>
<p>
<italic>Translated from the German by Joachim Redner</italic>
</p>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0725513612453422">
<label>1.</label>
<p>All quotations in the article have been translated by Joachim Redner, unless otherwise attributed.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0725513612453422">
<label>2.</label>
<p>The editor of <italic>Frühschriften</italic> (Early Writings), Rolf Tiedemann, cites a letter of Adorno (from the year 1969) in his ‘Editorische Nachbemerkung’ (Editor’s Comment): ‘The “main mistake” in my work on the concept of the unconscious has been that it relates to Freud one-sidedly to the epistemology of the school of Mach and Avenarius and neglects the materialistic element available from the beginning in Freud, which is described in his work by means of the fundamental concept of organ-pleasure’ (pp. 381–2).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0725513612453422">
<label>3.</label>
<p>From a letter by Adorno to Ernst Bloch in 1962. Also cited by Rolf Tiedemann in his ‘Editorische Nachbemerkungen’ (Editor’s Comment) (1973: 384).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0725513612453422">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Aphorism 82: ‘Drei Schritt vom Leibe’, 1945, in 1973d [1951a], renamed ‘Keeping one’s distance’ in the Jephcott translation (1974: 126–8).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0725513612453422">
<label>5.</label>
<p>‘The changing gesture of the puzzle game – not the bare solution as such, provides the prototype of the solutions, which the materialistic practice has at its sole disposal. Materialism has given this relation a name that is philosophically authenticated: dialectics. It seems to me that philosophical interpretation is only possible if it is dialectical’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0725513612453422">Adorno, 1973c [1931]</xref>, §15: 338). ‘All art works, and art as a whole, are riddles’, he concludes in <italic>The Aesthetic Theory</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0725513612453422">Adorno 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0725513612453422">1984</xref>): ‘Works of art contain the solution potentially, it is not objectively established … Truth content is the objective answer or solution to the riddle posed by any particular work. By calling for a solution, it points to its truth content, which in turn cannot actually be narrowed down, except by philosophical reflection. This alone is what legitimates aesthetics.’ See ‘Concerning the truth content of art works’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0725513612453422">Adorno 1984</xref> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0725513612453422">1970</xref>]: 186).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0725513612453422">
<label>6.</label>
<p>After partial publication, the ‘Studies in Husserl and the Phenomenological Antimonies’ did not appear in definitive form until 1956 in German, and were included in <italic>Zur Metakritik der Erkenntnistheorie</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0725513612453422">1971 [1956]</xref>: 7–245). An English translation by Willis Domingo appeared in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0725513612453422">1982</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0725513612453422">
<label>7.</label>
<p>This is what Adorno calls the rejection of ‘irrational, meaningless purposes, namely of desire – while only in defending these, reason would be really rational’ (1973d [1951a]: 67, 1974: 60); such rejection has consequences for the establishment of a therapeutic aim: the ‘cultivation’ instead of the ‘decomposition of the superego’. Cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0725513612453422">Adorno (1972e [1955]</xref>: 64–9). See also Adorno, <italic>Negative Dialektik </italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0725513612453422">1973e [1966a]</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0725513612453422">
<label>8.</label>
<p>The original English version of these studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0725513612453422">Löwenthal and Guterman 1987</xref> [1949]) appeared in German (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0725513612453422">1990</xref>) as ‘Falsche Propheten: Studien zur faschistischen Agitation’.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0725513612453422">
<label>9.</label>
<p>According to Adorno, the libido theory is ‘the core of psychoanalytical teaching’. For radical psychoanalysis, he writes, ‘libido is something “pre-social”, the “actual psychic reality”’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0725513612453422">Adorno 1972a [1946/1952]</xref>: 20–41].</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-0725513612453422">
<label>10.</label>
<p>It should be remembered here that Freud’s colleague and friend, Ernst Simmel, has characterized the exterminatory anti-Semitism of the Nazis and their allies as a psychosis. ‘This clinical syndrome, unrestricted, aggressive destructiveness under the spell of a delusion, in complete denial of reality, is well-known as a psychosis; it is the paranoiac form of schizophrenia. Anti-Semitism as a group phenomenon is, according to this view, not a group neurosis, but a group psychosis’. The pathologically weakened ‘ego of the individual psychotic, by submerging itself into a pathological mass, saves itself from individual regression by regressing collectively’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0725513612453422">Simmel 1946</xref>: 33, 49).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-0725513612453422">
<label>11.</label>
<p>Freud had considered the possibility of an abrupt dissolution of the cohesiveness of ‘artificial masses’ (like the church or the army): ‘the loss of the leader in some sense or other, the birth of misgivings about him, brings on the outbreak of panic, though the danger remains the same; the mutual ties between the members of the group disappear, as a rule, at the same time as the tie with their leader. The group vanishes in dust, like a Prince Rupert’s drop when its tail is broken off’, in <italic>Group Psychology and the Analysis of the Ego</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0725513612453422">Freud 1967</xref>: Chap. V: 29).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>) <source>Ästhetische Theorie</source>, <comment>GS 7</comment>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1971 [1956]</year>) <source>Zur Metakritik der Erkenntnistheorie: Studien über Husserl und die phänomenologischen Antinomien, GS 5</source>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>, <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>245</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1972a [1946a, 1952]</year>) <article-title>Die revidierte Psychoanalyse</article-title>, <source>GS</source> <volume>8</volume>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>, <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1972b [1946b]</year>) <article-title>Anti-Semitism and fascist propaganda</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Simmel</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Anti-Semitism: A Social Disease</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Universities Press</publisher-name> <comment>[reprinted in English in <italic>Gesammelte Schriften </italic>8. Frankfurt: Suhrkamp, 397–401]</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1972c [1950]</year>) <source>The Authoritarian Personality: Studies in Prejudice</source>, with <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Frenkel–Brunswick</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Levinson</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nevitt Sanford</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harper &amp; Brothers</publisher-name>. <comment>[Adorno’s contributions to this study are available in English in: Soziologische Schriften, <italic>GS </italic>9(1). Frankfurt: Suhrkamp, part 1, ch. 2]</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1972d [1951b]</year>) <article-title>Freudian theory and the pattern of fascist propaganda</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Róheim</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Psychoanalysis and the Social Sciences</source>, <volume>vol. 3</volume>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Universities Press</publisher-name>. <comment>[Adorno, <italic>GS</italic>, 8. Frankfurt: Suhrkamp, 408–433] [reprinted in Bernstein JM (ed.) (1991) <italic>The</italic> <italic>Culture Industry</italic>:<italic> Selected Essays on Mass Culture</italic>. London: Routledge]</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1972e [1955]</year>) <comment>Zum Verhältnis von Psychologie und Soziologie, <italic>GS</italic> 8</comment>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>, <fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1972f [1966b]</year>) <comment>Postscriptum, <italic>GS</italic> 8</comment>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>, <fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1973a [1924]</year>) <source>Die Transzendenz des Dinglichen und Noematischen in Husserls Philosophie</source>, <comment>GS 1</comment>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>, <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1973b [1927]</year>) <comment>Der Begriff des Unbewußten in der transzendentalen Seelenlehre. <italic>GS</italic> 1</comment>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>, <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1973c [1931]</year>) <comment>Die Aktualität der Philosophie, <italic>GS</italic> 1</comment>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>, <fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>344</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1973d [1951a]</year>) <source>Minima Moralia: Reflexionen aus dem beschädigten Leben</source>, <comment>GS 4</comment>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1973e [1966a]</year>) <source>Negative Dialektik</source>, <comment>GS</comment> <comment>6</comment>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1973f [1966a]</year>) <source>Negative Dialectics</source>, trans. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Ashton</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York: Seabury/London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <source>Minima Moralia: Reflections from Damaged Life</source>, trans. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Jephcott</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New Left Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1977 [1963]</year>) <article-title>Sexualtabus und Recht heute</article-title>, <source>GS</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>). <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>, <fpage>533</fpage>–<lpage>554</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <source>Against Epistemology: A Metacritique: Studies in Husserl and the Phenomenological Antinomies</source>, trans. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Domingo</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <source>Aesthetic Theory</source>, ed. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Tiedemann</surname>
<given-names>R, trans.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lenhardt</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003a [1940sa]</year>) <article-title>Notizen zur neuen Anthropologie</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Tiedemann</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Frankfurter Adorno-Blätter</source> <volume>VIII</volume>. <publisher-loc>Göttingen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Edition Text und Kritik</publisher-name>, <comment>69ff</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003b [1940sb]</year>) <article-title>Notiz zu Psychologie und Gesellschaft. See: Individuum und Gesellschaft: Entwürfe und Skizzen</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Tiedemann</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Frankfurter Adorno-Blätter</source> <volume>VIII</volume>. <publisher-loc>Göttingen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Edition Text und Kritik</publisher-name>, <fpage>86</fpage> ff.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Horkheimer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Briefwechsel</source> <volume>I</volume> <comment>(1927–1937)</comment>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>, <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bonss</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Psychoanalyse als Wissenschaft und Kritik. Zur Freudrezeption der kritischen Theorie</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Bonss</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Honneth</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Sozialforschung als Kritik: Zum sozialwissenschaftlichen Potential der Kritischen Theorie</source>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>, <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Claussen</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <source>Unterm Konformitätszwang: Zum Verhältnis von Kritischer Theorie und Psychoanalyse</source>. <publisher-loc>Bremen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bettina Wassmann</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23a-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cornelius</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1919 [1911]</year>) <source>Einleitung in die Philosophie</source>. <publisher-loc>Leipzig/Berlin</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dahmer</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) (<year>1980</year>) <source>Analytische Sozialpsychologie</source>, <volume>vol. 1</volume>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name> <comment>[includes German translations of Adorno’s ‘Freudian Theory and the Pattern of Fascist Propaganda’ and ‘Anti-Semitism and Mass Psychopathology’: 282–342]</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Freud</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1962 [1927]</year>) <source>The Future of an Illusion</source>, trans. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Robson-Scott</surname>
<given-names>WD with</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Strachey</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hogarth</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Freud</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1963a [1921]</year>) <source>Massenpsychologie und Ich-Analyse, GW 8</source>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>S. Fischer Verlag</publisher-name>, <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Freud</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1963b [1923]</year>) <comment>Bemerkungen zur Theorie und Praxis der Traumdeutung, <italic>GW</italic> 8</comment>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>S. Fischer Verlag</publisher-name>, <fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>314</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Freud</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1963c</year>) <article-title>Remarks upon the theory and practice of dream interpretation</article-title>. In: <source>Therapy and Technique</source>, trans. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Rieff</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Collier/Macmillan</publisher-name>, <volume>XVII</volume>: <fpage>212</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Freud</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1963d [1927]</year>) <source>Die Zukunft einer Illusion, GW</source> <comment>14</comment>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>S. Fischer Verlag</publisher-name>, <fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Freud</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1966</year>) <source>Jokes and Their Relation to the Unconscious</source>, trans. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Strachey</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Freud</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1967 [1921]</year>) <source>Group Psychology and the Analysis of the Ego</source>, trans. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Strachey</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Liverwright</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Freud</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1969 [1905]</year>) <source>Der Witz und seine Beziehung zum Unbewußten, GW</source> <comment>6</comment>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>S. Fischer Verlag</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Heinz</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dahmer</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>Psychoanalyse und Kantianismus: Ein Beitrag zur Theoriegeschichte</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Elrod</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <source>Der Wolf im Schafspelz: Erikson, die Ich-Psychologie und das Anpassungsproblem</source>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Campus</publisher-name>, <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Horkheimer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <source>Dialectic of Enlightenment</source>, trans. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Cumming</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York: Seabury/London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Horkheimer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1987a [1926]</year>) <article-title>Rudolf Eucken: Ein Epigone des Idealismus, <italic>GS </italic>2</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fischer</publisher-name>, <fpage>154</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Horkheimer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1987b [1944, 1947]</year>) <article-title>Limits of enlightenment</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Horkheimer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, <source>Dialektik der Aufklärung und Schriften 1940–1950, GS 5</source>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fischer</publisher-name>, <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37a-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lorenzer</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Psychoanalyse als kritische Theorie</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Schmidt</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Altwicker</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Max Horkheimer heute: Werk und Wirkung</source>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fischer</publisher-name>, <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Löwenthal</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Falsche Propheten: Studien zum Autoritarismus</article-title>. In: <source>Schriften</source> <volume>3</volume>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>, <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Löwenthal</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guterman</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1987 [1949]</year>) <source>Prophets of Deceit: A Study of the Techniques of the American Agitator</source> <comment>(Studies in Prejudice Series, vol. 5) [re-issued as <italic>False Prophets: Studies on Authoritarianism</italic> (Communication in Society Series, vol. 3)</comment>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction Books</publisher-name>.]</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Die Wunde Freud</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Klein</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Adorno Handbuch: Leben - Werk – Wirkung</source>. <publisher-loc>Stuttgart</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Metzler &amp; Poeschel</publisher-name>, <fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Simmel</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) (<year>1946</year>) <article-title>Anti<bold>-</bold>Semitism and mass psychology</article-title>. In: <source>Anti-Semitism: A Social Disease</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Universities Press</publisher-name>, <volume>Ch. 3</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Simmel</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Antisemitismus und Massen-Psychopathologie</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Dahmer</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Analytische Sozialpsychologie</source>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>, <fpage>282</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0725513612453422">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tiedemann</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Editorische Nachbemerkungen</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Adorno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <comment>(1973b [1927]) Der Begriff des Unbewußten in der transzendentalen Seelenlehre. <italic>GS</italic> 1</comment>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>, <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>