<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BJI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spbji</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Infection Prevention</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1757-1774</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1757-1782</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1757177413478537</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1757177413478537</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Your journal needs YOU! A call to interaction</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wigglesworth</surname><given-names>Neil</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>44</fpage>
<lpage>45</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Infection Prevention Society</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The <italic>Journal of Infection Prevention</italic> is one of the vehicles for the delivery of the Infection Prevention Society’s Strategic Plan 2011–2016 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1757177413478537">Storr et al, 2012</xref>), particularly those strategic objectives that are within Strategic Aim 2: “IPS will influence and promote the evidence base for infection prevention practice that is adopted universally”, specifically the provision of education, evidence and a mechanism for the publication of best practice, innovation and research.</p>
<p>It is my privilege to serve as Editor of the <italic>Journal of Infection Prevention</italic> until the autumn of 2014, and I’d like to use the opportunity of my first editorial, having given way to a guest editorial in the January issue, to issue a call to everyone who reads the journal. Not only a call to action but specifically a call to interaction! I would like to invite readers, subscribers and members of the Infection Prevention Society to interact with the journal and with the Editor, the Editorial Management Group, with the authors of articles, commentary and columns and with each other. We will come back to what forms these interactions might take shortly, but first, a digression.</p>
<p>Why do we read the <italic>Journal of Infection Prevention</italic> or any professional or academic publication? I can only speak for myself. I would list my reasons as education, information, stimulation, perhaps at times entertainment, and a professional responsibility to keep my knowledge of infection prevention and related specialities up to date. Does the <italic>Journal of Infection Prevention</italic> help with these aims? The January 2013 issue of this journal contained, amongst a range of contents, a comprehensive update on the prevention of surgical site infection. This March issue contains original articles and reports on subjects as diverse as commissioning in the new English NHS, healthcare waste, the preventability of Gram negative bacteraemia and novel disinfectants. Does this content meet your needs as infection prevention practitioners and other specialists? What else would you like to see published?</p>
<p>If you have views about the above questions or about the content of the journal, we’d like to hear them. So how can you respond to this call for interaction? There are two specific examples in this current issue. First, in the latest version of her Outbreak Column’, “Pseudo outbreaks (part 1)”, Dr Evonne Curran challenges the received wisdom regarding definitions of what constitutes an outbreak and what is a ‘pseudo-outbreak’, and argues for the creation of a new category of outbreak, which she terms “no-infection outbreaks” to be considered. Is she correct? I am certain Evonne will want your feedback on this proposal; indeed, she specifically invites comments as well as suggesting that colleagues write outbreak columns of their own for publication in the <italic>Journal of Infection Prevention.</italic> So our first example of interaction is a response to Evonne’s proposal: write a letter to the editor, give us your views and let’s start a debate. It is only through new ideas and vigorous debate about them that we move forward as a speciality. As well as the specific example given here, I would very much welcome letters to the Editor about any of the articles, reports and columns in the journal. Debating research findings and engaging in open professional critique is a vital function of academic and professional publishing. This debate and critique is facilitated by correspondence, so start writing those letters now! The second example of a very simple opportunity to interact can be found in the ‘Journal Watch’ feature in this issue. For the first time since its inception, a reader submitted an article for consideration for inclusion in the Journal Watch and it was duly included. As the current author of the Journal Watch feature I can only include papers that I become aware of, and this can only be a small fraction of the available literature on infection prevention and control and related subjects. You can be the eyes of the journal – how often do you come across an article that makes you think or highlights an interesting issue? Do you then raise awareness of it by sharing the information among your team and wider colleagues? Why not e-mail me (<email>editor@ips.uk.net</email>) and let me know? Perhaps we can share it with all of our readers.</p>
<p>The most obvious way to contribute something to the <italic>Journal of Infection Prevention</italic> is to submit something for publication. We’ve already discussed correspondence, a valid submission type in its own right, but what else? The most obvious, but by no means the only means, is a standard manuscript. This can be up to 4,000 words (sometimes more, especially if it involves qualitative research) about a piece of research, a service or quality improvement project or initiative. Or, what about a review paper? Have you had to review the evidence on a topic for an academic piece of work or to make service or policy recommendations? Why not share your efforts with your peers and the wider infection prevention and control community? There are also other options aside from the standard submission. If you have a smaller piece of work or a current issue to highlight, why not consider a short report? These can be anywhere between 1,000 and 2,000 words (about the length of this Editorial) and are a great way to dip your toe into writing for publication. One final option, and something I’d strongly encourage, is ‘photo surveillance’: a photograph and some explanation of an issue of interest or practice issue you’ve identified. For a good example see “Does this look familiar? Blind ends and dead legs” by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1757177413478537">Green and Avrell (2012)</xref> in the July 2012 edition of the <italic>Journal of Infection Prevention.</italic> Writing for publication can be a bit daunting, but don’t let it put you off. There are always people willing to help and every one of us has been through the experience of writing and submitting their first article. The Editorial Management Group can potentially offer help and advice or direct you to willing colleagues who can support you in getting your work into the journal.</p>
<p>Letters, articles, short reports, photo surveillance – there are many ways to get involved and interact! So I’ll conclude by paraphrasing Lord Kitchener’s famous rallying call in the First World War recruitment poster to the British public. The <italic>Journal of Infection Prevention</italic> is your journal whether you are a reader, subscriber, contributor and/or member of the Infection Prevention Society, and: Your journal needs YOU!</p>
<sig-block>
<sig><bold><italic>Neil Wigglesworth</italic></bold><break/>
<italic>Editor, Journal of Infection Prevention, Infection Prevention Society, Public Health Wales, Cardiff, Wales, UK</italic><break/>
<italic>Email: <email>neil.wigglesworth@wales.nhs.uk</email></italic></sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1757177413478537">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Avrell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Does this look familiar? Blind ends and dead legs</article-title>. <source>Journal of Infection Prevention</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>128</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1757177413478537">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Storr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loveday</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kilpatrick</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Disney, engagement, action: the Infection Prevention Society’s strategy from development to launch</article-title>. <source>Journal of Infection Prevention</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>