<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spscx</journal-id>
<journal-title>Science Communication</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1075-5470</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-8545</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1075547012458290</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1075547012458290</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Heightening Uncertainty Around Certain Science</article-title>
<subtitle>Media Coverage, False Balance, and the Autism-Vaccine Controversy</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>Graham N.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1075547012458290">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>Christopher E.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1075547012458290">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1075547012458290"><label>1</label>Cornell University, Ithaca, NY, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1075547012458290"><label>2</label>George Mason University, VA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1075547012458290">Graham N. Dixon, Department of Communication, Cornell University, 336 Kennedy Hall, Ithaca, NY 14850, USA. Email: <email>gnd5@cornell.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>35</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>358</fpage>
<lpage>382</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>To investigate how balanced presentations of the autism-vaccine controversy influence judgments of vaccine risk, we randomly assigned 327 participants to news articles that presented balanced claims both for and against an autism-vaccine link, antilink claims only, prolink claims only, or unrelated information. Readers in the balanced condition were less certain that vaccines did not cause autism and more likely to believe experts were divided on the issue. The relationship between exposure to balanced coverage and certainty was mediated by the belief that medical experts are divided about a potential autism-vaccine link. We discuss theoretical and practical implications of these findings.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>false balance</kwd>
<kwd>autism-vaccine controversy</kwd>
<kwd>risk communication</kwd>
<kwd>uncertainty</kwd>
<kwd>media norms</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1075547012458290" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>For many people, news media are important sources of health risk information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1075547012458290">Vasterman, Yzermans, &amp; Dirkzwager, 2005</xref>), especially for vaccine safety issues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1075547012458290">Freed, Clark, Butchart, Singer, &amp; Davis, 2011</xref>). This reliance on news media, however, raises a number of issues about media coverage of risk, including representations of (un)certainty about strength of scientific evidence for or against a particular risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1075547012458290">Corbett &amp; Durfee, 2004</xref>), norms or standards of conduct that may shape coverage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1075547012458290">Clarke, 2008</xref>), and how health officials can effectively communicate risk based on these considerations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1075547012458290">Clarke, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>This study examines, vis-à-vis the autism-vaccine controversy (AVC), how the ways journalists communicate certainty of scientific evidence about health risk shape perceived certainty about an autism-vaccine link. We build on literature on risk-related uncertainty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1075547012458290">Powell, Dunwoody, Griffin, &amp; Neuwirth, 2007</xref>), including the relationship between news media coverage of scientific uncertainty about risk and uncertainty judgments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1075547012458290">Corbett &amp; Durfee, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1075547012458290">Jensen &amp; Hurley, 2012</xref>). Such research, however, has not linked <italic>falsely balanced</italic> media coverage of scientific evidence about risk and uncertainty judgments. While balance is considered a prominent journalistic norm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1075547012458290">Clarke, 2008</xref>), “false balance” occurs when a perspective supported by an overwhelming amount of evidence is presented alongside others with less/no support and context—where the strength of evidence lies—is excluded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1075547012458290">Dearing, 1995</xref>). As a result, false balance may give the erroneous impression of scientific uncertainty about evidence for or against risk.</p>
<p>In the case of the AVC, where rigorous epidemiological studies have found no evidence of a link between vaccines and autism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1075547012458290">Gerber &amp; Offit, 2009</xref>), falsely balanced news media coverage may have contributed to public uncertainty about a link (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1075547012458290">Speers &amp; Lewis, 2004</xref>). However, while scholars have examined how media coverage of vaccine safety issues has influenced public confidence in immunization as well as uptake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1075547012458290">M. J. Smith, Ellenberg, Bell, &amp; Rubin, 2008</xref>), little is known whether and, if so, how falsely balanced AVC news media coverage affects readers’ perceptions of this issue. Thus, we explore whether falsely balanced news media representations—those that emphasize that vaccines may or may not cause autism—can give the <italic>impression</italic> of balanced coverage, whether this impression leads individuals to be more <italic>uncertain</italic> about an autism-vaccine link, and potential mechanisms that drive this effect: specifically, the role of a <italic>perception of a divide</italic> in the expert (medical) community about a link. In addressing each area, we discuss implications for journalism practice and risk communication.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1075547012458290">
<title>Literature Review</title>
<p>In the following sections, we define balanced media coverage as a journalistic norm, provide a conceptual overview of risk-related uncertainty, and document media coverage of the AVC, which informs our research questions and hypotheses.</p>
<sec id="section3-1075547012458290">
<title>The Balance Norm: Promise and Peril</title>
<p>As rules and expectations for behavior, norms guide individual action within groups, organizations, and institutions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1075547012458290">Cialdini, Kallgren, &amp; Reno, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1075547012458290">Merton, 1942</xref>). In the journalism profession, norms help shape how issues are reported and reflect a variety of social forces with which journalists must contend, including organizational pressures within the newsroom, such as editor expectations, as well as outside pressures (i.e., government laws; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1075547012458290">Hanitzsch et al., 2011</xref>). Among them is “balance,” which is particularly relevant when covering controversial stories that involve competing viewpoints.</p>
<p>Defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1075547012458290">Entman (1989)</xref>, balance “aims for neutrality [and] requires that reporters present the views of legitimate spokespersons of the conflicting sides in any significant dispute . . . with roughly equal attention” (p. 30). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1075547012458290">Clarke (2008)</xref> considered this approach an example of “balance as quality” where two well-known perspectives are presented in a point-counterpoint format (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1075547012458290">Gans, 1979</xref>). For example, in reporting science news, journalists may present the views of a “maverick”—a person whose views are at odds with an established authority—along with the views of the (scientific) establishment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1075547012458290">Dearing, 1995</xref>). However, journalists may also embrace a “balance as quantity” approach by highlighting all viewpoints regardless of how well known they are to audiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1075547012458290">Griffin &amp; Dunwoody, 1997</xref>).</p>
<p>A balanced approach to reporting, whether as quantity or quality, can be advantageous or disadvantageous. By including diverse viewpoints, journalists can achieve objectivity by abstaining from advocating particular positions; avoiding “distortion by personal feelings, prejudices, and interpretations” as well as by social, political, and economic forces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1075547012458290">Myrick, 2002</xref>, p. 1); and presenting “a diversity of positions and voices” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1075547012458290">Durham, 1998</xref>, p. 119) so that people can make informed decisions. Balance can also ensure accuracy in that important information on an issue is not omitted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1075547012458290">Singer, 1990</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1075547012458290">Dunwoody and Peters (1992)</xref> claimed that balance often acts as “a surrogate for validity checks” (p. 210) for journalists who, due to lack of time or topical expertise, cannot check the validity of every claim presented. Balance can also be used by journalists as a means to gain readership by highlighting a controversy between two or more perspectives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1075547012458290">Dunwoody, 1999</xref>). Journalists then have an opportunity to play an important role in not only reporting on controversy but also actively shaping how readers understand the issue.</p>
<p>However, scholars have also argued that balanced reporting can weaken a commitment to accuracy if journalists fail to scrutinize details, avoid errors, and ensure that the perspective with the most supporting scientific evidence is conveyed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1075547012458290">Boykoff &amp; Boykoff, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1075547012458290">Corbett &amp; Durfee, 2004</xref>). Balanced reporting without added context about where strength of evidence lies (i.e., false balance) may suggest that opposing forces are equally well supported by evidence when that may not be the case (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1075547012458290">Stocking, 1999</xref>). It may also suggest that well-established science is being openly debated within the scientific community when, in fact, that is not the case (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1075547012458290">Wilson, 2000</xref>). As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1075547012458290">Corbett and Durfee (2004)</xref> concluded,
<disp-quote>
<p>[Although] the long-standing tradition of bringing in opposing sides is an attempt to provide balance and objectivity . . . it is problematic to introduce dissent into an area where science largely agrees, particularly for readers unable to evaluate where the balance of the evidence lies. (p. 142)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1075547012458290">
<title>Risk-Related Uncertainty: Definition, Determinants, and the Role of News Media</title>
<p>By introducing dissent into an area where science largely agrees, falsely balanced news coverage could be an important determinant of perceptions of risk-related uncertainty. Uncertainty reflects a perceived lack of knowledge in situations where details of an event “are ambiguous, complex, unpredictable, or probabilistic” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1075547012458290">Brashers, 2001</xref>, p. 478) and where information needed to achieve clarification is lacking, incomplete, unclear, conflicting, or changing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1075547012458290">Frewer et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1075547012458290">Weary &amp; Jacobson, 1997</xref>). This deficit can apply to what one knows or does not know (internal certainty) and one’s belief about what others know (external certainty; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1075547012458290">Powell et al., 2007</xref>). In the context of risk, uncertainty represents one’s probabilistic judgment of an outcome occurring, such as a loss of some kind, and its perceived desirability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1075547012458290">Frewer et al., 2003</xref>). Our work builds on existing literature on social-psychological factors that shape uncertainty perceptions and reactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1075547012458290">Afifi &amp; Weiner, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1075547012458290">Powell et al., 2007</xref>); how such perceptions may inform risk perception, trust, and other judgments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1075547012458290">Corbett &amp; Durfee, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1075547012458290">Johnson &amp; Slovic, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1075547012458290">1998</xref>); and public and scientific views on different kinds of uncertainty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1075547012458290">Frewer et al., 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1075547012458290">Frewer et al., 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>In news coverage of risk, scientific uncertainty can be a function of what is included as well as of what is excluded in coverage. For example, content analytic studies suggest that news coverage of scientific studies often fails to report uncertainty by excluding limitations that serve to place study findings in a larger context of existing knowledge. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1075547012458290">Jensen (2008)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1075547012458290">Parascandola (2000)</xref>, and others have reasoned that hedging (i.e., presenting the limitations), as a means of expressing uncertainty, may shape people’s perceptions of uncertainty about the strength of evidence underlying scientific research. These perceptions, in turn, may serve as a cue that informs how people process scientific information and view the credibility of science and scientists. In one study, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1075547012458290">Jensen (2008)</xref> exposed undergraduate students to hedged or nonhedged newspaper articles about cancer research; hedged statements, in turn, were attributed to scientists either affiliated or not affiliated with the study. Attributing hedging to affiliated scientists resulted in participants rating scientists and journalists as more trustworthy compared to the other conditions. In a follow-up study, hedging attributed to scientists affiliated with a cancer-related research study reduced fatalistic beliefs about cancer (e.g., that everything causes cancer; that there is little one can do to prevent cancer; etc.) as well as backlash against nutritional recommendations related to cancer prevention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1075547012458290">Jensen, Moriarty, Hurley, &amp; Stryker, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Work by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1075547012458290">Corbett and Durfee (2004)</xref> is another area of research that links news media coverage of scientific uncertainty and audience perceptions of uncertainty. They pointed to evidence that media have often overplayed the level of uncertainty about the existence, extent, and effects of human-induced climate change. They manipulated newspaper articles about a thickening of the Antarctic ice sheet to emphasize controversy (other scientists disagreed with the findings), context (other studies have found the ice sheet to be thinning, which is consistent with climate change impacts), both controversy and context, or neither (as a control). They found that individuals exposed to the news article with context only expressed a significantly higher level of certainty that climate change was a scientific fact than stories that emphasized neither controversy nor context or only controversy. Thus, providing context that reflected the scientific consensus on global warming influenced perceptions of certainty about this issue.</p>
<p>A final area of research of relevance to our study examined convergent or divergent coverage of science issues and its relationship to viewer uncertainty. Divergent reporting often serves a strategic purpose by creating controversy in order to attract audiences and involves pitting multiple viewpoints against one another. By contrast, convergent information emphasizes similar viewpoints and consensus. Convergent-themed coverage within and across different media may strengthen one’s confidence in or certainty of issue-related information, whereas divergent coverage has the opposite effect. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1075547012458290">Jensen and Hurley (2012)</xref> exposed 242 college students to news coverage about two scientific controversies: dioxin regulation and gray wolf reintroduction. For each issue, participants received two news articles that were either consistent (both offered the same viewpoint on the merits or drawbacks of either issue) or divergent (one article discusses the merits and the other the drawbacks). Participants felt more uncertain about dioxin regulation after reading two divergent dioxin articles but felt less uncertain about wolf reintroduction when exposed to two divergent wolf articles.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1075547012458290">
<title>Balanced Reporting and the AVC</title>
<p>While science is largely a deliberative process where competing perspectives are weighed by the strength of evidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1075547012458290">J. Smith, 2005</xref>), rarely do two competing perspectives hold equal amounts of supporting evidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1075547012458290">Clarke, 2008</xref>). However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1075547012458290">Boykoff (2007)</xref> noted that a scientific consensus on an issue raises more, not less, avenues for news media to cover perspectives that disagree with that consensus. Moreover, journalists might deem events to be newsworthy if a degree of controversy exists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1075547012458290">Dunwoody, 1999</xref>), and they might therefore cover multiple sides of the controversy despite a scientific consensus supporting only one side (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1075547012458290">Stocking, 1999</xref>). For instance, in the case of global warming, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1075547012458290">Boykoff and Boykoff (2004)</xref> found that the majority (52.65%) of U.S. newspaper coverage gave roughly equal attention to human-induced warming—a view backed by a scientific consensus—and to the view that it was due exclusively to natural forces. The emphasis on both perspectives was speculated to have helped attenuate meaningful debate on and the implementation of policies for reducing global carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
<p>In the case of the AVC, journalists have been criticized for balancing prolink claims (i.e., that vaccines cause autism) against antilink claims (i.e., that vaccines do not cause autism; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1075547012458290">Lewis &amp; Speers, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1075547012458290">Offit &amp; Coffin, 2003</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1075547012458290">Clarke (2008)</xref> found that in a sample of 279 U.K. and U.S. newspaper articles about the AVC, 58% mentioned both pro- and antilink claims. In addition, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1075547012458290">Speers and Lewis (2004)</xref> analyzed U.K. television, radio, and newspaper coverage of the measles, mumps, and rubella (MMR) vaccine–autism issue from January to September 2002 and conducted two street surveys in April and October 2002, each involving 1,000 face-to-face interviews. A potential link between MMR and autism received coverage in 69% of stories; only 37% mentioned that MMR is safe. When asked about the weight of scientific evidence about a link, 39% of April respondents said that the evidence was equally divided for and against. By October, the figure increased to 53%. Moreover, the proportion of April respondents who felt that a connection was backed by research stood at 25% (falling only slightly by October to 20%), and only 23% of the October sample felt that the weight of evidence favored a rejection of a link. However, individual media exposure and perceptions of certainty about an autism-vaccine link were not recorded.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1075547012458290">
<title>The Present Study</title>
<p>In extending the aforementioned research, we first examine whether (falsely) balanced news media representations of the AVC can give news readers the <italic>impression</italic> of balanced coverage. It is this perception that may inform certainty judgments. Our first research question is as follows:</p>
<list id="list1-1075547012458290" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Research Question 1</italic>: Can readers perceive balance in a news article where two perspectives (MMR vaccine causes autism/MMR vaccine does not cause autism) are given approximately equal attention compared to articles that mention only one perspective (anti- or prolink only)?</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Second, we provide a more thorough assessment of certainty perceptions, focusing on confidence in one’s own knowledge about an issue as well in what others (e.g., scientists) know about it. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1075547012458290">Jensen’s (2008)</xref> work has yet to explore how hedging shapes perceptions of certainty about, for example, what people think experts believe about evidence for/against cancer prevention. Moreover, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1075547012458290">Corbett and Durfee (2004)</xref> focused on perceptions of certainty about climate change as conveyed in the article, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1075547012458290">Jensen and Hurley (2012)</xref> assessed people’s certainty about dioxin regulation and wolf reintroduction in general. Neither assessed how certain news consumers personally felt about evidence for/against these issues or what/how they believed experts viewed these issues. Also, whereas Jensen and Hurley examined how uncertainty judgments were shaped by a series of news articles about science issues that presented either convergent or divergent viewpoints, we focus on balancing different perspectives on the AVC within the same article. We believe that this approach is more aligned with the definition of balanced reporting presented earlier in this literature review: telling all (or both) sides within the same unit of coverage.</p>
<p>Finally, we contend that false balance as defined in this article, while conceptually similar to hedging and context controversy, is also sufficiently different in how it informs perceptions of risk-related certainty. On one hand, all three concepts are facets of a broader journalistic norm that speaks to objectivity, accuracy, and appropriate ways of informing people about scientific research and evidence. On the other hand, hedging and context-controversy emphasize the importance of providing context in such coverage, in terms of the limitations of scientific studies and the state of existing evidence in support of opposition to particular claims. False balance arguably represents a case of “balance gone bad,” in which competing claims are included in coverage without the context viewers need to assess their validity. It is this lack of context that may shape perceptions of a divided scientific community about, in this case, the AVC and may contribute to internal and external uncertainty about an autism-vaccine link. These relationships are not posited in the hedging or context-controversy literature.</p>
<p>We therefore argue that falsely balanced media coverage of the AVC may have erroneously led individuals to (a) become more <italic>uncertain</italic> about an autism-vaccine link (internal certainty) and (b) perceive scientists as more uncertain about the issue (external certainty). We hypothesize the following:</p>
<list id="list2-1075547012458290" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1 (Internal Certainty)</italic>: Individuals exposed to balanced coverage of claims for/against an autism-vaccine link will be significantly less certain that vaccines do not cause autism than individuals exposed to coverage that mentions claims only supporting a link (prolink; Hypothesis 1A), only refuting a link (antilink; Hypothesis 1B), or no perspective (control article; Hypothesis 1C).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 2 (External Certainty)</italic>: Individuals exposed to balanced coverage of claims for/against an autism-vaccine link will be significantly less certain that scientists agree that there is no link than individuals exposed to coverage that mentions claims only supporting a link (prolink; Hypothesis 2A), only refuting a link (antilink; Hypothesis 2B), or no perspective (control article; Hypothesis 2C).</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Moreover, we are interested in the mechanisms that link balanced media coverage to uncertainty. Specifically, we identify “perception of a divide”—a perception of medical experts being divided over whether vaccines cause autism—as a potential mediator between balance and certainty perceptions. We chose this mediator because previous research indicates that falsely balancing perspectives can imply that both sides are equally supported by evidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1075547012458290">Clarke, 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1075547012458290">2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1075547012458290">Wilson, 2000</xref>). Our hypotheses are as follows:</p>
<list id="list3-1075547012458290" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 3</italic>: Individuals exposed to balanced coverage of claims for/against an autism-vaccine link will be more likely to perceive a divide within the medical community on whether vaccines cause autism than individuals exposed to coverage that mentions claims only supporting a link (prolink; Hypothesis 3A), only refuting a link (antilink; Hypothesis 3B), or no perspective (control article; Hypothesis 3C).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 4</italic>: Perception of a divide will mediate the relationship between exposure to the balanced condition and internal certainty that vaccines do not cause autism.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 5</italic>: Perception of a divide will mediate the relationship between exposure to the balanced condition and external certainty that scientists agree that vaccines do not cause autism.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1075547012458290" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section8-1075547012458290">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>An experiment involving real newspaper articles about the MMR vaccination–autism issue was administered to undergraduate students (<italic>n</italic> = 327; mean age = 19.9 years; 70% female) at a midsized northeastern U.S. university from September to December 2011. Participants were recruited using both in-class announcements and an online system. Participants received class extra credit on completion of the experiment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1075547012458290">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>After signing a consent form, participants were randomly assigned to one of four conditions (antilink, <italic>n</italic> = 84; prolink, <italic>n</italic> = 82; balanced, <italic>n</italic> = 80; and control article, <italic>n</italic> = 81) positioned in separate experiment rooms. This procedure was conducted over the course of 3 months. Participants first completed a short online questionnaire that requested demographic data (age, sex, race, and ethnicity). After completing the questionnaire, participants were asked to open a folder next to their computer and read a newspaper article contained therein. They then returned their article and answered a postexposure questionnaire that assessed reactions to the article (the manipulation check), perceptions of internal and external certainty about an MMR vaccination–autism link, and perceptions of a divide in the medical community related to a link.</p>
<p>A thorough debriefing was given to all participants following completion of the study where it was specifically stressed that a link between vaccination and autism has never been found in any peer-reviewed study. In addition, we provided each participant with information sheets about the AVC from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) and the American Academy of Pediatrics.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1075547012458290">
<title>Materials and Measures</title>
<sec id="section11-1075547012458290">
<title>Independent variables</title>
<p>All conditions, including the control article, were real news articles from prominent U.S. or U.K. newspapers/television news websites published online and in print. While text length differed across articles, we used identical font and removed journalist affiliations and source title. No other changes were made to the articles’ content.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1075547012458290">1</xref></sup> The antilink article involved a scientist presenting only the perspective that the MMR vaccine does <italic>not</italic> cause autism, whereas the prolink article involved a scientist presenting only the perspective that the MMR vaccine <italic>could</italic> cause autism. The balanced article involved presenting both pro- and antilink perspectives. The control article was about an unrelated issue.</p>
<p>To establish measurement validity, the manipulation check assessed—using a 6-point Likert-type agreement scale—whether participants exposed to a particular article actually perceived the article as prolink, antilink, or balanced; there was no check for the control article. Participants answered this item:</p>
<p>To what extent do you think the article</p>
<list id="list4-1075547012458290" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>presents only the perspective that the MMR vaccine does not cause/trigger autism,</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>presents only the perspective that the MMR vaccine could cause/trigger autism, or</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>presents both perspectives stating (a) the MMR vaccine could cause/trigger autism and (b) the MMR vaccine does not cause/trigger autism?</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Articles were neither coded for balance in terms of the amount of space devoted to prolink and antilink perspectives nor manipulated in such a fashion. Instead, our balanced article was selected because it mentioned both prolink and antilink perspectives in general, and we examined whether participants perceived it as balanced for this reason compared to those who received prolink-only and antilink-only articles.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1075547012458290">
<title>Dependent variables</title>
<p>Both internal and external certainty were measured using a 6-point certainty scale (1 = <italic>very uncertain</italic>, 6 = <italic>very certain</italic>) adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1075547012458290">Corbett and Durfee (2004)</xref>. Internal certainty consisted of the following single item: “Please indicate how certain YOU are that vaccines do not cause autism.” External certainty consisted of the following single item: “Please indicate how certain you believe SCIENTISTS are that vaccines do not cause autism.”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1075547012458290">
<title>Mediating variable</title>
<p>Perception of divide within the medical community regarding an MMR vaccination–autism link was measured via a 6-point Likert-type agreement scale. We used the following item: “The medical community is divided over whether vaccines cause autism.”</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1075547012458290" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section15-1075547012458290">
<title>Manipulation Check</title>
<p>The manipulation check assessed whether participants who read a particular article actually perceived it as prolink, antilink, or balanced. Separate one-way analyses of variance (ANOVAs) were conducted for antilink, prolink, and balanced statements that participants endorsed, each time using condition as the independent variable. Significant main effects for all three dependent variables were observed: perception of antilink, <italic>F</italic>(2, 251) = 66.787, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, η<sup>2</sup> = .4223; perception of prolink, <italic>F</italic>(2, 242) = 67.267, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, η<sup>2</sup> = .44; and perception of balance, <italic>F</italic>(2, 242) = 97.889, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, η<sup>2</sup> = .1897. The Games-Howell post hoc comparison test revealed that participants who read the article we coded as antilink rated it as antilink (<italic>M</italic> = 4.12, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.36) significantly more than prolink (<italic>M</italic> = 1.85, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.995), <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001; and balanced (<italic>M</italic> = 3.08, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.41), <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. Participants who read the article we coded as prolink also rated it as prolink (<italic>M</italic> = 4.12, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.16) significantly more than antilink (<italic>M</italic> = 2.12, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.93), <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001; and balanced (<italic>M</italic> = 3.21, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.3), <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. Finally, participants who read the article we coded as balanced rated it as balanced (<italic>M</italic> = 4.43, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.93) significantly more than antilink (<italic>M</italic> = 2.29, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.83), <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001; and prolink (<italic>M</italic> = 2.77, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.15), <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. Thus, there is clear evidence that individuals can differentiate prolink, antilink, and balanced perspectives when reading articles about the AVC.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1075547012458290">
<title>Internal Certainty (Hypothesis 1) and External Certainty (Hypothesis 2)</title>
<p>Hypothesis 1 posited that readers of balanced coverage of claims for/against a MMR vaccine–autism link will be significantly <italic>less</italic> certain that MMR vaccination does not cause autism than readers of the prolink (Hypothesis 1A), antilink (Hypothesis 1B), or control articles (Hypothesis 1C). A one-way ANOVA with condition as the independent variable and perception of internal certainty as the dependent variable was significant, <italic>F</italic>(3, 323) = 7.708, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, η<sup>2</sup> = .0673. The Games-Howell post hoc comparison test (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1075547012458290">Figure 1</xref>) revealed readers of the balanced condition to be significantly <italic>less</italic> certain that the MMR vaccine does not cause autism (<italic>M</italic> = 3.179, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.276) than readers of the antilink (<italic>M</italic> = 4.119, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.236), <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001; and control conditions (<italic>M</italic> = 3.79, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.577), <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. No significant difference was found for the prolink article. Thus, we achieved support for Hypotheses 1B and 1C but not for Hypothesis 1A.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1075547012458290" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Internal certainty ratings: Participants’ certainty that vaccines do not cause autism.</p>
<p>Note: The <italic>y</italic>-axis represents readers’ certainty ratings (1 = <italic>very uncertain</italic>, 6 = <italic>very certain</italic>). The <italic>x</italic>-axis denotes condition.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1075547012458290-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>Hypothesis 2 posited that readers of balanced coverage of claims for/against an MMR vaccine-autism link will be significantly <italic>less</italic> certain that scientists agree that MMR vaccination does not cause autism than readers of the prolink (Hypothesis 2A), antilink (Hypothesis 2B), or control articles (Hypothesis 2C). A one-way ANOVA with condition as the independent variable and perception of external certainty as the dependent variable was significant, <italic>F</italic>(3, 324) = 6.686, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, η<sup>2</sup> = .0588. Using the Games-Howell post hoc comparison test (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1075547012458290">Figure 2</xref>), we found that readers of the balanced article rated their external certainty (<italic>M</italic> = 3.784, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.336) as significantly less than readers of the antilink article (<italic>M</italic> = 4.595, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.152), <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. There was no significant difference between the balanced and prolink and balanced and control conditions. Thus, we achieved support for Hypothesis 2B but not for Hypotheses 2A and 2C.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1075547012458290" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>External certainty ratings: Participants’ perception of scientists’ certainty that vaccines do not cause autism.</p>
<p>Note: The <italic>y</italic>-axis represents readers’ certainty ratings (1 = <italic>very uncertain</italic>, 6 = <italic>very certain</italic>). The <italic>x</italic>-axis denotes condition.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1075547012458290-fig2.tif"/></fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1075547012458290">
<title>Perception of a Divide</title>
<p>Hypothesis 3 predicted that readers of balanced coverage of claims for/against an MMR vaccine–autism link would be more likely to perceive that the medical community is divided over whether there is a link than readers of the prolink (Hypothesis 3A), antilink (Hypothesis 3B), or control articles (Hypothesis 3C). A one-way ANOVA with condition as the independent variable and perception of divide as the dependent variable was significant, <italic>F</italic>(3, 325) = 10.155, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, η<sup>2</sup> = .0699. The Bonferroni post hoc comparison test (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1075547012458290">Figure 3</xref>) revealed that readers of the balanced condition perceived more of a divide (<italic>M</italic> = 3.822, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.129) than those in the antilink (<italic>M</italic> = 3.107, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.14), <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001; and control condition (<italic>M</italic> = 3.0732, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.097), <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. The prolink condition was not significantly different from all other conditions. Thus, we achieved support for Hypotheses 3B and 3C but not for Hypothesis 3A.</p>
<fig id="fig3-1075547012458290" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Perception that the medical community is divided over whether vaccines cause autism.</p>
<p>Note: The <italic>y</italic>-axis represents readers’ perception of a divide (1 = <italic>strongly disagree</italic>, 6 = <italic>strongly agree</italic>). The <italic>x</italic>-axis denotes condition.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1075547012458290-fig3.tif"/></fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1075547012458290">
<title>Mediation Analysis</title>
<p>In Hypothesis 4, we surmised that perceiving that the medical community is divided over an MMR vaccine–autism link would mediate the relationship between exposure to balanced information about a link (e.g., being in the balanced condition) and internal certainty about a link. Hypothesis 5 proposed the same effect for external certainty. To explore these hypotheses, we used <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1075547012458290">Hayes’s (2012)</xref> PROCESS macro, which combines many of the features of earlier mediation, moderation, and conditional mediation and moderation macros. While our proposed mediation does not require many of PROCESS’s features, the macro is appropriate to use because it accommodates dichotomous independent variables (i.e., whether or not a participant was in the balanced condition). It also estimates indirect and direct effects among the mediator(s), independent variable, and dependent variable and provides a point estimate and bias-corrected 95% confidence interval (CI) for the indirect effects via bootstrapping, which is advantageous in that the sampling distribution for the indirect effect is not assumed to be normally distributed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1075547012458290">Preacher, Rucker, &amp; Hayes, 2007</xref>). Coefficients are estimated using ordinary least squares regression.</p>
<p>Hypothesis 4 achieved support, in that the mediating relationship was partial rather than full (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1075547012458290">Table 1</xref>). Specifically, being in the balanced condition was positively associated with perceiving a divide in the medical community, which was, in turn, negatively associated with perceived internal certainty about an MMR-autism link. Moreover, the direct path between the balanced condition and perceived certainty was significant. Bias-corrected CIs for the total indirect effect did <italic>not</italic> include zero (95% CI = −0.3528, −0.0771), indicating a statistically meaningful indirect effect.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1075547012458290" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Results From Mediation Analysis (Dependent Variable = Perceived Personal Certainty Related to an Autism-Vaccine Link).</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1075547012458290" xlink:href="10.1177_1075547012458290-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Predictor</th>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic> Coefficient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Equation predicting mediator (perception of divide)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Intercept</td>
<td>3.2236<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1075547012458290">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Exposure to balanced condition (1 = <italic>yes</italic>)</td>
<td>0.5841<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1075547012458290">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Equation predicting dependent variable (perceived personal certainty that there is no autism-vaccine link)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Intercept</td>
<td>5.2247<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1075547012458290">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Exposure to balanced condition (1 = <italic>yes</italic>)</td>
<td>−0.3633<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1075547012458290">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mediator: Perception of divide</td>
<td>−0.4417<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1075547012458290">***</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1075547012458290">
<p>Note: Standardized coefficients are reported. Completely standardized indirect effect of exposure to balanced condition on perceived certainty via perception of a divide = −0.1922 (95% bootstrapped confidence interval = −0.3528, −0.0771).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-1075547012458290">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Hypothesis 5 also achieved support in that the mediating relationship was full rather than partial (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1075547012458290">Table 2</xref>). Specifically, being in the balanced condition was positively associated with perceiving a divide in the medical community, which was, in turn, negatively associated with perceived external certainty about an MMR-autism connection. The direct path between the balanced condition and perceived certainty was not significant. Bias-corrected CIs for the total indirect effect did <italic>not</italic> include zero (95% CI = −0.3623, −0.0814), indicating a statistically meaningful indirect effect.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1075547012458290" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Results From Mediation Analysis (Dependent Variable = Perceived Certainty That Scientists Agree That There Is No Autism-Vaccine Link).</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1075547012458290" xlink:href="10.1177_1075547012458290-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Predictor</th>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic> Coefficient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Equation predicting mediator (perception of divide)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Intercept</td>
<td>3.2154<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1075547012458290">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Exposure to balanced condition (1 = <italic>yes</italic>)</td>
<td>0.6073<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1075547012458290">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Equation predicting dependent variable (perceived certainty that scientists agree that there is no autism-vaccine link)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Intercept</td>
<td>5.4468<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1075547012458290">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Exposure to balanced condition (1 = <italic>yes</italic>)</td>
<td>−0.1981</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mediator: Perception of divide</td>
<td>−0.383<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1075547012458290">***</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1075547012458290">
<p>Note: Standardized coefficients are reported. Completely standardized indirect effect of exposure to balanced condition on perceived certainty via perception of a divide = −0.197 (95% bootstrapped confidence interval = −0.3623, −0.0814).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-1075547012458290">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1075547012458290" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In the present study, we found clear evidence that individuals can differentiate between a news article about the AVC that provided balanced coverage—in terms of mentioning claims that vaccines may or may not cause autism—and others that included only one perspective: in this case, prolink (that vaccines cause autism) or antilink (that vaccines do not cause autism). This finding is an important first step to examining the possible effect of balanced coverage on risk-related uncertainty judgments related to an autism-vaccine link. However, future research can potentially improve the validity of this measure. Balance was not coded in terms of percentage of text devoted to pro- and antilink perspectives. Also, participants were not asked to consider whether the article was “falsely balanced” in terms of asking if they were aware that there was no scientific evidence of an autism-vaccine link. Future work could attempt to assess whether people (a) think an article is balanced in terms of quantity and (b) can distinguish balance from false balance. Another important point regarding balanced reporting of the AVC is that journalists may pit parental testimonials (i.e., that they blame vaccines for their children’s’ autism) against scientific evidence such as findings from epidemiological studies. While these are potentially important facets of balanced coverage of vaccine controversies, our study looked exclusively at balance between statements made by scientists, not laypeople versus scientists. However, future research could look specifically at how balancing parental perspectives/experiences with scientist statements affects certainty judgments about an autism-vaccine link. Issues of argument strength and quality could potentially come into play.</p>
<p>We also focused on whether falsely balanced coverage affects perceived certainty about whether there could be a link between vaccines and autism and what individuals think scientists believe about the issue. Evidence from our study suggests that false balance heightened readers’ internal and external uncertainty regarding vaccines’ relationship with autism. We believe that using both types of certainty extends existing literature, which has largely focused on internal certainty and in less specific terms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1075547012458290">Corbett &amp; Durfee, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1075547012458290">Jensen &amp; Hurley, 2012</xref>). Moreover, the external certainty outcome measure is particularly important for the AVC, which involves news media covering competing claims about scientific evidence for/against a link. From such coverage, individuals may infer (perhaps erroneously) the state of expert knowledge. In reality, a strong consensus exists within the medical community that vaccines do not cause autism. This finding speaks to Jensen’s study on hedging in that falsely balanced media coverage of the AVC, by lacking context of where the body of evidence actually lies (no link), does not allow individuals to effectively process information about this issue and make an accurate determination of one’s own knowledge and the state of expert knowledge about an autism-vaccine link (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1075547012458290">Jensen, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1075547012458290">Jensen et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Finally, our results suggest that a perception of a divide mediates the relationship between false balance and uncertainty. Specifically, readers of the falsely balanced article were more likely to perceive that relevant actors were divided over the autism-vaccine link, which in turn lowered their certainty perceptions. In addition to informing judgments of issue-related uncertainty, falsely balanced media representations of the AVC can communicate that there are two sides to this issue that are equally supported by evidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1075547012458290">Clarke, 2008</xref>) by not providing the context needed for individuals to realize that while there are two views on this issue, only one (no link) is supported by scientific evidence. This view, in turn, may make one <italic>less</italic> certain that there is no link between vaccines and autism—internally and externally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1075547012458290">Speers &amp; Lewis, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>We also reason that perception of divide might be capturing a more latent construct, such as trust in the scientific/medical community: that “the experts” know what is going on and are taking steps to ensure vaccine safety and study the autism-vaccine link. Trust can be an important determinant of perceptions of risk, risk behavior, and attitudes, especially in situations of low knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1075547012458290">Siegrist &amp; Cvetkovich, 2002</xref>); it might also predict risk-related uncertainty perceptions. Another important factor to consider is “deference toward science:” the extent to which people defer to scientists in assessing scientific issues. While it has been shown to predict positive attitudes toward and public support of emerging technology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1075547012458290">Brossard &amp; Nisbet, 2007</xref>), deference to science might also influence external and internal certainty judgments about health risk. Thus, while not explored in this study, we encourage further research on the AVC that includes these variables as well as potential moderators for our mediation model. For instance, balanced media coverage could potentially affect uncertainty judgments about vaccine risk through the mediating impact of trust in the scientific medical community but only for individuals high in scientific deference.</p>
<sec id="section20-1075547012458290">
<title>Implications for Vaccine Risk Communication and Journalism Practice</title>
<p>Traditionally, health officials have responded to the challenges of communicating vaccine risks and benefits by focusing on public education: that the more the public is informed about the benefits of vaccines, the more supportive they will be of vaccination. However, increased education does not necessarily lead to greater appreciation and acceptance of scientific or medical issues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1075547012458290">Bauer, Allum, &amp; Miller, 2007</xref>). During the AVC, for instance, health officials devoted a considerable amount of time and energy emphasizing the safety of vaccines that were under scrutiny. This strategy unfortunately failed to address whether the government was doing enough to assess the potential risks of the vaccines, in particular MMR, and explain the rationale for policy decisions such as not replacing the MMR with separate vaccines for measles, mumps, and rubella (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1075547012458290">Clarke, 2008</xref>). Some scholars, therefore, argue that health officials should consider a more nuanced communication strategy that incorporates the dissemination of vaccine safety messages and proactive monitoring of media coverage to identity important issues being raised. Such an approach has benefited health officials in the past. For example, during the 2001 anthrax attacks, the CDC monitored coverage in major news media outlets to identify trends and important themes, which helped CDC officials craft and tailor health messages for journalists that the agency wished to see covered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1075547012458290">Prue, Lackey, Swenarski, &amp; Gannt, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>Based on this study, we argue that effective vaccine risk communication requires health officials to think beyond messages they wish to see disseminated and focus on the challenges journalist face in conveying those messages within news coverage. Journalists must negotiate various norms when reporting controversial stories, from the need to present an accurate account of all perspectives on an issue to the need to create controversial news that sells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1075547012458290">Bennett, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1075547012458290">Clarke, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1075547012458290">Ryan, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1075547012458290">Singer, 1990</xref>). Recommendations for journalists to better communicate about vaccine safety issues like the AVC place present accurate information for public consumption; on the other hand, they must consider the political norms and economic pressures of presenting all sides of the story, even those within the minority. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1075547012458290">Wilson (2000)</xref> suggested modifying the journalist tenet of balance so that scientific consensus and dissent are reported accurately. Balance can therefore be achieved without being a false balance in that competing viewpoints, such as claims for/against an autism-vaccine link, are presented along with added context of where the strength of evidence lies: that there is a strong scientific consensus backed by a number of rigorous studies finding no link between vaccines and autism (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1075547012458290">Institute of Medicine, 2004</xref>). Although not investigated in this study, previous work on hedging and context-controversy suggests that adding context to a balanced article, in terms of where new scientific knowledge fits in with existing knowledge, could have a number of positive outcomes, including heightened credibility of scientists and higher certainty that there is no autism-vaccine connection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1075547012458290">Corbett &amp; Durfee, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1075547012458290">Jensen, 2008</xref>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1075547012458290">Stocking, 1999</xref>). Future research could explore how journalists conceptualize context in reporting health issues like the AVC and whether or how it would fit within existing reporting standards that they follow. For example, could providing context be viewed as advocating for particular viewpoints and breaching objectivity? Do journalists feel confident in their ability to do so given that they may lack sufficient knowledge of such viewpoints, which warrants a balanced approach in the first place (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1075547012458290">Dunwoody &amp; Peters, 1992</xref>)?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-1075547012458290">
<title>Exploring Effect on Behavioral Intentions</title>
<p>Another area for future research involves linking uncertainty judgments to (a) perceptions of vaccine-related risk, safety, and benefit; (b) attitudes toward vaccination; and (c) intentions to immunize oneself and/or one’s children in the future. Compared to other falsely balanced scientific controversies, such as climate change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1075547012458290">Boykoff &amp; Boykoff, 2004</xref>), falsely balancing the AVC could have a more immediate impact on public health. Public health officials, for instance, have argued that falsely balanced news media coverage of the AVC negatively influenced vaccine uptake, especially in the United Kingdom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1075547012458290">Offit &amp; Coffin, 2003</xref>). For example, in the months and years after the release of the now-discredited <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1075547012458290">Wakefield et al. (1998)</xref> study, which hypothesized an MMR vaccine–autism link, national rates of MMR coverage in the United Kingdom fell from 92% in 1998 to 80% in 2003 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1075547012458290">Gross, 2009</xref>), with some localities reporting a decrease of up to 30% and attaining only 50% coverage of eligible children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1075547012458290">Petts &amp; Niemeyer, 2004</xref>). Measles was declared endemic in England and Wales in 2008 for the first time in 14 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1075547012458290">Godlee, Smith, &amp; Marcovitch, 2011</xref>), and the first measles death in the United Kingdom occurred in more than a decade. In the United States, there was a smaller but detectable decrease in MMR immunization rates, although they rebounded before media coverage of the MMR vaccine–autism connection increased (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1075547012458290">M. J. Smith et al., 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Could uncertainty about an autism-vaccine link directly affect vaccine decision making? Media effects research specifically examining the influence of vaccine critical websites suggests that this connection could be a possibility. Antivaccination websites provide a platform for disseminating their views to individuals, especially parents. They are among the first hits on Internet search engines and include content questioning vaccine efficacy, emphasizing vaccine side effects argued to have been ignored, and stressing the right of an individual to refuse immunization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1075547012458290">Bean, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1075547012458290">Kata, 2010</xref>). Furthermore, research suggests that exposure to the content of these websites can affect individuals’ vaccine behaviors. In a recent study, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1075547012458290">Betsch, Renkewitz, Betsch, and Ulshofer (2010)</xref> found that viewing vaccine-critical websites for 5 to 10 minutes can increase perceived risk associated with vaccination and decrease one’s intention to immunize versus a control website that takes a more neutral stance. For an attentive audience, such as parents with vaccination-aged children, the effect of uncertainty from falsely balanced news coverage might also spur information-seeking behaviors that include the use of not only mediated channels (internet, magazines, etc.) but also interpersonal sources, such as friends, family members, and doctors. Therefore, the effect of false balance on vaccine decision making might be more multifaceted. Further research should investigate this issue.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-1075547012458290">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>Since our participants were undergraduate students aged 18 to 22 years and the majority female, care must be taken when making inferences about the generalizability of our results. We look forward to future research that uses parents who are perhaps more aware of the AVC and pay particularly close attention to news media coverage of vaccine risk and safety in the course of making an immunization decision for their children (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1075547012458290">Pineda &amp; Myers, 2011</xref>). While we asked participants of their intention to have children, it is reasonable to assume that students aged 18 to 22 years generally do not think about starting a family in their immediate future. We also recognize the advantage of using actual as opposed to artificially manipulated articles in terms of being able to comment, based on our results, on the content and implications of actual news media coverage of the AVC. For future work, however, manipulating context in a balanced article, as mentioned earlier, might better identify what key feature of balanced AVC coverage influences uncertainty judgments. Last, the use of multi-item measures instead of single-item measures could potentially improve measurement validity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-1075547012458290" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Despite the limitations and need for further research, this study demonstrates that the ways in which journalists present evidence in support of risk viewpoints can influence peoples’ risk-related certainty. Falsely balancing risk perspectives can be troubling, as it can heighten readers’ uncertainty perceptions around certain science. For health officials, this fact can be another obstacle to effectively communicating health risk to the public for which alternative methods of communication should be considered. For journalists, it might open up important discussions on the balance norm in terms of addressing its advantages and disadvantages in providing the public with health risk information.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors would like to thank Sahara Byrne, Paul Dixon, Julie Carmalt, Avery Holton, Brooke Weberling, and Michael Smith for their helpful feedback and guidance.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1075547012458290">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Please contact the corresponding author for stimulus materials.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Graham N. Dixon</bold> is a PhD student in the Department of Communication at Cornell University, studying news coverage of controversial science and health topics. His academic interests and research collaborations span the fields of communication, risk perception, journalism studies, and psychology.</p>
<p><bold>Christopher E. Clarke</bold> was a PhD student at the time of this research and is now an assistant professor in the Department of Communication at George Mason University. His research interests center on strategic communication of health and environmental risk, especially media portrayal of health risk issues.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Afifi</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Toward a theory of motivated information management</article-title>. <source>Communication Theory</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allum</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>What can we learn from 25 years of PUS survey research? Liberating and expanding the agenda</article-title>. <source>Public Understanding of Science</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bean</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Emerging and continuing trends in vaccine opposition website content</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1874</fpage>-<lpage>1880</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>An introduction to journalism norms and representations of politics</article-title>. <source>Political Communication</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>-<lpage>384</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Betsch</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Renkewitz</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Betsch</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ulshofer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The influence of vaccine-critical websites on perceiving vaccination risks</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Psychology</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>446</fpage>-<lpage>455</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boykoff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>From convergence to contention: United States mass media representations of anthropogenic climate change science</article-title>. <source>Transactions of the Institute for British Geographers</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>477</fpage>-<lpage>489</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boykoff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boykoff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Balance as bias: Global warming and the U.S. prestige press</article-title>. <source>Global Environmental Change</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brashers</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Communication and uncertainty management</article-title>. <source>Journal of Communication</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>477</fpage>-<lpage>497</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brossard</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nisbet</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Deference to scientific authority among low information public: Understanding U.S opinion on agricultural biotechnology</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Public Opinion Research</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>24</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cialdini</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kallgren</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reno</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>A focus theory of normative conduct: A theoretical refinement and reevaluation of the role of norms in human behavior</article-title>. <source>Advances in Experimental Social Psychology</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>201</fpage>-<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A question of balance: The autism-vaccine controversy in the British and American elite press</article-title>. <source>Science Communication</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>107</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A case of conflicting norms? Mobilizing and accountability information in newspaper coverage of the autism-vaccine controversy</article-title>. <source>Public Understanding of Science</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>609</fpage>-<lpage>626</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Corbett</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Durfee</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Testing public (un)certainty of science: Media representations of global warming</article-title>. <source>Science Communication</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>129</fpage>-<lpage>151</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dearing</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Newspaper coverage of maverick science: Creating controversy through balancing</article-title>. <source>Public Understanding of Science</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>341</fpage>-<lpage>361</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dunwoody</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Scientists, journalists, and the meaning of uncertainty</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunwoody</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Communicating uncertainty: Media coverage of new and controversial science</source> (pp. <fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>79</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dunwoody</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>H. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Mass media coverage of technological and environmental risks</article-title>. <source>Public Understanding of Science</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>199</fpage>-<lpage>230</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Durham</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>On the relevance of standpoint epistemology to the practice of journalism: The case for “strong objectivity”</article-title>. <source>Communication Theory</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>117</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Entman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <source>Democracy without citizens: Media and the decay of American politics</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freed</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Butchart</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Sources and perceived credibility of vaccine-safety information for parents</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<supplement>Suppl. 1</supplement>), <fpage>S107</fpage>-<lpage>S112</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frewer</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuznesof</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ness</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ritson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Public preferences for informed choice under conditions of risk uncertainty</article-title>. <source>Public Understanding of Science</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>363</fpage>-<lpage>372</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frewer</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuznesof</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ness</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ritson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The views of scientific experts on how the public conceptualize uncertainty</article-title>. <source>Journal of Risk Research</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>-<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gans</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <source>Deciding what’s news</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pantheon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Offit</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Vaccines and autism: A tale of shifting hypotheses</article-title>. <source>Clinical Infectious Diseases</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>456</fpage>-<lpage>461</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunwoody</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Community structure and science framing of news about environmental risks</article-title>. <source>Science Communication</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>362</fpage>-<lpage>384</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>A broken trust: Lessons from the vaccine-autism wars</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biology</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Godlee</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marcovitch</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Wakefield’s article linking MMR vaccine and autism was fraudulent</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source>, <volume>342</volume>, <fpage>64</fpage>-<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hanitzsch</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hanusch</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mellado</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anikina</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berganza</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cangoz</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Yuen</surname><given-names>E. K. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Mapping journalism cultures across nations: A comparative study of 18 countries</article-title>. <source>Journalism Studies</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>273</fpage>-<lpage>293</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <source>An analytical primer and computational tool for observed variable moderation, mediation, and conditional process modeling</source>. Manuscript submitted for publication</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Institute of Medicine</collab>. (<year>2004</year>). <source>Immunization safety review: Vaccines and autism</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Scientific uncertainty in news coverage of cancer research: Effects of hedging on scientists’ and journalists’ credibility</article-title>. <source>Human Communication Research</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>347</fpage>-<lpage>369</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Conflicting stories about public scientific controversies: Effects of news convergence and divergence on scientist’s credibility</article-title>. <source>Public Understanding of Science</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>689</fpage>-<lpage>704</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moriarty</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stryker</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Making sense of cancer news coverage trends: A comparison of three comprehensive content analyses</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Communication</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>136</fpage>-<lpage>151</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slovic</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Presenting uncertainty in health risk assessment: Initial studies of its effects on risk perception and trust</article-title>. <source>Risk Analysis</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>485</fpage>-<lpage>494</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slovic</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Lay views on uncertainty in environmental health risk assessment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Risk Research</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>261</fpage>-<lpage>279</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kata</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A postmodern Pandora’s box: Anti-vaccination misinformation on the Internet</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1709</fpage>-<lpage>1716</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Speers</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Misleading media reporting? The MMR story</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews: Immunology</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>913</fpage>-<lpage>918</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Merton</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1942</year>). <article-title>The normative structure of science</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Storer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The sociology of science: Theoretical and empirical investigations</source> (pp. <fpage>267</fpage>-<lpage>278</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Myrick</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>, <month>November</month> <day>1</day>). <article-title>The search for objectivity in journalism</article-title>. <source>USA Today</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1272/is_2690_131/ai_94384327">http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1272/is_2690_131/ai_94384327</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Offit</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coffin</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Communicating science to the public: MMR vaccine and autism</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parascandola</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Health in the news: What happens when researchers and journalists collide</article-title>. <source>Research Practitioner</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Petts</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niemeyer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Health risk communication and amplification: Learning from the MMR vaccination controversy</article-title>. <source>Health, Risk &amp; Society</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pineda</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Finding reliable information about vaccines</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>127</volume>(<supplement>Suppl. 1</supplement>), <fpage>S134</fpage>-<lpage>S137</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunwoody</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neuwirth</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Exploring lay uncertainty about an environmental health risk</article-title>. <source>Public Understanding of Science</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>343</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Preacher</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rucker</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Assessing moderated mediation hypotheses: Theory, methods, and prescriptions</article-title>. <source>Multivariate Behavioral Research</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>185</fpage>-<lpage>227</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Prue</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lackey</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swenarski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gannt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Communication monitoring: Shaping CDC’s emergency risk communication efforts</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Communication</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Journalistic ethics, objectivity, existential journalism, standpoint epistemology, and public journalism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Mass Media Ethics</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Siegrist</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cvetkovich</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Perception of hazard: The role of social trust and knowledge</article-title>. <source>Risk Analysis</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>713</fpage>-<lpage>720</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>A question of accuracy: How journalists and scientists report research on hazards</article-title>. <source>Journal of Communication</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>102</fpage>-<lpage>116</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Dangerous news: Media decision making about climate change risk</article-title>. <source>Risk Analysis</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1471</fpage>-<lpage>1482</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ellenberg</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Media coverage of the measles mumps-rubella vaccine and autism controversy and its relationship to MMR immunization rates in the United States</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>121</volume>, <fpage>e836</fpage>-<lpage>e843</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Speers</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Journalists and jabs: Media coverage of the MMR vaccine</article-title>. <source>Communication &amp; Medicine</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>169</fpage>-<lpage>179</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stocking</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>How journalists deal with scientific uncertainty</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunwoody</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Communicating uncertainty: Media coverage of new and controversial science</source> (pp. <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>42</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vasterman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yzermans</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dirkzwager</surname><given-names>A. J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The role of the media and media hypes in the aftermath of disasters</article-title>. <source>Epidemiologic Reviews</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>114</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murch</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Linnell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Casson</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Walker-Smith</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Ilead-lymphoid-nodular hyperplasia, non-specific colitis, and pervasive developmental disorder in children</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>, <volume>351</volume>, <fpage>637</fpage>-<lpage>641</lpage>. (Retracted)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weary</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Causal uncertainty beliefs and diagnostic information seeking</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>839</fpage>-<lpage>848</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1075547012458290">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Drought, debate, and uncertainty: Measuring reporters’ knowledge and ignorance about climate change</article-title>. <source>Public Understanding of Science</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>