<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjci</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Communication Inquiry</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0196-8599</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-4612</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0196859912466411</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0196859912466411</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>David, Goliath, and the Black Panthers</article-title>
<subtitle>The Paradox of the Oppressed Militant in the Rhetoric of Self-Defense</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Gatchet</surname><given-names>Amanda Davis</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0196859912466411">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Cloud</surname><given-names>Dana L.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0196859912466411">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0196859912466411"><label>1</label>Eastern New Mexico University, Portales, NM, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0196859912466411"><label>2</label>University of Texas at Austin, TX, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0196859912466411">Amanda Davis Gatchet, Department of Communication, Eastern New Mexico University, ENMU Station 27, 1500 S Ave. K, Portales, NM 88130, USA. Email: <email>Amanda.Gatchet@enmu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>37</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>5</fpage>
<lpage>25</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Both the Hebrew Bible and the Qur’an tell the story of David and Goliath, in which David, a youth armed only with stones and a sword, challenges and kills the giant Goliath, thus securing the victory of the Israelites over the Philistines. The event was a military victory; it also created and secured the identity of a people with a sense of its own power. Today the phrase “David and Goliath” is used as shorthand to refer to a situation in which a smaller or significantly weaker force defeats a larger and much more powerful one.</p>
<p>In this article, we develop a framework for examining the David and Goliath narrative when it is used as a rhetorical strategy in political and social movement discourse. We argue that the stance of the aggrieved Party (David) is a rhetorical resource that serves two functions for both mainstream political and oppositional social movement actors. First, it potentially legitimizes the use of violence in a social conflict by figuring political collectives as aggrieved victims. Second, it crafts a paradoxical collective persona: that of an oppressed militant (in the case of social movements) or a mighty victim (in the case of hegemonic powers), an agent who is at once both powerful and oppressed. It is beyond the scope of this article to analyze in detail the disparate treatment by the media of oppressed militants (framed negatively) and the hegemonic stance of “righteous victim” used to justify wars against weaker foes (framed positively). However, we make a note of this distinction’s importance toward the conclusion of this article. Elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0196859912466411">Cloud &amp; Gatchet, 2008</xref>), we argue that mainstream mass media and, by extension, the publics they influence, tacitly and problematically regard the violence of established powerful entities as more credible than self-defense among oppressed groups. Here we focus on the first dimension of the David and Goliath narrative by exploring the rhetoric of militancy among the oppressed as developed by members of the Black Panther Party for Self-Defense.</p>
<p>While there is extensive research about rhetorics warranting the violence of nation states, there is less research addressing the questions: How do movements for social change by oppressed groups warrant their turn to violence? What functions does a movement’s claim to the right of self-defense serve in the creation of the identity of its participants? Finally, how do dominant interests and mainstream media take up movement arguments about violence, and with what consequences?</p>
<p>In order to answer these questions, we examine the rhetoric and U.S. news media framing of the Black Panthers during the late 1960s.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0196859912466411">1</xref></sup> Based on this analysis, we argue that members of the Black Panther Party (BPP) rhetorically crafted a David-like persona to warrant the taking up of arms in self-defense. The Panthers utilized the David stance in their rhetoric of self-defense in two distinct ways. First, Panthers advocated armed self-defense as a necessary and righteous move against an invading and exploitative, even monstrous, enemy. Second, and perhaps more importantly, members of the Party recognized their militant stance as one that allowed Black Americans to define themselves as an oppressed but potentially powerful group. This latter strategy is characteristic of the construction of an agentive identity for social movements against oppression. However, mainstream media outlets often framed the BPP as a Goliath-like threat, ignoring or diminishing Panther grievances regarding the systematic oppression faced by members of inner-city Black communities at the hands of state and local police and often describing the BPP movement as equal with these dominant governmental powers in its assumption of the prerogative of violence. We argue that these frames are significant in managing the public meaning of political violence, from social movements and assassination attempts to terrorism and preemptive war.</p>
<p>We proceed as follows: First, we explore how appeals to violence serve as identity-forming moments for social movements in general and the Panthers in particular. Next, we turn our attention to speeches, media coverage, and newspaper editorials by and about the Black Panthers.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0196859912466411">2</xref></sup> Our analysis focuses first on the Panthers’ self-framing and then on the media frames that shaped public perception of their appeals to self-defense. Finally, we reflect on the implications of the David stance for contemporary political discourse.</p>
<sec id="section1-0196859912466411">
<title>Violence, Nonviolence, and Panther Identity Creation Through Self-Defense</title>
<p>Both affirmative and critical studies of rhetorical justifications for wars among nation-states are plentiful (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0196859912466411">Ivie, 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0196859912466411">2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0196859912466411">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0196859912466411">Medhurst &amp; Brands, 2000</xref>). However, little scholarship on the rhetoric of social movements acknowledges the significance of violence on the part of the oppressed. Some such work recognizes the significance of militancy and confrontation (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0196859912466411">Haiman, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0196859912466411">Scott &amp; Smith, 2001</xref>). Notably, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0196859912466411">Simons (2001)</xref> called attention to the establishment bias, which is inherent in privileging symbolic action over more aggressive modes of influence when parties in conflict establish and support the capacity to use coercive (economic or repressive) force to achieve their objectives. However, by the end of the 1980s, the field turned toward social movements in terms of “meaning” and “rhetorical form” (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0196859912466411">Cathcart, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0196859912466411">McGee, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0196859912466411">Sillars, 2001</xref>). With a few exceptions (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0196859912466411">Cloud, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0196859912466411">DeLuca &amp; Peeples, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0196859912466411">Jasinski, 2007</xref>), there is little recent work in the rhetorical study of movements that explores the intersections of movement discourse, media image, and violent confrontation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0196859912466411">Bowers, Ochs, &amp; Jensen, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0196859912466411">Morgan, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0196859912466411">Shaw &amp; Spinney, 1999</xref>). One exception is <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0196859912466411">Strain’s (2005)</xref> work on the Black Power movement, which recognizes the important historical role that armed self-defense played in creating identities of American citizenship and personhood for Black communities during the struggle for civil rights. Another exception is <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0196859912466411">Baldwin’s (2006)</xref> work, which highlights how the historical focus on the Black Panthers’ image ignores the important issues of legal redress behind their claims for the right to self-defense. In this article, we seek to extend this inquiry into the constitutive rhetorical dimensions of a social movement’s willingness to use violence, asking both how rhetorics strategically craft personae with legitimate claim to self-defense and how making such a claim, in turn, generates identities of particular communities. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0196859912466411">Charland (1987)</xref> argues that communication scholars should attend to how “peoples are constituted in discourse,” or, in other words, how collectivizing discourse calls a self-identified, agentive group (in his case, separatist Québecois) into being (p. 136). As he points out, members of these types of groups “become one with a persona . . . entering and embodying it” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0196859912466411">Charland, 1987</xref>, p. 137). The Black Panther Party in the late 1960s was just such a group, and we turn now to an exploration of how the identification and agency of its members worked through the persona of the Biblical David.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0196859912466411">
<title>The Dilemmatic History of the Black Panther Party</title>
<p>To understand how the BPP utilized the David persona in the creation of its militant identity, we must first examine the rhetorical situation in which the group emerged. Consideration of the Party’s dynamic history illustrates the ways in which the threat and use of violence by social movement actors can entail dilemmatic results; violence may contribute to a community’s sense of its own agency, but it also lends itself to unpredictable and potentially damaging media framing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0196859912466411">Rhodes, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>The Panthers emerged as prominent public figures in the late 1960s in response to direct police and military repression of mainstream civil rights movement activities and to the high incidence of systematic police brutality against Black citizens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0196859912466411">Baldwin, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0196859912466411">Carson, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0196859912466411">Morgan, 2006</xref>). As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0196859912466411">Carson (1995)</xref> explains, Panther cofounders, Huey P. Newton and Bobby Seale, were drawn to Malcolm X’s “harsh criticisms of established civil rights leaders who were deemed too cautious, dependent on white support, and unwilling to retaliate against white racist violence” (pp. ix-x). They were also inspired by Stokely Carmichael, his role in the “<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0196859912466411">Black Power turn within SNCC in 1965 and 1966</xref>,” and his establishment of the short-lived 1966 Lowdnes County Black Panther Party in Alabama (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0196859912466411">Self, 2006</xref>, p. 38). Carmichael outlined the political framework for Black Power when he called for Black Americans “to redefine themselves, embrace their history, reject integration and assimilation, and question the basic values and institutions of society” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0196859912466411">Rhodes, 1999</xref>, p. 102).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0196859912466411">3</xref></sup> Members of the BPP, too, could point directly to the shortcomings of nonviolent tactics—such as those employed earlier in the decade by Martin Luther King, Jr., in the American South—in the face of brutal racist reaction to and state violence against members of urban Black communities. And while the BPP eventually distanced itself from Carmichael and other Black Power advocates, the Party similarly enacted the use of militant rhetoric to reconstitute history and create new social and racial identities for oppressed people (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0196859912466411">Singh, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0196859912466411">Worgs, 2006</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0196859912466411">4</xref></sup> For the Panthers, armed self-defense became a means of empowering Black communities by providing physical protection against oppressive White violence. The Panthers also recognized that the organization of Black people around the idea of self-defense, in turn, allowed members of these communities to articulate empowered identities and space within oppressive situations.</p>
<p>Armed with guns and copies of the Bill of Rights, Newton, Seale, and fellow members of the Oakland Branch of the BPP followed police vehicles on patrol, making themselves a physical presence during police arrests of Black citizens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0196859912466411">Baldwin, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0196859912466411">Morgan, 2006</xref>). Although it was not until the Panthers staged an armed protest at the California State Capitol in Sacramento in 1967 that the Party received national media attention, direct confrontation with the police, and a willingness to retaliate against White violence was an early rallying point and recruitment tool for the Oakland Panthers. For example, in the BPP Platform, “What We Want, What We Believe,” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0196859912466411">Newton (1966)</xref> argued:
<disp-quote>
<p>We believe we can end police brutality in our black community by organizing black self-defense groups that are dedicated to defending our black community from racist police oppression and brutality. The Second Amendment of the Constitution of the United States gives a right to bear arms. We therefore believe that all black people should arm themselves for self-defense. (p. 3)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>As this point in the BPP Platform illustrates, one of the Party’s immediate concerns was to act against police brutality. However, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0196859912466411">Morgan (2006)</xref> points out, “By their bravado, their insistence on the right to carry guns and, if necessary, to use them in self-defense, the Panthers hoped to embolden and empower the inner city black population” (p. 329). In this way, the BPP’s insistence on the right to self-defense, particularly armed self-defense, became a central feature of their identity creation.</p>
<p>Critical analysis of Panther rhetoric is challenging in so far as the group’s stance regarding self-defense not only evolved over the course of the movement’s history but also never fully achieved ideological consensus among its membership. We argue, as does <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0196859912466411">Carson (1995)</xref>, that ideological rifts among Panther leaders and the difficulties they experienced during their efforts to build coalitions with other Black militant groups, stem partly from covert yet systematic operations by local police and the FBI to dismantle the Party. These efforts (discussed in more detail below) contributed to the break-up of Party leadership at the height of Panther activities: Huey P. Newton was incarcerated for an altercation with the police in October of 1967; Bobby Hutton, Party Treasurer, was killed by the police in April of 1968; Eldridge Cleaver, who “became one of the Party’s most effective and best-known spokespersons” after Newton’s arrest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0196859912466411">Carson, 1995</xref>, p. xii), ultimately chose to live in political exile rather than return to prison on a parole violation; and Bobby Seale was arrested in 1969 on charges of conspiracy to incite rioting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0196859912466411">Carson, 1995</xref>). Facing a crisis in leadership, members of the BPP attempted to align themselves with other established Black militant groups, most notably with Stokely Carmichael and other radicalized leaders within the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0196859912466411">Carson, 1995</xref>). Carmichael left SNCC over ideological disputes about the inclusion of White activists within the organization and briefly joined the BPP. His ties to the Panthers during the “Free Huey” Rallies in 1968 helped the Party garner national media attention and “establish strong chapters in the eastern United States” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0196859912466411">Carson, 1995</xref>, p. xiii). However, the Panthers later broke with Carmichael because his “advocacy of racial unity rather than interracial coalitions continued to put him at odds with other Panther leaders” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0196859912466411">Carson, 1995</xref>, p. xiii). As Carson points out, Carmichael’s break with the Panthers was only the beginning of “a period of pervasive, vicious infighting within the black militant community” (p. xiv). The BPP also suffered from infighting among its leaders and amidst various regional branches.</p>
<p>Panther leaders within the Oakland Branch disagreed on the use of violence as part of the group’s tactics. After his release from prison in 1970, Newton “sought to revive the Party and to reestablish his control by de-emphasizing police confrontations in favor of survival programs that would meet the everyday needs of black communities while also educating black people” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0196859912466411">Carson, 1995</xref>, p. xv).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0196859912466411">5</xref></sup> Newton’s attempt to shift focus and temper the Party’s negative media image prompted a permanent break with the exiled Eldridge Cleaver who called for violent revolution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0196859912466411">Carson, 1995</xref>).</p>
<p>Despite the Panthers’ complexity, we argue that during the Party’s largest period of growth (1967-1969) its biggest appeal to its base (young African Americans) and its best tactic for garnering national media attention was the willingness of the group’s members to confront the police and educate Black citizens about their rights to stand up to police brutality and oppression.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0196859912466411">6</xref></sup> It is also during this time period (specifically 1968) that the FBI, calling the Black Panthers a threat to national security, began its process of dismantling the group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0196859912466411">Carson, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0196859912466411">Morgan, 2006</xref>). Repression prompted Panther leaders to clarify and define the Party’s motivations and purpose amidst the beginnings of the group’s leadership crisis. In the analysis that follows, we focus on this particular moment in Panther history (1967-1969) and pay special attention to the founding leaders of the Oakland Branch—Newton, Cleaver, Seale, and Hilliard—who were arguably the most vocal about Panther politics and activities and the most successful at garnering national media attention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0196859912466411">Morgan, 2006</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0196859912466411">7</xref></sup> We also rely heavily on BPP rhetoric espoused in the Party’s official newspaper, <italic>The Black Panther</italic>, which served as the “official organ of the Party” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0196859912466411">Foner, 1970</xref>, p. xxviii). The rhetoric of self-defense used by the Panthers in this historical moment was often more a rhetoric of symbolic display and threat than the intent to initiate actual physical violent action, which would have provoked overwhelming backlash from the police. This identity-constituting function of arming oneself against an oppressive foe is our primary focus in this article. As the following analysis will show, by arguing for the right to self-defense, the Panthers rhetorically occupied the place of David as oppressed militant.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0196859912466411">
<title>The Paradox of the Oppressed Militant in the Identity of the Black Panther Party</title>
<p>The Black Panthers utilized the David stance in their rhetoric of self-defense to advocate armed self-defense and to define Black Americans as an oppressed but potentially powerful group. In their advocacy of armed self-defense, Panthers often articulated an argument for self-defense as justified violence. For example, in a statement read by Bobby Seale at the 1967 Panther protest at the California State Capitol, Huey <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0196859912466411">Newton (1967)</xref>, citing a history of Black repression by “the racist power structure of America” argued, “The Black Panther Party for Self-Defense believes that the time has come for Black people to arm themselves against this terror before it is too late” (p. 40). For Newton, the taking up of arms was a necessary instrument of social change for Black people terrorized by White violence. He argued that White violence had forced Black communities to reevaluate their approaches to resistance and emphasized that armed self-defense was the only viable means for change. The Mulford Act of 1967 (which was later signed into law) aimed to repeal a California state law that allowed citizens to carry loaded firearms. Protest against this legislation was of particular importance for the Oakland Panthers because the passing of the Mulford Act would (and eventually did) make their armed patrols and checks against police violence illegal, ultimately denying members of urban Black communities the legal right to armed-self defense. As Newton explained,<disp-quote>
<p>A people who have suffered so much for so long at the hands of racist society, must draw the line somewhere. We believe that Black communities of America must rise up as one man to halt the progression of a trend that leads inevitably to their total destruction. (pp. 40-41)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>For Newton, the right to armed self-defense was a matter of survival for members of urban Black communities who were oppressed and threatened by systematic police violence. Other prominent Panther leaders shared this sense of urgency regarding the need for self-defense and articulated it in their public rhetoric and writings.</p>
<p>In a message from prison, Bobby <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0196859912466411">Seale (1969)</xref> implored Black soldiers fighting in Vietnam to return to the United States and help fight in the armed struggle at home, claiming, “The same thing they’re doing over there to the Vietnamese people, they’re getting ready to . . . do to Black American people” (p. 92). Seale outlined police attacks against the BPP and argued that Black soldiers dreaming of coming home from war would only face the same oppressive violence they had witnessed abroad:
<disp-quote>
<p>They’ve attacked the Party; they’ve attacked our offices. And in some cases we’ve had to defend ourselves with weapons because we vowed that we would stand and defend ourselves, to defend our people and teach our people the correct methods to resist the pig power structure here in America, the fascist ruling class, the exploiters. (pp. 92-93)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Seale’s rhetoric made explicit connections between occupied Vietnam and the Black struggle for freedom. And, in both cases, the threat and use of violence is framed as a last resort for survival prompted by violent attack.</p>
<p>Panther Chief of Staff David Hilliard made similar arguments connecting struggles in urban Black communities to the war in Vietnam. In a speech delivered at the San Francisco Moratorium Demonstration against the Vietnam War, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0196859912466411">Hilliard (1969b)</xref> urged the crowd to recognize the similarities between the occupation of Vietnam by American troops and the occupation of urban Black communities by police. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0196859912466411">Hilliard (1969b)</xref> explained,<disp-quote>
<p>We will not fight and kill other people of color in the world, who like Black people are victims of US imperialism on an international level, and fascism domestically. So recognizing that, recognizing fascism, recognizing the occupation of all the pigs in the Black community, then it becomes evident that there’s a war at home, there’s a war of genocide being waged against Black people right here in America. (p. 128)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>For Hilliard, armed self-defense was a matter of survival for Black Americans being attacked by White police. He also argued that the federal government, led by then-President Richard Nixon, was waging war against the BPP. He claimed that Nixon had “unleashed the counter-insurgent teams upon the BPP” and was “responsible for all the attacks on the Black Panther Party nationally” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0196859912466411">Hilliard, 1969b</xref>, . 130). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0196859912466411">Hilliard (1969b)</xref> ultimately threatened retaliation for these actions, claiming, “We will kill Richard Nixon. We will kill any motherfucker that stands in the way of our freedom” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0196859912466411">Hilliard, 1969b</xref>, p. 130). In this statement (which ultimately led to Hilliard’s incarceration on charges of verbally threatening the president), Hilliard both outlined systematic violent attacks against the Panthers by the Federal Government and emphasized the ways in which these attacks reinforced the Party’s prerogative to take up arms in self-defense.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0196859912466411">8</xref></sup></p>
<p>Appeals to the necessity of self-defense were important and central to Panther rhetoric. The Panthers also used self-defense discourse as a rhetorical tool through which they attempted to define and unify a Black community with a common identity and sense of solidarity. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0196859912466411">Gamson (1992)</xref> explains, the process of identity construction in social movements, while insufficient in itself in achieving systemic social change, is crucially important as “one step in challenging cultural domination” (p. 60; contra <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0196859912466411">Laraña, Johnston, &amp; Gusfield, 1994</xref>). Gamson continues, “The content must necessarily be adversarial in some way to smoke out the invisible and arbitrary elements of the dominant cultural codes” (p. 60). Collective action requires an antagonistic identity frame (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0196859912466411">Gamson, 1992</xref>), and the rhetoric of self-defense was for the BPP a site of clear articulation of antagonism with White authority. The resulting David-like identity was simultaneously the stance of both victim of oppression and agent of change.</p>
<p>In the passages explored above, we can see how Panther discourse features two elements that foster the production of a David stance. First, the BPP argued that it was rising to protect an entire oppressed people, as David did with the Israelites. Second, as the passages below also illustrate, just as David’s battle was to define a people united in struggle, representatives of the BPP called attention to how the rhetoric of self-defense was constitutive of collective identity. Thus, like David, Panther discourse positions the ostensibly weaker force as mighty in its invocation of a righteous collective.</p>
<p>First, in the story of David and Goliath (1 Samuel 17 New English Translation), the Israelites fight a war against the incursion of a foreign power, that of the well-armed, large army of the Philistines, into Israel. David’s fellow Israelites saw the gargantuan Goliath and retreated in fear. However, David stood against the giant, and his victory gave confidence to his people. Analogously, the taking up of arms among the Black Panthers signaled a new agentive consciousness for minorities facing the Goliath of establishment repression. Following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0196859912466411">Fanon (1968)</xref>, many prominent members of the BPP argued that Black communities were colonies within the United States, often equating Black oppression with the oppression of colonized people around the world.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0196859912466411">9</xref></sup> Like David, the Panthers refused standard methods of warfare and stood as champions of the oppressed, armed not only with weapons of their own, but with the commitment to a righteous war for liberation.</p>
<p>Second, David’s actions served to gather the people of Israel together in common cause and to allow a fearless collective persona to emerge against others designated as moral and cultural inferiors. When David volunteered to do battle with Goliath, Saul told him that he was merely a youth, armed only with stones. David replied to Saul:
<disp-quote>
<p>Your servant has been a shepherd for his father’s flock. Whenever a lion or bear would come and carry off a sheep from the flock, I would go out after it, strike it down, and rescue the sheep from its mouth. If it rose up against me, I would grab it by its jaw, strike it, and kill it. Your servant has struck down both the lion and the bear. This uncircumcised Philistine will be just like one of them. (1 Samuel 17: 34-46)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In Christian rhetoric, a “flock” refers not only to sheep but also to a people in need of care and protection. David armed himself to protect the people, boasting that he had done so before. As David formed alliances with leaders across the region, the Israelite community (defined by the leadership of David) found itself on the offensive rather than on the defensive.</p>
<p>For the Panthers, likewise, armed self-defense provided a rallying point that could enable members of Black communities to recognize their shared oppression (both domestically and with oppressed people abroad) and their capacity to take action in their own interests. The BPP’s starkly polarizing “us vs. them” (oppressed vs. oppressor) rhetoric became a site for identification and unification within and across Black communities.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-0196859912466411">10</xref></sup> For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0196859912466411">Hilliard (1969a)</xref>, reporting on Panther demonstrations in Hayward on July 4, explained that members of the Black community had to make distinctions between friends and enemies, arguing, “When you make that basic distinction, you have already transcended a very major step in terms of self-transformation, in terms of reconstructing and getting your own ideas together” (p. 5).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-0196859912466411">11</xref></sup> For <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0196859912466411">Hilliard (1969a)</xref>, the first step to empower oppressed Black communities was to get the members of those communities to band together and distinguish themselves from their oppressors.</p>
<p>Just as David used terms such as “uncircumcised” to distinguish his people from the Philistines, members of the BPP often described enforcers of White oppression in morally inferior or insulting terms such as the term “pig,” which was used in reference to police officers and other members of the ruling class. A short segment (entitled “A Pig”) in a <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0196859912466411">1967</xref> issue of <italic>The Black Panther</italic> described a “pig” as “an ill-natured beast who has no respect for law and order, a foul traducer who’s usually found masquerading as a victim of an unprovoked attack” (p. 14). By using such language, the Panthers divided themselves from enforcers of White, state oppression and used this division as a way to empower oppressed communities.</p>
<p>In another example, Huey Newton explained that carrying guns had both symbolic and instrumental functions: to educate Black people that they possessed power and to convince them that they had the right to defend themselves. In an example of this identity construction, Newton stated, “The Panther program calls for the black community to become independent and self-governing,” as well as willing to “go into the streets in large numbers” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0196859912466411">Stern, 1967</xref>, p. 63). Panther leaders recognized the importance of armed self-defense as a part of identity creation and were very careful about distinguishing their taking up of arms in self-defense from violence for violence’s sake. For example, leaders of the Oakland branch published “Rules of the Black Panther Party,” which specifically addressed acceptable use of weapons by Panther members. These rules, among other things, dictated, “No party member will USE, POINT, or FIRE a weapon of any kind unnecessarily or accidentally at anyone” and, “All Panthers must learn to operate and service weapons correctly” (“Rules,” p. 5, emphasis in original). Similarly, the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0196859912466411">1968</xref> <italic>Black Panther</italic> article “On Violence” distinguished between armed self-defense as a matter of survival, resistance, and empowerment and unjustified violence: “We do not claim the right to indiscriminate violence. . . . We are not out to kill up white people. On the contrary, it is the cops who claim the right to indiscriminate violence and practice it everyday” (p. 19). Significantly, this passage suits the David and Goliath frame by justifying the taking up of arms in self-defense as necessary and collectively empowering, in contradistinction to the oppressive violence of the police. In an editorial appearing in <italic>The Black Panther</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0196859912466411">Crutch (1968)</xref> also defined the BPP’s militant stance and rhetoric in terms of its moral righteousness. Arguing against certain members of the BPP who he labeled as having the mistaken “purely military view,” Crutch claimed:
<disp-quote>
<p>We should not confine ourselves merely to fighting. But we must also shoulder such important tasks as doing propaganda among the people, organizing the people, arming the people, and helping them to establish revolutionary political power for Black people. Without those objectives fighting loses its meaning and the Black Panther Party loses the reason for its existence. (p. 22)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Like Crutch, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0196859912466411">Newton (1968)</xref> outlined the purpose of the BPP in relation to its militant stance by claiming that the function of the BPP was “to awaken the people and to teach them the strategic method of resisting the power structure” (p. 42). For Newton, as with other prominent leaders within the BPP, armed self-defense was a way to create an empowered identity and social change where other methods failed. In sum, the Black Panthers consistently promoted armed self-defense, arguing that self-defense was a necessary and justified type of violence. The Panthers also recognized their militant stance as one that allowed oppressed Black people to define and empower themselves. However, the construction of the David persona calling a militant collective into being had paradoxical consequences, as the public was encouraged by the mass media to regard the BPP as a monstrous threat (i.e., as Goliath) rather than as an organization for justified resistance.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0196859912466411">
<title>The Spectacle of “Negroes With Guns”: Media Framing of Panthers’ Claim to Self-Defense</title>
<p>Although there is extensive scholarly analysis of media framing casting movement actors as both threatening and trivial (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0196859912466411">Morgan, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0196859912466411">Rhodes, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0196859912466411">Staub, 1997</xref>), we believe that examining these frames in the context of the present article offers a new way to understand this process. We observe that while the BPP, during its period of growth stemming from 1967 to 1969, figured itself as David—an identity construct warranting righteous self-defense—the mass media during this same time period figured the Party as a Goliath characterized by an overwhelming focus on the BPP’s potential for violent extremes.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-0196859912466411">12</xref></sup> Some media coverage also represented Panther “violence” as the moral equivalent of establishment violence, as if each force were equally powerful and equally mistaken in engaging in militant struggle. In these ways, the media framing during this time period provided a public rationale for the violence of U.S. agencies in their surveillance and repression of the Panthers, as if the state itself were the vulnerable David facing a foe of insurmountable proportions.</p>
<p>While some scholars (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0196859912466411">Campbell, 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0196859912466411">Haines, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0196859912466411">Jeffries, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0196859912466411">2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0196859912466411">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0196859912466411">Rhodes, 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0196859912466411">2007</xref>) have acknowledged the role of violence and militancy in movements for social change, others recognize that violence often serves to discredit the movements that use it (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0196859912466411">Ackerman &amp; Duvall, 2001</xref>). Arguments against movement violence both inform and depend upon on the mainstream mass media’s ideological role (most often aligned with the state and dominant economic interests) in shaping public perception of the legitimacy or illegitimacy of collective violence. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0196859912466411">Hall (1981)</xref> defines ideology as “those images, concepts and premises which provide the framework through which we represent, interpret, understand and ‘make sense’ of some aspect of social existence” (p. 31). This process, as perpetuated by the commercial mass media, is neither entirely intentional nor univocal, but rather is conditioned by various influences, including sources, advertisers, owners, and editors, external communities, and the presence or absence of social movements. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0196859912466411">Shah and Thorton (2004)</xref> argue, the media generally present ideological views in ways that reinforce prevailing commonsense that is recognizable to consumers and comport with the interests of advertisers. However, the framing process is never completely closed or sutured; movement pressure, for example, can shift ideological balance in the mass media (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0196859912466411">Hoerl, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0196859912466411">Kumar, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0196859912466411">Morgan, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0196859912466411">Triece, 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>While the media framing process is never entirely fixed or stable, journalistic practices have more often than not marginalized militant protest groups and delegitimized their messages. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0196859912466411">Gitlin (2003)</xref> explains, “The processed image then tends to <italic>become</italic> ‘the movement’ for wider publics and institutions who have few alternative sources of information, or none at all, about it” (p. 3). News production is thus a complex hegemonic process that, in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0196859912466411">Gramsci’s (1999)</xref> ironic terms, organizes the “spontaneous” (but manufactured, hence the scare quotation marks) “consent given by the great masses of the population to the general direction imposed on social life by the dominant fundamental group” (p. 12; contra <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0196859912466411">DeLuca &amp; Peeples, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>One of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0196859912466411">Gitlin’s (2003)</xref> key arguments is that movements are often reduced to their actual, threatened, or imagined violence. Likewise, Chan and Lee argue that news coverage of social movements fits a “protest paradigm” in which stories about social movements focus on the appearances of protestors, emphasize violent actions, and make movements seem like attacks against the police. News coverage does not generally air movement arguments or recognize relations of power at play (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0196859912466411">Chan &amp; Lee, 1984</xref>). This focus on violence in the media often discredits movements that threaten or provoke violence, creating what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0196859912466411">Haines (1988)</xref> calls a negative flank effect (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0196859912466411">Morgan, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>The Panthers were well aware of their complicated and problematic relationship with the mainstream media. Protests, public events, and even their outward militant images were often calculated with media attention in mind. The Panthers recognized the symbolic and performative dimensions of their militant personae but faced a dilemma in this regard (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0196859912466411">Rhodes, 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0196859912466411">2007</xref>). Despite their dependence on the media for the perpetuation of their militant image, the Panthers continually expressed frustration with the media’s ability to distort their messages of resistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0196859912466411">Jeffries, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>Indeed, the Panthers’ show of arms was a touchstone in news coverage about them. In his <italic>New York Times</italic> article based on an interview with Huey Newton, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0196859912466411">Turner (1967)</xref> made numerous references to the Panthers’ insistence on bearing arms. Turner’s opening paragraphs described Newton in terms of his weaponry and his entourage:
<disp-quote>
<p>Huey Newton toyed with a foot-long stiletto that he said he had taken from an American Nazi party officer in a scuffle last weekend. Across the room, a bodyguard named Sherwin held a 12-gauge shotgun between his knees. In an easy chair, Warren, another guard, shifted the 45-caliber automatic in its holster. On the sofa, Terry, a karate expert, flexed his muscles. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0196859912466411">Turner, 1967</xref>, paras. 1-2)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In reference to the Party itself, Turner argued, “Organization members carry their guns openly, the side-arms at their hips, and the shotguns or rifles on their shoulders or held with both hands across their chests” (para. 19). In addition to elaborate descriptions of the Panthers’ weapons, Turner framed Newton as a paranoid, childish leader who “toys” with weapons while his three macho bodyguards (who are rendered in terms of their excess—flexed muscles, heavy-duty weaponry) look on. The article manufactures an image, itself a legacy of slavery-era stereotypes, of highly sexualized, dangerous Black men (with the suggestive descriptions of foot-long weapons, guns between the knees, and threatening musculature). This description of the Panthers in terms of their armory and the association of Black masculinity with threat are repeated throughout mainstream media coverage (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0196859912466411">Davies, 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0196859912466411">Lardner, 1969</xref>). For example, in a <italic>New York Times</italic> article describing Panther protests at the California State Capitol, Panthers are described as walking around “with their guns in full display” and as having “bandoliers of shells draped across their shoulders . . . and pistols on their hips” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0196859912466411">“Armed Negroes,” 1967</xref>, para. 4).</p>
<p>Thus, the Panthers understood both that their show of arms would garner press coverage and that the mainstream press would distort their message around the theme of violence. Prominent members of the Party consistently expressed frustration about the mainstream media’s focus on the BPP’s violent image and the media’s tendency to distort the Party’s political messages (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0196859912466411">Hilliard, 1969a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0196859912466411">Seale, 1968</xref>). David Hilliard expressed frustration with the types of mainstream coverage given to the Panthers and argued that the mainstream media’s focus on Panther violence ignored the types of positive social work performed by Panthers in their communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0196859912466411">Hilliard, 1969a</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-0196859912466411">13</xref></sup> Recognizing the framing process that devalued the Panthers as a political entity, Hilliard consistently emphasized the need for Black communities to define themselves for themselves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0196859912466411">Hilliard, 1969a</xref>).</p>
<p>Analysis of mainstream news coverage of Party activity confirms BPP suspicions. In numerous accounts of Panther activity, members of the mainstream press described the Party in terms of arms and simultaneously discredited Panther justifications for violence, ultimately denying the Panthers the David stance of righteous underdog. For example, Panther arrests and encounters with police were consistently described in terms of “Panther threat” to police officers and law-abiding citizens (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0196859912466411">“The Panthers,” 1969</xref>, para. 8). Panthers were often described as being involved in “gunbattle” with police officers (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0196859912466411">“Police Officer,” 1967</xref>, para. 1), as engaging in “urban guerrilla warfare” (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0196859912466411">“The Panthers,” 1969</xref>, para. 1), and waging “war with police” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0196859912466411">Baker, 1969</xref>, para. 1). In 1969, several news articles quoted FBI Director, J. Edgar Hoover, who argued that the BPP had “perpetrated numerous assaults on police officers” across the country and was “without question . . . the greatest threat to the internal security of the country” (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0196859912466411">“Hoover Calls,” 1969</xref>, paras. 1-2). In a description of a police raid that killed two Party members, a 1969 <italic>Washington Post</italic> article asked: “We need to know, for example, whether the police shot first in Chicago to kill two Panther leaders or whether the police were merely responding to a shotgun blast through a door” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0196859912466411">“The Panthers and the Police,” 1969</xref>, para. 3). The article later reported that “Examination of the bullet holes suggest that the first shooting came from the outside [from the police]” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0196859912466411">“The Panthers,” 1969</xref>, para. 3). However, despite recognition that police violence resulted in the deaths of two Panthers and the injury of many more, the article never addressed Panther concerns. Instead, the article focused on the problem of “carnage” in American cities and diminished the credibility of Panther claims as conspiratorial:
<disp-quote>
<p>Does police hostility around the country give substance to the Panther charge that there is a national campaign under way to eradicate them by any means, legal or extra-legal? One is reluctant to accept such a conspiratorial explanation of what is happening, but recent events have given added currency to the Panther charge and it needs to be examined. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0196859912466411">“The Panthers,” 1969</xref>, paras. 4-5)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>On the one hand, the article acknowledged police miscalculation and excessive force and may have prompted scrutiny of urban law enforcement. The author seems reluctantly convinced of Panthers’ critique of the police. On the other hand, the recitation of details about the Panthers’ armory implicitly locates the Party in a frame of moral equivalence, which condemns equally the violence of two sides without regard to actual political grievances and divergent material situations (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0196859912466411">Morgan, 2006</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-0196859912466411">14</xref></sup> In other words, the core dramatic principle of the David and Goliath story is that of inequality: a people united around the idea that the weak can vanquish the mighty. Therefore, media frames rendering the violence of the oppressed as morally equivalent to the violence of the oppressor can undermine the rhetorical work of the self-framing of the movement in terms of agentive oppression.</p>
<p>We see this maneuver at work in another example of the frame of moral equivalence, this one from a 1967 <italic>New York Times</italic> article comparing arguments by Black Panthers with those of White racists in the South. The article concluded that neither side’s violence can be justified, ignoring the asymmetry of power relations and the existence of real grievances on the part of Black communities: “History can explain but not justify the Black Panthers and the ‘black power’ zealots. Whites have neither excuse nor justification” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0196859912466411">“The Spirit,” 1967</xref>, para. 8). Another 1967 article in the <italic>New York Times</italic> describing Panther protest at the California State Capitol quoted then-Governor Ronald Reagan who denied the use of violence as a legitimate means to solving any social problem: “‘This is a ridiculous way to solve problems that have to be solved among people of good will,’ said Mr. Reagan. ‘There’s no reason why a citizen should be carrying loaded weapons on the street today’” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0196859912466411">“Armed Negroes,” 1967</xref>, paras. 8-9). By reducing the Panthers to their display of arms, this article and others like it ignored the violence of the state and diminished the political agency of the Party (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0196859912466411">Jeffries, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0196859912466411">Rhodes, 1999</xref>). As Jeffries argues, “While it is no secret that the Panthers held the police in contempt, the press did little to explore the reasons behind the Panthers indictment of them” (p. 33).</p>
<p>Sometimes the pressure of movements generates more flexible media frames. One example of a progressive shift in frame from the <italic>New York Times Magazine</italic> coverage of the Black Panthers is Sol <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0196859912466411">Stern’s 1967</xref> article “The Call of the Black Panthers.” On the one hand, Stern began his article by acknowledging how out-of-place the Panthers appeared to be: “The voice of the Panthers is a discordant one, full of the rhetoric of revolutionary violence and seemingly out of place in affluent America” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0196859912466411">Stern, 1967</xref>, p. 11). As his use of the word “seemingly” in this introduction suggests, however, Stern went on to portray the Panthers as more appropriate to the American scene—educated, organized, and representative of real collective outrage and desperation—than readers may have thought. Stern concluded the article with an observation that the Panthers’ message took root in urban desperation and the limits of civil rights programs. It is unclear whether Stern offered this analysis as an invitation (the <italic>call</italic> of the Black Panthers) or a warning: “There are a thousand black people in the ghetto thinking privately what any Panther says out loud” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0196859912466411">Stern, 1967</xref>, p. 64). However, the fact that a mainstream news article gave voice to the Panthers in this way is notable, particularly when one recognizes that dominant media frames of Panther coverage during the time period analyzed “was profoundly influenced by [the media industry’s] own fears and repulsion” and “by the conspiratorial rhetoric of political figures like J. Edgar Hoover” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0196859912466411">Rhodes, 1999</xref>, p. 114). Under FBI director J. Edgar Hoover, members of the Party suffered years of government harassment and violence. This violence of the state was rarely questioned (or even reported) in the mainstream news (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0196859912466411">Jeffries, 2002</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-0196859912466411">15</xref></sup> At the height of BPP recruitment and activity, Black Panthers were continually demonized as violent threats to national security in the mainstream media and assaulted with state-sanctioned uses of violence by the police and the FBI, which leads us to conclude that argumentative justifications for armed self-defense espoused by Panther leaders reached mostly deaf ears in regard to mainstream media outlets and the general public.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0196859912466411">
<title>Conclusion and Implications for Contemporary Politics</title>
<p>In contrast to rhetorics justifying hegemonic violence (e.g., in the War on Terror), social movement actors lay claim to the identity of the oppressed in terms of their particular counterhegemonic position in a socioeconomic order: that of the oppressed militant. The rhetoric of the U.S. War on Terror, on the other hand, framed the George W. Bush administration’s violence in terms of the <italic>mighty victim</italic>, despite the marked asymmetry of power relations between the United States and its targets. This difference may explain why (in an ideological not intentional sense) mass media and politicians more often than not framed the Panthers in discrediting ways. Explanations of sociopolitical phenomena in terms of system and structure are not commonsense or natural frames within which to interpret violence in liberal capitalist society, but critics should recognize their reasonable-ness (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0196859912466411">Hoerl, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0196859912466411">Hoerl, Jarvis, &amp; Cloud, 2009</xref>). Only the actors already in power maintain the prerogative of system blindness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0196859912466411">Hartsock, 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0196859912466411">1999</xref>).</p>
<p>In this article, we have demonstrated how the rhetoric of the BPP positions Black militants as David to the White establishment’s Goliath by arguing that, like David, the Party rose to protect an entire oppressed people. In defining a people united in struggle, the rhetoric of self-defense positions the ostensibly weaker force as mighty in its invocation of a righteous collective. We also noted, however, that the mainstream mass media generally reversed the frame (rendering the Black Panthers as Goliath) or denied it in a way that undermined the claim to self-defense and perhaps warranted state surveillance and repression.</p>
<p>Future research could discover whether this pattern—the establishment denial of the David stance to oppressed groups as if the most powerful forces in the world were the most aggrieved—pertains to the dynamics of agitation and control in other social movements. Our hope is that our analysis of Black Panther rhetoric alongside its public media framing might challenge commonplace assumptions about the violence of the oppressed in general. The question becomes, then, whose claims to self-defense are more <italic>empirically</italic> (as opposed to politically) legitimate? Whose call to arms is credited as righteous, and who is (as in the BPP’s definition of a “pig”) “masquerading as a victim”? The process of legitimizing one group’s violence while vilifying another’s is part and parcel of the struggle for economic, political, and state hegemony in a society starkly divided by race, class, nationality, gender, and access to resources. Calling only one side’s violence “terrorism” turns nongovernmental actors into monstrous Goliaths and enables the powerful to discredit resistance to established power as illegitimate, irrational, and ineffective.</p>
<p>By asking these questions equally of all rhetorics of self-defense, our framework enables us to recognize, contrary to prevailing commonsense, the prerogative of self-defense on the part of the oppressed and the unacceptable uses of self-defense rhetoric in justifications for wars undertaken, not in the interests of ordinary people, but to further the economic and political aims of elites. Otherwise, we risk literally and figuratively “disarming” victims of systematic violence while consenting again and again to a vicious cycle of provocation, blowback, and redoubled repression. The trap, if we accept these terms, is that only the already mighty can legitimately wage a righteous war.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-0196859912466411">
<title>Appendix</title>
<p>A search of online archives for news coverage containing the search term “Black Panther Party” in the <italic>New York Times</italic> and the <italic>Washington Post</italic> between the years 1967 and 1970 yielded 1,153 documents (with 791 appearing in the <italic>New York Times</italic> and 362 appearing in the <italic>Washington Post</italic>). When the terms “self-defense” and “self defense” were added to the original searches, documents appearing in the <italic>New York Times</italic> were limited to 37 and documents in the <italic>Washington Post</italic> were limited to 4. We examined 15 of these mainstream news articles and editorials concerning Party activity, selected from the total number of 41, for the ways in which they represent broader patterns in the coverage common to representation of the Panthers in the commercial mass media. The documents discussed in this article are emblematic examples of the examined articles. Because Panther rhetoric is limited in commercial news coverage, we have also included analysis of editorial essays written by Party members for the Party’s own newspaper the <italic>Black Panther</italic> and for autobiographic works published by prominent Party members.</p>
</app>
</app-group>
<ack>
<p>The authors would like to thank Joshua Gunn, James Jasinski, and Roger Davis Gatchet for their thorough and insightful comments on earlier versions of this article.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at">
<label>Authors’ Note</label>
<p>A version of this article was presented at the 2008 convention of the National Communication Association in San Diego, CA.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0196859912466411">
<label>1.</label>
<p>The <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-0196859912466411">Appendix</xref> summarizes texts selected for analysis.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0196859912466411">
<label>2.</label>
<p>While media frame analysis is generally applied to hard news content, it also is appropriate for the study of editorials. Newspaper editors select very few opinion essays to publish; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0196859912466411">Gitlin (2003)</xref> defines frames as principles of selection and omission, and these principles are at work in editorial pages as well as news. Although the process of opinion formation and reciprocal influence of news media, policy makers, and public opinion is complex, the editorial sections of the <italic>New York Times</italic> and the <italic>Washington Post</italic> operate as opinion leaders for large parts of the reading public (for similar argument see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0196859912466411">Christie, 2006</xref>).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0196859912466411">
<label>3.</label>
<p>We recognize that Stokely Carmichael might be considered a controversial figure in regard to his relationship with the Panthers, as he eventually broke with the Party over the inclusion of White activists in the movement. However, we mention Carmichael’s connection to the Panthers here because, during the time period analyzed, Carmichael was at the forefront in garnering press coverage for Panther activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0196859912466411">Stewart, 2001</xref>). In addition, Carmichael had been a well-known voice in the call for Black Power, which inspired the Panthers even before his brief membership in the group.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0196859912466411">
<label>4.</label>
<p>We recognize the complicated relationship between prominent members of the BPP and other Black Power groups of the era. However, the constitutive rhetoric used by the Panthers at this time often resembles arguments made by Black Power groups. This connection, we believe, is an important element of the Party’s historical context.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0196859912466411">
<label>5.</label>
<p>Newton was released on bail after his conviction of manslaughter was reversed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0196859912466411">Carson, 1995</xref>).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0196859912466411">
<label>6.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0196859912466411">Carson (1995)</xref> argues that the largest period of growth for the Panthers was 1967-1968. We also include rhetoric from 1969 because actions by the police and FBI in 1968 prompted prominent Panther leaders to continually define the Party’s motivations and mission.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0196859912466411">
<label>7.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0196859912466411">Morgan (2006)</xref> points out that mainstream national media “focused disproportionate attention on at least one of three Panther celebrities: Newton, Seale, or Cleaver” (p. 331). Although the precise circumstances and timing of Cleaver’s recruitment can be disputed, we include him in the Oakland Branch because of his ties with that branch’s leaders and mission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0196859912466411">Foner, 1970</xref>). We have also added Hilliard to our focus because of his involvement with and contributions to <italic>The Black Panther</italic>.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0196859912466411">
<label>8.</label>
<p>In a later interview with CBS news, Hilliard argued that his words in this speech were taken out of context. When questioned about whether or not he or any other member of the BPP meant to assassinate President Nixon, Hilliard reiterated Party sentiments regarding self-defense against state and police violence claiming, “We do not advocate violence . . . but we do understand that in order to get rid of the gun it will be necessary to take up the gun” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0196859912466411">Hilliard, 1969c</xref>, p. 134).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0196859912466411">
<label>9.</label>
<p>As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0196859912466411">Self (2006)</xref> points out, “Much of the immediate inspiration for and discourse of the early Panthers came from Frantz Fanon’s <italic>Wretched of the Earth</italic>” (p. 40); however, they were also heavily influenced by Mao, Malcolm X, and the work of Robert F. Williams (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0196859912466411">Williams, 1998</xref>).</p></fn> <fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-0196859912466411">
<label>10.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0196859912466411">Bowers, Ochs, and Jensen (1993)</xref> observe that polarization is the moment in social movements in which member identification with the cause is most intense. See also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0196859912466411">Burke (1969)</xref>, who observed that every act of identification is of a dual character: “Implied in it at every turn, its ironic counterpart: division” (p. 23).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-0196859912466411">
<label>11.</label>
<p>It is important to note that arguments like this became point of contention between Panther leaders and Stokely Carmichael, who later broke from the group due to differing opinions regarding a willingness to build coalitions with White supporters.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-0196859912466411">
<label>12.</label>
<p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0196859912466411">Staub (1997)</xref> for an examination of later (1970s) media coverage of Panther activities, which often served to belittle and delegitimize the movement.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-0196859912466411">
<label>13.</label>
<p>Along with many other community-based programs, Panthers provided free breakfasts and lunches for impoverished children in Black communities, bus services to area prisons for families of prison inmates, and free testing for sickle cell anemia.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-0196859912466411">
<label>14.</label>
<p>While the Panthers did not face the same kind of violence faced by victims of lynch mobs earlier in the 20th century, they did call attention to a very real (and ongoing) pattern of police violence against Black citizens. Additionally, Black people then and now are subject to the systematic violence endemic to a society divided by race, class, and gender. Thus, their stance and position regarding violent self-defense has a material basis <italic>and</italic> performative/symbolic dimensions. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0196859912466411">Trotsky (1973)</xref> distinguishes between the aggressive violence of the powerful and the resistant violence of the oppressed, arguing for the greater legitimacy of the latter.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-0196859912466411">
<label>15.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0196859912466411">Jeffries’ (2002)</xref> work focuses primarily on East Coast branches of the BPP. However, his claims hold true for members of the Oakland branch as well.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Amanda Davis Gatchet</bold> (PhD, University of Texas, Austin, 2008) is an assistant professor of communication at Eastern New Mexico University. Her teaching and research interests include political communication, rhetorical studies, feminist theory, social movements, and critical media studies.</p>
<p><bold>Dana L. Cloud</bold> (PhD, University of Iowa, 1992) is an associate professor of communication studies at the University of Texas, Austin. Her teaching and research interests are in the areas of rhetorical studies, Marxist theory, feminist theory, public sphere theory, cultural studies (race and gender in media), and social movements.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ackerman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duvall</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>A force more powerful: A century of nonviolent conflict</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave MacMillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal"><collab>Armed Negroes protest gun bill: 30 Black Panthers invade Sacramento legislature</collab>. (<year>1967</year>, <month>May</month> <day>3</day>). <source>The New York Times</source>, p. <fpage>23</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969</year>, <month>March</month> <day>2</day>). <article-title>A new breed of Panther</article-title>. <source>The Washington Post</source>, p. <fpage>37</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>In the shadow of the gun: The Black Panther Party, the Ninth Amendment, and discourse of self-defense</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lazerow</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>In search of the Black Panther Party: New perspectives on a revolutionary movement</source> (pp. <fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ochs</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Rescue in the heartland</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ochs</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The rhetoric of agitation and control</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>, pp. <fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Long Grove, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Waveland Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969</year>). <source>A grammar of motives</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1971</year>). <article-title>The rhetoric of radical black nationalism: A case study in self-conscious criticism</article-title>. <source>The Central States Speech Journal</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>160</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Forward</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The Black Panthers speak</source> (pp. <fpage>ix</fpage>-<lpage>xviii</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Da Capo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cathcart</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Movements: Confrontation as rhetorical form</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Readings in the rhetoric of social protest</source> (pp. <fpage>102</fpage>-<lpage>111</lpage>). <publisher-loc>State College, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Strata</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>The journalistic paradigm on civil protests</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Arno</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dissanayake</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The news media in national and international conflict</source> (pp. <fpage>183</fpage>-<lpage>202</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Boulder, CO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Westview</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Charland</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Constitutive rhetoric: The case of the</article-title> <source>Peuple Québecois. Quarterly Journal of Speech</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>133</fpage>-<lpage>150</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Framing rationale for the Iraq War</article-title>. <source>International Communication Gazette</source>, <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>519</fpage>-<lpage>532</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cloud</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The null persona: Race and the rhetoric of silence in the uprising of ‘34</article-title>. <source>Rhetoric and Public Affairs</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>177</fpage>-<lpage>209</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cloud</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gatchet</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Goliath in David’s clothing: Manufacturing consent to war out of the paradox of invincible weakness</source>. Unpublished manuscript.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crutch</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1968</year>, <month>October</month> <day>26</day>). <article-title>Correcting mistakes. <italic>The Black Panther</italic></article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The Black Panthers speak</source> (pp. <fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Da Capo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1968</year>, <month>April</month> <day>13</day>). <article-title>Black Panthers denounce policemen</article-title>. <source>The New York Times</source>, p. <fpage>12</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DeLuca</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peeples</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>From public sphere to public screen: Democracy, activism, and the “violence” of Seattle</article-title>. <source>Critical Studies in Media Communication</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>-<lpage>151</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fanon</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1968</year>). <source>The wretched of the earth</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Grove Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>). <article-title>Introduction</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The Black Panthers speak</source> (pp. <fpage>xx</fpage>-<lpage>xxxix</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Da Capo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gamson</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>The social psychology of collective action</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Frontiers in social movement theory</source> (pp. 53-76). <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gitlin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>The whole world is watching: Mass media in the making and unmaking of the New Left</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gramsci</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Selections from the prison notebooks</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>, <person-group person-group-type="translator">
<name><surname>Hoare</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, Trans.). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haiman</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The rhetoric of the streets: Some legal and ethical considerations</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Readings in the rhetoric of social protest</source> (pp. <fpage>10</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>). <publisher-loc>State College, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Strata</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haines</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>Black radicals and the civil rights mainstream, 1954-1970</source>. <publisher-loc>Knoxville</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Tennessee Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>The whites of their eyes: Racist ideologies and the media</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bridges</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brunt</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Silver linings</source> (pp. 28-52). <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence and Wishart</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hartsock</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <source>Money, sex, and power</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Longman</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hartsock</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>The feminist standpoint revisited</source>. <publisher-loc>Boulder, CO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Westview</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hilliard</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969a</year>, <month>July</month> <day>19</day>). <article-title>At Hayward July 4th</article-title>. <source>The Black Panther</source>, p. <fpage>5</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hilliard</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969b</year>, <month>November</month> <day>19</day>). <article-title>If you want peace you got to fight for it. <italic>The Black Panther</italic></article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The Black Panthers speak</source> (pp. <fpage>128</fpage>-<lpage>130</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Da Capo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hilliard</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969c</year>, <month>December</month> <day>28</day>). <article-title>Interview with CBS news. <italic>The Black Panther</italic></article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The Black Panthers speak</source> (pp. <fpage>130</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Da Capo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoerl</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Monstrous youth in suburbia: Disruption and recovery of the American dream</article-title>. <source>Southern Communication Journal</source>, <volume>67</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>-<lpage>276</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoerl</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cloud</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Deranged loners and demented outsiders? Therapeutic news frames of Presidential assassination attempts, 1973-2001</article-title>. <source>Communication, Culture, and Critique</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>83</fpage>-<lpage>109</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal"><collab>Hoover calls Panthers top threat to security</collab>. (<year>1969</year>, <month>July</month> <day>16</day>). <source>The Washington Post</source>, p. <fpage>A3</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ivie</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Images of savagery in American justifications for war</article-title>. <source>Communication Monographs</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>294</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ivie</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The rhetoric of Bush’s “war” on evil</article-title>. <source>KB Journal</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://kbjournal.org/node/53">http://kbjournal.org/node/53</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ivie</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Democracy and America’s War on Terror</source>. <publisher-loc>Tuscaloosa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Alabama Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jasinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). “<article-title>Acting as freemen”: Resistance, violence, and masculinity in Henry Highland Garnet’s 1843 “Address to the slaves</article-title>.” <source>Quarterly Journal of Speech</source>, <volume>93</volume>, <fpage>58</fpage>-<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jeffries</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Black radicalism and political repression in Baltimore: The case of the Black Panther Party</article-title>. <source>Ethnic and Racial Studies</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>64</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jeffries</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Local news coverage of the Black Panther Party: An analysis of the Baltimore, Cleveland, and New Orleans press</article-title>. <source>Journal of African American Studies</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jeffries</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.). (<year>2007</year>). <source>Comrades: A local history of the Black Panther Party</source>. <publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>On the picket line</source>. <publisher-loc>Urbana-Champaign</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Illinois</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Laraña</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gusfield</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.) (<year>1994</year>). <source>New social movements: From ideology to identity</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lardner</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group>(<year>1969</year>, <month>June</month> <day>19</day>). <article-title>Panthers: A recital of fear and crime</article-title>. <source>The Washington Post</source>, p. <fpage>1</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Social “movement”: Phenomenon or meaning</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Readings in the rhetoric of social protest</source> (pp. <fpage>125</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>). <publisher-loc>State College, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Strata</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Medhurst</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brands</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>2000</year>). <source>Critical reflections on the Cold War: Linking rhetoric and history</source>. <publisher-loc>College Station</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Texas A&amp;M University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Media culture and the public memory of the Black Panther Party</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lazerow</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>In search of the Black Panther Party: New perspectives on a revolutionary movement</source> (pp. <fpage>324</fpage>-<lpage>373</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>H. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1966</year>). <article-title>What we want, what we believe</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The Black Panthers speak</source> (pp. <fpage>2</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Da Capo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>H. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>, <month>June</month> <day>2</day>). <article-title>In defense of self-defense: Executive mandate number one</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The Black Panthers speak</source> (pp. <fpage>40</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Da Capo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>H. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1968</year>, <month>May</month> <day>18</day>). <article-title>The correct handling of a revolution</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The Black Panthers speak</source> (pp. <fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Da Capo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>On violence</collab>. (<year>1968</year>, <month>March</month> <day>23</day>). <article-title>The Black Panther</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The Black Panthers speak</source> (p. <fpage>19</fpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Da Capo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal"><collab>The Panthers and the police</collab>. (<year>1969</year>, <month>December</month> <day>17</day>). <source>The Washington Post</source>, p. <fpage>A24</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>A pig</collab>. (<year>1967</year>, <month>May</month>). <article-title>The Black Panther</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The Black Panthers speak</source> (p. <fpage>14</fpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Da Capo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal"><collab>Police officer killed in Black Panther row</collab>. (<year>1967</year>, <month>October</month> <day>29</day>). <source>The Washington Post</source>, p. <fpage>A3</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Fanning the flames of racial discord: The national press and the Black Panther Party</article-title>. <source>The Harvard International Journal of Press Politics</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>118</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Framing the Black Panthers: The spectacular rise of a Black Power icon</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The New Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>Rules of the Black Panther Party</collab> (<year>1966</year>). In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The Black Panthers speak</source> (pp. <fpage>4</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Da Capo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The rhetoric of confrontation</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Readings in the rhetoric of social protest</source> (pp. <fpage>26</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>). <publisher-loc>State College, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Strata</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seale</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1968</year>). <source>Seize the time: The story of the Black Panther Party and Huey P. Newton</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Random House</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seale</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969</year>, <month>September</month> <day>20</day>). <article-title>Black soldiers as revolutionaries to overthrow the ruling class</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Foner</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>The Black Panthers speak</source> (pp. <fpage>88</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Da Capo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Self</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The Black Panther Party and the long civil rights era</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lazerow</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>In search of the Black Panther Party: New perspectives on a revolutionary movement</source> (pp. <fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>55</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thorton</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Newspaper coverage of interethnic conflict: Competing visions of America</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spinney</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Rhetoric, repetition, and violence: A case study of clinic conflict in Milwaukee</article-title>. <source>College Literature</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>170</fpage>-<lpage>192</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sillars</surname><given-names>M. O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Defining movements rhetorically</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Readings in the rhetoric of social protest</source> (pp. <fpage>115</fpage>-<lpage>125</lpage>). <publisher-loc>State College, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Strata</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Requirements, problems, and strategies: A theory of persuasion for social movements</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Readings in the rhetoric of social protest</source> (pp. <fpage>34</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>). <publisher-loc>State College, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Strata</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Resistance, essentialism, and empowerment in Black Nationalist discourse in the African diaspora: A comparison of the Back to Africa, Black Power, and Rastafari movements</article-title>. <source>Journal of African American Studies</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal"><collab>The spirit of lawlessness</collab>. (<year>1967</year>, <month>May</month> <day>7</day>). <source>The New York Times</source>, p. <fpage>228</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Staub</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Black Panthers, new journalism, and the rewriting of the sixties</article-title>. <source>Representations</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>52</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>, <month>August</month> <day>6</day>). <article-title>The call of the Black Panthers</article-title>. <source>New York Times Magazine</source>, pp. <fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>, <fpage>62</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The evolution of a revolution: Stokley Carmichael and the rhetoric of Black Power</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Readings in the rhetoric of social protest</source> (pp. <fpage>428</fpage>-<lpage>446</lpage>). <publisher-loc>State College, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Strata</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Pure fire: Self-defense as activism in the Civil Rights Era</source>. <publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Georgia Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Triece</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Protest and popular culture</source>. <publisher-loc>Boulder, CO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Westview</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trotsky</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <source>Their morals and ours</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pathfinder</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>, <month>May</month> <day>21</day>). <article-title>A gun is power, Black Panther says</article-title>. <source>The New York Times</source>, p. <fpage>66</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Negroes with guns</source>. <publisher-loc>Detroit, MI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wayne State University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-0196859912466411">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Worgs</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>“Beware of the frustrated . . .”: The fantasy and the reality of African American violent revolt</article-title>. <source>Journal of Black Studies</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>