<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PSP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppsp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pers Soc Psychol Bull</journal-id>
<journal-title>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0146-1672</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7433</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0146167211422449</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0146167211422449</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Social Exclusion and Pain Sensitivity</article-title>
<subtitle>Why Exclusion Sometimes Hurts and Sometimes Numbs</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0146167211422449">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Claypool</surname><given-names>Heather M.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0146167211422449">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0146167211422449"><label>1</label>Penn State Abington, Abington, PA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0146167211422449"><label>2</label>Miami University, Oxford, OH, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0146167211422449">Michael J. Bernstein, Penn State Abington, Woodland Building, Abington, PA 19020 Email: <email>mjb70@psu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>38</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>185</fpage>
<lpage>196</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>23</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>28</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 Society for Personality and Social Psychology, Inc.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Society for Personality and Social Psychology, Inc.</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Some research indicates that social exclusion leads to increased emotional- and physical-pain sensitivity, whereas other work indicates that exclusion causes emotional- and physical-pain numbing. This research sought to examine what causes these opposing outcomes. In Study 1, the paradigm used to instantiate social exclusion was found to moderate the social exclusion-physical pain relation: Future-life exclusion led to a numbing of physical pain whereas Cyberball exclusion led to hypersensitivity. Study 2 examined the underlying mechanism, which was hypothesized to be the severity of the “social injury.” Participants were subjected to either the standard future-life exclusion manipulation (purported to be a highly severe social injury) or a newly created, less-severe version. Supporting our hypothesis, the standard (highly severe) future-life exclusion led to physical-pain numbing, whereas the less-severe future-life exclusion resulted in hypersensitivity. Implications of these results for understanding the exclusion–pain relation and other exclusion effects are discussed.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>ostracism</kwd>
<kwd>exclusion</kwd>
<kwd>social rejection</kwd>
<kwd>pain sensitivity</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Pain can be alleviated by morphine but the pain of social ostracism cannot be taken away.</p>
<attrib>—Derek Jarman</attrib>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Among the many experiences and motivations critical to human existence, the innate drive to affiliate with others is one of the most fundamental (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0146167211422449">Baumeister &amp; Leary, 1995</xref>). Many characteristics of humans, such as extended development, relative physical weakness, and comparatively high biparental investment in offspring, are indications that the survival of the human organism requires a stable social infrastructure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0146167211422449">Brewer, 2004</xref>). This line of thought is congenial with evolutionary perspectives, which argue that group living is a selected characteristic of human behavior because it has acted as a solution to a variety of adaptive problems throughout our history. Specifically, the ability to establish and maintain social connections has numerous survival and reproductive benefits: Groups provide social support, access to survival-relevant resources, and protection from environmental dangers, as well as access to potential mating partners (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0146167211422449">Brewer, 2004</xref>). It should come as no surprise, then, that belonging to social groups is often as motivationally relevant as obtaining food and water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0146167211422449">Baumeister &amp; Leary, 1995</xref>).</p>
<p>Beyond facilitating basic survival and reproduction, humans derive more proximal benefits from maintaining stable social connections. Those with social relationships tend to experience greater overall well-being (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0146167211422449">Baumeister, 1991</xref>), show better ability to cope with stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0146167211422449">Cohen, Sherrod, &amp; Clark, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0146167211422449">Cohen &amp; Wills, 1985</xref>), and engage in less antisocial and criminal behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0146167211422449">Sampson &amp; Laub, 1993</xref>). Social exclusion and isolation, however, are associated with a host of negative consequences, including increased anxiety (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0146167211422449">Baumeister &amp; Tice, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0146167211422449">Mathes, Adams, &amp; Davies, 1985</xref>), lower self-esteem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0146167211422449">Leary, Tambor, Terdal, &amp; Downs, 1995</xref>), decrements in immune functioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0146167211422449">Kiecolt-Glaser et al., 1984</xref>), and elevated violence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0146167211422449">Leary, Kowalski, Smith, &amp; Phillips, 2003</xref>). Thus, social exclusion poses numerous immediate threats to physical and mental health and threats to more long-term, inclusive fitness considerations. Therefore, it seems essential to human survival that individuals are able to adapt their cognitive and behavioral repertoires to detect and avoid threats of social exclusion and find ways of adapting and reaffiliating postexclusion.</p>
<p>Given the negative consequences that often ensue following exclusion from groups, it may come as no surprise that both scientists and laypeople have suggested that social exclusion may be experienced negatively, both psychologically and <italic>physically</italic>. The quote at the start of this article, suggesting that social exclusion causes a pain that cannot be eliminated, is one of a litany of similar quotations, poems, novels, musical compositions, and various other artistic endeavors focusing on the pain experienced with social exclusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0146167211422449">MacDonald &amp; Leary, 2005</xref>). From these anecdotal observations, it seems clear that pain and social exclusion are inherently intertwined in humans’ phenomenological experiences. Supportive of these assertions, there is some scientific evidence that social exclusion may trigger physical pain (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211422449">Eisenberger, Lieberman, &amp; Williams, 2003</xref>). Yet a closer examination of the literature suggests that the relation between social exclusion and physical pain may be complex, as some work suggests that exclusion triggers not pain, but numbing (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall &amp; Baumeister, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>The aim of this research is to focus on the circumstances under which pain is heightened or numbed following the experience of social exclusion. To preview our hypothesis, we believe that both outcomes are possible and depend on the severity of the social-exclusionary experience—with a “severe” social injury triggering numbing to pain and a “minor” social injury triggering hypersensitivity to pain. Below, we detail the existent research on the exclusion–pain relation and explain the rationale of our hypothesis.</p>
<sec id="section1-0146167211422449">
<title>Social Exclusion: Its Parallel Impacts on Social and Physical Pain</title>
<p>In the social-exclusion literature, two types of painful responses have received empirical and theoretical attention. The first is social pain, which has been defined as “the distressing experience arising from actual or potential psychological distance from close others or from a social group” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0146167211422449">Eisenberger &amp; Lieberman, 2005</xref>, p. 112), and the second is physical pain, or the “unpleasant sensory and emotional experience associated with actual or potential tissue damage” (International Association for the Study of Pain, 1979, as cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0146167211422449">Eisenberger &amp; Lieberman, 2005</xref>, p. 112). Multiple researchers have postulated a link between these pain types. Namely, both <italic>pain overlap theory</italic> (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0146167211422449">Eisenberger &amp; Lieberman, 2005</xref>) and <italic>social pain theory</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0146167211422449">MacDonald, Kingsbury, &amp; Shaw, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0146167211422449">MacDonald &amp; Leary, 2005</xref>) suggest that a system capable of detecting and responding to social pain “piggybacked” onto the preexisting physical-pain system during evolution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0146167211422449">Nelson &amp; Panksepp, 1998</xref>). Because both distance from others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0146167211422449">Baumeister &amp; Leary, 1995</xref>) and tissue damage pose threats to humans’ well-being and survival, a system of registering and responding to these threats is essential. A system for processing physical damage (and its associated pain) is believed to have developed early in the evolution of the human brain. As human civilization advanced and social/group living became more and more crucial for survival, a parallel system for detecting social threats (and its associated pain) became necessary, and rather than developing a separate system, it co-opted the one already in place for responding to tissue damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0146167211422449">MacDonald &amp; Leary, 2005</xref>). Because of this, pain overlap and social pain theories propose that both types of pain are processed with the same neurological hardware (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0146167211422449">Eisenberger &amp; Lieberman, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0146167211422449">MacDonald et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>One implication of both these perspectives, therefore, is that one’s emotional and physical reactions will coincide. An experience that triggers physical pain should be accompanied by an emotionally painful reaction, whereas physically numbing experiences should co-occur with emotional numbness. Therefore, if social exclusion affects one type of pain, it should trigger a concomitant reaction on the other type as well.</p>
<p>By definition, experiences of social exclusion, rejection, and ostracism create real or imagined distance between individuals. These are the very situations thought to trigger social pain. And, indeed, individuals report various types of emotional distress following social exclusion, including reduced mood (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0146167211422449">Williams et al., 2002</xref>), a reduced sense of meaningfulness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0146167211422449">Stillman et al., 2009</xref>), lowered self-esteem (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0146167211422449">Bernstein, Sacco, Brown, Young, &amp; Claypool, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0146167211422449">Leary et al., 1995</xref>), and so forth (for a meta-analytic review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0146167211422449">Gerber &amp; Wheeler, 2009</xref>; but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0146167211422449">Baumeister, DeWall, &amp; Vohs, 2009</xref>, for a rejoinder). If the social- and physical-pain systems are linked and social exclusion causes emotional pain, it too should trigger physical pain.</p>
<p>Supportive of this assertion, recent neuro-imaging studies show the dorsal anterior cingulate cortex (dACC), a structure known to activate during the experience of physical pain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0146167211422449">Price, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0146167211422449">Rainville, Duncan, Price, Carrier, &amp; Bushnell, 1997</xref>), also activates during an experience of social exclusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211422449">Eisenberger et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0146167211422449">Lieberman &amp; Eisenberger, 2005</xref>). For example, in Eisenberger and colleagues’ work, exclusion was manipulated using Cyberball, an online ball-tossing game reliably shown to successfully manipulate feelings of inclusion and exclusion (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0146167211422449">Williams et al., 2002</xref>). Participants were placed in an fMRI and led to believe they would be engaging in a game with two other participants, also in fMRIs. In reality, no other players were present, and the game unfolded via preprogrammed responses. During the course of the game, participants were included, were told they were unable to receive the ball (implicit exclusion), or received the ball at the start of the game and were then ostracized for the remainder of the experience (explicit exclusion). Regardless of exclusion type, dACC activation was heightened as compared to the inclusion condition. Moreover, within the explicit exclusion condition, results indicated that individuals’ experienced self-reported distress was positively correlated with dACC activation (self-reported distress was not measured in the implicit exclusion condition).</p>
<p>These results were interpreted by Eisenberger and colleagues as suggesting that the experiences of social pain and physical pain may share a neurological basis and that social exclusion can cause both. More recent evidence further corroborates this assertion; individuals taking acetaminophen (a common physical-pain suppressant) showed reduced dACC activity in response to social-exclusion experiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0146167211422449">DeWall et al., 2010</xref>). In other words, ingestion of a medication to quash physical pain attenuated a neurological reaction to a social threat.</p>
<p>In addition to this neurological evidence, other findings elucidate a correspondence between physical and emotional responses to social events. For example, in one study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0146167211422449">Eisenberger, Jarcho, Lieberman, &amp; Naliboff, 2006</xref>), participants’ baseline unpleasantness thresholds for cutaneous heat were assessed at the start of the study. Participants then engaged in a similar online ball-tossing task as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0146167211422449">Williams et al., 2002</xref>), during which participants were either included or excluded (exclusion was once again either explicit or implicit, as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211422449">Eisenberger et al., 2003</xref>). Following the last portion of the Cyberball game, pain threshold measures were taken again, and self-reported social distress was assessed. Results revealed that individuals whose baseline sensitivity to physical pain was high experienced greater social distress in response to social exclusion, compared to those low in physical-pain sensitivity. Furthermore, as reported social distress in response to the ball-tossing game increased, so too did postgame physical pain. Thus, these studies suggest that social distress and physical pain are intimately connected—greater distress in one domain seems to predict greater distress in the other.</p>
<p>If, indeed, social exclusion triggers social pain, then, as the just-described studies suggest, a parallel impact on physical pain should arise. But some have argued that social exclusion may trigger the opposing reactions, both emotional and physical numbness. MacDonald and colleagues (2005) propose that “both social and physical pain lead to reactions that prepare an organism for quick reaction to . . . danger” (p. 79). When responding to a physical threat, the body typically undergoes changes to ready an appropriate reaction. One such change is the release of analgesics that numb the body, which might aid one in fleeing while injured and still under attack (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0146167211422449">MacDonald et al., 2005</xref>). If, as both pain overlap and social pain theories assert, the physical- and social-pain systems are linked, then social threats might trigger the same numbing reaction, both emotionally and physically (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0146167211422449">MacDonald et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Consistent with this notion, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0146167211422449">Twenge, Catanese, and Baumeister (2003)</xref> found that social exclusion puts individuals into what they termed a “deconstructed state.” This involves a lack of emotion, lethargy, time distortion, and a desire to escape self-awareness, all pointing to a state of “inner numbness” (p. 409). Further evidence for emotional numbing postexclusion comes from a recent meta-analysis conducted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0146167211422449">Blackhart, Nelson, Knowles, and Baumeister (2009)</xref>. Based on an examination of the literature, they concluded that emotional reactions to social exclusion tend to be minimal, suggesting it is not uncommon following experimentally induced social exclusion for there to be no changes in mood at all. These researchers have asserted this is precisely because exclusionary experiences elicit an emotional numbness, which, as other findings suggest, appears to accompany a state of physical numbness.</p>
<p>Namely, in a series of studies conducted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall and Baumeister (2006)</xref>, participants’ pain tolerance (how much pain they could stand) and threshold (the point at which they first experienced a sensation as painful) were measured using a pressure algometer. Following these baseline measures, participants responded to a bogus personality test. They were then given false feedback, allegedly based on their answers, about their future lives (future-life paradigm), being told they would have lives full of long-lasting relationships (inclusion condition), lives alone (exclusion condition), lives full of physical mishaps (misfortune/control condition), or no information at all (no feedback/control condition). Pain tolerance and threshold measures were then measured again. Across four studies, the same basic finding occurred: Social exclusion led to physical <italic>insensitivity</italic> (numbing) to pain in comparison to the other conditions. They also found a similar pattern for participants’ emotional reactions. Specifically, excluded individuals were less extreme in their affective forecasting in response to possible positive and negative events (Study 3) and less able to empathize with others (Studies 4 and 5) than were those in the included and control conditions. The overall conclusion drawn by these researchers was that social exclusion leads to a <italic>numbing</italic> of both the physical- and social-pain systems.</p>
<p>Thus, the social-exclusion literature to date is quite consistent in showing that exclusion produces an effect on physical pain with a concomitant reaction on emotional pain. This is compelling evidence that the social- and physical-pain systems are connected. What is less clear, however, is whether the impact of social exclusion itself is one of hypersensitivity or numbness. Some evidence suggests that social exclusion makes victims hurt, both emotionally and physically (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211422449">Eisenberger et al., 2003</xref>), whereas other evidence suggests that social exclusion leads to simultaneous emotional and physical numbness (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall &amp; Baumeister, 2006</xref>). In the remainder of this article, we argue that both responses are possible and dependent, in part, on a crucial moderator—the severity of the social-exclusionary injury.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0146167211422449">
<title>Injury Severity and Pain</title>
<p>If the social- and physical-pain systems overlap, then factors known to moderate one type of painful reaction should similarly moderate the other type. In the domain of physical pain, one’s reactions vary based on experienced injury severity, or the extent of tissue damage done. In fact, the body’s reaction to physical injury is not linear. Stubbing one’s toe is a fairly minor injury that hurts less than breaking a finger, a comparably more severe injury. Generally speaking, as physical injuries increase in severity, so too does the associated pain. That is, as the event causes more tissue damage, the victim experiences more distress. However, at some point, an injury can become so severe that the body does not experience a heightened sense of pain but instead experiences a numbing. When painful stimulation is too great or occurs for too long, the body enters a state of shock in which pain and emotional responses are dulled (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0146167211422449">Kandel, Schwartz, &amp; Jessell, 2000</xref>, for a review). We can imagine the victim of a gunshot or a car crash and how the experienced feeling of the pain is not always commensurate with the severity of the injury. This serves to protect the body from wasting resources because of the hyperactivity of the many systems involved in pain detection that would be forced to continue if the pain were not dulled (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0146167211422449">Kandel et al., 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Given that the social pain system “co-opted” the physical pain system (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0146167211422449">Eisenberger &amp; Leiberman, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0146167211422449">MacDonald &amp; Leary, 2005</xref>), perhaps it is possible that the body might react in a similar manner to an extremely severe social injury as it would an extremely severe physical one. That is, an experience that causes major amounts of “social damage”—by instantiating psychological distance between the self and others of great magnitude or duration—may trigger numbing, rather than hypersensitivity. Physical injuries lead to nociceptive pain when the nerves responsible for detecting such pain (nociceptive nerves) are stimulated. These nerves can be overstimulated, however, and elicit physical numbness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0146167211422449">Kandel et al., 2000</xref>). Perhaps, similarly, the “nerves” that detect social injuries (e.g., self-esteem, as in the sociometer theory; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0146167211422449">Leary et al., 1995</xref>) might also become over stimulated if the social injury is “extreme” or “severe” enough, leading to a physical-pain numbing.</p>
<p>We believe the differing outcomes in the literature on the emotional and physical reactions to social exclusion (hypersensitivity vs. numbness) may be explained by our <italic>severity hypothesis</italic>. This hypothesis asserts that “minor” social injuries should trigger painful (hypersensitive) reactions, whereas “major” social injuries should result in numbing (insensitive) responses. In the current work, we focus exclusively on physical reactions, though our severity hypothesis would make identical predictions for emotional reactions. Researchers who have shown numbing in response to social exclusion may have been subjecting participants to quite severe or major social injuries, whereas researchers reporting hypersensitivity may have used more mild forms.</p>
<p>Consistent with this speculation, there does appear to be a confounding in the literature between social-exclusion paradigm and type of pain response. Broadly, studies showing physical pain numbness have tended to utilize the future-life manipulation, whereas those showing hypersensitivity have tended to utilize the Cyberball paradigm.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0146167211422449">1</xref></sup> On its face, not being thrown a virtual ball during a trivial computer game, though perhaps upsetting, does not seem nearly as devastating as being told that one’s future life will be spent alone. Indeed, given that the need to belong is fundamental (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0146167211422449">Baumeister &amp; Leary, 1995</xref>), it is difficult to imagine a worse prognosis. Thus, the perceived severity of the “social injury” may vary between these paradigms and ultimately may trigger different pain reactions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0146167211422449">
<title>Overview</title>
<p>To examine our severity hypothesis, we first assessed individuals’ perceptions of the severity of two different exclusion experiences. We then randomly assigned participants to be excluded or included in one of them. The paradigm participants reported as being most severe should result in physical-pain numbing, whereas the one rated as mildly severe should result in hypersensitivity. In a second experiment, we manipulated the severity of the exclusion experience within one of the paradigms itself to further examine whether high-severity social exclusions result in numbing, whereas low-severity ones result in hypersensitivity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0146167211422449">
<title>Pilot Study 1</title>
<p>In an initial pilot study, we asked participants to judge the perceived severity of social exclusionary and inclusionary experiences in the Cyberball and future-life paradigms. We examined these two paradigms specifically because they are the ones most commonly used in investigations of exclusion’s impact on physical-pain sensitivity and, because, as noted, they intuitively appear to vary in their perceived severity. In this pilot study, 36 students (23 females) participated for course credit. Students were randomly assigned to one condition of a 2 (Paradigm: Cyberball vs. future-life) × 2 (Inclusionary Status: exclusion vs. inclusion) between-subjects design. Participants were seated in front of computers and told they would be performing a task involving how they perceive different situations. All students were told they would read about a situation and would then rate it on several dimensions. Depending on condition, participants then read a brief description of a typical Cyberball study or a future-life study. Those in the Cyberball conditions were told to imagine playing a virtual ball-tossing game with two other people on a computer. Those in the inclusion condition were further asked to imagine that they were thrown the ball about one third of the time. Those in the exclusion condition were asked to imagine being thrown the ball twice near the beginning of the game, but then never again. Those in the future-life conditions were asked to imagine taking a personality test, having that test analyzed by a computer, and then receiving feedback about the results. Those in the exclusion condition read the future-alone feedback that forecasts a future devoid of meaningful social relationships (taken from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0146167211422449">Twenge, Baumeister, Tice, &amp; Stucke, 2001</xref>) and were asked to imagine that this is the feedback they received. Those in the inclusion condition did the same but read the future-belonging feedback that forecasts a future filled with meaningful relationships. After reading about and imagining one of these situations, participants rated them on a variety of dimensions, with the key one concerning how severely positive or negative they found the situation to be (rated on a scale of −4 = <italic>very negative</italic> to +4 = <italic>very positive</italic>).</p>
<p>Though the exclusion experiences would likely seem more negative than the inclusionary experiences, we predicted that this effect would be moderated by the manipulation of paradigm. Specifically, we expected future-alone to be perceived as more severely negative than Cyberball exclusion and future-belonging to be perceived as more positive than Cyberball inclusion. A 2 (Paradigm: Cyberball vs. future life) × 2 (Inclusionary Status: exclusion vs. inclusion) between-subjects ANOVA revealed a significant main effect of Inclusionary Status, <italic>F</italic>(1, 32) = 98.19, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, η<sup>2</sup> = .75. Exclusion experiences, overall (<italic>M</italic> = −2.73, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.66), were perceived as more negative than were inclusion experiences (<italic>M =</italic> 2.29, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.61). This main effect, however, was qualified by the predicted interaction, <italic>F</italic>(1, 32) = 10.80, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01, η<sup>2</sup> = .25. Imagined receipt of the life-alone feedback (<italic>M</italic> = −3.36, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.27) was perceived as significantly more negative than was imagined exclusion in the Cyberball game (<italic>M</italic> = −1.88, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.81, <italic>p</italic> = .036). In addition, imagined receipt of the future-belonging feedback (<italic>M</italic> = 3.11, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.17) was perceived as significantly more positive than was imagined inclusion in the Cyberball game (<italic>M</italic> = 1.38, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.60, <italic>p</italic> = .020).</p>
<p>Thus, it seems clear that people do indeed perceive exclusion as more negative than inclusion, not surprisingly. But, more importantly, future-alone exclusion was perceived as more severely negative and future-belonging inclusion as more severely positive than was Cyberball exclusion and inclusion. Therefore, if our severity hypothesis is correct in postulating that severe social injuries should result in numbing and mild social injuries should result in hypersensitivity, exclusion in the future-life paradigm should lead to numbing, whereas exclusion in the Cyberball paradigm should lead to hypersensitivity.</p>
<p>Interestingly, this hypothesis and the initial pilot data are quite consistent with the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0146167211422449">DeWall et al. (in press)</xref>. In their study, participants <italic>received</italic> either future-alone or future-belonging feedback (actual experience) or were asked to <italic>imagine</italic> they were to receive such feedback (imagined experience). Participants then rated their mood (actual experience) or how they thought they would feel (imagined experience) following the feedback. Among those who imagined the experience, expected mood was reported to be much lower in the future-alone than in the future-belonging condition. However, for actual experience, there was no difference between the two conditions with respect to mood. Thus, just as we speculate, future-alone exclusion is perceived quite negatively and severely but, when experienced, may lead to numbing.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0146167211422449">
<title>Study 1</title>
<p>Having shown that these manipulations of exclusion do differ in their perceived severity, we next examined if these manipulations affected participants’ physical pain sensitivities differently. In Study 1, participants’ initial pain threshold/tolerance levels were assessed shortly after arrival at the lab. Following this, they engaged in either Cyberball or the future-life paradigm and, within each, were either excluded or included. Following this activity, their pain threshold/tolerance levels were measured again. Because Cyberball exclusion may be akin to a “mild” social injury, we hypothesized that it (a less-severe social injury than is future-alone) should decrease pain threshold and tolerance (make individuals more sensitive to pain), whereas future-life exclusion (a more-severe social injury) should actually increase pain threshold and tolerance (make individuals less sensitive to pain). We predicted no differences between the inclusionary conditions or changes from baseline, as these conditions should be relatively akin to a control group. Indeed, in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall and Baumeister (2006)</xref>, there was no reliable or consistent change in pain tolerance and threshold between baseline and postmanipulation for those who were included. Moreover, the theories in the literature to date have argued specifically that exclusion should activate the pain system but are agnostic about the impact of inclusion on that same system.</p>
<sec id="section6-0146167211422449">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section7-0146167211422449">
<title>Participants and design</title>
<p>For course credit, 52 (29 female) undergraduates from the psychology participant pool participated. Participants were instructed not to ingest any foods, alcohol, or pain medicine for at least 4 hours prior to participating in the experiment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0146167211422449">Kanarek &amp; Carrington, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0146167211422449">Mercer &amp; Holder, 1997</xref>). Moreover, selected participants were nonsmokers and were right handed. These are similar participant requirements and a priori exclusion criteria used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall and Baumeister (2006)</xref>, except they told participants not to eat sugary foods 8 hours in advance, whereas we asked participants not to eat anything for only 4 hours in advance. All participants were randomly assigned to one condition of a 2 Inclusionary Status (exclusion vs. inclusion) × 2 Paradigm (Cyberball vs. future life) between-subjects design.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0146167211422449">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>Participants were run one at a time in the laboratory. After arriving at the lab and completing a thorough written and verbal informed consent process, participants’ baseline measures of pain threshold and tolerance were recorded. Single measures of both threshold and tolerance were taken at 90-second intervals to prevent habituation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall &amp; Baumeister, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0146167211422449">Orbach, Mikulincer, King, Cohen, &amp; Stein, 1997</xref>). Pain threshold and tolerance were measured using a pressure algometer (Wagner FPIX 50). This device assesses the amount of pressure applied to a bone or muscle and has been used as one method of assessing pain sensitivity in medicine and other research fields, including those in the rejection literature (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall &amp; Baumeister, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0146167211422449">Pauli, Wiedemann, &amp; Nickola, 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>Following the method of the aforementioned studies, the algometer was applied perpendicularly to the skin. All pain measurements were taken at the first dorsal interosseous muscle (i.e., behind the first knuckle of the index finger) of the participant’s right hand. Pressure was applied steadily at an average rate of 5 kPa per second. For pain threshold, participants were verbally instructed to say “now” when they first experienced pain because of the pressure increase. For pain tolerance, they were instructed to say “stop” when the pain became too uncomfortable to continue. When the participant acknowledged the sensation of pain (threshold) or requested the pressure to cease (tolerance), the algometer was immediately stopped, which automatically recorded the amount of pressure applied prior to its cessation.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0146167211422449">2</xref></sup> As in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall and Baumeister (2006)</xref>, the order of measurement for threshold and tolerance was counterbalanced. Participants had their threshold or tolerance measured first, took a 90-second break, and then continued with the other measure. This counterbalancing factor had no effect on the outcomes of the study.</p>
<p>Next, participants began either the Cyberball game or the future-life paradigm. For those in the future-life condition, they were asked to complete a personality test used in previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall &amp; Baumeister, 2006</xref>). After completing the personality test, the computer allegedly analyzed their responses. Participants first received accurate feedback based on their responses to the personality assessment concerning their levels of introversion or extroversion. This was done to bolster the believability of the bogus, randomly assigned “future-lives” feedback that they received next. This manipulation has been used previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0146167211422449">Baumeister, DeWall, Ciarocco, &amp; Twenge, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0146167211422449">Baumeister, Twenge, &amp; Nuss, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall &amp; Baumeister, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0146167211422449">Twenge et al., 2001</xref>) and constituted the manipulation of inclusionary status. Participants in the inclusion (future belonging) condition were told,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>You’re the type who has rewarding relationships throughout life. You’re likely to have a long and stable marriage and have friendships that will last into your later years. The odds are that you’ll always have friends and people who care about you.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Participants in the exclusion (future alone) condition were told,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>You’re the type who will end up alone later in life. You may have friends and relationships now, but by your mid 20’s most of these will have drifted away. You may even marry or have several marriages, but these are likely to be short-lived and not continue into your 30’s. Relationships don’t last, and when you’re past the age where people are constantly forming new relationships, the odds are you’ll end up being alone more and more.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>These feedback descriptions were taken directly from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0146167211422449">Twenge and colleagues’ (2001)</xref> work.</p>
<p>The other half of participants engaged in the online ball-tossing game called Cyberball (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0146167211422449">Williams et al., 2002</xref>). Participants in this condition were told they were playing with two other students from around campus who were also involved in similar studies. In reality, no other participants were involved, and the computer controlled the two agents involved in the game. Nonetheless, to facilitate this cover story, the experimenter placed two fake phone calls supposedly to one of the other laboratories involved in this study. Both calls were placed in the room with the actual participant, and in both calls the experimenter pretended to ask whether the other participants were ready, made a comment about it being good that everyone arrived on time, and stated that, should there be any problems, they should call back at the experimenter’s number. Participants were informed that they would be represented by an animated hand at the bottom of the screen whereas the two other players would be represented by animated figures located above and to the right and left of the participant’s figure. Participants were instructed to click on one of the two figures to throw them the ball throughout the task. For those in the inclusion condition, participants were thrown the ball roughly one third of the time by the other “players.” For those in the exclusion condition, they were thrown the ball twice at the beginning of the game and then not again for an additional 45 throws.</p>
<p>Immediately following both manipulations of social inclusionary status, two additional measures of pain threshold and tolerance were taken, using the same procedure from the beginning of the study.</p>
<p>Following this task, participants were given a thorough debriefing. Participants were told the exact nature of the study and how each aspect was related to the others. Importantly, participants in all conditions were told that the exclusion/inclusion feedback they received (future-life paradigm) or the exclusion/inclusion episode they experienced (Cyberball) was completely bogus and randomly assigned. After the debriefing, participants were thanked and encouraged to asked questions before leaving.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0146167211422449">
<title>Results</title>
<p>We hypothesized that exclusion in Cyberball would increase pain sensitivity (i.e., reduce pain tolerance and threshold) but that exclusion in the future-life paradigm would decrease pain sensitivity (i.e., increase pain tolerance and threshold). To test these predictions, we first standardized each participant’s baseline pain tolerance and pain threshold measures. Once standardized, these measures were averaged to form an overall measure of baseline pain sensitivity (with lower numbers indicating more sensitivity). The same procedure was performed for participants’ postmanipulation pain threshold/tolerance measures. We next conducted a 2 (Inclusionary Status: exclusion, inclusion) × 2 (Paradigm: Cyberball, future life) between-subjects ANCOVA on the postmanipulation averaged scores with the premanipulation averaged scores as a covariate (as per <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall &amp; Baumeister, 2006</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0146167211422449">3</xref></sup> The results revealed the predicted interaction, <italic>F</italic>(1, 47) = 16.44, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, η<sup>2</sup> = .26 (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0146167211422449">Figure 1</xref>). Simple effects analyses showed that though the future belonging (<italic>M</italic> = 0.098, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.71) and Cyberball inclusion (<italic>M</italic> = −0.024, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.96) conditions did not differ in terms of pain sensitivity, <italic>F</italic>(1, 23) &lt; 1, <italic>p</italic> &gt; .81, exclusion via Cyberball (<italic>M</italic> = −0.42, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.91) and exclusion via future alone (<italic>M</italic> = 0.29, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.02) were different from each other, <italic>F</italic>(1, 23) = 20.12, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0146167211422449" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The effects of exclusion and inclusion on pain sensitivity as a function of paradigm</p>
<p>Lower numbers indicate more sensitivity to pain (i.e., a lower combined pain threshold and tolerance).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0146167211422449-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Moreover, not only did future alone and Cyberball exclusions differ from each other, but both resulted in changes from baseline in the hypothesized directions. Using one-sample <italic>t</italic> tests, we compared the change in pain sensitivity in each of the four conditions to zero (i.e., a difference score of zero would indicate no change from Time 1 to Time 2, a negative change score would indicate hypersensitivity, and a positive change score would indicate numbing; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall &amp; Baumeister, 2006</xref>, for similar procedures). Although acceptance via Cyberball did not lead to any change in pain sensitivity from Time 1 to Time 2, <italic>t</italic>(12) = 0.59, <italic>p</italic> &gt; .50, Cyberball exclusion did, in fact, lead to a hypersensitivity to pain relative to baseline, <italic>t</italic>(11) = −4.27, <italic>p</italic> = .001. On the other hand, receiving future-belonging feedback did not lead to any change in pain sensitivity from baseline, <italic>t</italic>(12) = 0.094, <italic>p</italic> &gt; .90, but receiving future-alone feedback led to a significant decrease in pain sensitivity, <italic>t</italic>(13) = 2.68, <italic>p</italic> = .019.</p>
<p>To our knowledge, this study is one of the only studies to directly compare these two very different manipulations of social exclusion experimentally. Consistent with the meta-analytic evidence that exclusion manipulations are not interchangeable and can produce effects that differ in magnitude (e.g., on self-esteem; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0146167211422449">Gerber &amp; Wheeler, 2009</xref>), these results show, in a single study, that social exclusion can both increase and decrease pain tolerance/threshold and that the directional impact depends on the nature of the exclusionary experience. As predicted, Cyberball exclusion causes hypersensitivity to pain, whereas future-alone exclusion causes numbness to pain. Thus, our hypothesis was unambiguously supported.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0146167211422449">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>We hypothesized that an important determinant of exclusion’s influence on pain responses is the severity of the exclusionary experience itself. Our pilot data indicated that Cyberball exclusion is perceived as a “mild” social injury, whereas future-alone exclusion is perceived as a “severe” one. Accordingly, our severity hypothesis predicted that exclusion in the Cyberball paradigm should decrease pain threshold/tolerance (i.e., increase pain sensitivity) but that exclusion in the future-life paradigm should increase pain threshold/tolerance (i.e., decrease pain sensitivity). Indeed, this is exactly what this first study found. These results are important not only because they support the primary hypothesis set forth in this article but also because they represent experimental evidence showing that these two common manipulations of social exclusion lead to different effects.</p>
<p>Though Study 1 was successful in showing that Cyberball exclusion increases pain sensitivity and that future-life exclusion decreases it, there are, of course, limitations. Of primary concern is that there are numerous other factors, besides social-injury severity, that differ across these two paradigms. For example, they differ in temporality; Cyberball occurs in the present whereas future-life is in the future. Also, they differ in attributional ambiguity; the cause of the exclusion in Cyberball may be less clear, whereas in future-life it is levied directly on the participants’ personality. Thus, although our pilot data suggest that these two exclusion paradigms differ in perceived severity, the presence of these other confounding variables makes it difficult to definitively conclude that is it severity, and not one of the other factors, that produced hypersensitivity versus numbing across exclusion conditions.</p>
<p>To produce more compelling evidence for our severity hypothesis, therefore, we directly manipulated the severity (i.e., the extent of the “social damage”) of an exclusionary experience within one of these paradigms in Study 2 while keeping all other variables constant. Using this approach, if we again find that a severe social injury triggers numbing and a mild social injury causes hypersensitivity, we will have greater confidence in our hypothesized interpretation.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0146167211422449">
<title>Study 2</title>
<p>In this study, we manipulated the perceived severity of a social-exclusion experience directly while keeping all other aspects of the manipulation constant. We did this by creating a “high-severity” version of the standard future-alone feedback and a similarly worded, but less severe companion. We expected that individuals in the “high-severity” exclusion experience should show the same pattern of pain sensitivity as individuals excluded in the future-life paradigm of Study 1 (i.e., they should experience numbing), whereas those exposed to a “low-severity” exclusion should experience a pattern of sensitivity equivalent to those participants exposed to Cyberball exclusion in Study 1 (i.e., a hypersensitivity to pain). If these predictions are confirmed, this would lend much support to the hypothesis that the severity of the social-exclusion experience drives subsequent reactions on physical pain and is at the heart of the opposing findings in the literature concerning the relation social exclusion shares with pain sensitivity. We began with a pilot study to assess whether our manipulation of severity was valid.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0146167211422449">
<title>Pilot Study 2</title>
<p>Pilot tests of the severity manipulation were conducted using the same procedure as in the pilot for Study 1. In this study, 16 participants (11 females) participated for course credit. They were randomly assigned to one of two conditions (high severity vs. low severity) in a between-subjects design. Just as in Study 1, participants were told they would be performing a task involving how they perceive different situations. All students were told they would read about a situation and would then rate it on several dimensions.</p>
<p>All participants read about an exclusion experience, but the severity of that experience varied. Participants in the “high-severity” condition were asked to imagine being told a very similar version of the original future-alone feedback:</p>
<p>Your score indicates that you are the type who will end up almost completely alone later in life. You may have friends and relationships now, but by your mid-20s most if not all of these will have drifted away. All of your relationships you intend to be “long-term,” both the ones you have now and the ones you may make, are going to be short-lived and not continue into your 30s. All people change as they get older, but people who respond to our survey in the combination of ways that you did tend to have changes that don’t fit with those relationships they tend to currently have. Your relationships don’t last, and when you’re past the age where people are constantly forming new relationships, the odds are you’ll end up being alone more and more.</p>
<p>Participants in the “less severe” condition were asked to imagine being told,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Your score indicates that you are the type who will end up with fewer relationships later in life than you probably expected. You may have friends and relationships now, but by your mid-20s at least 71% (on average) of these will have drifted away. Most (about 75%) of the relationships you intend to be “long-term,” including the ones you have now and the ones you may make, are going to be short-lived and not continue into your 30s. All people change as they get older, but people who respond to our survey in the combination of ways that you did tend to have changes that don’t fit with those relationships they tend to currently have. Your relationships don’t last, and when you’re past the age where people are constantly forming new relationships, you’ll find you have fewer relationships than you would like to have and about 75% fewer relationships than the average individual.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>After reading about and imagining one of these situations, participants rated them on how severely positive or negative they found the situation to be (rated on a scale of −4 = <italic>very negative</italic> to +4 = <italic>very positive</italic>), just as in Study 1.</p>
<p>We predicted that the high-severity future-alone condition would be perceived as more severely negative than the low-severity future-alone condition. An independent-samples <italic>t</italic> test confirmed this to be true, <italic>t</italic>(14) = −2.29, <italic>p</italic> = .038; individuals asked to rate the high-severity feedback (<italic>M</italic> = −2.25, <italic>SD</italic> = 2.31) found it to be more negative than did those asked to imagine receiving the low-severity feedback (<italic>M</italic> = −0.13, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.25). It thus seems clear that our manipulation of severity did indeed differ in the way we predicted. With the manipulation pretested, we next conducted Study 2.</p>
<sec id="section13-0146167211422449">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section14-0146167211422449">
<title>Participants and design</title>
<p>For course credit, 24 (17 female) undergraduates from the psychology participant pool participated. As in Study 1, participants were instructed not to ingest any foods, alcohol, or pain medicine for at least 4 hours prior to participating in the experiment. They were all nonsmokers and were right handed. All participants were randomly assigned to one of two conditions. In both, participants suffered an experience of social exclusion, but some experienced a highly severe social injury whereas others experienced a less-severe social injury.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0146167211422449">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>Participants were run one at a time in the laboratory. After completing a thorough written and verbal informed consent procedure, participants’ baseline measures of pain threshold and tolerance were recorded. This procedure was identical to Study 1. Next, all participants were asked to complete the same bogus personality test used in Study 1. After completing the personality test, the computer analyzed their responses. Then, participants first received accurate feedback concerning their introversion/extroversion (see Study 1) followed by bogus feedback concerning their “personality profile” and how their responses predicted their future lives. This is where the manipulation of severity occurred.</p>
<p>Participants in the “high-severity” condition were given the feedback indicating they would lose virtually all of their social connections (as described in the Study 2 Pilot). In this situation, the extent of the “social damage” is quite extensive. Recipients are led to believe that essentially all of their social relationships will be “broken” and that they will exist in near isolation. Participants in the “less severe” condition were given the other feedback described in the pilot study, indicating they would lose much of the social connections but maintain some. In this condition, “social damage” has certainly occurred, but it is not as severe. Recipients still will feel connected to others, but the extent and magnitude of their social fulfillment is not what they would have hoped.</p>
<p>Just as in Study 1, immediately following receipt of this feedback, two additional measures of pain threshold and tolerance were taken, using the same procedure from the beginning of the study. Following this task, participants were given a thorough debriefing just as in Study 1. After the debriefing, participants were thanked and encouraged to ask questions before leaving.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0146167211422449">
<title>Results and Discussion</title>
<p>We hypothesized that the severity of the social injury (i.e., the exclusion experience) would affect the effect that exclusion has on pain sensitivity. Specifically, we predicted that when an exclusion experience is extremely severe, like the standard future-alone feedback, participants should experience a decrease in pain sensitivity. At the same time, a somewhat less severe experience of social exclusion should actually elicit more sensitivity to pain. To test these predictions, we once again standardized each participant’s baseline pain tolerance and pain threshold measures. Once standardized, these measures were averaged to form an overall measure of baseline pain sensitivity (with lower numbers indicating more sensitivity). The same procedure was performed for participants’ postmanipulation pain threshold/tolerance measures.</p>
<p>We performed an ANCOVA comparing the high-severity and lower-severity versions of the manipulation of social exclusion on the postmanipulation averaged pain scores while using the premanipulation as a covariate (as in Study 1).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0146167211422449">4</xref></sup> The result was significant and supported our hypothesis, <italic>F</italic>(1, 21) = 8.65, <italic>p</italic> = .008, η<sup>2</sup> = .29 (see Figure 2). Participants in the high-severity condition (<italic>M</italic> = 0.12, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.71) experienced a relative decrease in pain sensitivity compared to those in the lower-severity condition (<italic>M</italic> = −0.14, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.18). When using a one-sample <italic>t</italic> test to compare the difference between postmanipulation pain and premanipulation pain to 0, we found that participants in the high-severity condition experienced a decreased pain sensitivity (higher pain threshold and tolerance) relative to baseline, <italic>t</italic>(12) = 2.69, <italic>p</italic> = .02. Moreover, the opposite was found for the lower-severity condition; participants in this condition experienced a higher pain sensitivity (lower pain threshold and tolerance) relative to baseline, <italic>t</italic>(10) = −2.12, <italic>p</italic> = .058.</p>
<p>Overall, we hypothesized that the severity (or extent of “social damage”) of the exclusion experience might dictate the effect social exclusion has on pain sensitivity. In this second study, we employed two different versions of the future-alone feedback so that some participants were exposed to a very severe manipulation (which is quite similar to the one currently used in the literature), whereas others received a less-severe version. We hypothesized and found that the less-severe version of the manipulation actually led to more pain sensitivity (yielding results that looked very much like those engendered by Cyberball rejection in Study 1), whereas the more-severe version replicated the numbing of pain from Study 1 and prior work.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0146167211422449">
<title>General Discussion</title>
<p>Within the exclusion literature, a contradiction has existed regarding the effect of social exclusion on pain sensitivity. Though both pain overlap (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0146167211422449">Eisenberger &amp; Lieberman, 2005</xref>) and social pain theories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0146167211422449">MacDonald &amp; Leary, 2005</xref>) suggest that social exclusion might trigger a response from the physical- and social-pain systems, the nature of this response is unclear. Both a numbing (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall &amp; Baumeister, 2006</xref>) and a hypersensitivity reaction (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211422449">Eisenberger et al., 2003</xref>) appear possible. We hypothesized that these different patterns of findings may be the result of the severity of the social-exclusion experiences themselves. Physical injuries and experienced pain share a nonlinear relationship, such that as the damage from the injury increases, so too does the experience of pain, but only to a certain point; eventually, injuries become too severe and pain actually diminishes as the body experiences numbing. We asserted that perhaps social injuries follow a similar pattern, such that as social injuries (e.g., from social exclusion) increase in their perceived severity (i.e., as the victim perceives greater social distance from others), pain increases as well until a critical threshold is reached, at which point a numbing begins.</p>
<p>The results of Study 1 unambiguously supported this hypothesis: Cyberball exclusion (shown in pilot testing to be a relatively low-severity exclusion) caused hypersensitivity to pain, whereas future-alone exclusion (shown to be a relatively high-severity exclusion) caused numbness to pain. We believe the finding that the type of social exclusion experience itself can moderate the response to physical pain is a novel contribution itself. Furthermore, to our knowledge, this study is the first to directly compare these two very different manipulations of social exclusion within the same study and show that they produce opposing outcomes. Based on these results, it no longer seems wise to assume that all exclusion experiences affect their victims equivalently.</p>
<p>Though the results of Study 1 were consistent with our severity hypothesis, they were not completely conclusive because many other alternative explanations could apply. In Study 2, however, we directly manipulated the severity of the exclusion experience while holding all other features of the episode constant (thus ensuring none of the possible confounds from the manipulations in Study 1 were responsible for our findings). Consistent with the hypothesis, our results revealed that the manipulation of exclusion severity led to opposing pain responses, such that a less severe future-alone rejection led to an increase in sensitivity to painful stimuli, whereas the highly severe version led to pain numbing.</p>
<p>Though Study 1 offers novel evidence concerning the differences between these two different manipulations of exclusion, the results of Study 2 in particular may yield potentially important insights regarding possible moderators of social-exclusion outcomes more broadly. A lingering question among researchers studying exclusion focuses on explaining why the outcomes of social exclusion vary as they do. If the severity of the exclusion experience is the reason why Cyberball exclusion increases pain sensitivity and future-alone exclusion numbs one to pain, this might explain, in part, the tendency to find prosocial, adaptive responses following Cyberball exclusion and antisocial, maladaptive responses following future-alone exclusion.</p>
<p>Cyberball exclusion, we argue, leads to a low-severity experience of exclusion. It hurts, both emotionally (as shown previously) and physically. Just as physical pain directs us to engage in behaviors to remedy the situation, the social distress associated with the low-severity pain of Cyberball exclusion should lead us to engage in corrective behaviors. People should take steps toward fixing the injury and thus reducing the pain. Helping others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0146167211422449">Williams &amp; Sommer, 1997</xref>), engaging in behavioral mimicry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0146167211422449">Lakin &amp; Chartrand, 2005</xref>), and attending to cues relevant for reaffiliation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0146167211422449">Bernstein, Sacco, Brown, Young, &amp; Claypool, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0146167211422449">Bernstein, Young, Brown, Sacco, &amp; Claypool, 2008</xref>) are all behaviors that lead to the desired end state of reaffiliation and thus a reduction in social distress and pain.</p>
<p>On the other hand, future-alone exclusion is not a low-severity injury. It is a major, shock-inducing injury that numbs rather than hurts. Because it leads to emotional and physical numbness, people experience no pain and thus are not compelled in the same way to fix the situation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall and Baumeister (2006)</xref> argued that people may use their emotional faculties to understand the world around them and to determine how to interact with other people. If people’s emotional systems are shocked into numbness, this might explain why people engage in behaviors that seem to be counter to the goal of affiliating with others—like aggressive behavior (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0146167211422449">Twenge et al., 2001</xref>). Perhaps the only caveat to DeWall and Baumeister’s argument that we would add, then, is that it is not true that all exclusionary experiences lead to this numbing. The severity of the experience appears to be an important moderator. “Minor” social injuries should trigger pain, which may lead to prosocial responses. “Severe” social injuries, on the other hand, should trigger numbing and thus lead to more antisocial behaviors.</p>
<p>Future research should examine the extent to which low-severity social exclusions trigger reaffiliative behaviors and otherwise adaptive responses and the extent to which high-severity exclusions trigger more maladaptive and antisocial behaviors. Furthermore, to extend the link between physical pain and social pain even further, perhaps it would be best not to consider social exclusion as leading to either antisocial or prosocial responses but, instead, to consider that social exclusion leads to behaviors aimed at either fixing the situation or protecting the self and that the extent to which anti- versus prosocial reactions occur is likely moderated by the severity of the social exclusion. If this perspective were supported, it would offer a new understanding of social exclusion’s effects and might spawn new and interesting predictions. For instance, perhaps low-severity exclusions elicit the purchase of luxury items that indicate status (in an attempt to attract social connections), whereas high-severity social exclusions perhaps elicit the purchase of survival items (in an attempt to protect the self). Future research would benefit the literature by examining these ideas further.</p>
<p>Though there is much promise in this research, these studies, like all others, have some limitations. One obvious limitation is that Study 2 manipulated severity within the future-life paradigm only. The outcome was as hoped, that a less-severe future-alone manipulation triggered increased pain sensitivity. In subsequent work, however, it will be equally important to manipulate severity within other exclusion paradigms and to show that more and less severe versions can produce pain numbing and hypersensitivity, respectively. For instance, does writing about a time one experienced a mild exclusion (e.g., friends forgetting to call you on a Friday night) lead to heightened sensitivity to pain, and does writing about a more serious social infraction (e.g., the end of a multiyear relationship) lead to a numbing of pain?</p>
<p>We are also limited in our understanding of whether or not our results could be mapped at the neurological level. There is now ample evidence that social pain is experienced by the same centers of the brain as is physical pain (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0146167211422449">Eisenberger et al., 2003</xref>). It would be interesting to determine if the severity of a social injury also moderates the neurological reactions to rejection. Presently, we do not know whether our effect is driven by neurological responses or whether it is the result of other processes. Future research should investigate this issue.</p>
<p>In closing, we believe this work has the potential to make varied and valuable contributions to the social-exclusion literature. This work is the first to experimentally compare two distinct methods of social exclusion and show, in a single study, that not all methods of exclusion are the same. Moreover, this work showed that Cyberball exclusion can lead to pain hypersensitivity, that future-life exclusion can lead to pain numbing, and that these different patterns may be the result of the two types of exclusions varying in their perceived severity. In addition, this work offers new evidence in support of pain overlap theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0146167211422449">Eisenberger &amp; Lieberman, 2005</xref>) and social pain theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0146167211422449">MacDonald &amp; Leary, 2005</xref>), both of which argue that social and physical pain share a neurological system. Finally, and most broadly, this work shows, in a unique way, what social psychologists have long argued—that one’s social experiences can have profound effects on one’s functioning, in this case even altering one’s physical sensations.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0146167211422449">
<label>1.</label>
<p>One exception to this pattern comes from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0146167211422449">MacDonald, Kingsbury, and Shaw (2005)</xref>, who excluded or accepted participants in Cyberball (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0146167211422449">Williams et al., 2002</xref>). Prior to the game, participants’ proneness to hurt feelings was measured and, immediately after, their physical pain threshold was measured using a cold-pressor task. The results indicated that, among individuals who were highly prone to hurt feelings, social exclusion during the game elicited higher pain thresholds than did inclusion (indicative of numbing). Even this exception to the aforementioned pattern appears consistent with our severity hypothesis. The reason is simple: Just as people who are highly sensitive to physical pain may interpret the same amount of pressure as much more severe than others who are less sensitive to physical pain, perhaps those high in hurt-feeling proneness interpret the exclusion from Cyberball as a far more socially severe experience than those lower on this dimension might interpret the same experience.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0146167211422449">
<label>2.</label>
<p>If the pressure reached 250N, the application of pressure was immediately stopped to avoid injuring the participant. In those cases, we recorded that maximum allotted amount (of 250N) as the participant’s tolerance/threshold. A total of 8 participants received 250N, all when measuring tolerance. At baseline, 4 participants registered 250N, 3 of whom were in the Cyberball condition (2 rejection, 1 acceptance) and 1 of whom was in the future-life condition (1 acceptance). Postmanipulation, 2 of the same participants also registered 250N (both were in the Cyberball condition; 1 rejection, 1 acceptance). The remaining 4 participants also registered 250N postmanipulation, all of whom were in the future-life condition (3 rejection, 1 acceptance).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0146167211422449">
<label>3.</label>
<p>Though we ran our analyses using baseline measures of pain as a covariate, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0146167211422449">DeWall and Baumeister (2006)</xref> did, we also conducted a 2 (Inclusionary Status: exclusion, inclusion) × 2 (Paradigm: Cyberball, future life) × 2 Measurement Time (premanipulation, postmanipulation) mixed-model ANOVA with repeated measures on the last factor. This yielded a significant three-way interaction, <italic>F</italic>(1, 48) = 18.042, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. Significant two-way interactions between Inclusionary Status and Measurement Time were found for both the Cyberball and the future-life paradigms (both <italic>p</italic>s &lt; .04). The pattern exhibited using the covariate analyses remained true when using Measurement Time as a repeated-measures factor; among future-alone participants, excluded individuals became more numb to pain after the manipulation than prior to it (<italic>p</italic> = .003), whereas among participants excluded via Cyberball, individuals had a lower average pain threshold/tolerance after the manipulation than prior to it (<italic>p</italic> = .001). The acceptance conditions did not differ in either paradigm between Time 1 and Time 2 (both <italic>p</italic>s &gt; .58).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0146167211422449">
<label>4.</label>
<p>As in Study 1, when conducting the analyses using a 2 (Severity: high, low) × 2 Measurement Time (premanipulation, postmanipulation) mixed-model ANOVA with repeated measures on the last factor, the interaction was significant, and the pattern of data remained unchanged, <italic>F</italic>(1, 22) = 11.34, <italic>p</italic> = .003. Individuals in the “low-severity” condition experienced a decrease in their combined threshold/tolerance measure (<italic>p</italic> = .021), whereas individuals receiving the “high-severity” feedback experienced a numbing of pain sensitivity, as indicated by an increased combined threshold/tolerance (<italic>p</italic> = .033).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Meanings of life</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeWall</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ciarocco</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Twenge</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Social exclusion impairs self-regulation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>88</volume>, <fpage>589</fpage>-<lpage>604</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeWall</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vohs</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Social rejection, control, numbness, and emotion: How not to be fooled by Gerber and Wheeler</article-title>. <source>Perspectives on Psychological Science</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>489</fpage>-<lpage>493</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leary</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The need to belong: Desire for interpersonal attachments as a fundamental human motivation</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>117</volume>, <fpage>497</fpage>-<lpage>529</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tice</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Anxiety and social exclusion</article-title>. <source>Journal of Social and Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>165</fpage>-<lpage>195</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Twenge</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nuss</surname><given-names>C. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Effects of social exclusion on cognitive processes: Anticipated aloneness reduces intelligent thought</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>83</volume>, <fpage>817</fpage>-<lpage>827</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Claypool</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A preference for genuine smiles following social exclusion</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>196</fpage>-<lpage>199</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Claypool</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Adaptive responses to social exclusion: Social rejection improves detection of real and fake smiles</article-title>. <source>Psychological Science</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>981</fpage>-<lpage>983</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blackhart</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>B. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Rejection elicits emotional reactions but neither causes immediate distress nor lowers self-esteem: A meta-analytic review of 192 studies on social exclusion</article-title>. <source>Personality and Social Psychology Review</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>309</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Taking the social origins of human nature seriously: Toward a more imperialist social psychology</article-title>. <source>Personality and Social Psychology Review</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>113</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sherrod</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Social skills and the stress-protective role of social support</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>963</fpage>-<lpage>973</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wills</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Stress, social support, and the buffering hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>310</fpage>-<lpage>357</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DeWall</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Alone but feeling no pain: Effects of social exclusion on physical pain tolerance and pain threshold, affective forecasting, and interpersonal empathy</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DeWall</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Masten</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Eisenberger</surname><given-names>N. I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Acetaminophen reduces social pain: Behavioral and neural evidence</article-title>. <source>Psychological Science</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>931</fpage>-<lpage>937</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DeWall</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Twenge</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koole</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>in press</year>). <article-title>Automatic emotion regulation after social exclusion: Nonconscious attunement to positivity as a key to mental health</article-title>. <source>Emotion</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eisenberger</surname><given-names>N. I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jarcho</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naliboff</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>An experimental study of shared sensitivity to physical pain and social rejection</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>, <volume>126</volume>, <fpage>132</fpage>-<lpage>138</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eisenberger</surname><given-names>N. I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Why it hurts to be left out: The neurocognitive overlap between physical and social pain</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forgas</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>von Hippel</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The social outcast: Ostracism, social exclusion, rejection, and bullying</source> (pp. <fpage>109</fpage>-<lpage>130</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychology Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eisenberger</surname><given-names>N. I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Does rejection hurt? An fMRI study of social exclusion</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>302</volume>, <fpage>290</fpage>-<lpage>292</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>On being rejected: A meta-analysis of experimental research on rejection</article-title>. <source>Perspectives on Psychological Science</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>468</fpage>-<lpage>488</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kanarek</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Sucrose consumption enhances the analgesic effects of cigarette smoking in male and female smokers</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology</source>, <volume>173</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kandel</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jessell</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Principles of neural science</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Keicolt-Glaser</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ricker</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>George</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Messick</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Speicher</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Urinary cortisol levels, cellular immunocompetency, and loneliness in psychiatric inpatients</article-title>. <source>Psychosomatic Medicine</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lakin</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chartrand</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Exclusion and nonconscious behavioral mimicry</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forgas</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>von Hippel</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The social outcast: Ostracism, social exclusion, rejection, and bullying</source> (pp. <fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>296</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychology Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leary</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kowalski</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Teasing, rejection, and violence: Case studies of the school shootings</article-title>. <source>Aggressive Behavior</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>202</fpage>-<lpage>214</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leary</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tambor</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Terdal</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Self-esteem as an interpersonal monitor: The sociometer hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>518</fpage>-<lpage>530</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eisenberger</surname><given-names>N. I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A pain by any other name (rejection, exclusion, ostracism), still hurts the same: The role of dorsal anterior cingulate in social and physical pain</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cacioppo</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Social neuroscience: People thinking about people</source> (pp. <fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>187</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kingsbury</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Adding insult to injury: Social pain theory and response to social exclusion</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forgas</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>von Hippel</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The social outcast: Ostracism, social exclusion, rejection, &amp;; bullying</source> (pp. <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>90</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychology Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leary</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Why does social exclusion hurt? The relationship between social and physical pain</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>131</volume>, <fpage>202</fpage>-<lpage>223</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mathes</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Jealousy: Loss of relationship rewards, loss of self-esteem, depression, anxiety, and anger</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>1552</fpage>-<lpage>1561</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holder</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Antinociceptive effects of palatable sweet ingesta on human responsivity to pressure pain</article-title>. <source>Physiology &amp; Behavior</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>311</fpage>-<lpage>318</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Panksepp</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Brain substrates of infant-mother attachment: Contributions of opiods, oxytocin, and norepinephrine</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>437</fpage>-<lpage>452</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Orbach</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mikulincer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Thresholds and tolerance of physical pain in suicidal and nonsuicidal patients</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>646</fpage>-<lpage>652</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pauli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wiedemann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nickola</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Pressure pain thresholds asymmetry in left- and right-handers: Associations with behavioural measures of cerebral laterality</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Pain</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>156</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Psychological and neural mechanisms of the affective dimension of pain</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>288</volume>, <fpage>1769</fpage>-<lpage>1772</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rainville</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carrier</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bushnell</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Pain affect encoded in human anterior cingulate but not somatosensory cortex</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>277</volume>, <fpage>968</fpage>-<lpage>971</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laub</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>Crime in the making: Pathways and turning points through life</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crescioni</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeWall</surname><given-names>C. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fincham</surname><given-names>F. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Alone and without purpose: Life loses meaning following social exclusion</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>686</fpage>-<lpage>694</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Twenge</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tice</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stucke</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>If you can’t join them, beat them: Effects of social exclusion on aggressive behavior</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>1058</fpage>-<lpage>1069</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Twenge</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Catanese</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Social exclusion and the deconstructed state: Time perception, meaninglessness, lethargy, lack of emotion, and self-awareness</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>85</volume>, <fpage>409</fpage>-<lpage>423</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Govan</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Croker</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tynan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cruickshank</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Investigations into differences between social and cyber ostracism</article-title>. <source>Group Dynamics: Theory, Research, &amp;; Practice</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0146167211422449">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Social ostracism by one’s coworkers: Does rejection lead to loafing or compensation?</article-title> <source>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>693</fpage>-<lpage>706</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>