<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjcx</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Correctional Health Care</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1078-3458</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1940-5200</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1078345813486322</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1078345813486322</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Commentries</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>What Correctional Practitioners Want in an Electronic Health Record</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Paris</surname>
<given-names>Joseph E.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD, MD, CCHP-A</degrees>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1078345813486322">†</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1078345813486322"><label>†</label>The author passed away in September 2012. At the time this article was accepted for publication, he was an independent consultant in correctional health care. Email: <email>journal@ncchc.org</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>218</fpage>
<lpage>228</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">NCCHC</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The author analyzed electronic health records (EHR) systems in use in a dozen prisons or jails across the United States and defined 20 criteria for EHR in four categories: clinical interface; integration; logging, tracking, and reporting; and miscellaneous. The majority of EHR surveyed did not meet more than a few of the criteria. It should be feasible to incorporate these criteria in a single EHR. The author aims to provide criteria to help correctional health care administrators and practitioners make informed choices regarding EHR.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>electronic health records</kwd>
<kwd>EHR</kwd>
<kwd>correctional health care</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1078345813486322">
<title>Dawn of the Correctional EHR Era</title>
<p>The author has performed National Commission on Correctional Health Care (NCCHC) accreditation surveys as a senior physician surveyor since 1990. In the past few years, electronic health records systems (EHR) were found in a dozen prisons or jails. There were wide differences between systems. Some EHR evolved as an extension of preexisting, security-oriented information technology (IT). Others were commercial products originally intended for noncorrectional ambulatory clinics. Some of the correctional EHR implementations had proceeded in fits and starts, with some systems reverting temporarily to paper records. In some systems, the transition from paper to EHR resulted in workflow dislocations and bottlenecks. In some instances, EHR implementation caused unanticipated changes in provider clinical behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1078345813486322">Paris, 2009a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1078345813486322">2009c</xref>). As recently as 2007, penetration of fully functional EHR in ambulatory care practices in the United States was only 4% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1078345813486322">Desroches et al., 2008</xref>). Yet, it is evident that correctional health services are moving toward EHR.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1078345813486322">
<title>Advantages of Using EHR</title>
<p>Why the urge to go with correctional EHR? There are several theoretical advantages: (a) legibility both on screen and when printed, (b) all electronic signatures and grades are present and legible, (c) all entries are accurately time-stamped, (d) records may be simultaneously available at multiple workstations, (e) data can be aggregated and presented in graph or table form, and (f) future patient appointments can be generated automatically.</p>
<p>While the above advantages are generally agreed upon, there are additional advantages that appear self-evident but have not been experimentally proven. For example, EHR should (a) require fewer personnel, (b) save provider time, and (c) increase patient safety and minimize medical errors.</p>
<p>In the correctional EHR surveyed, more provider, nursing, and clerical staff—not less—was required for many months after implementation. Some of the paper health records staff had to be retained in order to maintain remaining paper record activities. In addition, IT staff had to be hired in order to nurture the new EHR. In the systems reviewed, provider productivity (patients seen per hour) had decreased after EHR adoption due to increased staff time spent in electronic review and charting.</p>
<p>The issue of patient safety with EHR is complex. Currently, there is no official organization for health care practitioners to report adverse events that result from EHR implementation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1078345813486322">Sittig &amp; Classen, 2010</xref>). Consequently, there are no data of the volume of EHR-related medical mishaps. These do occur, as exemplified by isolated reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1078345813486322">Sittig, Ash, Zhang, Osheroff, &amp; Shabot, 2006</xref>). The jury is still out on the issue of decrease of medical errors with EHR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1078345813486322">Schiff &amp; Bates, 2010</xref>). It is believed that future EHR will provide the tools to address clinical safety problems and to help health care organizations to improve their performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1078345813486322">Radecki &amp; Sittig, 2011</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1078345813486322">
<title>Deciding to Adopt EHR</title>
<p>At the correctional facilities surveyed, EHR purchase decisions were rarely shared with health staff. Instead, administrators and other nonmedical staff with the power of the purse decided to implement EHR and selected the system to use. In some cases, medical staff did attend EHR sales pitch sessions and expressed some opinions but did not participate in the final selection. After EHR purchase, key medical staff may be asked to beta-test the program and give suggestions. However, such involvement after the selection was made seldom led to major improvements or changes. Ideally, before committing to a given EHR, medical staff should visit and review one or more fully installed EHR elsewhere.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1078345813486322">
<title>The Myth of Provider Resistance to EHR</title>
<p>Some correctional health care EHR implementations reviewed had failed, requiring temporary return to paper records. Other EHR systems had endured despite their weaknesses but were blamed for substantial losses of efficiency and perceived losses in clinical quality. Faced with poor return of EHR investment, administrators and programmers may find physicians and other providers an easy target to blame for the failures. However, the same physicians who allegedly were resistant to EHR had computers at home, used an iPhone, Blackberry, or other personal digital assistant (PDA) device, and embraced IT in their personal lives. It appears that physicians and other providers would use IT enthusiastically if it facilitates, not hinders, their work.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1078345813486322">
<title>Technical Considerations</title>
<p>Here is a partial listing of issues to be considered before committing to an EHR purchase: (a) integration with security (often times a legacy system); (b) connectivity between sites, firewalls, and levels of security; (c) sufficient bandwidth (data transfer speed) and storage capacity; (d) backup systems, power failure safeguards, and alternatives during breakdowns; (e) vendor support for upgrades (and future financing of these); and (f) cost of hardware, software, new staff, and training.</p>
<p>It is beyond the scope of this article to discuss these important technical points. The remainder of this article will deal exclusively with criteria relevant to the clinical user.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1078345813486322">
<title>Experience With EHR During NCCHC Accreditation Reviews</title>
<p>A key component of NCCHC accreditation surveys is the assessment of clinical performance. Such assessment is primarily achieved by having a seasoned physician surveyor review a representative sample of inmate-patient records of sick call, chronic care, infirmary care, emergency care, and specialty consultation.</p>
<p>In the past few years, NCCHC surveyors transitioned to reviewing EHR. Several changes in the review approach became necessary. Because each EHR being surveyed was unique, the physician surveyor was always behind the learning curve and thus unable to efficiently review unassisted. Physician surveyors learned to routinely request the assignment of an EHR-experienced local staff member (usually a nurse) for the duration of the survey. Even with such help, the number of files reviewed was usually lower than it would be for comparable facilities with paper records.</p>
<p>A number of EHR systems encountered in NCCHC accreditation surveys were technologically advanced, but the final product was nearly unusable because of major flaws in the design of the provider interface, poor clinical capabilities, and lack of management features.</p>
<p>Careful analysis of the shortcomings of EHR systems in use in a dozen prisons or jails across the United States led to developing 20 criteria dealing with clinical interface; integration; logging, tracking, and reporting; and miscellaneous (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1078345813486322">Table 1</xref>). It was observed that the majority of EHR surveyed did not meet more than a few of the criteria proposed here.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1078345813486322" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The 20 Proposed Criteria.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1078345813486322" xlink:href="10.1177_1078345813486322-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Clinical Interface Criteria</th>
<th>Integration Criteria</th>
<th>Logging, Tracking, and Reporting Criteria</th>
<th>Miscellaneous Criteria</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center">User-friendly display</td>
<td>Booking data</td>
<td>Callouts</td>
<td>No dual (paper plus EHR) records</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Decision support</td>
<td>Inmate-signed letters, requests, consents, andgrievances</td>
<td>Chronic care</td>
<td>Minimizes workflow disruptions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Preset prompts</td>
<td>Lab and other reports</td>
<td>Interval from request to performance</td>
<td>Allows easy customizing</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Problem list</td>
<td>Medication administration records</td>
<td>Aggregated clinical activity reports</td>
<td>Capable of well-laid-out printed output</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Identification of key events</td>
<td>e-Prescribing</td>
<td>Processing consultation, lab, and X-ray reports</td>
<td>Generates “to-do” lists</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1078345813486322">
<title>Individual Criteria Descriptions, Rationale, and Discussion</title>
<sec id="section8-1078345813486322">
<title>Clinical Interface Criteria</title>
<sec id="section9-1078345813486322">
<title>User-friendly display</title>
<p>The EHR should be able to display at least two “pages” simultaneously. The layout should be designed with the provider in mind.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: Providers typing a note should be able to see the last note of the same kind, copying and pasting as needed. They should also have continuous access to the problem list; the medications list; the medication administration records (MAR); and the lab, X-ray, consultant, and other reports so that a good clinical note can be created with a minimum of memorization of complex data.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: In some systems, pertinent EHR areas can be accessed by toggling between a progress note and the appropriate data screen, but such approach is cumbersome and requires the provider to memorize the data being transcribed. Some EHR employed pull-down listings that partially occluded the progress note being written. None of the systems reviewed displayed more than one page. As larger flat screens become more affordable, the ability to display two, four, or even six electronic pages should be within reach. Other relevant interface improvements are suggested. For questionnaires, the “YES” and “NO” boxes should line up so providers can easily spot patients with all negative answers. A few systems used green for “NO” checkmarks or buttons and red for “YES” (condition present and in need of attention), a welcome feature. The encounter date should appear in every page (screen) and should be much larger than other dates, such as “date printed,” “date of birth,” “date reviewed,” and the like, because EHR reviewers should rapidly be keyed into the date of occurrence of medical events.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1078345813486322">
<title>Decision support</title>
<p>The EHR includes clinical decision support.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: Today’s technology allows EHR to include hyperlinks to relevant databases such as ideal patient weight and body mass index, emergency poison antidotes, formularies, and Physician’s Desk Reference.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: Decision support would be particularly useful in furnishing access to guidelines for the management of chronic disorders, such as diabetes, hypertension, hyperlipidemia, and HIV. In addition to links to static databases, true clinical decision support would entail the ability to generate a differential diagnosis from the clinical data entered. However, this capability borders on artificial intelligence, requires huge computing power, and generally has not been included in correctional EHR. It is anticipated that clinical decision support will become an integral part of EHR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1078345813486322">Greenberg &amp; Ridgely, 2011</xref>).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1078345813486322">
<title>Preset prompts</title>
<p>Carefully designed preset prompts help providers to chart basic clinical data.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: Providers chart repetitive data, such as vital signs, physical findings, and the like. Preset prompts relieve providers from keyboarding these headings over and over.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: Every system reviewed displayed prompts, but prompt usefulness varied widely. For physical exam or review of systems items, positive or negative answers need to line up, thus allowing rapid scanning of positive findings in need of attention. It is user-friendly to display the prompts in boldface and the provider entries in regular typeface. In a number of EHR, the program creators had mandated, for each clinical situation, the checking of numerous clinical descriptors that the physician must fill in or the page will not save. Some providers become inured to the profusion of required information and filled all mandatory fields as negative so they could “get on with the real charting by keyboarding a narrative” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1078345813486322">Paris, 2009b</xref>). In fact, one EHR reviewed included a button that providers could click to have all the prompts in the screen checked as negative. The use of such “all negative” buttons may entice certain providers to ignore the prompts and not examine or question the patient item by item.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1078345813486322">
<title>Problem list</title>
<p>The EHR updates the problem list automatically.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: An accurate, up-to-date problem list is a key component of the health record.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: In all EHR systems reviewed, problem lists were entered by hand. Providers may become oblivious of such requirement and frequently fail to update the problem list, which soon may become obsolete. It should be possible for a correctional EHR to automatically create a problem list by reproducing in the problem list the initial appearance of key terms in progress notes, such as “congestive heart failure” or “onset of diabetes.” Another possible solution would be to insert in the medical encounter screens a reminder for providers to update the problem list. Recent literature describes the failure of EHR to effectively integrate the creation, updating, reorganization, and inactivation of items on problem lists into the clinician’s workflow. It has been said that “the problem list has been one of the great failures of clinical informatics” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1078345813486322">Schiff &amp; Bates, 2010</xref>).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1078345813486322">
<title>Identification of key events</title>
<p>Providers can easily retrieve previous key clinical events.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: Clinicians need to know when a medical event has occurred in the past, such as the onset of a new chronic condition.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: In the correctional EHR reviewed, providers searching for key past medical events would see a list of previous clinical encounters sorted by date. Encounters were listed as “sick call,” “chronic care,” and the like, offering no clues on the clinical events involved. Some EHR did have word search capabilities. In theory, a provider could search for key words in order to drill into the relevant encounter. In practice, such searches produce numerous iterations of the key word unrelated to the relevant event. Providers wishing to know when a certain clinical finding, such as cough, had first appeared had to open dozens or even hundreds of individual encounter screens. Such laborious searches were seldom undertaken. Instead, providers would ask the patient, who may not remember or may tell incomplete or incorrect medical histories. EHR could display meaningful listings of encounters by prompting providers to add a descriptor of salient events to be incorporated into encounter listings. Another solution would be to display encounter lists with the corresponding chief complaint, thus giving the reviewer some clues regarding key clinical events.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1078345813486322">
<title>Integration Criteria</title>
<sec id="section15-1078345813486322">
<title>Booking data</title>
<p>Relevant demographic and medical data obtained in booking should be incorporated into the EHR seamlessly and automatically.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: Booking includes questioning and observing the inmate for certain medical conditions and needs. Incorporating booking data automatically into the EHR would save medical staff time and improve clinical performance.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: In most prisons and jails, booking operations are automated but, in most cases, the IT system in use was procured by security staff and is different and separate from the EHR. It is important to incorporate medical booking data into the EHR. Appropriate interfaces, firewalls, passwords, and levels of security are needed so as to avoid the “contamination” of security data by unauthorized staff.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1078345813486322">
<title>Inmate-signed letters, requests, consents, and grievances</title>
<p>Inmate-signed documents should enter the EHR seamlessly and automatically.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: Automatically incorporating into the EHR all inmate-signed documents would result in staff time savings and would streamline patient care.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: In many prisons and jails using EHR, inmate-signed documents are still paper based. These can be scanned, properly indexed, and incorporated in the EHR as images (a time-consuming task), but the text in such images cannot be searched electronically. Lack of integration of medical service requests and EHR was one of the most glaring flaws of the observed EHR. In extreme cases, inmates writing a paper medical service request received from medical staff a handwritten response that differed from the electronically entered response.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<p>In one of the correctional EHR observed, inmates had access to sturdy keyboards in the law library and a keyboard in a cart roving the cellblocks. The keyboards were interfaced with the EHR. A spell-checker was included. Inmates could only input their health service requests, letters to the medical service, or grievances, without access to the EHR itself. Keyboard-illiterate inmates were assisted by staff.</p>
<p>It is anticipated that, in the future, systems allowing inmate keyboarding will become commonplace because they allow seamless integration into the EHR of inmate-written documents.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1078345813486322">
<title>Lab and other reports</title>
<p>Laboratory, X-ray, consultation, and emergency room (ER) reports and hospital discharge summaries should enter the EHR seamlessly and automatically.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: Large numbers of reports from labs, X-rays, consultations, ER, and hospital visits arrive daily to correctional institutions. A method is needed to efficiently incorporate the incoming reports into the EHR.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: Most EHR reviewed lacked the ability to incorporate incoming reports. Instead, much staff time was spent scanning incoming printed reports. Scanned reports are hard to find unless very carefully “indexed” (i.e., each scanned report is given a highly descriptive file name). Scanned data represent an inferior form of EHR because it does not lend itself to electronic searches; only the index can be searched. The issue of how to distribute electronic lab and other reports is discussed below under Logging, Tracking, and Reporting Criteria.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1078345813486322">
<title>MAR</title>
<p>An electronic, portable MAR includes at least all of the paper MAR functions.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: A fully functional electronic MAR is a key component of a correctional EHR.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: Older electronic MAR systems used the medical unit PCs. In the absence of portable laptops, nurses passing medications cellside had to write on paper scraps whether medications were administered or refused. After their return to the medical unit, nurses had to wait for a free PC terminal before entering their electronic notes hours after medication administration. Delayed entries may lead to medication errors. To be useful for cellside and pill line administration, an electronic MAR should be portable. Some EHR reviewed did provide roving laptops or tablet PCs to nurses administering medications. Roving laptops or tablet PCs may be wirelessly connected to an intranet or may store the entries until “dumped” into the EHR upon return to the medical unit. Efficiency could be increased by integrating bar-code readers into the MAR process. Nurses would wand the inmate’s bar-coded bracelet and the bar-coded medication blister pack and select in the screen the box for “administered,” “refused,” or “other.” None of the correctional EHR reviewed included bar-coding capabilities. </p>
<p>The MAR software observed was flawed. The paper MAR of today is the result of many decades of evolution. Standard paper MARs show a whole month and display up to eight medications per sheet. These features are very helpful to pill call nurses and providers, who may assess a month of adherence to all medication at a glance. Other desirable features of paper MARs are the ability to display in each box the initials of the administering nurse or correctional officer and the ability to display, for each box, codes familiar to health care staff, such as A for Administered, R for Refused, O for Out of the institution, W for Wasted, S for Spit out, U for Unavailable, and so on. None of the electronic MARs reviewed incorporated all of the features described above.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1078345813486322">
<title>e-Prescribing</title>
<p>A correctional EHR should include e-prescribing, formulary and medication cost information, side effects and drug interactions, individual medication profiles and allergies, pharmacy inventory control, and provider prescriptive profiles.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: In noncorrectional medicine, e-prescribing is becoming mainstream, with providers benefiting from the e-prescribing power of PCs, laptops, tablets, or portable PDAs.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: e-prescribing technology should be adaptable to correctional medicine. However, structural barriers remain, such as prohibition of PDA use by staff in many penal institutions and paucity of signal in secure areas with thick walls.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-1078345813486322">
<title>Logging, Tracking, and Reporting</title>
<sec id="section21-1078345813486322">
<title>Callouts</title>
<p>The EHR system should be capable of generating recurrent inmate appointments or “callouts.”</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: EHRs should be capable of generating recurrent appointments or callouts for the performance of regularly scheduled clinical activities, such as annual physicals, tuberculosis skin tests, lab tests, chronic clinic visits, and age-dependent screening such as colonoscopy or mammography. These medical appointments should be relayed to security electronically or on paper.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: Integration between EHR-generated callouts and security allows advance planning aimed to escort the scheduled inmate-patient to the medical area in question while rescheduling other institutional inmate appointments, such as visitation, law library, chapel, or education, as needed. Callout capabilities varied widely in the EHR reviewed.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-1078345813486322">
<title>Chronic care</title>
<p>The EHR should be capable of producing lists of all chronic care patients at the facility, sorted by disease, with the ability to identify all patients with two, three, or more chronic diseases.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: A list of multiple chronic care patients allows providers to stay on top of the most difficult cases.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: During institutional surveys, NCCHC surveyors requested a list showing, in descending order, patients with the most chronic illnesses. None of the reviewed EHR was capable of retrieving patient names that way.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-1078345813486322">
<title>Interval from request to performance</title>
<p>The EHR system should be capable of generating aggregated tracking tables of intervals between inmate health service request, physician consultation request, lab or X-ray request, and ultimate performance.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: Intervals from request to performance of clinical activities should not exceed preset limits and should be continuously reviewed by health service administrators and senior clinicians with aim to eliminate stragglers and dropped requests. Interval between request and performance data should be presented in user-friendly tracking table format encompassing all involved inmates, without forcing the observer to open each individual patient EHR.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: Recurrent clinical activity screens should give the observer, at a glance, an idea on how many of these encounters are taking place within the allowed deadlines and how many are falling out of compliance. If out of compliance, a visit should be automatically rescheduled and tracked until completion.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-1078345813486322">
<title>Aggregated clinical activity reports</title>
<p>The EHR should create administrative reports such as number of monthly or yearly visits, consultations, laboratory or X-ray tests, ER visits, hospital bed days, and the like.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: Aggregated clinical activity data are important to anyone charged with health care administration duties. Such data should be created automatically. In addition to bulk data, the information should be easily sorted by provider, inmate location, dates, specific diseases, and other variables.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-1078345813486322">
<title>Processing lab, consultation, and X-ray reports</title>
<p>The EHR should track all received consultation, lab, or X-ray reports indicating when they were received and when they were electronically reviewed, initialed, and time-stamped by the involved providers.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: Clinical coordinators and administrators should be able to review aggregated data tracking all received consultation, lab, or X-ray reports indicating when they were received and when they were electronically reviewed, initialed, and time-stamped by the involved providers without resorting to opening many individual patients’ EHR.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: As a risk management strategy, it is important to ensure that all consultation, lab, and X-ray reports are promptly reviewed by the involved providers so as to make timely clinical decisions. The crafting of fail-safe methodology for lab and other reports entering the EHR to ensure timely review by providers is complex. </p>
<p>In some EHR reviewed, lab data streamed directly into the individual patient records, with the expectation that the information would reach the provider who ordered the tests. However, the ordering provider may be out sick or on vacation, or may have left the institution for good. If no one opened the involved record, no one would be aware that an abnormal, critical report had arrived, posing a serious patient safety issue. </p>
<p>Paper report management offers some clues regarding this workflow issue. Paper lab or other reports usually come to a health records specialist or a nurse who flags the abnormal results and finds or calls a provider responsible for patient clinical care. To ensure patient safety, EHR need to replicate these processes. In addition to the individual patient EHR, electronic lab and other reports should stream into computers at an office manned with qualified staff. These staff would read the incoming reports, flag abnormalities, and assign the responsibility for follow-up to available providers. Recently arrived, flagged reports should remain posted in the office computers until electronically countersigned by a responsible clinician. None of the EHR systems reviewed included these functions.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-1078345813486322">
<title>Miscellaneous Criteria</title>
<p>The following criteria were harder to classify and were grouped under “miscellaneous.”</p>
<sec id="section27-1078345813486322">
<title>No dual (paper plus EHR) records</title>
<p>The proposed EHR should eliminate the need for paper plus EHR records.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: After a transition period, all health records and reports such as consultations, lab, and X-ray data should be entered electronically so only one record (the EHR) is in use.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: Facilities employing EHR but failing to implement integration criteria as above described will need to use dual records indefinitely. Providers facing a confusing mixture of paper and electronic entries would have difficulty completing a thorough review. Clinical quality may suffer.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section28-1078345813486322">
<title>Minimization of workflow disruptions</title>
<p>The proposed EHR minimizes workflow disruptions.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: Workflow disruptions consume valuable staff time and may lead to serious clinical deficiencies.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: In paper-based correctional health care, workflow is frequently driven by physical transfer of pieces of paper. A paper document placed in someone’s in-box or into the person’s hands is a powerful, simple, and easily understood prompt or reminder that a task has been assigned and needs to be accomplished. In many EHR reviewed, there was no equivalent of these paper prompts. To replicate task-assigning prompts in EHR, it is necessary to craft electronic pathways for health care information to generate assignments to responsible health care workers. </p>
<p>Devising workflow for an incoming EHR is a daunting task. A proactive approach would be beta-testing, with aim to iron out the wrinkles before full implementation. </p>
<p>Brisk medical workflow (throughput) requires assigning a workstation to each provider. Roving laptops or tablet PCs (linked via wireless or under store-and-forward protocol) should be provided to all workers passing medication or performing other ministrations cellside. Sufficient bandwidth (data transfer speed) is critical. Some systems reviewed worked fine at 7 a.m. but slowed to a crawl by mid-morning, when all daytime health staff was online.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-1078345813486322">
<title>Allows easy customizing</title>
<p>The proposed EHR system should be easily customized by local staff.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: EHR customization should be achievable without resorting to costly programming time for minor modifications.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: Some correctional administrators believe that an EHR purchase is a one-time expenditure and do not budget for upgrades. However, anyone with experience with paper record systems knows that paper forms need continuous revisions. The same is true for EHR. Local staff customization should be helpful in keeping an EHR current.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section30-1078345813486322">
<title>Capable of well-laid-out printed output</title>
<p>The proposed EHR system should print well-laid-out records that resemble paper records in structure and content.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: Printing is needed to transfer health records to outside institutions with incompatible EHR or no EHR, to attorneys, and to other parties and is the only way a health record is presently acceptable to the courts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1078345813486322">Paris, 2009b</xref>).</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: In the past, some correctional EHR existed where little thought had been given to printouts. In some of these, each printed page contained a few lines of clinical text plus patient demographics and cryptic words like &lt;return&gt;, &lt;expand&gt;, and other computer terms. Encounter dates may be buried in inconspicuous spots. In the past few years, correctional EHR capable of generating readable printouts have emerged.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section31-1078345813486322">
<title>Generates “To-do” lists</title>
<p>The EHR system should be capable of integrating all clinical functions so each worker can generate a summary of all activities expected to be performed in a given day to stay in compliance.</p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Rationale: To-do lists are extremely useful to staff, who would use these for the planning of the workday, thus keeping up with workloads.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Discussion: Many EHR reviewed lacked to-do functionality. In correctional institutions, to-do tasks are created daily, such as for chronic care, sick call, lab draws, and other activities. The to-do lists should arrive electronically to a centralized office as described in the criteria for processing lab reports. Management personnel, such as a director of nursing or a clinical coordinator, would review daily the various to-do tasks and allocate workloads to available staff, verifying at the end of the day that all tasks have been accomplished or rescheduled.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section32-1078345813486322">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The EHR criteria listed here are not unattainable. Many of these criteria exist today in some systems. It should be feasible to incorporate all described criteria into an EHR. It is hoped that this article may help correctional health care administrators and providers to make informed choices regarding EHR.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section33-1078345813486322">
<title>The Future of Correctional EHR</title>
<p>Because of technological advances, in a few years it should be possible to display in EHR screens all images, such as X rays, MRIs, and computerized tomography, at the appropriate level of resolution. In addition to increased resolution, EHR displays will likely become larger so as to accommodate the simultaneous display of multiple record areas.</p>
<p>Because upright large, flat displays can be distracting during clinical encounters, these will probably be laid down on the providers’ desks, thus being read in the same position as the old paper charts. Bright flat displays can be tiring on the eyes. Nonluminous, matte displays like those in the Kindle<sup>®</sup> or other e-book readers may be preferred because they can be read for many hours without strain. As with iPhones and tablets, EHR flat displays may incorporate smart touch screens that allow virtual page turning with one’s fingers.</p>
<p>Refined correctional EHR systems with many enhancements are expected to emerge after a decade or more of furious competition with many vendors entering the marketplace. In the end, only a few systems may survive. These will become standard and should be interoperable. Interoperability will help materialize the dream of a universal portable EHR for all patients, in and out of corrections.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1078345813486322">
<label>Author’s Note</label>
<p>Parts of this article were presented at the National Conference on Correctional Health Care in Las Vegas, Nevada, on October 11, 2010.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn2-1078345813486322">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author disclosed no conflicts of interest with respect to the authorship and/or publication of this article. For information about <italic>JCHC</italic>’s disclosure policy, please see the Self-Study Program.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-1078345813486322">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1078345813486322">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Desroches</surname>
<given-names>C. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>E. G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rao</surname>
<given-names>S. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Donelan</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ferris</surname>
<given-names>T. G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jha</surname>
<given-names>A., </given-names>
</name>
</person-group>…<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname> Blumenthal</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Electronic health records in ambulatory care—A national survey of physicians</article-title>. <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>, <volume>359</volume>, <fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1078345813486322">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Greenberg</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ridgely</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Clinical decision support and malpractice risk</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source>, <volume>306</volume>, <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1078345813486322">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Paris</surname>
<given-names>J. E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009a</year>). <article-title>Electronic health records in correctional health care: A skeptical view</article-title>. <source>Correctional Health Care Report</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1078345813486322">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Paris</surname>
<given-names>J. E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009b</year>). <article-title>Going to court with an EHR</article-title>. <source>CorrectCare</source>, <volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1078345813486322">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Paris</surname>
<given-names>J. E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009c</year>). <article-title>The litmus test of electronic health record performance</article-title>. <source>CorrectCare</source>, <volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1078345813486322">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Radecki</surname>
<given-names>R. P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sittig</surname>
<given-names>D. F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Application of electronic health records to the Joint Commission 2011 National Patient Safety Goals</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source>, <volume>306</volume>, <fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1078345813486322">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schiff</surname>
<given-names>G. D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bates</surname>
<given-names>D. W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Can electronic clinical documentation help prevent diagnostic errors?</article-title> <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>, <volume>362</volume>, <fpage>1066</fpage>–<lpage>1069</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1078345813486322">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sittig</surname>
<given-names>D. F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ash</surname>
<given-names>J. F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Osheroff</surname>
<given-names>J. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shabot</surname>
<given-names>M. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Lessons from “Unexpected increased mortality after implementation of a commercially sold computerized physician order entry system.”</article-title> <source>Pediatrics</source>, <volume>118</volume>, <fpage>797</fpage>–<lpage>801</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1078345813486322">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sittig</surname>
<given-names>D. F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Classen</surname>
<given-names>D. C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Safe electronic health record use requires a comprehensive monitoring and evaluation framework</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source>, <volume>303</volume>, <fpage>450</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>