<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="other" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CTX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spctx</journal-id>
<journal-title>Contexts</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1536-5042</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1537-6052</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1536504212447925</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1536504212447925</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Features</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Viewpoints</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Understanding “Occupy”</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>14</fpage>
<lpage>16</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 American Sociological Association</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<kwd-group>
  <kwd>Benjamin Barber</kwd>
<kwd>Occupy Wall Street</kwd>
<kwd>social movements</kwd>
<kwd>anarchism</kwd>
<kwd>consensus</kwd>
<kwd>militancy</kwd>
<kwd>public rhetoric</kwd>
<kwd>rising inequality</kwd>
<kwd>equalizing insitutions</kwd>
<kwd>emotion</kwd>
<kwd>world-making</kwd>
<kwd>political desire</kwd>
<kwd>prefiguration</kwd>
<kwd>global culture</kwd>
<kwd>democracy</kwd>
<kwd>protest</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta xlink:type="simple">
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>Spring 2012</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<sub-article article-type="other" id="sub1-1536504212447925" xml:lang="EN">
<front-stub>
<title-group>
<article-title>What Democracy Looks Like</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1536504212447925">Benjamin Barber is Walt Whitman Professor of Political Science Emeritus at Rutgers University and founder and president of the Interdependence Movement. He is the author of the forthcoming book <italic>If Mayors Ruled the World</italic>.</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</front-stub>
<body>
<p>In a nation fed up with predatory banks, and disturbed by the irresponsibility of politicians, the Occupy Wall Street movement was a revelation. It announced two truths: that America is deeply divided—with up to 99 percent of the population dominated economically by 1 percent, and that our democracy is in deep crisis.</p>
<p>In this Presidential election year, when the two parties are drawing further apart, it may be the decisions that OWS makes about national politics and participation in the elections that determine the future of our nation. For above all, OWS, like the Tea Party, is channeling anger at inequality and injustice. More like philosopher Jean-Jacques Rousseau than the Tea Party, however, OWS turns anger to constructive civic purposes. It distrusts the patter of politicians about democracy as one more transparent attempt to “throw garlands of flowers over our chains.” To be authentic, democracy must be palpable, participatory, local—like Occupy Wall Street itself.</p>
<p>If the myriad and varied denizens of this profoundly democratic movement decide to manifest their convictions politically and take a stand at the polls, they will contribute to revivifying democracy. If they withdraw from politics, and sit the election out while insisting that the differences between the parties and candidates are marginal and the similarities overwhelming, our democracy will be even worse off—whoever triumphs in the polls.</p>
<p>Understanding what OWS is as a political movement is therefore crucial. OWS certainly has an inclination to political commitment; but it also is skeptical about the political realm. OWS dismisses American democracy as a fraud—and sees politicians as just as corrupt and wayward as the bankers and corporate CEOs who have been buying them. At the same time, it holds up its own existence as a model of “what democracy looks like.”</p>
<p>To be sure, the occupiers, with their multi-hued cornucopia of perspectives, are a diverse lot. The many encampments embrace a panoply of causes, and contain tensions and fissures the protesters themselves acknowledge and even welcome. OWS has become a vessel into which people pour their own fears and aspirations. That is not to say there is no unifying theme. It’s “Occupy Wall Street” not “Occupy the Times Square military recruiting station” or “Occupy Gracie Mansion.” It’s about the MONEY, stupid—the money that replaces votes (the people) with dollars (the plutocracy). Money, OWS recognizes, has unraveled the social contract. The occupiers may not have demands, but they do have an agenda. It is their powerful process that speaks to their principles.</p>
<p>Their process is a bold attempt to embody an alternative paradigm of participatory engagement, suggesting that the protesters, so cynical about democracy, have figured out how to practice it. What the process offers is a compelling rejection of the <italic>instrumentalism</italic> so beloved of American politicians—“the end justifies the means.” President Obama has to raise funds from big-time bundlers and lobbyists (despite his pledge not to do so)—how else can he get reelected? Off-shore drilling may risk cataclysmic environmental disaster but we need the jobs and independence from foreign oil. The protesters’ principles, in contrast, are in their processes, and the processes are quite remarkable—not only for the contrast they offer to how we normally conduct business, but for how well they actually work.</p>
<p>The key process requires that all decisions—whether about tactics or money expended, or principles or changes in structure—be submitted to the General Assembly (GA), which then convenes almost every day and is the source of the movement’s “general will,” and its legitimacy. The GA’s process is maddeningly open, transparent, and changing.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1536504212447925" position="float">
<caption>
<p>Occupying Wall Street</p>
<p>&lt;&lt; A series of photographs by Accra Shepp On September 30, 2011, Shepp went to Zuccotti Park to investigate the protest. “The diversity of the participants and the range of their activities was so great,” he says, that he wanted “to consider each protester as an individual.” Here are some of the photographs he took over the course of several months.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_1536504212447925-fig1.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Moreover, and here is the both the glory and the peril of the process, decisions are taken by consensus. Not a majority, but consensus. Consensus must be realized in an evolving constituency in successive meetings where full legitimacy comes only after every amendment is considered, every point of process and every concern is put “on stack” and aired; and where—most tellingly—every voice has to be heard, including those of participants so offended by a proposal that they respond with a “block”—signified by arms crossed in an X. Blocks must be registered, responded to and overcome (or not) if consensus is to prevail. This requires patience and tolerance. And a great deal of talk, debate and deliberation.</p>
<disp-quote>
<p>OWS has become a vessel into which people pour their own fears and aspirations.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>Cynics on the right dismiss OWS as a bunch of crazies and collectivists, but I know of no democratic process so attuned to the autonomy and rights of individuals. Indeed, one of the serendipitous features of the process is the “people’s microphone”—an innovation necessitated by the refusal of the city to allow electronic voice amplification. With crowds of several hundred or more at the GA, individual voices cannot be heard, so speakers voice their concerns in snippets that are repeated by the crowd at least once, and sometimes twice, in an expanding circle.</p>
<p>The “people’s microphone” is a clumsy process that makes complex and nuanced speech difficult. But it forces relatively straightforward speech that enhances clarity and communication; and it requires that in dealing with naysayers and “blocks,” the majority must mouth and voice the actual words of those who disagree. How better to kindle sympathy for minority voices than for their majority opponents to rehearse their protests, word for word, and even mimic their affect? How fitting that a movement wedded to moral protest should be attuned to protests from within.</p>
<graphic alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_1536504212447925-fig2.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
<p>OWS may be naive and exasperating in its refusal to engage in ordinary politics and its initial disdain for voting, especially in this primary silly season where it is apparent how much is at stake. Yet the occupiers know that American anger, right and left, runs deeper; that there is something intrinsically wrong with how we do business. It has impaired leadership and undermined democracy.</p>
<p>Democracy itself is in deep trouble, and so America is in trouble. Occupy Wall Street speaks as our civic conscience. We need the angry deputies of the “99” in politics this year. But we cannot demand that they become more like us. We must become more like them.</p>
<graphic alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_1536504212447925-fig3.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
</body>
</sub-article>
</article>