<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ESP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spesp</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of European Social Policy</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0958-9287</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7269</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0958928711425268</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0958928711425268</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Doctoral Researcher Prize</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Mass political polarization and attitudes towards education as part of the welfare state in Norway, Sweden and Finland</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Fladmoe</surname><given-names>Audun</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0958928711425268">NTNU, Norway</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0958928711425268">Audun Fladmoe, Department of Sociology and Political Science/Multi-Disciplinary Research School in Educational Research, SVT, NTNU, Trondheim, Norway. Email: <email>audun.fladmoe@svt.ntnu.no</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>22</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>45</fpage>
<lpage>62</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The education systems of the Nordic countries have long been regarded as integral parts of the welfare state. The argument here is that this welfare dimension is ideologically controversial at the elite level, and that recent trends in international academic assessments may have intensified a conflict between the academic and welfare dimensions in education. Two central aspects of the welfare dimension are explored through survey evidence from Norway, Sweden and Finland: (1) the ability of schools to integrate all children, independent of social background, and (2) the extent to which schools should focus on teaching social skills as opposed to academic skills. The results generally support the argument. Mass political polarization is evident in all three countries. Sympathizers of left-wing parties express higher expectations concerning the welfare dimension in education, and are more inclined to support a focus on social skills in schools.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>education</kwd>
<kwd>Nordic welfare state</kwd>
<kwd>political polarization</kwd>
<kwd>public opinion</kwd>
<kwd>survey analysis</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In this article attitudes towards education as part of the welfare state in Norway, Sweden and Finland are explored: the core question is whether attitudes are polarized according to party sympathy. In addition to the teaching of academic skills, the comprehensive schools of the Nordic countries have several functions including a focus on nation building and the teaching of democratic civic skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0958928711425268">Ahonen and Rantala, 2001</xref>). The education systems have been regarded as an integral part of the welfare state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0958928711425268">Arnesen and Lundahl, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0958928711425268">Telhaug et al., 2006</xref>). Schools have been predominantly owned by the state/municipalities,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0958928711425268">1</xref></sup> with obligatory attendance and comprehensive curricula. The political ambition has been to integrate all children, independent of social background, into a common system. In this article I refer to the focus on social integration and social skills in educational institutions as a ‘welfare dimension’.</p>
<p>Anti-welfare sentiments have been modest in the Nordic countries, and consequently a popular view is that the welfare state is associated with political consensus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0958928711425268">Sejersted, 2005</xref>). Party competition on welfare issues is often characterized by <italic>valence</italic>, meaning that party positions do not diverge significantly on ideological grounds and that parties rather compete in appearing as the most trustworthy in pursuing policies with broad consensus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0958928711425268">Bjørklund and Saglie, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0958928711425268">Söderlund, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0958928711425268">Stokes, 1963</xref>). In this article I argue that the welfare dimension in education represents an ideological cleavage, and that party competition on this dimension is an example of <italic>position</italic> politics where the parties diverge on ideological grounds (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0958928711425268">Stokes, 1963</xref>). This ideological cleavage is largely associated with the relation between the education system and the welfare state.</p>
<p>The political left has been the strongest proponent of compulsory and comprehensive state schools, while the political right has been the strongest proponent of parental freedom of choice and private schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0958928711425268">Telhaug et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0958928711425268">Tuastad, 2008</xref>). Moreover, there is reason to believe that recent educational debate, with its increased focus on academic achievement tests (for example, PISA, TIMSS, PIRLS<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0958928711425268">2</xref></sup>), highlights a contradiction between the academic and welfare dimensions. According to some, these tests represent a ‘neoliberal’ trend focusing on education as a means for economic prosperity, downplaying the welfare dimension in education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0958928711425268">Arnesen and Lundahl, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0958928711425268">Biesta, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0958928711425268">Christie, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0958928711425268">Telhaug et al., 2006</xref>). Assuming this to be true, it is important to gain an understanding of public attitudes on this dimension: are the populations in Norway, Sweden and Finland characterized by polarization or consensus?</p>
<p>Previous research exploring attitudes towards education as part of the welfare state is limited. Exceptions include election studies, where education as a political issue tends to be highlighted (for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0958928711425268">Hedberg, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0958928711425268">Karlsen and Aardal, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0958928711425268">Pesonen, 2004</xref>). However, these studies are usually nationally oriented, and are seldom related to the various dimensions of the education system. As part of an international comparative survey project (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0958928711425268">Strabac and Aalberg, 2009</xref>), a range of relevant questions were included. These address respondents’ perceptions as to whether the education system is able to integrate all children independent of social background, and, moreover, their support for schools to focus on social skills as opposed to academic skills. The empirical results suggest that there is a recognizable left–right polarization where sympathizers of left-wing parties have greatest expectations concerning the welfare dimension and are most inclined to support a focus on social skills in schools.</p>
<sec id="section1-0958928711425268">
<title>Welfare attitudes</title>
<p>Although there are few studies investigating attitudes towards education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0958928711425268">Elstad, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0958928711425268">Hedberg, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0958928711425268">Karlsen and Aardal, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0958928711425268">Pesonen, 2004</xref>), literature on attitudes towards the welfare state (in which the Nordic education systems are nested) is more common (for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0958928711425268">Andress and Heien, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0958928711425268">Blekesaune, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0958928711425268">Blekesaune and Quadagno, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0958928711425268">Edlund, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0958928711425268">Ervasti et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0958928711425268">Jakobsen, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0958928711425268">Jæger, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0958928711425268">Kumlin, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0958928711425268">Svallfors, 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0958928711425268">2007</xref>). Scholars have traditionally explained support for the welfare state as including (at least) two components: rational self-interest and ideology (for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0958928711425268">Andress and Heien, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0958928711425268">Blekesaune and Quadagno, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0958928711425268">Hasenfeld and Rafferty, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0958928711425268">Jæger, 2006</xref>). The focus in this article is on the ideological component, but a brief note on the rational self-interest tradition may be made. Rational theory in studies of welfare attitudes anticipate public support for welfare to be strongest among those who benefit most from social welfare, and weakest among those who benefit least. Hence, in the vocabulary of social stratification, members of the lower strata in society are expected to support social welfare policies more than those in the upper strata. Empirically this is typically studied through socio-demographic characteristics such as age, gender, income and social class (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0958928711425268">Blekesaune and Quadagno, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0958928711425268">Hasenfeld and Rafferty, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0958928711425268">Jæger, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0958928711425268">Svallfors, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>The ideological component concerns fundamental beliefs and values of ‘what is just’ and the role of government in promoting social justice. A theoretical distinction has been proposed between economic individualism/work ethic (the political right) and social equality/collective responsibility (the political left) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0958928711425268">Hasenfeld and Rafferty, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0958928711425268">McClosky and Zaller, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0958928711425268">Wilensky, 1975</xref>). In its ideal type, the political right argues that economic success is a function of hard work and thrift, and that individuals are responsible for their own welfare. Conversely, the political left argues that governments have a key role in providing equal opportunity, and to ensure acceptable standards of living for all citizens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0958928711425268">Hasenfeld and Rafferty, 1989</xref>). The actual landscape of party politics is obviously more complex, especially in European countries with multiparty systems (for example where both the political left and right comprise several parties, and where there are separate parties in the political centre (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0958928711425268">van Oorschot, 2010</xref>: 19)). Individuals in different countries also interact with different value systems. Some countries are politically more to the left (or right) than others, and welfare attitudes are likely to be adjusted according to the current set-up of the welfare state. For example, by living in comprehensive welfare states the average Nordic citizen has expectedly become more positive towards public welfare schemes than the average US citizen (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0958928711425268">Jakobsen, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0958928711425268">Listhaug and Aalberg, 1999</xref>). For the purpose of this article, however, the left–right distinction is useful as a theoretical construct.</p>
<p>Making a sharp distinction between self-interest and ideology is theoretically questionable as individuals’ ideological considerations are possibly linked to their self-interest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0958928711425268">Hasenfeld and Rafferty, 1989</xref>). For instance, it is reasonable to believe that some supporters of the welfare state have become ideologically supportive because they benefit from social welfare. The distinction nevertheless makes sense empirically because both factors can contribute independently in explaining welfare attitudes. Although the ideological dimension is emphasized in this study, controls for rational self-interest are included in the statistical analyses.</p>
<sec id="section2-0958928711425268">
<title>Ideological cleavages and the politics of education</title>
<p>The ideological component discussed above can be identified in the politics of education. In a discussion of common denominators of a ‘Nordic model of education’, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0958928711425268">Arnesen and Lundahl (2006)</xref> identify a tension between what they call ‘social democratic’ and ‘liberal/specialist’ policy patterns in all the Nordic countries (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0958928711425268">Antikainen, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0958928711425268">Telhaug et al., 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0958928711425268">2006</xref>). The welfare dimension is one central aspect of social democratic policy patterns. These policies are associated with a strong emphasis on the social/cultural functions of education, universalism and the central state as main actor (state schools). Liberal/specialist education policies are associated with a strong emphasis on the economic functions of education, particularism and pluralism of relevant actors (for example, more leeway for private schools) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0958928711425268">Arnesen and Lundahl, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>In an empirical study of how different left–right cleavages are manifested in Norwegian party politics, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0958928711425268">Tuastad (2008)</xref> identifies a pattern similar to that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0958928711425268">Arnesen and Lundahl (2006)</xref>. Based on extensive empirical material of educational political debates in the Norwegian parliament and in party programmes, he finds a relatively consistent trend through 60 years, resembling the ideological component. The political left argues that justice and equal opportunities for all children are best achieved within a publicly owned and comprehensive ‘common school’ (social democratic policy patterns), because children will then be equally empowered to make choices in the future. The political right argues that parental freedom is more important than politics (liberal policy patterns); parents should be able to choose education for their children (that is, more leeway for private schools).</p>
<p>This cleavage between social democratic (left) and liberal/specialist (right) policy patterns is relevant because it suggests that relative support for a strong link between education and the welfare state, and hence support for the welfare dimension in education is stronger among left-wing parties. The question remains, however, whether this actually is an issue of political polarization among citizens: are citizens ideologically and politically aware of these issues at all? This question relates to the <italic>degree</italic> of mass polarization.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0958928711425268">
<title>The degree of political polarization in the politics of education</title>
<p>In the literature there is some disagreement concerning the degree of political polarization with regard to the Nordic welfare states. In brief, some scholars have highlighted political struggles and conflict while others have highlighted ‘class compromise’ – that is pragmatism and broad political support. While none of these studies reject political polarization per se (for example, compromises are often the results of initial political conflict), this literature can further our understanding of the possible degree of mass polarization – and therefore offer explanations for a possible lack of polarization.</p>
<p>The arguments supporting the research hypothesis (mass polarization) are associated with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0958928711425268">Korpi’s (1983)</xref> ‘power resources’ argument, which is a conflict perspective on the development of welfare states. Korpi argued that variations in welfare states could be characterized according to the level of organization and unity among members of the working class. The Nordic welfare states became universal and comprehensive because the working class overcame its collective action problems and united in common unions and (social democratic) parties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0958928711425268">Korpi, 1983</xref>). A similar argument was offered by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0958928711425268">Esping-Andersen (1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0958928711425268">1990</xref>) when emphasizing the social democratic, as opposed to liberal and conservative ideology of the Nordic welfare states. This left–right polarization is also evident in the education policy patterns described above where social democratic policies are associated with social/cultural functions of education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0958928711425268">Arnesen and Lundahl, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0958928711425268">Telhaug et al., 2006</xref>). Conservative parties were initially sceptical about the comprehensive school model and advocated a more ‘neoliberal’ education philosophy – where schools should focus mainly on basic academic skills as a foundation for later economic success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0958928711425268">Arnesen and Lundahl, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0958928711425268">Telhaug et al., 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>On the other hand, there are also sound arguments opposing such a conflict perspective. Education free-of-charge for all segments of society has received broad political support in the Nordic countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0958928711425268">Aasen, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0958928711425268">Ahonen, 2002</xref>). This is in line with perspectives of the Nordic welfare states as the product of cross-class compromise (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0958928711425268">Sejersted, 2005</xref>). Political conflict has been comparatively modest in the Nordic countries, and strong anti-welfare opposition has been historically weak. Parties throughout the entire left–right spectrum have in general supported the welfare state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0958928711425268">Sejersted, 2005</xref>). Moreover, it may also be the case that citizens are less polarized than political elites. Empirical studies have shown that voters are generally more moderate than party elites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0958928711425268">Valen and Narud, 2007</xref>). Finally, other studies have revealed high levels of political trust and social capital in the Nordic countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0958928711425268">Fridberg and Kangas, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0958928711425268">Listhaug and Ringdal, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0958928711425268">Listhaug and Wiberg, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0958928711425268">Milner, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0958928711425268">Rothstein and Stolle, 2003</xref>), suggesting low levels of conflict and high levels of political consensus.</p>
<p>Both kinds of argument seem valid depending upon which aspect of the welfare state is studied. The argument here is that the welfare dimension in education is likely to represent an ideological cleavage, and thus an example of <italic>position</italic> politics (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0958928711425268">Stokes, 1963</xref>). To regard education as an integrated part of the welfare state is controversial, and the left–right ideological distinction elaborated on above is likely to be manifested among citizens.</p>
<p>Further, recent focus on international academic assessments in popular debates (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0958928711425268">Elstad and Sivesind, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0958928711425268">Grek, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0958928711425268">Välijärvi et al., 2002</xref>) highlights the tension between the academic and welfare dimensions in education. In Norway and Sweden – where pupils have performed below national expectations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0958928711425268">Carlgren, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0958928711425268">Christie, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0958928711425268">Elstad and Sivesind, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0958928711425268">Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development, 2009</xref>) – the welfare dimension can face limited legitimacy among certain segments of the population if it is perceived to undermine the academic dimension. Finland performs well on academic tests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0958928711425268">Rautalin and Alasuutari, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0958928711425268">Välijärvi et al., 2002</xref>) but has faced comparatively (in Nordic terms) more social and economic challenges since the early 1990s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0958928711425268">Castells and Himanen, 2002</xref>). This can lead certain segments of the population to urge for a stronger focus on the welfare dimension.</p>
<p>In summary, the welfare dimension in education is expected to be more strongly associated with sympathy for left political parties. Left partisans will advocate most strongly a comprehensive education system where all children, independent of social background, are equally integrated. Moreover, left partisans will be those who are most likely to support a focus on social skills in schools at the expense of academic skills. Against this background the following hypotheses are proposed:</p>
<list id="list1-0958928711425268" list-type="simple"><list-item><p>H1: Sympathizers of left-wing parties have the highest expectations concerning the ability of the education system to integrate all children equally.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>H2: Sympathizers of left-wing parties show strongest support for focusing on social skills – as opposed to academic skills – in schools.</p></list-item></list>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0958928711425268" sec-type="methods">
<title>Data and methods</title>
<p>Data on attitudes towards the welfare dimension in education in Norway, Sweden and Finland were sampled as part of a larger comparative survey project (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0958928711425268">Strabac and Aalberg, 2009</xref>). Representative samples were interviewed by YouGov<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0958928711425268">3</xref></sup> using internet questionnaires in the three countries. The sampling procedure in each country consisted of drawing panels of pools of respondents who had agreed to participate in web surveys. With large databases of potential respondents, samples were drawn from these pools by applying a matching algorithm – estimating a random sample based on the Norwegian, Swedish and Finnish populations. Based upon socio-demographic characteristics, 1200 individuals were interviewed in each country. In a second step, the sample was re-matched with the target populations and downscaled to a best fit of 1000 individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0958928711425268">Strabac and Aalberg, 2009</xref>). Internet surveys are a relatively new tool in the social sciences and may face methodological challenges. As part of the larger project, additional telephone surveys with a replication of some key questions were commenced with representative samples in Norway and in the US. Comparative analyses of the web and telephone surveys reveal that variations in the distribution of answers were minimal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0958928711425268">Strabac and Aalberg, 2011</xref>). Further, weighting variables were constructed by YouGov – and applied in the analyses – as to rule out the remaining differences in socio-demographic characteristics between the sample and the populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0958928711425268">Strabac and Aalberg, 2009</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0958928711425268">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>To address H1, <italic>sympathizers of left-wing parties have the highest expectations concerning the ability of the education system to integrate all children equally</italic>, five questions are analysed. First respondents were asked whether they believed that (1) society and (2) the education system ‘takes good care of all children’. By comparing the responses to these questions I explore whether my argument that although there might be widespread consensus concerning the welfare state, the welfare dimension in education is associated with polarization. Moreover, citizens in different countries express opinions and evaluations in different social contexts (value systems), and it is therefore problematic to compare countries employing only absolute figures (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0958928711425268">Jakobsen, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0958928711425268">Listhaug and Aalberg, 1999</xref>). By introducing a baseline variable (‘society’) it is also possible to make comparisons within countries and one can get a grip on the relative standing of the education system as a welfare institution. General questions might be interpreted differently by different respondents. Some might think of other dimensions when responding to ‘takes good care of all children’. Therefore three more specific questions addressing whether the education favours certain social groups are also analysed: (1) ‘Children growing up in a family with an academic background’, (2) ‘Girls’ and (3) ‘Children with an ethnic [Norwegian/Swedish/Finnish] family background’. Responses to all five questions were registered on a 1 (strongly disagree) to 5 (strongly agree) Likert scale.</p>
<p>To address H2, <italic>sympathizers of left-wing parties show strongest support for focusing on social skills – as opposed to academic skills – in schools</italic>, a question where respondents were asked what the ‘primary challenge’ was for their national education system are analysed. Upon answering respondents had to choose on a scale a number between 0 (schools should focus more on educating foundational skills, that is, reading, mathematics and nature science) and 10 (schools should focus more on providing good social skills for all children). The aim of this question was to tap into a potential ‘conflict’ between the academic and welfare dimension which some argue has appeared in popular debates in the aftermath of international assessments (such as the PISA tests) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0958928711425268">Biesta, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0958928711425268">Christie, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>The main determinant, party attachment (Party ID), was measured by asking whether the respondent felt closer to a particular party than all other parties, and if so, which party. The responses were coded into three categories: ‘Party ID: Left parties’, ‘Party ID: Centre parties’ and ‘Party ID: Right parties’. Those choosing socialist, social democratic or green parties have been collapsed into the Left category; those choosing agrarian, liberal, Christian, and other such parties have been collapsed into the Centre category; while those choosing conservative or populist parties have been collapsed into the Right category. Respondents not choosing a party have been collapsed into the category ‘No Party ID’. Comparing party ID between countries is challenging, but is possible when this is restricted to the Nordic countries since their party systems are fairly similar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0958928711425268">Heidar, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0958928711425268">Petersson, 2005</xref>) and as most of the parties cooperate formally across national boundaries.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0958928711425268">5</xref></sup> Initial analyses revealed that treating parties separately did not change the results substantially. One advantage of using party ID is that it theoretically distinguishes between more and less ideologically conscious citizens. On average, those who indicate sympathy towards a particular party are probably more ideologically aware than those not possessing any particular party identification.</p>
<p>I include a range of control variables. First, it is reasonable to believe that there is a relationship between the two hypotheses – that is, expectations on behalf of the welfare dimension in education are likely to be associated with preferences for social/academic skills in schools. When addressing H1, I therefore include the variable ‘preference for social/academic skills’ as a control, and vice versa when addressing H2. Second, I control for rational self-interest (socio-demographic characteristics). Third, I control for media use and political awareness. These dimensions are important because they highlight variation according to the supply of political information and how that information is processed among individuals (for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0958928711425268">Converse, 1964</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0958928711425268">Laycock, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0958928711425268">Milner, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0958928711425268">Zaller, 1992</xref>).</p>
<p>All values on the variables are coded to vary between 0–1 [0.1–0.9] in the equations. Descriptive statistics as well as information on control variables are presented in the <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0958928711425268">appendix</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0958928711425268" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>I begin this section by exploring aggregated statistics. In the second part, statistical tests are undertaken in order to investigate the extent to which welfare attitudes are explained by party attachment when other relevant variables are included in the equations.</p>
<p>How do Nordic citizens evaluate the welfare dimension in education? In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0958928711425268">Figure 1</xref>, I compare public evaluations of whether (1) society and (2) the education system takes good care of all children. Negative answers (disagreeing that society/education systems take good care of all children) have been subtracted from positive answers (agreeing that society/education systems take good care of all children).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0958928711425268" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>All children are taken good care of by … . Positive minus negative responses in percent of total.</p>
<p><italic>Note</italic>: c<sup>2</sup> = 1874.71, df = 2, p&lt;0.01.</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0958928711425268">Strabac and Aalberg (2009)</xref>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0958928711425268-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>Finns are most inclined to believe that the education system takes good care of all children. The bars in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0958928711425268">Figure 1</xref> illustrate why it was useful to include a ‘baseline’ question (‘society’). In all countries there is a tendency of more critical (negative) perceptions of children’s welfare in society than in the education system. Norwegians are most inclined to believe that society is taking good care of all children. While both Norwegians and Swedes perceive the education system more positively than society, this difference is more pronounced in Finland. This suggests that the education system is perceived as a relatively unique institution in the Finnish welfare state.</p>
<p>To get a better grasp of the welfare dimension, the survey also included three specific questions addressing whether the education system favours various groups of pupils: (1) ‘Children growing up in a family with an academic background’, (2) ‘Girls’ and (3) ‘Children with an ethnic [Norwegian/Swedish/Finnish] family background’. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0958928711425268">Figure 2</xref> presents aggregated responses to these questions (strongly and somewhat (dis)agree collapsed).</p>
<fig id="fig2-0958928711425268" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>The education system favours … .</p>
<p><italic>Notes</italic>: a: c<sup>2</sup> = 22.58, df = 4, p &lt; 0.01; b: c<sup>2</sup> = 150.62, df = 4, p &lt; 0.01; c: c<sup>2</sup> = 66.15, df = 4, p&lt;0.01.</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0958928711425268">Strabac and Aalberg (2009)</xref>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0958928711425268-fig2.tif"/></fig>
<p>The bars in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0958928711425268">Figure 2a</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0958928711425268">c</xref> are interesting as they deviate from those in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0958928711425268">Figure 1</xref>. On all three questions Finns have the highest number of respondents agreeing that the education system favours certain social groups at the expense of others. However, the number of Finns disagreeing do not deviate much from the Norwegian and Swedish respondents, simply because Finns are least likely to answer ‘neither/nor’. This suggests higher levels of polarization among Finns over these evaluative aspects. The relatively high level of ‘neither/nor’ answers in Norway and Sweden indicate either that these questions are less salient in the public sphere, or that citizens are more ambivalent concerning these issues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0958928711425268">Clements and Bartle, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>When Finns are asked more specific questions related to the welfare dimension they become more critical. What could be the reason for this? One explanation is that Finns have a general positive view of their education system, that the general question opens up for too much interpretation, and that more specific questions are therefore needed to reveal polarization on the welfare dimension. This explanation is not possible to investigate directly by the data. Rather, the data can tell us <italic>who</italic> expresses more critical evaluations on the specific questions. This is analysed below.</p>
<p>The somewhat mixed results concerning public evaluations make it interesting to explore how these findings are related to the possible tension between social and academic skills in schools. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0958928711425268">Figure 3</xref> illustrates the distribution of answers to the question whether the education system should focus more on academic or social skills (0–4 collapsed into academic skills, 5 into neutral, 6–10 into social skills).</p>
<fig id="fig3-0958928711425268" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Policy preference: schools should focus more on … .</p>
<p><italic>Note</italic>: c<sup>2</sup> = 145.81, df = 4, p&lt;0.01.</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0958928711425268">Strabac and Aalberg (2009)</xref>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0958928711425268-fig3.tif"/></fig>
<p>While 67 percent of Norwegians and 62 percent of Swedish respondents prefer more focus on academic skills in school, only 47 percent of Finns do so; 12 percent and 14 percent in Norway and Sweden respectively support more focus on social skills, while 31 percent of Finns do so (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0958928711425268">Figure 3</xref>). Thus, most respondents in all three countries prefer more focus on academic skills, but the distribution is close to even in Finland. These country differences are interesting in light of the discussion above concerning results on academic achievement tests and social challenges in society. On academic tests Finland is a top-performer while Norway and Sweden are mediocre performers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0958928711425268">Lie et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0958928711425268">Matti, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0958928711425268">Mejding and Roe, 2006</xref>; Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Developement, 2009), and these tests gain attention in public debates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0958928711425268">Carlgren, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0958928711425268">Christie, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0958928711425268">Elstad and Sivesind, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0958928711425268">Grek, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0958928711425268">Rautalin and Alasuutari, 2009</xref>). On the other hand, in Nordic terms Finland has faced comparatively more social and economic challenges in recent decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0958928711425268">Castells and Himanen, 2002</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section6-0958928711425268">
<title>Welfare attitudes and mass polarization</title>
<p>As illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0958928711425268">Figures 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0958928711425268">3</xref>, attitudes are measured by different evaluations of the performance of the welfare dimension and policy preferences (academic vs social). The effect of party attachment on these six measures is summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0958928711425268">Tables 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0958928711425268">3</xref>. The tables report the effect of the target variable (party attachment) when controlling for a range of variables measuring welfare attitudes, socio-demographic characteristics, media use and political awareness.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0958928711425268" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Norway: The effect of party attachment on attitudes towards the welfare dimension in education (ordinary least squares [OLS] regressions)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0958928711425268" xlink:href="10.1177_0958928711425268-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Society takes good care of all children</th>
<th align="left">Education system takes good care of all children</th>
<th align="left">Education system favours children growing up in a family with an academic background</th>
<th align="left">Education system favours girls</th>
<th align="left">Education system favours children with an ethnic Norwegian family background</th>
<th align="left">Preference for social skills in schools</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">(model 1)</th>
<th align="left">(model 2)</th>
<th align="left">(model 3)</th>
<th align="left">(model 4)</th>
<th align="left">(model 5)</th>
<th align="left">(model 6)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Party ID: Centre parties<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0958928711425268">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.056<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>0.064<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.065<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.086<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.007</td>
<td>−0.086<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Party ID: Right parties<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0958928711425268">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.017</td>
<td>0.051<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.091<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>−0.041<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.107<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No Party ID:<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0958928711425268">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.0004</td>
<td>0.044<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.071<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>0.007</td>
<td>−0.039<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.041<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Preference for social skills</td>
<td>0.055</td>
<td>0.073<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.045</td>
<td>0.034</td>
<td>0.084<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td align="center">–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Society takes good care of all children</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td>0.048</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Education system takes good care of all children</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td>0.086</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Female</td>
<td>−0.053<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.022</td>
<td>−0.023</td>
<td>−0.073<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>0.004</td>
<td>0.014</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25–34 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.017</td>
<td>−0.040</td>
<td>0.014</td>
<td>−0.016</td>
<td>0.040</td>
<td>0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>35–44 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>−0.033</td>
<td>0.024</td>
<td>−0.034</td>
<td>−0.006</td>
<td>−0.018</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45–54 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.021</td>
<td>−0.021</td>
<td>0.028</td>
<td>−0.014</td>
<td>0.028</td>
<td>−0.030</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>55–64 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.010</td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>0.005</td>
<td>−0.068<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.018</td>
<td>−0.072<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>≥65 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.009</td>
<td>0.028</td>
<td>0.018</td>
<td>−0.037</td>
<td>0.011</td>
<td>−0.039</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>High school<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0958928711425268">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.020</td>
<td>0.033</td>
<td>−0.059<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.010</td>
<td>0.004</td>
<td>0.032</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>University etc.</td>
<td>−0.004</td>
<td>0.028</td>
<td>−0.038</td>
<td>−0.001</td>
<td>0.009</td>
<td>0.038</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>News exposure (PBS)</td>
<td>−0.021<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>−0.033</td>
<td>−0.001</td>
<td>0.053<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>−0.007</td>
<td>−0.044</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>News exposure (commercial TV)</td>
<td>−0.024</td>
<td>0.047</td>
<td>0.002</td>
<td>−0.051<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>−0.016</td>
<td>−0.064<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Newspaper exposure</td>
<td>0.044</td>
<td>0.039</td>
<td>−0.010</td>
<td>−0.008</td>
<td>0.028</td>
<td>−0.035</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Identification of PISA</td>
<td>−0.008</td>
<td>−0.012</td>
<td>−0.002</td>
<td>−0.003</td>
<td>0.022</td>
<td>−0.022</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Political trust</td>
<td>0.155<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>0.098<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.094<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.085<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.079<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.035</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>High political interest<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0958928711425268">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.055</td>
<td>−0.012</td>
<td>0.006</td>
<td>0.016</td>
<td>−0.018</td>
<td>−0.014</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Medium political interest<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0958928711425268">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.038<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.028</td>
<td>0.014</td>
<td>0.029<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>0.013</td>
<td>−0.006</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Politics complicated</td>
<td>−0.097<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.068</td>
<td>0.039</td>
<td>−0.019</td>
<td>0.030</td>
<td>0.160<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>0.468</td>
<td>−0.033</td>
<td>−0.001</td>
<td>0.053<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>−0.007</td>
<td>0.285</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Observations</td>
<td>876</td>
<td>886</td>
<td>890</td>
<td>891</td>
<td>889</td>
<td>870</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>0.086</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>0.070</td>
<td>0.092</td>
<td>0.061</td>
<td>0.127</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<attrib id="table-fn1-0958928711425268"><italic>Source</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0958928711425268">Strabac and Aalberg, 2009</xref>.</attrib>
<fn id="table-fn2-0958928711425268">
<p>Entries are unstandardized regression coefficients. †p&lt;0.1, *p&lt;0.5, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0958928711425268">
<label>a</label>
<p>Dummy: Reference category is Left parties.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0958928711425268">
<label>b</label>
<p>Dummy: Reference category is &lt;24 years.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0958928711425268">
<label>c</label>
<p>Dummy: Reference category is basic school.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0958928711425268">
<label>d</label>
<p>Dummy: Reference category is low political interest.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-0958928711425268" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sweden: The effect of party attachment on attitudes towards the welfare dimension in education (ordinary least squares (OLS) regressions)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0958928711425268" xlink:href="10.1177_0958928711425268-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Society takes good care of all children</th>
<th align="left">Education system takes good care of all children</th>
<th align="left">Education system favours children growing up in a family with an academic background</th>
<th align="left">Education system favours girls</th>
<th align="left">Education system favours children with an ethnic Swedish family background</th>
<th align="left">Preference for social skills in schools</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">(model 1)</th>
<th align="left">(model 2)</th>
<th align="left">(model 3)</th>
<th align="left">(model 4)</th>
<th align="left">(model 5)</th>
<th align="left">(model 6)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Party ID: Centre parties<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0958928711425268">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.050<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>0.021</td>
<td>−0.086<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.008</td>
<td>−0.025</td>
<td>−0.071<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Party ID: Right parties<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0958928711425268">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.014</td>
<td>0.069<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.092<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.007</td>
<td>−0.049<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.098<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No Party ID:<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0958928711425268">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.021</td>
<td>0.036<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.040<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.016</td>
<td>−0.022</td>
<td>−0.045<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Preference for social skills</td>
<td>0.019</td>
<td>−0.019</td>
<td>0.118<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>0.011</td>
<td>0.088<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td align="center">–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Society takes good care of all children</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td>0.049</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Education system takes good care of all children</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td>−0.046</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Female</td>
<td>−0.054<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.013</td>
<td>−0.015</td>
<td>−0.070<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.003</td>
<td>−0.009</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25–34 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.058<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>−0.080<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>0.018</td>
<td>−0.076<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.006</td>
<td>−0.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>35–44 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.106<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.089<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>0.045</td>
<td>−0.085<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.002</td>
<td>−0.049</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45–54 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.123<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.137<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>0.084<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.088<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.032</td>
<td>−0.058</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>55–64 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.091<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.112<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>0.065<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.062<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>0.042</td>
<td>−0.078<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>≥65 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn10-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.067</td>
<td>−0.053</td>
<td>0.069<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>−0.098<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.046</td>
<td>−0.102<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>High school<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn11-0958928711425268">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.030</td>
<td>−0.034</td>
<td>−0.008</td>
<td>−0.007</td>
<td>0.008</td>
<td>0.005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>University etc.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn11-0958928711425268">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.023</td>
<td>−0.040</td>
<td>−0.036</td>
<td>−0.002</td>
<td>0.022</td>
<td>−0.014</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>News exposure (PBS)</td>
<td>0.031</td>
<td>0.016</td>
<td>0.021</td>
<td>0.036</td>
<td>0.009</td>
<td>0.031</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>News exposure (commercial TV)</td>
<td>−0.008</td>
<td>0.023</td>
<td>−0.020</td>
<td>−0.023</td>
<td>−0.002</td>
<td>−0.097<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Newspaper exposure</td>
<td>0.061<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.046<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>−0.010</td>
<td>0.006</td>
<td>−0.016</td>
<td>−0.009</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Identification of PISA</td>
<td>−0.008</td>
<td>0.004</td>
<td>0.025</td>
<td>0.037<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.025</td>
<td>−0.039<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Political trust</td>
<td>0.196<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>0.175<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.098<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.029</td>
<td>−0.031</td>
<td>0.070</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>High political interest<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn12-0958928711425268">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.024</td>
<td>−0.090<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>0.046</td>
<td>−0.024</td>
<td>−0.010</td>
<td>0.037</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Medium political interest<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn12-0958928711425268">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.026</td>
<td>−0.022</td>
<td>0.008</td>
<td>0.005</td>
<td>−0.010</td>
<td>0.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Politics complicated</td>
<td>0.002</td>
<td>0.031</td>
<td>0.039</td>
<td>0.071<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.043</td>
<td>0.185<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>0.458(0.046)</td>
<td>0.461(0.040)</td>
<td>−0.474(0.045)</td>
<td>−0.540(0.041)</td>
<td>−0.541(0.043)</td>
<td>0.348(0.062)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Observations</td>
<td>900</td>
<td>917</td>
<td>919</td>
<td>919</td>
<td>916</td>
<td>898</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>0.102</td>
<td>0.102</td>
<td>0.115</td>
<td>0.073</td>
<td>0.035</td>
<td>0.096</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<attrib id="table-fn7-0958928711425268"><italic>Source</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0958928711425268">Strabac and Aalberg, 2009</xref>.</attrib>
<fn id="table-fn8-0958928711425268">
<p>Entries are unstandardized regression coefficients. †p&lt;0.1, *p&lt;0.5, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn9-0958928711425268">
<label>a</label>
<p>Dummy: Reference category is Left parties.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn10-0958928711425268">
<label>b</label>
<p>Dummy: Reference category is &lt;24 years.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn11-0958928711425268">
<label>c</label>
<p>Dummy: Reference category is basic school.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn12-0958928711425268">
<label>d</label>
<p>Dummy: Reference category is low political interest.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table3-0958928711425268" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Finland: The effect of party attachment on attitudes towards the welfare dimension in education (ordinary least squares (OLS) regressions)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0958928711425268" xlink:href="10.1177_0958928711425268-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Society takes good care of all children</th>
<th align="left">Education system takes good care of all children</th>
<th align="left">Education system favours children growing up in a family with an academic background</th>
<th align="left">Education system favours girls</th>
<th align="left">Education system favours children with an ethnic Finnish family background</th>
<th align="left">Preference for social skills in schools</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">(model 1)</th>
<th align="left">(model 2)</th>
<th align="left">(model 3)</th>
<th align="left">(model 4)</th>
<th align="left">(model 5)</th>
<th align="left">(model 6)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Party ID: Centre parties<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn15-0958928711425268">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.007</td>
<td>0.008</td>
<td>0.009</td>
<td>−0.012</td>
<td>−0.027</td>
<td>−0.039</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Party ID: Right parties<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn15-0958928711425268">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.023</td>
<td>0.039<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>−0.067<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.052<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.043<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.056<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No Party ID:<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn15-0958928711425268">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.016</td>
<td>−0.010</td>
<td>−0.020</td>
<td>−0.048<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.037<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>0.024</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Preference for social skills</td>
<td>−0.068<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.047</td>
<td>0.078<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.030</td>
<td>0.014</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Society takes good care of all children</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td>−0.090<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Education system takes good care of all children</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td align="center">–</td>
<td>−0.034</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Female</td>
<td>−0.042<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.022</td>
<td>−0.010</td>
<td>−0.023</td>
<td>−0.028<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>0.019</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25–34 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn16-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.055</td>
<td>−0.048</td>
<td>0.029</td>
<td>0.035</td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>0.031</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>35–44 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn16-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.070<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.082<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.056<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>0.064<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>0.033</td>
<td>−0.042</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45–54 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn16-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.080<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.054</td>
<td>0.030</td>
<td>0.073<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.004</td>
<td>0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>55–64 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn16-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.061</td>
<td>−0.076<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.049</td>
<td>0.083<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.037</td>
<td>−0.065</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>≥65 years<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn16-0958928711425268">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.056</td>
<td>−0.052</td>
<td>0.017</td>
<td>0.089</td>
<td>−0.016</td>
<td>−0.080</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>High school<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn17-0958928711425268">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.019</td>
<td>−0.008</td>
<td>−0.014</td>
<td>0.019</td>
<td>−0.031</td>
<td>0.012</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>University etc.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn17-0958928711425268">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.060<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>−0.060<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>0.040<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.001</td>
<td>0.034</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>News exposure (PBS)</td>
<td>−0.013</td>
<td>−0.016</td>
<td>0.096<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>0.056<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>−0.028</td>
<td>−0.090<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>News exposure (commercial TV)</td>
<td>0.037</td>
<td>0.054<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>−0.016</td>
<td>−0.030</td>
<td>0.018</td>
<td>0.063</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Newspaper exposure</td>
<td>−0.069<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.025</td>
<td>−0.003</td>
<td>0.017</td>
<td>0.017</td>
<td>−0.059</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Identification of PISA</td>
<td>0.030<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>0.040<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.049<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">**</xref></td>
<td>0.023</td>
<td>0.004</td>
<td>−0.014</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Political trust</td>
<td>0.424<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>0.294<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.199<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.052</td>
<td>−0.036</td>
<td>0.076</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>High political interest<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0958928711425268">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.024</td>
<td>−0.060</td>
<td>0.055</td>
<td>0.055<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>0.023</td>
<td>−0.014</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Medium political interest<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn18-0958928711425268">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.026</td>
<td>−0.027</td>
<td>0.039<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.029<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">†</xref></td>
<td>0.015</td>
<td>−0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Politics complicated</td>
<td>−0.020</td>
<td>−0.005</td>
<td>0.059</td>
<td>0.020</td>
<td>0.085<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn14-0958928711425268">*</xref></td>
<td>0.053</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>0.331(0.048)</td>
<td>0.438(0.052)</td>
<td>−0.447(0.052)</td>
<td>−0.616(0.056)</td>
<td>−0.520(0.059)</td>
<td>0.493(0.073)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Observations</td>
<td>942</td>
<td>919</td>
<td>904</td>
<td>915</td>
<td>856</td>
<td>916</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>0.260</td>
<td>0.148</td>
<td>0.144</td>
<td>0.080</td>
<td>0.034</td>
<td>0.102</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<attrib id="table-fn13-0958928711425268"><italic>Source</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0958928711425268">Strabac and Aalberg, 2009</xref>.</attrib>
<fn id="table-fn14-0958928711425268">
<p>Entries are unstandardized regression coefficients. †p&lt;0.1, *p&lt;0.5, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn15-0958928711425268">
<label>a</label>
<p>Dummy: Reference category is Left parties.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn16-0958928711425268">
<label>b</label>
<p>Dummy: Reference category is &lt;24 years.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn17-0958928711425268">
<label>c</label>
<p>Dummy: Reference category is basic school.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn18-0958928711425268">
<label>d</label>
<p>Dummy: Reference category is low political interest.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The results presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0958928711425268">Tables 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0958928711425268">3</xref> generally support the arguments of this article. The reference category in each country is respondents having sympathy with Left parties. Hence, the coefficient estimates, Party ID: Centre, Party ID: Right and No Party ID, measure divergence from sympathizers of Left parties. Model 1 measures whether respondents believe that <italic>society</italic> is taking good care of all children. In this model, political polarization is virtually non-existent. But when asking respondents whether the <italic>education system</italic> takes good care of all children (Model 2), political polarization is more evident. Hence, the education system appears more politicized than society in general. Sympathizers of right-wing parties (and centre parties in Norway) are more inclined to believe that the education system takes good care of all children, compared with respondents sympathizing with left-wing parties.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0958928711425268">6</xref></sup></p>
<p>Concerning the three more specific questions (Models 3 to 5), sympathizers of left-wing parties in all three countries are most inclined to believe that the ‘education system favours children growing up in a family with an academic background’ and that the ‘education system favours children with an ethnic [Norwegian/Swedish/Finnish] family background’. The strongest degree of polarization is evident in Model 3 (bias towards children from academic families). In sum, these findings support H1, <italic>sympathizers of left-wing parties have the highest expectations concerning the ability of the education system to integrate all children equally.</italic></p>
<p>In Finland, there is also significant polarization on the gender dimension (Model 4). Sympathizers of left-wing parties are most inclined to believe that the education system favours girls. This finding is more tricky to interpret as gender differences in educational achievement are not large in Finland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0958928711425268">Matti, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0958928711425268">Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development, 2009</xref>). However, the Finnish comprehensive school differentiates between an academic and a vocational track, and empirical studies do suggest that girls are more likely to choose the academic track than boys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0958928711425268">Pekkarinen, 2008</xref>). Given that this gender difference is salient in the citizenry, H1 is also supported by this estimate. Polarization is not evident on this dimension in Norway and Sweden.</p>
<p>Finally (Model 6), in all three countries sympathizers of right-wing parties support more focus on academic skills, while sympathizers of left-wing parties support more focus on social skills. Hence, H2, <italic>sympathizers of left-wing parties show strongest support for focusing on social skills – as opposed to academic skills – in schools</italic>, is supported by these analyses.</p>
<p>The models control for the effects of welfare attitudes, and the results here are somewhat mixed. In Models 3 (academic family background) and 5 (ethnic Nordic family background) the significant relationships are positive, suggesting that those who believe the system is biased towards one of the groups also support more focus on social skills in schools.</p>
<p>Looking further at the control variables, the argument of the welfare dimension as politically polarized is strengthened. Political trust is the strongest consistent determinant in the evaluative models (1–5), suggesting a close relationship between educational and political institutions (more trust in politics = more positive evaluations). Further strengthening the argument is the lack of significant socio-demographic variables. In all three countries men are more inclined than women to believe that <italic>society</italic> takes good care of all children. However, with regard to the <italic>education system</italic>, gender differences are negligible.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0958928711425268">7</xref></sup> Further, respondents’ level of education is largely irrelevant as a determinant in all three countries. The weak effects of gender and education contradict the literature on rational self-interest in which women and the low-educated are typically expected to be more supportive of welfare than men and highly educated citizens (for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0958928711425268">Aalberg, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0958928711425268">Kaltenthaler et al., 2008</xref>). This previous research has predominantly focused on attitudes towards economic welfare issues (for example, distribution and rewards), and it seems as though these findings are not easily transferable to the welfare dimension in education. In sum, politics is a better predictor than any other available variable in explaining variations in attitudes towards the welfare dimension in education.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0958928711425268" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Concluding remarks</title>
<p>Recall the puzzling finding above – that Finns expressed more positive perceptions on the general questions compared with the more specific questions. In addition to the possibility that Finns do not interpret the general question as related to social welfare, this is explained by the fact that left-leaning citizens report more critical evaluations when being asked specific questions (Models 3–5; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0958928711425268">Table 3</xref>). The methodological implication therefore is that with general questions one would fail to tap the latent ideological polarization that obviously exists in the Finnish population. One possibility is that the Finnish education system has largely been framed in positive terms after continuous academic success on international comparisons, and that the general question taps this academic dimension in Finland. One methodological hypothesis for future survey research on public evaluations of political institutions would therefore be that the more positive image an institution has in society, the more specific questions are needed to reveal potential mass political polarization.</p>
<p>Based on the empirical analyses, the main conclusion is that the welfare dimension in education triggers political polarization among citizens. Public opinion resembles the expected ideological polarization at the elite level. Citizens sympathizing with left-wing parties have the highest expectations on behalf of the welfare dimension in education; left-leaning citizens support more focus on social skills; right-leaning citizens support more focus on academic skills. These findings outweigh any alternative explanation included in the models. Note also that among the control variables, political trust was the most consistent significant determinant. Theoretically, these findings suggest that the measured dimensions of welfare that revealed significant polarization can be described more in terms of conflict (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0958928711425268">Korpi, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0958928711425268">Nygård, 2006</xref>) than in terms of compromise (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0958928711425268">Aasen, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0958928711425268">Sejersted, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>What are the possible implications of these findings for the link between education and the Nordic welfare states? At the elite level one would generally expect the welfare dimension to have its strongest proponents in left-leaning governments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0958928711425268">Nygård, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0958928711425268">Tuastad, 2008</xref>). However, irrespective of political colour, any government needs public support for its policies. The results suggest that at the aggregated level the welfare dimension is not strongly supported in Norway and Sweden. Aggregated support for more focus on social skills is stronger in Finland, while only a small segment of left-leaning citizens in Norway and Sweden expresses support. Similarly, right-leaning citizens overall are more satisfied with present welfare performance, and there is a larger share of ‘indifferent’ (neither/nor) citizens in Norway and Sweden than in Finland. Based on these findings, one hypothesis is that comparatively poor academic performance in Norway and Sweden undermines public support for the welfare dimension. Finland is an academic top-performer, but public demand for more focus on social skills is not overwhelming even though it is stronger than in Norway and Sweden. Overall, this suggests that if Nordic governments want to strengthen the welfare dimension in education, they need first to secure acceptable (as perceived by mass publics) academic standards. Hence, a hypothesis for future research is that public perceptions of high academic performance increase the leeway for policy-makers to commence other-than-academic educational aims.</p>
<p>An alternative explanation is that the results do not necessarily suggest any threat towards the welfare dimension in education. The evaluative measures suggest that right-leaning citizens are satisfied with the present state of affairs, and that they urge more focus on academic skills in schools. This does not necessarily mean that they discredit the welfare dimension. Rather it could simply mean that they want to keep the welfare dimension as it is, but at the same time increase focus on academic skills. Nevertheless, the welfare dimension is characterized by political polarization rather than consensus, and, given that there is a tension between social democratic and liberal/specialist policy patterns in the Nordic countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0958928711425268">Arnesen and Lundahl, 2006</xref>), its future sustainability vis-a-vis the academic dimension might depend upon the political colour of future governments.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<table-wrap id="table4-0958928711425268" position="float">
<label>Appendix Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Variables, coding and descriptive statistics</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0958928711425268" xlink:href="10.1177_0958928711425268-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variables</th>
<th align="left">Operationalization</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Norway</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Sweden</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Finland</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="left">Mean</th>
<th align="left">SD</th>
<th align="left">n</th>
<th align="left">Mean</th>
<th align="left">SD</th>
<th align="left">n</th>
<th align="left">Mean</th>
<th align="left">SD</th>
<th align="left">n</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Society takes good care of all children</td>
<td>‘The [country] society takes good care of all its children’<break/>(1 (Strongly disagree) –5 (Strongly agree)) 0.1–0.9 scale</td>
<td>0.475</td>
<td>0.195</td>
<td>970</td>
<td>0.448</td>
<td>0.199</td>
<td>971</td>
<td>0.429</td>
<td>0.230</td>
<td>992</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Education system takes good care of all children</td>
<td>‘The [country] education system is taking good care of all children independent of their family background’<break/>(1 (Strongly disagree) –5 (Strongly agree)) 0.1–0.9 scale</td>
<td>0.505</td>
<td>0.184</td>
<td>994</td>
<td>0.480</td>
<td>0.197</td>
<td>997</td>
<td>0.541</td>
<td>0.214</td>
<td>971</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Education system favours children growing up in a family with an academic background</td>
<td>‘The [country] education system favours children growing up in a family with an academic background’<break/>(1 (Strongly disagree) –5 (Strongly agree))</td>
<td>0.464</td>
<td>0.190</td>
<td>998</td>
<td>0.474</td>
<td>0.203</td>
<td>1000</td>
<td>0.480</td>
<td>0.220</td>
<td>953</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Education system favours girls</td>
<td>‘The [country] education system favours girls’<break/>(1 (Strongly disagree) –5 (Strongly agree))</td>
<td>0.563</td>
<td>0.181</td>
<td>999</td>
<td>0.604</td>
<td>0.171</td>
<td>999</td>
<td>0.523</td>
<td>0.206</td>
<td>966</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Education system favours children with an ethnic (Norwegian/Swedish/ Finnish) family background</td>
<td>‘The [country] education system favours children with an ethnic [country] family background’<break/>(1 (Strongly disagree) –5 (Strongly agree))</td>
<td>0.543</td>
<td>0.178</td>
<td>997</td>
<td>0.539</td>
<td>0.184</td>
<td>996</td>
<td>0.510</td>
<td>0.208</td>
<td>900</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Preference for social skills in schools</td>
<td>‘In your opinion, what is at present the primary challenge for the Finnish education system: Schools should focus more on providing good social skills for all children (10), OR schools should focus more on educating foundational skills (reading, mathematics, and nature science) (0)?’ 0–1 scale</td>
<td>0.319</td>
<td>0.228</td>
<td>965</td>
<td>0.343</td>
<td>0.232</td>
<td>969</td>
<td>0.434</td>
<td>0.249</td>
<td>986</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Party attachment</td>
<td>‘Is there a particular political party you feel closer to than all the other parties?’</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Party ID: Left parties</td>
<td>Norway: Arbeiderpartiet, Sosialistisk <break/>Venstreparti<break/>Sweden: Socialdemokraterne,<break/>Vänsterpartiet, Miljöpartiet<break/>Finland: Suomen<break/>Sosiaalidemokraattinen Poule,<break/> Vasemmistoliitto, Vihreä Liitto</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>288</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>261</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>244</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Party ID: Centre parties</td>
<td>Norway: Senterpartiet, Venstre,<break/>Kristelig Folkeparti<break/>Sweden: Centerpartiet, Folkpartiet,<break/>Kristdemokraterna<break/>Finland: Suomen Keskusta,<break/>Suomen Kristillisdemokraatit, Ruotsalainen Kansanpuolue</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>82</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>77</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>114</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Party ID: Right parties</td>
<td>Norway: Høyre, Fremskrittspartiet<break/>Sweden: Moderaterna<break/>Finland: Kansallinen Kokoomus,<break/>Perussuomalaiset</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>290</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>211</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>249</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No Party ID</td>
<td>No Party ID</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>310</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>409</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>382</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="11">Socio–demographic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td>Are you…1 = female</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>507</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>496</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>516</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0 = male</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>493</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>504</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>484</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age</td>
<td>≤24 years</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>100</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>71</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>25–34 years</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>234</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>213</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>183</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>35–44 years</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>279</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>190</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>189</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>45–54 years</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>193</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>190</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>214</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>55–64 years</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>151</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>283</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>321</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>≥65 years</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>43</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>53</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Education (dummy)</td>
<td>Nation-specific level of education collapsed into three categories‘<break/>What is the highest level of education you have achieved?’</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td> Basic School (reference category)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>95</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>81</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>147</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td> High school</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>422</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>465</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>363</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td> University etc.</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>466</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>436</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>485</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="11">News consumption</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> News exposure (PBS TV)</td>
<td>‘In a typical week, how often do you watch [name of PBS main news programme]?’<break/>(1 (Seldom or never) –5 (Every day)) 0.1–0.9 scale</td>
<td>0.531</td>
<td>0.293</td>
<td>979</td>
<td>0.455</td>
<td>0.289</td>
<td>990</td>
<td>0.482</td>
<td>0.288</td>
<td>981</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> News exposure (Commercial TV)</td>
<td>‘In a typical week, how often do you watch [name of commercial channel main news programme]?’<break/>1 (Seldom or never) –5 (Every day)) 0.1–0.9 scale</td>
<td>0.555</td>
<td>0.281</td>
<td>983</td>
<td>0.460</td>
<td>0.278</td>
<td>988</td>
<td>0.442</td>
<td>0.257</td>
<td>989</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Newspaper exposure</td>
<td>‘In a typical week, how often do you read your daily newspaper?’<break/>1 (Seldom or never) –5 (Every day)) 0.1–0.9 scale</td>
<td>0.616</td>
<td>0.307</td>
<td>983</td>
<td>0.645</td>
<td>0.302</td>
<td>996</td>
<td>0.669</td>
<td>0.274</td>
<td>995</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="11">Political awareness</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PISA (dummy)</td>
<td>‘PISA is a comparative measure organized by the OECD, carried out to several countries including [country]. Do you know what PISA measures?’ (1 (Economic development), 2 (Air pollution), 3 (Education), 4 (Healthcare))<break/>1 = Correct answer</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>300</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>104</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>512</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>0 = Incorrect answer</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>700</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>896</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>488</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Political trust</td>
<td>‘Please indicate on a scale of 0 to 10 how much you personally trust each of the institutions bellow. Zero means you do not trust an institution at all, and 10 means you have complete trust’ (Parliament + politicians) 0–1 scale</td>
<td>0.487</td>
<td>0.223</td>
<td>969</td>
<td>0.458</td>
<td>0.222</td>
<td>970</td>
<td>0.523</td>
<td>0.229</td>
<td>988</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Political interest</td>
<td>‘How interested would you say you are in politics – are you:</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Low interest (‘Not at all interested’)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>465</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>563</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>533</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Medium interest (‘Hardly interested’ + ‘Quite interested’)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>449</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>362</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>397</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>High interest (‘Very interested’)’</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>83</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>70</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Politics complicated</td>
<td>‘How often does politics seem so complicated that you can’t really understand what is going on?’<break/>(1 (Never) –5 (Frequently)) 0.1–0.9 scale</td>
<td>0.496</td>
<td>0.196</td>
<td>983</td>
<td>0.515</td>
<td>0.217</td>
<td>983</td>
<td>0.519</td>
<td>0.229</td>
<td>986</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<attrib id="table-fn19-0958928711425268"><italic>Source</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0958928711425268">Strabac and Aalberg, 2009</xref>.</attrib>
<fn id="table-fn20-0958928711425268">
<p><italic>Note</italic>: All continuous variables are standardized (0–1 [0.1–0.9]).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</app-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0958928711425268">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Share of public expenditure on educational institutions (Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development, 2007): Norway 96.7 percent (2003); Sweden 88.4 percent (2004); Finland 96.3 percent (2004); Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development average 75.4 percent (2004)</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0958928711425268">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Programme for International Student Assessment (PISA) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oecd.org">www.oecd.org</ext-link>), Trends in International Mathematics and Science Study (TIMSS) and Progress in International Reading Literacy Study (PIRLS) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://timss.bc.edu">http://timss.bc.edu</ext-link>) are cross-country standardized assessments measuring pupils’ competencies in various subjects.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0958928711425268">
<label>3.</label>
<p>YouGov is a multi-national research and consulting company that conducts representative surveys and polls as web questionnaires – see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://corp.yougov.com/">http://corp.yougov.com/</ext-link> or <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://yougov.dk">http://yougov.dk</ext-link> (accessed 15 August 2011).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0958928711425268">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Note that all survey methods are associated with some sorts of biases. In the study comparing the web survey used here with a similar telephone survey, age-bias was found in both samples. The Norwegian web sample was younger than the population, while the Norwegian telephone sample was older than the population. By applying the weights constructed by YouGov, these differences become minimal. Further, differences are also minimal in substantial analyses (answers to political knowledge questions and regression analyses estimating determinants of knowledge) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0958928711425268">Strabac and Aalberg, 2011</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0958928711425268">
<label>5.</label>
<p>See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.norden.org">www.norden.org</ext-link> (accessed 15 August 2011).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0958928711425268">
<label>6.</label>
<p>Significance p &lt; 0.05.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0958928711425268">
<label>7.</label>
<p>The exception is that women are less likely than men to believe that the education system favours girls in Norway and Sweden.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aalberg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Achieving Justice: Comparative Public Opinion on Income Distribution</source>. <publisher-loc>Leiden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brill</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aasen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) ‘<article-title>Det sosialdemokratiske prosjektet. Utdanningsreformer i Sverige og Norge i etterkrigstiden [The Social Democratic Project: Educational Reforms in Sweden and Norway in the Post-war Period]</article-title>’ [<comment>in Norwegian</comment>], in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Telhaug</surname><given-names>A.O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aasen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Både-og. 90-tallets utdanningsreformer i historisk perspektiv</source>. <publisher-loc>Oslo</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cappelen Akademisk Forlag</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ahonen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) ‘<article-title>From an Industrial to a Post-industrial Society: Changing Conceptions of Equality in Education</article-title>’, <source>Educational Review</source> <volume>54</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ahonen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rantal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2001</year>) <source>Nordic Lights: Education for Nation and Civic Society in the Nordic Countries, 1850–2000</source>. <publisher-loc>Helsinki</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Finnish Literature Society</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Andress</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heien</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) ‘<article-title>Four Worlds of Welfare State Attitudes? A Comparison of Germany, Norway, and the United States</article-title>’, <source>European Sociological Review</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Antikainen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) ‘<article-title>In Search of the Nordic Model in Education</article-title>’, <source>Scandinavian Journal of Educational Research</source> <volume>50</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arnesen</surname><given-names>A.-L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lundahl</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) ‘<article-title>Still Social and Democratic? Inclusive Education Policies in the Nordic Welfare States</article-title>’, <source>Scandinavian Journal of Educational Research</source> <volume>50</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Biesta</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<article-title>Good Education in an Age of Measurement: On the Need to Reconnect with the Question of Purpose in Education</article-title>’, <source>Educational Assessment, Evaluation and Accountability</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bjørklund</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saglie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) ‘<article-title>Velferdsstat og valenspolitikk: lokalvalget i 1999</article-title>’ [<trans-title xml:lang="en">Welfare State and Valence Politics: The 1999 Norwegian Local Elections</trans-title>] [<comment>in Norwegian</comment>], <source>Norsk Statsvitenskapelig Tidsskrift</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blekesaune</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) ‘<article-title>Economic Conditions and Public Attitudes to Welfare Policies</article-title>’, <source>European Sociological Review</source> <volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>403</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blekesaune</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quadagno</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) ‘<article-title>Public Attitudes Toward Welfare State Policies: A Comparative Analysis of 24 Nations</article-title>’, <source>European Sociological Review</source> <volume>19</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carlgren</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<article-title>The Swedish Comprehensive School: Lost in Transition?</article-title>’, <source>Zeitschrift Fur Erziehungswissenschaft</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>633</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Castells</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Himanen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>The Information Society and the Welfare State: The Finnish Model</source>. <publisher-loc>Helsinki</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suomen itsenäisyyden juhlarahasto</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) ‘<article-title>I skyggen av PISA [In the shadow of PISA]</article-title>’ [<comment>in Norwegian</comment>], <source>Nytt Norsk Tidsskrift</source> <volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>200</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bartle</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<article-title>The European Issue and Party Choice at British General Elections, 1974–2005</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Elections, Public Opinion and Parties</source> <volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Converse</surname><given-names>P.E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1964</year>) ‘<article-title>The Nature of Belief Systems Among Mass Publics</article-title>’, in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Apter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Ideology and Discontent</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edlund</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) ‘<article-title>Trust in the Capability of the Welfare State and General Welfare State Support: Sweden 19972–002</article-title>’, <source>Acta Sociologica</source> <volume>49</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elstad</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) ‘<article-title>PISA i norsk offentlighet [PISA in the Norwegian public]</article-title>’ [<comment>in Norwegian</comment>], in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Elstad</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sivesind</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>PISA: sannheten om skolen?</source> <publisher-loc>Oslo</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Universitetsforlaget</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elstad</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sivesind</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>PISA: sannheten om skolen?</source> [<source>PISA: The Truth About School?</source>] [<comment>in Norwegian</comment>]. <publisher-loc>Oslo</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Universitetsforlaget</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ervasti</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fridberg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hjerm</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. (eds) (<year>2008</year>) <source>Nordic Social Attitudes in a European Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Cheltenham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elgar</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Esping-Andersen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <source>Politics Against Markets: The Social Democratic Road to Power</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Esping-Andersen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>The Three Worlds of Welfare Capitalism</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fridberg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kangas</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) ‘<article-title>Social Capital</article-title>’, in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ervasti</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fridberg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hjerm</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (eds) <source>Nordic Social Attitudes in a European Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Cheltenham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Edward Elgar</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grek</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<article-title>Governing by Numbers: The PISA “effect” in Europe</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Education Policy</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hasenfeld</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rafferty</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) ‘<article-title>The Determinants of Public Attitudes Toward the Welfare State</article-title>’, <source>Social Forces</source> <volume>67</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1027</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hedberg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<source>Svenska folkets bedömning av skol – och utbildningsfrågor som viktiga frågor för partival i riksdagen</source> [<trans-source xml:lang="en">Swedish People’s Assessment of School and Education as Important Issues for the Choice of Party in Parliamentary Elections</trans-source>]’ [<comment>in Swedish</comment>]. <publisher-loc>Göteborg (Göteborgs Universitet)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Valforskningsprogrammet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heidar</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Nordic Politics: Comparative Perspectives</source>. <publisher-loc>Oslo</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Universitetsforlaget</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jakobsen</surname><given-names>T.G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) ‘<article-title>Public versus Private: The Conditional Effect of State Policy and Institutional Trust on Mass Opinion</article-title>’, <source>European Sociological Review</source> <volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jæger</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) ‘<article-title>What Makes People Support Public Responsibility for Welfare Provision: Self-interest or Political Ideology? A Longitudinal Approach</article-title>’, <source>Acta Sociologica</source> <volume>49</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaltenthaler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ceccoli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gelleny</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) ‘<article-title>Attitudes toward Eliminating Income Inequality in Europe</article-title>’, <source>European Union Politics</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Karlsen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aardal</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) ‘<article-title>Politisk dagsorden og sakseierskap [Political Agendas and Issue Ownership]’ [in Norwegian]</article-title>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Aardal</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Norske velgere. En studie av stortingsvalget 2005</source>. <publisher-loc>Oslo</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Damm and Søn</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Korpi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <source>The Democratic Class Struggle</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge, Kegan and Paul</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kumlin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>The Personal and the Political: How Personal Welfare State Experiences Affect Politcal Trust and Ideology</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laycock</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<article-title>Experience Versus Perceptions: Accounting for the NHS “Perception Gap”</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Elections, Public Opinion and Parties</source> <volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lie</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Linnakylä</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2003</year>) <source>Northern Lights on PISA: Unity and Diversity in the Nordic Countries in PISA 2000</source>. <publisher-loc>Oslo</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Teacher Education and School Development, University of Oslo</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Listhaug</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aalberg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) ‘<article-title>Comparative Public Opinion on Distributive Justice</article-title>’, <source>International Journal of Comparative Sociology</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Listhaug</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ringdal</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) ‘<article-title>Trust in Political Institutions</article-title>’, in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ervasti</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fridberg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hjerm</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (eds) <source>Nordic Social Attitudes in a European Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Cheltenham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Edward Elgar</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Listhaug</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wiberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) ‘<article-title>Confidence in Political and Private Institutions</article-title>’, in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Klingemann</surname><given-names>H.-D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Citizens and the State</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McClosky</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaller</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <source>The American Ethos: Public Attitudes Toward Capitalism and Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Matti</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) (<year>2009</year>) <source>Northern Lights on Pisa 2006: Differences and Similarities in the Nordic Countries</source>. <publisher-loc>Copenhagen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nordic Council of Ministers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Mejding</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2006</year>) <source>Northern Lights on PISA 2003: A Reflection from the Nordic Countries</source>. <publisher-loc>Copenhagen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nordic Council of Ministers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Civic Literacy: How Informed Citizens Make Democracy Work</source>. <publisher-loc>Hanover</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University Press of New England</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nygård</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) ‘<article-title>Welfare-Ideological Change in Scandinavia: A Comparative Analysis of Partisan Welfare State Positions in Four Nordic Countries, 19702–003</article-title>’, <source>Scandinavian Political Studies</source> <volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>356</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Education at a Glance 2009. OECD Indicators</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>OECD</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pekkarinen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) ‘<article-title>Gender Differences in Educational Attainment: Evidence on the Role of Tracking from a Finnish Quasi-experiment</article-title>’, <source>Scandinavian Journal of Economics</source> <volume>110</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>807</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pesonen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) ‘<article-title>Dangerous Curves in Finnish Politics: A Sweet Victory and a Sour Honeymoon</article-title>’, <source>Tidsskrift for Samfunnsforskning</source> <volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Petersson</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Nordisk politik</source> [<trans-source xml:lang="en">Nordic Politics</trans-source>] [<comment>in Swedish</comment>]. <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Norstedts juridik</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rautalin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alasuutari</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<article-title>The Uses of the National PISA Results by Finnish Officials in Central Government</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Education Policy</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rothstein</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stolle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) ‘<article-title>Introduction: Social Capital in Scandinavia</article-title>’, <source>Scandinavian Political Studies</source> <volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sejersted</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Sosialdemokratiets tidsalder: Norge og Sverige i det 20. århundre</source> [<source>The Era of Social Democracy: Norway and Sweden in the 20th century</source> [<comment>in Norwegian</comment>]. <publisher-loc>Oslo</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pax</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Söderlund</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) ‘<article-title>Retrospective Voting and Electoral Volatility: A Nordic Perspective</article-title>’, <source>Scandinavian Political Studies</source> <volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1963</year>) ‘<article-title>Spatial Models of Party Competition</article-title>’, <source>American Political Science Review</source> <volume>57</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>368</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strabac</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aalberg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Media use, political knowledge and perception of reality. A cross national survey – Project description, questionnaires and codebook. ISS Report, No. 74</source>. <publisher-loc>Trondheim</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Norwegian University of Science and Technology</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strabac</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aalberg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) ‘<article-title>Measuring Political Knowledge in Telephone and Web Surveys: A Cross-National Comparison</article-title>’, <source>Social Science Computer Review</source> <volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Svallfors</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) ‘<article-title>Class, Attitudes and the Welfare State: Sweden in Comparative Perspective</article-title>’, <source>Social Policy and Administration</source> <volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Svallfors</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) (<year>2007</year>) <source>The Political Sociology of the Welfare State</source>. <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Telhaug</surname><given-names>A.O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mediås</surname><given-names>O.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aasen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) ‘<article-title>From Collectivism to Individualism? Education as Nation Building in a Scandinavian Perspective</article-title>’, <source>Scandinavian Journal of Educational Research</source> <volume>48</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Telhaug</surname><given-names>A.O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mediås</surname><given-names>O.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aasen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) ‘<article-title>The Nordic Model in Education: Education as Part of the Political System in the Last 50 Years</article-title>’, <source>Scandinavian Journal of Educational Research</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tuastad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) ‘<article-title>Liberal modernisering. Den normative dimensjonen i norsk politikk – sett gjennom skuleporten [Liberal Modernisation. The Normative Dimension in Norwegian politics: A View from the School Gate]</article-title>’ [<comment>in Norwegian</comment>], <source>Tidsskrift for Samfunnsforskning</source> <volume>49</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Valen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Narud</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) ‘<article-title>The Conditional Party Mandate: A Model for the Study of Mass and Elite Opinion Patterns</article-title>’, <source>European Journal of Political Research</source> <volume>46</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van Oorschot</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) ‘<article-title>Public Perceptions of the Economic, Moral, Social and Migration Consequences of the Welfare State: An Empirical Analysis of Welfare State Legitimacy</article-title>’, <source>Journal of European Social Policy</source> <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Välijärvi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Linnakylä</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kupari</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2002</year>) <source>The Finnish Success in PISA – and Some Reasons Behind It: PISA 2000</source>. <publisher-loc>Jyväskylä</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Institute for Educational Research, University of Jyväskyle</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilensky</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <source>The Welfare State and Equality</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkely, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0958928711425268">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zaller</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <source>The Nature and Origins of Mass Opinion</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>