<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PBI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppbi</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Positive Behavior Interventions</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1098-3007</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1538-4772</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1098300713479575</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1098300713479575</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>What’s Inside—Highlights From This Issue</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>V. Mark</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>Lee</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>67</fpage>
<lpage>70</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 Hammill Institute on Disabilities</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Hammill Institute on Disabilities</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This issue of <italic>Journal of Positive Behavior Interventions</italic> (<italic>JPBI</italic>) will be the last one coedited by Bob Koegel, one of the journal’s founding editors (with Glen Dunlap). We wish to thank Bob for helping to create the journal and for more than 15 years of incredible service that led to its current status as one of the premier journals in the field. <italic>JPBI</italic> is incredibly fortunate to welcome Lee Kern from Lehigh University who will begin serving as coeditor starting with the next issue. We thought it would be appropriate to mark this transition with some reflections from both Glen Dunlap and Bob Koegel, and their reminiscences are next, followed by the highlights of this issue’s contents.</p>
<sec id="section1-1098300713479575">
<title>Origins of <italic>JPBI</italic></title>
<p>Starting <italic>JPBI</italic> was one of the most exciting efforts in our careers. It required the establishment of a new field of science, as well as establishing a sophisticated mechanism (<italic>JPBI</italic>) of disseminating knowledge to the field. This was extremely difficult, but also extremely rewarding.</p>
<p>Prior to 1990, the bulk of the work in the area of behavioral interventions was driven by a singular emphasis on scientific rigor and reliable data evaluations without an emphasis on the ethical aspects of the intervention strategies. Even when an approach went against established values (such as giving electric shocks to children), if the data showed the technique worked, then researchers argued in favor of using it. However, a group of professionals began to emphasize the systematic integration of values and science, such that approaches needed to be grounded in both scientific rigor and also support the values of being nonaversive and respectful of people’s dignity. By the mid-1990s, positive behavior support (PBS) had been established as an effective and preferred approach for addressing problems of behavioral adaptation. The field, focusing on both values and science, was expanding and maturing very rapidly, fueled by important data and perspectives from a variety of disciplines and a diverse assemblage of professionals, family members, and researchers. However, the development of PBS was frustrated to some extent by the absence of a focused journal dedicated to the dissemination of new, credible information on this emerging discipline. People needed to have a ready source of new information and a ready source of evidence showing that PBS worked.</p>
<p>The idea for the journal emerged out of the regular meetings of the Research and Training Center on Positive Behavior Support, a national consortium of researchers and trainers funded by the National Institute on Disability and Rehabilitation Research of the U.S. Department of Education. The principal champion of the idea was Edward G. (Ted) Carr,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1098300713479575">1</xref></sup> although other members of the consortium were also enthusiastic. Indeed, several of the consortium’s researchers agreed to reserve their best manuscripts to submit to early issues if a new journal could be developed. At every research and training center steering committee meeting, Ted Carr would ask for updates on the progress of forming a new journal. Somehow (in hindsight, we are not sure how this happened), we were assigned to the task of showing that progress was being made in forming the journal.</p>
<p><italic>JPBI</italic> began to take form in 1997 when we established contact with Dr. Judy Voress, who was periodicals director for PRO-ED (later transferred to the Hammill Institute on Disabilities). We called Judy Voress with an enormous amount of anxiety, as the importance of success, and the need to report back to Ted Carr and the steering committee was weighing heavily. We were therefore extremely excited when Dr. Voress was intrigued by the idea and, after a series of phone conversations, invited us to PRO-ED’s headquarters in Austin, Texas, to discuss the idea further and to meet with the publisher, Don Hammill. The meetings, consisting of grueling questions as well as enjoyable social interactions and dinners in Texas, ended with an agreement for PRO-ED to take a gamble (which they would evaluate in a year) and publish the new journal. At that time, “positive behavior support” was not a very well-known term, and some of us liked the idea of the word “intervention” as it implied change, so a decision was made to substitute “interventions” for “support” in the journal’s title. Thus, <italic>JPBI</italic> was born.</p>
<p>The year 1998 was busy with the recruitment, review, and editing of manuscripts, the development of procedures and policies, and the creation of a board of editors. Launching a new journal can be treacherous because there is an immediate need for a supply of high-quality manuscripts, and such a supply can be difficult to produce without a track record. Indeed, we were quite worried at first that we would not be able to attract enough manuscripts to make it work. However, we were fortunate to have an excellent group of close colleagues who all wanted to contribute and help make the journal a success. As a result, we quickly amassed an initial collection of manuscripts from well-established researchers who were willing to take a chance that the journal and the field would be a success. This resulted in a great deal of excitement as the journal began to represent the field of PBS. Obviously, we were delighted at the outpouring of interest and support for the journal and the field, culminating in what would eventually lead to <italic>JPBI</italic> becoming one of the top experimental journals in the fields of special education and clinical psychology.</p>
<p><italic>JPBI</italic>’s first issue was in the winter of 1999. In that issue, we presented an introduction in which we described the context and the purpose of the journal. We explained some key terms and discussed how significant developments from a variety of disciplines were altering the ways in which behavior support was conceptualized and implemented. We noted,
<disp-quote>
<p>As a whole, the field of behavioral support needs to nurture and integrate these varied and vital perspectives; thus the major purpose of this new journal is to provide a publication outlet for the exchange of constructive perspectives and credible information so that the field can move increasingly toward a comprehensive, effective and humane response to the substantial challenges of behavioral adaptation. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1098300713479575">Dunlap &amp; Koegel, 1999</xref>, p. 2)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>We explained further that
<disp-quote>
<p>the <italic>Journal of Positive Behavior Interventions (JPBI)</italic> has been developed to produce and exchange knowledge that is useful for helping people with behavioral needs to live better lives and to build good relationships with their families, friends, peers, support providers, and other members of their communities. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1098300713479575">Dunlap &amp; Koegel, 1999</xref>, p. 2)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Our vision for the journal was captured well in these statements of purpose. Of course, we also wanted the journal to be successful. We wanted a good readership, and we wanted the contents to add substantively to the literature and to be useful in practice. We believe our ambitions have been realized. This is because our ambitions were not ours alone. They were owned by a large and expanding group of individuals who were (and are) committed to the development of improved knowledge and improved practice in PBS. <italic>JPBI</italic> is in great shape and it is in extremely capable hands. The coeditors, Mark Durand and Lee Kern, are dedicated and brilliant scholars, and their associate editors and editorial board members will help them to build on the important traditions that <italic>JPBI</italic> represents. It has been an honor for us to serve a role in the origins of <italic>JPBI</italic>.</p>
<p>Glen Dunlap and Robert L. Koegel</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1098300713479575">
<title>Lowering Stress and Increasing Empowerment in Families</title>
<p>There is now overwhelming evidence that family members of persons diagnosed with autism spectrum disorder (ASD) experience significant and chronic stress. This is of obvious concern because this type of stress can interfere with a harmonious home life and can increase levels of anxiety and depression. At the same time, experiencing emotional stress over long periods of time can actually effect the brain in a way that makes it even more difficult to respond appropriate to anxiety-provoking situations (e.g., a child screaming in the store). Finding ways to reduce stress in these families is an essential goal for ASD professionals.</p>
<p>Recently, a team of researchers from Seattle Children’s Research Institute in Washington (Mendy Boettcher Minjarez), Durham University in Durham City in the United Kingdom (Emma Mercier), and Stanford University School of Medicine (Sharon Williams and Antonio Hardan) conducted a study that trained parents how to teach their young children with ASD to improve their language skills (using a training package called “pivotal response training” or PRT). They measured their levels of stress and feeling of empowerment before and after this 10-week training program and observed positive changes in the families after they participated in the program. Although there was no comparison group, the authors commented that some aspect of this program reduced stress and made family members feel better about their ability to help their children.</p>
<p>Lead researcher Mendy Boettcher Minjarez told us,<disp-quote>
<p>We were honestly somewhat surprised, but also very encouraged, to find that the PRT parent training group had a significant impact on decreasing parent stress and improving empowerment. Research in this area often finds that even when children make progress, their parents remain stressed because autism is a chronic condition, thus parents face ongoing challenges. In exploring this finding further with parents, many told us that it was as much about what they learned from us (PRT), as it was the support they received from the other parents in the group. As a result, I believe future research should focus on expanding group models for delivering parent education interventions.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1098300713479575">
<title>Improving Reading by Understanding Behavior Problems</title>
<p>Do problems with reading cause students to misbehave or is it the other way around? The answer to this question is yes—Research suggests that misbehaving in school can interfere with academic performance, and having trouble with what teachers present to students can result in behavior problems. The real question is to tease this out for each student individually.</p>
<p>This was the challenge faced by researchers Amanda Sanford (Portland State University) and Rob Horner (University of Oregon). They identified four students in Grades 2 and 3 who were misbehaving during their reading instruction sessions. They assessed why these particular students were acting out and found that it appeared to be an effort to escape from reading tasks that may have been outside of their current skill level. They then modified the curriculum materials to better match the students reading level and, in general, found that the students were better behaved when instruction was at their appropriate level.</p>
<p>The first author, Amanda Sanford, observed that<disp-quote>
<p>effective education requires attention to both academic and behavior supports. In this study, we documented how improving reading instruction directly related to improved classroom behavior. We must do both with the right level of intensity to ensure students are successful.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1098300713479575">
<title>Set a Goal, Make a Plan, Adjust</title>
<p>Although the title of this piece sounds like advice for creating and keeping your New Year’s resolutions, it comes from a program designed to reduce challenging behavior and increase self-determination in students. Called the “Self-Determined Learning Model of Instruction” (or SDLMI), it is intended to help students who exhibit behavior problems in school create behavioral goals (e.g., “I need to not call out in class”), make a plan for positive change (e.g., “listen and focus on my work/raise my hand”), and, where necessary, adjust the goal (e.g., “I will ask the teacher for a quiet place when others are talking to me”).</p>
<p>Recent research looks at this approach with students at risk for, or with, emotional disturbance during preadolescence. This population is important to study because—if not helped appropriately—they are much more likely to face school expulsion, drop out of school, and ultimately may face incarceration during their school-age years. Researchers from Western Carolina University (Valerie Mazzotti) and the University of North Carolina at Charlotte (David Test and Charles Wood) used an SDLMI program with four preadolescents between the ages of 10 and 11. In an important twist, they designed a training package that used multimedia instruction in an effort to free up teacher time in the classroom. They found that these students could learn the steps in the SDLMI program and had concurrent reductions in their problem behavior in the classroom.</p>
<p>As reported by researcher Valerie Mazzotti,<disp-quote>
<p>Teaching students with disabilities self-determination skills has been shown to be an evidence-based practice and predictor of postschool success. This study showed that by teaching students to self-set behavioral goals, make a plan to reach those goals, and adjust progress towards those goals, preadolescent students at-risk for, or with, ED can exhibit reduced disruptive behavior in the classroom. Further, one teacher saw “substantial improvement” in one student’s self-determination skills, and three students’ disruptive behaviors fell into the socially acceptable range compared to the “best behaved” students in the class.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1098300713479575">
<title>Homeschool Communication and Student Disruption</title>
<p>Collaboration between parents and teachers is often identified as key to student success. One aspect of collaboration is communication—exchanging information about the student for parents to support the efforts being made by teachers in the classroom and vice versa. This can sometimes be a sensitive issue because feedback about what a child does at school (e.g., “Angela screamed during lunchtime”) can sometimes be misinterpreted (e.g., “Her teacher thinks I’m a bad mother because of my daughter’s misbehavior”). These communications must therefore be crafted with care.</p>
<p>Teresa LeBel from the West Hartford Public Schools in Connecticut and Sandra Chafouleas, Preston A. Britner, and Brandi Simonsen from the University of Connecticut examined the use of daily report cards as a method for preschool teachers to communicate with parents about their child’s progress in preschool. Importantly, the process began with separate meetings led by the researchers with the teachers, the parents, and the students about the process, and enlisted their cooperation. The teachers then completed the report cards each day for four identified preschoolers in situations that were most challenging for each of them, and used praise and rewards such as stickers for “smiley faces,” which indicated good behavior. Parents were instructed to follow up at home with similar positive feedback for earning smiley faces. The researchers observed improved behavior for all four students following the start of the program.</p>
<p>Teresa LeBel, the first author on this study, commented that<disp-quote>
<p>the findings of this study are particularly exciting given the ease and flexibility of the intervention. Classroom teachers often need better access to effective behavior and communication tools that are less cumbersome to implement. These results demonstrate that the usability of the daily report card can be extended into early childhood classrooms.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1098300713479575">
<title>When Ignoring a Student Can Be a Good Thing</title>
<p>Teachers are frequently encouraged to engage with all of their students to encourage good behavior and better academic performance. However, like anything else in life, too much of anything can be a bad thing. In the case of a student who may be acting up in class to get a teacher’s (or peer’s) attention, it is important to teach the student how to behave better and be more involved in classwork without the teacher constantly having to attend to him or her.</p>
<p>Research over the past few decades repeatedly shows that “function-based” plans that include finding out why a student may be acting up (e.g., to get attention from others), teaching the student better ways to get what they want (e.g., how to solicit attention in ways that are acceptable to teachers—such as asking for help occasionally) and not giving the student what he or she wants when misbehavior occurs (called “extinction”) can be a highly effective way to improve behavior in a classroom. One question that is beginning to be asked is, “Is each of these components of a behavior plan necessary?” This is an important question because with teachers being so busy, any way to simplify their jobs would be greatly welcomed.</p>
<p>A group of researchers from the University of Arizona (Donna Janney, now at Towson University, John Umbreit, Jolenea Ferro, and Carl J. Liaupsin) and Vanderbilt University (Kathleen Lane) sought to tease out whether including the component of this plan that requires withholding what a child wants during the misbehavior (extinction) is necessary for a behavior plan’s success. Three elementary-school-aged students who were referred because of their behavior problems each received a comprehensive function-based plan for their misbehavior. However, each time the extinction component was removed (i.e., teacher ignoring misbehavior), their behavior problems returned.</p>
<p>Donna Janney, who led the research team, reported that each teacher knew she had been reinforcing the target behavior, yet found it difficult to refrain from doing so, without consultation, training, and additional supports in the classroom. Teachers reported that they continued to use the interventions, even when supports were removed, because not only were they using familiar strategies, but they also observed increased on-task behaviors by numerous students, in addition to the one for whom the intervention had been developed. This suggests the importance of determining the effects of the primary components and individual elements of function-based interventions on both target and other students within the same setting.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1098300713479575">
<title>Sticks and Stones</title>
<p>Can words hurt? Despite the instructional idiom (“Sticks and stones can break my bones but words will never hurt me”), saying the wrong thing at the wrong time can indeed do much damage. Teachers need to be especially careful with some students who can—based on their personalities or their past experiences—be quite sensitive to words and attitudes communicated by persons in authority. Authors Hal Holloman and Peggy Yates from East Carolina University describe how teachers can be more mindful of the language they use with students and how they can modify it to promote respect and build positive relationships. Lead author Hal Holloman observed,<disp-quote>
<p>In our research, Peggy and I have observed many passionate and thoughtful educators asking, basically, the same question over and over—“What are we going to ‘do’ about this problem? What are we going to ‘do’ about this student?” Unfortunately, these “What are we going to ‘do’?” discussions frequently lead to vague action steps with the best intentions, but without the sensitive and interpersonal elements to truly make a profound and life-changing impact on students. Peggy and I observed the power of our professional language, and we believe Best Practice Language (BPL) is <italic>the</italic> practical, relational, and structural foundation of <italic>all</italic> problem solving, relationship building, and positive behavior intervention. We encourage today’s educators to incorporate the questions—“What are we going to ‘say’?” and “How are we going to ‘say’ it?” into all PBIS conversations and school improvement discussions.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sig-block><sig>V. Mark Durand<break/><italic>University of South Florida St. Petersburg</italic>
<break/>Lee Kern<break/><italic>Lehigh University</italic></sig></sig-block>
</body>
<back>
<notes><fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1098300713479575"><label>1.</label>
<p>It is worth noting that Ted Carr (1949–2009) was also the leading proponent for the creation of the Association for Positive Behavior Support, and he served as the organization’s first president.</p></fn>
</fn-group></notes>
<ref-list>
<title>Reference</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1098300713479575">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dunlap</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koegel</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Welcoming editorial</article-title>. <source>Journal of Positive Behavior Interventions</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>