<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ISW</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spisw</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Social Work</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0020-8728</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7234</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0020872811414037</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0020872811414037</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A pilot study on a knowledge-based case library to support suicide risk assessment</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-0020872811414037">The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Hong Kong</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-0020872811414037">The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Hong Kong</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>Zeno C.S.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff3-0020872811414037">The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Hong Kong</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0020872811414037">Dr C.F. Cheung, Associate Professor and Associate Director, Knowledge Management Research Centre, Department of Industrial and Systems Engineering, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Hung Hom, Kowloon, Hong Kong. Email: <email>mfbenny@inet.polyu.edu.hk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>56</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>208</fpage>
<lpage>227</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">IASSW, ICSW, IFSW</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article describes the system development processes for an electronic case library, built to facilitate and support the suicide prevention service provided by a social service organization in Hong Kong. It is a knowledge management system in which both ‘rule-based reasoning’ (RBR) and ‘case-based reasoning’ (CBR) are adopted. Initial test results, potentials and limitations of this knowledge management approach are discussed.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>case library</kwd>
<kwd>case-based reasoning</kwd>
<kwd>knowledge management</kwd>
<kwd>knowledge system technology</kwd>
<kwd>knowledge-based system</kwd>
<kwd>rule-based reasoning</kwd>
<kwd>social service administration</kwd>
<kwd>suicide risk assessment</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0020872811414037">
<title>Background</title>
<p>The suicide rate in Hong Kong has been increasing in the past 20 years. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0020872811414037">Figure 1</xref> shows that the overall suicide rate rose from 9.7 per 100,000 in 1981 to 13.8 in 2009, with the peak rate of 18.6 observed in 2003. Although youth (age 15–24) maintains a substantially lower rate than other age groups, a significant increase in this age group from 5.9 to 8.4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0020872811414037">Figure 2</xref>) was detected during the period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0020872811414037">HKJC Centre for Suicide Research and Prevention, 2011</xref>). A timely and quality service on suicide prevention is definitely needed in the community.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0020872811414037" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Completed suicide rate (per 100K) in Hong Kong 1981-2009</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0020872811414037">HKJC Centre for Suicide Research and Prevention, HKU, 2011</xref>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0020872811414037-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-0020872811414037" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Completed suicide rate by age groups (per 100K) in Hong Kong 1981-2009</p>
<p><italic>Source</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0020872811414037">HKJC Centre for Suicide Research and Prevention, HKU, 2011</xref>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0020872811414037-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>On the other hand, recent changes in social welfare policy in Hong Kong, in particular the new subvention system and quality assurance mechanisms adopted since 2000,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0020872811414037">1</xref></sup> have posed tremendous demands on social service organizations, both in terms of service quantity and quality. The organizations are thus facing growing challenges but at the same time constrained budgets and accountability demands. Recent research shows that there are increasing needs for more efficient and effective administrative measures in coping with all these demands, knowledge management being one (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0020872811414037">Chan et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0020872811414037">Hong Kong Council of Social Service, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>In view of this background, a local social service organization (hereafter known as ‘the Organization’) providing suicide prevention services for young people (aged 13 to 25) has joined our research team in developing a knowledge-based case library system to support risk assessment of suicide attempts. This action research on knowledge management in social services aims at experimenting with the systematic retrieval and reuse of social workers’ recorded practical knowledge to support respective clinical decisions, through respective computing technologies.</p>
<p>This article describes the research processes and presents part of the results. It introduces the technical system development approach in which both ‘rule-based reasoning’ (RBR) and ‘case-based reasoning’ (CBR) are adopted. The process of formulating a suicide risk assessment tool that determines the algorithm of the RBR engine is then elaborated, followed by reporting of the initial testing results. Last but not least, the potential and limitations of this knowledge management approach in supporting risk assessment is discussed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0020872811414037">
<title>Rule-based and case-based reasoning</title>
<p>Conventionally, assessment tools, whether for suicide risk or other kind of risks, are used and then attached to the cases concerned and stored, either as hard copies or digitally in the case records. Face-to-face sharing among social workers is the dominant method of cross-referencing of similar cases, whereas learning from organizational databases and artifacts is often under-developed. Computerized decision-support or expert systems have been suggested or experimented with in social care (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0020872811414037">Carlson, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0020872811414037">Goodman et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0020872811414037">Nolan, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0020872811414037">Schoech et al., 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0020872811414037">2001</xref>), although more are found in the health care areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0020872811414037">Alexandrini et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0020872811414037">Chang, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0020872811414037">Chang et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0020872811414037">Frize and Walker, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0020872811414037">Hsu and Ho, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0020872811414037">López and Plaze, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0020872811414037">Trivedi et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0020872811414037">Zhang et al., 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>Most of these systems are developed with the ‘rule-based reasoning’ (RBR) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0020872811414037">Frye et al., 1995</xref>). In a rule-based system, knowledge is stored in the knowledge base in the form of ‘if–then’ rules. With the rules predefined in the computer programs, human decision-making capability (of comparison and elimination) can be simulated by the system. Most suicide risk assessment tools, using the actuarial methods in which an assessor judges a client’s risk level with respect to a predefined checklist of suicide risk indicators, are rule-based. In fact, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0020872811414037">Ferns (1995)</xref> has developed Lifenet, a rule-based tool for assessing suicide risk in adolescents. Its main functions are to help paraprofessional caseworkers reach unbiased and consistent risk assessments, minimizing false-negatives (mistaking high-risk clients as low-risk) and false-positives (mistaking low-risk ones as high).</p>
<p>On the other hand, people often adopt another type of decision-making process. When meeting new challenges, we often recall previous experiences, search for scenarios that are most similar to our present situation, and adopt a coping strategy that worked before, perhaps with modification. This can be termed ‘case-based reasoning’ (CBR) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0020872811414037">Aamodt and Plaza, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0020872811414037">Kolodner, 1993</xref>). CBR systems carry decision logics that differ from the RBR ones. In the CBR view, people do not judge by rules or linear logics, rather they look for the similar cases and solutions. BOLERO, a case-based learning system validated for diagnosing pneumonia is an example (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0020872811414037">López and Plaze, 1997</xref>).</p>
<p>During the discussion of the algorithmic design of the case library system, social workers of the Organization agreed that both kinds of logic apply in their daily practices of suicide risk assessment – that they will be informed by the ruled-based risk assessment inventory on the one hand, and recall and share similar cases that have been handled before on the other. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0020872811414037">Zhang et al. (1999)</xref> proposed an approach that combines RBR and CBR for designing a system that supports intervention strategy choice for clinical incidents, and this approach is adopted here. While RBR design is relatively simple and speedy both in terms of system development and operation, CBR can help suggest intervention strategies that are needed after the assessment is made. It is important to note that such an RBR+CBR design does not only facilitate social workers’ assessment by providing different perspectives and decision logics, but it can also lead to a computer system that helps retain and reuse valuable knowledge of suicide prevention by retrieving the most similar cases and their recordings, stored in the organization databases.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0020872811414037">
<title>Formulating system algorithms</title>
<p>As the RBR inference engine will compute the suicide risk level of the case in query and also feed data to the CBR to retrieve successful past interventions for reference, the underlying RBR algorithm in a way determines the success or failure of this whole research project. Its formulation was an iterative, collaborative, trial-and-error teamwork process between researchers and social workers of the Organization.</p>
<p>The process started by reviewing existing risk assessment tools used in the Organization and others discussed in the literature, as suggested by the practitioners. Many tools have been developed since <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0020872811414037">Beck’s (1979)</xref> construction of the scale of suicide ideation (SSI) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0020872811414037">Askland et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0020872811414037">Beautrais, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0020872811414037">Bongar, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0020872811414037">Fremouw et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0020872811414037">Hall et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0020872811414037">Heriberto, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0020872811414037">Leung et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0020872811414037">Wingate et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0020872811414037">Yip et al., 2004</xref>). Most of these tools cover multi-dimensions and are presented as comprehensive predefined checklists for the assessors’ use. Checklists are straightforward and easy to use. Some are designed for special target groups where a higher validity can be expected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0020872811414037">Bongar, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0020872811414037">Leung et al., 2003</xref>). Another advantage is that weightings can be added to the chosen indicators if they are considered to have special significance. However, these checklists are usually lengthy and some 50 to 60 indicators may be included. Efficiency may be a concern during an emergency.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0020872811414037">Wingate et al. (2004)</xref>, on the other hand, suggest an alternative framework in which a ‘decision tree’ is used instead. A step-by-step guide will facilitate the assessor to evaluate the risk level of the client as either low, medium or high. A decision tree format tool is concise, efficient and can help the assessor to visualize the risk level easily. This kind of tool can be used for quick screening and serves as an alarm system for timely intervention. The limitation, of course, is the lack of comprehensive assessment of the clients’ situations.</p>
<p>To balance precision and conciseness, the team referred back to the system objective, which mainly aimed at a first screening of at-risk young people served by the mental health and rehabilitation division of the Organization. Basically, there are three levels of risk defined in the system, which include high, medium and low levels of risk. As detailed assessment and other follow-up treatment are conducted in the conventional ways, a concise tool free from false-negatives (i.e. underestimating high-risk cases) is preferred. In other words, a prudent approach is adopted in the system design for risk classification so as to avoid under-estimation of risk. With reference to the above reviews, together with existing inventories used in the Organization, commonly used risk factors were revealed. These factors were then further discussed with the Organization’s representatives. Eventually, 15 risk factors (consisting of 29 sub-factors) were identified and adopted for the RBR algorithm. The level of a particular risk factor is defined by its existence (e.g. suicide plan, substance abuse, sexual abuse history), frequency (e.g. suicide ideation, attempt history) and severity (e.g. stress, impulsivity, lack of social support), either reported by the clients or assessed by the social workers. Each factor is scaled to three risk levels: low, medium or high, scoring 1, 2 or 3 respectively. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0020872811414037">Table 1</xref> shows this list of factors, sub-factors and descriptions of the respective scoring scales.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0020872811414037" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Risk factors for the RBR algorithm</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0020872811414037" xlink:href="10.1177_0020872811414037-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Low risk</th>
<th align="left">Medium risk</th>
<th align="left">High risk</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1. Suicide ideation</td>
<td><list id="list1-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>No current suicide thoughts</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list2-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Intermittent or fleeting suicide thoughts</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list3-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Constant suicide thoughts</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2. Suicide plan<list id="list4-0020872811414037" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Details</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Availability of means</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Time</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lethality of method</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Chance of intervention</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Final arrangements</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list5-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Vague or no specific plan</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Not available, will have to get</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>No specific time or in future</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Pills, slash wrists</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Others present most of time</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>None</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list6-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Has plan</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>In proximity</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Within a few hours</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Drugs and alcohol, car wreck, carbon monoxide</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Others available if called upon</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Evident planning</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list7-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Well thought out, knows when, where, how</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Have in hand</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Immediately</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Hanging or jumping</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Isolated, no one available nearby to rescue</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Saying goodbye; giving belongings away</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3. Attempt history<list id="list8-0020872811414037" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Number of past attempts</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lethality of past attempt</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list9-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>No previous attempt</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Pills, slash wrists</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list10-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Have one past attempt</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Drugs and alcohol, car wreck, carbon monoxide</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list11-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Have two or more past attempt</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Hanging or jumping</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4. Stress</td>
<td><list id="list12-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>No significant stress currently</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list13-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Moderate stress</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list14-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Severe stress</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5. Coping behavior</td>
<td><list id="list15-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Slight reaction to loss or environmental changes</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list16-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Moderate reaction to loss/environmental changes</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list17-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Severe reaction to loss or environmental changes</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6. Coping</td>
<td><list id="list18-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Daily activities continue as usual with little changes</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list19-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Daily activities disrupted; disturbance in sleeping, eating, school, work</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list20-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Gross disturbance in daily functioning</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7. Psychotic features</td>
<td><list id="list21-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Mild</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list22-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Moderate</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list23-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Overwhelm</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8. Depression<list id="list24-0020872811414037" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Depressed mood</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Loss of pleasure in activities</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Insomnia or hypersomnia</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Psychomotor symptoms</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Fatigue or loss of energy</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Increase/decrease in appetite with significant weight change</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Difficult to concentrate</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Guilty/shame</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list25-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Mild</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mild</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mild</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mild</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mild</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mild</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mild</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mild</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mild</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list26-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Moderate</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Moderate</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Moderate</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Moderate</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Moderate</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Moderate</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Moderate</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Moderate</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Moderate</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list27-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Overwhelm</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Overwhelm</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Overwhelm</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Overwhelm</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Overwhelm</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Overwhelm</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Overwhelm</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Overwhelm</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Overwhelm</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9. Anger/rage</td>
<td><list id="list28-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Mild</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list29-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Moderate</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list30-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Overwhelm</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10. Impulsivity</td>
<td><list id="list31-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Mild</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list32-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Moderate</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list33-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Overwhelm</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11. Social supports and resources</td>
<td><list id="list34-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Help available; significant others concerned and willing to help</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list35-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Family and friends available but unwilling to help consistently</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list36-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Family and friends not available or are hostile, exhausted, detrimental</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12. Personality traits</td>
<td><list id="list37-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Stable relationships, personality and school performance</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list38-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Acute suicidal gestures in stable personality</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list39-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Suicide behavior in unstable personality and emotional disturbance, repeated difficulty with peers, family &amp; teachers</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13. Substance abuse</td>
<td><list id="list40-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>No history of substance/drug or alcohol use</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list41-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Recent but sporadic episodes of acting out behavior and substance/drug/alcohol use</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list42-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Indulgence in substance/drug/alcohol</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14. Health &amp; medical problems<list id="list43-0020872811414037" list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item><p>Severity</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Nature</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list44-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>No significant medical and health problem</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list45-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Mild illness</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Short-term illness</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list46-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Severe illness</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Chronic illness</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15. Past history of sexual abuse</td>
<td><list id="list47-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>None</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list48-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Disclosed incidents; treatment underway</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list id="list49-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>No disclose; no treatment; repeated occurrences</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>In the next step, the research team suggested that co-existence of some risk factors might increase the suicide risk in a nonlinear manner. Hence, we collected some combinations of factors from the literature and the results were discussed with the practitioners, resulting in the correlated factors summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0020872811414037">Figure 3</xref> below. With the values suggested by the practitioners, weights were allocated for the computation process when the corresponding factors co-exist for a particular case. However, it should be noted that the rules created are not fully validated and they were created for system prototype development and testing only.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0020872811414037" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Correlations among risk factors</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0020872811414037-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The system algorithm was thus decided. The RBR engine will firstly compute the risk scores of individual factors (or ‘factor score’ [FS]), then the overall risk score of the case in query (or ‘overall score’ [OS]). Values of OS and thus the risk level (RL) of the case will be then reported as ‘high’ (OS ≥ 35), ‘medium’ (25 ≤ OS ≤ 35) or ‘low’ risk (OS ≤ 25), unless the correlated factors shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0020872811414037">Figure 3</xref> are found. The three-step algorithm can also be represented by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0020872811414037">Equations 1</xref> to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-0020872811414037">3</xref>:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0020872811414037">
<label>(1)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-0020872811414037">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mstyle displaystyle="true">
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mstyle>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>≤</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>≤</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0020872811414037" xlink:href="10.1177_0020872811414037-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where S<sub>i</sub> means sub-factors and <italic>n</italic> represents the number of sub-factors under the respective risk factor</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0020872811414037">
<label>(2)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math2-0020872811414037">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mstyle displaystyle="true">
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>F</mml:mi>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mstyle>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0020872811414037" xlink:href="10.1177_0020872811414037-eq2.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <italic>n</italic> represents the number of risk factors.</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0020872811414037">
<label>(3)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math3-0020872811414037">
<mml:mtable columnalign="left">
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>H</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>≥</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>35</mml:mn>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>or</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>correlational</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>factors</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>coexist</mml:mtext>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mn>25</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>≤</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>35</mml:mn>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>25</mml:mn>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-0020872811414037" xlink:href="10.1177_0020872811414037-eq3.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>After the computation, the risk profile of the case in query will be visualized in the format of a radar chart, for easier evaluation by the assessor. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0020872811414037">Figure 4</xref> shows an example.</p>
<fig id="fig4-0020872811414037" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Risk profile of a case in query</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0020872811414037-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Built based on the Nearest-Neighbour Retrieval technique (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0020872811414037">Aamodt and Plaza, 1994</xref>), the CBR engine receives this risk profile data from the RBR and searches for the most similar cases from the validated case library. Retrieved case details can thus provide further information as well as possible solutions for the responsible workers to assess the risk and thus design their intervention.</p>
<p>The system prototype was then developed and a trial run was undertaken to test the validity of the algorithm. Completed cases with known risk levels were used to test both the RBR and CBR engines. The testing focused on the following in particular:</p>
<list id="list50-0020872811414037" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Does the system give accurate risk scores and categorization of these known cases?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Does the system retrieve similar cases for reference and thus facilitate cross-referencing among cases?</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Other concerns, such as system response rate and user friendliness, were also taken into consideration.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0020872811414037">
<title>System trial run and results</title>
<p>A training session was held for the users on how to operate the risk assessment tool for the trial run. A step-by-step operation manual was also distributed to all practitioners afterward. A total of 11 cases were used to test the system prototype. Among them, two were actual suicide attempts, while no one had completed suicide. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0020872811414037">Table 2</xref> summarizes some background information of the cases, the accuracy of system predictions and practitioners’ suggestions on discrepancies in prediction. Post-pilot interviews were carried out to collect practitioners’ feedback on using the prototype system. Their recommendations on improving the system algorithms are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0020872811414037">Table 3</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0020872811414037" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Testing results of the system prototype</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0020872811414037" xlink:href="10.1177_0020872811414037-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top">Case no.</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top">Suicide attempt?</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Risk level<hr/></th>
<th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top">Reasons for discrepancy suggested by social workers</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Actual</th>
<th align="left">Predicted</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Correct prediction</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Medium</td>
<td>Medium</td>
<td>Correct prediction</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Correct prediction</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Medium to Low</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>The assessment does not cover negative effect of physical injuries or bad events that happened currently.<break/>This case has acute, severe and a number of symptoms, but since the client has neither shown any suicide intention nor attempt, the predicted risk level is affected.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>High</td>
<td>High</td>
<td>Correct prediction</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Medium to Low</td>
<td>Medium</td>
<td>Correct prediction</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Medium to Low</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>No comment</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Correct prediction</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Correct prediction</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Correct prediction</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Correct prediction</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table3-0020872811414037" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Recommendations from the practitioners</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0020872811414037" xlink:href="10.1177_0020872811414037-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Recommendations</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1 Add new factors/sub-factors: Intention of the client</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 Add new factors/sub-factors: Gender</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 Add new factors/sub-factors: Age</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 Add new factors/sub-factors: Financial situation of the patient</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 Add more leading questions on assessing suicide ideation:<break/> How often do these thoughts occur?<break/> Thought about staying alive?<break/> What is the feeling of talking about suicide ideation?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 Add new factors/sub-factors: Family history of suicide</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 Add new factors/sub-factors: Low/inappropriate self image</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 Add new factors/sub-factors: Negative thoughts of the patient</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9 Include more factors about mood problems other than those mentioned in Factors 8 to 10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 Add a new choice ‘<italic>None</italic>’ to ‘Psychotic features’ and ‘Depression’ to represent cases that have no such kind of problems</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11 Amend the choices of ‘Health and medical problems’ to eliminate confusion of the co-existence of ‘acute’ and ‘chronic’ for describing physical illness</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12 Include multiple methods for committing suicide in ‘Lethality of past attempt’</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13 Add more choices for the lethality method in Factor 2d</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14 Add a choice for the Factor 2(c) Chance of Intervention to indicate the situation that the relatives are willing to help but insisting on inappropriate methods</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>There were nine correct predictions (81.8 percent), and two under-estimations were found (i.e. Case 4 and Case 7). The social worker of Case 4 suggested two reasons for the discrepancy. Firstly, some uncommon risk factors (such as a recent physical injury in one of the cases) were excluded from the algorithm. These factors were thought of as being trivial and difficult to categorize, and thus were excluded in the RBR design. However, when these ‘trivial’ factors were manifested in a particular case context, they might have some significance on the risk level. The second reason was caused by the time lag between when the data of risk factors were captured and when the case was judged by the social worker. The ‘predicted’ risk level was computed according to the raw data obtained at the case intake sessions. However, the ‘actual’ risk level judged by the social worker was determined at the point she wrote the case report. This ‘time lag’ problem, giving an inaccurate prediction, may be more acute for those clients who choose to cover up their information in the intake stage, or those who are experiencing rapid changes within short periods of time. For Case 7, the social worker had no comment on the discrepancy. It is interesting to note that the practitioners gave inter-levels risk for grey areas of risk from their professional judgment (i.e. medium to low). Since there are three levels of risk (i.e. high, medium and low) used in the system development and the NGO tends to adopt a prudent approach for risk assessment so as to avoid under-estimation of risk, the inter-levels given by the feedback of the practitioners, such as medium to low, is considered to be medium risk in the evaluation of the accuracy of the system.</p>
<p>Concerning the performance of the CBR engine, practitioners agreed that similar cases could be retrieved for their reference. However, it was commented that when excessive textual data was displayed, they had to further screen relevant bits of knowledge to be reused. It is obvious that the situation will be even more serious when the number of reference cases builds up in the library.</p>
<p>The relevance of risk factors and the computation logics were also reviewed. All of the practitioners agreed that the risk factors chosen were appropriate. Four expressed the opinion that additional factors should be put back in for consideration, such as age, gender and financial condition.</p>
<p>The research team came up with three suggestions to improve the prototype. Firstly, some ‘trivial’ factors such as age and gender were added back to the list. The significance of these factors is in fact proven in the literature, but they were previously excluded as the practitioners considered them not that critical clinically. For an uncommon risk factor or event, instead of proposing a new risk factor category right away, an open textbox was added to record the data, and users were requested to give a score manually to show its influence. If, upon further review, the respective risk factor was found to occur frequently, a new category would be considered to be added to the risk profile. The second modification was adding more detailed sub-factors, hopefully to attain more precise assessment results. Concerning the CBR retrieval, mechanisms for retrieved case adoption rates and users’ ratings were introduced. While the former shows the percentage of a particular retrieved case that has been adopted as a reference, the latter indicates the average score (1 to 5) that it is thought to be useful. Another more significant concern is the quality of case recording found, but it is out of the control of the system design. Concerning the time lag issue, no change was made in the prototype and users were reminded that suggestions for more assessments could be made during the whole case management process.</p>
<p>Overall, practitioners commented that the system prototype was easy to use. The system interface was user-friendly, the risk level (i.e. high, medium, low) shown was more useful than the risk profile (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0020872811414037">Figure 4</xref>) in assisting their decision making. They thought that the decision time could be shortened, their awareness in risky cases increased and more information on previous successful cases could be obtained. With further enhancement on the RBR engine being made so as to ensure better prediction, they expressed the view that they were willing to adopt the system to support their daily operations in suicide prevention service.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0020872811414037">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Although the prototype of the knowledge-based case library developed is far from completion, and its performance is not yet fully reliable at this stage of development, the pilot project has demonstrated the high potential of the technical knowledge management approach to enhance social service delivery, particularly in the area of risk assessment and management.</p>
<sec id="section6-0020872811414037">
<title>Quick decision support</title>
<p>In conventional social work practice for risk assessment, practitioners fill in paper forms and manually compute the risk score, usually after the interview session. This process may take half an hour or more, and errors in calculation may also occur. With the knowledge-based case library, the computation can be done much faster immediately after the social worker has filled in the electronic forms. With the specific interface designs that help speed up data entry and reduce input errors, the system will help practitioners to finish the task in less than 10 minutes, and with the assessment results shown both numerically and graphically, a quick reference for their case assessment and intervention plan can thus be provided.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0020872811414037">
<title>Risk alert system</title>
<p>The system is built as a plug-in module in the Organization’s existing case information system, which means social workers are required to enter the respective data during their daily case duties. In other words, extra information will be provided to support the service but no extra workload is required from the practitioners. Hence, irrespective of whether the practitioner intends to check the suicide risk, a risk alert system has been set up for reference. When the problems of accuracy and in particular any false negative misreporting are tackled, the system may serve as an automatic alarm for risk management.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0020872811414037">
<title>Reusing organizational knowledge</title>
<p>The quality of human service depends on the experience and skills of the practitioners. While the reliance on conventional face-to-face knowledge sharing among social workers is considered to be highly contextual, efficient and effective, the knowledge-based case library system can play a complementary role. This may be of particular help when colleagues are not available or there is staff turnover, which is apparently common in the highly stressful suicide prevention service area.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0020872811414037">
<title>Supporting other ‘risk-situated’ decisions</title>
<p>This new type of knowledge management strategy in social services may also be adopted in other types of case-based and ‘risk-situated’ services, such as child protection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0020872811414037">Baird and Wagner, 2000</xref>) and services for families at risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0020872811414037">Repetti et al., 2002</xref>). These services share similarities with suicide prevention in that practitioners are required to make timely decisions, and in which multi-facets of the case situation need to be assessed and considered. Provided that the assessment inventory and respective system algorithm are well designed, this approach should have high potential in promoting learning of both the individual and the organization, and in turn advance knowledge of the profession as a whole.</p>
<p>Despite the potential mentioned, the research team concede that there are limitations to be overcome and caution is needed in future work, before this technical knowledge management approach can fully contribute in the manner aimed at.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0020872811414037">
<title>Adequate approved cases needed</title>
<p>Apart from a validated RBR algorithm, an adequate number of approved cases is needed in the case library in order to have reliable cross-case assessment support and the retrieval of relevant cases by the CBR engine for the practitioners’ reference. In the authors’ experience, the case library starts to have better performance when the case number is over 30 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0020872811414037">Wang et al., 2007</xref>). Ideally it should contain as many as several hundreds of cases, including as many typical and rare case types as possible. The term ‘approved’ means not every completed case would be put into the case library, but only those considered as having a reference value for other practitioners should be included. This implies that there is a lot of screening and approval work to be conducted.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0020872811414037">
<title>Inadequacy of the organizational knowledge base</title>
<p>Success of the case library, and in turn of this knowledge management approach, obviously depends on validity of the system algorithm. In the prototype development process, decisions on the included risk factors and the algorithm were predominantly based on the practitioners’ experiences and other internal knowledge sources in the Organization. It is generally a recognized approach in knowledge management practice that respective strategies and activities are developed based on the ‘justified true beliefs’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0020872811414037">Nonaka, 1994</xref>) of the organization concerned. However, in this project, the research team viewed that the coverage and validity of the pool of organizational knowledge should also be carefully examined. As reflected in the pilot results and the post-pilot feedback, inadequacy of the organization knowledge base or the carelessness of not including crucial factors will significantly undermine the system quality. The underpinnings of suicide are always diverse and complex, as well as socially and culturally bounded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0020872811414037">Pritchard, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0020872811414037">Yip et al., 2000</xref>). These factors should be given due attention in the course of discussing suicide prevention and other types of risk-situated services. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0020872811414037">Pawson et al. (2003)</xref> suggest five types of knowledge sources be included when practicing knowledge management in social care. Apart from the organization knowledge and practitioners’ knowledge, one should also include knowledge from the policy makers and research community, as well as knowledge from the service users. The categorization of the knowledge sources is definitely worth full attention in future knowledge management practice in the area.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0020872811414037">
<title>Don’t let machines dominate</title>
<p>From the very beginning of this project, both the research team and the Organization agreed and accepted that this case library system would only play a decision support role in the suicide prevention service. It is clearly understood that the respective clinical decision is a complex human judgment process that should not and would not be replaced. Nevertheless, it should also be cautioned that when more accurate predictions are to be made by the modified system, there could be a chance that the machine will dominate the process. It would be extremely dangerous and could occur particularly when staff members participating in this action research leave the Organization. The newcomers, perhaps relatively inexperienced as well, when facing a system claiming to have stored validated organizational knowledge on suicide prevention, could have difficulty in overruling the machine’s judgment whenever a discrepancy emerges. Hence, the administration should make sure that such understanding on the role of the system will not disappear as time goes by, thus the system users should receive adequate training and be reminded of these issues before they use the system.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0020872811414037">
<title>Possible future work</title>
<p>The knowledge-based case library system developed in this action research aims at promoting systematic retrieval and reuse of organizational knowledge to facilitate and support the suicide prevention service. While there is still room for improvement in the prototype and further tests are needed before it can claim to be completely successful, the research team sees the potential contribution of this kind of technical knowledge management strategy in risk-situated social work practice. With regard to this case library system, three possible areas can be further worked on. First, the reasoning logic of both the RBR and CBR engines should be revised and enhanced. The case library should be maintained with high-quality and many typical and rare case types. By doing so, the system can help record and retrieve relapsed cases for which handling intervention strategies can be different. Second, practical research work should be conducted to verify the validity of organizational knowledge, and to incorporate other sources of evidence-base knowledge on suicide prevention into the system. Last but not least, as mentioned above, by adopting a similar system design, different assessment tools can be developed so that prevention alerts may be established in other service areas. For example, relapse and violence are other serious problems that contribute a lot to the overall risk of the case.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors would like to express their sincere thanks to the Research Committee of the Hong Kong Polytechnic University for financial support of the research work under the Project Code G-YE18.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0020872811414037">
<label>1.</label>
<p>They are the Lump Sum Grant (LSG) and the Service Performance Monitoring System. The LSG has shifted the subvention system from an input-control orientation to an output-oriented one. Social service organizations receiving subventions are allowed a more administrative freehand. Meanwhile, the SPMS specifies the output measures to monitor the performance and the value-for-money use of public resources. More information of the two systems can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.swd.gov.hk/en/index/site_ngo/">www.swd.gov.hk/en/index/site_ngo/</ext-link></p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author biographies</title>
<p><bold>Dr C.F. Cheung</bold> is Associate Professor and Associate Director at the Knowledge Management Research Centre, Department of Industrial and Systems Engineering, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Hung Hom, Kowloon, Hong Kong.</p>
<p><bold>Dr W.M. Wang</bold> is Research Associate at the Knowledge Management Research Centre, Department of Industrial and Systems Engineering, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Hung Hom, Kowloon, Hong Kong.</p>
<p><bold>Dr Zeno C.S. Leung</bold> is Lecturer at the Department of Applied Social Sciences, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Hung Hom, Kowloon, Hong Kong.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aamodt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Plaza</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) ‘<article-title>Case-based Reasoning: Foundational Issues, Methodological Variations, and System Approaches</article-title>’, <source>AI Communications</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alexandrini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krechel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maximini</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>von Wangenheim</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) ‘<article-title>Integrating CBR into the Health Care Organization</article-title>’, <conf-name>Proceedings of the 16th IEEE Symposium on Computer-based Medical Systems</conf-name> (CBMS’03).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Askland</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sonnenfeld</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crosby</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) ‘<article-title>A Public Health Response to a Cluster of Suicidal Behaviors: Clinical Psychiatry, Prevention, and Community Health</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Psychiatric Practice</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) ‘<article-title>The Relative Validity of Actuarial- and Consensus-based Risk Assessment Systems</article-title>’, <source>Children and Youth Service Reviews</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>11/12</issue>): <fpage>839</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beautrais</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) ‘<article-title>Risk Factors for Suicide and Attempted Suicide Among Young People</article-title>’, <source>Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry 2000</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>420</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>) ‘<article-title>Assessment of Suicidal Intention: The Scale for Suicide Ideation</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology</source> <volume>47</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bongar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>The Suicidal Patient: Clinical and Legal Standards of Care</source>, <edition>2nd edn.</edition> <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) ‘<article-title>Using Case-based Reasoning to Develop Computerized Guidance for Effective Practice</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Technology in Human Services</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>2/3</issue>): <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>Centre for Suicide Research and Prevention</collab> (<year>2008</year>) ‘<article-title>Suicidality Among Secondary School Students in Hong Kong</article-title>’. <access-date>Retrieved 8 Nov 2008</access-date> from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://csrp.hku.hk/WEB/eng/pageHandler.asp?id=91">http://csrp.hku.hk/WEB/eng/pageHandler.asp?id=91</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K.T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>D.P.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sze</surname><given-names>A.Y.H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>S.K.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>Z.C.S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Report on an Exploratory Survey of Boards of Directors of Subvented Non-governmental Organizations in Hong Kong</source>. <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Applied Social Sciences, Hong Kong Polytechnic University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) ‘<article-title>Using Case-based Reasoning to Diagnostic Screening of Children with Developmental Delay</article-title>’, <source>Expert Systems with Applications</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) ‘<article-title>Using Case-based Reasoning to Establish a Continuing Care Information System of Discharge Planning</article-title>’, <source>Expert Systems with Applications</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>601</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ferns</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) ‘<article-title>Lifenet: A Knowledge-based Decision Support Tool for the Risk Assessment of Adolescent Suicide</article-title>’, <source>Expert Systems with Applications</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fremouw</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Perczel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>Suicide Risk Assessment and Response Guidelines</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pergamon Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frize</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) ‘<article-title>Clinical Decision-support Systems for Intensive Care Units Using Case-based Reasoning</article-title>’, <source>Medical Engineering &amp; Physics</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>671</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zelazo</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palfai</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) ‘<article-title>Theory of Mind and Rule-based Reasoning</article-title>’, <source>Cognitive Development</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>527</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gingerich</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Shazer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) ‘<article-title>Briefer: An Expert System for Clinical Practice</article-title>’, <source>Computers in Human Services</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1/2</issue>): <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) ‘<article-title>Suicide Risk Assessment: A Review of Risk Factors for Suicide in 100 Patients Who Made Severe Suicide Attempts. Evaluation of Suicide Risk in a Time of Managed Care</article-title>’, <source>Psychomatics</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heriberto</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) ‘<article-title>Risk Factor Model for Suicide Assessment and Intervention</article-title>’, <source>Professional Psychology: Research and Practice</source> <volume>32</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>Hong Kong Council of Social Service</collab> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Report on NGOs Training Needs Survey on Staff Competency</source>. <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>HKCSS</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>HKJC Centre for Suicide Research and Prevention</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://csrp.hku.hk/WEB/eng/statistics.asp">http://csrp.hku.hk/WEB/eng/statistics.asp</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) ‘<article-title>A New Hybrid Case-based Architecture for Medical Diagnosis</article-title>’, <source>Information Sciences</source> <volume>166</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kolodner</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>Cased-based Reasoning</source>. <publisher-loc>San Mateo, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Leung’s Suicide Risk Assessment Tool Manual</source>. <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>. ISBN: <isbn>9889741512</isbn>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>López</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Plaza</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) ‘<article-title>Case-based Learning of Plans and Goal States in Medical Diagnosis</article-title>’, <source>Artificial Intelligence in Medicine</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) ‘<article-title>DISXPERT: A Rule-based Vocational Rehabilitation Risk Assessment System</article-title>’, <source>Expert Systems with Applications</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nonaka</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) ‘<article-title>A Dynamic Theory of Organizational Knowledge Creation</article-title>’, <source>Organization Science</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pawson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boaz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grayson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>SCIE Knowledge Review 03: Types and quality of knowledge in social care</source>. <access-date>Retrieved 3 November 2010</access-date> from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scie.org.uk/publications/knowledgereviews/kr03.asp">http://www.scie.org.uk/publications/knowledgereviews/kr03.asp</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) ‘<article-title>Suicide in the People’s Republic of China Categorized by Age and Gender: Evidence of the Influence of Culture on Suicide</article-title>’, <source>Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>362</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Repetti</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seeman</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) ‘<article-title>Risky Families: Family Social Environments and the Mental and Physical Health of Offspring</article-title>’, <source>Psychological Bulletin</source> <volume>128</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>330</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schoech</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fitch</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacFadden</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schkade</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) ‘<article-title>From Data to Intelligence: Introducing the Intelligent Organization</article-title>’, <source>Administration in Social Work</source> <volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schoech</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rycraft</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) ‘<article-title>Data Mining in Child Welfare</article-title>’, <source>Child Welfare</source> <volume>79</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>633</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grannemann</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altshuler</surname><given-names>K.Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sunderajan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) ‘<article-title>A Computerized Clinical Decision Support System as a Means of Implementing Depression Guidelines</article-title>’, <source>Psychiatric Services</source> <volume>55</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>879</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>C.F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W.B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kwok</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) ‘<article-title>Knowledge-based Treatment Planning for Adolescent Early Intervention of Mental Healthcare: A Hybrid Case-based Reasoning Approach</article-title>’, <source>Expert Systems</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>232</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wingate</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Joiner</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jobes</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) ‘<article-title>Empirically Informed Approaches to Topics in Suicide Risk Assessment</article-title>’, <source>Behavioral Sciences and Law</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>651</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>P.S.F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Callanan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) ‘<article-title>Urban/Rural and Gender Differentials in Suicide Rates: East and West</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Affective Disorders</source> <volume>57</volume>(<issue>1–3</issue>): <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>P.S.F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K.Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) ‘<article-title>Suicidality Among High School Students in Hong Kong, SAR</article-title>’, <source>Suicide and Life-threatening Behavior</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>284</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0020872811414037">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>W.Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) ‘<article-title>A Knowledge-based Approach to Design of Intervention Strategies for Incidents, Systems, Man, and Cybernetics, 1999</article-title>’. <conf-name>IEEE SMC ’99 Conference Proceedings. 1999 IEEE International Conference</conf-name>, <conf-date>12–15 October</conf-date>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>