<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JRM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjrm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Research in Music Education</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0022-4294</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1945-0095</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022429411434460</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0022429411434460</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>The National Solo and Ensemble Contest 1929–1937</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>Brian D.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0022429411434460">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0022429411434460"><label>1</label>Adelphi University, Garden City, NY, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0022429411434460">Brian D. Meyers, Adelphi University, PAC Rm. 208, One South Avenue, Garden City, NY 11530 Email: <email>bmeyers@adelphi.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-0022429411434460">
<p>Brian D. Meyers is assistant professor of music education at Adelphi University. His research interests include solo and ensemble activities, the integration of the Kodály philosophy into the instrumental classroom, and sociological aspects of music education.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>60</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>43</fpage>
<lpage>61</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>8</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>15</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 National Association for Music Education</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">MENC: The National Association for Music Education</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This study is the first investigation of the nine-year history of the National Solo and Ensemble Contests, held in the United States in conjunction with the National School Band and Orchestra Contests of the late 1920s and early to mid-1930s. Primary sources used include letters from those involved with the planning of the contests, meeting minutes from the responsible organization, and music journals from the early twentieth century. Dissertations and research articles pertaining to the National Band Contests are the secondary sources that helped corroborate the existence of the events described and provide foundational information. This research offers a picture of the interest in the Solo and Ensemble Contests and how they flourished during a time of substantial change in the philosophy of music contests. Changes in the rules and format of the Contests also are explored as they affected the establishment of solo and ensemble contests across America, many of which are still in existence today. This work adds to the previous research conducted about the National Band Contests by documenting a little-known but important element of the contest movement.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>music contests</kwd>
<kwd>historical research</kwd>
<kwd>solo and ensemble</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A lesser-known component of the National School Band and Orchestra Contests of the 1920s and 1930s was the National Solo and Ensemble Contest. For this study, I examined the nine-year history of the National Solo and Ensemble Contests in the United States. Numerous primary sources were used, including manuals and letters pertaining to the contests collected from the A. A. Harding Archives at the University of Illinois, the H. A. Vandercook Archives at the Vandercook College of Music and the MENC Historical Archives at the University of Maryland, <italic>The School Musician</italic>—the official publication of the National School Band and Orchestra Association (NSBOA)—and the <italic>Music Supervisors’ Journal</italic> and the <italic>Music Educators Journal</italic>. The following questions guided this research: (1) Who was responsible for the formation and organization of the National Solo and Ensemble Contests? (2) How did the rules of the contest evolve during its history? (3) In what ways did the format, qualifications, and adjudication of the contest change? and (4) What, if any, were the lasting effects of the Solo and Ensemble Contest on today’s solo and ensemble events? Findings from this study bring to light a component of the contest movement that largely was overshadowed by the large-ensemble contests. Furthermore, knowledge of how the National Solo and Ensemble Contest evolved and why changes occurred may help illuminate the ways in which the contest was important in its time and the philosophical foundations for the establishment of such events today.</p>
<sec id="section1-0022429411434460">
<title>The Beginning of the Contest Movement in America</title>
<p>Music competitions have long been a part of music history. It is believed that some festivals and feasts in ancient Greece included competitions for groups of singers and instrumentalists as well as individual performers.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0022429411434460">1</xref></sup> Singing contests are known to have existed throughout Europe, most notably the German <italic>Minnesingers</italic> and <italic>Meistersingers</italic> contests beginning in the seventh century and Welsh <italic>eisteddfods</italic> in the fourteenth century. Early evidence of community music competitions in America indicates that contests for voice and violin were held in Virginia in 1737 as well as a continued tradition of <italic>eisteddfods</italic> by Welsh miners in Pennsylvania and Kansas in the 1800s.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0022429411434460">2</xref></sup></p>
<p>Keene pointed to the <italic>eisteddfod</italic> tradition in Kansas as a principal reason for the desire to provide a contest for school musicians, leading to the formation of the All-Kansas Music Competition Festival in 1912.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0022429411434460">3</xref></sup> Events for school bands appeared in a contest in Emporia, Kansas, in 1916, followed closely by events for solo instruments at Bethany College in Lindsborg, Kansas, in 1919.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0022429411434460">4</xref></sup> Soon, other states began to organize their own local and state-level contests for bands, orchestras, choirs, and other performers.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0022429411434460">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>Mounting interest in contests prompted the Chicago Piano Club and the Music Industry Chamber of Commerce to organize the first national school band contest in the United States, titled “The School Band Contest of America,” in Chicago’s Grant Park on June 4–6, in 1923. The popularity of the contest was noteworthy, but fears about the commercialization of school bands prompted the National Bureau for the Advancement of Music, headed by C. M. Tremaine in New York City, to take over control of the contest with the aid of the Music Supervisors National Conference (MSNC) and its Committee on Instrumental Affairs.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0022429411434460">6</xref></sup> The two organizations began plans for the next national competition and, in his “Third Annual Report of the Standing Committee on Instrumental Affairs” in 1925, chairman Jay W. Fay updated the MSNC on the growing success of the state-level contests and preparations for the 1926 National Contest, stating, “The Committee is considering the extension of the contest idea to orchestras and soloists.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0022429411434460">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>The planning of the Committee and Bureau resulted in the first National School Band Contest, held in Fostoria, Ohio, on June 4–5, 1936.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0022429411434460">8</xref></sup> On the second day of the contest, attending directors voted to form the National School Band Association (NSBA), which was slated to take over control of the national contest in the coming years. However, the first project of the NSBA became the organization of the solo contest mentioned the previous year by Fay, which would be conducted alongside the National School Band Contest. After discussions between NSBA president A. R. McAllister and Tremaine, a plan for a solo contest was taken before the Committee for approval in late 1927 or early 1928. The plan was approved, and McAllister began the organization of the National Solo Contest.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0022429411434460">9</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0022429411434460">
<title>The Early National Solo and Ensemble Contests (1928–1931)</title>
<p>The 1928 National School Band Contest was held in Joliet, Illinois, on May 24–26, but conflicting information makes it unclear if McAllister was able to orchestrate a National Solo Contest for that year.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-0022429411434460">10</xref></sup> The official manual of the National Band Contests, <italic>State &amp; National School Band Contests 1928</italic>, makes no mention of a solo contest.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-0022429411434460">11</xref></sup> However, the <italic>State &amp; National School Band Contests 1929</italic> manual includes the pictures and names of “Winners of Solo Events, National School Band Contest, 1928.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-0022429411434460">12</xref></sup> This is the only mention of a 1928 solo contest that can be found, and I have discovered no other corroborating information. Adding to this confusion are two other items that intimate the initial inclusion of solo events for the 1929 contest. The 1929 manual includes rules, qualifications, and eligible instruments for the solo contest that year, stating that “there will be solo events at the 1929 national contest . . . held under the auspices of the National School Band Association.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-0022429411434460">13</xref></sup> No such notification is found in the 1928 manual. Additionally, a statement in the 1929 <italic>Music Supervisors’ Journal</italic> by Joseph Maddy notes, “An added feature of the band contest will be a contest for solo players of the various band instruments.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-0022429411434460">14</xref></sup></p>
<p>While some sort of solo contest was held in 1928, it may not have been national in scope. The list of winners printed in the 1928 manual included winners from only three states: Illinois, Iowa, and Michigan. The list also includes the cities in which the winners resided. Each of the cities accounted for also had a band that competed in the 1928 National School Band Contest.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-0022429411434460">15</xref></sup> The lack of any additional record of the 1928 solo contest may point to the event being an informal contest limited to those students who were already in attendance at the large-ensemble contest as a member of a competing band. If so, the solo event of 1928 may have served as a trial for the first advertised national solo contest in 1929.</p>
<p>Regardless of the existence of a 1928 event, the solo contest was a major project for McAllister, and it was his duty to structure the contest, including writing rules, compiling music lists, and formulating judging criteria. To aid him in this task, McAllister enlisted the help of several noted educators, such as A. Austin Harding, the director of bands at the University of Illinois at Urbana–Champaign. McAllister’s request for assistance reads,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I do not like to bother such a busy man as yourself, but I wonder if you have had time to give any thought to the selection of suitable solos for use in our high school state and national solo contests. . . . I have the list well under way and have had the inest [<italic>sic</italic>] kind of cooperation in compiling same. I am the weakest on solos for flute, oboe, and French horn.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-0022429411434460">16</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Denver, Colorado, was the site of the inaugural National Solo Contest, conducted on the morning of May 25, 1929 (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0022429411434460">Table 1</xref> for a complete list of contest locations). The contest was open to any NSBA member who had placed first in his or her event at the state level and belonged to a band program that participated in state or national events. As an incentive, each first-place winner received a half scholarship ($150) funded by the National Association of Band Instrument Manufacturers, to the National School Band and Orchestra Camp, later known as Interlochen. Scholarships were presented in the following categories: Flute or Piccolo, Oboe or English Horn, Bassoon, Clarinet, Alto or Bass Clarinet, Cornet, Trumpet or Flugelhorn, French Horn, Trombone, Baritone, Tuba, Saxophone, and Marimba or Xylophone.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-0022429411434460">17</xref></sup></p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0022429411434460" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>National Solo and Ensemble Contest Locations</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0022429411434460" xlink:href="10.1177_0022429411434460-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Year</th>
<th align="center">Band instrument contest</th>
<th align="center">String instrument contest</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1929</td>
<td>Denver, Colorado</td>
<td>none</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1930</td>
<td>Flint, Michigan</td>
<td>none</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1931</td>
<td>Cleveland, Ohio</td>
<td>Oklahoma City, Oklahoma</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1932</td>
<td>Marion, Indiana</td>
<td>(joint contest)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1933</td>
<td>Evanston, Illinois</td>
<td>Elmhurst, Illinois</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1934</td>
<td>Des Moines, Iowa</td>
<td>Ottawa, Kansas</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1935</td>
<td>Madison, Wisconsin</td>
<td>(joint contest)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1936</td>
<td>Cleveland, Ohio</td>
<td>(joint contest)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1937</td>
<td>Columbus, Ohio</td>
<td>(joint contest)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The NSBA held its annual meeting on May 25, 1929, and voted to welcome orchestra directors into the organization. With this vote, the organization was renamed the National School Band and Orchestra Association. The Committee for Instrumental Affairs already had approved and managed the first National School Orchestra Contest the previous week (May 17–18) in Iowa City, Iowa, although no solo contest was held in conjunction with that contest.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-0022429411434460">18</xref></sup></p>
<p>The first announcement of the 1930 contests in the January <italic>The School Musician</italic> introduced the expansion of the contest “to include certain small ensembles.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-0022429411434460">19</xref></sup> McAllister began this project by again contacting various educators and musicians, including Harding, to enlist their help in compiling a music list. McAllister asked for Harding’s assistance “in compiling this list in order that it may be authoritative and most beneficial to the participants”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20-0022429411434460">20</xref></sup> and told Harding, “I will hold the list, which is now practically completed, until I receive your recommendation.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21-0022429411434460">21</xref></sup> This list was printed in the January 1930 issue of <italic>The School Musician</italic> and includes the same solo instruments listed in the 1929 contest, with the addition of woodwind and saxophone trios, quartets, quintets, and sextets, and brass quartets. McAllister also took the time to thank those who helped him compile the list: Harold Bachman, Ed. Cherette, Capt. L. H. Condy, Carl Fischer, George Gault, Capt. A. R. Gish, Victor Grabel, A. P. Lesinsky, Baxter Northup, A. J. Prochaska, Rubank, and Roy Zeigler.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22-0022429411434460">22</xref></sup></p>
<p>Flint, Michigan, was the location of the 1930 National Solo and Small Ensemble Contest, held on Wednesday, May 21. The National Bureau, Committee, and NSBOA continued to be the primary organizers of the contests, but financial support now came from the School Band Contest Supporting Committee, which comprised seven musical instrument companies, most notably C. G. Conn, Buescher, and Ludwig.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23-0022429411434460">23</xref></sup> It is unclear whether the National Band and Orchestra Camp scholarships continued under this new organization. Thirteen states were represented; however, the exact number of participants is unknown. At the annual NSBOA meeting on May 24, an increase in membership fees was approved and, as a sign of the increasing interest and commitment in the Solo and Ensemble Contest, a sizable portion of the increase was devoted to its further development.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24-0022429411434460">24</xref></sup> One week later, on May 30–31, the National School Orchestra Contest was held in Lincoln, Nebraska, without a solo or ensemble contest.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25-0022429411434460">25</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although the previous National Solo and Ensemble Contests included only band instruments, the contest expanded in 1931 to be included with the National School Orchestra Contest. An announcement in the January 1931 <italic>The School Musician</italic> states that the addition of solo and ensemble events to the orchestra contest “will be the most important innovation of the contest.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26-0022429411434460">26</xref></sup> Solo events included violin, viola, cello, bass, piano, and harp as well as trios, quartets, and string ensembles (three to eight players). Changes also were made to the list of eligible band instruments—adding E-flat clarinet and snare drum. Additional adjustments were made to the saxophone category, separating it into Group I (“Soprano/Mezzo-Soprano/Alto”) and Group II (“Tenor/Baritone/Bass”).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27-0022429411434460">27</xref></sup> The list of ensembles also was expanded with the addition of Flute Quartet, Clarinet Quartet, Woodwind Quintet, Woodwind Sextet, Horn Quartet, Trombone Quartet, Brass Quartet, Brass Sextet, Saxophone Quartet, and Saxophone Sextet. Trios were eligible to compete within the quartet categories, and brass quintets were eligible to perform in the Brass Sextet category.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28-0022429411434460">28</xref></sup></p>
<p>With increased interest in the Solo and Ensemble Contests, it became necessary for the NSBOA to clarify further rules, judging criteria, and qualifications. Qualifications for the contest remained similar to previous years, although students from states without an organized contest could qualify through a “preliminary contest”; however, this contest is not mentioned in any other literature. Soloists from the host band (and, presumably, orchestra) also were eligible to participate in the Solo and Ensemble Contest regardless of their placement in state events.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29-0022429411434460">29</xref></sup></p>
<p>Aside from these qualifications, the NSBOA also felt it necessary to introduce rules pertaining to the actual performances. Accompanists would be provided for all soloists if “it is not convenient for a soloist to have his own accompanist.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30-0022429411434460">30</xref></sup> Each performance was limited to a maximum of five minutes, with one point deducted from the total score for every minute or fraction thereof over the limit. Participants were not permitted to play the same solo that they had played at a previous national contest, and each student could perform in only one solo event, although students also could perform in one ensemble event. While it is unclear whether the awarding of scholarships continued after the 1929 Contest, medals were awarded: a gold medal for first place, silver for second, and bronze for third.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31-0022429411434460">31</xref></sup></p>
<p>The expansion of the contest required that the judging criteria receive some attention. Points for the contest were based on the following categories:</p>
<list id="list1-0022429411434460" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Selection</italic>: Consideration will be given to the grade of the number selected, its appropriateness and if the number is one which justifies the study required and is worthy to remain in the soloists’ repertoire.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Interpretation:</italic> Interpretation consists of the soloist’s ideas of how a number should be played as to phrasing, tempo, expression, etc. The judges will decide whether those ideas make a musical and artistic performance, or otherwise.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Tone Quality:</italic> The correct, most approved and most musical tone will be expected from the instrument judged by the standards for that instrument.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Technic</italic> [Technique]: Under this heading will be judged the performer’s proficiency in manipulating his or her instrument, largely from the mechanical standpoint, and consideration will be given to the difference in difficulty in performing on the various instruments.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32-0022429411434460">32</xref></sup></p></list-item></list>
<p>Although the music list had been published in <italic>The School Musician</italic> in previous years, the list does not appear in any editions leading up to the 1931 contest and was instead available by written request. Registration for the event was handled by McAllister, with all entries being sent directly to him “at least ten days before date of the National contest,”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33-0022429411434460">33</xref></sup> giving McAllister a relatively short time to organize and distribute the final schedule.</p>
<p>The first National Solo and Ensemble Contest for stringed instruments was held during the day on May 15, 1931, in Cleveland, Ohio.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34-0022429411434460">34</xref></sup> As an added facet of the competition, the winning orchestra from Glenville High School of Cleveland and first-place winners in the Solo and Ensemble Contest performed in a radio broadcast on the evening of May 16 from Severance Hall, the home of the Cleveland Orchestra.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35-0022429411434460">35</xref></sup> This broadcast and the grandeur of the venue show how the National Orchestra Contest, as well as the Solo and Ensemble Contest, had grown into a notable event in a short time.</p>
<p>Tulsa, Oklahoma, was the venue of the 1931 band National Solo and Ensemble Contest, held on May 20. One hundred seventy-eight students from seventeen states competed in the solo portion of the contest, in addition to thirty ensembles from six states. The June 1931 <italic>The School Musician</italic> paints a vivid and colorful picture of the Solo and Ensemble Contest of that year. Aside from printing a complete list of band participants and orchestra winners, the article gives an impression of the contest’s atmosphere and speaks of the plethora of sounds heard in preparation for the contests as well as the large scale of the endeavor, stating that the contest was “held in a score or more of rooms at the high school.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36-0022429411434460">36</xref></sup></p>
<p>The June 1931 <italic>The School Musician</italic> also recaps the NSBOA meetings held at both the band and orchestra contests. While most of the decisions dealt with the lowering of membership fees from $1 a year to $0.25 for those without a subscription to <italic>The School Musician</italic>, there are indicators of the growth of the Solo and Ensemble Contests. While no entry fee had been established for previous contests, the increasing cost of the event necessitated a fee of $1 per person to be charged for all solo and ensemble events:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>It has been found over the past two years that these contests cannot be supported and continued without additional funds. They are growing in popularity with more and more entries every year, requiring more and better judges.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37-0022429411434460">37</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0022429411434460">
<title>Concerns with Rankings and Competition (1932)</title>
<p>Throughout their short histories, the large-group and solo and ensemble contests had been subject to scrutiny and discussions about problems with their format and operation. According to a letter from McAllister, a special meeting was held in Chicago on June 24, 1931, with “a large number of band directors” to discuss “some phases of the manner of handling national contests which were not satisfactory.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38-0022429411434460">38</xref></sup> Recommendations were made at this meeting and were presented at a special NSBOA meeting on September 19. McAllister’s opening statement reviewed the events that had led up to this meeting and highlighted what seems to be the principal concern of many of the bandmasters: the control of the national contests. The contests had been controlled by the Bureau for the Advancement of Music and the Committee on Instrumental Affairs, and McAllister recalled details from the June 24 meeting that members felt they had neither a say in determining the locations of future National contests nor time to discuss the health and future of the contests. While other items were raised, it was the control of both the large ensemble and solo and ensemble contests that became the main focus. It was the consensus of the group that the NSBOA should be the controlling agent of all facets of the contests (the NSBOA was already the controlling organization for the solo and ensemble contests).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39-0022429411434460">39</xref></sup></p>
<p>A greater signal of change came in future MENC president and Interlochen founder Joseph Maddy’s “Instrumental Music Department” report in the October 1931 <italic>Music Supervisors’ Journal</italic>. He first mentioned a problem with the lack of high-quality literature for the soloists and ensembles: “The growth of school ensemble and solo contests has been hindered by the dearth of suitable literature for certain instruments and combinations of instruments.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40-0022429411434460">40</xref></sup> Maddy said the Committee, with the help of McAllister, was devising a survey to determine what literature should be included on the list of appropriate works. In the second section of his article titled “Eliminating Contest Evils,” Maddy described a new plan of adjudication introduced by noted music educator and former MSNC president Frank Beach “for the Emporia contest” held in Kansas.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41-0022429411434460">41</xref></sup> This plan consisted of judging performance based on five ratings: <italic>excellent</italic>, <italic>superior</italic>, <italic>good</italic>, <italic>fair</italic>, and <italic>poor</italic>, thus eliminating the ranking of performers into places.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42-0022429411434460">42</xref></sup> Maddy wrote, “My own opinion was that, since the greatest incentive of every contestant is to win first place, this plan would result in a diminishing interest in contests because there would be no opportunity to win undisputed first place.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43-0022429411434460">43</xref></sup> Even with this change, contests continued to grow in states where the plan had been adopted. Maddy experienced this plan himself when judging a contest in North Carolina: “The experience completely changed my opinion and made me a strong advocate for the new plan.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44-0022429411434460">44</xref></sup> He cited the difficulty of ranking groups as a significant problem, saying, “Where opinions weigh so heavily, it seems much more fair to lessen the weight of the decisions, and that is what the new plan aims to do.” In closing his article, Maddy said, “I firmly believe that Mr. Beach and his Contest Committee have worked out the most equitable contest plan we have yet tried, and I do not hesitate to recommend it without qualification.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45-0022429411434460">45</xref></sup></p>
<p>The discussions of change continued until the first National School Bandmasters’ Clinic, held at the University of Illinois at Urbana–Champaign on January 6–9, 1932. By far the most significant decision from this clinic and its meetings was the cancellation of the 1932 National School Band and Orchestra Contests. In a piece in the January <italic>The School Musician</italic>, this decision was discussed at length, citing two main reasons: the significant financial difficulties of the time and to allow schools to “prepare their musicianship and fatten their purses for their trip to the 1933 contest.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46-0022429411434460">46</xref></sup></p>
<p>There were other decisions made at the clinic, one of which was the separation of the NSBOA into the National School Band Association and the National School Orchestra Association (NSOA).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47-0022429411434460">47</xref></sup> A second significant decision was the adoption of a three-division rating system for the national contests. In this method of judging, performances would receive a First Division, Second Division, or Third Division rating, each group being a step lower in excellence than the previous.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48-0022429411434460">48</xref></sup></p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>This method of grading approaches closely the tournament idea. It is an acknowledgement of the contention that it is humanly impossible to choose individually between a number of bands performing so excellently.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49-0022429411434460">49</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Due to the relatively low cost to schools and the largely individual expense involved, the NSBA and NSOA decided to hold the 1932 National Solo and Ensemble Contest jointly, with both band and orchestra instruments together. A location for the contest was not determined until March when Marion, Indiana, was announced as the city; the dates were to be May 20–21.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50-0022429411434460">50</xref></sup> The amount of planning needed to undertake such an event in a short time is evident in McAllister’s statement in the April <italic>The School Musician</italic>:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>It is exceedingly important that as soon as each and every contestant has qualified in his own state, he send to me immediately for the enrollment card. It is absolutely necessary that every boy and girl definitely enroll at the earliest possible moment for two reasons: first, the Housing Committee of Marion require a basis for their arrangements, and second, we must know how many contestants will be participating in order to provide sufficient judges and facilities for conducting the contest.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51-0022429411434460">51</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Other adjustments were made in the wake of the change to divisional ratings. Soloists would be divided into three or four groups, depending on the number of performers, that would be “run simultaneously so that all solo entries may be heard the first day, Friday, and all of the ensemble events, the second day, Saturday.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52-0022429411434460">52</xref></sup> The public was permitted to attend concert events for a nominal charge, and the winners were to compete in a final formal contest on Saturday evening.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53-0022429411434460">53</xref></sup></p>
<p>A list of “winners” from the 1932 National Solo and Ensemble Contest was printed in the June <italic>The School Musician</italic>. Within each division, scores were not reported, and participants were not listed in any form of obvious order. It is unclear whether this order was representative of their ranked scores or merely random. For the first time since its inception, the judges for the Solo and Ensemble Contest were acknowledged: H. A. Converse, George Dasch, Ernest Glover, V. J. Grabel, Julius Gross, Albert L. Goldberg, A. A. Harding, Oscar Hild, Guy E. Holmes, Neil Kjos, Max T. Krone, Peter J. Michelsen, P. L. Montani, A. J. Murphy, Frank Simon, George Waln, and M. J. Webster.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54-0022429411434460">54</xref></sup> In an article that accompanies the list of winners, the author stated, “Nearly two thousand people, contestants, accompanists, chaperones, band and orchestra directors, judges, and celebrities of instrumental music”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55-0022429411434460">55</xref></sup> attended the contest, which appeared to be a significant success.</p>
<p>Although the National contest was no longer a true “contest,” top musicians from each event still were chosen by the judges to perform at the “final contest” on Saturday. From this group of 23 performers, one winner (clarinetist Joseph Rosensweig of Cleveland Heights, Ohio) was chosen to receive a scholarship to the National School Band and Orchestra Camp at Interlochen.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56-0022429411434460">56</xref></sup> The inclusion of this final “competition” is curious in light of the recent decision to move away from ranking performances.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0022429411434460">
<title>The Divisional Rating Years (1933–1937)</title>
<p>Members of the NSBA and NSOA went quickly to work planning the 1933 Contests, producing a handbook for the first time with the Instrumental Affairs Committee of the MSNC. The qualifications still speak of “winning” soloists and ensembles, possibly showing that the new system had not yet taken hold in the state-level events. One addition to the rules was the requirement for soloists to memorize their pieces, the failure of which would lower the performer’s rating a whole division.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57-0022429411434460">57</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although there had been considerable discussion during the 1932 deferment year of holding the band and orchestra contests on an alternating biennial basis, both contests were held in 1933, with the orchestra Solo and Ensemble Contest held in Elmhurst, Illinois, on Saturday, June 3, and the band Solo and Ensemble Contest in Evanston, Illinois, a week later on Friday, June 9, on the campus of Northwestern University. A total of 463 soloists competed in the contests, 76 on orchestral instruments and 387 at the band contest, as well as a combined 94 ensembles.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58-0022429411434460">58</xref></sup> While the large-group contests continued to be the focus, the ever-increasing number of students competing in the Solo and Ensemble Contests was noted in the postcontest article in the June <italic>The School Musician</italic>: “At least it must be readily admitted that the volume of solo and ensemble entries has grown much more rapidly than the volume of band and orchestra entries has grown.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59-0022429411434460">59</xref></sup></p>
<p>Locations for the 1934 Solo and Ensemble Contests were announced at the National Bandmasters’ Clinic in January, with Ottawa, Kansas, hosting the orchestra Solo and Ensemble Contest on the morning of May 26, and the band Solo and Ensemble Contest planned for the morning and afternoon of May 31 in Des Moines, Iowa.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60-0022429411434460">60</xref></sup> However, the more important outcome of the clinic was the decision to begin holding the band and orchestra contests on alternating years starting with the 1935 Contest. The planning for the 1934 contest was already under way, and there was no way for the hosting cities to reverse their plans at such a late juncture. While the band and orchestra contests were to be held in opposing years, the National Solo and Ensemble Contest would continue on a yearly basis for both band and string instruments, hosted by whichever large-group contest was scheduled for that year.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61-0022429411434460">61</xref></sup> While the cost of transporting a band or orchestra was no doubt a factor in this decision, the increasing number of participants at the solo and ensemble events may indicate their popularity and how directors and students valued the individualized and small-group performance opportunities on a national level.</p>
<p>A final change made for the 1934 contests was the adoption of a five-division rating system, similar to the one proposed by Maddy in 1932. The three-division system created issues in that the small number of groupings caused judges to place large numbers of unequal performers into the same rating division. Edward Meltzer, a judge for the 1934 orchestra contest, pointed out that the Third Division rating was often reserved “only as a rebuke for insincere preparation,” the First Division rating for truly outstanding soloists, and the Second Division rating was flooded “with those who had barely missed first . . . those who almost placed third, and all the general averages between these extremes.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62-0022429411434460">62</xref></sup> While the Second Division rating had been the only rating of choice for those who were not outstanding or were ill-prepared in previous years, separation of the division into three parts (Second, Third, and Fourth Division ratings) allowed for a better grouping of ability and performance levels that served the performers and ensembles in more meaningful ways.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63-0022429411434460">63</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although scholarships had been awarded in the past, the introduction of the divisional ratings would require a change in this practice. The May <italic>The School Musician</italic> shed some light on how scholarships to the National School Band and Orchestra Camp at Interlochen would be awarded. Soloists finishing in First Division would receive a $100 scholarship; Second Division finishers, a $75 scholarship; and Third Division placers, a $50 scholarship. Joseph Maddy, the head of the MSNC Instrumental Affairs Committee and the director of Interlochen, also introduced four $250 scholarships: the Juilliard Foundation Scholarship, Eastman Foundation Scholarship, Goldman Scholarship, and Sousa Memorial Scholarship.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64-0022429411434460">64</xref></sup> The criteria for these scholarships were not given.</p>
<p>The November <italic>The School Musician</italic> announced a special event to take place in conjunction with the MSNC Biennial Conference in Chicago on April 8–13, 1934. The National Ensemble Contest would involve performances by four different ensembles: string quartets, woodwind quartets, woodwind quintets, and brass sextets. While the contest was part of the MSNC Conference, it was run jointly by the NSBA and NSOA with the cooperation of the Instrumental Affairs Committee. Criteria for registering for the contest were similar to those of the Solo and Ensemble Contest, with one exception. Since most states would not have held their solo and ensemble events prior to the registration deadline, ensembles were not required to place first in their respective regions or states. However, a preliminary contest would be held at the conference, for which each ensemble prepared four selected pieces, all of which appeared on earlier contest music lists. At the time of the preliminary contest, the ensembles would be asked to perform one of these compositions, and groups placing in the top three division ratings (First, Second, and Third Division) would perform in a final concert at the Conference.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65-0022429411434460">65</xref></sup></p>
<p>Ensembles were to arrive in Chicago prior to the preliminary competition, held on the morning of April 9 at the Stevens Hotel. The performance of the winning ensembles was held the following evening in the grand ballroom and was “well received by a large and appreciative audience.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66-0022429411434460">66</xref></sup> According to the list of winners, five woodwind quartets, seven woodwind quintets, twelve string quartets, and eight brass sextets participated, although it is not clear whether this was the total number of entries for the entire contest, including the preliminaries, or the final concert.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67-0022429411434460">67</xref></sup></p>
<p>When the National Solo and Ensemble Contests finally were held on their respective dates, there was noticeable increase in the number of participants. Four hundred ninety soloists and ninety-eight ensembles participated in the 1934 Solo and Ensemble Contests. Results from the band contest were printed in the June <italic>The School Musician</italic>, but string results were not listed at all.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68-0022429411434460">68</xref></sup></p>
<p>The January 1935 <italic>The School Musician</italic> served as the location of the Official Bulletin of the National Solo and Ensemble Contest. Events for student conductors and drum majors were added to the contest, with eligibility under the same guidelines as soloists. To moderate the growth of the band portion of the contest, the rules stipulated that while any string student who qualified at the state level was eligible for the national contest, band soloists and ensembles would follow an “eligibility quota” of one to ten. This meant that only one out of every ten First Division soloists or ensembles (or fraction thereof) in an event would be eligible for the national contest. If forty-five flute soloists were awarded a First Division rating from a state, the state could send only five of those students to the National Contest. However, there were no guidelines as to how these five students would be chosen. It may have been left to the discretion of the individual states, but this was never stated. The music list was similar in size to previous years, and one rule change allowed soloists and ensembles to perform pieces not on the official lists, provided they obtained prior permission from the Contest Committee.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn69-0022429411434460">69</xref></sup></p>
<p>The 1935 National Solo and Ensemble Contest was held on Saturday, May 18 in Madison, on the campus of the University of Wisconsin, and the growth of the event was substantial, even in light of the eligibility quota. A total of 651 solo events and 147 ensembles performed, a significant increase from 1934. There were 113 First Division and 201 Second Division soloists in the contest. It is not clear if scholarships for division placements were given, but three special scholarships continued to be awarded: The Wainwright Camp Scholarship, The Sousa Memorial Scholarship, and the American Bandmasters Association (ABA) Scholarship.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn70-0022429411434460">70</xref></sup></p>
<p>The announcement of the 1936 Solo and Ensemble Contest was not made until January, presumably after the meeting of the NSBA at the National Band Clinic early in January. Cleveland, Ohio, would host what would become the final National Band Contest on May 14–16. It was estimated by the NSBA that “over a hundred school bands from all corners of the nation” would participate in the Contest.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn71-0022429411434460">71</xref></sup> The amount of press that both the band and solo and ensemble contests received in <italic>The School Musician</italic> seemed to have decreased significantly. Following the announcement of the 1936 contest dates, there was no mention of the Contests until the June issue, which includes a recap of the contest, although the May 1936 <italic>Music Educators Journal</italic> does present a list of judges for the contest.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn72-0022429411434460">72</xref></sup></p>
<p>The increasing participation in all portions of the National contests quickly was becoming a significant issue for the NSBA and NSOA. For the National School Band Association Clinic and Annual Meeting in January 1936, meeting minutes note that the increased enrollment of the contests resulted in a greater need for more rehearsal and performance facilities in the host cities. McAllister further stated,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Because of these conditions, we have been forced to realize that the time is definitely past when free housing and free breakfasts can be supplied by host cities. If we want to continue our contests on such a broad scale, we must do so under conditions whereby each band assumes its own expenses.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn73-0022429411434460">73</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>McAllister continued this discussion in an article titled “The Future of the National Contests” in the September 1936 <italic>Music Education Journal</italic>, stating,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>It is quite generally conceded that the national school band contests and the instrumental solo and ensemble contests are becoming too large to be efficiently managed and to give all participants the consideration to which they are entitled.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn74-0022429411434460">74</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The national scope of the contests also had come into question. McAllister continued,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Again, it is conceded that the national contests as now conducted, even with the large number of bands attending, are not nationally representative. A few bands from widely-separated points are able to overcome the problems of finance and extended absence in order to attend a central contest, but by far the majority of the participants represent the general area in which the host city is located.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn75-0022429411434460">75</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>McAllister outlined a plan that would deal with these perceived difficulties. This plan included the division of the nation into eight to twelve districts that would hold their own contests, which would “be recognized as a part of the National contest.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn76-0022429411434460">76</xref></sup> The end of rankings in favor of divisional ratings made a central, large-scale contest less important, since a First Division performance at the district level would conceivably be a First Division performance at the national level. This would eliminate the need for one city to host an increasing body of students and would help limit the financial burden on performers who resided a great distance from the contest site. This change to a more “localized” format also would allow the district contests to be held on an annual basis instead of biennially. The district contests would be supervised by the Committee on Festivals and Contests of MENC (Music Educators National Conference, the new name for the MSNC) and a national board of directors consisting of national officers and each district’s president.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn77-0022429411434460">77</xref></sup></p>
<p>This plan proposed by McAllister undoubtedly was discussed significantly over the following months until the annual meetings of the NSBA and NSOA at the National Band Clinic in early January. While the upcoming 1937 National Orchestra Contest and the Solo and Ensemble Contest had been announced to be held in Columbus, Ohio, on May 13–15 in connection with Ohio State University, the district plan had received a considerable amount of positive support, and both organizations voted in favor of moving forward with the district plan for the upcoming 1937 contests, not wanting to wait until 1938 to make the switch. As part of this change, both organizations voted to become affiliated with MENC, serving as units of the national organization and using <italic>Music Educators Journal</italic> as its official publication.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn78-0022429411434460">78</xref></sup> The nation was divided into ten districts (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0022429411434460">Table 2</xref>), mostly along state lines, and interim directors of each district were appointed.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn79-0022429411434460">79</xref></sup></p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0022429411434460" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Regional Plan State Assignments</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0022429411434460" xlink:href="10.1177_0022429411434460-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Region</th>
<th align="center">States</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Region 1</td>
<td>Idaho, Montana, Oregon, Washington, Wyoming</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Region 2</td>
<td>Iowa, Minnesota, North Dakota, South Dakota, Wisconsin</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Region 3</td>
<td>Illinois, Indiana, Michigan, Ohio</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Region 4</td>
<td>Connecticut, Delaware, Maine, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, New Jersey, New York, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island, Vermont</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Region 5</td>
<td>Arizona, California, Nevada</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Region 6</td>
<td>New Mexico, Oklahoma, Texas</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Region 7</td>
<td>Alabama, Arkansas, Kentucky, Louisiana, Mississippi, Tennessee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Region 8</td>
<td>Florida, Georgia, Maryland, North Carolina, South Carolina, Virginia, West Virginia</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Region 9</td>
<td>East Colorado, Kansas, Missouri, Nebraska</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Region 10</td>
<td>West Colorado, South Idaho, East Nevada, Utah, Southwest Wyoming</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The contest in Columbus was not canceled because of the change to the district plan. Five of the ten districts (Districts 6, 7, 8, 9, and 10) were able to plan their district contests in time for the end of the 1937 contest season, however, the five remaining districts did not plan their own contest and attended the Columbus event.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn80-0022429411434460">80</xref></sup> It is unclear if the preceding districts were able to organize a solo and ensemble contest, but numbers from the 1937 National Solo and Ensemble Contest still indicate a significant increase. The May 1937 <italic>Music Educators Journal</italic> reported that 289 ensembles and 797 soloists performed at the Columbus contest.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn81-0022429411434460">81</xref></sup> This immense growth in numbers points either to a truly national event or perhaps to the fact that the district plan afforded more students the opportunity to travel to these competitions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0022429411434460">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The merger of the NSBA and NSOA with MENC and the move to the district format signaled the end of the National Contest movement in the United States. While the district contests were meant to be part of the national contest structure, the lack of one central contest effectively ended the movement in the larger sense. The contests had served to increase the visibility and involvement in school bands and orchestra across the nation, but that increase eventually became its demise as the size of the events became increasingly unmanageable, for both the organizers and the host city. The Solo and Ensemble Contest was a part of this increase, as is seen in the number of participants in the 1937 contest. In the coming years, the district activities would become too large to be handled in a meaningful way, as happened with the national contests, and the state music organizations would come to be the managers of the festival/contest movement, as they still are today.</p>
<p>The effects of the contest movement on the rise of school band and orchestra programs in the public schools are undeniable. Even in the difficult times of the Depression, the contests grew in prominence, visibility, and involvement, helping to bring more students into the world of instrumental music education and increasing support for the inclusion of instrumental music in school curricula. The National Solo and Ensemble Contests provided a performance venue for individual students and small ensembles on a national scale and may have aided and promoted the value of including solo and ensemble activities into school instrumental programs’ curricula. Rules and guidelines of the contest became more clearly defined during its nine-year history as the number of participants increased, necessitating changes in participation qualifications and time guidelines in order to make the size of the event manageable while also allowing opportunity for more students to participate. As solo and ensemble festivals in the regions and individual states continued in the years following the end of the national contests, many of these rules and guidelines continued to be used and formed the foundation of solo and ensemble events that are held in many states today.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn82-0022429411434460">82</xref></sup></p>
<p>The change from rankings to ratings made in 1932 is perhaps the most significant to music educators today. Discussions of the purpose and value of ranked competitions versus ratings-based festivals, both as part of large ensemble and solo and ensemble events, have taken place on local, state, and national levels many times over the years and still are waged today. It behooves educators to investigate the arguments that were made for and against competition at the national level in 1931 and 1932 because they may help illuminate issues and concerns that still exist today. In moving to the three- and five-division rating plans in 1932 and 1935, respectively, the educators of the time felt that festival-style events better served their students and were more in line with their educational goals. The five-division rating plan evolved in various ways into the ratings that are most familiar today: the ratings of <italic>superior</italic>, <italic>excellent</italic>, <italic>good</italic>, <italic>fair</italic>, and <italic>poor</italic> (similar to the Kansas plan) and the numerical ratings of <italic>I</italic>, <italic>II</italic>, <italic>III</italic>, <italic>IV</italic>, and <italic>V</italic> (from the original five-division plan).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn83-0022429411434460">83</xref></sup></p>
<p>Further research is needed on the history of the regional contests following the end of the national contest movement. Also, a historical survey of the solo and ensemble events in the individual states may yield more information on how the National Solo and Ensemble Contest impacted the development of state events. Because the current research provides considerable information on the names of winners of the contests over the years, an investigation of the careers of the winning performers could provide an idea of how participation in the contest influenced their musical careers. A more in-depth study of the proceedings of the National School Band and Orchestra Association and their various transformations over the contest years may provide a better understanding of the educational mission of the organizations and illuminate their importance to the school music movement in the United States. Additionally, a biographical study of A. R. McAllister, the longtime president of the NSBOA and primary organizer of the Solo and Ensemble Contests, is needed to consider his influence on the development of music education during his lifetime.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0022429411434460">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Michael L. Mark and Charles L. Gary, <italic>A History of American Music Education</italic>, 2nd ed. (Reston, VA: MENC–The National Association for Music Education, 1999), 10.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0022429411434460">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Mark and Gary, <italic>American Music Education</italic>, 271 and James A. Keene, <italic>A History of Music Education in the United States</italic> (Hanover: University Press of New England, 1987), 295.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0022429411434460">
<label>3.</label>
<p>Keene, <italic>Music Education</italic>, 295.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0022429411434460">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Ibid. Events at the Bethany College contest “included events for organ, piano, voice, violin, violincello, brass and woodwind instruments.”</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0022429411434460">
<label>5.</label>
<p>Ibid., 295–296.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0022429411434460">
<label>6.</label>
<p>Emil A. Holz, “The School Band Contest of America,” <italic>Journal of Research in Music Education</italic> 10 (Spring 1962): 6–12.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0022429411434460">
<label>7.</label>
<p>Jay W. Fay, “Third Annual Report of the Standing Committee on Instrumental Affairs,” <italic>Music Supervisors’ Journal</italic> 11 (May 1925): 56.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0022429411434460">
<label>8.</label>
<p>More detailed information regarding the first National Concert Band Contest can be found in James E. Moore, “The National School Band Contests from 1926 to 1931” (PhD diss., University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, 1968), 32–61; and Noreen D. Burdett, “The High School Music Contest Movement in the United States” (DMA diss., Boston University, 1985), 30–39.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0022429411434460">
<label>9.</label>
<p>Moore, “The National School Band Contests,” 96.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-0022429411434460">
<label>10.</label>
<p>Moore, “The National School Band Contests,” 97–98; and Burdett, “The High School Music Contest Movement,” 55–56. Moore provides information about a contest in 1928, including a list of winners and judges for the contest. Burdett, however, questions the existence of the contest that year, citing that other sources state that the solo contest first appeared in 1929.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-0022429411434460">
<label>11.</label>
<p>
<italic>State &amp; National School Band Contests 1928</italic> (New York: National Bureau for the Advancement of Music).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-0022429411434460">
<label>12.</label>
<p>
<italic>State &amp; National School Band Contests 1929</italic> (New York: National Bureau for the Advancement of Music), 56.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-0022429411434460">
<label>13.</label>
<p>Ibid., 66.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-0022429411434460">
<label>14.</label>
<p>Joseph Maddy, “Instrumental Music Department,” <italic>Music Supervisors’ Journal</italic> 15 (May 1929): 65.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-0022429411434460">
<label>15.</label>
<p>
<italic>State &amp; National School Band Contests 1929</italic>, 56.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-0022429411434460">
<label>16.</label>
<p>Letter from A. R. McAllister to A. A. Harding, October 10, 1928, University of Illinois Archives, Champaign–Urbana, IL.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn17-0022429411434460">
<label>17.</label>
<p>Maddy, “Instrumental Music Department,” 65.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn18-0022429411434460">
<label>18.</label>
<p>Moore, “The National School Band Contests,” 144.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn19-0022429411434460">
<label>19.</label>
<p>A. R. McAllister, “Choose NOW! to win, in the 1930 National Solo Contest,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (January 1930): 32.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn20-0022429411434460">
<label>20.</label>
<p>Letter from A. R. McAllister to A. A. Harding, October 14, 1929, University of Illinois Archives, Champaign–Urbana, IL.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn21-0022429411434460">
<label>21.</label>
<p>Letter from A. R. McAllister to A. A. Harding, November 25, 1929, University of Illinois Archives, Champaign–Urbana, IL.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn22-0022429411434460">
<label>22.</label>
<p>McAllister, “Choose NOW!,” 32.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn23-0022429411434460">
<label>23.</label>
<p>Moore, “The National School Band Contests,” 159.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn24-0022429411434460">
<label>24.</label>
<p>Ibid., 189.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn25-0022429411434460">
<label>25.</label>
<p>Ibid., 193.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn26-0022429411434460">
<label>26.</label>
<p>“Solo and Ensemble Events,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (January 1931): 47.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn27-0022429411434460">
<label>27.</label>
<p>A. R. McAllister, “Solo and Ensemble Events for the National Contest,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (March 1931): 17.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn28-0022429411434460">
<label>28.</label>
<p>Ibid., 18.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn29-0022429411434460">
<label>29.</label>
<p>Ibid., 17.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn30-0022429411434460">
<label>30.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn31-0022429411434460">
<label>31.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn32-0022429411434460">
<label>32.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn33-0022429411434460">
<label>33.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn34-0022429411434460">
<label>34.</label>
<p>“Orchestras Compete in National Contest,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (June 1931): 14.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn35-0022429411434460">
<label>35.</label>
<p>Ibid., 14–15.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn36-0022429411434460">
<label>36.</label>
<p>“Solo and Ensemble Events,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (June 1931): 16.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn37-0022429411434460">
<label>37.</label>
<p>“What Happened at Your Association Meeting,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (June 1931): 21.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn38-0022429411434460">
<label>38.</label>
<p>Letter from A. R. McAllister to A. A. Harding, September 9, 1931, University of Illinois Archives, Champaign–Urbana, IL.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn39-0022429411434460">
<label>39.</label>
<p>Minutes of the National School Band and Orchestra Association, University of Illinois Archives, Champaign–Urbana, IL.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn40-0022429411434460">
<label>40.</label>
<p>Joseph E. Maddy, “Instrumental Music Department,” <italic>Music Supervisors’ Journal</italic> 18 (October 1931): 42.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn41-0022429411434460">
<label>41.</label>
<p>Maddy, “Instrumental Music Department,” 42.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn42-0022429411434460">
<label>42.</label>
<p>While current adjudication models use <italic>superior</italic> as the top rating, Maddy’s article lists ratings in this order, placing <italic>excellent</italic> at the top of the scale.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn43-0022429411434460">
<label>43.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn44-0022429411434460">
<label>44.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn45-0022429411434460">
<label>45.</label>
<p>Ibid., 43.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn46-0022429411434460">
<label>46.</label>
<p>“1932 National Band Contest Deferred,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (January 1932): 7.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn47-0022429411434460">
<label>47.</label>
<p>“Association News and Announcements,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (April 1932): 20. The official separation of the organization did not take place until an official vote on April 6, 1932, at an association meeting in Cleveland. Little is written as to the reason for this separation, but the announcement states, “For administrative reasons it would be more practical to have two separate organizations. But you are urged, gentle reader, to keep strictly in mind that the separation is merely a matter of detail. In spirit and purpose we are all for one and one for all. The closest harmony will be maintained between the National School Band Association and the National School Orchestra Association. And even administratively, the annual National Solo and Ensemble Contest will continue to be a joint affair.”</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn48-0022429411434460">
<label>48.</label>
<p>“1932 National Band Contest Deferred,” 9.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn49-0022429411434460">
<label>49.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn50-0022429411434460">
<label>50.</label>
<p>“Association News and Announcements,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (March 1932): 23.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn51-0022429411434460">
<label>51.</label>
<p>“Editorial,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (April 1932): 4.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn52-0022429411434460">
<label>52.</label>
<p>“National Solo and Ensemble Contest, Marion, Ind., May 20–21,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (March 1932): 23.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn53-0022429411434460">
<label>53.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn54-0022429411434460">
<label>54.</label>
<p>“Chosen, Our Most Outstanding School Musician,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (June 1932): 15.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn55-0022429411434460">
<label>55.</label>
<p>“Winners in the National Solo and Ensemble Contest,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (June 1932): 6.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn56-0022429411434460">
<label>56.</label>
<p>“Chosen, Our Most Outstanding School Musician,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (June 1932): 14–15.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn57-0022429411434460">
<label>57.</label>
<p>
<italic>State and National School Band and Orchestra Contests 1933</italic> (Chicago: Committee on Instrumental Affairs of the Music Supervisors National Conference, Chicago), n.p.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn58-0022429411434460">
<label>58.</label>
<p>“Solo and Ensemble Events,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (June 1933): 16–19, 32, 35, 37; and “Ensemble Events,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (June 1933): 38.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn59-0022429411434460">
<label>59.</label>
<p>“Solo and Ensemble Events,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (June 1933): 16.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn60-0022429411434460">
<label>60.</label>
<p>“National Orchestra Contest to be Held at Ottawa Kansas,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (January 1934): 14–15; and “Des Moines, Iowa National Band Contest City for 1934,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (January 1934): 12–13.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn61-0022429411434460">
<label>61.</label>
<p>“Touching the Bare Facts of the Annual Band Clinic,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (January 1934): 7–10.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn62-0022429411434460">
<label>62.</label>
<p>Edward Meltzer, “A Judge’s Impression of the Five Group Grading Plan,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (June 1934): 20.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn63-0022429411434460">
<label>63.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn64-0022429411434460">
<label>64.</label>
<p>“National Band Contest Des Moines, Iowa,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (May 1934): 7.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn65-0022429411434460">
<label>65.</label>
<p>“National Ensemble Contest to be Musical Feature of the Biennial Conference,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (November 1933): 12–13.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn66-0022429411434460">
<label>66.</label>
<p>“National Ensemble Contest Winners,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (April 1934): 17.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn67-0022429411434460">
<label>67.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn68-0022429411434460">
<label>68.</label>
<p>“Six Hundred Soloists and Ensembles Vie for National Places,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (June 1934): 14.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn69-0022429411434460">
<label>69.</label>
<p>“National Solo and Ensemble Contests–1935,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (January 1935): 45–50.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn70-0022429411434460">
<label>70.</label>
<p>“Scholarships,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (June 1935): 9, 40.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn71-0022429411434460">
<label>71.</label>
<p>“Final Dates Set for the 1936 National Band Contest,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (February 1936): 7.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn72-0022429411434460">
<label>72.</label>
<p>“Ninth National School Band Contest,” <italic>Music Educators Journal</italic> 22 (May 1936): 30–33.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn73-0022429411434460">
<label>73.</label>
<p>“National School Band Association Clinic and Annual Meeting,” <italic>Music Educators Journal</italic> 22 (February 1936): 58.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn74-0022429411434460">
<label>74.</label>
<p>A. R. McAllister, “The Future of the National Contests,” <italic>Music Educators Journal</italic> 23 (September 1936): 33.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn75-0022429411434460">
<label>75.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn76-0022429411434460">
<label>76.</label>
<p>A. R. McAllister, “What Next in National Contests?,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (June 1936): 7.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn77-0022429411434460">
<label>77.</label>
<p>McAllister, “What Next,” 7.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn78-0022429411434460">
<label>78.</label>
<p>“1937 Nat’l Orchestra Contest,” <italic>The School Musician</italic> (December 1936): 18.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn79-0022429411434460">
<label>79.</label>
<p>A. R. McAllister, “National School Music Competition,” <italic>Music Educators Journal</italic> 24 (February 1938): 38.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn80-0022429411434460">
<label>80.</label>
<p>“National School Band Association,” <italic>Music Educators Journal</italic> 23 (March 1937): 84–85.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn81-0022429411434460">
<label>81.</label>
<p>“National Orchestra Finals at Columbus,” <italic>Music Educators Journal</italic> 23 (May 1937): 64.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn82-0022429411434460">
<label>82.</label>
<p>The researcher has completed a quantitative study on attitudes of high school band directors toward solo and ensemble activities. A brief investigation of the rules and adjudication of these events in various states indicates that guidelines regarding number of events per student (such as Illinois, Ohio, and Arizona), time limits (such as California, Kentucky, and Rhode Island), and adjudication categories (such as Nevada, Iowa, and Pennsylvania) closely match those found in the National Contests.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn83-0022429411434460">
<label>83.</label>
<p>Variations of these systems abound in the United States. Nevada uses the five-division Kansas plan. Some combine the use of the five-division system with the rating titles of the Kansas plan (including Arizona, Illinois, Michigan, Pennsylvania, Tennessee, Texas, and Utah). Kentucky uses a three-level rating plan (I, II, and III) similar to that used by the National Contest beginning in 1932.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
</back>
</article>