<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">FST</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spfst</journal-id>
<journal-title>Food Science and Technology International</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1082-0132</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1532-1738</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1082013211428219</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1082013211428219</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Amino acid composition and antioxidant activities of hydrolysates and peptide fractions from porcine collagen</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>Jing</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1082013211428219">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1082013211428219">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1082013211428219">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1082013211428219"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1082013211428219"><label>1</label>College of Food Science and Nutritional Engineering, China Agricultural University, Beijing, China</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1082013211428219"><label>2</label>Beijing Higher Institution Engineering Research Center of Animal Product, Beijing, China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1082013211428219">Bo Li, College of Food Science and Nutritional Engineering, China Agricultural University, Beijing 100083, China; Beijing Higher Institution Engineering Research Center of Animal Product, Beijing 100083, China. Email: <email>libo@cau.edu.cn</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>425</fpage>
<lpage>434</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>5</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The amino acid composition and antioxidant activities of different hydrolysates from porcine collagen were analyzed. The gelatin was hydrolyzed for antioxidative peptides with various proteases, namely papain, protease from bovine pancreas, protease from <italic>Streptomyces</italic>, and cocktail mixture of protease from bovine pancreas and protease from <italic>Streptomyces</italic>. The hydrolysates were assessed using methods of DPPH radical-scavenging ability, metal-chelating ability and lipid peroxidation inhibition activity. It was found that the collagen hydrolysates by different protease treatments had different amino acid compositions and antioxidant properties. However, the contents of Hyp and Pro were improved and the content of Gly was decreased in each collagen hydrolysate compared with collagen. The hydrolysate prepared with the cocktail mixture of proteases, which exhibited the highest antioxidant activity, was separated into 6 fractions by gel filtration chromatography. Fraction 2 was further separated by ion exchange chromatography. Fraction 2b with abundant basic amino acids and Fraction 2d which was slightly acidic fractions had higher radical-scavenging and metal-chelating activities, and both Fraction 2b and 2d contained more hydrophobic amino acids. The results confirmed that the antioxidative peptides were rich in Hyp, Pro and Gly, which accounted for half of amino acid composition. This article added further support to the preparation of natural antioxidative peptides from porcine skin collagen.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Amino acids</kwd>
<kwd>antioxidative peptides</kwd>
<kwd>porcine collagen</kwd>
<kwd>radical-scavenging activity</kwd>
<kwd>metal-chelating activity</kwd>
<kwd>enzymatic hydrolysis</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1082013211428219" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>It has been widely recognized that free radicals are generated during the normal cellular metabolism. These free radicals at low concentrations involve physiological roles in defense against infectious agents, in the function of a number of cellular signaling pathways, and the induction of a mitogenic response. However, overproduction of free radicals will result in oxidative stress which may cause damage to cell structures and induce aging and chronic diseases, including cancer, cardiovascular disease, diabetes and Alzheimer’s diseases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1082013211428219">Valko et al., 2007</xref>). Improvement of the body’s antioxidant defense ability through dietary antioxidant supplementation seems to provide a reasonable and practical approach to reduce the level of oxidative stress, and lower the risk of chronic diseases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1082013211428219">Finkel and Holbrook, 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>In recent studies, there is a growing interest to identify antioxidative compounds from natural resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1082013211428219">Astley and Lindsay, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1082013211428219">Shahidi and Wanasundara, 1992</xref>), among which peptides isolated from protein sources have been confirmed as potent antioxidants for their ability of scavenging free radicals, chelating transition metal ions and inhibiting lipid peroxidation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1082013211428219">Sarmadi and Ismail, 2010</xref>). Some hydrolysates from animal and plant protein have been found to possess antioxidant activity, such as soybean protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1082013211428219">Peña-Ramos and Xiong, 2002</xref>), milk proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1082013211428219">Hernández-Ledesma et al., 2005</xref>), egg-white albumin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1082013211428219">Tsuge et al., 1991</xref>) and myofibrillar protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1082013211428219">Saiga et al., 2003</xref>). Several studies have been performed to identify potential uses of fish skin gelatin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1082013211428219">Kim et al., 2001a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1082013211428219">Mendis et al., 2005</xref>), porcine skin collagen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1082013211428219">Li et al., 2007</xref>) and bovine skin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1082013211428219">Kim et al., 2001b</xref>). Extensive researches on optimizing the methods of purifying and identifying the antioxidative peptides hydrolyzed from food proteins have been conducted. However, the structure–function relationship between peptide characteristics and antioxidant properties needs more studies to elucidate. The biological activity of a peptide is widely recognized to be based on amino acid composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1082013211428219">Sarmadi and Ismail, 2010</xref>). The presence of certain amino acids, such as Cys, His, Trp, Tyr, Phe, Met, Leu, Gly or Pro, has been reported to enhance the scavenging activities of peptides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1082013211428219">Chen et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1082013211428219">Gao et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1082013211428219">Pownail et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Collagen is the most abundant protein in organisms, accounting for 30%. Collagen and associated hydrolysates have desirable characteristics for various industrial applications, such as high water retention, low incidence of causing allergic reactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1082013211428219">Hattori, 1998</xref>). Stockbreeding annually produces a great deal of bovine and porcine skin and bones, which are usually discarded as wastes. These wastes are high-quality resources of collagen and with no hazards. Porcine collagen can be a safe and potent antioxidant resource used in functional food if with further studies.</p>
<p>The aim of this work was to explore the effects of different amino acid components on antioxidant capacity of porcine collagen, hydrolyzed by different enzymes.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec2-1082013211428219" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="sec3-1082013211428219" sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title>
<sec id="sec4-1082013211428219"><title>Raw materials and enzymes</title>
<p>Porcine skin collagen powder, obtained from Protein Products GmbH + Co KG., butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT), Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA), 2,4,6-trinitrobenzenesulfonic acid (TNBS) and pepsin (P7000, 800–2500 U/mg protein), papain (crude powder, P3375, 1.5–3.5 U/mg solid), protease from bovine pancreas (crude powder, P4630, ∼5 U/mg solid, protease I), and protease from <italic>Streptomyces</italic> (Actinase E, P8811, ∼4 U/mg solid, protease II), were purchased from Sigma Chemical Co. (St. Louis, MO). All other chemicals were of reagent grade.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec5-1082013211428219" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec6-1082013211428219"><title>Extraction of gelatin from porcine skin collagen powder</title>
<p>Porcine skin collagen in deionized water (5% w/w) was preheated to 90 °C for 5 min, and then hydrolyzed for 24 h with pepsin. Pepsin was preliminarily dissolved in 10 mM HCl solution (pH 2.0). The pH of substrate solution was adjusted to 2.0. The ratio of the enzyme/collagen substrate was 1/2500 for pepsin. The hydrolysis temperature was 37 °C. Samples withdrawn at 1, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28 h were immediately heated in boiling water bath for 5 min; subsequently the hydrolysate was neutralized and centrifuged (10 min at 20,000 × <italic>g</italic>). The supernatant was stored at 0 °C for future assays.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec7-1082013211428219"><title>Enzymatic hydrolysis of porcine gelatin</title>
<p>The supernatant of pepsin hydrolysate at 24 h (gelatin) was hydrolyzed for 24 h by papain, protease from bovine pancreas (protease I), protease from <italic>Streptomyces</italic> (protease II), the cocktail mixture of protease I and protease II, respectively. The hydrolysis temperature was 25 °C for papain, and 37 °C for the other two enzymes, and the ratio of the enzyme/gelatin substrate was 1/50 for papain and 1/125 for proteases I and II, respectively. Papain was dissolved in deionized water, and proteases I and II were dissolved in 10 mM sodium acetate buffer (pH 7.5), respectively. The pH of substrate solution was adjusted to the optimal value for the specific proteases (pH 6.2 for papain, pH 7.5 for protease I and II) before initiating the hydrolysis. Inactivation of the enzymes was accomplished by heating for 5 min in boiling water; subsequently the hydrolysate was neutralized, and then centrifuged at 20,000 × <italic>g</italic> for 10 min. The supernatant was stored at 0 °C for future use. Each sample was replicated.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec8-1082013211428219"><title>Separation of antioxidant peptide fractions from hydrolysate</title>
<p>The hydrolysate showing higher antioxidant activity was concentrated and loaded onto a Sephadex LH-20 gel filtration column (2.0 × 90 cm), which was previously equilibrated with deionized water. The column was then eluted with the deionized water. Fractions (4 mL) were collected at a flow rate of 1 mL/min. The peptides in each fraction were detected at 254 and 280 nm, and the radical-scavenging activity and metal-chelating activity of each fraction were also examined. The fractions showing antioxidant activity were pooled and vacuum concentrated. The fractions were loaded respectively onto a DEAE-Sephadex A-25 ion-exchange column (2.518 cm; Sigma Chemical Co., St. Louis, MO) previously equilibrated with 0.5 M tris-HCl buffer (pH 8.2). The column was washed with the same buffer (90 mL) and eluted with a linear gradient of NaCl concentrations from 0 to 0.5 M (200 mL), subsequently eluted with 0.5 M NaCl (90 mL), then the concentration of NaCl decreased from 0.5 M to 0. Fractions (6 mL) were collected at a flow rate of 3 mL/min. The peptides in each fraction were detected at 254 and 280 nm, and the radical-scavenging and metal-chelating activities of each fraction were also examined.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec9-1082013211428219"><title>Degree of hydrolysis</title>
<p>Degree of hydrolysis (DH), defined as the percentage of peptide bonds cleaved, was calculated by the determination of free amino groups by reaction with TNBS according to the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1082013211428219">Alder-Nissen (1979)</xref>. The total number of amino groups was determined in the sample 100% hydrolyzed at 110 °C in 6 N HCl for 24 h (10 mg sample in 4 mL of HCl).</p></sec>
<sec id="sec10-1082013211428219"><title>Measurement of DPPH radical-scavenging activity</title>
<p>DPPH radical-scavenging activity was measured based on the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1082013211428219">Bersuder et al. (1998)</xref>. A 500 µL test sample was mixed with 500 µL of 99.5% ethanol and 125 µL of 99.5% ethanol containing 0.02% DPPH. This mixture was kept in the dark at room temperature for 60 min before measuring for absorbance at 517 nm. Deionized water of 500 µL instead of sample was measured as control. Ethanol of 125 µL instead of 0.02% DPPH solution was measured as blank. Radical-scavenging activity was calculated as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1082013211428219"><label>(1)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math1-1082013211428219"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Radical Scavenging Activity</mml:mtext><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>%</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>control</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>blank</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>sample</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>control</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-1082013211428219" xlink:href="10.1177_1082013211428219-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p></sec>
<sec id="sec11-1082013211428219"><title>Metal-chelating assay</title>
<p>The metal-chelating effects of samples were determined using ferrous ions chelating assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1082013211428219">Chung et al., 2002</xref>). A test sample of 800 µL was mixed with 10 µL of 2 mM FeCl<sub>2</sub> and 20 µL of 5 mM ferrozine, the mixture vortexed and kept at room temperature for 10 min prior to measuring for absorbance at 562 nm. Deionized water replacing test sample was measured as control, EDTA was used as a standard metal-chelating agent. Metal-chelating activity was calculated as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-1082013211428219"><label>(2)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math2-1082013211428219"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Chelating Effect</mml:mtext><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>%</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>   </mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>absorbance</mml:mi><mml:mi>of</mml:mi><mml:mi>sample</mml:mi><mml:mi>at</mml:mi><mml:mn>562</mml:mn><mml:mi>nm</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>absorbance</mml:mi><mml:mi>of</mml:mi><mml:mi>control</mml:mi><mml:mi>at</mml:mi><mml:mn>562</mml:mn><mml:mi>nm</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-1082013211428219" xlink:href="10.1177_1082013211428219-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p></sec>
<sec id="sec12-1082013211428219"><title>Measurement of lipid peroxidation inhibition (LPI) activity in linoleic acid model system</title>
<p>Linoleic acid was oxidized in a linoleic acid model system to measure the antioxidant activity following the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1082013211428219">Mendis et al. (2005)</xref> with some modifications. For oxidation, 1.5 mL of 0.1 M sodium phosphate buffer (pH 7.0) and 1.5 mL of 50 mM linoleic acid in ethanol (99.5%) were mixed in a glass test tube and a test sample of 2.0 mL (pH 7.0) added. BHT (2.0 mM and 20 mM in methanol) was used instead of test sample as positive control. The mixed solution in a lightly sealed screw cap glass tube was incubated in the dark at 60 °C. The degree of linoleic acid oxidation was measured at 24-h intervals using the ferric thiocyanate method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1082013211428219">Osawa and Namiki, 1981</xref>). An aliquot (100 µL) of the reaction mixture was mixed with 75% ethanol (4.5 mL) followed by the addition of 30% ammonium thiocyanate (100 µL), 1.0 N HCl (200 µL) and 20 mM ferrous chloride solution in 3.5% HCl (100 µL). The reaction solution was 5 mL in total. After 5 min incubation, the colour development, which represents the linoleic acid oxidation, was measured at 500 nm. Antioxidant activity (%) was calculated as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-1082013211428219"><label>(3)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math3-1082013211428219"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Antioxidant Activity</mml:mtext><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>%</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>   </mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-1082013211428219" xlink:href="10.1177_1082013211428219-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>A<sub>c</sub><sub>,</sub><sub>t</sub></italic> and <italic>A<sub>c</sub></italic><sub>0</sub> are the absorbances of the control at 72 h and 0 h, respectively; <italic>A<sub>S</sub><sub>,</sub><sub>t</sub></italic> and <italic>A<sub>s</sub></italic><sub>0</sub> are the absorbances of the sample at 72 h and 0 h, respectively.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec13-1082013211428219"><title>Amino acid analysis</title>
<p>Hydrolysates of collagen were hydrolyzed in 6 N HCl at 110 °C for 22 h. Amino acid analysis of the hydrolysates was performed with Dionex D-300 amino acid analyzer (Dionex Co., USA) by the method of ion exchange chromatography.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec14-1082013211428219"><title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>All assays were carried out in triplicate. Data were expressed as means with standard deviations. Statistical analysis was conducted on SAS (SAS institute, Inc. Cary, NC). All means were subjected to analysis of variance at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 (or <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) to determine statistical significance.</p></sec></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec15-1082013211428219" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title>
<sec id="sec16-1082013211428219"><title>Pepsin hydrolysis for extraction of gelatin from porcine skin collagen</title>
<p>The test material porcine skin collagen was partially purified from porcine skin, with most of fat removed. In the native state, collagen cannot be dissolved even in hot water and showed a resistance to hydrolysis. Thermal treatment of protein improved the DH values. Collagen was heated at 95 °C for 5 min before enzymatic hydrolysis. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1082013211428219">Table 1</xref> shows the effects of hydrolysis time on DH and radical-scavenging activity of collagen hydrolysates by pepsin. Collagen was difficult to be hydrolyzed by pepsin. After 24 h of hydrolysis, DH of gelatin increased from 5.50% to 8.39%. However, most of the hydrolysates could be dissolved in water, and the hydrolysates also had gelatin properties. Gelatin had some DPPH radical-scavenging activity (very weak), and the radical-scavenging activity increased with increasing DH. There was no significant metal-chelating activity for all of the gelatins (data not shown). After pepsin hydrolysis, fat and the deposit were discarded and collagen was purified after centrifugation.
<table-wrap id="table1-1082013211428219" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Effect of hydrolysis time on degree of hydrolysis and radical scavenging activity (by DPPH) of collagen hydrolysates by pepsin (gelatin)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1082013211428219" xlink:href="10.1177_1082013211428219-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Hydrolysis time by pepsin (h)</th>
<th>Degree of hydrolysis (DH, %)</th>
<th>Radical-scavenging activity (DPPH) (%)</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>5.50 ± 0.69 b</td>
<td>11.81 ± 0.47 c</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>5.91 ± 0.86 b</td>
<td>12.52 ± 1.91 b, c</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>6.38 ± 0.82 b</td>
<td>13.37 ± 1.50 b, c</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>6.59 ± 0.97 a, b</td>
<td>16.34 ± 0.63 a, b</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td>6.43 ± 0.82 a, b</td>
<td>14.33 ± 1.14 b, c</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td>6.99 ± 0.53 a, b</td>
<td>15.15 ± 0.98 a, b, c</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>24</td>
<td>8.39 ± 1.04 a</td>
<td>18.56 ± 1.84 a</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>28</td>
<td>8.69 ± 1.96 a</td>
<td>19.25 ± 1.85 a</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1082013211428219"><p>Results are mean values of three replicates ± SD. Values followed by different letters are significantly different by Duncan test (<italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p></sec>
<sec id="sec17-1082013211428219"><title>DH and antioxidant activities of hydrolysates by different enzymatic hydrolysis</title>
<p>During the course of enzymatic hydrolysis of porcine collagen, a natural pH drift (such as for pepsin, from pH 2.0 to 2.3 and for protease I, from pH 7.5 to 8.6) rather than maintaining a stable pH (pH-stat). It was an advantage for avoiding formation of salts of free amino acids. Also it minimized the amount of chemicals in the final hydrolysis product mixture. Termination of enzymatic action was achieved by thermal treatment and this avoided the use of any chemical. All of hydrolysates were neutralized for comparing of the antioxidant activity. The hydrolysate was centrifuged or filtrated (0.45 µm) for separating the particulates.</p>
<p>Although the hydrolysates obtained by papain or protease I showed similar DH (20.4 ± 2.6% and 21.6 ± 1.5%, respectively; <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05), DH of the hydrolysates between A, B and C, D was significantly different (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1082013211428219">Figure 1</xref>). Protease II was the most effective enzyme among proteases to hydrolyze the porcine gelatin, with the highest DH (48.9 ± 2.0%). The hydrolysate obtained by mixture of protease I and protease II presented also relatively high DH (44.9 ± 3.6%).
<fig id="fig1-1082013211428219" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Evaluation of four commercially available enzymes and their different treatments on degree of hydrolysis (DH), DPPH radical-scavenging activity (DPPH), metal-chelating activity (MCH) and lipid peroxidation inhibition (LPI) activity of the gelatin hydrolysates. Gel referred to gelatin, sample A, B, C, D were the hydrolysates obtained by papain, protease from bovine pancreas (protease І), protease from <italic>streptamyces</italic> (protease ІІ), and the cocktail mixture of protease І and ІІ, respectively. Butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) and EDTA were used as positive controls (PC). Values are the means of triplicate analyses, and error bars show the standard deviations. Data with different lowercase letters in the same test are significantly different (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 for DH and LPI, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01 for DPPH and MCH). (□) DPPH radical scavenging activity, (▪) metal chelating activity, (▪) lipid peroxidation inhibition, (x) degree of hydrolysis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1082013211428219-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>All hydrolysates exhibited a significant (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) potential to scavenge DPPH radicals relatively at a low concentration of 25 mg/mL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1082013211428219">Figure 1</xref>). Sample C (hydrolyzed by protease II) and Sample D (hydrolyzed by cocktail mixture of two proteases) showed the same radical-scavenging activity as 2.0 mM BHT (85.3 ± 0.6%). However, all of hydrolysates showed lower metal-chelating activities than 1 mM EDTA. Among the hydrolysates, the chelating activities of both sample C and D were the strongest (55.4 ± 4.9% and 53.3 ± 4.0%, respectively).</p>
<p>In addition, all hydrolysates were tested for their antioxidant activity against the peroxidation of linoleic acid in a linoleic acid model system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1082013211428219">Figure 1</xref>). After incubation in a linoleic acid oxidation system for 72 h, sample C and D exhibited a significant (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) higher LPI activity compared with that of gelatin, and sample B had the similar antioxidant activity as gelatin, but sample A possessed weaker LPI activity than gelatin. In particular, sample D even displayed the same antioxidant activity (85.28 ± 0.83%) as 2.0 mM BHT (84.19 ± 3.61%).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1082013211428219">Saiga et al. (2003)</xref> reported that the papain hydrolysate from porcine myofibrillar protein exhibited higher DPPH radical-scavenging activity and metal-chelating acticity than the actinase hydrolysate. However, in our study, the papain hydrolysate (sample A) exhibited lower activity than the protease I hydrolysate (sample B) in both methods. The difference may be caused by the different preparation of protein hydrolysates besides the different materials. In that paper, the hydrolysates were extracted by four volumes of ethanol (99.5%) to remove unhydrolyzed protein and insoluble peptide, but in this article, the hydrophobic peptides in the hydrolysates may be removed from the hydrolysates by centrifuge. This also explains the difference of amino acid composition among the hydrolysates by different protease treatments based on same gelatin.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec18-1082013211428219"><title>Amino acid compositions of the hydrolysates</title>
<p>The major constituent amino acids of gelatin and all hydrolysates were Gly, Pro, Glu, Hyp and Ala, with small amounts of Cys, Tyr, Met and His residues (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1082013211428219">Table 2</xref>). The contents of Hyp and Pro were improved and the content of Gly was significantly decreased in gelatin and gelatin hydrolysates compared with collagen. Many researchers had reported that Gly, Ala, Hyp and Pro were the abundant amino acids in collagen obtained from different raw materials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1082013211428219">Ahmad et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1082013211428219">Alemán et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1082013211428219">Kim et al., 2001a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1082013211428219">2001b</xref>). Hydrolysis of porcine collagen with pepsin yielded gelatin with slightly increased contents of amino acids except Gly and Ala. In particular, there was a remarkable decrease of Gly (from 21.99% to 12.5%). As a fact, pepsin preferentially cleaves C-terminal to Phe, Leu and Glu, and it does not cleave at Val, Ala or Gly. After the hydrolysate was centrifuged for separating the particulates, the amino acid composition of gelatin was different from that of collagen.
<table-wrap id="table2-1082013211428219" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Amino acid compositions of collagen, gelatin, hydrolysates (A–D) by different protease treatments and fractions of hydrolysate D. Amino acid composition expressed as percentage of the amount of total amino acids in each sample</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1082013211428219" xlink:href="10.1177_1082013211428219-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th/>
<th align="center" colspan="9">Composition (%)<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th rowspan="2">Amino acid</th>
<th rowspan="2">Collagen</th>
<th rowspan="2">Gelatin</th>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Hydrolysates of gelatin<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Fractions of hydrolysate D<hr/></th></tr>
<tr><th>A</th>
<th>B</th>
<th>C</th>
<th>D</th>
<th>2b</th>
<th>2d</th>
<th>2f</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Hyp</td>
<td>9.06</td>
<td>10.15</td>
<td>10.19</td>
<td>10.39</td>
<td>11.42</td>
<td>19.24</td>
<td>16.14</td>
<td>17.40</td>
<td>15.45</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Asp</td>
<td>6.21</td>
<td>7.16</td>
<td>6.59</td>
<td>6.20</td>
<td>5.22</td>
<td>4.86</td>
<td>1.21</td>
<td>7.75</td>
<td>13.61</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Thr</td>
<td>2.20</td>
<td>2.33</td>
<td>2.24</td>
<td>2.40</td>
<td>1.93</td>
<td>1.96</td>
<td>0.46</td>
<td>1.49</td>
<td>1.67</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Ser</td>
<td>3.57</td>
<td>3.86</td>
<td>3.86</td>
<td>3.86</td>
<td>3.32</td>
<td>3.15</td>
<td>2.89</td>
<td>4.44</td>
<td>3.38</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Glu</td>
<td>10.45</td>
<td>11.27</td>
<td>11.20</td>
<td>11.51</td>
<td>11.21</td>
<td>10.54</td>
<td>2.67</td>
<td>15.62</td>
<td>22.39</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Pro</td>
<td>10.07</td>
<td>12.04</td>
<td>12.37</td>
<td>11.81</td>
<td>13.53</td>
<td>12.11</td>
<td>28.72</td>
<td>14.76</td>
<td>10.27</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Gly</td>
<td>21.99</td>
<td>13.50</td>
<td>13.99</td>
<td>14.30</td>
<td>16.57</td>
<td>14.52</td>
<td>16.14</td>
<td>19.36</td>
<td>22.24</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Ala</td>
<td>8.78</td>
<td>8.49</td>
<td>8.85</td>
<td>8.81</td>
<td>8.68</td>
<td>8.16</td>
<td>3.06</td>
<td>6.05</td>
<td>5.01</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Cys</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>0.44</td>
<td>0.43</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>0.85</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Val</td>
<td>3.47</td>
<td>3.59</td>
<td>3.69</td>
<td>3.52</td>
<td>3.29</td>
<td>3.22</td>
<td>0.38</td>
<td>0.80</td>
<td>0.90</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Met</td>
<td>0.90</td>
<td>1.19</td>
<td>1.27</td>
<td>1.35</td>
<td>1.24</td>
<td>0.72</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.59</td>
<td>0.00</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Ile</td>
<td>1.68</td>
<td>1.81</td>
<td>1.69</td>
<td>1.91</td>
<td>1.60</td>
<td>1.61</td>
<td>0.50</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>0.00</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Leu</td>
<td>3.87</td>
<td>4.33</td>
<td>4.26</td>
<td>3.98</td>
<td>2.79</td>
<td>2.51</td>
<td>1.48</td>
<td>1.90</td>
<td>1.07</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Tyr</td>
<td>1.13</td>
<td>1.28</td>
<td>1.26</td>
<td>1.17</td>
<td>1.11</td>
<td>0.94</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Phe</td>
<td>2.38</td>
<td>2.66</td>
<td>2.58</td>
<td>2.58</td>
<td>2.17</td>
<td>2.03</td>
<td>0.62</td>
<td>0.58</td>
<td>0.00</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>His</td>
<td>1.18</td>
<td>1.33</td>
<td>1.30</td>
<td>1.24</td>
<td>0.97</td>
<td>0.85</td>
<td>1.24</td>
<td>0.84</td>
<td>0.63</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Lys</td>
<td>4.36</td>
<td>4.62</td>
<td>4.73</td>
<td>4.82</td>
<td>4.79</td>
<td>4.31</td>
<td>13.08</td>
<td>2.01</td>
<td>0.69</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Arg</td>
<td>7.79</td>
<td>8.75</td>
<td>8.39</td>
<td>8.26</td>
<td>7.06</td>
<td>6.51</td>
<td>10.91</td>
<td>4.77</td>
<td>0.92</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Although the main amino acids consisting of gelatin and all the four hydrolysates were basically the same, the amino acid compositions of hydrolysates by different protease treatments were different. Upon hydrolysis with different proteases respectively, an increase in Hyp, Pro and Gly appeared in four hydrolysates compared with gelatin (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1082013211428219">Table 2</xref>). It is worth noting that the content of Gly increased, especially that of sample C was up to 16.57%. However, sulfur-containing amino acids (Cys and Met), and aromatic amino acids (Phe, Tyr) and His, which were regarded as potent amino acids contributing to the antioxidant property of peptides, were presented low contents in hydrolysates. The lack of these amino acids may be attributed to the inherent characters of porcine skin collagen. However, the peptides in the four hydrolysates by different protease treatments may be different in the structure and length, because different proteases preferentially cleaved different sides of amino acids in the peptide linkages. Then peptides with different length and peptide sequences contributed to different antioxidant activities. As for differences in amino acid composition among hydrolysates, it might arise from different peptides remaining in the supernatant after the centrifugation step. The centrifugation step should be crucial for differentiating the amino acid composition of hydrolysates.</p>
<p>Sample A and sample B, exhibited no significant difference on DH, so it can be deduced that the amino acid composition and peptide sequence should be responsible for the different antioxidant properties between sample A and B (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1082013211428219">Figure 1</xref>). Sample A containing relatively higher contents of Asp, Tyr, His and Arg exhibited metal-chelating activity twice as strong as sample B. All of these amino acids (Asp, Tyr, His and Arg) have electronic properties, and it was known that carboxyl of acidic amino acid and hydroxyl of some amino acids were the proposed binding sites for metal ion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1082013211428219">Wang et al., 2009</xref>). Chelating peptides were enriched in certain amino acids, such as His and Arg (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1082013211428219">Megías et al., 2008</xref>). It was proposed that the antioxidant activity of His-containing peptides was in relation with the metal-ion-chelating ability of the imidazole group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1082013211428219">Sarmadi and Ismail, 2010</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1082013211428219">Pownall et al. (2010)</xref> proposed that fractions rich in aromatic amino acids (Phe, Tyr and Trp) exhibited relatively high chelating activity.</p>
<p>On the other hand, sample B had higher abilities on scavenging DPPH radicals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1082013211428219">Figure 1</xref>) compared with sample A. Sample B contained higher contents of Ile, Met, Hyp, Thr and Gly. It was said that certain hydrophobic amino acids (such as Ile and Met) could donate electrons or hydrogen, thereby converting the radical to a more stable species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1082013211428219">Pownall et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1082013211428219">Saiga et al., 2003</xref>). This property could contribute to higher radical-scavenging activity of Sample B.</p>
<p>Gly was the most abundant amino acid in sample C (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1082013211428219">Table 2</xref>), while sample D contained significantly higher content of Hyp (19.24%). Furthermore, both sample C and D were rich in Pro. The contents of some amino acids (Thr, Val, Ile, Phe, Cys) between sample C and D were similar. In particular, Cys was not observed in sample C and D. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1082013211428219">Figure 1</xref>, sample C and D displayed similar metal-chelating activity and DPPH radical-scavenging activity.</p>
<p>The antioxidant activities of protein hydrolysates are not only affected by amino acid composition, but also influenced by the degree of hydrolysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1082013211428219">Li et al., 2007</xref>). In this study, the DH of sample C and D were higher than that of sample A and B.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec19-1082013211428219"><title>Separation of antioxidative peptide fractions from the hydrolysate by serial chromatography</title>
<p>To isolate and characterize the antioxidative peptides in the hydrolysates, peptides in sample D were separated by serial chromatography. The hydrolysate D was initially separated into six fractions (1–6) on Sephadex LH-20 gel filtration column. Fraction 2 showed strong radical-scavenging and metal-chelating activities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1082013211428219">Figure 2(a)</xref>). Fraction 2 was pooled apart according to the peak and vacuum concentrated, and then was loaded onto a DEAE-Sephadex A-25 ion exchange column. The peptides in Fraction 2 were further separated into six fractions (2a–2f) as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1082013211428219">Figure 2(b)</xref>. The antioxidant activities of peptide fractions from hydrolysate D were measured.
<fig id="fig2-1082013211428219" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Separation scheme of antioxidative peptide obtained from cocktail hydrolysate of porcine skin collagen (sample D) by chromatography. (a) Gel filtration chromatography on a Sephadex LH-20 column. The sample was separated into six fractions (Fraction 1–6) and tested for radical-scavenging activities of DPPH and metal-chetaling activities. (b) Ion-exchange chromatography on DEAE-Sephadex A-25 of Fraction 2. Fraction 2 obtained from gel ﬁltration chromatography was separated into six fractions and tested for DPPH radical-scavenging activities and metal-chelating activities. (○)absorbance at 254 nm; (×) DPPH; (▴) MCH.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1082013211428219-fig2a.tif"/><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1082013211428219-fig2b.tif"/></fig>
</p>
<p>Fraction 2d possessed the strongest activity for scavenging DPPH radical, followed by Fraction 2b, whereas Fraction 2a, 2c and 2f presented lower activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1082013211428219">Figure 2(b)</xref>). Fraction 2 scavenged closing to 90% of DPPH radicals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1082013211428219">Figure 2(a)</xref>). However, the further separated fractions did not show enhanced radical-scavenging activity, because the concentration of sample loaded onto ion exchange column decreased and the purified fractions were diluted significantly. Four of six sub-fractions (Fraction 2b–2e) showed very strong metal-chelating activity, and Fraction 2a and 2f displayed weak metal-chelating activity.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec20-1082013211428219"><title>Amino acid compositions of peptide fractions versus antioxidant activities</title>
<p>The amino acid compositions of hydrolysate D and several peptide fractions (2b, 2d, 2f) were compared to investigate the effects of amino acid compositions on antioxidant activities. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1082013211428219">Table 2</xref>, Gly, Hyp and Pro were the most abundant amino acids in the three fractions, the sum of them account for half (or more) of the amino acid composition. Acidic amino acids (Asp and Glu) increased in percentage as the retention time of the fractions increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1082013211428219">Figure 2(b)</xref>), and Fraction 2f had the richest acidic amino acids. In contrary, basic amino acids (Arg, His and Lys) decreased in content from Fraction 2b to 2f, and Fraction 2b had the richest basic amino acids. Fraction 2d was lightly acidic fraction containing some acidic amino acids and basic amino acids. Besides, higher contents of hydrophobic amino acids (Pro, Ile, Leu, Ala, Phe) were observed in Fraction 2b and 2d than 2f (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1082013211428219">Table 2</xref>), and other hydrophobic amino acids, such as Met, Tyr, Ile and Phe, were not detected in Fraction 2f. From the results, we can see that the basic fraction (2b) and lightly acidic fraction (2d) had higher radical-scavenging and metal-chelating activities than acidic fraction (2f). Some peptides that included basic amino acid residues such as His and Lys possessed high radical-scavenging activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1082013211428219">Chen et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1082013211428219">Tsuge et al., 1991</xref>), but in this study, lightly acidic fraction (2d) exhibited higher radical-scavenging activity than the main basic fraction (2b).</p>
<p>Generally, the quenching of free radicals has been attributed to the donation of hydrogen, and some amino acids such as His, Cys, Tyr and Met, enhanced the scavenging activities of peptides. The identified radical-scavenging peptides obtained from the β-Lactoglobulin hydrolysate contained Trp, Tyr, Met and His, and Met was speculated prone to oxidation of the Met sulfoxide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1082013211428219">Hernández-Ledesma et al., 2005</xref>). The amino acids with aromatic residues (Trp, Tyr and Phe) could donate protons to electron-deficient radicals, and this property improved the radical-scavenging properties of the amino acid residues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1082013211428219">Sarmadi and Ismail, 2010</xref>). As a hydrophobic amino acid, Leu and Met had been reported for their contribution to antioxidant activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1082013211428219">Gao et al., 2010</xref>). Histidine was another outstanding amino acid attributing to antioxidant activities due to the proton-donation ability of the His imidazole group in many peptides, such as soybean hydrolysate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1082013211428219">Chen et al., 1995</xref>), and egg white albumin hydrolysate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1082013211428219">Tsuge et al., 1991</xref>). It has also been reported that His and Pro played important roles in the antioxidant activities of peptides, and among the tested peptides, Pro–His–His was the most antioxidative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1082013211428219">Chen et al., 1996</xref>).</p>
<p>It was noted that Fraction 2b had no content of Cys, Met and Tyr, which were recognized as effective radical scavengers, and it might be the cause that the radical-scavenging activity of Fraction 2b was lower than that of Fraction 2d. Besides, compared with Fraction 2f, Fraction 2b and 2d contained relatively higher contents of Hyp, Gly and Pro. Kim et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1082013211428219">2001a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1082013211428219">2001b</xref>) isolated gelatin-derived antioxidative peptides containing the Gly–Pro–Hyp sequence from marine fish and bovine skin. The strong radical-scavenging peptide from Hoki fish skin (His–Gly–Pro–Leu–Gly–Pro–Leu) also produced Gly–Pro amino acid residues with the exception of His (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1082013211428219">Mendis et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>In summary, the results indicated that a combination of His and some certain hydrophobic amino acids (Pro, Phe, Met and Leu), may have contributed to the radical-scavenging activity of Fraction 2b and 2d. The sequence Gly–Pro–X such as Gly–Pro–Hyp also played an important role in the antioxidative peptides.</p>
<p>Enzymatic hydrolysis of food protein can release peptides that are able to chelate with metal and show different biological activities. For example, peptides hydrolyzed from casein have been shown to bind and increase calcium absorption in the intestine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1082013211428219">Sato et al., 1986</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1082013211428219">Megías et al. (2007)</xref> identified copper-chelating peptides from chickpea protein hydrolysates. From the results, Fraction 2b and 2d had significantly high metal-chelating activities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1082013211428219">Figure 2(b)</xref>). It was known that the special amino acids of the peptides during proteolytic digestion, such as Glu, Asp and His could form soluble complexes with iron and enhance iron absorption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1082013211428219">Storcksdieck et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1082013211428219">Swain et al., 2002</xref>). It was well understood that Fraction 2d had abundant acidic amino acids as well as basic amino acids and showed high metal-chelating activity. Fraction 2b had highest content of basic amino acids which also showed high metal-chelating activity. It was consistent with the results of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1082013211428219">Megías et al. (2008)</xref>. The latter reported that peptides purified with afﬁnity chromatography containing high contents of basic amino acids (His and Arg) possessed higher copper-chelating activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1082013211428219">Megías et al., 2008</xref><bold>)</bold>.</p>
<p>Glutathione is a well-known antioxidative peptide; however, fraction 2f, which contained the richest acidic amino acids (Asp and Glu) and relatively high content of Cys among three fractions, possessed the lowest metal-chelating activity. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1082013211428219">Pownail et al. (2010)</xref> observed negligible metal-chelating activity of glutathione containing Cys. The results implied that not only the amounts of metal-chelating amino acids (His, Glu, Asp), but also the amino acid sequence had an important impact on the metal-chelating ability of peptides.</p>
<p>It is well known that collagen is one of the most plentiful proteins present in the bodies of mammals and plays a significant role in physiology. In fact, it connects and supports other bodily tissues, such as skin, bone, tendons and muscles. Collagen working with the extracellular matrix plays an important role in the force transmission and bone structure maintenance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1082013211428219">Tzaphlidou, 2005</xref>). Collagen also works with keratin to provide the skin with strength, flexibility and resilience. In addition, collagen also has many biomedical applications, such as skin replacement, bone substitutes and artificial blood vessels and valves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1082013211428219">Lee et al., 2001</xref>). Collagens from different resources have excellent biocompatibility and weak antigenecity. As for the peptides isolated from collagen hydrolysate, because they are easily absorbed, especially possess antioxidant activities and typical amino acid composition of collagen, they could be applied in cosmetics and nurtures with many biological functions of collagen.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec21-1082013211428219" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Basic amino acids contributed more to donating hydrogen or chelating (metal) than acid amino acids, and the amounts of basic amino acids were related to the antioxidant activities of peptides. This work also suggested that collagen-derived peptides are rich in collagen special amino acids, such as Hyp, Pro and Gly, and should also possess the properties of collagen, which may benefit the applications of collagen. The findings of this study should be useful in proper utilization of porcine collagen in functional food products and cosmetics.</p></sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec22-1082013211428219"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This work is financially supported by the National Natural science Foundation Committee of People’s Republic of China (No 20976205).</p></sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Benjakul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nalinanon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Compositional and physicochemical characteristics of acid solubilized collagen extracted from the skin of unicorn leatherjacket (<italic>Aluterus monoceros</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Food Hydrocolloids</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>6-7</issue>): <fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>594</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alder-Nissen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Determination of the degree of hydrolysis of food protein hydrolysates by trinitrobenzenesulfonic acid</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1256</fpage>–<lpage>1262</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alemán</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giménez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Montero</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gómez-Guillén</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant activity of several marine skin gelatins</article-title>. <source>LWT - Food Science and Technology</source> <volume>44</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Astley</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>European research on functional effects of dietary antioxidants</article-title>. <source>Molecular Aspects of Medicine</source> <volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bersuder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hole</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Antioxidants from a heated histidine-glucose model system. I: Investigation of the antioxidant role of histidine and isolation of antioxidants by high-performance liquid chromatography</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Oil Chemists’ Society</source> <volume>75</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Muramoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Structural analysis of antioxidative peptides from soybean β-conglycinin</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source> <volume>43</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>574</fpage>–<lpage>578</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Muramoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nokihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant activity of designed peptides based on the antioxidative peptide isolated from digests of a soybean protein</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source> <volume>44</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>2619</fpage>–<lpage>2623</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Antioxidative activity and safety of the 50 ethanolic extract from red bean fermented by Bacillus subtilis IMR-NK1</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source> <volume>50</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>2454</fpage>–<lpage>2458</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finkel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Holbrook</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Oxidants, oxidative stress and the biology of ageing</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>408</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant activity of peptide fractions derived from cottonseed protein hydrolysate</article-title>. <source>Journal of Science of Food and Agriculture</source> <volume>90</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>1855</fpage>–<lpage>1860</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Collagen—molecular assemble and its application</article-title>. <source>High Polymers <italic>(Japan)</italic></source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>394</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hernández-Ledesma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dávalos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartolomé</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Amigo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Preparation of antioxidant enzymatic hydrolysates from α-Lactalbumin and β-Lactoglobulin. Identification of active peptides by HPLC-MS/MS</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source> <volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>593</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Joo</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahidi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001a</year>). <article-title>Isolation and characterization of antioxidative peptides from gelatin hydrolysate of Alaska pollack skin</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source> <volume>49</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1984</fpage>–<lpage>1989</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001b</year>). <article-title>Purification and characterization of antioxidative peptides from bovine skin</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Singla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Biomedical applications of collagen</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Pharmaceutics</source> <volume>221</volume>(<issue>1-2</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Isolation and identification of antioxidative peptides from porcine collagen hydrolysate by consecutive chromatography and electrospray ionization-mass spectrometry</article-title>. <source>Food Chemistry</source> <volume>102</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1135</fpage>–<lpage>1143</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Megías</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedroche</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yust</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Girón-Calle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Alaiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Millan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Affinity purification of copper chelating peptides from chickpea protein hydrolysates</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source> <volume>55</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>3349</fpage>–<lpage>3954</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Megías</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedroche</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yust</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Girón-Calle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Alaiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Millan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Production of copper-chelating peptides after hydrolysis of sunflower proteins with pepsin and pancreatin</article-title>. <source>LWT-Food Science Technology</source> <volume>41</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1973</fpage>–<lpage>1977</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajapakse</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant properties of a radical-scavenging peptide purified from enzymatically prepared fish skin gelatin hydrolysate</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source> <volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>587</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Namiki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>A Novel type of antioxidant isolated from leaf wax of eucalyptus leaves</article-title>. <source>Agricultural and Biological Chemistry</source> <volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>739</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peña-Ramos</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant activity of soy protein hydrolysates in a liposomal system</article-title>. <source>Journal of Food Science</source> <volume>67</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>2952</fpage>–<lpage>2956</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pownail</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Udenigwe</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Aluko</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Amino acid composition and antioxidant properties of pea seed (<italic>Pisum sativum L.</italic>) enzymatic protein hydrolysate fractions</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source> <volume>58</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>4712</fpage>–<lpage>4718</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saiga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant activity of peptides obtained from porcine myofibrillar proteins by protease treatment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source> <volume>51</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>3661</fpage>–<lpage>3667</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarmadi</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Antioxidative peptides from food proteins: A review</article-title>. <source>Peptides</source> <volume>31</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1949</fpage>–<lpage>1956</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Naito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Casein phosphopeptide (CPP) enhances calcium absorption from the ligated segment of rat small intestine</article-title>. <source>Journal of Nutritional Science and Vitaminology</source> <volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shahidi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanasundara</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Phenolic antioxidants</article-title>. <source>Critical Reviews in Food Science &amp; Nutrition</source> <volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Storcksdieck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonsmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurrell</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Iron-binding properties, amino acid composition, and structure of muscle tissue peptides from in vitro digestion of different meat sources</article-title>. <source>Journal of Food Science</source> <volume>72</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>S019</fpage>–<lpage>S029</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabatabai</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Histidine content of low-molecular-weight beef proteins influences nonheme iron bioavailability in Caco-2 cells</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Nutrition</source> <volume>132</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuge</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Eikawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugisawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant activity of peptides prepared by enzymatic hydrolysis of egg-white albumin</article-title>. <source>Nippon Nogeikagaku Kaishi</source> <volume>65</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>1635</fpage>–<lpage>1641</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzaphlidou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The role of collagen in bone structure: an image processing approach</article-title>. <source>Micron</source> <volume>36</volume>(<issue>7-8</issue>): <fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leibfritz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moncol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>MTD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Telser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Free radicals and antioxidants in normal physiological functions and human disease</article-title>. <source>The International Journal of Biochemistry &amp; Cell Biology</source> <volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1082013211428219"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Complexation of Al (III) with reduced glutathione in acidic aqueous solutions</article-title>. <source>Journal of Inorganic Biochemistry</source> <volume>103</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>657</fpage>–<lpage>665</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>