<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JHS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjhs</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Hand Surg Eur Vol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Hand Surgery (European Volume)</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1753-1934</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2043-6289</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753193411422679</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1753193411422679</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Full length articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Joint replacement in 131 painful osteoarthritic and post-traumatic distal interphalangeal joints</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sierakowski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Zweifel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sirotakova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sauerland</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1753193411422679">Hand Surgery Department, St Andrew’s Centre For Plastic Surgery, Broomfield Hospital, Chelmsford, Essex, UK; Medical Faculty, University of Witten/Herdecke, Germany</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1753193411422679">Mr. D. Elliot MA FRCS, Hand Surgery Department, St Andrew’s Centre for Plastic Surgery and Burns, Broomfield Hospital, Court Road, Chelmsford, Essex, CM1 7ET, UK Email: <email>info@david-elliot.co.uk</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jhs.sagepub.com/content/suppl/2012/03/23/1753193411422679.DC1/JHS2012_02.mp3">http://jhs.sagepub.com/content/suppl/2012/03/23/1753193411422679.DC1/JHS2012_02.mp3</ext-link>.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>37</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>304</fpage>
<lpage>309</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>30</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>3</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>15</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The British Society for Surgery of the Hand</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This study reports the results of Swanson replacement of 131 DIP joints for painful osteoarthritis and two for ongoing pain after injury. Thirty-seven arthroplasties (28 patients) were carried out with extensor tendon division and repair, and postoperative immobilization for 8 weeks. Ninety-four (60 patients) were then carried out without tendon division, allowing immediate mobilization. At assessment after a mean period of 57 months, the mean postoperative range of movement was 39°, and the mean extensor lag was 11°, with significant improvement of both in both operative groups. The severity of pain improved significantly following surgery. All but one patient were satisfied with the cosmetic result of replacement. The overall complication rate was 7/131(5%). Three joints developed cellulitis and one developed osteomyelitis, requiring subsequent fusion. Two joints had subsequent fusions because of persistent lateral instability and marked ulnar deviation and one had a persistent mallet-type deformity, corrected by tendon shortening.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Arthroplasty</kwd>
<kwd>distal interphalangeal joint</kwd>
<kwd>joint replacement</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1753193411422679" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Degenerative changes of the distal interphalangeal (DIP) joints can be painful, disabling and disfiguring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1753193411422679">Swanson and Swanson, 1983</xref>). If nonoperative treatment fails to relieve the pain, arthrodesis is still considered by most surgeons to be the gold standard of operative treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1753193411422679">Leibovic, 1997</xref>). However, patients are often unenthusiastic about losing movement of the DIP joints, particularly in the index and middle fingers, realizing that many finer functions of the hand rely on the rapid movement of these joints through a small range of motion. Therefore, they perceive joint fusion as exchange of one disability for another.</p>
<p>Since they were first described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1753193411422679">1968</xref> by Swanson, silicone elastomer spacers have been, and are still widely used, for replacement of proximal interphalangeal (PIP) and metacarpophalangeal (MCP) joints destroyed by arthritis. These implants maintain the joint space and allow motion whilst retaining stability. There is little in the literature about silicone arthroplasty of the DIP joints, with the total recorded experience being only 67 distal interphalangeal replacement arthroplasties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193411422679">Brown, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1753193411422679">Schwartz and Peimer, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1753193411422679">Snow et al., 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1753193411422679">Wilgis, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1753193411422679">Zimmerman et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1753193411422679">1991</xref>). These papers identify this procedure as a good alternative to arthrodesis, achieving excellent pain relief and allowing stable pinch, but with the benefit of retaining 20–30° of DIP joint movement.</p>
<p>The standard technique of DIP joint replacement used in these studies has involved transection of the extensor tendon, necessitating 6 to 8 weeks of postoperative joint immobilization and risking loss of some of the movement of the joint. The first cohort of patients in this study uses this technique of prosthesis insertion. In the second cohort, a new technique of DIP joint replacement without dividing the extensor tendon, with immediate postoperative mobilization, is introduced.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1753193411422679" sec-type="methods">
<title>Patients and methods</title>
<p>Between January 2004 and December 2009, 85 patients had 131 silicone interpositional arthroplasties of the DIP joint inserted at 94 operations. Sixty-nine of the patients were female and 16 were male. The indications for the operation were pain and deformity in a DIP joint still retaining a degree of movement. Generally, patients with little, or no, movement have no pain and were not treated surgically. Those few in this group who still had pain were treated by joint fusion. The underlying diagnosis was osteoarthritis in 83 patients and previous trauma in two patients. Fifty-eight implants were placed in the index finger, 36 in the middle finger, 20 in the ring finger and 17 in the little finger.</p>
<p>Twenty-eight patients had DIP joint replacement(s) by the standard, extensor-dividing technique and 60 had replacement(s) by the new, extensor-sparing technique. Most patients fell within one group or the other because of the time of first presentation. Two patients had a standard procedure to one digit each and, at a later time, an extensor-sparing procedure to a different single digit. One patient had a standard procedure to one digit and, at a later time, an extensor-sparing procedure to two further digits. For the purpose of this study, each finger was analysed as an individual unit after a minimum of 6 months from insertion.</p>
<p>The first 37 consecutive implants were inserted during 29 operations using the standard method, with division of the extensor tendon (Group 1). This group comprised 28 patients, of which 20 were female and eight were male. Eight patients had two prostheses inserted at a single operation. One patient had three prostheses inserted at two operations. The mean age at the time of surgery was 58 (range 22–84) years. Eighteen implants were placed in the index finger, ten in the middle finger, five in the ring finger and four in the little finger.</p>
<p>The following 94 consecutive implants were inserted at 65 operations, with the extensor tendon spared (Group 2). This group comprised 60 patients, of which 52 were female and eight were male. Nineteen patients had two prostheses inserted at a single operation. Five patients had three prostheses at a single operation. Three patients had three prostheses inserted at two operations. One patient had five prostheses inserted at two operations. The mean age at the time of surgery was 59 (range 23–86) years. Forty prostheses were placed in the index finger, 26 in the middle finger, 15 in the ring finger and 13 in the little finger.</p>
<sec id="section3-1753193411422679">
<title>Surgical procedure</title>
<p>Procedures involving a single joint were carried out under digital ring block anaesthesia. Procedures involving multiple joints, or involving another upper limb procedure synchronously, such as trapezectomy, were performed under brachial block anaesthesia. A dorsal ‘H-shaped’ incision was used to approach the DIP joint. This creates proximal and distal flaps which were carefully elevated off the underlying extensor tendon and bone. All of these procedures were carried by two consultant hand surgeons with more than a decade of experience of prosthetic joint replacement.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1753193411422679">
<title>Group 1: standard replacement technique with extensor tendon division</title>
<p>The collateral ligaments were divided at their insertion to the middle phalanx and the extensor tendon divided transversely approximately 5 mm proximal to its insertion into the distal phalanx. The joint was debrided of osteophytes using a rongeur. The head of the middle phalanx was removed transversely with an oscillating saw and the intramedullary canals of the middle and distal phalanges prepared using reamers and/or a burr drill. The joint was then irrigated with sterile saline and sized for either a size 1, 0 or 00 Wright implant (Wright Medical Technology, Inc., Arlington, TN, USA). The appropriate implant was inserted with a no-touch technique. The extensor tendon was then repaired with non-absorbable 5-0 polypropylene (Prolene) mattress sutures and the skin closed with interrupted 5-0 polyglactin 910 (Vicryl Rapide) sutures. The digit was placed in a volar splint for 8 weeks, maintaining the joint in extension at 0°. We did not use a K-wire to protect the repair as reported in some previous papers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1753193411422679">Wilgis, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1753193411422679">Zimmerman et al., 1991</xref>). All patients received a course of prophylactic oral antibiotics postoperatively for 5 days.</p>
<p>The patients were encouraged to move the other joints of the involved finger and the remainder of the hand from the day after operation, with specific attention to the proximal interphalangeal joint of the involved finger(s) to avoid extensor tendon tethering and tightening of the dorsal capsule of this joint (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1753193411422679">Kulkarni et al., 2006</xref>). After removal of the splint, this group of patients were taught to carry out active flexion and extension exercises of the DIP joint(s) of the involved finger(s) themselves five times per day. The patients were seen every 2 weeks over the following month by the therapists, then as required thereafter.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1753193411422679">
<title>Group 2: new replacement technique with extensor tendon sparing</title>
<p>The collateral ligaments were divided proximally in the early patients in this group. Later, this was changed to separation of the collateral ligaments from the distal phalanx to facilitate removal of associated osteophytes, which are mainly on the distal phalanx. The tissues lateral to the extensor tendon were excised (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1753193411422679">Figure 1B</xref>) while leaving the latter intact. By laterally flexing the joint and retracting the extensor tendon from one side to another with a tendon hook, one is then able to gain access to the joint surfaces of the middle and distal phalanges whilst preserving the extensor tendon. Careful handling of the extensor tendon is imperative, as rough manipulation and excessive traction can lead to rupture of the tendon. The distal end of the middle phalanx was removed with a rongeur, not a saw, to avoid damage to the extensor tendon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1753193411422679">Figure 1C</xref>). The bone ends were then prepared and the implant inserted using the same method as for Group 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1753193411422679">Figure 1D</xref>). If the procedure has been performed under local anaesthetic, active movement can be tested intraoperatively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1753193411422679">Figure 1E,F</xref>). A Zimmer splint was applied to immobilize the DIP joint and the affected limb was elevated overnight. All patients received a course of prophylactic oral antibiotics postoperatively for 5 days.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1753193411422679" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>A. Preoperative view of the left index finger of a patient with DIP joint osteoarthritis. There was pain on movement, moderate swelling and ulnar deviation of the distal phalanx. B. Intraoperative view showing the same DIP joint exposed following elevation of the ‘H’ flap, division of the collateral ligaments and removal of all tissue lateral to the extensor tendon, which remains intact. C. Lateral intraoperative view showing the resulting joint space once osteophytes have been removed and the end of the middle phalanx excised. The extensor tendon remains intact. D. Intraoperative view after insertion of the silicone implant. E. The patient can immediately flex the joint to 40°. F. There remains an extensor lag of 15°, which is accentuated visually to 30° by dorsal bony swelling under the extensor attachment to the distal phalanx, which cannot be removed easily at surgery.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1753193411422679-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Postoperatively, this group of patients were taught to carry out active flexion and extension exercises of the DIP joint(s) of the involved finger(s) themselves five times per day. Appropriate and liberal analgesia was used to allow this very active early mobilization. A protective mallet-type splint was only worn at night for 8 weeks and, in some patients, for protection from unintentional trauma when ‘out and about’ in the first month. The patients were seen every 2 weeks over the following month, then as required thereafter.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1753193411422679">
<title>Assessment</title>
<p>Patients were evaluated preoperatively and on each visit postoperatively to the surgical follow-up clinic. All had a minimum of 6 months follow-up postoperatively. The preoperative range of movement of each DIP joint for replacement was measured using a goniometer. Generally, the angles were measured with the goniometer on the dorsum of the finger. In cases with a prominent osteophyte beneath the attachment of the extensor to the base of the distal phalanx, the angles were measured using the lateral approach. Extension was measured with all the fingers maximally extended. Flexion was measured with the fingers in the ‘cat’s claw’, or ‘karate fist’, position. The same measurements were performed postoperatively on each occasion on which the patient attended for surgical follow-up.</p>
<p>Extensor lag was measured relative to 0° as the maximum possible extension. The same measurements were performed postoperatively on each occasion on which the patient attended for surgical follow-up. Pain severity was determined pre- and postoperatively by subjective patient self-assessment using a visual analogue pain scale (VAS) consisting of a 10 cm long horizontal line, where 0 represented ‘no pain’ and 10 ‘the worst imaginable pain’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193411422679">Carlsson, 1983</xref>). Stability of the involved joints was not assessed preoperatively, but patients were questioned about this postoperatively on each occasion on which they attended for surgical follow-up. Patients were asked at the final follow-up surgical appointment whether they were not satisfied, satisfied or very satisfied with the appearance of the involved finger(s) after replacement. Immediate postoperative and more long-term complications such as wound infection or haematoma and the need for further surgery procedures were recorded.</p>
<p>Statistical analyses for normally distributed variables (e.g. range of movement, extensor lag) were made using Student’s paired <italic>t</italic>-test for within-group comparisons, and Student’s unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test for comparisons between groups. Pain scores on the VAS were compared within each group using the Wilcoxon matched-pairs test. Between-group comparison was done by using the Mann–Whitney test. A <italic>p</italic> value of less than 0.05 was considered significant. The data were analysed using GraphPad InStat and PASW Statistics 18 for Microsoft Windows.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1753193411422679" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>At the time of assessment, the 131 implants had been in place for a mean period of 36 (range 6–76) months. In Group 1, 37 implants had been in place for 57 (range 49–76) months and, in Group 2, 94 implants had been in place for 27 (range 6–48) months.</p>
<p>The mean preoperative range of movement for all 131 DIP joints was 24° (range 5–45°), being 26° (range 10–45°) in Group 1 and 24° (range 5–40°) in Group 2 . The mean postoperative range of movement for all 131 DIP joints was 39° (range 15–70°), being 41° (range 25–55°) in Group 1 and 38° (range 15–70°) in Group 2. This improvement was statistically significant for both groups (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 for each group). When compared against each other, there was no statistically significant difference between the postoperative range of movement achieved in Group 2 and that achieved in Group1 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.204). Analysing only those in Group 2 who were followed-up for more than 1 year, this statement is still true.</p>
<p>One patient in Group 2, who had a total of five implants inserted at two operations, developed a persistent mallet-type deformity in one of the replaced joints which was corrected after 18 months by shortening the extensor tendon at the DIP joint level. The mean preoperative extensor lag for all 131 DIP joints was 20° (range 0–45°), being 23° (range 0–45°) in Group 1 and 19° (range 0–35°) in Group 2. The mean postoperative extensor lag for all 131 DIP joints was 11° (range 0–45°), being 13° (range 5–30°) in Group 1 and 11° (range 0–45°) in Group 2. The improvement observed in both groups was statistically significant (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 for each group).</p>
<p>The severity of pain, as measured subjectively on the VAS, improved significantly following surgery. In both groups, the average pain score reduced from 8 preoperatively to 1 postoperatively (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 for each group). Neither preoperative nor postoperative pain scores showed a significant between-group difference (<italic>p</italic> = 0.67 and <italic>p</italic> = 0.47, respectively).</p>
<p>One patient in Group 2 with persistent lateral instability of an index finger DIP joint had this joint fused. Subjectively, lateral instability was not reported by any other patient in any other DIP joint on specific questioning.</p>
<p>Overall patient satisfaction with the appearance of their digit(s) postoperatively was high. In Group 1, eight of 28 (29%) patients were very satisfied, 20 (71%) were satisfied and none were not satisfied with the appearance of their digit(s) postoperatively. In Group 2, 35 of 61 (57%) patients were very satisfied, 25 out of 61 (41%) patients were satisfied with the appearance of their digit(s) postoperatively and one patient with persistent lateral instability in her index finger DIP joint, who eventually had this joint fused, was not satisfied. One patient in Group 2 developed marked ulnar deviation of the index finger distal phalanx and did not like the appearance. This was caused by a bone spike left on one edge of the middle phalangeal resection margin. At secondary surgery, the joint was fused at the patient’s request.</p>
<p>The overall complication rate in this series of 131 DIP joint replacements was 7/131 (5%), with 4/131 (3%) requiring further surgery. Three patients developed cellulitis which settled with antibiotics. One patient in Group 2, who had a total of five implants inserted at two operations, developed osteomyelitis in one of these joints. This required removal of the implant 9 months following the original surgery. The joint was subsequently fused. The same patient also developed a persistent mallet-type deformity in one of the other replaced joints. This was corrected after 18 months by shortening the extensor tendon at the DIP joint level. One patient in Group 2 with persistent lateral instability of an index finger DIP joint had this joint fused. A second patient in Group 2 developed ulnar deviation of the index finger distal phalanx as a result of a bone spike left on one edge of the middle phalangeal resection margin. At surgery, the joint was fused at the patient’s request.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1753193411422679" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Multiple techniques for DIP joint arthrodesis have been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1753193411422679">Engel et al., 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1753193411422679">Mantovani et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1753193411422679">Tomaino, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1753193411422679">Zavitsanos et al., 1999</xref>). The procedure is seen by many to be the gold standard for treatment of pain and deformity in this joint (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1753193411422679">Leibovic, 1997</xref>), although it is not entirely without complications. Rates of delayed union and non-union from 0% to 20% have been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1753193411422679">Mantovani et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1753193411422679">Zavitsanos et al., 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>Some argue that implant arthroplasty is unnecessary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1753193411422679">Rehart and Kerschbaumer, 2003</xref>), or should only be considered under exceptional circumstances, such as in musicians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1753193411422679">Culver and Fleegler, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1753193411422679">Schwartz and Peimer, 1998</xref>). However, this may underestimate the functional benefits of a moving DIP joint (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1753193411422679">Evans, 1990</xref>). The DIP joint of the index finger (and the IP joint of the thumb) is particularly important for pinch. The middle finger DIP becomes involved in chuck pinch and the ring and little finger DIP joints are important for the fine control of larger objects when all five digit tips are involved in span gripping. These joints moving through a small range of motion with speed are integral to many daily activities. In this respect, we believe that more effort should be made to preserve this movement.</p>
<p>To date, only a few case series, describing 67 DIP joint replacements in total, all with Swanson implants, have been published (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193411422679">Brown, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1753193411422679">Schwartz and Peimer, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1753193411422679">Snow et al., 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1753193411422679">Wilgis, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1753193411422679">Zimmerman et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1753193411422679">1991</xref>). These reports showed that the replaced DIP joints had a range of motion of approximately 30° at the time of assessment, with a mean extensor lag of about 12°. Unfortunately, none have recorded preoperative ranges of motion. The authors describe excellent pain relief and stable pinch. The complication rate leading to implant removal ranged from 1 to 10%, which is comparable to the reported complications following arthrodesis.</p>
<p>That prosthetic replacement should have stability equal to that of the original joint may be surprising, given that the lateral ligaments are divided at insertion of a Swanson prosthesis. However, two factors may come into play post-replacement. The intramedullary parts of a Swanson prosthesis provide lateral stability to the replaced joint, albeit by a different process to that of intact lateral joint ligaments. As has been recognized for a long time by observation of the change from instability to stability in the fingers of patients with arthritis mutilans when the profundus flexor tendon is activated to flex the finger, the active profundus tendon makes passive lateral movement of the DIP joint almost impossible, both in a normal DIP joint and one which has been replaced with a Swanson prosthesis.</p>
<p>This study considerably extends the number of reported patients who have undergone silicone interpositional arthroplasty of the DIP joint and confirms that this procedure is an acceptable alternative to arthrodesis of this joint. In our study, the range of movement of 30–40° achieved in both patient groups is more than reported previously, although the extensor lag remains as in previous studies. Extensor lag after this replacement, as with those to other joints, probably relates mostly to the relative length of the resected tissues and that part of the implant inserted between the bone ends. We agree with previous authors that pain relief in cases without complications is excellent and that the overall complication rate of 5% is low.</p>
<p>Although not a major feature of our study, and only assessed in a very rudimentary way, the appearance of these fingers is generally satisfactory to the patients. However, this may relate more to the simultaneous removal of the osteophytes around the DIP joint at surgery than to the specific joint procedure. Whilst the technique has primarily been used in older patients suffering from osteoarthritis, we have also applied it successfully in two younger patients with persistent joint pain following trauma.</p>
<p>The standard technique of DIP joint replacement described in previous papers includes transection of the extensor tendons, then repair after insertion of the prostheses. This requires strict immobilization for 6 to 8 weeks postoperatively. This study describes a technique of prosthesis insertion which preserves the extensor tendon and allows mobilization from the first postoperative day. The authors believe this new technique has a very rapid learning curve, simplifies and shortens follow-up, although the results in our patients do not show any obvious improvement in respect of range of movement or reduction of extensor tendon lag.</p>
<p>In carrying out this study, we used the Swanson prostheses manufactured by Wright Medical Technology Ltd. Most of the prostheses used were ‘Wright’ size 00. The numbers on Swanson prostheses made by different suppliers may not correspond to the same size, and there may be no equivalent sufficiently small prosthesis supplied by other manufacturers, creating a dilemma after resecting the head of the middle phalanx.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="section9-1753193411422679">
<title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1753193411422679">
<title>Conflict of interests</title>
<p>None declared.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distal interphalangeal joint flexible implant arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1989</year>, <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>653</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carlsson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of chronic pain: Aspects of the reliability and validity of the visual analogue scale</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>. <year>1983</year>, <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Culver</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fleegler</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Osteoarthritis of the distal interphalangeal joint</article-title>. <source>Hand Clin</source>. <year>1987</year>, <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>403</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsur</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A comparison between K-wire and compression screw fixation after arthrodesis of the distal interphalangeal joint</article-title>. <source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source>. <year>1977</year>, <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A study of the zone 1 flexor tendon injury and implications for treatment</article-title>. <source>J Hand Ther</source>. <year>1990</year>, <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The significance of extensor tendon tethering and dorsal joint capsule tightening after injury to the hand</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Eur</source>. <year>2006</year>, <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leibovic</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Internal fixation for small joint arthrodeses of the hand: the interphalangeal joints</article-title>. <source>Hand Clin</source>. <year>1997</year>, <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>601</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mantovani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fukushima</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aita</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lino</surname><given-names>W</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Alternative to the distal interphalangeal joint arthrodesis: Lateral approach and plate fixation</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2008</year>, <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rehart</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kerschbaumer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Endoprothetik an der Hand</article-title>. <source>Orthopäde</source>. <year>2003</year>, <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>779</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peimer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distal interphalangeal joint implant arthroplasty in a musician</article-title>. <source>J Hand Ther</source>. <year>1998</year>, <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boyes</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greider</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Implant arthroplasty of the distal interphalangeal joint of the finger for osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source>. <year>1977</year>, <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>558</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Silicone rubber implants for replacement of arthritic or destroyed joints in the hand</article-title>. <source>Surg Clin North Am</source>. <year>1968</year>, <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>1113</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Osteoarthritis in the hand</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1983</year>, <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tomaino</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distal interphalangeal joint arthrodesis with screw fixation: why and how</article-title>. <source>Hand Clin</source>. <year>2006</year>, <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilgis</surname><given-names>EFS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distal interphalangeal joint silicone interpositional arthroplasty of the hand</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1997</year>, <volume>342</volume>: <fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zavitsanos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Somia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kleinbert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distal interphalangeal joint arthrodesis using intramedullary and interosseous fixation</article-title>. <source>Hand Surg</source>. <year>1999</year>, <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Suhey</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilgis</surname><given-names>EFS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Silicone interpositional arthroplasty of the distal interphalangeal joint</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1989</year>, <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>882</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1753193411422679">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilgis</surname><given-names>EFS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distal interphalangeal joint silicone interpositional arthroplasty: Surgical technique and functional outcome</article-title>. <source>Semin Arthroplasty</source>. <year>1991</year>, <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>