<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PCH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppch</journal-id>
<journal-title>World Journal for Pediatric and Congenital Heart Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2150-1351</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2150-0136</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2150135113480220</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2150135113480220</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Left Mammary Artery Bypass Grafting Rescued a Patient With Hypoplastic Left Heart Syndrome With Ascending Aorta Obstruction After Norwood Stage I Procedure</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Takeuchi</surname>
<given-names>Koh</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150135113480220">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-2150135113480220"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Minegishi</surname>
<given-names>Sachito</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150135113480220">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kobayashi</surname>
<given-names>Jotaro</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150135113480220">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tsuchiya</surname>
<given-names>Keiji</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2150135113480220">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-2150135113480220"><label>1</label>Division of Cardiovascular Surgery, Japanese Red Cross Medical Center, Hiroo Shibuya, Tokyo, Japan</aff>
<aff id="aff2-2150135113480220"><label>2</label>Department of Pediatrics, Japanese Red Cross Medical Center, Hiroo Shibuya, Tokyo, Japan</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-2150135113480220">Koh Takeuchi, Division of Cardiovascular Surgery, Japanese Red Cross Medical Center, 4-1-22, Hiroo, Shibuya-ku, Tokyo, 150-8935, Japan. Email: <email>koutakeuchi-circ@umin.ac.jp</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>290</fpage>
<lpage>292</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>22</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>1</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">World Society for Pediatric and Congential Heart Surgery</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>A three-month-old boy with hypoplastic left heart syndrome (mitral atresia, aortic atresia) and moderate tricuspid regurgitation developed ascending aorta obstruction two months after a Norwood stage I procedure. An emergent left mammary artery bypass grafting to the ascending aorta and extracorporeal membrane oxygenator support resulted in successful salvage. The patient subsequently underwent a bidirectional Glenn procedure and tricuspid valve repair at the age of five months. Follow-up at an outpatient clinic reveals no electrocardiographic evidence of ischemia, and echocardiography shows recovery of ventricular function.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>hypoplastic left heart syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>myocardial injury</kwd>
<kwd>coronary artery surgery</kwd>
<kwd>revascularization</kwd>
<kwd>ECMO</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-2150135113480220">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Although several cases of thrombus formation in the native aortic root in patients with hypoplastic left heart syndrome (HLHS) have been reported,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-2150135113480220">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-2150135113480220"/>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-2150135113480220"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-2150135113480220">4</xref>
</sup> it is distinctly unusual to detect a remediable anatomic cause for ventricular dysfunction after a modified Norwood stage I operation for HLHS. We present a case of distal native ascending aorta obstruction two months after a Norwood stage I procedure in a patient with aortic atresia. Early diagnosis, timely mechanical extracorporeal support, and surgical intervention, all contributed to a successful outcome.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-2150135113480220">
<title>Patient and Methods</title>
<p>The ethics committee of the Japanese Red Cross Medical Center approved this study, and an individual consent for the report was obtained. A term infant with a birth weight of 3.3 kg and a prenatal diagnosis of HLHS was referred to our institution for surgical-staged palliation. Postnatal two dimensional echocardiography demonstrated aortic and mitral atresia, with a hypoplastic left ventricle and juxtaductal coarctation of the aorta. The ascending aorta and transverse arch measured 2 and 4.7 mm, respectively. There was moderate-to-severe tricuspid regurgitation (TR) but no pulmonary regurgitation, and the ventricular function was normal.</p>
<p>In accordance with our institutional strategy for HLHS, on day 4 of life, bilateral pulmonary artery banding was performed, and patency of the ductus arteriosus was maintained by means of continuous infusion of prostaglandin E1. On day 36 of life, a Norwood stage I procedure was performed, including an atrial septectomy and insertion of a 3.5-mm expanded polytetrafluoroethylene (ePTFE) tube graft between the innominate artery and the right pulmonary artery. To achieve the amalgamation of the main pulmonary trunk with the aorta, an anastomosis was created between the transected pulmonary artery and the lesser curvature of the aortic arch, without incising the distal ascending aorta. The patient could not be weaned from cardiopulmonary bypass because of arterial desaturation and myocardial dysfunction and was therefore returned to the intensive care unit with extracorporeal membrane oxygenator (ECMO) support. Three days later, the patient was weaned from the ECMO in the operating room following systemic to pulmonary artery shunt revision (4 mm ePTFE graft with small clips).</p>
<p>The patient remained in the hospital for the next two months due to poor weight gain. Then, he suddenly developed bradycardia and hypotension with ischemic changes on the electrocardiogram (ECG). He was resuscitated by cardiac massage, inotropic support, and fluid challenge. Two-dimensional echocardiography demonstrated flow in the ascending aorta away from the coronary arteries during diastole and increased diastolic retrograde flow in the descending aorta. Stenosis was seen at the distal end of the ascending aorta, although it was not in the region of the suture line for aortic arch repair. After resuscitation, the patient was rushed to the operating room and underwent in situ bypass grafting to the ascending aorta using the left mammary artery. We were concerned about the possible drawback associated with patch repair, in that it could cause a coronary steal again. The patient could not be weaned from cardiopulmonary bypass, so he remained on the ECMO for the next five days. After weaning from ECMO support, the patient remained in good condition, although echocardiography revealed diminished right ventricular (RV) ejection fraction (approximately 30%) and persistence of significant TR. There was no evidence of coronary flow disturbance.</p>
<p>At five months of age, the patient underwent a bidirectional Glenn (BDG) procedure, with tricuspid annuloplasty and with the takedown of the right-modified Blalock–Taussig (B–T) shunt under cardiopulmonary bypass without cardiac arrest. Coronary perfusion was maintained via the left mammary artery graft, even during cross-clamping of the proximal neoaorta. The ascending aorta was observed to have grown to 5 mm in diameter. The patient was successfully weaned from the cardiopulmonary bypass. He was weaned from mechanical ventilation and was extubated on the fifth postoperative day. Postoperative echocardiography demonstrated mild-to-moderate TR. The patient has been followed up at an outpatient clinic where echocardiography revealed RV ejection fraction of 49%.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-2150135113480220">
<title>Comments</title>
<p>We have described an instance of obstruction of retrograde flow into the native ascending aorta resulting in myocardial ischemia following a modified stage I Norwood in a neonate with aortic atresia and HLHS. The patient had a successful outcome after surgical reintervention. Prompt detection and treatment of the complications that may occur after Norwood stage I palliation are extremely important. Such complications may be life threatening or may limit the suitability of the infant for eventual BDG anastomosis and completion Fontan procedure. Major complications after Norwood stage I include TR, ventricular dysfunction, and neoaortic regurgitation as well as recoarctation of the aorta. However, an autopsy study<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-2150135113480220">5</xref>
</sup> suggested that impaired coronary perfusion because of precoronary obstruction (ie, the native aortic root) was an important cause of death (27% of the cases). Our patient did not have obstruction prior to the Norwood stage I procedure, and the suture line for pulmonary artery-to-aortic anastomosis did not involve the distal end of the ascending aorta. The presence of a mild obstruction coupled with the runoff to the pulmonary circulation through the B–T shunt may have resulted in a tenuous coronary circulation. A small native ascending aorta (&lt;2 mm) may underlie coronary ischemia, which has been known as a risk factor for early death after stage I palliation.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-2150135113480220">6</xref>
</sup> This precoronary event could occur even two months after the Norwood stage I procedure. To avoid this complication, the arch reconstruction and amalgamation of the proximal main pulmonary artery with the aorta should include a long incision in the ascending aorta with the reconstruction extending close to the coronary artery orifices or alternative techniques such as ascending aortic reimplantation.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-2150135113480220">7</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>From the technical point of view, patch plasty to directly augment the narrowed area would be a plausible technique. However in this technique, coronary ischemia may be a potential continuing problem even after repair due to runoff into the pulmonary circulation. The potential benefit of mammary artery grafting is that it may avoid coronary blood flow disturbance. The mammary artery in this patient was 1 to 1.5 mm in diameter and very thin compared to an adult mammary artery. It proved to be an adequate conduit to provide sufficient blood flow into the coronary arteries. The left mammary artery also grew in diameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2150135113480220">Figure 1</xref>). This appears to be an acceptable alternative way to restore the coronary blood flow in the setting of the ascending aorta obstruction.</p>
<fig id="fig1-2150135113480220" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>a, Lateral view of angiogram. Left mammary artery was anastomosed to the ascending aorta and the ascending aorta and coronary arteries were enhanced. <bold>b,</bold> Frontal view. Left mammary artery, ascending aorta as well as coronary arteries were enhanced.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2150135113480220-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation support is generally considered not to improve survival in patients with residual cardiac defects, especially palliated patients with single ventricle physiology.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-2150135113480220">8</xref>
</sup> However, our case suggests that ECMO support was beneficial while undertaking a search for a surgically remediable solution to the problem.</p>
<p>Since myocardial dysfunction was obvious, cardioplegic arrest of the heart was not introduced for the BDG procedure and concomitant tricuspid annuloplasty. Instead, continuous perfusion was supplied by the mammary artery graft. The patient was successfully extubated and discharged to his home. Since then, the patient has not had evidence of myocardial ischemia on serial ECGs. Because a single-vessel bypass graft may not be adequate to perfuse the myocardium in the long term, we are planning to repair the stenotic lesion at the ascending aorta during the next stage of surgical reconstruction.</p>
<p>This case exemplifies the limitations and potential disadvantages of techniques of aortopulmonary anastomosis which do not incorporate most of the length of the ascending aorta in the aortopulmonary amalgamation. Based on our experience, we believe incision of the medial aspect of the ascending aorta and construction of a lengthy anastomosis with the neoaorta is an important technique to avoid precoronary stenosis after a Norwood stage I procedure. Since this had not been done at the time of the initial procedure in this patient, it was reasonable to perform mammary artery grafting to the native ascending aorta to achieve salvage, resulting in survival to superior cavopulmonary connection and recovery of ventricular function.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-2150135113480220">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-2150135113480220">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<glossary content-type="abbr">
<title>Abbreviations and Acronyms</title>
<def-list>
<def-item>
<term id="term1-2150135113480220">BDG</term>
<def>
<p>bidirectional Glenn</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term2-2150135113480220">B–T</term>
<def>
<p>Blalock–Taussig</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term3-2150135113480220">ECG</term>
<def>
<p>electrocardiogram</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term4-2150135113480220">ECMO</term>
<def>
<p>extracorporeal membrane oxygenator</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term5-2150135113480220">ePTFE</term>
<def>
<p>expanded polytetrafluoroethylene</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term6-2150135113480220">HLHS</term>
<def>
<p>hypoplastic left heart syndrome</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term7-2150135113480220">RV</term>
<def>
<p>right ventricular</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term8-2150135113480220">TR</term>
<def>
<p>tricuspid regurgitation</p>
</def>
</def-item>
</def-list>
</glossary>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-2150135113480220">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mookerjee</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rosental</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Simpson</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Formation of thrombus in a native aortic sinus of Valsalva after palliation of hypoplastic left heart syndrome</article-title>. <source>Cardiol Young</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>330</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-2150135113480220">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Graham</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shakir</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ats</surname>
<given-names>Am</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ringewald</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bradley</surname>
<given-names>SM.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>Neoaortic root modification for late thrombosis after Norwood palliation</article-title>. <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>82</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e29</fpage>–<lpage>e30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-2150135113480220">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Owens</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gomez-Fifer</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ensing</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Thrombus formation in the native aortic root in patients with hypoplastic left heart syndrome</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Cardiol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-2150135113480220">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brennan</surname>
<given-names>TV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rodefeld</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tacy</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reddy</surname>
<given-names>VM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hanley</surname>
<given-names>FL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Late thrombosis of the native aortic root after Norwood reconstruction for hypoplastic left heart syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>1</volume>
<volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>580</fpage>-582.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-2150135113480220">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bartram</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grunenfelder</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Van Praagh</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cause of death after the Norwood procedure: a study of 122 postmortem cases</article-title>. <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1795</fpage>–<lpage>1802</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-2150135113480220">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Forbess</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cook</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roth</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Serraf</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mayer</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jonas</surname>
<given-names>RA.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>Ten-year institutional experience with palliative surgery for hypoplastic left heart syndrome-risk factors related to stage I mortality</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>suppl 9</issue>):<fpage>II262</fpage>–<lpage>266</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-2150135113480220">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Abdullah</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Van Arsdell</surname>
<given-names>GS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hornberger</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Adatia</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Precoronary stenosis after stage I palliation for hypoplastic left heart syndrome</article-title>. <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2147</fpage>–<lpage>2149</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-2150135113480220">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shuhaiber</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thiagarajan</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Laussen</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fynn-Thompson</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>del Nido</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pigula</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Survival of children requiring repeat extracorporeal membrane oxygenation after congenital heart surgery</article-title>. <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1949</fpage>–<lpage>1955</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>