<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JHS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjhs</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Hand Surg Eur Vol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Hand Surgery (European Volume)</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1753-1934</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2043-6289</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753193412445144</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1753193412445144</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Full length articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The relationship between displacement and clinical outcome after distal radius (Colles’) fracture</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Finsen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1753193412445144">Faculty of Medicine, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, and Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, St.Olav’s University Hospital, Trondheim, Norway</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Rod</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Rød</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Rajabi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Alm-Paulsen</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-1753193412445144">Faculty of Medicine, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, Trondheim, Norway</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Russwurm</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff3-1753193412445144">Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, St.Olav’s University Hospital, Trondheim, Norway</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1753193412445144">Vilh. Finsen, Dept. of Orthopaedic Surgery, St.Olav’s University Hospital, 7006 Trondheim, Norway Email: <email>vilh.finsen@ntnu.no</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>38</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>116</fpage>
<lpage>126</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>18</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>14</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>21</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The British Society for Surgery of the Hand</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We reviewed 260 patients who had been treated non-operatively for a dorsally displaced distal radius fracture a mean 6.3 (range 2.5–12.7) years earlier, in an attempt to find the limits of displacement compatible with a good clinical outcome. We excluded patients with previous or later injuries to the same limb. Bivariate analysis revealed a highly statistically significant relationship between radiographic displacement at review and clinical outcome scores. Correlation coefficients varied between 0.14 and 0.30. However, multiple linear regression analysis using most factors commonly thought to be of importance in determining the clinical outcome as independent variables explained only 23% of the variability of the clinical outcome. Dorsal angulation, ulnar variance, and radial inclination together accounted for only 11% of the variability. We conclude that the final alignment of the distal radius as shown radiologically has only a minor influence on the clinical outcome of Colles’ type distal radius fractures.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Distal radius fracture</kwd>
<kwd>Colles’ fracture</kwd>
<kwd>clinical outcome</kwd>
<kwd>ulnar variance</kwd>
<kwd>dorsal angulation</kwd>
<kwd>radial inclination</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1753193412445144" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Until fairly recently, most clinicians felt that Abraham <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1753193412445144">Colles (1814)</xref> was correct when he stated that after dorsally displaced fractures of the distal radius the wrist would eventually regain very good or full function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412445144">Altissimi et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1753193412445144">Smail, 1965</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1753193412445144">Warwick et al., 1993</xref>). Historically, the large majority of these fractures were treated non-operatively, even when there was quite considerable remaining displacement of the distal radial fracture fragment. Recently, there has been greater emphasis on obtaining correct realignment of the skeleton in order to obtain a good clinical outcome. In spite of numerous studies, it is still unclear how much displacement may be acceptable.</p>
<p>When closed reduction fails to provide the desired realignment, operative options are available. Lately, open reduction and fixation with angular stable volar plates has become popular. In 2008, there were reported to be more than 30 different volar plating systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1753193412445144">Chen and Jupiter, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1753193412445144">Downing and Karantana, 2008</xref>). Their use varies from country to country and hospital to hospital. Some national societies have tried to formulate guidelines, but have only been able to put forward tentative recommendations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1753193412445144">American Academy of Orthopedic Surgeons [AAOS], 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1753193412445144">Hølmer et al., 2001</xref>). Nonetheless, the rate of volar plating of these fractures appears to be increasing. The practice in our department is probably fairly typical for Scandinavia: in 2009 and 2010 we treated 53% of patients with distal radius fractures over the age of 30 years by simply placing the wrist in a plaster of Paris (POP) cast; 22% with manipulation and plaster casting; and we performed open reduction and stabilization with volar plates in 19%. Similar patterns of treatment have also been reported from Oslo (Knut Melhuus, personal communication, 2007) and Sweden (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193412445144">Abramo et al., 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Our hypothesis was that, although there is great heterogeneity in both patients and fractures of the distal radius, it would be possible to determine the limits to bony displacement that usually are compatible with a good clinical outcome by reviewing a sufficiently large number of patients treated non-operatively for a distal radius fracture.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1753193412445144" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>We reviewed the case notes and radiographs of all patients treated non-operatively for dorsally displaced distal radial fractures at our hospital during 1997 and 1998, and between June 2003 and December 2006. Our inclusion criteria were fractures with initial displacement in a dorsal direction of at least 5° from the normal volar tilt of 10°. Our exclusion criteria were AO type B fractures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1753193412445144">Muller et al., 1987</xref>); case-note or radiological evidence of previous or later injuries or conditions that might influence the long-term function of the injured or contralateral wrist; and patients who did not live in our city or three adjoining municipalities. We excluded patients under 30 years old at the time of fracture as many have high-energy comminuted fractures. We excluded patients over age 85 years, as they were unlikely to be available for review.</p>
<p>Patients who complied with our inclusion criteria were asked by letter to attend a review between June and September 2009. We assessed the history, looking at the mechanism and energy of injury, and other diseases or injuries that might influence function in the injured or contralateral wrist and hand at review. We measured the range of motion (ROM) of the forearm and wrist with a hand-held goniometer. We recorded the total wrist ROM, adding together the values for extension, flexion, ulnar deviation, and radial deviation. Values for supination and pronation were added together to give forearm motion. We measured grip strength in both hands using a Jamar dynamometer set at position two (A. Preston Corp., Clifton, New Jersey, USA). The median value of three attempts was recorded. For comparison, we increased the recorded value in the non-dominant hand by 10% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1753193412445144">Bechtol, 1954</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1753193412445144">Földhazy et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1753193412445144">Kelly et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1753193412445144">MacDermid et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1753193412445144">Wilcke et al., 2007</xref>). Any losses of ROM or grip strength were calculated as a percentage of that of the uninjured wrist.</p>
<p>Pain during daily activities in the previous week before review was recorded on a visual analogue scale (VAS), where 0 denoted no pain and 100 worst imaginable pain. Patients completed the short version of the Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand (Q-DASH) questionnaire (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1753193412445144">Finsen, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1753193412445144">Gummesson et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1753193412445144">Hudak et al., 1996</xref>) and the Patient Rated Wrist Evaluation (PRWE) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1753193412445144">Changulani et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1753193412445144">MacDermid et al., 1998</xref>). The Q-DASH consists of 11 questions related to pain and function using both upper extremities, and the PRWE consists of 15 questions about pain and function only in the injured wrist. Both are scored from 0 (best) to 100 (worst).</p>
<p>Both wrists of each patient had posteroanterior and lateral radiographs. Fractures were classified according to the AO system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1753193412445144">Muller et al., 1987</xref>). Dorsal angulation of the distal fragment and radial inclination were measured in relation to the long axis of the radius. Volar angles were given a negative value. Ulnar variance was measured as the axial difference between the articular surfaces of the ulna and radius at the distal radio-ulnar joint and given a positive value when the ulna was longer then the radius. Intra-articular fracture step-offs and fracture gaps were measured.</p>
<p>In addition to the PRWE and Q-DASH scores, we constructed a new composite score, the Global Wrist Outcome Score (GWOS), which combines subjective and objective outcomes. GWOS is scored between 0 (best) and 100 (worst). The PRWE contributes 50%; the VAS score for pain, 20%; loss of grip strength, 20%; and loss of wrist mobility, 10%. The score is arrived at by adding together the PRWE score divided by two, the VAS score for pain (on a scale of 0 to 100) divided by five, the percentage strength loss divided by five, and the percentage loss of wrist ROM divided by 10. Thus, pain contributes approximately 45% to the score; function, 25%; and objective findings (strength and mobility), 30%. Loss of supination and pronation were not included in the GWOS because they proved to be minimal. The GWOS correlated well with the PRWE (<italic>r</italic> = 0.907; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and Q-DASH (<italic>r</italic> = 0.764; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Data in the present paper were analyzed using all three scores, but the results are mainly presented for the GWOS.</p>
<p>We used scatter plots and Spearman’s correlation to find correlations between variables. Multiple linear regression analysis and ordinal regression analysis were used to evaluate to what extent the functional outcome at review could be explained by the data we had collected. We selected independent variables based on previous reports: radiographic measurements (dorsal angulation, radial inclination, ulnar variance, fracture classification, gap or step-off of intra-articular fractures, involvement of the distal radioulnar joint, and fracture of the ulnar styloid); complications; patients’ age; gender; and time between injury and review. Variables that did not significantly contribute in a multiple linear regression analysis were omitted in subsequent analyses.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1753193412445144" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>We invited 558 patients for review; 296 attended. Eight were excluded because of incomplete data or they did not fulfil the inclusion criteria. Four more were excluded because they had suffered high-energy trauma. Of the remainder, 24 patients had other injuries or conditions of the fractured extremity; thus, there remained 260 patients in whom outcome parameters based only on the injured limb could be calculated. Of these, 46 had injuries on the opposite limb making direct comparison invalid, leaving 214 patients for whom outcome parameters based on comparison between the two limbs could be calculated.</p>
<p>Of the 260 patients, there were 32 men and 228 women with a mean age at injury of 62 (range 30–84) years. The fractures were reduced with a haematoma block and application of a POP in 184 patients. The remaining 76 patients just had application of a POP. Mean time between injury and review was 6.3 (range 2.5–12.7) years.</p>
<p>Patients reported few verifiable complications. These included many problems that might have been unrelated to the fracture or were short term, but for completeness, we note them all: three clear cases of complex regional pain syndrome 1; six cases of carpal tunnel syndrome since the fracture; two cases of frozen shoulder; and one rupture of the extensor pollicis longus tendon. In addition, 16 patients had complained of a tight POP, 20 patients remembered pain for several months after the fracture, one reported some reduced sensibility in the hand at review, three reported occasional paraesthesia in the hand after the fracture, one had been treated for tenosynovitis of the wrist, and one developed Dupuytren’s disease, which he ascribed to the fracture. Student’s <italic>t</italic>-test revealed no significant difference in dorsal angulation or ulnar variance between patients with complications and those without. However, mean radial inclination was 17° among patients with complications and 20° among those without (<italic>p</italic> = 0.002).</p>
<p>Among the 214 patients with an uninjured contralateral extremity, there was a mean loss of grip strength of 12% (SD 18%), a loss of wrist mobility of 10% (SD 12%), and a loss of pronation and supination of 2% (SD 7%). For the full cohort of 260 patients, the mean score for pain was 6 (SD 15) on a scale of 0 to 100. Eighteen patients stated that they had had to change their work activities since the fracture.</p>
<p>Mean PRWE score was 11 (SD 16), mean Q-DASH score was 13 (SD 16) and mean GWOS score was 11 (SD 13). GWOS scores varied between 0 and 75; 77% had a score below 15, indicating that the scores were not normally distributed. This was also the case for Q-DASH and PRWE scores. Scatter plots of the chosen radiological parameters and GWOS (and also of PRWE and Q-DASH, data not shown) confirmed this and, furthermore, gave no indication of a significant association between clinical outcome scores and radiographic measurements (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1753193412445144">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1753193412445144" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Scatter plots for Global Wrist Outcome Score (GWOS) and radiological measurements at review. (A) Dorsal angulation. (B) Ulnar variance. (C) Radial inclination.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412445144-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Subdivision of the outcome parameters gave the impression of poorer clinical outcome with increasing radiological displacement at review (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1753193412445144">Table 1</xref>). The standard errors of the means, however, indicate extensive overlap of the mean outcome scores at differing degrees of displacement.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1753193412445144" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of patients and mean Global Wrist Outcome Score (GWOS), Patient Rated Wrist Evaluation (PRWE), and Quick Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand (Q-DASH) scores</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1753193412445144" xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412445144-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="3">GWOS<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Q-DASH<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">PRWE<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="left">n</th>
<th align="left">Mean</th>
<th align="left">SEM</th>
<th align="left">Mean</th>
<th align="left">SEM</th>
<th align="left">n</th>
<th align="left">Mean</th>
<th align="left">SEM</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Dorsal angulation at review (degrees)</td>
<td>≤ 0</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>1–5</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>3.1</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>2.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>6–10</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>2.4</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>2.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>11–15</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>3.3</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>4.3</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>3.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>16–20</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>5.5</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>2.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>21–25</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>2.9</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>2.6</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>3.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>≥ 26</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>4.0</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>4.2</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>3.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ulnar variance at review (mm)</td>
<td>≤ 0</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>1.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>1–2</td>
<td>74</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>89</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>1.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>3–4</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>2.1</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>3.0</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>2.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>5–6</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>4.3</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>4.7</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>4.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>7–13</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>5.5</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>5.4</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>5.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Radial inclination at review (degrees)</td>
<td>0–10</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>11.0</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>10.2</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>11.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>11–15</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>3.1</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>16–20</td>
<td>85</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>105</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>21–25</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>1.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>26–34</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>2.7</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>2.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age at injury</td>
<td>30–50</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>2.7</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>2.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>51–70</td>
<td>119</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>155</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>10.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>71–84</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>71</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>2.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sex</td>
<td>Men</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>2.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Women</td>
<td>189</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>229</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Treatment</td>
<td>Casted</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>1.8</td>
<td>76</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>1.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Reduced + casted</td>
<td>148</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>184</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AO fracture type</td>
<td>A2</td>
<td>161</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>199</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>A3</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>4.5</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>4.6</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>4.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>C1</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>1.8</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>1.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>C2</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>2.8</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>5.0</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>5.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fracture of ulnar styloid</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>128</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>153</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Tip</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>2.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Base</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>2.8</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>2.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DRUJ fracture</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>196</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>238</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>1.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>2.1</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>3.7</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>2.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intra-articular step-off at injury</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>201</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>246</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>1.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>1 mm</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>3.5</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>2.7</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>3.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>2–4 mm</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>2.9</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>4.4</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>4.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intra-articular gap at injury</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>195</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>239</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>1.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>1 mm</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>3.5</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>2.7</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>3.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>2–5 mm</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>3.4</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>2.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Years between injury and review</td>
<td>2.5–4 y</td>
<td>89</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>105</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>1.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>4–7 y</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>2.1</td>
<td>80</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>1.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>10-13 y</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>1.1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1753193412445144">
<p>0 = best; 100 = worst; n = number of patients; DRUJ = distal radioulnar joint; SEM = standard error of the mean.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Spearman’s test showed a statistically significant correlation between each of the four radiographic measurements at review and PRWE, Q-DASH, and GWOS scores (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1753193412445144">Table 2</xref>). The correlation coefficients were between 0.14 and 0.30. In subsequent analyses ulnar variance, rather than radial length, was used to indicate radial shortening, as the latter depends on both radial shortening and decrease in radial inclination.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1753193412445144" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Correlation (Spearman) of the recorded data with the Global Wrist Outcome Score (GWOS), Patient Rated Wrist Evaluation (PRWE), and Quick Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand (Q-DASH) outcome scores</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1753193412445144" xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412445144-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">GWOS</th>
<th align="left">PRWE</th>
<th align="left">Q-DASH</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>GWOS</td>
<td/>
<td>0.884<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
<td>0.750<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PRWE</td>
<td>0.884<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>0.799<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Q-DASH</td>
<td>0.750<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
<td>0.799<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age at injury</td>
<td>0.141<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">*</xref></td>
<td>0.059</td>
<td>0.073</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sex</td>
<td>0.100</td>
<td>0.112</td>
<td>0.140<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AO fracture type</td>
<td>−0.148<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.068</td>
<td>−0.049</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Frykman fracture type</td>
<td>−0.125</td>
<td>−0.059</td>
<td>−0.022</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ulnar styloid fracture (no/tip/base)</td>
<td>0.212<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>0.189<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>0.163<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DRUJ involved</td>
<td>0.091</td>
<td>0.091</td>
<td>0.088</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Treatment (casting only/reduction + casting)</td>
<td>0.089</td>
<td>0.032</td>
<td>0.071</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Time between injury and review</td>
<td>−0.192<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.220<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.163<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>At injury</bold></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dorsal angulation at injury</td>
<td>0.126</td>
<td>0.065</td>
<td>0.017</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ulnar variance at injury</td>
<td>0.223<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>0.145<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">*</xref></td>
<td>0.135<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Radial inclination at injury</td>
<td>−0.125</td>
<td>−0.113</td>
<td>−0.139<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Radial length at injury</td>
<td>−0.239<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.183<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.179<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intra-articular step-off at injury</td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>0.015</td>
<td>0.078</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intra-articular gap at injury</td>
<td>0.015</td>
<td>0.026</td>
<td>−0.018</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>At review: injured wrist</bold></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dorsal angulation at review</td>
<td>0.296<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
<td>0.189<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>0.185<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ulnar variance at review</td>
<td>0.293<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
<td>0.192<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>0.194<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Radial inclination at review</td>
<td>−0.199<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.134<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.160<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Radial length at review</td>
<td>−0.249<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.224<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.237<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intra-articular step-off at review</td>
<td>0.082</td>
<td>0.008</td>
<td>0.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intra-articular gap at review</td>
<td>−0.022</td>
<td>0.002</td>
<td>−0.023</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><bold>At review: difference from contralateral</bold></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dorsal angulation</td>
<td>0.271<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
<td>0.208<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>0.217<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ulnar variance</td>
<td>−0.206<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.160<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.135<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Radial inclination</td>
<td>0.237<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">***</xref></td>
<td>0.196<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>0.209<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Radial length</td>
<td>0.227<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>0.201<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
<td>0.213<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412445144">**</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1753193412445144">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; **<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-1753193412445144">
<p>DRUJ = distal radioulnar joint.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Linear regression analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1753193412445144">Table 3</xref>) showed that 23% of the variability (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) of the GWOS was accounted for when one included the variables dorsal angulation at review, ulnar variance at review, radial inclination at review, time between fracture and review, age at injury, gender, treatment (reduced and casted or only casted), fracture type, fracture of the ulnar styloid, involvement of the distal radioulnar joint, step-off of the distal radial articular surface as seen on radiographs at review, and complications. The same analysis with PRWE as the dependent variable gave an <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> of 20%, and with the Q-DASH as the dependent variable, an <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> of 16%. Step-wise regression analysis revealed that only complications, ulnar variance, dorsal angulation, and time since fracture significantly contributed to GWOS and PRWE scores (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 24% and 21%, respectively). Complications, radial inclination, time since fracture, and ulnar variance significantly contributed to the Q-DASH score (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 16%). The significance of these factors was confirmed by ordinal regression.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1753193412445144" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Key figures from regression analysis with GWOS as the dependent variable <italic>Model 1:</italic> Predictors: radial inclination at review, dorsal angulation at review, ulnar variance at review, time from injury to review, sex, involvement of distal radioulnar joint, treatment, ulnar styloid fracture, Frykman fracture type, age at injury, and intra-articular step-off at injury. <italic>Model 2:</italic> Predictors: dorsal angulation at review, ulnar variance at review, time between injury and review, and complications. <italic>Model 3:</italic> Predictors: radial inclination at review, dorsal angulation at review, ulnar variance at review</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1753193412445144" xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412445144-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="5"><bold>Table 3a.</bold> Model summary<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Model</th>
<th align="left"><italic>R</italic></th>
<th align="left"><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></th>
<th align="left">Adjusted <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></th>
<th align="left">SE of estimate</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.5226</td>
<td>0.273</td>
<td>0.229</td>
<td>11.295</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>0.500</td>
<td>0.250</td>
<td>0.235</td>
<td>11.251</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>0.348</td>
<td>0.121</td>
<td>0.109</td>
<td>12.148</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="6"><bold>Table 3b.</bold> Coefficients<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Model</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Unstandardized coefficients<hr/></th>
<th align="left">Standardized coefficients<hr/></th>
<th align="left"><italic>t</italic></th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">B</th>
<th align="left">SE</th>
<th align="left">Beta</th>
<th/>
<th/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1 (Constant)</td>
<td>15.959</td>
<td>8.557</td>
<td/>
<td>1.865</td>
<td>0.064</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Dorsal angulation at review</td>
<td>0.191</td>
<td>0.074</td>
<td>0.167</td>
<td>2.587</td>
<td><bold>0.010</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Ulnar variance at review</td>
<td>1.159</td>
<td>0.380</td>
<td>0.211</td>
<td>3.054</td>
<td><bold>0.003</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Radial inclination at review</td>
<td>−0.249</td>
<td>0.171</td>
<td>−0.099</td>
<td>−1.461</td>
<td>0.146</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Time from injury to review</td>
<td>−0.659</td>
<td>0.230</td>
<td>−0.183</td>
<td>−2.869</td>
<td><bold>0.005</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Age at injury</td>
<td>−0.087</td>
<td>0.078</td>
<td>−0.038</td>
<td>−1.113</td>
<td>0.267</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Sex</td>
<td>1.517</td>
<td>2.494</td>
<td>0.074</td>
<td>0.608</td>
<td>0.544</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Treatment</td>
<td>0.608</td>
<td>1.763</td>
<td>0.022</td>
<td>0.345</td>
<td>0.731</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Frykman fracture type</td>
<td>−0.814</td>
<td>0.393</td>
<td>−0.151</td>
<td>−1.252</td>
<td>0.212</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Ulnar styloid fracture</td>
<td>−0.52</td>
<td>1.060</td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>−0.049</td>
<td>0.961</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Fracture into DRUJ</td>
<td>5.965</td>
<td>4.243</td>
<td>0.132</td>
<td>1.406</td>
<td>0.161</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Intra-articular step-off at injury</td>
<td>1.057</td>
<td>4.659</td>
<td>0.015</td>
<td>−0.227</td>
<td>0.821</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Complications</td>
<td>9.605</td>
<td>2.039</td>
<td>0.300</td>
<td>4.712</td>
<td><bold>0.000</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 (Constant)</td>
<td>7.717</td>
<td>1.921</td>
<td/>
<td>4.017</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Dorsal angulation at review</td>
<td>0.200</td>
<td>0.070</td>
<td>0.174</td>
<td>2.867</td>
<td><bold>0.005</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Ulnar variance at review</td>
<td>1.215</td>
<td>0.332</td>
<td>0.222</td>
<td>3.657</td>
<td><bold>0.000</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Complications</td>
<td>10.604</td>
<td>1.947</td>
<td>0.331</td>
<td>5.448</td>
<td><bold>0.000</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Time from injury to review</td>
<td>−0.615</td>
<td>0.220</td>
<td>−0.170</td>
<td>−2.800</td>
<td><bold>0.006</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 (Constant)</td>
<td>15.520</td>
<td>3.999</td>
<td/>
<td>3.881</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Dorsal angulation at review</td>
<td>0.206</td>
<td>0.076</td>
<td>0.179</td>
<td>2.712</td>
<td><bold>0.007</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Ulnar variance at review</td>
<td>0.812</td>
<td>0.377</td>
<td>0.148</td>
<td>2.155</td>
<td><bold>0.032</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Radial inclination at review</td>
<td>−0.440</td>
<td>0.174</td>
<td>−0.176</td>
<td>−2.529</td>
<td><bold>0.012</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1753193412445144">
<p>DRUJ = distal radioulnar joint.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Finally, a linear regression analysis was performed using only dorsal angulation at review, ulnar variance at review, and radial inclination at review as independent variables. These three variables together accounted for 11% of the variability of the GWOS, 7% of the variability of the DASH, and 6% of the variability of the PRWE.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1753193412445144" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>We only contacted patients living fairly close to our hospital in the hope that this would increase the likelihood that they would return for review. Even so, only just over half came for the review. A similarly low rate of follow-up is reported in previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193412445144">Abramo et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412445144">Altissimi et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1753193412445144">Barton et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1753193412445144">Chung et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1753193412445144">Földhazy et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1753193412445144">Kopylov et al., 1993</xref>).</p>
<p>We selected 1997–98 initially because we wanted to include patients from a time when non-operative treatment was more common. We could not assess patients from before 1997 as their radiographs had been destroyed. In spite of treating approximately 500 distal radius fractures every year at our hospital, relatively few remained because of our exclusion criteria and because some radiographs had been lost. To increase the number of patients, we chose fractures sustained after June 2003 when our case-notes and radiographs were digitalized.</p>
<p>Ours is the only local hospital for our area. In spite of excluding the numerous patients where our case-notes indicated previous or later injuries that could influence function in either upper limb, a considerable number had to be excluded at review because they proved to have injuries that we had missed in our files or were unknown to us. Even though the prevalence of such confounding injuries is extremely high in the elderly population, it seems rarely to be taken into account in reviews of distal radius fracture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193412445144">Abramo et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1753193412445144">Arora et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1753193412445144">Foreward et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1753193412445144">Solgaard, 1988</xref>).</p>
<p>We agree with other authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1753193412445144">Amadio et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1753193412445144">Changulani et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1753193412445144">Földazy et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1753193412445144">Foreward et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1753193412445144">MacDermid et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1753193412445144">Wilcke et al., 2007</xref>) that it seems reasonable to consider both objective and subjective data when evaluating the outcome after distal radius fractures. In order to reduce the risk of finding spurious significant correlations by having many outcome measures, we have amalgamated most of them into our GWOS. The weighting of the components of the score can be disputed. From clinical experience we feel that pain is the most serious problem after distal radius fracture, and we have allotted just under half the points to this, similar to the PRWE. We placed more weight on grip strength than on ROM, as it is our experience that even a fairly substantial loss of mobility has little impact on the daily activities of most patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1753193412445144">Jaremko et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1753193412445144">Nelson, 1997</xref>). It seemed reasonable to select the PRWE for our GWOS as it measures function only in the relevant wrist. Our score has not formally been validated, but shows a high degree of correlation not only with the PRWE, but also with Q-DASH. In the bivariate analyses of our data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1753193412445144">Table 2</xref>), the GWOS was more closely associated with 18 of the 23 suggested predictors of outcome than was either the PRWE or Q-DASH.</p>
<p>There was a statistically significant correlation between radiological measurements at review and the functional result among our patients. However, this alone does not indicate the magnitude or importance of this association. Multiple regression analysis showed that its influence on the final clinical outcome was, in fact, quite small. Furthermore, we found that neither age, fracture type, fracture of the ulnar styloid, involvement of the DRUJ, or intra-articular step-off significantly influenced the final clinical outcome. Only a few of our patients had intra-articular displacement.</p>
<p>Unexpectedly, we found that time between injury and follow-up had a highly statistically significant influence on the clinical outcome, even though our shortest follow-up was 2.5 years. This might indicate that the final result after distal radius fracture has not been reached even 2.5 years after fracture. This has not been reported in other studies.</p>
<p>This is a retrospective study, which raises the question of whether our sample of patients is representative. The strengths of this study are that the patients we assessed had no previous disabilities of the upper extremities; that they were able to come to the review probably indicates they did not have a lower demand on their wrists than the average for their age; and many of the fractures healed with considerable displacement (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1753193412445144">Table 1</xref>). Thirty-six patients (14%) had a final dorsal angulation of &gt; 20°, 38 (15%) an ulnar variance of &gt; 5 mm, and 46 (18%) &lt; 15° of radial inclination at review.</p>
<p>The decision to treat a distal radius fracture operatively is based primarily on radiographs during the first few days after injury, long before the clinical outcome is known. The patients who had surgery of their fracture therefore have no bearing on our findings. The main confounder is that some conservatively treated patients with painful wrists will have been treated with a corrective osteotomy or ulnar shortening. Between 2005 and 2009, we only performed corrective osteotomies for malunited distal radius fractures in eight patients from the municipalities chosen for this study. For geographical reasons, it is unlikely that they will have had the procedure performed at some other institution.</p>
<p>Although we felt that we had included most of the factors commonly assumed to be of importance in determining the outcome after distal radial fracture, most of the variation in the GWOS, PRWE, and Q-DASH scores could not be explained by our data. Factors such as physiotherapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1753193412445144">Kay et al., 2008</xref>) may be of importance for the final result. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1753193412445144">Grewal et al. (2007)</xref> found that injury compensation cases and length of education accounted for 16% of the variation in PRWE in 222 patients reviewed 1 year after fracture. Others have found injury compensation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1753193412445144">MacDermid et al., 2002</xref>) and level of income (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1753193412445144">Chung et al., 2007</xref>) to be the strongest determinants of outcome.</p>
<p>Many experts feel that, as in most other fractures, re-establishing bony anatomy is important in order to obtain a good clinical outcome after a distal radius fracture. In 25 papers dealing with the association between radiological and clinical outcome after distal radius fracture, six found that none of the common radiological predictors was useful (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193412445144">Abramo et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1753193412445144">Chung et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1753193412445144">Kopylov et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1753193412445144">MacDermid et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1753193412445144">Smail, 1965</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1753193412445144">Stewart et al., 1985</xref>). Nine of the 25 studies found dorsal angulation to be of importance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412445144">Altissimi et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1753193412445144">Batra and Gupta, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1753193412445144">Brogren et al., 2011A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1753193412445144">Dixon et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1753193412445144">Gliatis et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1753193412445144">Grewal and MacDermid, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1753193412445144">Pechlaner et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1753193412445144">Tsukazaki, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1753193412445144">Wilcke et al., 2007</xref>). Three concluded that the cut-off point was at 10° dorsal angulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1753193412445144">Brogren et al., 2011A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1753193412445144">Gliatis et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1753193412445144">Grewal and MacDermid, 2007</xref>), and three at 15° (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412445144">Altissimi et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1753193412445144">Dixon et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1753193412445144">Wilcke et al., 2007</xref>). Six of the 25 studies concluded that loss of radial inclination was important (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412445144">Altissimi et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1753193412445144">Grewal and MacDermid, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1753193412445144">Jenkins and Mintowt-Czyz, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1753193412445144">Kumar et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1753193412445144">Pechlaner et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1753193412445144">Wilcke et al., 2007</xref>). Two found a cut-off point at 15° remaining radial inclination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1753193412445144">Grewal and MacDermid, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1753193412445144">Kumar et al., 2008</xref>), one at 10° (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1753193412445144">Wilcke et al., 2007</xref>), and one at 5° (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412445144">Altissimi et al., 1986</xref>).</p>
<p>Sixteen of the 25 studies found loss of radial length to be a predictor of clinical outcome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412445144">Altissimi et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1753193412445144">Batra and Gupta, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1753193412445144">Brogren et al., 2011A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1753193412445144">Dixon et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1753193412445144">Földhazy et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1753193412445144">Foreward et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1753193412445144">Grewal and MacDermid, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1753193412445144">Karnezis et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1753193412445144">Kumar et al., 2008</xref>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1753193412445144">Ng and McQueen, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1753193412445144">Pechlaner et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1753193412445144">Solgaard, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1753193412445144">Trumble et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1753193412445144">Villar et al., 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1753193412445144">Warwick et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1753193412445144">Wilcke et al., 2007</xref>). Three papers reported this as radial height (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1753193412445144">Ng and McQueen, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1753193412445144">Solgaard, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1753193412445144">Villaret al., 1987</xref>) and one of them found a cut-off point at 2 mm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1753193412445144">Ng and McQueen, 2011</xref>). The remainder reported radial shortening as ulnar variance. One paper found a cut-off point at 2 mm ulnar variance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1753193412445144">Wilcke et al., 2007</xref>), two at 3 mm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1753193412445144">Dixon et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1753193412445144">Grewal and MacDermid, 2007</xref>), and one at 5 mm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412445144">Altissimi et al., 1986</xref>).</p>
<p>Very few of the papers that found a statically significant association between one or more measures of radiological displacement and clinical outcome estimated the magnitude or importance of this factor. In our patients the association was highly statistically significant, but the impact on the clinical result surprisingly small. In a recent overview, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1753193412445144">Ilyas and Jupiter (2010)</xref> endorse the view that in closed fractures without associated injuries, radial inclination of &gt; 15°, radial shortening of ≤ 5 mm, radial tilt of &lt; 15° dorsal or 20° volar, and &lt; 2 mm intra-articular step-off are acceptable after closed reduction. The <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1753193412445144">AAOS (2011)</xref> recently reviewed the literature and found only moderate evidence to support operative fixation for fractures with post-reduction radial shortening of &gt; 3 mm, dorsal tilt &gt; 10°, or intra-articular displacement or step-off of &gt; 2 mm as opposed to cast fixation.</p>
<p>A number of studies report the results among elderly patients in isolation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1753193412445144">Fujii et al. (2002)</xref> reviewed 22 patients aged 69 (range 60–88) years with severely displaced fractures that were reduced, pinned, and plastered. At review after 24 (12–53) months, radial shortening &gt; 6 mm indicated a poor clinical outcome. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1753193412445144">Egol et al. (2010)</xref> compared 44 patients over the age of 65 years who had been treated operatively to 46 patients who had been treated conservatively. One year after fracture, the operated patients had better radiographic parameters and grip strength. DASH scores, pain scores, and ROM were the same in the two groups.</p>
<p>Most studies of distal radius fractures in elderly patients have found no association between radiological displacement and clinical outcome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1753193412445144">Anzarut et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1753193412445144">Barton et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1753193412445144">Dayican et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1753193412445144">Grewal and MacDermid, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1753193412445144">Horne et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1753193412445144">Jaremko et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1753193412445144">Jupiter et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1753193412445144">Kelly et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1753193412445144">Kumar et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1753193412445144">Synn et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1753193412445144">Young and Rayan, 2000</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1753193412445144">Roumen et al. (1991)</xref> studied 43 patients aged over 55 who had radiological evidence of re-displacement of the distal fracture fragment in POP. Half were re-reduced and stabilized with an external fixator. When reviewed after 6 months, radiographs in the external fixation group were better than the control group, but function was no better than in the control group. There was no correlation between anatomical and functional outcome.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1753193412445144">Arora et al. (2009)</xref> recommended surgery to 114 patients over the age of 70 years with reduced dorsally displaced fractures that had re-displaced to &gt; 20° dorsal angulation, 3 mm radial shortening, or had an intra-articular step of ≥ 2 mm. Surgery was refused by 61 patients, who continued non-operative treatment without re-reduction (mean follow-up 53 months) and 53 patients were treated surgically with fracture reduction and application of a volar locking plate (mean follow-up 62 months). At final review, there was no significant difference between the two groups with regard to ROM, grip strength, DASH, PRWE, or <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1753193412445144">Green and O’Brien (1978)</xref> scores. VAS for pain was significantly higher in the operated group.</p>
<p>In a literature review, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1753193412445144">Diaz-Garcia et al. (2011)</xref> identified 21 English-language papers on the management of patients over 60 years with unstable distal radius fractures. They concluded that cast immobilization gave a worse radiographic outcome, but that the clinical result was that same as in those treated with volar locking plates, external fixation, or K-wire stabilization. The <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1753193412445144">AAOS (2011)</xref> found the evidence to be inconclusive to support operative treatment for patients over age 55 with distal radius fractures.</p>
<p>There are indications that clinical improvement is more rapid when skeletal anatomy has been restored (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1753193412445144">Brogren et al., 2011B</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1753193412445144">Chen et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1753193412445144">Chung et al., 2007</xref>), and there is often no need for POP after volar plating. Both of these points are of benefit to the patient, but must be weighed against the considerably increased risk of complications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1753193412445144">Downing and Karantana, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1753193412445144">Hakimi et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1753193412445144">Jupiter et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1753193412445144">Sahu et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1753193412445144">Sügün et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1753193412445144">Wilcke et al., 2007</xref>). In their literature review, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1753193412445144">Diaz-Garcia et al. (2011)</xref> found that there were complications requiring surgery in 11% of patients who had volar plates and 1% in those who had been immobilized in a cast.</p>
<p>It seems fairly well established that only the very most displaced or comminuted fractures in the elderly may possibly benefit from surgery. Elderly patients should be made aware of this before consenting to surgery and also of the very considerable risk of post-operative complications and need for re-operation.</p>
<p>The aim of the present study was to find the limits of fracture malunion that are compatible with a good clinical outcome. Our results indicate that almost all degrees of malunion are compatible with good function, and that poor function may be seen in the presence of normal radiological anatomy. This appears to be in accordance with many previous studies. A Cochrane review (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1753193412445144">Handoll and Madhok, 2003</xref>) was unable even to conclude that reduction of the fracture improves the clinical outcome.</p>
<p>We conclude that the present state of knowledge indicates that the radiological outcome after dorsally displaced distal radius fractures, counter-intuitively, has only a minor influence on long-term clinical outcome. It may be that the considerable resources allocated by many hard-pressed health services to open reduction and internal fixation of distal radius fractures would be better used in other ways. This is especially so for elderly patients who should probably only be treated surgically for the few most-markedly comminuted and displaced fractures.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>We thank Ingunn Brøndbo, St. Olav’s University Hospital, for invaluable administrative assistance, and Olav E. Foss, PhD, Norwegian Orthopaedic Implant Research Unit and Mette Langaas and Øyvind Salvesen, Unit for Applied Clinical Research, NTNU, Trondheim, for advice on statistical analysis.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interests</label>
<p>None declared.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
<p>The study was approved by the regional ethics committee and the Norwegian social sciences data service.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abramo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kopylov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tägil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of a treatment protocol in distal radius fractures. A prospective study in 581 patients using DASH as outcome</article-title>. <source>Acta Orthop Scand</source>. <year>2008</year>, <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>376</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Altissimi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Antenucci</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fiacca</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term results of conservative treatment of fractures of the distal radius</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop</source>. <year>1986</year>, <volume>206</volume>: <fpage>202</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Amadio</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ilstrup</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schleck</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Outcome after Colles fracture: The relative responsiveness of three questionnaires and physical examination measures</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1996</year>, <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>American Academy of Orthopedic Surgeons</collab>. <article-title>The treatment of distal radius fractures. Summary of recommendations</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2011</year>, <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>775</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anzarut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>RGW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blitz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Majumdar</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Radiological and patient-reported functional outcome in an elderly cohort with conservatively treated distal radius fractures</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2004</year>, <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1121</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gabl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gschwentner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deml</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krappinger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A comparative study of clinical and radiological outcomes of unstable Colles type distal radius fractures in patients older than 70 years: Nonoperative treatment versus volar locking plates</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Trauma</source>. <year>2009</year>, <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A comparison between subjective outcome score and moderate radial shortening following a fractured distal radius in patients of mean age 69 years</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Eur</source>. <year>2007</year>, <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Batra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of fracture-related factors on the functional outcome at 1 year in distal radius fractures</article-title>. <source>Injury</source>. <year>2002</year>, <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>499</fpage>–<lpage>502</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bechtol</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Grip test. The use of a dynamometer with adjustable handle spacings</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1954</year>, <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>820</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brogren</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petranek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dahlin</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Atroshi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Relationship between distal radius fracture malunion and arm-related disability: A prospective population-based cohort study with 1-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>BMC Musoloskelet Disord</source>. <year>2011A</year>, <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brogren</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petranek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dahlin</surname><given-names>L B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Atroshi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Fractures of the distal radius in women aged 50 to 75 years: natural course of patient-reported outcome, wrist motion and grip strength between 1 year and 2-4 years after fracture</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Eur</source>. <year>2011B</year>, <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>568</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Changulani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Okonkwo</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keswani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalairajah</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Outcome evaluation measures for wrist and hand: which one to choose?</article-title> <source>Int Orthop</source>. <year>2008</year>, <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jupiter</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Management of distal radius fractures</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2007</year>, <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>2051</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kotsis</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of functional outcomes after surgical treatment of distal radius fractures</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2007</year>, <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Colles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>On the fracture of the carpal extremity of the radius</article-title>. <source>Edinburgh Med Surg</source>. <year>1814</year>, <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>182</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dayican</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Unal</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ozkurt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Portakal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nuhoglu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tumoz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Conservative treatment in intra-articular fractures of the distal radius: a study on the functional and anatomic outcome in elderly patients</article-title>. <source>Yonsei Med J</source>. <year>2003</year>, <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>836</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Diaz-Garcia</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shauver</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A systematic review of outcome and complications of treating unstable distal radius fractures in the elderly</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2011</year>, <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>824</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Which Colles’ fractures should be manipulated?</article-title> <source>Injury</source>. <year>2005</year>, <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Downing</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karantana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A revolution in the management of fractures of the distal radius?</article-title> <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>2008</year>, <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>1271</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Egol</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romo-Cardoso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dorsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paksima</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paksima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distal radial fractures in the elderly: Operative compared with nonoperative treatment</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2010</year>, <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>1851</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Finsen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Norwegian version of the DASH questionnaire for examination of the arm shoulders and hand [Norwegian]</article-title>. <source>Tidsskr Nor Laegeforen</source>. <year>2008</year>, <volume>128</volume>: <year>1070</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Földhazy</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Törnkvist</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elmstedt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hagsten</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahrengart</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term outcome of nonsurgically treated distal radius fractures</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2007</year>, <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1374</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foreward</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>TRC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sithole</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Do young patients with malunited fractures of the distal radius inevitably develop symptomatic post-traumatic osteoarthritis?</article-title> <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>2008</year>, <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henmi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kanematsu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mishiro</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Terai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Fractures of the distal end of radius in elderly patients: a comparative study of anatomical and functional results</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Surg</source> (<comment>Hong Kong</comment>). <year>2002</year>, <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gliatis</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Plessas</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Outcome of distal radial fractures in young adults</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br</source>. <year>2000</year>, <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Open reduction of carpal dislocations: indications and operative techniques</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1978</year>, <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>250</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacDermid</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chesworth</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Baseline predictors of pain and disability one year following extra-articular distal radius fractures</article-title>. <source>Hand (NY)</source>. <year>2007</year>, <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacDermid</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The risk of adverse outcomes in extra-articular distal radius fractures is increased with malalignment in patients of all ages but mitigated in older patients</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2007</year>, <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>962</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gummesson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Atroshi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The shortened Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand questionnaire (QuickDASH): validity and reliability based on responses within the full-length DASH</article-title>. <source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord</source>. <year>2006</year>, <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>44</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hakimi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jungbluth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Windolf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wild</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Functional results and complications following locking palmar plating on the distal radius: a retrospective study</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Eur</source>. <year>2010</year>, <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Handoll</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Madhok</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Conservative interventions for treating distal radial fractures in adults</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2003</year>: <comment>CD000314</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hølmer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krøner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reference program regarding Colles fractures [Danish]</article-title>. <source>Danish Orthopaedic Society</source>. <year>2001</year>; <comment>ISSN: 1398-1560</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Horne</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Devane</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Purdie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A prospective randomized trial of external fixation and plaster cast immobilization in the treatment of distal radial fractures</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Trauma</source>. <year>1990</year>, <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hudak</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amadio</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bombardier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Development of an upper extremity outcome measure: the DASH</article-title>. <source>Am J Int Med</source>. <year>1996</year>, <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>602</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ilyas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jupiter</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distal radius fractures – Classification and indications for surgery</article-title>. <source>Hand Clin</source>. <year>2010</year>, <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jaremko</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>RGW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Majumdar</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Do radiographic indices of distal radius fracture reduction predict outcome in older adults receiving conservative treatment?</article-title> <source>Clin Radiol</source>. <year>2007</year>, <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mintowt-Czyz</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mal-union and dysfunction in Colles’ fracture</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br</source>. <year>1988</year>, <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jupiter</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weitzel</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Surgical treatment of redisplaced fractures of the distal radius in patients older than 60 years</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2002</year>, <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>714</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Karnezis</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Panagiotopoulos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tallianakis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Megas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lambris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Correlation between radiological parameters and patient-rated wrist dysfunction following fractures of the distal radius</article-title>. <source>Injury</source>. <year>2005</year>, <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1435</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stiller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An advice and exercise program has some benefits over natural recovery after distal radius fracture: a randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Aust J Physiother</source>. <year>2008</year>, <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warwick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crichlow</surname><given-names>TPK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Is manipulation of moderately displaced Colles’ fractures worthwhile? A randomized trial</article-title>. <source>Injury</source>. <year>1997</year>, <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kopylov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jonell</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Redlund-Johnell</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bengner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Fractures of the distal end of the radius in young adults: a 30-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br</source>. <year>1993</year>, <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Penematsa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sadri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deshmukh</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Can radiological results be surrogate markers of functional outcome in distal radial extra-articular fractures?</article-title> <source>Int Orthop</source>. <year>2008</year>, <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>MacDermid</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turgeon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beadle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Patient rating of wrist pain and disability: a reliable and valid measurement tool</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Trauma</source>. <year>1998</year>, <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>MacDermid</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Patient versus injury factors as predictors of pain and disability six months after a distal radius fracture</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>2002</year>, <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>849</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nazarian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <source>AO classification of fractures</source>. <publisher-loc>Springer Verlag, Berlin</publisher-loc>, <year>1987</year>: <fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Functional wrist motion</article-title>. <source>Hand Clin</source>. <year>1997</year>, <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McQueen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>What are the radiological predictors of functional outcome following fractures of the distal radius?</article-title> <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>2011</year>, <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pechlaner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gabi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distale radiusfrakturen – ätiologie, behandlungsmethoden und ergebnisse</article-title>. <source>Handchir Microchir Plast Chir</source>. <year>2007</year>, <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roumen</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hesp</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bruggink</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Unstable Colles’ fractures in elderly patients. A randomised trial of external fixation for redisplacement</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1991</year>, <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sahu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charalambous</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Batra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ravencroft</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reoperation for metalwork complications following the use of volar locking plates for distal radius fractures: A United Kingdom experience</article-title>. <source>Hand Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>, <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smail</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term follow-up of Colles’s fracture</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1965</year>, <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Solgaard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Function after distal radius fracture</article-title>. <source>Acta Orthop Scand</source>. <year>1988</year>, <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Innes</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Factors affecting the outcome of Colles’ fracture: an anatomical and functional study</article-title>. <source>Injury</source>. <year>1985</year>, <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sügün</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karabay</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gürbüz</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Özaksar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toros</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kayalar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Screw prominences related to palmar locking plating of distal radius</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Eur</source>. <year>2011</year>, <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>320</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Synn</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Makhni</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Makhni</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rozental</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distal radius fractures in older patients. Is anatomical reduction necessary?</article-title> <source>Clin Orthop</source>. <year>2009</year>, <volume>467</volume>: <fpage>1612</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trumble</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vedder</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Factors affecting functional outcome of displaced intra-articular distal radius fractures</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1994</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tsukazaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Poor correlation between functional results and radiographic findings in Colles’ fracture</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br</source>. <year>1993</year>, <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Villar</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rushton</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greatorex</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Three years after Colles’ fracture</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1987</year>, <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>635</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Warwick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prothero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Function ten years after Colles’ fracture</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1993</year>, <fpage>270</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilcke</surname><given-names>MKT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abbaszadegan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adolphson</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Patients-perceived outcome after displaced distal radius fractures. A comparison between radiological parameters, objective physical variables, and the DASH score</article-title>. <source>J Hand Ther</source>. <year>2007</year>, <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>290</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1753193412445144">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rayan</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Outcome following nonoperative treatment of displaced distal radius fractures in low-demand patients older than 60 years</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2000</year>, <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>