<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JHS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjhs</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Hand Surg Eur Vol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Hand Surgery (European Volume)</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1753-1934</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2043-6289</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753193412451383</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1753193412451383</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Full length articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Comparison of three dimensional and radiographic measurements in the analysis of distal radius malunion</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1753193412451383">Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Osaka University Graduate School of Medicine, Osaka, Japan</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-1753193412451383">Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Kyoritsu Hospital, Hyogo, Japan</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Moritomo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff3-1753193412451383">Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Osaka University Graduate School of Medicine, Osaka, Japan</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sugamoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff4-1753193412451383">Department of Orthopaedic Biomaterial Science, Osaka University Graduate School of Medicine, Osaka, Japan</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff5-1753193412451383">Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Osaka University Graduate School of Medicine, Osaka, Japan</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1753193412451383">Junichi Miyake MD, Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Osaka University Graduate School of Medicine, 2-2 Yamadaoka, Suita 565-0871, Osaka, Japan Email: <email>miyake-osk@umin.ac.jp</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>38</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>133</fpage>
<lpage>143</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>12</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>17</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>21</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The British Society for Surgery of the Hand</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>To estimate the accuracy of radiographic deformity evaluation for distal radius malunion, we compared the results obtained from radiographic measurements (palmar tilt, radial angle, and ulnar variance) with those from the three-dimensional (3D) method using computer bone models in 20 dorsally tilted malunions. Dorsal tilt deformity, radial tilt deformity, and shortening deformity were calculated using the unaffected side as a reference. The 3D method showed a slightly lower value for dorsal tilt deformity than the radiographic evaluation, but the difference was &lt; 10° in all cases. In patients with dorsal tilt ≥ 40°, notable differences in radial tilt evaluation were observed between the two methods compared with patients with less dorsal tilt. The 3D shortening showed positive correlations with radiographic evaluation, but a discrepancy of ≥ 2 mm was observed in eight cases. Palmar tilt is reliable for surgical planning, but radial angle and ulnar variance may be less accurate than previously thought.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Distal radius malunion</kwd>
<kwd>three-dimensional analysis</kwd>
<kwd>dorsal tilt</kwd>
<kwd>radial angle</kwd>
<kwd>ulnar variance</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1753193412451383" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Patients with symptomatic malunion, restricted wrist range of motion, reduced grip strength, late neuropathy, and/or unsightly appearance are considered for corrective osteotomy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1753193412451383">Fernandez, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1753193412451383">Jupiter and Fernandez, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1753193412451383">Ladd and Huene, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1753193412451383">Prommersberger et al., 2002</xref>). Pre-operative deformity evaluation using plain radiographs has been widely employed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1753193412451383">Fernandez, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1753193412451383">Kreder et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1753193412451383">Ladd and Huene, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1753193412451383">Prommersberger et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1753193412451383">von Campe et al., 2006</xref>). For planning surgery, the differences in palmar tilt, radial angle, and ulnar variance between the normal and affected sides have been used to determine the amount of correction of dorsal tilt deformity (rotational deformity in the sagittal plane), radial tilt deformity (rotational deformity in the coronal plane), and shortening deformity, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1753193412451383">Hollevoet et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1753193412451383">Ladd and Huene, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1753193412451383">Prommersberger et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1753193412451383">von Campe et al., 2006</xref>). However, several studies have revealed that distal radius malunion usually has a three-dimensional (3D) deformity; malunion is sometimes a complex deformity and pre-operative planning based on evaluation by plain radiography is not always sufficiently accurate to ensure anatomical correction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412451383">Athwal et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1753193412451383">Bilic et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1753193412451383">Jupiter et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1753193412451383">Miyake et al., 2012</xref>). Studies have revealed that the prevalence of residual deformity ranged from 38% to 60%, even after procedures carried out by experienced surgeons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1753193412451383">Hove and Molster, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1753193412451383">Prommersberger et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1753193412451383">von Campe et al., 2006</xref>). Biomechanical and clinical studies have suggested that residual deformity after corrective osteotomy can affect outcome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1753193412451383">Fraser et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1753193412451383">Kihara et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1753193412451383">Miyake et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1753193412451383">Pogue et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1753193412451383">Prommersberger et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1753193412451383">Short et al., 1987</xref>).</p>
<p>On the other hand, advances in computer technology have made accurate 3D pre-operative planning possible, and one can evaluate the deformity more precisely using 3D computer bone models created from computed tomography (CT) data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412451383">Athwal et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1753193412451383">Jupiter et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1753193412451383">Oka et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1753193412451383">Miyake et al., 2011</xref>). The purpose of this study was to estimate the accuracy of radiographic deformity evaluation for distal radius malunions by comparing the results obtained from plain radiographic measurement with those of the 3D method using 3D computer bone models. To our knowledge, a study comparing 3D quantification of malunited fracture deformities of the distal radius with plain radiographic measurement has not been reported.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1753193412451383" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>After obtaining approval from our institutional review board, informed consent was obtained from 20 patients who had dorsally tilted malunions of distal radius fractures between April 2004 and November 2010. There were five males and 15 females of an average age of 54 (range 18–79) years. The dominant upper limb, which was the right in all patients, was involved in five cases. We included patients with dorsally displaced metaphyseal malunion without intra-articular malunion, which was confirmed by CT imaging. Radiographically, all patients had sustained extra-articular fractures (Association for Osteosynthesis/Association for the Study of Internal Fixation classification, A3) at initial injury. All patients were initially treated by closed reduction and cast immobilization. After bony union was achieved, they visited our institution complaining of wrist pain, deformity, and/or numbness in the median nerve region. They had not previously undergone surgery. The average interval between injury and examination was 12 (range 3–53) months. There was no history of trauma to the contralateral wrist in all patients.</p>
<p>The affected and contralateral limbs of all patients were scanned using a CT scanner (LightSpeed Ultra 16; GE Healthcare, Waukesha, Wisconsin, USA) with a low radiation dose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1753193412451383">Oka et al., 2009</xref>) (scan time 0.5 s; scan pitch 0.562:1; tube current 10–30 mA; and tube voltage 120 kV). Imaging was undertaken in the prone position with the shoulder in full flexion and both limbs overhead. Data were sent to a workstation in a standard format (Digital Imaging and Communications in Medicine). The 3D bone surface models of the entire bilateral radius were created from the 1.25 mm-slice digital data using an original computer program based on Visualization Toolkit (Kitware; Clifton Park, New York, USA). The 3D deformity was analyzed by superimposing the affected radius onto the mirror image of the contralateral normal radius, which was considered to be the preinjured model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412451383">Athwal et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1753193412451383">Jupiter et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1753193412451383">Oka et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1753193412451383">Miyake et al., 2012</xref>). The coordinate system was defined in the mirror image of the normal side of the radius based on the radius coordinate system for the hand and wrist, as advocated by the International Society of Biomechanics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1753193412451383">Wu et al., 2005</xref>). The amount of deformity was evaluated as the distance between the mirror image of the normal radius and image of the affected radius superimposed proximally to distally. The proximal/distal part of the affected radius model was superimposed onto the corresponding part of the mirror image of the contralateral normal radius using independent implementation of the iterative closest point algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1753193412451383">Besl, 1992</xref>). We quantified the amount of deformity by subtracting the distance value of the proximal radius from that of the distal radius. The amount of deformity was represented by the rotation angle around the unique axis established in the mirror image of the normal radius with 6 degrees of freedom using the Euler angles method (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1753193412451383">Figure 1</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1753193412451383">Takeyasu et al., 2011</xref>). We the calculated <italic>3D dorsal tilt, 3D radial tilt</italic>, and <italic>3D axial rotation.</italic> To evaluate the shortening deformity by simply using the mirror image of the contralateral normal radius is not feasible, because differences in the length of the sides exist in the forearm bones, although there is a strong relation between absolute length differences between individuals’ radius and ulna (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1753193412451383">Vroemen et al., 2012</xref>). Therefore, the requisite lengthening of the ulnar-palmar part of the affected radius to match the length of ulna, identical to the opposite side, was calculated following simulation of rotational reduction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1753193412451383">Figure 2</xref>). The requisite lengthening was defined as <italic>3D shortening</italic>.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1753193412451383" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Deformity evaluation using 3D computer bone models. 3D dorsal tilt, 3D radial tilt, and 3D axial rotation were calculated by quantifying the displacement of the distal part of the affected side relative to the mirror image of the normal side.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412451383-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-1753193412451383" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>3D shortening: the needed lengthening of the ulnar-palmar part of the affected radius to match the length of ulna, identical to the opposite side, was calculated following simulation of rotational reduction.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412451383-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Standard posteroanterior and lateral radiographs of both wrists were obtained with the forearm maintained in neutral rotation and the elbow flexed at 90°. Palmar tilt, radial angle, and ulnar variance were measured according to the method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1753193412451383">Kreder et al. (1996)</xref>. To measure palmar tilt, we drew a line perpendicular to the central long axis of the radius. A line connected the dorsal and anterior margins of the distal radial articular surface in the lateral radiographs. The angle made by the two lines was measured as the palmar tilt using a standard goniometer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1753193412451383">Figure 3A</xref>). The central long axis of the radius was determined by connecting the two midpoints of the radial shaft at 3 and 5 cm below the mid-region of the proximal lunate articular surface. The radial angle was determined by the two lines in the posteroanterior radiographs. The first line was perpendicular to the central long axis of the radius drawn at the level of the ulnar margin of the distal radial articular surface. The central long axis of the radius was determined by connecting two midpoints of the radial shaft at 3 and 5 cm in the proximal mid-region of the proximal lunate articular surface. The second line connected the radial and ulnar margins of the distal radial articular surface. If two articular surface lines of the distal radius were observed, the proximal cortical line was used, i.e., the dorsal cortical line was used in dorsally tilted malunions. The angle between the two lines was then measured as the radial angle using a goniometer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1753193412451383">Figure 3B</xref>). To measure the ulnar variance, we drew the two lines perpendicular to the central long axis of the radius. The first line was at the level of the ulnar margin of the distal radial articular surface; the second line was at the level of the distal ulnar articular surface. With respect to the former, the palmar cortical line was used. We then measured the distance between these two lines as the ulnar variance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1753193412451383">Figure 3C</xref>). For the purpose of evaluating dorsal tilt deformity, radial tilt deformity, and shortening deformity, the status of the contralateral normal wrist was considered to be preinjured (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1753193412451383">Hollevoet et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1753193412451383">Ladd and Huene, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1753193412451383">Prommersberger et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1753193412451383">von Campe et al., 2006</xref>) and the differences in palmar tilt, radial angle, and ulnar variance between the normal and affected sides were defined as <italic>radiographic dorsal tilt, radiographic radial tilt</italic>, and <italic>radiographic shortening</italic>.</p>
<fig id="fig3-1753193412451383" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption><p>Radiographic examination: measurement of (A) palmar tilt, (B) radial angle, and (C) ulnar variance.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412451383-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>To ensure intraobserver reliability, two examination sessions were conducted by one hand surgeon (JM). To establish interobserver reliability, evaluation was performed by two independent hand surgeons (JM and YY). Intraclass correlation coefficients were calculated and reliability rated as <italic>acceptable</italic> if the result was ≥ 0.80. To determine the accuracy of radiographic deformity evaluation, correlations between plain radiographs and 3D evaluations were analyzed using Pearson’s correlation coefficient and simple regression analysis. Differences between evaluation using plain radiographs and the 3D method were assessed. With respect to radial tilt deformity, we speculated that malunions with severe dorsal tilt have smaller radial angles than those with slight dorsal tilt because of the shape of the distal radius. Therefore, two groups of patients were defined according to 3D dorsal tilt as follows: those with a 3D dorsal tilt ≥ 40° were assigned to the <italic>severely dorsal-tilted</italic> group and those with a 3D dorsal tilt &lt; 40° were assigned to the <italic>moderately dorsal-tilted</italic> group. Comparison of the distribution of differences of &gt; 10° in evaluations by plain radiographs and the 3D method in these two groups was investigated using the Chi-square test. To determine the influence of axial rotational deformity, correlations between the degree of 3D axial rotation and differences between evaluation by plain radiography and the 3D method were examined using Pearson’s correlation coefficient. The results were deemed significant if <italic>p</italic> values were &lt; 0.05. SD indicates standard deviations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1753193412451383" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section4-1753193412451383">
<title>Dorsal tilt deformity (rotational deformity in the sagittal plane)</title>
<p>On 3D measurement, the average 3D dorsal tilt was 30° (range 7° to 56°; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1753193412451383">Table 1</xref>). The average palmar tilt on plain radiographs of the affected wrists was −19° (range −40° to 0°), whereas that of the contralateral normal wrists was 14° (range 9° to 21°). Consequently, the average radiographic dorsal tilt, i.e., the differences in palmar tilt between the normal and affected sides, was 33° (range 12° to 57°; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1753193412451383">Table 1</xref>). Inter- and intraobserver reliabilities were adequate to assess the deformity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1753193412451383">Table 2</xref>). The 3D dorsal tilt showed positive correlations with the radiographic dorsal tilt (<italic>R</italic> = 0.97, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1753193412451383">Figure 4</xref>). The 3D dorsal tilt showed slightly smaller values than those of the radiographic dorsal tilt (<italic>y</italic> = 1.02x – 3.3), but the absolute difference between evaluations by the 3D method and plain radiographs was &lt; 10° in all cases (average 3.3°, SD 2.5°).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1753193412451383" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Comparison of results between 3D and radiographic analysis</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1753193412451383" xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412451383-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Case</th>
<th align="left">Affected side</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Dorsal tilt deformity<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Radial tilt deformity<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Shortening deformity<hr/></th>
<th align="left">Axial rotational deformity</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="left">3D dorsal tilt, °</th>
<th align="left">Radiographic dorsal tilt, °<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1753193412451383">*</xref></th>
<th align="left">Difference, °</th>
<th align="left">3D radial tilt, °</th>
<th align="left">Radiographic radial tilt, °<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1753193412451383">†</xref></th>
<th align="left">Difference, °</th>
<th align="left">3D shortening, mm</th>
<th align="left">Radiographic shortening, mm<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1753193412451383">‡</xref></th>
<th align="left">Difference, mm</th>
<th align="left">3D axial rotational deformity, °<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1753193412451383">§</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 1</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>−5</td>
<td>−9</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>R</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>−1</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>−1</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>−3</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>−2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>R</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>−1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>−3</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14</td>
<td>R</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>−1</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>17</td>
<td>R</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>19</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td>R</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average</td>
<td/>
<td>30</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>3.0</td>
<td>2.3</td>
<td>1.8</td>
<td>15</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1753193412451383">
<label>*</label>
<p>Radiographic dorsal tilt, difference in palmar tilt between the affected and unaffected side.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-1753193412451383">
<label>†</label>
<p>Radiographic radial tilt, difference in radial angle between the affected and unaffected side.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-1753193412451383">
<label>‡</label>
<p>Radiographic shortening, difference in ulnar variance between the affected and unaffected side.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-1753193412451383">
<label>§</label>
<p>The plus sign of 3D axial rotational deformity reflects pronation deformity of the distal radius.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-1753193412451383" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Inter- and intraobserver reliability</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1753193412451383" xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412451383-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Intraclass correlation coefficient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Interobserver</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Radiographic dorsal tilt</td>
<td>0.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Radiographic radial tilt</td>
<td>0.96</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Radiographic shortening</td>
<td>0.81</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 3D dorsal tilt</td>
<td>0.95</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 3D radial tilt</td>
<td>0.92</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 3D shortening</td>
<td>0.92</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Intraobserver</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Radiographic dorsal tilt</td>
<td>0.95</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Radiographic radial tilt</td>
<td>0.95</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Radiographic shortening</td>
<td>0.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 3D dorsal tilt</td>
<td>0.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 3D radial tilt</td>
<td>0.92</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 3D shortening</td>
<td>0.90</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig4-1753193412451383" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption><p>Correlations between 3D dorsal tilt and radiographic dorsal tilt. The dotted line illustrates the hypothesis that the values of radiographic evaluation equate with those of 3D evaluation. The actual approximated line (solid line) is deviated downward from the dotted line. This indicates that the values of radiographic evaluation tend to be slightly greater than those of 3D evaluation.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412451383-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1753193412451383">
<title>Radial tilt deformity (rotational deformity in the coronal plane)</title>
<p>On 3D measurement, the average 3D radial tilt was 10° (range −5° to +27°; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1753193412451383">Table 1</xref>). Of 20 patients, three patients showed ulnar tilt. On plain radiographs, the average radial angle of the affected wrists was 11° (range −24° to +30°), whereas that in the contralateral normal wrists was 24° (range 18° to 29°). Consequently, the average radiographic radial tilt, i.e., the differences in radial angle between the normal and affected sides, was 13° (range −9° to +47°; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1753193412451383">Table 1</xref>). Inter- and intraobserver reliabilities were adequate to assess the deformity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1753193412451383">Table 2</xref>). The 3D radial tilt showed positive correlations with the radiographic radial tilt (<italic>R</italic> = 0.79, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1753193412451383">Figure 5</xref>). However, the 3D radial tilt showed a decrease of 30% in value compared to the radiographic radial tilt (<italic>y</italic> = 0.69x + 1.1), and the absolute difference between evaluations using the 3D method and plain radiographs was up to 21° (average 5.7°, SD 5.9°). Moreover, three patients in the severely dorsal-tilted group (<italic>n</italic> = 6) showed differences of &gt; 10° between 3D and plain radiographic evaluations of the radial tilt deformity, whereas none in the moderately dorsal-tilted group had differences of &gt; 10° (<italic>n</italic> = 14). A significant difference was observed between these two groups (<italic>p</italic> = 0.004).</p>
<fig id="fig5-1753193412451383" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption><p>Correlations between 3D radial tilt and radiographic radial tilt. The dotted line illustrates the hypothesis that the values of radiographic evaluation equate with those of 3D evaluation. The actual approximated line (solid line) is more gradual than the dotted line. This indicated that the values of radiographic evaluation tend to be greater than those of 3D evaluation.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412451383-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1753193412451383">
<title>Shortening deformity</title>
<p>On 3D measurement, the average 3D shortening was 3.0 mm (range 0–10 mm; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1753193412451383">Table 1</xref>). The average ulnar variance on plain radiographs of the affected wrists was 2.5 mm (range 0–5 mm), whereas that of the contralateral normal wrists was 0.5 mm (range −1 to +3 mm). Consequently, the average radiographic shortening, i.e., the differences in ulnar variance between the normal and affected sides, was 2.0 mm (range −1 to +6 mm; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1753193412451383">Table 1</xref>). Inter- and intraobserver reliabilities were adequate to assess the deformity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1753193412451383">Table 2</xref>). The 3D shortening showed positive correlations with the radiographic shortening (<italic>R</italic> = 0.45, <italic>p</italic> = 0.04, <italic>y</italic> = 0.68x + 1.6; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1753193412451383">Figure 6</xref>). However, the absolute difference between the 3D and radiographic evaluations ranged from 0 to 6 mm (average 1.8, SD 1.9 mm), and there was a discrepancy of ≥ 2 mm in eight cases.</p>
<fig id="fig6-1753193412451383" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption><p>Correlations between 3D shortening and radiographic shortening. The dotted line illustrates the hypothesis that the values of radiographic evaluation equate with those of 3D evaluation.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412451383-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1753193412451383">
<title>Influence of axial rotational deformity</title>
<p>The axial rotational deformity was 13° (SD 11°; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1753193412451383">Table 1</xref>) and did not show a correlation with the differences between evaluation using plain radiography and the 3D method (dorsal tilt deformity, <italic>p</italic> = 0.27; radial tilt deformity, <italic>p</italic> = 0.15; shortening deformity, <italic>p</italic> = 0.17).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1753193412451383" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Radiographic dorsal tilt showed almost identical values as those corresponding to 3D evaluation. Radiographic evaluation of dorsal tilt deformity was therefore considered to be sufficiently accurate for planning appropriate surgery. Conversely, in most cases, the values of the radiographic radial tilt were larger than those corresponding to 3D evaluation. In particular, three patients in the severely dorsal-tilted group showed differences of &gt; 10° between 3D and plain radiographic evaluations. von Campe et al. stated that 60% of patients showed a residual deformity of &gt; 10° and that overcorrection of radial tilt deformity was common even after corrective osteotomy after preoperative planning using plain radiographs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1753193412451383">von Campe et al., 2006</xref>). This may be the result of inappropriatepre-operative evaluation of the radial tilt deformity</p>
<p>The radial angle was the acute angle determined by a line perpendicular to the central long axis of the radius and the line connecting the radial and ulnar margins of the distal radial articular surface on a posteroanterior view on plain radiographs. In a 2D projected view, as the distal radius tilts more dorsally, the radial margin of the distal radial articular surface moves more proximally and the acute angle of the two lines becomes smaller. A simple dorsally tilted malunion without radial tilt deformity could therefore show reduction in the radial angle on plain radiographs because of the triangular shape of the distal radius (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1753193412451383">Figure 7A</xref>). Therefore, during corrective osteotomy, the radial angle may be spontaneously reduced after correction of the dorsal tilt deformity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1753193412451383">Figure 7B</xref>). Del Piñal et al described such a malunion as <italic>sagittal rotational malunion</italic>, which can be restored anatomically by pure derotational osteotomy only in the sagittal plane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1753193412451383">Del Piñal et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig7-1753193412451383" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption><p>(A) A case of dorsal tilted malunion showed reduction in the radial angle in an evaluation using plain radiograph (Case 5). However, the radial tilt deformity was minimal in 3D analysis. (B) Computer simulation showed that anatomical reduction was obtained by correction of only the dorsal tilt deformity in this case. The continuous radial-palmar cortex (*) indicates that no correction of radial tilt deformity was done.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412451383-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Ulnar variance is an additional important parameter on plain radiograph to assess shortening deformity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1753193412451383">Fernandez, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1753193412451383">Ladd and Huene, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1753193412451383">Prommersberger et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1753193412451383">von Campe et al., 2006</xref>). An experimental study revealed that shortening deformity &gt; 2 mm increased the ulnar load and was associated with poor outcome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1753193412451383">Palmer and Werner, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1753193412451383">von Campe et al., 2006</xref>). During corrective osteotomy, the ulnar-palmar cortex is the pivot point to correct the deformity in most cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1753193412451383">Fernandez, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1753193412451383">von Campe et al., 2006</xref>). Therefore, we used the ulnar margin of the palmar rim of the radial articular surface as a measuring point for shortening deformity on the radiographic evaluations. Nevertheless, there was a discrepancy of ≥ 2 mm in eight cases between the plain X-ray shortening and 3D shortening in the present study. von Campe et al. stated that 47% of patients showed a residual shortening deformity of ≥ 2 mm after a procedure comprising systematic pre-operative planning using plain radiographs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1753193412451383">von Campe et al., 2006</xref>). Del Piñal et al. also stated that ulnar variance improved by 3 mm after derotational osteotomy in the sagittal plane, without lengthening of sagittal rotational malunion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1753193412451383">Del Piñal et al., 2009</xref>). Therefore, we considered that ulnar variance has less accuracy for the planning of corrective osteotomy compared with 3D evaluation. Based on the results of the present study, additional intraoperative radiographic control or fluoroscopic assistance is recommended during surgery to correct the shortening deformity.</p>
<p>Axial rotational deformity is difficult to detect radiographically. A previous cadaveric study revealed that this deformity does not affect the radiographic parameters of palmar tilt, radial inclination, and radial length, although cortical width discrepancy between the distal and proximal fragments on a 45° oblique pronated view can indicate the presence of axial rotational deformity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1753193412451383">Lee et al., 2010</xref>). In agreement with the findings of that study, axial rotational deformity did not correlate with the differences between evaluation by plain radiography and the 3D method in this study with clinical cases.</p>
<p>Coupled with its almost perfect inter- and intraobserver reliabilities, the method using 3D computer bone models is considered to be the most appropriate for deformity evaluation. However, disadvantages of 3D evaluation include radiation exposure during CT, the need for specialized computer programs, and the time and effort required for computer operations. The additional cost of CT scanning is also necessary. Although clinical studies have demonstrated a correlation between a more anatomical correction and overall wrist function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1753193412451383">Cooney et al., 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1753193412451383">Fernandez, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1753193412451383">McQueen and Caspers, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1753193412451383">Villar et al., 1987</xref>), the clinical impact of mild residual deformity after partial correction may be minimal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193412451383">Altissimi et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1753193412451383">Wada et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1753193412451383">Warwick et al., 1993</xref>). Therefore, 3D evaluation may be indicated only for cases with severe 3D deformity. Further investigation is necessary to determine the efficacy or cost-effectiveness of this 3D technique (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1753193412451383">Leong et al., 2010</xref>). The sample size of this study is relatively small (<italic>n</italic> = 20), and the precision of all calculated values therefore is limited. Nevertheless, to our knowledge, this is the first report on the comparative analysis of the accuracy of radiographic evaluation versus 3D CT reconstruction of distal radius malunion. Radiographic evaluation of dorsal tilt deformity showed reasonable accuracy. On the other hand, radiographic evaluation of radial tilt deformity and shortening deformity showed less accuracy compared to 3D evaluation. Radial tilt deformity was overestimated by radiographic evaluation using radial angle, particularly in malunions with severe dorsal tilt. We believe that the information obtained in the present study will improve our understanding of the deformity in distal radius malunion and contribute to appropriate surgical treatment.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>The authors wish to thank the assistance of computer programmer Ryoji Nakao during parts of the experimental procedure. The authors also acknowledge the contribution of Sumika Ikemoto for assisting in the creation of the model.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interests</label>
<p>None declared.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other">
<label>Ethical approval</label>
<p>Each author certifies that this study was conducted as an institutional committee-approved retrospective study. The study number was 08332. Each author certifies that informed consent for participation in the study was obtained.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Altissimi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Antenucci</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fiacca</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term results of conservative treatment of fractures of the distal radius</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1986</year>, <volume>206</volume>: <fpage>202</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Athwal</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pichora</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Computer-assisted distal radius osteotomy</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2003</year>, <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>951</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Besl</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A method for registration of 3-D shapes</article-title>. <source>IEEE transactions on pattern analysis and machine intelligence</source>. <year>1992</year>, <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bilic</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zdravkovic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boljevic</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Osteotomy for deformity of the radius. Computer-assisted three-dimensional modelling</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1994</year>, <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>150</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cooney</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dobyns</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Linscheid</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Complications of Colles′ fractures</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1980</year>, <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>613</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Del Piñal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garcia-Bernal</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Studer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Regalado</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ayala</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cagigal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Sagittal rotational malunions of the distal radius: the role of pure derotational osteotomy</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Eur</source>. <year>2009</year>, <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>160</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Correction of post-traumatic wrist deformity in adults by osteotomy, bone-grafting, and internal fixation</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1982</year>, <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>1164</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of multiplanar distal radius fractures on forearm rotation: in vitro biomechanical study</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2009</year>, <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>838</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hollevoet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Maele</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Seymortier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Verdonk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of palmar tilt, radial inclination and ulnar variance in left and right wrists</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br</source>. <year>2000</year>, <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hove</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Molster</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Surgery for posttraumatic wrist deformity. Radial osteotomy and/or ulnar shortening in 16 Colles′ fractures</article-title>. <source>Acta Orthop Scand</source>. <year>1994</year>, <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>434</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jupiter</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Computer-generated bone models in the planning of osteotomy of multidirectional distal radius malunions</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1992</year>, <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>406</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jupiter</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Complications following distal radial fractures</article-title>. <source>Instr Course Lect</source>. <year>2002</year>, <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Short</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fortino</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of dorsally angulated distal radius fractures on distal radioulnar joint congruency and forearm rotation</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1996</year>, <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kreder</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hanel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jupiter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGillivary</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swiontkowski</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>X-ray film measurements for healed distal radius fractures</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1996</year>, <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ladd</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huene</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reconstructive osteotomy for malunion of the distal radius</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1996</year>, <volume>327</volume>: <fpage>158</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zingman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loona</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Correlation of malrotation deformity in distal radius fractures with radiographic analysis: cadaveric study</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2010</year>, <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>228</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buijze</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stockmans</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jupiter</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Computer-assisted versus non-computer-assisted preoperative planning of corrective osteotomy for extra-articular distal radius malunions: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord</source>. <year>2010</year>, <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>282</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McQueen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caspers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Colles fracture: does the anatomical result affect the final function?</article-title> <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1988</year>, <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>649</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hashizume</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagayama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Malunited Colles′ fracture. Analysis of stress distribution</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br</source>. <year>1994</year>, <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>737</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moritomo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sugamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Distal radius osteotomy with volar locking plates based on computer simulation</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>2011</year>, <volume>469</volume>: <fpage>1766</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moritomo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sugamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Three-dimensional deformity analysis of malunited distal radius fractures and their influence on wrist and forearm motion</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Eur</source>. <comment>Epub ahead of print</comment> <day>8</day> <month>May</month> <year>2012</year>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753193412443644</pub-id>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moritomo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sugamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Accuracy analysis of three-dimensional bone surface models of the forearm constructed from multidetector computed tomography data</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Robot</source>. <year>2009</year>, <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>452</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moritomo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sugamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Corrective osteotomy using customized hydroxyapatite implants prepared by preoperative computer simulation</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Robot</source>. <year>2010</year>, <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Biomechanics of the distal radioulnar joint</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1984</year>, <volume>187</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pogue</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Viegas</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of distal radius fracture malunion on wrist joint mechanics</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1990</year>, <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>721</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Prommersberger</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Schoonhoven</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lanz</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Outcome after corrective osteotomy for malunited fractures of the distal end of the radius</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br</source>. <year>2002</year>, <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Short</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A biomechanical study of distal radial fractures</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1987</year>, <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Takeyasu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Three-dimensional analysis of cubitus varus deformity after supracondylar fractures of the humerus</article-title>. <source>J Shoulder Elbow Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>, <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>440</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Villar</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rushton</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greatorex</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Three years after Colles′ fracture. A prospective review</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1987</year>, <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>635</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>von Campe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arbab</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dumont</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Corrective osteotomies in malunions of the distal radius: do we get what we planned?</article-title> <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>2006</year>, <volume>450</volume>: <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vroemen</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dobbe</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jonges</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strackee</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Streekstra</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Three-dimensional assessment of bilateral symmetry of the radius and ulna for planning corrective surgeries</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2012</year>, <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>982</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tatebe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ozasa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical outcomes of corrective osteotomy for distal radial malunion: a review of opening and closing-wedge techniques</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2011</year>, <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1619</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Warwick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prothero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Radiological measurement of radial shortening in Colles′ fracture</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br</source>. <year>1993</year>, <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1753193412451383">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Helm</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Veeger</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>ISB recommendation on definitions of joint coordinate systems of various joints for the reporting of human joint motion—Part II: shoulder, elbow, wrist and hand</article-title>. <source>J Biomech</source>. <year>2005</year>, <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>981</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>