<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TDO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptdo</journal-id>
<journal-title>Tropical Doctor</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0049-4755</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1758-1133</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0049475513491727</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0049475513491727</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Series and Case Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Atypical small bowel obstruction following repair of inguinal hernia: a case of intestinal stenosis of Garre</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Weledji</surname><given-names>Elroy P</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0049475513491727">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0049475513491727">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0049475513491727"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Theophile</surname><given-names>Nana</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0049475513491727">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0049475513491727"><label>1</label>Senior Lecturer in Anatomy and Clinical Surgery, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Buea, Cameroon</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0049475513491727"><label>2</label>General Surgeon, Regional Hospital Buea, Cameroon</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0049475513491727"><label>3</label>Physician, Department of Surgery, Regional Hospital Buea, Cameroon</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0049475513491727">Elroy P Weledji, PO Box 126, Limbe, SW Region, Buea, Cameroon. Email: <email>elroypat@yahoo.co.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>43</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>88</fpage>
<lpage>91</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We report an atypical case of small bowel obstruction 10 days after the repair of an inguinal hernia that had been recurrently reduced. A preoperative diagnosis of the rare intestinal stenosis of Garre is difficult, and was based on the clinical, operative and pathological findings. Forced reduction of a hernia is not recommended because of the risk of rendering its contents ischaemic with subsequent fibrotic stenosis, or reducing a strangulated bowel into the abdominal cavity with subsequent perforation and peritonitis.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Reduction of hernia</kwd>
<kwd>acute ischaemia</kwd>
<kwd>fibrosis</kwd>
<kwd>intestinal stenosis of Garre</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0049475513491727" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>A benign stricture of the intestine is a rare intestinal complication seen in patients who habitually reduce their hernias (inguinal, femoral, etc.).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0049475513491727">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0049475513491727"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0049475513491727">3</xref></sup> It is a small bowel stenosis secondary to acute ischaemia. Small intestinal stenosis due to ischaemia following strangulated hernia repair is uncommon as patients with external hernias have ready access to elective herniorrhaphy. It can follow the preoperative reduction or operative reduction of an incarcerated, obstructed or strangulated hernia. A preoperative diagnosis of intestinal stenosis of Garre is difficult and, therefore, this relatively rare but life-threatening surgical emergency should be borne in mind even with the operative reduction of an apparently viable incarcerated, obstructed or strangulated bowel. We report a case of intestinal stenosis of Garre and present a brief review of the literature.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0049475513491727" sec-type="cases"><title>Case report</title>
<p>A 30-year-old male farmer presented to the emergency unit with a 1-year history of a progressive left inguino-scrotal swelling associated with pain. The swelling was noticed about a year before by the patient during lifting. It was localized in the left inguinal region and was initially painless. It progressively increased in size extending to the scrotum but was reducible. About 2 weeks before the consultation the swelling became painful. It was relieved by rest and self-reduction a day before consultation. The swelling recurred, became acutely painful radiating to the scrotum and irreducible by the patient. There was no fever, vomiting, abdominal distension, altered bowel habit or dysuria. The persistence of the pain prompted consultation to send him to the emergency unit. The patient had never before undergone an operation. He had no history of an inguinal swelling during childhood, bladder outflow obstruction, sexually transmitted infections or chronic cough. He did not smoke. As a farmer, he was used to lifting very heavy loads.</p>
<p>On examination the patient laid supine in bed with the left leg flexed to alleviate the pain. There were no signs of dehydration. His blood pressure (BP) was 126/80 mmHg, pulse 92/min, respiratory rate (RR) 20/min and he weighed 62 kg. The lungs were clear and the heart sounds were normal. The abdomen was soft, not distended and non-tender. The right inguinal canal was normal but the left inguinal canal revealed a firm, fluctuant mass extending to the scrotum, tender on palpation with an expansile cough impulse. It did not transilluminate and both testes were non-tender and palpable in the scrotum. The receiving physician diagnosed an incarcerated/irreducible hernia which he reduced under sedation. The pain subsided and after an hour the patient was discharged and advised to return for surgery when financially ready. One week later he returned with a recurrent but asymptomatic left inguino-scrotal hernia. Again the hernia was reduced. The patient was prepared and taken to theatre. Under general anaesthesia, a left inguinal incision identified an indirect inguinal hernia. The sac was identified. The contents were already reduced and the sac was isolated, ligated and cut. The Bassini method of repair was performed. There were no postoperative complications and he was discharged 3 days later.</p>
<p>One week after discharge (10 days post hernia repair) he was readmitted as an emergency with sudden onset generalized abdominal pain associated with vomiting, abdominal distension and constipation. However, he passed flatus. His vital signs were normal with a blood pressure of 129/88 mmHg and pulse 78/min. There were no signs of dehydration. There was no inguinal swelling or tenderness as evidence of recurrence and there was no evidence of peritonitis. The tentative diagnosis was a subacute small bowel obstruction secondary to the internal scar, between knuckles of small intestine or to the lateral wall of the pelvis. A plain abdominal X-ray revealed central fluid levels and the full blood count was normal. He was managed conservatively with analgesia, nasogastric aspirations and intravenous fluid hydration for 48 h (‘drip and suck’). The symptoms resolved and he was discharged 3 days later.</p>
<p>Five days later (21 days post hernia repair), he was readmitted with recurrent symptoms and signs of acute small bowel obstruction. He had severe colicky abdominal pain with: increasing frequency (<sub>∼</sub> every 5 min); profuse vomiting soon after a feed; and absolute constipation with no passage of flatus for 2 days. He had no fever but was moderately dehydrated. Vital signs were BP 120/76 mmHg, pulse 86/min. His abdomen was centrally distended with visible peristalsis and tinkling bowel sounds. There was mild generalized abdominal tenderness from the distension but no peritonitis. Again there was no inguinal swelling or pain. On digital examination the rectum was empty. The diagnosis of an unresolved small bowel obstruction was made for which he underwent an emergency laparotomy. Under general anaesthesia a midline abdominal incision was made which revealed grossly distended small bowel loops. No perforations, adhesions nor pus were seen. However, there was stenosis of a segment of ileum about 30 cm from the ileo-caecal junction. A resection of the stenosed segment and end-to-end anastomosis was carried out and the specimen sent for histopathology. The patient made an uneventful recovery and was discharged 10 days later. Histopathology revealed inflammatory lesions but no malignancy. The patient had no further complaints 2 months after follow-up.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-0049475513491727" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>The following questions should be asked: what are the possible causes of intestinal obstruction after a good inguinal hernia repair; what is the cause of the intestinal stenosis in the patient; and should hernias be habitually reduced before surgery?</p>
<p>Benign fibrous stricture of the bowel following an episode of strangulation first appeared in the literature in 1784.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0049475513491727">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0049475513491727"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0049475513491727"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0049475513491727">4</xref></sup> In 1892, Garre of Germany reviewed the previous literature and coined the term ‘intestinal stenosis’.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0049475513491727">1</xref></sup> This term, therefore, is referred to as the ‘benign stenosis of Garre’. This ischaemic stricture follows: forceful reduction of an asymptomatic hernia; an incarcerated hernia (where the contents are fixed in the sac because of their size or adhesions but the bowel is not strangulated or obstructed); or as the result of an inadvertent reduction of an obstructed or strangulated hernia. It can also still occur as a complication with the operative reduction of an obstructed/strangulated hernia even after observing viability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0049475513491727">5</xref></sup> Accordingly, the involved segment is either resected or, if circulation improves and the intestine begins to recover its normal appearance, it is replaced in the abdominal cavity, usually with complete recovery.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0049475513491727">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0049475513491727">7</xref></sup> The condition is probably due either to vasospasm or to vaso-insufficiency within the strangulated loop, with resulting ischaemia. Although not sufficient to devitalize the bowel completely and permit perforation, this ischaemia is sufficient to cause marked fibrosis and stricture, a process not unlike Volksmann’s ischaemic contracture in the limb – a condition due to ischaemia and subsequent fibrosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0049475513491727">8</xref></sup> Intestinal mucosa is more vulnerable to ischaemia than the overlying seromuscular layer. The consequent mucosal ulcer heals by fibrosis causing an annular stenotic stricture of the small bowel that leads to small bowel obstruction.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0049475513491727">2</xref></sup> Rarely, the intestine perforates proximal to the stricture and the patient present with features of generalized peritonitis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0049475513491727">9</xref></sup> Signs of subacute or acute intestinal obstruction (colicky abdominal pain, vomiting, abdominal distention and constipation) occurs days, weeks or months after surgical repair of the hernia depending on the degree of ischaemia. A case of acute intestinal obstruction after a period of 15 months has been reported.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0049475513491727">10</xref></sup> The differential diagnosis includes postoperative adhesions which should not be overlooked and, in this part of the world, TB of the ileum and the rare Crohn’s disease.</p>
<p>Small intestinal stenosis secondary to ischaemia may lead to: acute small bowel obstruction; acute or chronic obstruction; or chronic small bowel obstruction. It may also give rise to a blind loop syndrome. Conservative management (‘drip and suck’) inevitably fails, although it may give temporary relief as seen in this case.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0049475513491727">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0049475513491727">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0049475513491727">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0049475513491727">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0049475513491727">11</xref></sup> Laparotomy is inevitable. A fibrous stricture is found at the site of previous obstruction/strangulation or incarceration. The proximal bowel to the stricture is distended and the distal bowel collapsed. There is usually no adhesion of any significance. When seen in the late stage, there is a small segment of bowel which is contracted but which possesses a very thick wall. The lumen of the bowel is greatly narrowed or even occluded. Resection of the strictured segment and an end-to-end anastomosis is the definitive treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0049475513491727">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0049475513491727">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0049475513491727">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0049475513491727">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0049475513491727"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0049475513491727">14</xref></sup> The pathological picture is of fibrosis of all the layers of the bowel wall. There is a uniform type of granulation tissue that extends to the muscularis propria and peri-intestinal tissue with associated fibrosis and scarring. Haemosiderin laden macrophages are seen in granulation tissue base.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0049475513491727">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0049475513491727">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0049475513491727">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0049475513491727">11</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0049475513491727" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>External hernia is still the most common cause of intestinal obstruction in developing countries with a strangulation rate of about 5% and 30% for inguinal and femoral hernia, respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0049475513491727">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0049475513491727">15</xref></sup> A benign Garre stenosis of the small bowel, although uncommon, especially as most hernias are repaired electively, is always a possible complication following repair of hernia. Clinically, the manual reduction of a hernia is aimed at diagnosis. It is not a therapeutic measure as it will recur almost immediately. Diagnosing a hernia by its spontaneous reduction on lying down is safer and more convenient to the patient than manual reduction. Forced reduction of a hernia is never safe because of the greater risk of rendering its contents ischaemic or reducing a strangulated bowel into the abdominal cavity with subsequent perforation and peritonitis. It is possible to forcefully push a hernia back through the abdominal wall, apparently reducing it, without actually pushing the contents out of the sac (reduction en-masse).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0049475513491727">16</xref></sup> If they were strangulated in the first position they will still be strangulated in the second. Occasionally, however, it is possible to reduce an obstructed hernia safely and relieve the obstruction, but care is needed to ensure that the bowel is viable, the obstruction really relieved and the bowel not ruptured. The danger of reducing a non-viable bowel must always be borne in mind. A patient with acute symptoms of a hernia which is irreducible should have urgent surgery and, if strangulated (i.e. tense, tender, irreducible lump in the inguinal canal with no cough impulse) or obstructed, should receive immediate surgery after resuscitation.</p>
<p>In most cases, a direct approach to the hernia is appropriate. The incarcerated tissue may reduce under anaesthesia and, should this occur, it is unlikely that there will have been strangulation. It is debatable, therefore, whether a full laparotomy to inspect spontaneously reduced tissue from the hernia is indicated, but the possibility that a gangrenous loop of bowel has dropped back into the abdominal cavity should always be kept in mind. This is usually readily apparent in the early postoperative period.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0049475513491727">17</xref></sup> Preoperative diagnosis of intestinal stenosis of Garre is difficult and, therefore, this relatively rare but life-threatening surgical emergency should be kept in mind following operative reduction of an apparently viable incarcerated, obstructed or strangulated bowel during hernia repair.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec5-0049475513491727"><title>Declaration of conflicting interests</title>
<p>None declared.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0049475513491727"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0049475513491727"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Garre C. Beitrage zur klin. <italic>Chir</italic> 1892; 19</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0049475513491727"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maas</surname></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ueber die Entstchung von Darmstenose nach Brucheinklemming</article-title>. <source>Dent Mediz-Wehsch</source> <year>1895</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>365</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0049475513491727"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Guignard. Retreassement cicatriciel de Intestin. <italic>These Paris</italic> 1866</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0049475513491727"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Richter AG. Traite des Hernies 1788</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0049475513491727"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cherney</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Intestinal stenosis following strangulated hernia: a review of the literature and report of a case</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source> <year>1959</year>; <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>991</fpage>–<lpage>994</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0049475513491727"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konstam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Intestinal obstruction from fibrous stricture: following strangulated hernia</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>1948</year>; <volume>252</volume>: <fpage>569</fpage>–<lpage>570</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0049475513491727"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luke Teskey</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Benign stricture of the intestine</article-title>. <source>Canada Med Assoc J</source> <year>1955</year>; <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0049475513491727"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De la Pierre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamorca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peracino</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Considerations on a case of primary stenosing ulcer of the small intestine</article-title>. <source>Minerva Gastroenterol</source> <year>1966</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0049475513491727"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cattell</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stenosis of the intestine after strangulated hernia with fatal complication following</article-title>. <source>Am J Surg</source> <year>1948</year>; <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>729</fpage>–<lpage>729</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0049475513491727"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dakubo</surname><given-names>JCB</given-names></name><name><surname>Akoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Etwire</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ileal stricture following strangulated inguinal hernia</article-title>. <source>Trop Doct</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>4260</fpage>–<lpage>4262</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0049475513491727"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Meister</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stenosis due to scarring of the small intestine. Report of 7 cases</article-title>. <source>Ann Chir</source> <year>1977</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>999</fpage>–<lpage>1005</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0049475513491727"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barry Hugh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fibrous stricture of small intestine following strangulated hernia</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source> <year>1942</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0049475513491727"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bratton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A case of Intestinal stenosis following strangulation with a pathological description</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source> <year>1943</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0049475513491727"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Raw</surname></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stricture of small bowel following strangulated hernia</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>1943</year>; <volume>241</volume>: <fpage>460</fpage>–<lpage>460</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0049475513491727"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Presentation and outcome of strangulated external hernia in a district general hospital</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source> <year>1981</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0049475513491727"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>An Introduction to the Symptoms and Signs of Surgical Disease</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Edward Arnold</publisher-name>, <year>1988</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0049475513491727"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>JJT</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Acute conditions of the small bowel and appendix</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Paterson-Brown</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Emergency Surgery and Critical Care: A Companion to Specialist Surgical Practice</source>, <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WB Saunders</publisher-name>, <year>1997</year>, pp. <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>