<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="letter">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JHS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjhs</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Hand Surg Eur Vol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Hand Surgery (European Volume)</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1753-1934</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2043-6289</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753193411424703</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1753193411424703</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Short report letters</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Closed rupture of abductor pollicis longus and extensor pollicis brevis associated with fracture of the distal radius</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Al-Najjim</surname><given-names>Mr. Munnan</given-names></name>
<degrees>MRCSEd</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Fenton</surname><given-names>Dr. Carl</given-names></name>
<degrees>MBBS</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>Mr. Thomas</given-names></name>
<degrees>FRCS Orth</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1753193411424703">Royal Cornwall Hospital, Truro, Cornwall, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1753193411424703">Email: <email>malnajjim@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>37</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>176</fpage>
<lpage>177</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The British Society for Surgery of the Hand 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The British Society for Surgery of the Hand</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Dear Sir,</p>
<p>A 49-year-old right-hand dominant lady fell from a horse, landing on her outstretched hand. There was no history of previous trauma to this limb. Examination revealed moderate swelling and deformity of the right wrist with tenderness over the right distal radius and base of the thumb and a reduced range of motion.</p>
<p>Radiographs showed an isolated intra-articular comminuted avulsion fracture of the radial styloid process. The distal radio-ulnar joint and ulnar styloid were intact (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1753193411424703">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1753193411424703" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Anteroposterior and lateral radiograph of the fracture.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1753193411424703-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The following day the patient underwent open reduction and internal fixation of the fracture through a dorsal incision centred over Lister’s tubercle. There was mild volar comminution of the radial styloid fragment with volar subluxation of the carpus. Both abductor pollicis longus (APL) and extensor pollicis brevis (EPB) tendons had ruptured at their musculotendinous junctions.</p>
<p>The fracture was debrided, reduced, and fixed with a single cannulated screw. The APL and EPB tendons were irreparable. The wrist and hand were supported in a plaster of Paris backslab. One week later, the plaster was exchanged for a thermoplastic splint to hold the thumb in an abducted position, protecting the wrist and allowing mobilisation of the fingers.</p>
<p>At 5 weeks the patient had a good early range of movement in her wrist. Extension and abduction of the thumb was slightly limited. Five months post-operatively she had regained nearly full movement at the wrist and thumb, and the patient had returned to work in IT.</p>
<p>Traumatic tendon ruptures associated with fracture of the distal radius are common. Damage to the extensor pollicis longus (EPL) is the most frequently reported tendon injury with an estimated incidence of 0.2–3% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1753193411424703">Oren and Wolf, 2009</xref>). There are no reported cases of traumatic injury of both the APL and EPB following fracture of the distal radius. A single study reported two cases: the first, a rupture caused by necrosis of the tendons following a cat bite; and the second, where excision of the tendons had been performed to resolve recurrent De Quervain’s syndrome. Both patients were found to have retained near normal function at 10 year’s follow-up, despite slight loss of extension of the thumb reported in one case (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193411424703">Britto and Eliot, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>Cadaveric and clinical studies suggest that APL is predominantly a stabilizer of the thumb and wrist, rather than having a primary motor function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193411424703">Britto and Eliot 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193411424703">Brunelli and Brunelli, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1753193411424703">Oudenaarde, 1991</xref>). EPB is thought to have only a minor functional role in extension of the thumb at the metacarpophalangeal (MP) joint. Anatomical studies have shown variation in the tendons, and the degree of influence that they exert is reflected in these differences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193411424703">Britto and Eliot, 2002</xref>). The excellent clinical outcome in our patient supports previous findings that APL and EPB have only limited functional roles. The loss of these tendons appears to be compensated by the actions of EPL and APB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193411424703">Britto and Eliot, 2002</xref>).</p>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="section1-1753193411424703">
<title>Conflict of interests</title>
<p>None declared.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1753193411424703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Britto</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eliot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Thumb function without the abductor pollicis longus and extensor pollicis brevis</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br.</source> <year>2002</year>, <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1753193411424703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brunelli</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brunelli</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Anatomy of the extensor pollicis brevis muscle</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br.</source> <year>1992</year>, <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1753193411424703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oren</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Soft-tissue complications associated with distal radius fractures</article-title>. <source>Operative techniques in orthopaedics.</source> <year>2009</year>, <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1753193411424703">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Van Oudenaarde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The function of the abductor pollicis muscle as a joint stabiliser</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br.</source> <year>1991</year>, <volume>174</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>