<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CGJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcgj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Cultural Geographies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1474-4740</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0881</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1474474011434454</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1474474011434454</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Liquid Materialities: A History of Milk, Science and the Law. By Peter Atkins. Aldershot, UK: Ashgate. 2010</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<issue-title>Special issue: Narrating landscape and environment</issue-title>
<fpage>134</fpage>
<lpage>135</lpage>
<product>
<source>Liquid Materialities: A History of Milk, Science and the Law</source>. By <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>Aldershot, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>. <year>2010</year>. <page-count count="xx"/> + <page-count count="334"/> pp. <price>£65</price> <comment>hardback</comment>. ISBN <isbn>978754679219</isbn>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>What is milk? After reading Peter Atkins’ 30-year-in-the-making <italic>Liquid Materialities: A History of Milk, Science and the Law</italic>, you won’t answer this question easily. Nor will eating a bowl of cereal be quite the same again. This is because the white liquid – skim, two percent, whole, or raw – is multiple and bears traces of Britain’s past (even if you consume milk ‘made in the USA’).</p>
<p>Atkins’ book is atypical food history. His focus is on the ‘stuff in food<italic>stuffs</italic>’ – the materiality of milk. Over ten chapters, Atkins explores how science, commerce, and the law have understood, standardized, and disciplined the ‘milk multiple’ over a 200-year period in Britain. As industrial cities grew and agro-food networks stretched, milk became a battleground for food quality governance. Producers and retailers watered it down, extracted cream, added chemicals and preservatives, and colored it. Consumers and public health advocates responded with ‘good milk’ and ‘clean milk’ campaigns. The ‘morality of the laboratory and the procedural probity of the courtroom’ mediated the emergent qualities of this amazingly complex substance.</p>
<p>Atkins organizes <italic>Liquid Materialities</italic> around the processual materiality of milk. He shows how nature-society boundaries were drawn, redrawn, and policed and the impacts of these practices on agro-food networks and also on the substance of the commodity. Atkins’ theoretical approach is influenced by anthropologist Tim Ingold’s insights on processual properties, Paul David’s work on path-dependence, and French philosopher Gilbert Simondon’s theory of individuation. Sweeping in scope, <italic>Liquid Materialities</italic> reveals how milk has been stabilized in particular ways by institutions, interests, technologies, scientific networks, regulations, and consumer politics. Atkins renders milk as a product ‘loaded with technicity’ in a constant state of becoming; it is, in Simondon’s terms, ‘transductive’. From the dawn of commodity milk in 1850 to its stabilization in 1993 as a Euro-commodity, Atkins traces how we have known milk, how it has been changed, and how it has been an active participant in its own history.</p>
<p><italic>Liquid Materialities</italic> contributes to a growing body of scholarship that brings analytics from science studies to bear on agro-food studies. While others have focused on commodities in this way – papaya (Ian Cook), imitation crab (Becky Mansfield), or soybeans (Sarah Whatmore) – Atkins’ work is distinguished by its ambition. He envisions this as the first volume of four on the history of milk in Britain. Subsequent volumes will explore milk and disease, the political ecology of dairying in Britain, and the relationship of infant feeding to morbidity and mortality. Atkins’ enthusiasm and ability to make connections across disparate literatures, times, and places make the text compelling, but also make it feel diffuse and watered-down at times. The book’s staccato organization around numerous vignettes drawn from mostly secondary and some archival material requires the reader, whose interest has just been peaked by one story, to take a leap of faith to the next. Ultimately, <italic>Liquid Materialities</italic> impresses upon its readers a denaturalized understanding of milk that will certainly generate interest among ‘milk scholars’. Sections will also be a welcome addition in undergraduate and graduate agro-food studies seminars. The book’s interdisciplinary nature and approach to the historical epistemology and ontology of modern food should also attract a broader audience.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig><bold>Sara Safransky</bold><break/>
<italic>Department of Geography, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</italic></sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>