<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ERG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sperg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Ergonomics in Design: The Quarterly of Human Factors Applications</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1064-8046</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1064804612471793</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1064804612471793</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Departments</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Books</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Reviews of Human Factors and Ergonomics, Volume 6</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Cades</surname><given-names>David M.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>34</fpage>
<lpage>34</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>Douglas H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2010</year>, <page-count count="264"/> pages, <price>$95.00</price> <publisher-loc>Santa Monica, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</publisher-name> ISBN <isbn>978-0-945289-38-8</isbn>
</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Human Factors and Ergonomics Society</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The first five volumes of <italic>Reviews of Human Factors and Ergonomics</italic> exposed those interested in HF/E to a variety of topics, exhibiting the full breadth of the field. Volume 6 is no different. Doug Harris’s goal was to “gain participation from the broadest range of expertise that exists in the [Human Factors and Ergonomics] Society and the profession.” Like the varied subject matter of our field, this volume covers topics as broad as outer space and cognitive processing, including both theoretical discussions and examples of HF/E methods in practice.</p>
<p>The chapters in this volume are excellent avenues to gain exposure to a new area in HF/E and to get a snapshot of the work that exists on given topics. Each chapter is written so that both novices and experts can learn about an area, and each contains sufficient depth to provide a thorough understanding of the topic.</p>
<p>A chapter on transportation accident investigation takes a historical perspective, following the evolution of this field with eyes to the future, emphasizing that more accident investigations include and rely on HF/E. Human supervisory control is detailed with a mix of theory and real-world applications, using theory-based research to support effective human supervisory control benefits in the world. Contributor R. Key Dismukes describes prospective memory with a focus on how to move the area forward and employ more effective research initiatives by combining work in laboratory settings with naturalistic studies.</p>
<p>The motor cognition chapter is a detailed focus on how the role of cognition in the control of movement needs to be at the forefront of design and analysis. Patricia Jones and Edna Fiedler follow this with a look at how human factors plays a role in most aspects of human performance in space. The collection of reviews concludes with a chapter discussing how judgment and decision making are integral in many other HF/E areas, such as problem solving and error mitigation.</p>
<p>With the diverse field that is HF/E and the seemingly endless ways in which HF/E professionals can tend their craft, the Reviews series, and this volume specifically, provide an excellent way to learn about new areas and simply keep up with our ever-advancing and widening field.</p>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<p>David M. Cades is a scientist at Exponent. He received his PhD in psychology in the Human Factors and Applied Cognition Program at George Mason University. His interests include the role of interruptions and distractions in human performance in real-world settings.</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>