<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ECR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">specr</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Early Childhood Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1476-718X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-2927</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1476718X12443028</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1476718X12443028</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: T. Waller, J. Whitmarsh and K. Clark (eds), <italic>Making Sense of Theory and Practice in Early Childhood: The Power of Ideas</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wailling</surname><given-names>Kim</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>332</fpage>
<lpage>333</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whitmarsh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds), <source>Making Sense of Theory and Practice in Early Childhood: The Power of Ideas</source>. <publisher-loc>Maidenhead</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open University Press/McGraw Hill Publishers</publisher-name>, <year>2001</year>, <page-count count="171"/> pp., <price>£60.00</price>, hbk, ISBN: <isbn>9780335242474</isbn>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This book is a launch pad for anyone working or studying in the field of early childhood education who wishes to gain a deeper understanding of the relationship between theory and practice. The array of theories featured in this edited book allows its audience to pick and mix ideas to follow personal interests or to support their own research projects.</p>
<p>The book is divided into two parts. Part one (chapters one to six) looks at community, interaction and identity. It addresses several different aspects of the social constructivist theory. Part two (chapters seven to eleven) explores structure, power and knowledge. It includes a range of theoretical perspectives that probes the complex relationships between individuals, institutions and society at large.</p>
<p>In chapter one Faye Stanley introduces the reader to aspects of Vygotskian social culturalism, focusing on the importance of the adult-child and child-child dialogue. Linking this with well-known studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1476718X12443028">Sylva et al., 2004</xref>) shows how Vygotskian theory underpins government initiatives – for example, ‘Every Child a Talker’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1476718X12443028">National Strategies Early Years, 2008</xref>). It is easy to forget how recently his published work has become available in English.</p>
<p>Lynn Richards begins chapter two with a discussion of Jerome S. Bruner’s well-known concepts and challenges childcare practitioners to reflect upon their use of language in their work with young children and their families. To this end Richards draws on her research that seeks to uncover ‘embedded racial scripts’ contained in the everyday talk of childcare practitioners. This chapter illustrates the power of words that frame our experiences and are part of children’s cultural landscape.</p>
<p>Sue Fawson and Gill Woods provide a balanced critique in chapter three of Howard Gardner’s world of multiple intelligences. This is a useful reminder of the influences that mould the curriculum of both early years and primary education. It recognizes that children have different learning styles and that all areas of learning and development are equally important and interconnected. Understanding Gardner’s theory prevents this familiar statement from becoming a meaningless mantra.</p>
<p>In chapter four, Martin Needham encourages a consideration of the unwritten rules and tacit agreements between practitioners, children and their parents/carers during a stay and play session at a Children’s Centre. The key message here is that a balance of independent and collaborative interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1476718X12443028">Rogoff, 1998</xref>) benefits learning, a theme that surely resonates at every stage of education. It is refreshing to read, in this chapter, research based around children under three.</p>
<p>Jenny Worsley in chapter five provides a detailed explanation of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1476718X12443028">Lave and Wenger’s (1991)</xref> communities of practice and sets this in a research context about online support for groups of part-time early years students. Worsley gives a frank account of her research. She concedes that while the theories underpinning the notion of communities of practice are easily explained, putting these ideas into practice is harder – a view that many readers can empathize with.</p>
<p>Liz Brooker concisely explains in chapter six the different aspects of learning dispositions. She gives a useful overview of their conception and of how they are applied in practice. This is an informative chapter, which sits well with the current Early Years Foundation Stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1476718X12443028">DCSF, 2008</xref>) climate, providing a review of a relatively new approach to how children learn best.</p>
<p>Chapter seven fronts part two of the book. Here, Tim Waller and Angeliki Bitou discuss themes of agency, participation and power. This is an ambitious chapter that deals with complex ideas. However, these ideas perhaps need to be explained more clearly and illustrated more vividly so as not to overwhelm readers who may be new to, or less familiar with these concepts.</p>
<p>June O’Connor in chapter eight begins a potted history of Bourdieu. She makes the important point that although young children do not feature in Bourdieu’s work, the value of his ideas on social inequalities and differentiated outcomes is now being recognized. As O’Connor maintains, Bourdieu’s work forms a solid foundation for reflection upon one’s own taken-for-granted practices.</p>
<p>In chapter nine, Rohan Jowallah reviews critical literacy pedagogy from a Freirean perspective. Clearly presented, with a useful framework of the assessment of critical literacy in action, this chapter is thought provoking, particularly about the tensions arising from the use of critical literacy in adhering to curriculum learning frameworks.</p>
<p>Maggie Leese in chapter ten applies Foucault’s ideas about power, truth and knowledge to multi-agency working in children’s services. She proposes reflective questions such as ‘Are some parents hard to reach?’ and presents a case study to illustrate concepts such as the ‘good enough parent’. This is an uncomfortable area for many but one which makes reading Foucault and some of the suggested further reading so worthwhile.</p>
<p>Finally, in chapter eleven, Jo Winwood considers the relevance of the ethic of care (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1476718X12443028">Gilligan, 1993</xref>). Within a feminist paradigm, this chapter provides a welcome contrast between the constituent elements of integration and inclusion. It serves as a prompt for practitioners to consider the influences on their decisions. The section on the weakness of the ethic of care is valuable as it offers an opportunity to disagree.</p>
<p>For practitioners connecting theory and practice, this well edited book is a flavourful synopsis, the academic equivalent of a culinary <italic>amuse-gueule.</italic> Its strength is that the contributors promote critical thinking on the reader’s part and do not present theories as ‘one size fits all’. This encourages readers embarking on study projects to find their own research pathways, drawing on theories that are increasingly becoming a familiar part of the language of early years practice.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1476718X12443028">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>DCSF</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <source>The Statutory Framework for the Early Years Foundation Stage</source>. <publisher-loc>Nottingham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>DCSF</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1476718X12443028">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gilligan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>In a Different Voice</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1476718X12443028">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lave</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wenger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>Situated Learning: Legitimate Peripheral Participation</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1476718X12443028">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Strategies Early Years</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Every Child’s a Talker. Guidance for Early Language Lead Practitioners</source>. <publisher-loc>Nottingham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>DCSE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1476718X12443028">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rogoff</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Cognition as a collaborative process</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siegler</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Handbook of Child Psychology</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1476718X12443028">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sylva</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Melhuish</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sammons</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siraj-Blatchford</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taggert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The Effective Provision of Pre-School Education (EPPE) Project</article-title>. Findings from preschool to the end of Key Stage 1, Institute of Education, University of London.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>