<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ISW</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spisw</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Social Work</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0020-8728</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7234</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0020872812437227</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0020872812437227</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Predictors of violence and delinquency among high risk youth and youth gang members in San Salvador, El Salvador</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Parada</surname><given-names>Henry</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Saracostti</surname><given-names>Mahia</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Reininger</surname><given-names>Taly</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Olate</surname><given-names>René</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0020872812437227">Ohio State University College of Social Work, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Salas-Wright</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-0020872812437227">Boston College Graduate School of Social Work, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>Michael G.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff3-0020872812437227">Saint Louis University, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0020872812437227">René Olate, Ohio State University College of Social Work, 1947 College Road, Columbus, OH 43210-1162, USA. Email: <email>olate.1@osu.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-0020872812437227">
<p>René Olate, PhD, is Assistant Professor in the Ohio State University College of Social Work, USA. His research interests center on youth violence, high risk youth and Latino gangs, civic engagement and volunteerism, community participation, and capacity building.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio2-0020872812437227">
<p>Christopher Salas-Wright is a PhD candidate at Boston College Graduate School of Social Work, USA. His dissertation topic is ‘Spirituality, religiosity, and problem behavior in a sample of high risk and gang-involved youth in El Salvador’.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio3-0020872812437227">
<p>Michael G. Vaughn, PhD, is Associate Professor in the School of Social Work at Saint Louis University, USA. He is a nationally recognized scholar in the areas of adolescent antisocial behavior, substance abuse, violence, delinquency, and juvenile psychopathy. He has published over 120 peer-reviewed articles, is Assistant Editor of the <italic>Journal of Adolescence</italic>, serves on several editorial boards and is an ad hoc reviewer for over 30 journals in multiple fields of study.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>55</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<issue-title>Special issue: Social Work in Latin America</issue-title>
<fpage>383</fpage>
<lpage>401</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">IASSW, ICSW, IFSW</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Low future orientation, low empathy, educational difficulty, school expulsion, delinquent peers, gang membership, and low social support were found to be significant risk factors for violence and delinquency among a sample (<italic>N</italic> = 174) of high risk youth and youth gang members in San Salvador, El Salvador.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Central America</kwd>
<kwd>delinquency</kwd>
<kwd>El Salvador</kwd>
<kwd>gangs</kwd>
<kwd>youth violence</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0020872812437227" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>El Salvador is geographically the smallest (21,041 sq. km.) and most densely populated (6 million approximately) country in the Central American region. It is currently referred to as part of the ‘northern triangle of violence’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0020872812437227">1</xref></sup> (along with Guatemala and Honduras), which has the ‘highest murder rate of any region in the world, and very high rates of other forms of violent crime’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0020872812437227">UNODC, 2010</xref>: 239). Since the end of the civil war in 1992, El Salvador has faced a growing problem of youth street gangs. While gangs, or <italic>pandillas</italic>, contribute to the high level of violence and crime, they are certainly not the only cause of these complex phenomena. Poverty, social exclusion, practices of the civil war, access to illicit guns, drug trafficking routes (cocaine from South America), organized crime, weak institutions, corruption, and deported gang members from the US are often factors cited as the main causes of the level of violence and crime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0020872812437227">Aguilar, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0020872812437227">Cruz, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0020872812437227">ERIC et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0020872812437227">Seelke, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>The definition of youth gangs has been hotly debated worldwide. A commonly accepted definition was developed by a group of researchers, stating that, ‘A street gang is any durable, street-oriented youth group whose involvement in illegal activity is part of its group identity’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0020872812437227">Klein and Maxson, 2006</xref>: 4). In Central America various researchers have differentiated gangs (<italic>pandillas</italic>) from <italic>maras</italic>, referring to the latter as more recent, violent, and with transnational origin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0020872812437227">Hagedorn, 2008</xref>). Since the term <italic>maras</italic> is rejected as an umbrella term by active gang members, this article employs the concept of <italic>pandillas</italic> (gangs).</p>
<p>The most important and dominant gangs in El Salvador and the northern triangle are the ‘Mara Salvatrucha’ (MS) and the ‘18th Street’ (18). Both gangs were originated by Latinos in Los Angeles, California as a reaction to the processes of integration and social exclusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0020872812437227">Vigil, 1988</xref>). Mexican and Chicano youth in the 1960s founded the 18, while Salvadoran youth in the 1980s started the MS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0020872812437227">Savenije, 2009</xref>). A small percentage of the Salvadorans, Guatemalans, and Hondurans deported from the US were responsible for influencing gang culture in Central America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0020872812437227">Dingeman and Rumbaut, 2010</xref>). However, Salvadoran youth gangs are not a simple product of the influence of American gang culture on marginalized youth, but derive from a constellation of diverse factors in constant adaptation and change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0020872812437227">Rodgers, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The majority of gang members are male, unemployed, live in urban areas, and have dropped out of school (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0020872812437227">Cruz, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0020872812437227">Olate et al., 2011</xref>). Though El Salvador’s two primary gangs are portrayed by the mainstream media as the main actors contributing to high levels of crime and delinquency, gangs are estimated to have accounted for less than a third of the homicides and extortions in El Salvador in 2009 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0020872812437227">Policía Nacional Civil, 2010</xref>). Gangs are primarily involved in small-scale localized crime and delinquency; there is no evidence of their involvement in large-scale transnational drug trafficking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0020872812437227">UNODC, 2010</xref>). Examples of their illegal activities include: use of illegal drugs and small-scale trafficking, petty theft, muggings, extortion of local businesses and drivers of public transportation vehicles, control of territories, use of illegal weaponry, and murders, particularly of members of the rival gang (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0020872812437227">UNODC, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>The Salvadoran government has launched several anti-gang policies also known as <italic>Mano Dura</italic> (Iron Fist) (2003), <italic>Super Mano Dura</italic> (2004), and recently the <italic>Proscripción de Pandillas</italic> (2010). One of the direct consequences of the implementation of these policies has been the steady increase in the incarcerated population, especially gang members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0020872812437227">USAID, 2006</xref>). Owing to limitations in data collection, underreporting, and political factors, determining an accurate number of active gang members is an elusive task; however, official statistics suggest that there are approximately 8500 gang members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0020872812437227">Policía Nacional Civil, 2010</xref>) in prison in El Salvador,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0020872812437227">2</xref></sup> most from MS and 18. The number of youth involved in gangs outside of prison remains uncertain.</p>
<p>Although Iron Fist policies have been widely supported by political actors and the Salvadoran population, their results are less than optimal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0020872812437227">PNUD, 2009</xref>). The judiciary and prison systems do not have the resources and institutional capacity to face the high demand produced by the implementation of these policies. Prison conditions, especially for those exclusively receiving gang members, have reached unsanitary levels due to overcrowding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0020872812437227">Seelke, 2011</xref>). In addition, the level of crime decreased only temporarily and, due to the level of repression, the gangs have become more organized and violent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0020872812437227">Aguilar, 2006</xref>). Arguably, one of the most negative effects of the anti-gang policies has been the criminalization of youth, especially those from poor communities. Youth struggling with situations of ‘multiple marginality’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0020872812437227">Vigil, 1988</xref>) are not only the most common perpetrators of violence, but also the most frequent victims of violence and delinquency. Over the last decade youth aged 18 to 25 have emerged as the group most likely to perpetrate and be victimized by violent criminal activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0020872812437227">Cruz, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0020872812437227">WOLA, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Policies and government interventions designed to tackle the problem of youth violence and delinquency have been criticized for being homogeneous and dysfunctional, emphasizing the stick without the carrot (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0020872812437227">Bellanger and Rocha, 2007</xref>) and explicitly avoiding the causes of the problem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0020872812437227">Cruz, 2007</xref>). National policies have not considered the specific and unique characteristics of youth and communities in their design and implementation, have overemphasized jail as the solution, and have not shown results in prevention and, especially, in rehabilitation. Despite the efforts of the new political administration in El Salvador, specific interventions for rehabilitation and non-repressive strategies to deal with youth gangs are still in their infancy.</p>
<p>Prevention programs designed to address the risk factors have also been developed by the government and NGOs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0020872812437227">Jütersonke et al., 2009</xref>). Drawing from the principles of public health and social epidemiology, the first step in violence prevention is to identify the particular individual, social, and environmental factors that place youth at risk for taking part in violent activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0020872812437227">Farrington, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0020872812437227">Olate et al., 2010</xref>). Risk factors for violence have been defined by a variety of scholars (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0020872812437227">Hawkins et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0020872812437227">Loeber and Farrington, 1998</xref>), but the general consensus is that a risk factor is any individual, social, or environmental factor that increases the likelihood of a negative outcome, in this case of violent behavior. Researchers generally categorize risk factors for violence and delinquency into one of five particular domains of risk: individual, family, school, peer, and community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0020872812437227">Esbensen et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0020872812437227">Hawkins et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0020872812437227">Herrenkohl et al., 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>Several cross-sectional studies have been conducted in El Salvador to identify the characteristics of youth gangs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0020872812437227">Demoscopía, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0020872812437227">ERIC et al., 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0020872812437227">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0020872812437227">Savenije, 2009</xref>). The literature about gangs is strong in descriptive areas such as the dynamics of gangs, rituals of initiation, conflict among gangs, and illegal practices. Furthermore, several researchers have suggested the importance of prevention among high risk youth and social reintegration for gang members (Aguilar; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0020872812437227">Cruz, 2007</xref>). However, relatively little is known empirically as to how the risk factors contribute to youth violence and delinquency in the Salvadoran context.</p>
<p>This study examines the relative predictive power of risk factors from the five aforementioned domains in a population of high risk and gang-involved youth in a variety of marginalized communities in the Greater San Salvador Metropolitan Area. It should be noted that the data from this study are relatively unique as – unlike most studies of high risk youth and gangs in Central America – they were collected not from third party informants or from detained gang members, but rather from surveys administered with gang-involved and non-gang youth in their shared communities in San Salvador.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0020872812437227" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section3-0020872812437227">
<title>Sample and procedures</title>
<p>This investigation utilized a cross-sectional survey of youth (aged 13–24) from a nonprobability sample (<italic>N</italic> = 174) of 10 urban and semi-urban neighborhoods located in four municipalities within the Greater San Salvador Metropolitan Area. The data were collected between August 2009 and February 2010. Respondents were recruited by staff members of a Salvadoran non-governmental high risk youth development organization that works closely with active gang members and high risk youth associated with the gangs. This organization was working with 12 youth projects that correspond to 12 gang cliques. Two of the cliques refused to participate in the study for security reasons.</p>
<p>The surveys were administered at the youth organization work sites in a variety of communities by four interviewers, two from the Boston research team and two based in San Salvador. The researchers from the Boston research team trained the San Salvador-based interviewers in survey administration. Fifty-six percent of the surveys were administered individually and 44.2 percent were administered in groups ranging from two to 14 youth. The group interviews were carried out under the supervision of at least two of the four interviewers involved in the data collection. All subjects completed the survey in Spanish in 35 to 50 minutes. The study was reviewed and approved by the institutional review board at Boston College in Boston, Massachusetts.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0020872812437227">
<title>Measures</title>
<sec id="section5-0020872812437227">
<title>Violent behavior</title>
<p>Three dichotomous variables from the Self-Report of Delinquency (SRD) Scale originally developed for the Denver Youth Survey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0020872812437227">Huizinga et al., 1990</xref>) were used to measure youth involvement with violent behavior during the previous 90 days: 1) having attacked someone with a weapon or with the idea of seriously hurting or killing them, 2) having hit someone with the idea of hurting them but not with the idea of seriously injuring or killing them, and 3) having carried an unspecified hidden weapon during the previous three months. For all three variables, answers of ‘yes’ were coded as 1 and ‘no’ as 0. Nearly two-thirds of respondents (65.2%) reported having taken part in one of these activities while less than one third (28.3%) answered in the affirmative to all three measures.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0020872812437227">
<title>Non-violent delinquency</title>
<p>Three additional dichotomous variables from the SRD were used to measure delinquent behavior during the previous 90 days: 1) having tried to steal or actually stolen money or things worth between $5 and $50, 2) having tried to buy or sell things that were stolen, and 3) having sold marijuana. As with violent behavior, answers of ‘yes’ were coded as 1 and ‘no’ as 0. More than half of the respondents (56.1%) reported having taken part in one of these activities while less than one fifth (17.0%) answered in the affirmative to all three questions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0020872812437227">
<title>Risk factors</title>
<p>Categorized according to risk domains listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0020872812437227">Table 1</xref>, 11 predictor variables were selected – three in the individual domain and two in each remaining risk domain – so as to capture the breadth of risk factors without exceeding the limits of the independent variable/sample size ratio.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0020872812437227" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Risk factors organized by domain.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0020872812437227" xlink:href="10.1177_0020872812437227-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Individual</th>
<th align="left">Family</th>
<th align="left">School</th>
<th align="left">Peer</th>
<th align="left">Community</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>High impulsivity</td>
<td>Unstable home</td>
<td>Educational difficulty</td>
<td>Delinquent peers</td>
<td>Neighborhood disorder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Low empathy</td>
<td>Difficulty at home</td>
<td>Expelled from school</td>
<td>Gang membership</td>
<td>Low social support</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Low future orientation</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0020872812437227">
<title>Individual</title>
<p>Individual risk factors were measured by three multi-item indexes. The Basic Empathy Scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0020872812437227">Joliffe and Farrington, 2006</xref>) uses a five-point Likert scale ranging from ‘strongly agree’ to ‘strongly disagree’. The scale includes items such as: ‘I can understand my friend’s happiness when she/he does well at something’, and ‘After being with a friend who is sad about something, I usually feel sad.’ Internal consistency in the present sample was .645. The Impulsivity Index (Grasmick et al., 1983; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0020872812437227">Higgins, 2007</xref>) uses the same Likert scale and includes prompts such as: ‘When I am really angry, other people should stay away from me’, and ‘I often act on the spur of the moment without stopping to think.’ Based on factor analytic and reliability analyses the Impulsivity Index was reduced from 16 items to nine items such that all items were significantly correlated and had an acceptable Cronbach’s alpha value (.783). The Future Orientation Scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0020872812437227">Kazdin et al., 1986</xref>) also uses a five-point Likert scale and includes products such as: ‘The future seems unclear and confusing to me’, and ‘I never get what I want, so it’s dumb to want anything.’ The future orientation scale was reduced from seven items to four items such that all items were significantly correlated and the Cronbach’s alpha value was adequate (.637).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0020872812437227">
<title>Family</title>
<p>Family risk factors were measured in terms of personal residential instability and difficulty at home. The personal residential stability was measured by a dichotomous question, ‘Do you have a stable place to live?’ In order to remain consistent with the risk factor coding, this variable was reverse coded such that lack of stability is indicated by ‘1’ and stability by ‘0’. Difficulty at home was also measured by a dichotomous question: ‘Do you have problems at home?’ in which answers of ‘yes’ were coded as 1 and ‘no’ as 0.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0020872812437227">
<title>School</title>
<p>Educational risk factors were measured by a multi-item index and one binary variable. A brief version of the School Dropout Risk Inventory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0020872812437227">Vaughn, 2011</xref>) uses a three-point ordinal scale ranging from ‘never’ to ‘always’. The scale measures learning difficulties, antisocial behavior in school, and academic interest and includes items such as: ‘I have a hard time doing all the school work that is assigned’ and ‘Do you think about dropping out of school?’ Youth who had already graduated or dropped out of school were asked to answer these questions retrospectively. Internal consistency and exploratory factor analysis were conducted, reducing the original 23-item scale to nine-item scale in order to achieve an acceptable Cronbach’s alpha score of .811 with significant correlations for all items. The binary item measured whether a youth had ever been expelled from school in which answers of ‘yes’ were coded as 1 and ‘no’ as 0.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0020872812437227">
<title>Peer</title>
<p>The peer delinquency and gang membership items were measured by dichotomous items. Peer delinquency was assessed by the question, ‘Is doing illegal things accepted by or okay for your group?’ Gang membership was a lifetime measure which read, ‘Have you ever participated in a gang?’ While some debate exists as to the operationalization of gang membership, this method of self-reported gang participation has been used frequently by gang researchers and is generally considered the best method available (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0020872812437227">Klein and Maxson, 2006</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0020872812437227">
<title>Community</title>
<p>Community risk factors were measured by two multi-item indexes. The Community Disorganization Index uses a three-point scale ranging from ‘no problem’ to ‘big problem’ and measures items on the topics of crime, neighborhood maintenance, and access to transportation. Internal consistency and exploratory factor analysis were conducted, reducing the original eight-item scale to seven items in order to achieve an acceptable Cronbach’s alpha score of .859 with significant correlations for all items. Social support was measured by five yes/no items and included prompts such as: ‘There is at least one adult in my community who I trust to give me advice’ and ‘There is at least one adult in my community who supports me in making positive changes in my life.’ The Social Support Scale was used in its original format with a Cronbach’s alpha value of .771.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0020872812437227">
<title>Control variables</title>
<p>Three control variables were used in the study. First, we controlled for age as respondents varied in age from 13 to 24 thus representing a spectrum in terms of late childhood, adolescent, and youth development. Second, we controlled for having children, as 28.0 percent of non-gang youth and 43.0 percent of gang-involved youth in the sample reported having at least one child of their own. Finally, we controlled for gender as 62 percent of non-gang youth and 91 percent of gang-involved youth in the sample were male.</p>
<p>Importantly, all continuous independent variables were dichotomized so as to facilitate a clear ‘yes/no’ distinction between having or not having been exposed to a particular risk factor. Although this procedure results in a loss of information, many of these variables were badly skewed and beyond standard transformation techniques. To the extent possible, scores within the highest 25 percent of a risk distribution were identified as ‘at risk’ and coded as ‘1’ while the other three quartiles of the sample were considered to be within a spectrum of relative safety and thus were coded as ‘0’. In most cases, a recoding at the exact 75th percentile was not possible and thus the closest cut-point available – generally a difference of plus or minus two to three percentage points – was selected.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0020872812437227">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>Assessment of the distributional properties of study variables including means and percentages were calculated for all study variables. Next, chi-square and independent <italic>t</italic>-tests were performed to examine if demographic variables, violence and delinquency variables, and risk factors differed between non-gang youth and gang-involved youth (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0020872812437227">Table 2</xref>). Zero-order correlations were then employed to assess associations among all study variables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0020872812437227">Table 3</xref>). Multiple logistic regression analyses were performed to estimate the relative effects of risk factor variables in the prediction of violence and delinquency – specifically, attack with a weapon, hitting someone, carrying a weapon, stealing valuable item, buy or sell stolen item, and sold marijuana (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0020872812437227">Table 4</xref>). Regression diagnostic procedures revealed no problems with multicollinearity in all regression models. All tolerance values exceeded 0.25. Finally, in terms of missing data, the sample size was considered to be too small to justify multiple imputation and consequently listwise deletion was used. All regression analyses were conducted using STATA 11.0.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0020872812437227" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Descriptive characteristics of study participants.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0020872812437227" xlink:href="10.1177_0020872812437227-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="4">High risk non-gang (<italic>n</italic> = 58)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="4">Gang involved (<italic>n</italic> = 116)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="left">SD</th>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left">Range</th>
<th align="left"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="left">SD</th>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left">Range</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><italic>Demographic variables</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age</td>
<td>18.2</td>
<td>2.9</td>
<td/>
<td>(13–23)</td>
<td>18.8</td>
<td>3.0</td>
<td/>
<td>(13–24)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>62.07</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>91.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0020872812437227">***</xref></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>37.93<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0020872812437227">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>8.62</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Having a child</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>28.0</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>43.0</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><italic>Violence and delinquency</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Attack with a weapon</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>5.0</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>45.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0020872812437227">***</xref></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hitting someone</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>16.0</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>57.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0020872812437227">***</xref></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Carrying a weapon</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>19.0</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>58.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0020872812437227">***</xref></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Stealing valuable item</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>12.0</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>42.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0020872812437227">***</xref></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Buy or sell stolen item</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>21.0</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>54.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0020872812437227">***</xref></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sold marijuana</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>16.0</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>38.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0020872812437227">**</xref></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Risk factors</italic></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> High impulsivity</td>
<td>27.9</td>
<td>6.4</td>
<td/>
<td>(15–45)</td>
<td>30.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0020872812437227">*</xref></td>
<td>6.6</td>
<td/>
<td>(15–43)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Low hope</td>
<td>23.7</td>
<td>3.3</td>
<td/>
<td>(17–31)</td>
<td>22.7</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td/>
<td>(15–32)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Low empathy</td>
<td>67.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0020872812437227">*</xref></td>
<td>8.9</td>
<td/>
<td>(33–86)</td>
<td>63.7</td>
<td>7.7</td>
<td/>
<td>(44–87)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Unstable home</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>24.14</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>24.56</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Difficulty at home</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>24.0</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>36.0</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Educational difficulty</td>
<td>13.9</td>
<td>2.8</td>
<td/>
<td>(9–23)</td>
<td>15.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0020872812437227">*</xref></td>
<td>3.9</td>
<td/>
<td>(7–26)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Expelled from school</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>27.0</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>41.0</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Delinquent peers</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>30.0</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>63.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0020872812437227">***</xref></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> High neighborhood disorder</td>
<td>13.1</td>
<td>3.7</td>
<td/>
<td>(7–21)</td>
<td>12.4</td>
<td>4.0</td>
<td/>
<td>(6–21)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Low social support</td>
<td>4.0</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td/>
<td>(0–5)</td>
<td>3.8</td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td/>
<td>(0–5)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0020872812437227">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05; ** <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; *** <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 between high risk non-gang youth and gang-involved youth.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table3-0020872812437227" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Correlation matrix for independent and dependent variables.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0020872812437227" xlink:href="10.1177_0020872812437227-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">1</th>
<th align="left">2</th>
<th align="left">3</th>
<th align="left">4</th>
<th align="left">5</th>
<th align="left">6</th>
<th align="left">7</th>
<th align="left">8</th>
<th align="left">9</th>
<th align="left">10</th>
<th align="left">11</th>
<th align="left">12</th>
<th align="left">13</th>
<th align="left">14</th>
<th align="left">15</th>
<th align="left">16</th>
<th align="left">17</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1. Attack with weapon</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2. Hitting</td>
<td><bold>.57</bold></td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3. Carrying weapon</td>
<td><bold>.51</bold></td>
<td><bold>.36</bold></td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4. Stealing valuable item</td>
<td><bold>.63</bold></td>
<td><bold>.38</bold></td>
<td><bold>.49</bold></td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5. Sell/buy stolen item</td>
<td><bold>.51</bold></td>
<td><bold>.30</bold></td>
<td><bold>.39</bold></td>
<td><bold>.60</bold></td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6. Sold marijuana</td>
<td><bold>.45</bold></td>
<td><bold>.24</bold></td>
<td><bold>.32</bold></td>
<td><bold>.33</bold></td>
<td><bold>.37</bold></td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7. High impulsivity</td>
<td><bold>.26</bold></td>
<td><bold>.21</bold></td>
<td><bold>.26</bold></td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td><bold>.20</bold></td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8. Low hope</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td><bold>.21</bold></td>
<td><bold>.23</bold></td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>−.10</td>
<td><bold>.16</bold></td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9. Low empathy</td>
<td><bold>.25</bold></td>
<td><bold>.25</bold></td>
<td>.09</td>
<td><bold>.20</bold></td>
<td>.08</td>
<td><bold>.16</bold></td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10. Unstable home</td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>−.08</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>−.13</td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>−.02</td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11. Difficulty at home</td>
<td><bold>.18</bold></td>
<td><bold>.18</bold></td>
<td><bold>.27</bold></td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.15</td>
<td><bold>.18</bold></td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12. Educational difficulty</td>
<td><bold>.20</bold></td>
<td><bold>.37</bold></td>
<td>.10</td>
<td><bold>.27</bold></td>
<td><bold>.19</bold></td>
<td>.07</td>
<td><bold>.28</bold></td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>−<bold>.18</bold></td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13. Expelled from school</td>
<td><bold>.30</bold></td>
<td><bold>.25</bold></td>
<td><bold>.16</bold></td>
<td><bold>.18</bold></td>
<td>.07</td>
<td><bold>.22</bold></td>
<td><bold>.24</bold></td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>−.00</td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td><bold>.24</bold></td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14. Delinquent peers</td>
<td><bold>.36</bold></td>
<td><bold>.43</bold></td>
<td><bold>.27</bold></td>
<td><bold>.37</bold></td>
<td><bold>.29</bold></td>
<td><bold>.31</bold></td>
<td><bold>.18</bold></td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td><bold>.27</bold></td>
<td><bold>.18</bold></td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15. Gang membership</td>
<td><bold>.45</bold></td>
<td><bold>.46</bold></td>
<td><bold>.42</bold></td>
<td><bold>.28</bold></td>
<td><bold>.26</bold></td>
<td><bold>.24</bold></td>
<td><bold>.16</bold></td>
<td>.07</td>
<td><bold>.26</bold></td>
<td>.05</td>
<td><bold>.18</bold></td>
<td><bold>.20</bold></td>
<td>.10</td>
<td><bold>.36</bold></td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16. High neighborhood disorder</td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>−<bold>.17</bold></td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>−.08</td>
<td>−<bold>.19</bold></td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>−<bold>.19</bold></td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>−<bold>.20</bold></td>
<td>−.10</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>17. Low social support</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td><bold>.18</bold></td>
<td><bold>.17</bold></td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>−.00</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>−.15</td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table4-0020872812437227" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption><p>Logistic regression analyses predicting violence and delinquency.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0020872812437227" xlink:href="10.1177_0020872812437227-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Model 1 Attack with weapon (<italic>n</italic> = 116)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Model 2 Hitting (<italic>n</italic> = 116)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Model 3 Carrying weapon (n = 116)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Model 4 Stealing valuable item (<italic>n</italic> = 116)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Model 5 Buy or sell stolen item (<italic>n</italic> = 116)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Model 6 Sold marijuana (<italic>n</italic> = 116)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Predictor</th>
<th align="left">OR</th>
<th align="left">95% CI</th>
<th align="left">OR</th>
<th align="left">95% CI</th>
<th align="left">OR</th>
<th align="left">95% CI</th>
<th align="left">OR</th>
<th align="left">95% CI</th>
<th align="left">OR</th>
<th align="left">95% CI</th>
<th align="left">OR</th>
<th align="left">95% CI</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="13"><italic>Individual</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> High impulsivity</td>
<td>2.1</td>
<td>(0.7-6.4)</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>(0.3-3.0)</td>
<td>2.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227"><italic>†</italic></xref></td>
<td>(0.9-7.8)</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>(0.3-2.6)</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>(0.3-2.1)</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>(0.6-4.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Low future orientation</td>
<td>0.9</td>
<td>(0.3-3.1)</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>(0.4-4.7)</td>
<td><bold>3.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.0-11.1)</bold></td>
<td><bold>3.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.1-10.2)</bold></td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>(0.7-4.6)</td>
<td><bold>0.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(0.1-1.0)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Low empathy</td>
<td><bold>3.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.0-11.1)</bold></td>
<td><bold>3.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.2-12.9)</bold></td>
<td>0.7</td>
<td>(0.2-2.2)</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>(0.6-5.3)</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>(0.4-2.8)</td>
<td>2.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227"><italic>†</italic></xref></td>
<td>(0.9-8.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13"><italic>Family</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Unstable home</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>(0.4-4.6)</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>(0.2-2.0)</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>(0.4-3.8)</td>
<td>0.7</td>
<td>(0.2-2.5)</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>(0.4-3.1)</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>(0.4-3.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Difficulty at home</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>(0.5-4.5)</td>
<td>1.8</td>
<td>(0.6-5.6)</td>
<td>2.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227"><italic>†</italic></xref></td>
<td>(0.9-7.5)</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>(0.4-3.6)</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>(0.6-3.8)</td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>(0.7-5.4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13"><italic>School</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Educational difficulty</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>(0.2-2.7)</td>
<td><bold>4.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.2-19.3)</bold></td>
<td>0.5</td>
<td>(0.2-1.8)</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>(0.7-6.9)</td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>(0.7-5.2)</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>(0.2-1.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Expelled from school</td>
<td><bold>5.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">**</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.8-19.3)</bold></td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>(0.7-6.1)</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>(0.5-4.2)</td>
<td>2.1</td>
<td>(0.7-5.7)</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>(0.4-2.6)</td>
<td><bold>3.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.2-9.2)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13"><italic>Peer</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Delinquent peers</td>
<td><bold>4.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.4-16.0)</bold></td>
<td><bold>3.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.3-10.7)</bold></td>
<td><bold>2.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.0-8.2)</bold></td>
<td><bold>5.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">**</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.8-17.6)</bold></td>
<td>2.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></td>
<td>(1.0-6.3)</td>
<td>2.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227"><italic>†</italic></xref></td>
<td>(0.9-8.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gang membership</td>
<td><bold>10.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.7-63.2)</bold></td>
<td><bold>4.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.2-18.7)</bold></td>
<td><bold>3.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.0-11.6)</bold></td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>(0.2-3.7)</td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>(0.5-5.0)</td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>(0.5-7.4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13"><italic>Community</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> High neighborhood disorder</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>(0.4-4.8)</td>
<td>0.7</td>
<td>(0.2-2.2)</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>(0.2-1.7)</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>(0.4-3.1)</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>(0.4-2.8)</td>
<td>0.5</td>
<td>(0.2-1.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Low social support</td>
<td>2.9</td>
<td>(0.6-14.5)</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>(0.1-3.0)</td>
<td>0.5</td>
<td>(0.1-2.1)</td>
<td><bold>6.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></bold></td>
<td><bold>(1.4-27.6)</bold></td>
<td>3.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227"><italic>†</italic></xref></td>
<td>(1.0-13.9)</td>
<td>2.3</td>
<td>(0.5-9.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="13"><italic>Control variables</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>(0.9-1.5)</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>(0.8-1.2)</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>(0.9-1.4)</td>
<td>1.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227"><italic>†</italic></xref></td>
<td>(1.0-1.5)</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>(0.8-1.2)</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>(0.9-1.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Have children</td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td>(0.2-2.8)</td>
<td>1.8</td>
<td>(0.5-6.3)</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>(0.3-3.5)</td>
<td>0.7</td>
<td>(0.2-2.3)</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>(0.5-4.1)</td>
<td>1.1</td>
<td>(0.4-3.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male</td>
<td>4.8</td>
<td>(0.3-73.0)</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>(0.3-11.1)</td>
<td>4.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227"><italic>†</italic></xref></td>
<td>(0.8-21.8)</td>
<td>5.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227"><italic>†</italic></xref></td>
<td>(0.8-40.3)</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>(0.2-3.9)</td>
<td>0.7</td>
<td>(0.1-3.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> −2 log likelihood</td>
<td colspan="2">48.2</td>
<td colspan="2">50.1</td>
<td colspan="2">56.0</td>
<td colspan="2">54.6</td>
<td colspan="2">69.1</td>
<td colspan="2">57.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Likelihood ratio χ<sup>2</sup></td>
<td colspan="2">56.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">***</xref></td>
<td colspan="2">60.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">***</xref></td>
<td colspan="2">47.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">***</xref></td>
<td colspan="2">43.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">***</xref></td>
<td colspan="2">19.8</td>
<td colspan="2">28.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0020872812437227">*</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0020872812437227">
<p><italic>Note</italic>: OR (Odds Ratio) and 95% CI (Confidence Interval) in bold are significant at <italic>p</italic> &lt;. 05 or lower.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0020872812437227">
<label>†</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .10; *<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05; **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; *** <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0020872812437227" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section16-0020872812437227">
<title>Descriptive characteristics</title>
<p>Descriptive characteristics of the study samples are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0020872812437227">Table 2</xref>. Overall, the age of respondents ranged from 13 to 24, with an average age of 18.2 years for high risk youth non-gang members (SD = 2.9) and 18.8 for youth gang members (SD = 3.0). Most youth were male in both groups (62.1% vs 91.4%), though 38 percent were females in the group of non-gang members. The group of gang members has a higher average of having a child (43%), though this difference is not significant. Overall, more than three in four respondents reported having ‘stable housing’ (76%). However, well more than half lived in ‘single parent households’ (63%), and roughly one-third reported having ‘problems at home’ (32%). Almost 40 percent (39%) of the respondents had been ‘expelled from school’ at least once and the average years of formal education was 7.78.</p>
<p>All variables considered for violence and delinquency were significantly (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05) higher for youth gang members, ranging from 2.4 to 9.0 times more than youth non-gang members. Regarding risk factors, youth gang members showed statistically higher levels of impulsivity, educational difficulty and delinquent peers. Youth gang members reported significantly (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05) lower levels of empathy than their non-gang counterparts. However, in six risk factors statistically significant differences between both groups were not found.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0020872812437227">
<title>Correlations of study variables</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0020872812437227">Table 3</xref> presents correlations of the study variables. The three variables included as indicators of violence (‘attack with weapon’, ‘hitting’, and ‘carrying a weapon’) are positively associated with the majority of the variables with the exception of ‘unstable home’ and ‘low social support’. Specific distinctions for the variables of violence included: ‘low future orientation’ is correlated with ‘carrying a weapon’; ‘low empathy’ and ‘educational difficulty’ are associated with ‘attacks with weapon’ and ‘hitting’; and ‘high neighborhood disorder’ is associated with ‘hitting’.</p>
<p>Regarding the variables included in the delinquency index, ‘stealing a valuable item’ was positively associated with ‘selling or buying a stolen item’, ‘sold marijuana’, ‘low hope’, ‘low empathy’, ‘educational difficulty’, ‘expelled from school’, ‘delinquent peers’, ‘gang membership’, and ‘low social support’. ‘Selling or buying a stolen item’ was positively associated with ‘selling marijuana’, ‘educational difficulty’, ‘delinquent peers’, ‘gang membership’, and ‘low social support’. ‘Sold marijuana’ was positively associated with ‘high impulsivity’, ‘low empathy’, ‘expelled from school’, ‘delinquent peers’, ‘gang membership’, and negatively associated with high ‘neighborhood disorder’. Three general aspects were highlighted regarding type of risk factors and the variables included for violence and delinquency: a) all peer risk factors variables were positively associated with all variables for violence and delinquency, b) no variables for family risk factors were associated with delinquency, and c) all variables for violence and delinquency were positively associated among each other.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0020872812437227">
<title>Predictors of violence and delinquency</title>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0020872812437227">Table 4</xref>, six separate sets of multiple logistics regression analyses were executed to identify determinants of various forms of youth violence and delinquency. The first three models examined the effect of predictors on violence: attack with a weapon (Model 1), hitting someone (Model 2), and carrying a weapon (Model 3). The second three models examined the predictors of delinquency: stealing valuable item (Model 4), buying or selling a stolen item (Model5), and sold marijuana (Model 6). All models were statistically significant with the exception of Model 5, buying or selling a stolen item.</p>
<p>Results show that ‘delinquent peers’ and ‘gang membership’ significantly increased the likelihood of ‘attack with a weapon’ (OR = 4.8, 95% CI = 1.4–16.0 and OR = 10.4, 95% CI = 1.7–63.2), ‘hitting someone’ (OR = 3.7, 95% CI = 1.3–10.7 and OR = 4.7, 95% CI = 1.2–18.7.2), and ‘carrying a weapon’ (OR = 2.9, 95% CI = 1.0–8.2 and OR = 3.4, 95% CI = 1.0–11.6) (see Models 1, 2 and 3). ‘Low empathy’ significantly increased the likelihood of ‘attack with a weapon’ (OR = 3.4, 95% CI = 1.0–11.1) and ‘hitting someone’ (OR = 3.9, 95% CI = 1.2–12.9) (see Models 1 and 2). ‘Expelled from school’ was also associated with increased likelihood of ‘attack with a weapon’ (OR = 5.9, 95% CI = 1.8–19.3) (see Model 1). ‘Educational difficulty’ significantly increased the likelihood of ‘hitting someone’ (OR = 4.9, 95% CI = 1.2–19.3) (see Model 2). Finally, ‘low future orientation’ significantly increased the likelihood of ‘carrying a weapon’ (OR = 3.4, 95% CI = 1.0–11.1) (see Model 3).</p>
<p>‘Low empathy’ significantly increased the likelihood of ‘stealing a valuable’ item (OR = 3.3, 95% CI = 1.1–10.2) and significantly decreased the likelihood of ‘having sold marijuana’ (OR = 0.3, 95% CI = 0.1–1.0) (see Models 4 and 6). ‘Expelled from school’ significantly increased the likelihood of ‘having sold marijuana’ (OR = 3.3, 95% CI = 1.2–9.2) (see Model 6). Finally, ‘delinquent peers’ and ‘low social support’ significantly increased the likelihood of ‘stealing a valuable item’ (OR = 5.6, 95% CI = 1.8–17.6 and OR = 6.2, 95% CI = 1.4–27.6) (see Model 4).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0020872812437227" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Youth violence, delinquency, and gangs present serious challenges to Salvadoran society in terms of individual, family, and community well-being and national development. This study sought to examine the effects of key risk factors derived from several interrelated domains in a population of high risk and gang-involved youth in the Greater San Salvador Metropolitan Area. Overall, findings indicated that low future orientation, empathy deficits, educational difficulties, delinquent peers, gang membership, and lack of social support were found to be significant risk factors for violence and delinquency. These findings offer an empirical contribution to the relatively limited research base on these youth in Latin America in general and El Salvador in particular. Results also suggest numerous avenues for developing prevention and intervention methodologies.</p>
<p>The robustness of gang membership and the presence of delinquent peers across the distinct manifestations of violence are consistent with previous empirical research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0020872812437227">Cruz, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0020872812437227">2007</xref>) and the observations of informed scholars (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0020872812437227">Rodgers, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0020872812437227">Savenije, 2009</xref>) in El Salvador and Central America. Indeed, empirical research in the United States has repeatedly shown that youth who associate with delinquent and antisocial peers are more likely to take part in youth violence and antisocial behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0020872812437227">Hawkins et al., 1998</xref>). It is worth noting, however, that while the presence of delinquent peers was predictive of violent behavior, gang membership was not found to be a significant predictor of any non-violent delinquent behaviors. This finding may suggest that the antisocial sequelae associated with gang membership in San Salvador are manifested as aggression and violence rather than non-violent delinquent misbehavior. While it has been observed that delinquency is generally a collective endeavor (Elliot et al., 1985) in which youth participation frequently increases as a function of peer approval, it may be that the relatively pedestrian delinquency items measured in this study fall outside of the scope of contemporary Salvadoran gang behavior.</p>
<p>Low levels of empathy were found to be a significant predictor of the two most active forms of violence – attacking with a weapon and hitting – but were not found to be significant (except for marginal significance in terms of marijuana sales) in terms of weapon carrying or any delinquent behaviors. This finding may suggest that, in the Salvadoran context, low levels of empathy are predictive of overtly violent behavior but not the more indirectly violent or delinquent behaviors. While some prior studies have found low levels of empathy to be predictive of more indirectly violent/delinquent behaviors such as drug dealing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0020872812437227">Schreiber, 1992</xref>) and fire setting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0020872812437227">Walsh et al., 2004</xref>), the results here may indicate that empathy is more predictive of directly violent behavior, as has been found to be the case with studies examining sexual offending (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0020872812437227">Farr et al., 2004</xref>) and bullying (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0020872812437227">Gini et al., 2007</xref>). These disparate findings are also most likely related to different measures of empathy.</p>
<p>The tendency to discount the future was the only other individual level predictor found to be significant, yielding somewhat paradoxical results. Consistent with theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0020872812437227">Little and Steinberg, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0020872812437227">Robbins and Bryan, 2004</xref>), future discounting predicted weapon carrying and stealing of valuable items yet was also inversely related to marijuana sales. That is, youth with lower levels of future orientation were more likely to carry a weapon and to steal something valuable yet less likely to sell marijuana. While typically future discounting is thought to be a risk factor for delinquent behavior – as is the case with two of the dependent variables – it may be the case that, in the San Salvador sample, a bidirectional relationship exists between higher levels of future orientation and marijuana sales. Given the level of poverty and lack of opportunities in Salvadoran society (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0020872812437227">Savenije, 2009</xref>), a negative correlation between low future orientation and marijuana selling may illustrate youth’s beliefs that the only opportunity for economic success is from an income generated from selling marijuana (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0020872812437227">Chassin et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0020872812437227">Hagan, 1993</xref>).</p>
<p>Some risk factors previously identified as important in research studies conducted in the United States, Western Europe and Australia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0020872812437227">Hemphill et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0020872812437227">Van Der Merwe and Dawes, 2007</xref>) were not found to be significant predictors of violence in the San Salvador sample. Notably, across all of the manifestations of violence and all but one delinquent behavior, no risk factors in the family or community domains were found to be significant predictors of violent behavior. It is unclear whether this finding is accurately measuring the reality of risk factors in the Salvadoran context or is a function of limitations in the survey instrument and sampling methodology. In terms of family risk, the measures used only assessed the stability of one’s living environment and the rather vague notion of ‘problems at home’. As such, the study may have failed to capture important particular family risk factors such as child abuse, domestic violence, and inconsistent or severe parenting.</p>
<p>As for community risk factors, the sampling of youth in poor and marginalized communities alone may not have allowed for enough statistically measurable variance in the sample. In all of the neighborhoods where youth were surveyed, virtually all of the elements of neighborhood disorder could be readily observed. Additionally, in these neighborhoods many of the most prominent adults – that is, those who would presumably offer ‘social support’ – are active gang members and thus may not offer the kind of pro-social support that would be associated with non-violent or non-delinquent behavior.</p>
<p>This study is unique and unlike most studies of high risk youth and gangs in Central America due to the fact that data were collected not from third party informants or from detained gang members, but rather from surveys administered with high risk and gang-involved youth in their communities. Even so, there are several limitations worth highlighting. First, this investigation was a cross-sectional sample of convenience and therefore causal inferences cannot be justified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0020872812437227">Farrington, 2000</xref>) and representativeness is an open question. Second, the study also relied on self-report measures (with a potential problem of under-reporting or over-reporting). Third, while all measures were translated into Spanish, the survey instrument itself is a compilation of measures and scales designed and validated in the United States and the cultural context of some words may have influenced some responses. Fourth, the varied data collection techniques (individual and collective interviews) may have compromised reliability. Fifth, given the limited sample size and the limitations of the survey instrument itself, only 11 risk factors were examined in the study. Studies conducted in the United States with larger sample sizes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0020872812437227">Thornberry et al., 2003</xref>) have included up to 40 risk factors which allows for a much broader analysis of specific factors as well as a more powerful examination of cumulative risk.</p>
<p>Despite these limitations, the findings of this study offer several important recommendations for youth violence prevention in the Salvadoran context, including the development of programs that take into account the impact of peers and gang membership. The best approach to violence prevention in San Salvador may be gang prevention. Effective efforts to prevent delinquency may be those targeting delinquent peer relationships. The results of this article offer specific suggestions for developing social work interventions, including the creation of workshops and community interventions for youth involved in gangs which emphasize the discussion of positive concepts of the future, increasing levels of empathy, supporting at-risk youth who are in school, decreasing the influence of gangs in school settings, and increasing the community and family social support.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>This research was funded by the Boston College Graduate School of Social Work and the Boston College Jesuit Institute.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0020872812437227">
<label>1.</label>
<p>The homicide rates in 2008 per 100,000 inhabitants for El Salvador, Guatemala, and Honduras were 52, 48, and 50 respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0020872812437227">PNUD, 2009</xref>) while those for Belize, Costa Rica, Nicaragua, and Panama were 32, 11, 13, and 19. The rate for El Salvador in 2009 was 72.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0020872812437227">
<label>2.</label>
<p>The assistant director of the National Police, Official Cotto, estimated in 2010 that there were 13,000 gang members on the streets. The incarcerated population in San Salvador in November 2010 was 24,300; 8574 were identified as gang members.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) ‘<article-title>Los efectos contraproducentes de los planes Mano Dura</article-title>’, <source>Revista de Pensamiento Iberoamericano</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Las maras o pandillas juveniles en el triángulo norte de Centroamérica</article-title>. <publisher-loc>San Salvador, El Salvador</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UCA Editores</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bellanger</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) ‘<article-title>The Politics of Policies about Gangs in Central America</article-title>’, in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Street Gangs in Central America</source>, pp. <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. <publisher-loc>San Salvador, El Salvador</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UCA Editores</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chassin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vargas-Chanes</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Losoya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<article-title>Substance Use Treatment Outcomes in a Sample of Serious Juvenile Offenders</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment</source> <volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) ‘<article-title>El Salvador: Tatuados por la violencia’, in Fundación Arias</article-title>, <source>La cara de la violencia urbana en América Central</source>. <publisher-loc>San José, Costa Rica</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fundación Arias</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) (<year>2007</year>) <source>Street Gangs in Central America</source>. <publisher-loc>San Salvador, El Salvador</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UCA Editores</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duffee</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinke</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naccaratto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<article-title>On the Meaning and Measurement of Engagement in Youth Residential Treatment Centers</article-title>’, <source>Research on Social Work Practice</source> <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Demoscopía</collab> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Maras y pandillas, comunidad y policía en Centroamérica</article-title>. <publisher-loc>San José</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Demoscopía</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dingeman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rumbaut</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) ‘<article-title>The Immigration–Crime Nexus and Post-deportation Experiences</article-title>’, <source>University of La Verne Law Review</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>ERIC, IDESO, IDIES and IUDOP</collab> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Maras y pandillas en Centroamérica</source>. <publisher-loc>Managua</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UCA Publicaciones</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>ERIC, IDESO, IDIES and IUDOP</collab> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Maras y pandillas en Centroamérica: Pandillas y capital social</source>. <publisher-loc>San Salvador</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UCA Publicaciones</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Esbensen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Terrance</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freng</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<article-title>Similarities and Differences in Risk Factors for Violent Offending and Gang Membership</article-title>’, <source>Australian and New Zealand Journal of Criminology</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Farr</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beckett</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) ‘<article-title>Ability to Empathize and Masculinity Levels</article-title>’, <source>Psychology, Crime and Law</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Farrington</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) ‘<article-title>Explaining and Preventing Crime: The Globalization of Knowledge</article-title>’, <source>Criminology</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albiero</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benelli</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altoe</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) ‘<article-title>Does Empathy Predict Adolescents’ Bullying and Defending Behavior?</article-title>’, <source>Aggressive Behavior</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grasmick</surname><given-names>H.G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tittle</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bursik</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arneklev</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) ‘<article-title>Testing the core empirical implications of Gottredsons and Hirshi’s General Theory of Crime</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Research in Crime and Delinquency</source>, <volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hagan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) ‘<article-title>The Social Embeddedness of Crime and Unemployment</article-title>’, <source>Criminology</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hagedorn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>A World of Gangs: Armed Young Men and Gangsta Culture</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) ‘<article-title>Risk and Protective Factors for Alcohol and Other Drug Problems in Adolescence and Early Adulthood</article-title>’, <source>Psychological Bulletin</source> <volume>112</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Herrenkohl</surname><given-names>T.I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farrington</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harachi</surname><given-names>T.W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) ‘<article-title>A Review of Predictors of Youth Violence</article-title>’, in <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Loeber</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farrington</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Serious and Violent Juvenile Offenders</source>, pp. <fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hemphill</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toumbourou</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Herrenkohl</surname><given-names>T.I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McMorris</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romaniuk</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<article-title>Modifiable Determinants of Youth Violence in Australia and the United States</article-title>’, <source>The Australian and New Zealand Journal of Criminology</source> <volume>42</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Herrenkohl</surname><given-names>T.I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kosterman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>B.H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) ‘<article-title>Early Adolescent Predictors of Youth Violence as Mediators of Childhood Risks</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Early Adolescence</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>447</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) ‘<article-title>Examining the original Grasmick scale: A Rasch model approach</article-title>’, <source>Criminal Justice and Behavior</source> <volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huizinga</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Esbensen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weiher</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>Denver Youth Survey</source>. <publisher-loc>Boulder</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Colorado</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jolliffe</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farrington</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) ‘<article-title>Development and Validation of the Basic Empathy Scale</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Adolescence</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>611</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jütersonke</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muggah</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<article-title>Urban Violence and Security Promotion in Central America</article-title>’, <source>Security Dialogue</source> <volume>40</volume>(<issue>4–5</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kazdin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Redgres</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cobus</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) ‘<article-title>The Hopelessness Scale for Children: Psychometric Characteristics and Concurrent Validity</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Consulting &amp; Clinical Psychology</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kazdin</surname><given-names>A.E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cobus</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) ‘<article-title>The Hopelessness Scale for Children: Psychometric Characteristics and Concurrent Validity</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>245</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maxson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Street Gang Patterns and Policies</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) ‘<article-title>Psychosocial Correlates of Adolescent Drug Dealing in the Inner City</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Research in Crime and Delinquency</source> <volume>43</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Loeber</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farrington</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>1998</year>) <source>Serious and Violent Juvenile Offenders</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Olate</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salas-Wright</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) ‘<article-title>¿Cómo intervenir en los problemas de violencia y delincuencia juvenil?</article-title>’, <source>Revista de Trabajo Social</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Olate</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salas-Wright</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) ‘<article-title>A Cross-national Comparison of Externalizing Behaviors in Metropolitan Boston and San Salvador</article-title>’, <source>Victims &amp; Offenders</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Policía Nacional Civil</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Estadísticas sobre criminalidad en El Salvador</source>. <publisher-loc>San Salvador</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PNC</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Programa de las Naciones Unidas para el Desarrollo (PNUD)</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Informe sobre desarrollo humano para América Central 2009–2010</source>. <publisher-loc>Colombia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PNUD</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) ‘<article-title>Relationships between Future Orientation, Impulsive Sensation Seeking, and Risk Behavior among Adjudicated Adolescents</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Adolescent Research</source> <volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>428</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) ‘<article-title>Gangs</article-title>, <source>Mano Dura</source> and the New Urban Geography of Conflict in Central America’, <source>Development and Change</source> <volume>40</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>949</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Savenije</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Maras y barras</source>. <publisher-loc>San Salvador</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>FLACSO Programa El Salvador</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) ‘<article-title>The Adolescent Crack Dealer</article-title>’, <source>Journal of the American Academy of Psychoanalysis</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seelke</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Gangs in Central America</source>. <publisher-loc>Congressional Research Service. Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Library of Congress</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thornberry</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krohn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lizotte</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Gangs and Delinquency in Developmental Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC)</collab> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Crime and Development in Central America: Caught in the Crossfire</source>. <publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>United Nations</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC)</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>World Drug Report 2010</source>. <publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>United Nations</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>United States Agency for International Development (USAID)</collab> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Central America and Mexico Gangs Assessment</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>USAID</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Van Der Merwe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dawes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) ‘<article-title>Youth Violence</article-title>’, <source>Journal of Child and Adolescent Mental Health</source> <volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) ‘<article-title>School Dropout Risk Inventory</article-title>’, <comment>unpublished document</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vigil</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <source>Barrio Gangs</source>. <publisher-loc>Austin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Texas Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lambie</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) ‘<article-title>Sparking Up: Family, Behavioral and Empathy Factors in Adolescent Fire Setters</article-title>’, <source>American Journal of Forensic Psychology</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0020872812437227">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Washington Office on Latin America (WOLA)</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Community Based Responses to Youth Gang Violence in Central America and Central American Immigrant Communities in the United States</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WOLA</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>