<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">LUP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">splup</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lupus</journal-id>
<journal-title>Lupus</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0961-2033</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0962</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0961203311427550</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0961203311427550</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Antinuclear and antiphospholipid antibodies in patients with multiple sclerosis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Szmyrka-Kaczmarek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0961203311427550">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0961203311427550"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Pokryszko-Dragan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0961203311427550">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Pawlik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0961203311427550">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Gruszka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0961203311427550">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Korman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0961203311427550">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Podemski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0961203311427550">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wiland</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0961203311427550">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Szechinski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0961203311427550">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0961203311427550"><sup>1</sup>Department of Rheumatology and Internal Diseases, Wrocław Medical University, Poland; and <sup>2</sup>Department of Neurology, Wrocław Medical University, Poland</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0961203311427550">Magdalena Szmyrka-Kaczmarek, Department of Rheumatology and Internal Diseases, Wrocław Medical University, Ul. Borowska 213, 50-556 Wrocław, Poland Email: <email>magda_szmyrka@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>412</fpage>
<lpage>420</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s), 2011. Reprints and permissions: http://www.sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The prevalence of autoantibodies in multiple sclerosis (MS) patients and their clinical associations differ between various studies. This study investigated antiphospholipid and antinuclear antibodies in 85 patients with multiple sclerosis (MS) and clinically isolated syndrome (CIS) with regard to their association with demographic features, MS specific clinical features and symptoms of connective tissue diseases. Autoantibodies tested included antinuclear antibodies (ANA) with their specificities and anticardiolipin (aCL) and anti-beta-2-glycoprotein I (anti-β2GPI) antibodies.</p>
<p>Antinuclear antibodies were more prevalent in MS patients than in controls (63.5% vs. 3.3%; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) and in 19% of patients specific antinuclear antibodies were detected. Anti-β2GPI IgM antibodies were more frequent in MS patients than in the control group (20% vs. 3.3%; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). The frequency of anticardiolipin antibodies did not differ between MS patients and controls.</p>
<p>MS patients seropositive for ANA and extractable nuclear antigens (ENA) had significantly shorter disease duration than seronegative patients (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and a lower disability score (Expanded Disability Status Score; EDSS) (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Anti-β2GPI antibodies were more frequent in patients with secondary progressive MS (SP-MS) and specific ANA antibodies were more frequent in patients with clinically isolated syndrome (CIS) (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). The presence of autoantibodies was not associated with the predominant site of neurological involvement or the clinical features of connective tissue diseases.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>anti-beta2 glycoprotein I antibodies</kwd>
<kwd>anticardiolipin antibodies</kwd>
<kwd>antinuclear antibodies</kwd>
<kwd>connective tissue diseases</kwd>
<kwd>multiple sclerosis</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0961203311427550" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a chronic and multifocal demyelinating process which affects the central nervous system (CNS). It is mainly considered a T-cell-mediated autoimmune disorder, characterized by T-cell infiltration of the CNS, which initiates an inflammatory cascade and causes oligodendrocyte and microglia injury and myelin sheath destruction, accompanied by axonal injury. Recent studies, however, have pointed out the equally important role of B cells and humoral response in MS pathogenesis, on the basis of the detection of clonally expanded memory B cells and myelin-specific autoantibodies in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) and demyelinative lesions, as well as B-cell follicle-like structures in the brain meninges of MS patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0961203311427550">1</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0961203311427550">3</xref></sup> These discoveries have led to a new approach in the treatment of MS which uses B-cell-depleting agents, such as rituximab.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0961203311427550">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>As well as oligoclonal bands of immunoglobulins (directed against myelin-specific antigens) found in the CSF of MS patients, the presence of multiple non-organ-specific autoantibodies in their sera has also been described: among others, antinuclear (ANA) and antiphospholipid antibodies (aPL).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0961203311427550">5</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0961203311427550">11</xref></sup> Results published to date differ in the prevalence and specificity of these antibodies. Their presence seems to be associated with an increased autoimmune humoral response, but their significance in MS has not been fully elucidated. Some authors have reported a higher prevalence of certain types of aPL in MS and their association with specific clinical subtypes of the disease (especially with optic neuritis and spinal cord involvement).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0961203311427550">9</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0961203311427550">11</xref></sup> Antiphospholipid antibodies in MS patients have aroused special attention, as neurological symptoms of antiphospholipid syndrome may mimic certain clinical types of MS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0961203311427550">12</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0961203311427550">15</xref></sup></p>
<p>The main aim of our study was to assess the presence of antiphospholipid and antinuclear antibodies in patients with multiple sclerosis and to investigate their possible association with demographic variables, clinical features and the course of MS. A secondary aim was to investigate whether detected autoantibodies were associated with the clinical manifestation of connective tissue diseases possibly coexisting with MS.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec2-0961203311427550" sec-type="subjects|methods"><title>Patients and methods</title>
<p>The study group consisted of consecutive patients with either MS clinically defined according to McDonald’s criteria<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0961203311427550">16</xref></sup> or clinically isolated syndrome (CIS), who were under the care of the Outpatient Multiple Sclerosis Clinic at the Department of Neurology, Wrocław Medical University, over the years 2008–2009. The control group consisted of 30 healthy volunteers, matched for age and sex, with neither neurological nor connective tissue disease. All the subjects were enrolled after giving their informed consent to participate in the study. The study was carried out in accordance with the Helsinki protocol and was approved by the local bioethics committee.</p>
<sec id="sec3-0961203311427550"><title>Clinical assessment</title>
<p>The following clinical data were obtained on the basis of the patients’ medical records: age, sex, age at MS onset, duration of the disease, disease course (relapsing–remitting [RR-MS] or secondary progressive [SP-MS]), and annual exacerbation rate (AER) for those patients with RR-MS. On the basis of neurological examination, symptoms and signs of neurological deficit were established and the degree of disability was assessed using the Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0961203311427550">17</xref></sup> Progression of disability was assessed by means of the Multiple Sclerosis Severity Scale (MSSS).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0961203311427550">18</xref></sup></p>
<p>Patients were divided into subgroups according to the dominant symptoms of the neurological deficit, i.e. those presenting with: cerebral/hemispheric type (hemiparesis or tetraparesis with sensory disturbances), infratentorial type (signs of brainstem or cerebellar involvement), spinal syndrome with spastic paraparesis and bladder dysfunction, concomitant optic neuritis and multi-system involvement.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec4-0961203311427550"><title>Detection of autoantibodies</title>
<p>Sera of patients and controls were tested for the presence of antinuclear antibodies (ANA) and antiphospholipid antibodies (aPL), which included anticardiolipin antibodies (aCL) and anti-beta-2-glycoprotein I antibodies (anti-β2GPI).</p>
<p>ANA were detected by indirect immunofluorescence on Hep2 cells (EUROIMMUN, Germany), and the laboratory estimated cut-off titre of≥1:160 was considered positive. Using a commercially available immunoblot test (Recom Line ANA/ENA IgG, Microgen, Germany) according to the manufacturer’s instructions, sera positive for ANA were subsequently tested for anti-double-stranded DNA (anti-dsDNA) antibodies, anti-histone antibodies and antibodies against the following extractable nuclear antigens (ENA): anti-Ro/SS-A, anti-La/SS-B, anti-Sm, antibodies against complexes made of small nuclear ribonucleoprotein particles (anti-RNP), antibodies against proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA), and anti-Scl70 as well as anti-centromere antibodies (anti-CENP), anti-Jo1 and antibodies against ribosomal P proteins (anti-Rib P) of the IgG class.</p>
<p>Antiphospholipid antibodies, i.e. aCL antibodies of IgG and IgM subclasses and anti-β2GPI of IgG and IgM subclasses, were detected with the use of a commercially available enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (EUROIMMUN, Germany) with manufacturer-determined cut-off values of 20 GPL and MPL respectively.</p>
<p>In all the patients serological tests were performed either during remission (for CIS and RR-MS) or during the progressive phase (for SP-MS), at least 3 months after corticosteroids (administered because of a previous relapse) were tapered. None of the patients were being treated with immunosuppressive medications at the time of the tests. Fourteen subjects were concurrently treated with immunomodulating agents, i.e. with interferon β or with glatiramer acetate. Eight patients had received such treatment in the past but it had been terminated for various reasons at least 12 months before this study.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec5-0961203311427550"><title>Assessment for concomitant connective tissue diseases</title>
<p>All the patients were interviewed for individual and family histories of autoimmune disease.</p>
<p>A questionnaire was developed to screen for the symptoms of autoimmune systemic diseases (connective tissue diseases – CTD) or antiphospholipid syndrome (APS). It was divided into three sections. The first was focused on symptoms of arthritis and lupus (SLE) or lupus like syndrome, the second on symptoms of antiphospholipid syndrome and the third on symptoms of Sjögren syndrome (SjS). The detailed questionnaire is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0961203311427550">Figure 1</xref>.
<fig id="fig1-0961203311427550" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>A questionnaire screening for symptoms of connective tissue diseases or APS.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0961203311427550-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Patients were considered as having symptoms of arthritis if they had previously been given a diagnosis of arthritis or answered positively two questions dealing with arthritis (part A, question 1 and 2). Patients were considered as having symptoms of lupus or lupus like syndrome if they had previously been given a diagnosis of SLE or lupus like syndrome or gave positive answers to at least two questions from part A (other than or in addition to questions 1 and 2). Patients were considered as having symptoms of APS when they had previously been given a diagnosis of APS or answered positively at least two questions from part B. Patients were considered as having symptoms of Sjögren syndrome when they had previously been given a diagnosis of this syndrome or answered positively at least two questions from part C.</p>
<p>Patients seropositive and seronegative for each of the investigated autoantibodies were compared with regard to demographic variables (age and sex), MS-related clinical variables (age at disease onset, disease duration, disease course, degree of disability [EDSS] and progression of disability [MSSS]), dominant symptoms of neurological deficit, and features suggestive of concomitant connective tissue disease.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec6-0961203311427550"><title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Statistical analysis was carried out with the use of Statistica (StatSoft). <italic>p</italic> = 0.05 was considered the basic significance level. Comparisons of frequencies were performed using the χ<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0961203311427550">2</xref></sup> test. When the expected values of results were very low a Yates correction of this test was used. In certain cases, in view of the low number of observations, the Fisher exact test was also performed to assess the relationship between two factors. To examine the differences between two independent continuous variables the <italic>t</italic> test was used when possible. In other cases the Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic> test was applied. Pearson’s correlation coefficient was computed to detect the relationship between continuous normally distributed variables. If the normality assumption was not met the Spearman rank correlation coefficient was used.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec7-0961203311427550" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title>
<p>Eighty-five patients, 71 women and 14 men, of an average age of 38.5 years (minimum 18, maximum 62, SD 11.06) were enrolled onto the study. Seventy-four patients had clinically defined MS according to McDonald’s criteria. In 11 cases (13%) clinically isolated syndrome (CIS) was recognized. The average age at disease onset was 29 years (minimum 10, maximum 54, SD 9.93) and average disease duration was 8.73 years. In the group under study there were 62 patients (73%) with RR-MS, 12 patients (14%) with SP-MS and 11 patients (13%) with CIS.</p>
<p>EDSS score ranged from 1 to 9 (mean 3.31, SD 1.90). MSSS score ranged from 0 to 9.97 (mean 4.25, SD 2.71).</p>
<p>In terms of the dominant symptoms of neurological deficit, 25 patients (29%) presented with the cerebral/hemispheric type of MS, 32 (38%) with the infratentorial type, 23 (27%) with spinal syndrome, and five (6%) with concomitant optic neuritis and multi-system involvement. No patient presented with concomitant spinal cord and optic nerve involvement.</p>
<p>Patients’ characteristics are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0961203311427550">Table 1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="table1-0961203311427550" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics of the study group (MS and CIS patients)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0961203311427550" xlink:href="10.1177_0961203311427550-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th/>
<th>Patients <italic>n</italic> = 85</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Gender</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> Male</td>
<td>14 (16.5%)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td>71 (83.5%)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Mean age, years</td>
<td>38.5 (11)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Age at onset, years</td>
<td>28.8 (9.9)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Disease duration, years</td>
<td>8.73 (7.15)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>EDSS</td>
<td>3.31 (1.89)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>MSSS</td>
<td>4.25 (2.71)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Disease course:</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> CIS</td>
<td>11 (13%)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> RR-MS</td>
<td>62 (73%)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> SP-MS</td>
<td>12 (14%)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Clinical presentation:</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> Cerebral/hemispheric</td>
<td>25 (29%)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Spinal syndrome</td>
<td>23 (27%)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Infratentorial</td>
<td>32 (38%)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Optic neuritis</td>
<td>5 (6%)</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0961203311427550"><p>Age, age at onset, disease duration, EDSS and MSSS are represented as mean (standard deviation).</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0961203311427550"><p>CIS: clinically isolated syndrome, EDSS: Expanded Disability Status Scale, MSSS: Multiple Sclerosis Severity Scale, RR-MS: relapsing–remitting multiple sclerosis, SP-MS: secondary progressive multiple sclerosis</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<sec id="sec8-0961203311427550"><title>Autoantibodies</title>
<p>ANA were detected in 54 patients (63.5%) and in one control subject (3.3%), and this difference was statistically significant (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). ANA were detected in medium to high titres: in 41 patients (48%) ANA were positive at 1:320, in 12 patients (14%) at 1:1000, and in one patient (1%) at 1:3200.</p>
<p>In 16 (19%) patients ANA specificity could be defined. Anti-dsDNA antibodies were detected in three patients (3.5%) and anti-histones in four patients (4.7%). In 13 patients (15%), ANA were identified as antibodies against specific ENA: anti-Sm in six patients (7%), anti-RNP in four (4.7%), anti-Ro/SS-A (Ro 60 kD) in two (2.3%), anti-La/SS-B in one (1%), and anti-Rib P in one (1%). Five patients had more than one detectable specific autoantibody: one had concomitant anti-Ro/SS-A and anti-histones, one anti-dsDNA and anti-Sm, one anti-RNP and anti-histones, and two anti-RNP and anti-Sm.</p>
<p>Those MS patients seropositive for ANA had significantly shorter disease duration than seronegative patients (7.5 vs.11 years, <italic>p</italic> = 0.012). Similarly, patients positive for ENA had a significantly shorter disease duration (4.3 vs. 9.5 years; <italic>p</italic> = 0.011).</p>
<p>Patients with detectable ANA had a significantly lower EDSS score than seronegative patients – 2.95 vs. 3.95 (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Characteristics of ANA positive and negative patients are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0961203311427550">Table 2</xref>.
<table-wrap id="table2-0961203311427550" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of the clinical features in MS and CIS patients with regard to ANA status</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0961203311427550" xlink:href="10.1177_0961203311427550-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th/>
<th>ANA positive <italic>n</italic> = 54</th>
<th>ANA negative <italic>n</italic> = 31</th>
<th><italic>p</italic> value</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Gender</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> Male <italic>n</italic> = 14</td>
<td>7 (13%)</td>
<td>7 (22.6%)</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Female <italic>n</italic> = 71</td>
<td>47 (87%)</td>
<td>24 (77.4%)</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Mean age (years)</td>
<td>36.7</td>
<td>41.5</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Age at onset (years)</td>
<td>28.5</td>
<td>29.5</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Disease duration (years)</td>
<td>7.5</td>
<td>11</td>
<td><italic>p</italic> = 0.012</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>EDSS</td>
<td>2.95</td>
<td>3.95</td>
<td><italic>p</italic> = 0.045</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Disease course:</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> CIS</td>
<td>7 (12.9%)</td>
<td>4 (12.9%)</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> RR-MS</td>
<td>43 (79.6%)</td>
<td>19 (61.3%)</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> SP-MS</td>
<td>4 (7.4%)</td>
<td>8 (25.8%)</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Clinical presentation:</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> Cerebral/hemispheric</td>
<td>17 (31.5%)</td>
<td>8 (26%)</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Spinal syndrome</td>
<td>11 (20%)</td>
<td>12 (39%)</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Infratentorial</td>
<td>22 (41%)</td>
<td>10 (32%)</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Optic neuritis</td>
<td>4 (7.5%)</td>
<td>1 (3%)</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0961203311427550"><p>Data are mean or number and percentage. ANA: antinuclear antibodies, CIS: clinically isolated syndrome, EDSS: expanded disability status scale, RR-MS: relapsing–remitting multiple sclerosis, SP-MS: secondary progressive multiple sclerosis</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Antibodies against ENA were significantly more frequent in patients with CIS (36%) than in patients with clinically definite MS (RR-MS 14.5%, SP-MS 0%, <italic>p</italic> = 0.031) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0961203311427550">Table 3</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table3-0961203311427550" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Distribution of ENA antibodies in subgroups of patients divided according to disease course</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0961203311427550" xlink:href="10.1177_0961203311427550-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th/>
<th>ENA positive <italic>n</italic> = 13</th>
<th>ENA negative <italic>n</italic> = 72</th>
<th><italic>p</italic> value</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>CIS</td>
<td>4/11 (36%)</td>
<td>7/11 (64%)</td>
<td rowspan="3"><italic>p</italic> = 0.031</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>RR-MS</td>
<td>9/62 (14.5%)</td>
<td>53/62 (85.5%)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>SP-MS</td>
<td>0/12 (0%)</td>
<td>12/12 (100%)</td></tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0961203311427550"><p>CIS: clinically isolated syndrome, ENA: extractable nuclear antigens, RR-MS: relapsing–remitting multiple sclerosis, SP-MS: secondary progressive multiple sclerosis</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>aPL were detected in 19 patients (22%), aCL in five (5.9 %) patients: aCL IgM were positive in four (4.7%) and aCL IgG in one (1%). Seventeen (20%) patients were positive for anti-β2GPI IgM antibodies, and none had detectable anti-β2GPI IgG antibodies. The prevalence of aCL antibodies did not differ between MS patients and controls. The prevalence of anti-β2GPI IgM antibodies was significantly higher in MS patients (20%) than in the control group (3.3%) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.023). Anti-β2GPI antibodies were detected significantly more often in female patients (17/71 vs. 0/14) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.032). Patients positive and negative for aCL or anti-β2GPI did not differ in mean age, age at onset, disease duration, EDSS or MSSS.</p>
<p>There was no relationship between seropositivity for ANA and aPL, but there was a significant correlation between the presence of aCL IgM and anti-β2GPI IgM (<italic>p</italic> = 0.029).</p>
<p>There was a significant difference in the presence of anti-β2GPI IgM antibodies between patients with different disease courses – they were detected in 33% of patients with SP-MS, in 21% of patients with RR-MS and in none of the patients with CIS (<italic>p</italic> = 0.047). No such association was observed for ANA, anti-dsDNA, anti-β2GPI IgG or aCL antibodies. Characteristics of patients positive and negative for anti-β2GPI IgM antibodies are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0961203311427550">Table 4</xref>.
<table-wrap id="table4-0961203311427550" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of the clinical features in MS and CIS patients with regard to anti-b2GPI IgM status</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0961203311427550" xlink:href="10.1177_0961203311427550-table4.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th/>
<th>B2GP1 IgM positive <italic>n</italic> = 17</th>
<th>B2GPI IgM negative <italic>n</italic> = 68</th>
<th><italic>p</italic> value</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Gender</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = 0.032</td></tr>
<tr>
<td> Male <italic>n</italic> = 14</td>
<td>0 (0%)</td>
<td>14 (20%)</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td> Female <italic>n</italic> = 71</td>
<td>17 (100%)</td>
<td>54 (80%)</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Mean age (years)</td>
<td>39.5</td>
<td>38.2</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Age at onset (years)</td>
<td>28.4</td>
<td>28.9</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Disease duration (years)</td>
<td>10.32</td>
<td>8.33</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>EDSS</td>
<td>414</td>
<td>3.11</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Disease course:</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = 0.047</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>CIS <italic>n</italic> = 11</td>
<td>0 (0%)</td>
<td>11 (16%)</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>RR-MS <italic>n</italic> = 62</td>
<td>13 (76%)</td>
<td>49 (72%)</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>SP-MS <italic>n</italic> = 12</td>
<td>4 (33%)</td>
<td>8 (12%)</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Clinical presentation:</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Cerebral/hemispheric</td>
<td>4 (23.4%)</td>
<td>21 (31%)</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Spinal syndrome</td>
<td>3 (17.6%)</td>
<td>19 (28%)</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Infratentorial</td>
<td>10 (59%)</td>
<td>22 (32%)</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Optic neuritis</td>
<td>0 (0%)</td>
<td>5 (73.5%)</td>
<td>NS</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-0961203311427550"><p>Data expressed as mean or number and percentage. CIS: clinically isolated syndrome, EDSS: Expanded Disability Status Scale, RR-MS: relapsing–remitting multiple sclerosis, SP-MS: secondary progressive multiple sclerosis</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Mean MSSS was significantly higher in patients in whom at least one of the autoantibodies had been detected than in those with no detectable autoantibodies (mean 5.60 vs. 3.86 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.02).</p>
<p>There was no association between dominant symptoms of neurological deficit and the presence of autoantibodies. In particular, we found no association between either ANA or aPL and spinal cord involvement or optic neuritis.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec9-0961203311427550"><title>Assessment for concomitant connective tissue diseases</title>
<p>The questionnaire assessing symptoms of connective tissue diseases was completed by 74 patients. In the assessment of the results of the questionnaire, each section was first considered separately. Then the questionnaire was assessed as a whole, and was regarded as being answered ‘positively’ when at least one section was considered as having been answered positively. In the statistical analysis we tested the association of each group of antibodies tested (ANA, aCL and anti-β2GPI) with the results of the questionnaire as a whole, as well as with symptoms of each of the diseases screened for separately.</p>
<p>In general, 35% (26 out of 74) of patients responded positively to the questionnaire. Fifteen patients reported symptoms suggestive of arthritis and eight patients reported symptoms suggestive of SLE or SLE like disease; seven patients complained of symptoms of Sjögren’s syndrome and six patients reported symptoms suggestive of APS. No association was found between any of the antibodies tested and results of the questionnaire as a whole or any part of it.</p>
<p>Even MS patients with a high titre of ANA (&gt;1:1000) did not declare symptoms suggestive of connective tissue disease more often than ANA negative patients. There were also no such findings for patients with specific ENA antibodies. Presence of aPL in MS patients did not correlate with clinical features of antiphospholipid syndrome, such as obstetric morbidity or thromboembolic events.</p>
<p>Patients responding positively to the questionnaire had higher MSSS (mean 4.59) than patients giving negative responses (mean 3.16) (<italic>p</italic> = 0.32).</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec10-0961203311427550" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our results showed that ANA were frequently detected in patients with MS and correlated with shorter disease duration and a lower degree of disability. This may suggest that ANA are synthesized early in the course of MS and are associated with its inflammatory phase, reflecting general B-cell activation and humoral response predominant at that stage of the disease. It is not clear whether ANA exert any pathogenic effect on MS course. Lower EDSS in ANA positive patients might be indicative of a protective humoral response preventing neuronal injury, a concept described by Schwartz et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0961203311427550">19</xref></sup> although lower disability may be associated with a short duration of MS. It is worth noting that in 15% of patients ANA were detected in high titres (equal to or higher than 1:1000) and in 19% they could be identified as specific anti-chromatin or anti-ENA, mostly specific for SLE. The presence of these antibodies in our patients was not associated with any clinical symptoms of connective tissue disease. However, considering that their presence may antedate the clinical manifestations of such diseases, this subgroup would require further follow up. This refers in particular to those patients with CIS, frequently positive for specific ANA, whose presumed diagnosis of MS might be verified over time and perhaps turn out to be one of the connective tissue diseases with early neurological manifestation. It can be hypothesized as well that the presence of ANA is associated with certain pathological patterns of MS, as described by Luchinetti et al<italic>.</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0961203311427550">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0961203311427550">21</xref></sup> and reflects ongoing autoimmune stimulation by exposition of self antigens during oligodendrocyte apoptosis. Early apoptotic oligodendrocyte lesion has been postulated as an early event in all MS lesions,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0961203311427550">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0961203311427550">23</xref></sup> and ANA were detected mainly in patients with early disease.</p>
<p>Anti-β2GPI antibodies of the IgM subclass were significantly more prevalent in MS patients than in controls, and were associated with secondary progressive course of MS and female gender. Their presence in the later, secondary progressive stage of the disease may be indicative of a more chronic type of CNS injury, characteristic of the advanced phase of the disease. In contrast to ANA, anti-β2GPI antibodies were not associated with shorter disease duration or lower EDSS. There was also no relationship between the presence of anti-β2GPI antibodies and ANA, which may point to their differing roles in the disease process.</p>
<p>Our results confirm findings reported by several other authors. A high prevalence of ANA antibodies in MS patients has been reported by, among others, Roussel et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0961203311427550">6</xref></sup> (59%) and Tourbah et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0961203311427550">7</xref></sup> (26%). Although no association with early disease has been reported, most patients of the Roussel cohort were tested in early disease, at the time of diagnosis and before any disease modifying treatment was introduced.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0961203311427550">6</xref></sup></p>
<p>Earlier studies on the prevalence of aPL in MS focused mainly on aCL, and some authors reported their higher prevalence in MS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0961203311427550">11</xref></sup> Studies on the broad spectrum of aPL show varying results. Roussel et al. detected aPL in 32.6% of MS patients, with a similar prevalence of anti-β2GPI IgM (15.7%) and aCL IgG antibodies (21%).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0961203311427550">6</xref></sup> Anticardiolipin antibodies correlated with ANA and antibodies against myelin.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0961203311427550">6</xref></sup> Tourbah investigated only anticardiolipin antibodies and reported aCL of mainly IgG isotype in 6% of patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0961203311427550">7</xref></sup> Both authors found no association between aPL and disease course and no distinct clinical form of the disease.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0961203311427550">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0961203311427550">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Gaarg et al. reported a high prevalence of aPL (55%) in MS and CIS patients, with predominant anti<bold>-</bold>phosphatidylethanolamine (16%) and anticardiolipin (6%) antibodies, mainly of IgM isotype (77%).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0961203311427550">8</xref></sup> In contrast to our results, anti-β2GPI were found in only 2% of patients and ANA in only 3% of patients. Similarly to our observations, different autoantibodies were more prevalent in patients with CIS (74%), with predominant IgM antiphospholipid antibodies against phosphatidylethanolamine and phosphatidylserine. They reported the association of aPL with older age, longer disease duration and higher EDSS, but not with clinical features of antiphospholipid syndrome. As in our study, there was a trend toward a higher frequency of aPL in SP-MS compared with RR-MS. aPL were correlated with higher T2 lesion volume on MRI. No correlation was found with any specific clinical presentation of MS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0961203311427550">8</xref></sup></p>
<p>Bidot et al. reported the association of various aPL of the IgM subclass with disease relapses and the presence of active (gadolinium enhanced) MRI lesions in patients with RR-MS. The antibodies against factor VII/VIIa, phosphatidylcholine and phosphatidylserine correlated with burden of active lesions in MRI.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0961203311427550">24</xref></sup></p>
<p>Other studies on this subject did not confirm higher prevalence of aPL in MS. Sastre-Garriga et al., who analysed the largest unselected group of MS patients to date (<italic>n</italic> = 296), found neither a greater prevalence of aPL (anti-prothrombin, aCL and anti-β2GPI IgG and IgM) in MS than in the general population nor a correlation of aPL with specific clinical features of MS or clinical symptoms of antiphospholipid syndrome.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0961203311427550">25</xref></sup> Their results on aCL prevalence in MS have been confirmed by Heinzlef et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0961203311427550">26</xref></sup></p>
<p>We found no correlation of ANA or aPL presence with distinct clinical features of MS. Some authors have suggested that optic neuritis, transverse myelitis and cerebellar syndrome are more common among aPL positive MS patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0961203311427550">9</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0961203311427550">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0961203311427550">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0961203311427550">28</xref></sup> It should be remembered, however, that the MS classification used in these studies was based on the older diagnostic criteria and that patients with neuromyelitis optica and acute disseminated encephalomyelitis (ADEM) might have been included in the studied groups. Some of these studies comprised mainly patients with atypical MS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0961203311427550">11</xref></sup> After the exclusion of such frontier patients, suggestive of another neurological condition, the majority of authors have failed to link autoantibodies to any specific clinical features of MS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0961203311427550">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0961203311427550">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0961203311427550">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0961203311427550">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0961203311427550">29</xref></sup></p>
<p>The influence of disease-modifying therapies used in MS upon the presence of autoantibodies should be taken into account. None of our patients was being treated with immunosuppressive agents at the time the tests were performed, and a time frame of at least 3 months was kept to minimize the influence of corticosteroids upon the immunological profile of the patients. As for interferon (IFN)β and glatiramer acetate, only three patients being treated with these medications were positive for ENA, and two who had been treated with IFNβ in the past were positive for anti-β2GP IgM. The possibility of developing autoimmune diseases as an adverse effect of treatment with IFNβ has been discussed, but it is assumed that the presence of autoantibodies is not associated with the immunomodulating activity of IFNβ, or with the effectiveness of this therapy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0961203311427550">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0961203311427550">31</xref></sup> Overall, the presence of autoantibodies in MS seems to be independent of disease-modifying treatment.</p>
<p>The shortcomings of our study are the relatively low numbers of patients in subgroups, and the assessment of only two subtypes of antiphospholipid antibodies. We did not include the test for lupus anticoagulant in our analysis, but we used activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT) as a screening test in some of our patients and found it normal (data not shown). Thus, a broader profile of antibodies tested and a larger group of patients differing in course or stage of disease might be included in further studies. Another aspect worth investigating would be the analysis of ANA and aPL prevalence during relapses and remission of MS. We did not study patients during disease exacerbations, and literature data suggest a higher prevalence of certain types of aPL of predominantly IgM subclass in such patients. This finding, if confirmed, might allow better insight into the pathogenesis of both MS and APS with neurological involvement. Another direction for further study might involve the evaluation of the responsiveness of MS patients, seropositive for ANA or aPL, to certain treatment strategies, especially those based on B-cell depletion.</p>
<p>In conclusion, we found that ANA were frequent in patients with MS and CIS and were associated with shorter disease duration and lower disability scores. Anti-β2GPI IgM antibodies were detected more often in MS patients, mainly those in the secondary progressive phase of the disease, than in controls. There were no other relationships between ANA or aPL and MS-related clinical variables. Presence of autoantibodies was not associated with any clinical features of connective tissue diseases.</p></sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec11-0961203311427550"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research was supported by the Wrocław Medical University Research Grant (Grant number 1731/2008).</p></sec>
<sec id="sec12-0961203311427550"><title>Conflict of interest</title>
<p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>We acknowledge Katarzyna Grzebyk for the statistical analysis of data and Dr Marta Mosca for valuable advice on manuscript preparation.</p></ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0961203311427550"><label>1.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraussen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrolix</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Martinez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>B cell characterization and reactivity analysis in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Autoimmun Rev</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>654</fpage>–<lpage>658</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0961203311427550"><label>2.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franciotta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lolli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Serafini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aloisi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>B cells and multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>852</fpage>–<lpage>858</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0961203311427550"><label>3.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Archelos</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Storch</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartung</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of B cells and autoantibodies in MS</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>694</fpage>–<lpage>706</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0961203311427550"><label>4.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Waubant</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>B-cell depletion with rituximab in relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>358</volume>: <fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>688</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0961203311427550"><label>5.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spadaro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Amendolea</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzucconi</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Autoimmunity in multiple sclerosis: a study of wide spectrum of autoantibodies</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0961203311427550"><label>6.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roussel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jauberteau</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and clinical significance of antiphospholipid antibodies in multiple sclerosis: a study of 89 patients</article-title>. <source>J Autoimmun</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>265</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0961203311427550"><label>7.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tourbah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Clapin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gout</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Systemic autoimmune features and multiple sclerosis. A 5-year follow up</article-title>. <source>Arch Neurol</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>517</fpage>–<lpage>521</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0961203311427550"><label>8.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaarg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zivadinov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramanathan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical and MRI correlates of autoreactive antibodies in multiple sclerosis patients</article-title>. <source>J Neuroimmunol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>187</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0961203311427550"><label>9.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ijdo</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti-Kelly</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-phospholipid antibodies in patients with multiple sclerosis and MS-like illnesses: MS or APS?</article-title> <source>Lupus</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0961203311427550"><label>10.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fukazawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Moriwaka</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tashiro</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anticardiolipin antibodies in Japanese patients with multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>184</fpage>–<lpage>189</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0961203311427550"><label>11.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karussis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Leker</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashkenazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramsky</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A subgroup of multiple sclerosis patients with anticardiolipin antibodies and unusual clinical manifestations: do they represent a new nosological entity?</article-title> <source>Ann Neurol</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0961203311427550"><label>12.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>GRV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The antiphospholipid syndrome and ‘multiple sclerosis’</article-title>. <source>Lupus</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0961203311427550"><label>13.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>D’Cruz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>GRV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multiple sclerosis, neuropsychiatric lupus and antiphospholipid syndrome: where do we stand?</article-title> <source>Rheumatology (Oxford)</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>434</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0961203311427550"><label>14.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Brey</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Non-stroke neurological syndromes associated with antiphospholipid antibodies: evaluation of clinical and experimental studies</article-title>. <source>Lupus</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>514</fpage>–<lpage>517</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0961203311427550"><label>15.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuadrado</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Khamashta</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballesteros</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Can neurologic manifestations of Hughes (antiphospholipid) syndrome be distinguished from multiple sclerosis? Analysis of 27 patients and review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Lupus</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0961203311427550"><label>16.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Compston</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Edan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Recommended diagnostic criteria for multiple sclerosis: guidelines from the International Panel on the diagnosis of multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0961203311427550"><label>17.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurtzke</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rating neurologic impairment in multiple sclerosis: an expanded disability status scale (EDSS)</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>1983</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>1444</fpage>–<lpage>1452</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0961203311427550"><label>18.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roxburgh</surname><given-names>RHSR</given-names></name><name><surname>Seaman</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Masterman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multiple Sclerosis Severity Score. Using disability and disease duration to rate disease severity</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>1144</fpage>–<lpage>1151</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0961203311427550"><label>19.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kipnis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multiple sclerosis as a by-product of the failure to sustain protective autoimmunity: a paradigm shift</article-title>. <source>Neuroscientist</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0961203311427550"><label>20.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luchinetti</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Reingold</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Eden</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multiple sclerosis – lessons from neuropathology</article-title>. <source>Semin Neurol</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0961203311427550"><label>21.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luchinetti</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruck</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The pathology of multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Neurol Clin</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0961203311427550"><label>22.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Prineas</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Relapsing and remitting multiple sclerosis: pathology of the newly forming lesion</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>458</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0961203311427550"><label>23.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The pathology of multiple sclerosis: a paradigm shift</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Neurol</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>242</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0961203311427550"><label>24.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bidot</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Horstman</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jy</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical and neuroimaging correlates of antiphospholipid antibodies in multiple sclerosis: a preliminary study</article-title>. <source>BMC Neurol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0961203311427550"><label>25.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sastre-Garriga</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Reverter</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Font</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tintoré</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Espinosa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Montalban</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anticardiolipin antibodies are not a useful screening tool in a nonselected large group of patients with multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0961203311427550"><label>26.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinzlef</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Weill</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Johanet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anticardiolipin antibodies in patients with multiple sclerosis do not represent a subgroup of patients according to clinical, familial and biological characteristics</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>647</fpage>–<lpage>649</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0961203311427550"><label>27.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukazawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Visual function in patients with optic neuritis associated with acute transverse myelopathy in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Jpn J Ophthalmol</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>290</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0961203311427550"><label>28.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of serum anti-phospholipid antibodies in patients with multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Tohoku J Exp Med</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>178</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0961203311427550"><label>29.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cordoliani</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Michon-Pasturel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Arvieux</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>[Multiple sclerosis and antiphospholipid antibodies: study of 62 consecutive patients]</article-title>. <source>Rev Med Interne</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>635</fpage>–<lpage>639</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0961203311427550"><label>30.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colosimo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozilli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Frontoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>No increase of serum autoantibodies during therapy with recombinant human interferon-b-1a in relapsing remitting multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>372</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0961203311427550"><label>31.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciccarelli</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagnato</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mainero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antinuclear antibodies and response to IFN-β therapy in relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>