<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjic</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Intensive Care Med</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Intensive Care Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0885-0666</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1525-1489</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0885066611402165</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0885066611402165</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Analytic Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Arrhythmias in the Coronary Care Unit</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Badhwar</surname>
<given-names>Nitish</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0885066611402165">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0885066611402165"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kusumoto</surname>
<given-names>Fred</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0885066611402165">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goldschlager</surname>
<given-names>Nora</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0885066611402165">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0885066611402165">
<label>1</label>Section of Electrophysiology, Division of Cardiology, Department of Medicine, University of California, San Francisco, CA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0885066611402165">
<label>2</label>Electrophysiology and Pacing Service, Division of Cardiology, Department of Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville FL, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0885066611402165">
<label>3</label>University of California, Cardiology Division, Department of Medicine, San Francisco General Hospital, San Francisco CA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0885066611402165">Nitish Badhwar, Section of Electrophysiology, Division of Cardiology, University of California, San Francisco, 500 Parnassus Ave, MUE-431, San Francisco, CA 94143, USA. Email: <email>Badhwar@medicine.ucsf.edu</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>267</fpage>
<lpage>289</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>7</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>16</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>23</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Symptomatic sustained cardiac arrhythmias are frequently observed in in the coronary care unit and often lead to hemodynamic compromise, especially in the presence of multisystem disease. The predominant arrhythmias noted in intensive care units are tachyarrhythmias, particularly atrial fibrillation and flutter, and ventricular tachycardia. Bradycardias, arguably less life-threatening than tachyarrhythmias, can arise from sinus node dysfunction or atrioventricular conduction block; transient vagally-mediated bradycardias are frequently encountered as well. Prompt diagnosis of the patient with tachycardia is critical as treatment depends on the accurate diagnosis of tachycardia mechanism. The electrocardiogram remains the most important diagnostic tool for the evaluation of both wide and narrow complex tachycardia. The electrocardiographic diagnosis of wide complex tachycardia is based on evaluation of atrioventricular relationship and QRS morphology while the diagnosis of narrow complex tachycardia is based on the location and morphology of P waves. It is important for critical care specialists to understand the principles of cardiac arrhythmia diagnosis and remain current with the recent advances in the pharmacologic and non-pharmacologic management of patients with arrhythmias. </p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>arrhythmia</kwd>
<kwd>bradycardia</kwd>
<kwd>supraventricular tachycardias</kwd>
<kwd>ventricular tachycardia</kwd>
<kwd>cardiac intensive care</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>September/October 2012</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0885066611402165">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The Coronary Care Unit, developed as an entity in the 1960s, revolutionized diagnosis and treatment in patients with acute myocardial infarction (MI) and led to the identification and importance of cardiac arrhythmia diagnosis, characterization, prognosis, and management. While its place in today’s medical milieu has undergone substantial changes, with fewer patients admitted for acute coronary syndromes in this era of percutaneous interventions and aggressive medical therapies, its role as an intensive care unit that manages all patients with cardiovascular disease remains. Moreover, as both pharmacologic and nonpharmacologic therapies for cardiac arrhythmias continue to evolve, its role as an arrhythmia-monitoring critical care unit has likely increased.</p>
<p>It is imperative that all critical care specialists, including cardiologists, fully understand the principles of cardiac arrhythmia diagnosis and management strategies. This review focuses on arrhythmias seen in today’s coronary care units in all patients, but applies also to hospital units that are designated as intensive care or critical care units. As our recognition and understanding of cardiac arrhythmias advances, their complexity increases, making their recognition and approach to management ever more relevant.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0885066611402165">
<title>Bradycardias</title>
<sec id="section3-0885066611402165">
<title>Mechanisms</title>
<sec id="section4-0885066611402165">
<title>Sinus node dysfunction</title>
<p>In sinus node dysfunction, normal automaticity function of the sinus node is absent. There are several ECG manifestations of sinus node dysfunction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0885066611402165">Figure 1</xref>). The most common finding that raises concern among clinicians is a sinus pause. This is commonly observed after termination of an atrial tachycardia such as fibrillation or flutter, where it is part of the bradycardia-tachycardia syndrome. Sinus pauses often occur abruptly, during normal sinus rhythm, where they may represent type I or type II sinoatrial block. A junctional rhythm is another ECG manifestation of sinus node dysfunction. In this case, abnormally slow sinus node automaticity leads to the emergence of an atrioventricular (AV) junctional focus (an escape focus) that “drives” the heart rate. In junctional rhythms P waves will not be observed preceding the QRS complexes. If a subsidiary site within the atria (usually in the low right atrium) rather than the AV junction has a faster intrinsic “pacemaker” rate, an inverted or biphasic P wave preceding the QRS complexes will be seen in the inferior ECG leads.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Some ECG manifestations of sinus node dysfunction. Top: An episode of atrial fibrillation terminates with a pause before sinus activity occurs. Middle: The sinus node abruptly stops firing, resulting in the absence of P waves. In this case, neither an atrial nor a junctional escape focus takes over and the patient develops a ventricular rhythm (wide QRS complexes occurring at a slow rate without preceding P waves). Bottom: An ectopic atrial site other than the sinus node (notice the low amplitude P wave in lead II) “drives” the heart, due in this instance to sinus bradycardia; the ectopic atrial rhythm is thus an escape rhythm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0885066611402165">
<title>Atrioventricular block</title>
<p>The atrioventricular (AV) node and the His bundle normally form the pathway for conduction of electrical activity from the atria to the ventricles. Disease processes that affect these regions can lead to abnormal AV conduction patterns. Electrocardiographically abnormal AV conduction is defined by the relationship between atrial and ventricular activity. In first-degree AV block, a 1:1 relationship between atrial activity (P waves) and ventricular activity (QRS complexes) is maintained. However, conduction is delayed, leading to an abnormally prolonged PR interval. In second-degree AV block, some, but not all, P waves lead to QRS complexes because of intermittent block of AV conduction. Second-degree AV block is further subclassified into Type I 2° AV block, where gradual delay in AV conduction, manifested by progressive prolongation of the PR interval is observed before a nonconducted P wave occurs, resulting in the absence of a QRS complex, and Type II 2° AV block in which the PR interval remains fairly constant both before and after the nonconducted P waves and absent QRS complex. It is important to note that transient type I or type II 2° AV block can be a normal finding at night due to the normal increase in parasympathetic tone during these hours. This “vagotonic” AV block is almost always accompanied by a slowing of sinus rate prior to the nonconducted P wave(s); because the sinus rate is not constant, this type of AV block is not a true type I or II second-degree AV block and it has no prognostic significance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0885066611402165">Figure 2</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0885066611402165">Figure 3</xref> shows another common condition that is interpreted as abnormal second-degree AV block. In this case, every third P wave is premature (note the deformation of the T waves) and is associated with block in the AV node due to its prematurity and decremental conduction within the AV node. Advanced AV block exists where 3 or more P waves fail to conduct to the ventricle and is always abnormal. Advanced AV block should be distinguished from third-degree (complete) AV block in which no P waves conduct to the ventricles; in complete AV block, therefore, AV dissociation is present.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Example of vagotonic AV block due to increased parasympathetic tone. Notice that the P-P intervals gradually increase (due to the effect of increased parasympathetic tone on the sinus node) prior to the nonconducted P wave. Note also the variation in the PR intervals, also due to changing vagal tone. Vagotonic AV block is of no clinical consequence, even if prolonged pauses in rhythm occur.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Nonconducted premature atrial depolarizations (note the deformities of the T waves in which they are present), mimicking sinus block with pauses. Adapted with permission from: Kusumoto FM. ECG Interpretation: From Pathophysiology to Clinical Application. Springer Publishing, New York NY 2009.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>From a clinical standpoint, it is important to determine whether the site of AV block is at the level of the AV node or His bundle, or infra-His, within the fascicles. Block within the His bundle or below can lead to episodes of profound bradycardia due to both the slow automatic firing rate and also the inherent unreliability of pacemaker activity (automaticity) of Purkinje-ventricular tissue. Block within the His bundle is likely if advanced AV block is associated with a narrow, normal-appearing QRS complex; block distal to the His bundle is likely if a wide QRS complex, indicating bundle branch disease is present. Interestingly, the presence of severe 1° AV block (PR interval &gt; 0.30 s) is more often associated with block within the AV node. AV block with an AV ratio of 2:1 can indicate either an AV nodal or subjunctional site of block, and changing the AV conduction ratio is usually diagnostic of the site of block. If the PR interval of the conducted P waves is prolonged and the QRS complexes are narrow, AV nodal block is expected, whereas if the PR interval of the conducted P waves is normal and the QRS complexes wide, subjunctional block is expected to be present. Changing the AV conduction ratio by intravenous atropine or exercise, both of which enhance AV nodal conduction, usually clarifies the site of block and therefore the clinical importance of the block.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0885066611402165">
<title>Bradycardias in Specific Clinical Conditions</title>
<sec id="section8-0885066611402165">
<title>Coronary Artery Disease</title>
<p>Myocardial ischemia and infarction are associated with bradycardia in 3 clinically distinct time periods: (1) early, within the first 4 hours from the onset of symptoms, (2) later, approximately 24 hours after onset of symptoms, and (3) with coronary artery reperfusion. During the early period, bradycardia can be due to either sinus node dysfunction or AV conduction abnormalities. Bradycardia is most commonly observed in the setting of inferior wall MI, with or without posterior wall or right ventricular involvement. Sinus bradycardia, sometimes with associated AV nodal rhythms, develops in up to 40% to 60% of patients with an inferior wall MI.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0885066611402165">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0885066611402165"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0885066611402165"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0885066611402165">4</xref></sup> Abnormal AV conduction occurs less frequently, and is present in 10% to 25% of patients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0885066611402165">Figure 4</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0885066611402165">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0885066611402165"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0885066611402165"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0885066611402165">4</xref></sup> Both sinus node dysfunction and AV block occurring during this first period is traditionally thought to be mediated by enhanced vagal tone (Bezold Jarisch reflex) due to stimulation of vagal efferents in the posterior left ventricle. This putative mechanism is supported by the observation that atropine is often effective for increasing the sinus rate or alleviating AV block. However, an angiographic study has found that early episodes of bradycardia are more commonly associated with proximal lesions (21%) rather than distal lesions (3%) of the right coronary artery, suggesting that ischemia to the AV node, due to reduced flow via the AV nodal artery, may also be an important contributing mechanism.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0885066611402165">1</xref></sup>
</p>
<fig id="fig4-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Patient with an inferior wall ST segment elevation myocardial infarction. Complete atrioventricular block is present with P waves (*) best seen in lead II that do not conduct to the ventricles (the QRS complexes are independent of P-wave activity). The QRS complexes are narrow, suggesting a focus of origin in the AV node or His bundle. Adapted with permission from: Kusumoto FM. ECG Interpretation: From Pathophysiology to Clinical Application. Springer Publishing, New York NY 2009.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Atrioventricular block, usually occurring within the AV node or, more rarely, the His bundle, can also develop after 24 hours. This second peak in bradycardic rhythms appears to be due to myocardial tissue edema and is usually not reversible with administration of atropine although aminophylline has been found to be useful in some patients. If, during an inferior wall MI, AV block develops during this later time period, it can often persist for prolonged periods of time (up to 3-10 days) but will eventually normalize. Several older studies have found that the development of complete heart block is associated with a higher rate of in-hospital complications and mortality (20% vs 4%) although the posthospitalization prognosis after inferior wall MI appears to be similar to those patients who do not develop complete heart block.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0885066611402165">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0885066611402165">3</xref></sup>
</p>
<p>Advanced or complete AV block can also occur in the setting of an acute anterior wall MI although it is much less common. In the recently published Trandolapril Cardiac Evaluation Trial (TRACE), complete heart block developed in 2.5% of patients with an anterior wall MI, compared to 9.4% of patients with an inferior wall MI.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0885066611402165">5</xref></sup> Development of AV block is associated with larger MIs and is therefore associated with a more unfavorable long-term prognosis, with a 4-fold increase in 30-day mortality. Evaluation of a large Medicare database of more than 100 000 patients who suffered an MI revealed that the development of AV block was associated with a worse prognosis in patients with either inferior wall or anterior wall MI, but that 1-year mortality was actually lower in those patients with an inferior MI (17% relative risk reduction) and higher in those patients with an anterior wall MI (15% increase in relative risk).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0885066611402165">6</xref></sup>
</p>
<p>The third distinct clinical period associated with bradycardia during MI is during reperfusion. This leads to accelerated ventricular rhythm and is discussed in the section of <italic>Tachycardia</italic>.</p>
<p>
<italic>Treatment</italic>. Management of bradycardia during MI depends on the clinical situation and the hemodynamic status of the patient. Temporary pacing can be considered in any situation that the clinician feels that bradycardia is contributing to hemodynamic compromise.</p>
<p>The recent ACC/AHA/HRS 2008 Guidelines for Device-Based Therapy for Cardiac Rhythm Abnormalities have provided recommendations for the use of permanent pacing, including during MI, and are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0885066611402165">Table 1</xref>
.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0885066611402165">7</xref></sup> It is important for the clinician to remember that clinical conditions will dictate the appropriate implantable device for a patient being considered for permanent cardiac pacing. In patients with persistent AV block, cardiac resynchronization therapy may be an important adjunctive therapy for heart-failure symptoms and reduced left ventricular function; implantable cardiac defibrillators for treatment of possible future ventricular arrhythmias have not been shown to be beneficial if performed early after MI.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0885066611402165">8</xref></sup>
</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Class I Indications for Permanent Pacing in the Coronary Care Unit<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0885066611402165">a</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0885066611402165" xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Condition</th>
<th>Notes</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Myocardial infarction</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Persistent and symptomatic 2° or 3° AV block</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
<td>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Similar to recommendations for any type of AV block</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Persistent 2° AV block with alternating bundle-branch block or 3° infranodal AV block</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
<td>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>No symptoms are required</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Recommendation based on poor prognosis with infranodal AV block</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>May be difficult to determine the site of block</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Transient advanced 2° or 3° infranodal AV block and associated bundle branch block</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
<td>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>No symptoms are required</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Recommendation based on poor prognosis with infranodal AV block</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>May be difficult to determine the site of block</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Postsurgical</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>2° or 3° AV block not expected to resolve after cardiac surgery</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
<td>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>No symptoms are required</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Final decision left to “physician’s discretion”</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Persistent inappropriate or symptomatic bradycardia not expected to resolve after cardiac transplant</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
<td>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Based on poor prognosis associated with sinus node dysfunction after cardiac transplant</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Less common with new surgical techniques</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0885066611402165">
<p>
<sup>a</sup> Adapted from Ref 7.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0885066611402165">
<title>Postsurgical</title>
<p>Bradycardia is associated with both percutaneous procedures and open-heart cardiac surgical procedures. Most bradycardic rhythms are due to injury to the region near the AV conduction axis—AV node and His bundle. Alcohol septal ablation in patients with hypertrophic obstructive cardiomyopathy is associated with an incidence of complete AV block in up to 50% to 60% of patients but usually resolves within the first 24 hours.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0885066611402165">9</xref></sup> New intraventricular conduction blocks also develop in approximately 60% of patients; permanent cardiac pacing is required in approximately 15% of patients after alcohol septal ablation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0885066611402165">9</xref></sup> It has been postulated that infarction of the region supplied by the first septal perforator of the left anterior descending coronary artery is the underlying cause. Probably due to a similar mechanism, a “jailed” septal perforator has also been implicated as a cause of AV block occurring during percutaneous revascularization procedures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0885066611402165">10</xref></sup> Percutaneous aortic valve replacement has been reported to be associated with a 50% incidence of left bundle branch block and a 20% incidence of complete AV block requiring permanent pacing.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0885066611402165">11</xref></sup>
</p>
<p>Cardiac surgical procedures that involve anatomic regions near the AV node and penetrating His bundle region are similarly associated with development of AV block. In a recent retrospective study of 214 patients undergoing aortic valve surgery, 15 patients (7.2%) required implantation of a permanent pacemaker.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0885066611402165">12</xref></sup> Clinical variables associated with increased risk for the development of AV block included preoperative first-degree AV block (HR: 12.5) and combined aortic and mitral valve surgery (HR: 11.5). In another large retrospective study of 4694 valve surgeries from a single center, preprocedural right bundle branch block (odds ratio [OR], 3.6; 95% confidence interval [CI], 2.3-5.7) and multivalve surgery that included the tricuspid valve (OR, 3.7; 95% CI, 2.3-6.1) were the strongest predictors for postsurgical implantation of a permanent pacemaker.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0885066611402165">13</xref></sup> Interestingly, in a series of patients who had permanent pacemakers implanted after cardiac surgery, approximately 40% became nondependent on their pacemaker during followup.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0885066611402165">14</xref></sup> The most important predictor for the requirement of long-term pacing was the presence of complete AV block. Atrioventricular block is more common after mitral valve surgery. In a retrospective series of 391 patients undergoing mitral valve replacement or repair, postoperative AV block occurred in 23.5% of 391 patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0885066611402165">15</xref></sup> The most common conduction disorder was first-degree AV block (70/391); second-degree AV block was observed in 5/391 and complete heart block in 4% of patients (17/391). Postoperative AV block after ventricular septal defect repair was significantly less at approximately 1%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0885066611402165">16</xref></sup>
</p>
<p>It is important to acknowledge the variable natural history of AV block after cardiac surgery.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0885066611402165">17</xref></sup> In fact, in the recommendations for permanent cardiac pacing in published guidelines (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0885066611402165">Table 1</xref>), it is explicitly stated that “…the decision for permanent pacing is at the physician’s discretion” in postoperative patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0885066611402165">7</xref></sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0885066611402165">
<title>Drugs</title>
<p>A number of medications can be associated with bradycardia. Cardiac drugs with rate slowing properties such as digoxin (acting through vagal mechanisms), calcium channel blockers (other than dihydropyridines), and β-blockers are the most common cause of drug-related bradycardia. In the critical care environment, the most commonly observed scenario is the patient with atrial fibrillation in whom diltiazem or β-blockers are used for the control of ventricular rate. When the atrial fibrillation terminates, a prolonged pause may be observed, due to overdrive suppression of the sinus node or to exacerbation of preexisting sinus node dysfunction. This pause in itself is not an indication for permanent or temporary cardiac pacing. Transient suppression of the sinus node after atrial fibrillation terminates is common (brady-tachy syndrome) and in the critical care situation the pause can be very prolonged since drugs used to slow AV node conduction also suppress sinus node automaticity.</p>
<p>Amiodarone is the most commonly prescribed oral antiarrhythmic medication in the United States and can also cause bradycardia. In large studies evaluating the use of amiodarone in clinical practice, symptomatic bradycardia (due to both sinus bradycardia and AV block) developed in approximately 2% to 10% of patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0885066611402165">18</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0885066611402165"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0885066611402165">20</xref></sup> In a long-term cohort study of nearly 9000 patients, amiodarone use was associated with a 2-fold increase in the risk for permanent pacemaker implant.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0885066611402165">20</xref></sup>
</p>
<p>Intravenous amiodarone has emerged as first-line therapy for many patients with significant ventricular arrhythmias. Although intravenous amiodarone is useful for slowing AV conduction in patients with atrial fibrillation and systolic dysfunction, when used to treat ventricular arrhythmias, profound bradycardia is infrequent.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0885066611402165">21</xref></sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0885066611402165">
<title>Metabolic/Hypothermia</title>
<p>Hyperkalemia can be associated with AV block, but the most common and well-described rhythm is a slow wide QRS rhythm which originates in the sinus node, despite the absence of P waves representing atrial depolarization due in turn to the sensitivity of atrial myocytes to the effects of hyperkalemia. This rhythm is called “sino-ventricular conduction,” reflecting its origin in the sinus node.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0885066611402165">22</xref></sup> The QRS complexes are wide, reflecting the effects of hyperkalemia on the Purkinje conduction system.</p>
<p>Mild to moderate hypothermia at 32°C to 35°C has emerged as an important treatment for postischemic postarrhythmic neurologic injury and is now commonly used in the critical care setting.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0885066611402165">23</xref></sup> Sinus bradycardia with a heart rate of 45 to 55 bpm is a normal heart rate when the core temperature falls to 33°C. In addition, slowed AV conduction can lead to prolongation of the PR interval, and slowed intraventricular conduction leads to QRS widening,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0885066611402165">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0885066611402165">24</xref></sup> not to be confused with the Osborn wave characteristic of hypothermia. In a small pilot study that evaluated the use of hypothermia during primary angioplasty for acute MI, significant bradycardia requiring temporary cardiac pacing was observed in 17% of patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0885066611402165">23</xref></sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0885066611402165">
<title>Infection</title>
<p>Conduction abnormalities (usually AV block) are observed in 1% to 15% of patients with infective endocarditis and usually represent periannular extension of the infection. The development of new AV block has a positive predictive value of 66% for the presence of a periannular abscess.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0885066611402165">25</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0885066611402165"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0885066611402165">27</xref></sup> Transesophageal echocardiography is the best modality for identifying a developing abscess and should be considered in a patient with endocarditis and the development of evidence for AV conduction abnormalities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0885066611402165">27</xref></sup>
</p>
<p>Lyme disease can be associated with cardiac involvement during the first few months after the tick bite and subsequent infection with the <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> spirochete in approximately 4% to 10% of patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0885066611402165">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0885066611402165">29</xref></sup> Complete heart block usually at the level of the AV node is the most common manifestation of Lyme carditis although second-degree and first-degree AV block can also be observed. Usually, the heart block will resolve and permanent pacing is required in very few cases although prolonged support with temporary pacing is sometimes required.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0885066611402165">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0885066611402165">29</xref></sup> Acute rheumatic fever and acute hemorrhagic fever have also been associated with AV block probably due to the associated carditis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0885066611402165">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0885066611402165">31</xref></sup> In both of these conditions, AV block usually resolves and permanent pacing is rarely required.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0885066611402165">
<title>Management</title>
<p>When treating patients with bradycardia in the critical care setting, it is important to remember that the presence of symptoms or hemodynamic decompensation, rather than heart rate or ECG findings per se, is the principle driver for treatment. Treatment of bradycardia due to reversible causes such as hypothermia, hyperkalemia or specific drugs is directed at the primary causes. Once the metabolic abnormalities have been corrected, the bradycardia usually resolves.</p>
<p>Once any offending agents have been discontinued, bradycardia is usually treated with intravenous atropine (0.5-2.0 mg) or isoproterenol (1-4 μg/min) in appropriate patients (most of them without heart disease). It is important to note that bradycardia due to hyperkalemia is often unresponsive to atropine.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0885066611402165">32</xref></sup> Finally, although pharmacologic measures can be effective for transient episodes of bradycardia, if heart rate support is required for a more prolonged period, transvenous pacing is usually required.</p>
<p>Temporary pacing can be performed using transcutaneous electrodes or transvenous electrodes (once central vascular access has been achieved). With transcutaneous pacing large body surface electrodes are placed in the anterior-posterior position or the apical-anterolateral position. Current is increased until ventricular capture is achieved. Musculoskeletal stimulation and patient discomfort usually precludes long-term use of transcutaneous pacing; moreover, transcutaneous pacing is not stable over time, being affected by changing thoracic impedance and alterations in resistances at the skin, muscle, bone, and lung.</p>
<p>Temporary transvenous pacing is normally performed via a balloon-tipped catheter placed in the right ventricle from the right internal jugular vein or a femoral vein. The morphology of the paced QRS complex can provide important clues as to the location of the temporary pacing electrodes. Pacing from the right ventricle will typically lead to a paced QRS complex having a left bundle branch block morphology since the right ventricle is activated in advance of the left ventricle. Pacing from the right ventricular apex is expected to produce negative QRS complexes in the inferior leads since the apical area is activated in advance of the base, while pacing from the right ventricular outflow tract (which is unstable in the temporary setting and might be due to migration of the pacing electrodes) will have positive QRS complexes in the inferior leads since the base will be activated in advance of the apex. Finally, if the pacing electrode was inadvertently placed into the left ventricle (due, eg, to accidental arterial access, ventricular perforation, or placement of the electrode in a venous branch of the coronary sinus), the paced QRS complex will have a right bundle branch block morphology (positive QRS complex in lead V<sub>1</sub>). In cases where temporary pacing will be required for longer periods of time, a permanent pacing lead with an active fixation mechanism can be used to ensure stable lead placement.</p>
<sec id="section14-0885066611402165">
<title>Pacemaker emergencies</title>
<p>Since the first cardiac pacemaker was implanted in 1958, the field of cardiac pacing has grown rapidly. The number of pacemakers implanted annually increased from 94,755 in 1990 to 267,278 in 2002. From 1990 to 2002, there were 2.25 million pacemakers implanted in the United States.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0885066611402165">33</xref></sup> Thus, it is likely that most physicians will have an opportunity to manage the patients with these devices. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0885066611402165">Table 2</xref>
gives a list of pacemaker emergencies that need to be recognized and treated promptly.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Pacemaker Emergencies</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0885066611402165" xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>Failure to capture</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Failure to sense</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Oversensing<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>Pauses in paced rhythm</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Rapid triggered ventricular paced rates</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Rapid ventricular paced rates</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>No output</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0885066611402165">
<title>Failure to capture</title>
<p>Failure to capture and failure to output are serious complications that can be life threatening. The severity of their consequences depends on the duration of the problem (intermittent vs persistent) and whether the patient is pacemaker dependent (asystolic or symptomatic without adequate rate support). The electrocardiographic diagnosis of failure to capture is made by demonstrating the occurrence of the stimulus output, which, when delivered outside the refractory period of atrial or ventricular tissue, is not followed by a P wave or QRS complex. The causes of failure to capture fall into 1 of the 3 major categories.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0885066611402165">1</xref></sup> increase in myocardial stimulation threshold from various causes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0885066611402165">Table 3</xref>
)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0885066611402165">2</xref></sup>; defective pacing leads; and<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0885066611402165">3</xref></sup> pulse generator battery depletion. It is important to note that stimulus delivery during tissue refractoriness is not true failure to capture, and is designated “functional noncapture.”</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Causes of Pacemaker Noncapture</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0885066611402165" xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>Elevation of stimulation threshold<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Metabolic disturbances (hyperkalemia, hyperglycemia, alkalemia or acidosis, hypoxemia or hypercapnia, hypothyroidism)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Drugs (quinidine, procainamide, lidocaine, mexiletine, encainide, flecainide)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Acute myocardial infarction</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Exit block due to lead fibrosis</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Pacing lead defects (fractures, insulation break)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Lead maturation, dislodgement, or perforation</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Inappropriately low-programmed output</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Battery end of life</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Failure to capture is usually due to an increase in atrial or ventricular stimulation threshold (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0885066611402165">Table 3</xref>). Increase in stimulation threshold is the most common cause of failure to capture that occurs in the first 8 weeks after pacemaker implantation and is due to the maturation process at the interface of the electrodes and myocardial tissue. This problem can be managed by noninvasively reprogramming the energy output of the pulse generator to a higher value (by increasing the pulse duration or the voltage amplitude or both). The stimulation threshold decreases to a stable level after 2 months, at which time the energy output can be reprogrammed to a lower value to prolong the battery life. The use of corticosteroid-eluting pacing leads has decreased the local tissue reaction and the thickness of the fibrous capsule surrounding the tip electrode, reducing both acute and chronic stimulation thresholds.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0885066611402165">34</xref></sup>
</p>
<p>Various metabolic disturbances are known to increase the myocardial stimulation threshold. Although hypoglycemia does not cause important changes in stimulation threshold, severe hyperglycemia (serum glucose level above 600 mg/dL) has been reported to cause a more than 50% increase.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0885066611402165">35</xref></sup> Hyperkalemia can also increase the stimulation threshold significantly, generally when the serum potassium level exceeds 7 mEq/L (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0885066611402165">Figure 5</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0885066611402165">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0885066611402165">37</xref></sup> Although the determination of the serum potassium level can take time, there is usually electrocardiographic evidence of hyperkalemia that should suggest this diagnosis: this evidence includes a prolonged P wave duration, loss of visible P waves, markedly prolonged QRS complex duration (spontaneous or paced), and merging of the QRS complex with the ST-T wave (“sine wave” morphology). Management includes correction of the hyperkalemia and/or temporarily increasing the energy output of the pulse generator by noninvasive programming or both. This latter maneuver is not always successful, however, and simply increasing pulse generator voltage output will not reverse any accompanying electromechanical dissociation. Both metabolic acidosis and alkalosis can increase the stimulation threshold by as much as 70% to 80%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0885066611402165">38</xref></sup> Hypoxemia and hypercarbia can also increase the capture threshold, which can be reversed by supplemental oxygen and hyperventilation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0885066611402165">35</xref></sup>; although uncommon today, this may be especially relevant during induction of general anesthesia in patients with cardiac pacemakers. Many of these metabolic disturbances occur during cardiopulmonary resuscitation. In patients who are pacemaker-dependent, correction of these metabolic disturbances is crucial to a successful resuscitation.</p>
<fig id="fig5-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Type II Pacemaker exit block in a patient with hyperkalemia.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Drugs that affect the excitability of myocardial tissue can increase the stimulation threshold, especially when high doses are required to achieve a therapeutic effect. All classes of antiarrhythmic agents are used in intensive care units, and many of them have been shown to affect myocardial stimulation threshold (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0885066611402165">Table 4</xref>
). Sodium channel blockers, including quinidine and procainamide (Vaughn Williams class IA antiarrhythmic agents), lidocaine and mexiletine (class IB), and encainide and (especially) flecainide (class IC) have all been reported to increase cardiac stimulation thresholds.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0885066611402165">39</xref></sup> Digitalis, β-adrenergic antagonists (class II antiarrhythmic agents), and angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors have no important effect on the pacing threshold.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0885066611402165">39</xref></sup> The effect of amiodarone (class III antiarrhythmic agent), whether given intravenously or orally, on pacing threshold is not well defined, although evidence suggests no significant effect. Verapamil, a calcium channel antagonist (class IV antiarrhythmic agent), has been reported to increase capture threshold,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0885066611402165">40</xref></sup> but this is unusual and usually of no clinical consequence. Atropine, isoproterenol, corticosteroids, and epinephrine have been shown to decrease the myocardial capture threshold.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0885066611402165">39</xref></sup> Successful management of failure to capture due to the effects of antiarrhythmic agents includes rapid detection and correction of any accompanying metabolic disturbance or electrolyte imbalance. Sodium lactate and sodium bicarbonate have been reported to reverse the effects of the sodium channel antagonists quinidine and procainamide. Removal of quinidine or procainamide by hemodialysis or hemoperfusion is not effective because of their extensive tissue distribution. Noninvasive programming of the pulse generator to a higher energy output may temporarily allow consistent capture until the offending drugs are excreted.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Effects of Drugs on Pacing Threshold</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0885066611402165" xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>Increase pacing threshold<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Bretylium</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Flecainide</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Propafenone</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Sotalol</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Possible increase <list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>β-Blockers</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Lidocaine</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Procainamide</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Quinidine</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Decrease pacing threshold <list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Atropine</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Epinephrine</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Isoproterenol</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Steroids</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Acute MI (especially involving the inferior wall) can result in an increase in stimulation threshold and failure to capture. The mechanisms responsible include local hyperkalemia from tissue necrosis, shock, and high levels of certain antiarrhythmic agents. Capture threshold increase is usually, but not always, accompanied by undersensing of the intracardiac electrical signal which, in single chamber ventricular pacing systems, can result in inappropriately early stimulus delivery and repetitive ventricular beating.</p>
<p>Failure to capture can result from insufficient energy reaching myocardial tissue due to lead fracture or lead insulation failure. Interrogation of the pacing system will reveal high-lead impedance along the fractured lead, while a low-lead impedance is seen in lead insulation failure. Lead displacement, including myocardial penetration and perforation, is a common cause of failure to capture early after implantation. When lead-related problems are suspected, highly penetrated radiographs of the chest in both posteroanterior and lateral views should be obtained and compared with those taken immediately after pacing system implantation; however, the radiographs may be unrevealing and should not per se lead the clinician away from a suspected diagnosis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0885066611402165">
<title>Failure of output</title>
<p>Failure of output is manifested on the surface electrocardiogram as an absence of pacing artifacts. Absence of pacing stimuli due to the failure of output should not be confused with the absence of visible pacing stimuli due to lead fracture, loose connections between the pulse generator and the leads, oversensing and low-programmed voltage generating low-amplitude artifacts; in these circumstances, pacing pulses are emitted by the pulse generator in the normally expected manner. True output failure indicates battery depletion or component failure. To confirm the diagnosis of failure of output, a magnet can be placed over the pulse generator to demonstrate the absence of pacing artifacts or a change in rate on the electrocardiogram. True output failure due to battery end-of-life will yield the expected battery voltage depletion on pacemaker interrogation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0885066611402165">
<title>Sensing problems: oversensing and undersensing</title>
<p>Problems related to sensing the intracardiac electrical signal can be classified into those caused by oversensing of unwanted signals or undersensing of the intrinsic intracardiac signal. Appropriate sensing in the atrium and ventricle is an indispensable part of pacemaker function. Several factors influence sensing functions, including the lead configuration (bipolar vs unipolar) the amplitude and the slew (rate of change of voltage [d<italic>V</italic>/d<italic>t</italic>]) of the intracardiac signals, and the programmed sensitivity setting (sensing threshold) of the pacemaker generator. The pacemaker “senses” the voltage difference between the 2 electrodes (anode and cathode) of the pacing system. In unipolar systems, 1 electrode (the cathode) is the tip of the pacing wire and the other electrode (the anode) is the pacemaker generator itself. The large antenna thus created enlarges the intracardiac signal (as well as extracardiac signals), allowing for easier sensing. In bipolar pacing systems, the electrodes are in proximity to each other on the lead; the sensed signal is between the closely spaced electrodes. Although studies indicate little difference in the sensed signal between unipolar and bipolar lead configurations, on occasion, in the acute setting, unipolarization of a temporary pacing system can be useful.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0885066611402165">41</xref></sup> Unipolarization can also be used in permanent pacing systems in some cases of lead insulation break, to reestablish normal pacing and sensing functions, at least temporarily until lead replacement can be carried out.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0885066611402165">
<title>Oversensing</title>
<p>Oversensing is present when the pulse generator’s sensing circuit identifies an electrical event sensed in the ventricular channel as an R wave or an electrical event sensed in the atrial channel as a P wave. These electrical events may be generated in the pacing system itself, in the heart, in the body musculature, or in the environment. The consequence of oversensing is a pause (appropriate inhibition of output) in pacing stimulus delivery or, if an oversensed atrial electrical event triggers pacing stimulus output in the ventricle, an earlier than expected paced ventricular event, provided temporal opportunity to capture is present.</p>
<p>The sensing circuits of the pacemaker generator are able to differentiate P, R, and T waves by their amplitudes, slew rates, and durations. It is not uncommon for the atrial sensing circuit to detect a remote (“far field”) electrical signal such as an R wave, because of its large amplitude, a phenomenon termed <italic>far-field oversensing</italic> “Crosstalk” can occur in the ventricular channel upon sensing an atrial pacing stimulus of high output. Inhibition of ventricular stimulus output due to crosstalk can result in long pauses in rhythm. Management of the far-field oversensing and crosstalk consists of decreasing the sensitivity of the atrial or ventricular channel by noninvasive programming, programming a sufficiently long post ventricular atrial refractory period (PVARP; a period of time after paced or spontaneous ventricular depolarization during which the atrial channel does not respond to sensed input) and, in the case of ventricular crosstalk, decreasing the atrial voltage output.</p>
<p>T-wave oversensing is rare in today’s permanent pacing systems but is still observed during temporary pacing. It is often the paced T wave with its larger intracardiac amplitude that is oversensed. Skeletal myopotentials, particularly pectoralis major myopotentials, can achieve amplitudes as high as 3 mV. Myopotential oversensing is not uncommon in unipolar pacing systems, and the incidence of inappropriately long pauses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0885066611402165">Figure 6</xref>) can be as high as 30%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0885066611402165">42</xref></sup> In contrast, bipolar pacing systems are relatively immune to skeletal muscle interference even when programmed sensitivity is increased, which is 1 of the reasons that the majority of current systems implanted utilize bipolar leads. Diaphragmatic myopotential oversensing by bipolar electrodes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0885066611402165">43</xref></sup> has been reported, however, and has been accompanied by a high-programmed sensitivity and provoked by cough, hiccoughs, or a Valsalva maneuver. In a unipolar system, if myopotential oversensing cannot be corrected by noninvasive programming to a lower sensitivity, or if undersensing results from the programming change, change to a bipolar lead may be required.</p>
<fig id="fig6-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Myopotential oversensing leading to pauses in pacing.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>External electromagnetic interference (EMI) from the environment, particularly from electrical appliances emitting energy at frequency of 50 to 60 Hz, can also cause oversensing with resulting inhibition of output or triggered ventricular pacing. Sources of interference include radiofrequency transmitting devices, arc welding, automobile ignition systems, radar, and portable music players.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0885066611402165">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0885066611402165">44</xref></sup> In response to interference, some pulse generators revert from their programmed mode to an “interference mode,” which is usually a fixed-rate (asynchronous) mode of function at a specific “interference rate.” Newer pacemaker generators have special shielding and filters that have eliminated or significantly reduced the incidence of EMI oversensing.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0885066611402165">
<title>Undersensing</title>
<p>When native R waves and P waves are not detected by the sensing circuits of the pacemaker system, inappropriate delivery of pacing stimuli ensues. The consequences of undersensing depend on the response of the pacing system to sensed events. In single-chamber demand pacing systems, complete undersensing causes asynchronous fixed-rate pacing and intermittent undersensing results in inappropriate stimulus delivery at the programmed rate. R-wave undersensing could cause a stimulus output to be delivered in the T wave, the vulnerable period, potentially causing a transient or sustained ventricular arrhythmia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0885066611402165">Figure 7</xref>). Similarly, an atrial stimulus delivered in the vulnerable period of atrial tissue can cause atrial arrhythmias such as atrial fibrillation although this appears to be rare. The common causes of undersensing are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0885066611402165">Table 5</xref>
and generally reflect poor quality of the intracardiac signals or an inappropriately programmed sensitivity which does not allow the pacing system to “see” the intracardiac signal.</p>
<fig id="fig7-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Delivery of ventricular pacing stimulus on the T-wave (arrow) due to R-wave undersensing leads to ventricular tachycardia.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table5-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Causes of Undersensing</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0885066611402165" xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>Low amplitude or slew of intracardiac signals<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Acute myocardial infarction</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Congestive heart failure</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Ventricular origin</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Hyperkalemia</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Some antiarrhythmic agents (especially Class IA agents)</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Pacing system<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Lead fracture</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Lead insulation break</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Lead maturation or dislodgement</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Inappropriately programmed sensitivity</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Battery depletion</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Native intracardiac signals can become smaller in magnitude and longer in duration with a slower rate of change of voltage (slew) during conditions such as congestive heart failure and acute MI.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0885066611402165">45</xref></sup> Hyperkalemia or drug toxicity, especially from class IA antiarrhythmic agents, can decrease the slope and amplitude of phase 0 of the cardiac action potential, thereby generating a suboptimal intracardiac signal. Undersensing during these conditions is often transient and can be managed by watchful waiting, providing there is no accompanying failure of capture and the patient is not pacemaker-dependent. In addition to treating the underlying clinical problems, the pulse generator can be noninvasively programmed to a higher sensitivity or programmed to unipolar configuration (in specific devices) to enhance the magnitude of the native depolarization.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0885066611402165">
<title>Rapid ventricular paced rates</title>
<p>Tracking the sensed sinus rate is an important function of a dual-chamber pacing system that senses in the atrium. During tracking, a sensed atrial event triggers a ventricular output at the end of the programmed AV interval (similar to a PR interval) unless a spontaneous ventricular event is sensed. One potential problem during normal tracking function is oversensing in the atrial channel, which inhibits atrial output but triggers ventricular pacing at an inappropriate time. The consequence is an undesirable paced ventricular rate. Decreasing the atrial sensitivity risks atrial undersensing, and programming to a nonsensing mode may be necessary in the acute clinical situation. Removal of the patient from the source of environmental EMI will eliminate the problem of EMI oversensing. If a unipolar atrial lead has been used and noninvasive programming cannot solve the problem, change to a bipolar lead may be required as it will be less prone to oversensing; temporary mode change to a single chamber ventricular pacing system will also solve the problem in the acute setting. In an emergency situation where neither a programmer nor knowledgeable personnel are available, application of a magnet to the pulse generator will eliminate sensing and provide pacing at the (nonprogrammable) factory-set magnet rate; the magnet rate, however, varies with the manufacturer and is, for many pulse generators, 100/min, which may not be desirable in specific clinical situations.</p>
<p>If atrial tachyarrhythmias occur in patients with dual chamber-pacing systems, tracking up to the programmed upper rate limit can occur. When the atrial rate exceeds the programmed upper rate limit (sinus tachycardia, atrial tachycardia, and atrial flutter), ventricular pacing can resemble an “electronic AV block,” either as a second-degree fixed-ratio block or Wenckebach-type response. Pacemaker-mediated tachycardia (PMT) is a well-known complication of dual chamber pacing systems.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0885066611402165">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0885066611402165">47</xref></sup> The PMT usually begins with a premature ventricular complex with retrograde ventriculoatrial (VA) conduction; the retrograde P wave is sensed in the atrial channel, triggering a ventricular output that once again causes retrograde VA conduction, thus creating an “endless loop” (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0885066611402165">Figure 8</xref>). The initiating mechanism of PMT is almost always AV dissociation, created by a ventricular extrasystole, loss of atrial capture, or oversensing in the atrial channel. The easiest way to terminate PMT is by application of a magnet over the pulse generator. The elimination of atrial sensing will abolish the triggered ventricular output. Other more definitive ways to prevent sensing of retrograde P waves include programming a longer PVARP and programming the specific pulse generator response to detection of premature ventricular depolarizations; PMT can also be terminated by programming “on” specific algorithms designed for this purpose.</p>
<fig id="fig8-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>Pacemaker mediated tachycardia initiated by PVC(*). The V1 and lead II rhythm strips are continuous.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig8.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Magnet application over a pulse generator can yield useful information and even lead to correction of certain pacemaker emergencies. Asynchronous pacing in response to magnet application gives an assessment of pacemaker capture. The pacing rate with magnet application indicates the battery status and this is variable for different manufacturers. Temporary loss of sensing with magnet application will terminate rapid ventricular pacing due to PMT as well as ventricular bradyarrhythmias due to crosstalk inhibition and oversensing. In cases where doubt as to the function and/or appropriateness of pacemaker exists, a pacemaker specialist or manufacturer’s representative can be called upon to assist in making the correct diagnosis and providing management strategies.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0885066611402165">
<title>Tachycardias</title>
<sec id="section23-0885066611402165">
<title>Mechanisms</title>
<sec id="section24-0885066611402165">
<title>Supraventricular Tachycardias</title>
<p>Supraventricular tachycardias (SVTs) denote all tachyarrhythmias that originate from supraventricular tissue or require it to be a part of a reentrant circuit. They include paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardia (PSVT), atrial fibrillation (AF), and atrial flutter (AFl; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-0885066611402165">Table 6</xref>
).</p>
<table-wrap id="table6-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Table 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Supraventricular Tachycardia in the ICU</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-0885066611402165" xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>Sinus node<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>Sinus tachycardia (physiologic)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Sinus node reentry (pathologic)</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>AV node independent tachycardia <list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>Atrial fibrillation</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Atrial flutter</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Atrial tachycardia</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>AV node dependent tachycardia <list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>AV node reentry tachycardia</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>AV reentry tachycardia (accessory pathway mediated)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Junctional tachycardia</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-0885066611402165">
<title>Paroxysmal Supraventricular Tachycardia</title>
<p>Paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardia denotes a clinical syndrome characterized by a rapid tachycardia with an abrupt onset and termination. These arrhythmias are frequently encountered in otherwise healthy patients without structural heart disease. The 3 most common causes of PSVT include atrioventricular nodal reentrant tachycardia (AVNRT) (56%), followed by atrioventricular reentrant tachycardia (AVRT; 27%), and atrial tachycardia (AT) (17%).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0885066611402165">48</xref></sup> Rare causes of PSVT include focal junctional tachycardia, nodoventricular tachycardia, and atriofascicular tachycardia. The mechanism responsible for AVNRT and AVRT is reentry, while focal AT is due to triggered activity, abnormal automaticity, or microrentry. Reentry requires 2 distinct pathways that have different speeds of conduction (slow and fast) and varying recovery times (refractoriness). Extra, early beats, such as premature atrial or ventricular contractions (PACs or PVCs), may fail to conduct down the normal (fast conducting but slow to recover) pathway but can travel down the fast recovering but slow conducting pathway. At the distal junction of the 2 pathways, the arriving slow impulse then returns in a retrograde fashion up the now recovered fast normal pathway. This completes the circuit with activation of the myocardial tissue at each end of the pathway.</p>
<p>Resting 12-lead ECG should be examined for rhythm disturbances, P-wave morphologies, premature supraventricular complexes, PR interval abnormalities (eg very short, or a sudden prolongation in the presence of a premature supraventricular complex), delta waves, ST-segment and T-wave abnormalities, and any evidence of structural heart disease (such as Q waves of MI). The presence of overt ventricular preexcitation implicates AVRT as the culprit tachycardia. The 12-lead ECG during SVT provides important diagnostic information and should be obtained as long as hemodynamic stability is not compromised (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0885066611402165">Figures 9</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0885066611402165">10</xref>

). If the 12-lead ECG is not available, a rhythm strip (preferably simultaneously recorded 2 or 3 leads) can be helpful. While most SVTs present as a narrow-complex (QRS duration ≤ 120 ms) tachycardia, they can also present as a wide-complex (QRS &gt; 120 ms) tachycardia as a result of functional or preexisting bundle branch block or preexcitation, either from a “bystander” pathway or as part of the circuit in the case of an antidromic tachycardia (in which ventricular depolarization proceeds down an accessory pathway rather than the normal AV conduction system, and retrograde VA conduction proceeds along the normal AV conduction system). Both the regularity of the QRS complexes and the relationship of the P waves to the onset of QRS complexes during the tachycardia provide important diagnostic information (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table7-0885066611402165">Table 7</xref>
).</p>
<fig id="fig9-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 9.</label>
<caption>
<p>Illustrative lead II tracings showing categorization of supraventricular tachycardias into short RP (tracing B, RP &lt; PR) vs long RP tachycardias (tracing C, RP &gt; PR). Tracing A shows normal sinus rhythm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig9.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig10-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 10.</label>
<caption>
<p>Two different forms of paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardia. (A) Atrioventricular nodal reentrant tachycardia (AVNRT) with P-wave deflection at the terminal part of QRS (*). (B) Atrioventricular reentrant tachycardia (AVRT) with short RP tachycardia (*).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig10.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table7-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Table 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Categorization of Narrow-Complex Supraventricular Tachycardias Based on Regularity of QRS Complexes and RP vs PR Relationship on the ECG<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0885066611402165">a</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table7-0885066611402165" xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-table7.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Regular QRS Complexes</th>
<th>Irregular QRS Complexes</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Short RP:</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Typical (slow-fast) AVNRT</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Orthodromic AVRT</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Atypical (slow-slow) AVNRT (rare)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Junctional tachycardia</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Atrial tachycardia (rare)</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
<td>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Atrial tachycardia with variable AV conduction</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Multifocal atrial tachycardia</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Atrial flutter with variable AV conduction</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Atrial fibrillation</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Long RP:</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>Atrial tachycardia (more common)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Atypical (fast-slow) AVNRT</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Permanent junctional reciprocating tachycardia</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Sinus tachycardia</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0885066611402165">
<p>
<sup>a</sup> Short RP denotes RP &lt; PR; long RP denotes RP &gt; PR.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-0885066611402165">
<title>Nonparoxysmal Junctional Tachycardia</title>
<p>Nonparoxysmal junctional tachycardia is usually a relatively benign arrhythmia with a mechanism due to either enhanced automaticity from a junctional focus or triggered activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0885066611402165">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0885066611402165">50</xref></sup> It is characterized by heart rates that are much lower than that seen in focal junctional tachycardia, usually in the range of 70 to 120 bpm, with “warm-up” and “cool-down” phases prior to extinction. Nonparoxysmal junctional tachycardia is usually encountered in patients after cardiac surgery or who have myocardial ischemia or infarction, metabolic disorders (eg digoxin toxicity, hypokalemia), chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, or myocarditis. There is usually a 1:1 AV association, unless digoxin toxicity is present in which case AV Wenckebach block may be present.</p>
<p>Nonparoxysmal junctional tachycardia is managed by correcting the underlying physiologic or metabolic abnormality. In the now rare patient with digoxin toxicity, agents to bind digoxin may be considered if high-grade AV block and/or ventricular arrhythmias are present. β-Blockers and calcium-channel blockers may be used to suppress abnormal junctional firing. In cases where enhanced sympathetic tone and accentuated junctional automaticity result in loss of AV synchrony with hemodynamic compromise, overdrive atrial pacing may be used to maintain AV synchrony.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-0885066611402165">
<title>Atrial Flutter and Atrial Tachycardia</title>
<p>There are overlaps in terminology between AFl and AT due to macroreentry.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0885066611402165">51</xref></sup> Atrial flutter is a very rapid atrial rhythm with little or no diastolic interval. Atrial flutter may occur in typical or atypical forms, with atrial cycle lengths of 300 ± 10 ms. Drugs (eg amiodarone) or structural atrial disease may produce slower rates of AFl, but there is no precise rate cutoff to distinguish AFl from AT due to macroreentry. Atrial flutter may arise from the left atrium (LA) or the right atrium (RA). The most common form (“typical” flutter) arises from the RA and accounts for 90% of patients with this arrhythmia. In typical flutter, the ECG shows negative flutter waves in the inferior leads II, III, and AVF, corresponding to the “sawtoothed” pattern, and positive flutter waves in V<sub>1</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0885066611402165">Figure 11</xref>). The circuit of this arrhythmia involves a critical area of slow conduction referred to as isthmus, between the coronary sinus ostium and the tricuspid valve. The impulse travels in a counter-clockwise fashion in the RA. Typical AFL can also be associated with impulse propagation in a clockwise fashion that leads to positive flutter waves in the inferior leads and negative flutter waves in V<sub>1</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0885066611402165">Figure 11</xref>). Catheter ablation is the first line therapy for typical right atrial flutter with a success rate of 95%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0885066611402165">52</xref></sup>
</p>
<fig id="fig11-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 11.</label>
<caption>
<p>Two distinct ECG patterns of typical right atrial flutter in the same patient. (A) Negative flutter waves in leads II, III, and aVF and positive flutter waves in V<sub>1</sub> due to counterclockwise rotation of the flutter wavefront. (B) Positive flutter waves in leads II, III, and aVF and negative flutter waves in V<sub>1</sub> due to clockwise rotation of the flutter wavefront.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig11.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Atrial flutter may develop in areas of the atrium that have been affected by surgical procedures (eg- Mustard/Senning/Fontan/Atrial Septal Defect repair/Valve surgery). This type of flutter is referred to as “incisional” flutter.</p>
<p>Focal ATs, caused by abnormal automaticity or triggered activity, tend to arise from defined anatomic regions in the RA (about 63%) and LA (about 37%).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0885066611402165">53</xref></sup> Although less commonly seen in recent years, digoxin toxicity should be considered as a possible cause when automatic AT is present, especially when associated with AV block or ventricular bigeminy. In addition to digoxin toxicity, conditions associated with AT include congenital heart disease (pre and postrepair), cardiomyopathy, severe pulmonary disease and associated cor pulmonale, mitral stenosis, postaccessory pathway ablation, postcardiac transplantation, theophylline toxicity, atrial tumors, pregnancy, swallowing, and certain postures. Recently, with the advent of AF ablation procedures, postablation left-sided ATs have been reported.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0885066611402165">54</xref></sup>
</p>
<p>Tachycardias may also arise from the sinoatrial node and include sinus node reentrant tachycardia (paroxysmal) and inappropriate sinus tachycardia (usually incessant). Sinoatrial node reentrant tachycardia begins and ends abruptly, with P-wave morphology indistinguishable from normal sinus rhythm. It arises from the junction between atrium and superior vena cava in the sinus node region.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section28-0885066611402165">
<title>Atrial Fibrillation</title>
<p>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the most common sustained arrhythmia, with a prevalence of 5.9% in patients &gt;65 years. It is growing in epidemic proportions with an estimated prevalence of 8.9 million in 2020.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0885066611402165">55</xref></sup> It is now classified as paroxysmal, persistent, and chronic or permanent. Focal triggers, multiple wave reentry and dominant rotors with mother and daughter wavelets are some of the mechanisms proposed for atrial fibrillation. It is associated with significant morbidity and mortality and it accounts for 20 to 25% of the strokes in octogenarians. AF accounts for one-third of the all patient discharges with arrhythmia as the principal diagnosis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-0885066611402165">
<title>Supraventricular Arrhythmias Associated With MI</title>
<p>Patients recovering from acute MI have been noted to have various forms of SVT (varying from premature beats to AF) during Holter monitoring, with a decreased incidence after early and complete revascularization.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0885066611402165">56</xref></sup> The most common SVT after MI is AF with an incidence of 8% to 28%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0885066611402165">57</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0885066611402165"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0885066611402165"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0885066611402165">60</xref></sup> Multifocal AT and reentrant SVT are not commonly associated with MI. Inflammation (pericarditis), ischemia (atrial infarction), enhanced sympathetic tone, left ventricular dysfunction and sinus node dysfunction with tachycardia-bradycardia syndrome are some of the mechanisms involved in the pathogenesis of AF post MI. Inferior MI and atrial infarction on ECG have been shown to predict AF post-MI.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0885066611402165">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0885066611402165">62</xref></sup>
</p>
<p>Atrial fibrillation has been shown to trigger heart failure in acute MI due to loss of effective atrial contractions with impairment of hemodynamic state. Post-MI patients with new onset AF have a higher in-hospital mortality than those without AF.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0885066611402165">58</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0885066611402165"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0885066611402165">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0885066611402165">63</xref></sup> Chest pain and ST abnormalities suggesting ischemia or infarction are common in patients presenting to emergency department with AF and rapid ventricular rates. ECG findings of ST elevation and &gt; 2mm ST depression have been shown to be discriminators that predict MI in these patients,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0885066611402165">64</xref></sup> although “demand ischemia” related to rapid ventricular rates are more common.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section30-0885066611402165">
<title>Ventricular Tachycardia</title>
<p>Ventricular tachycardia (VT) usually manifests as aborted sudden cardiac death (SCD), syncope or near syncope, and wide QRS complex tachycardia. The most serious is its degeneration into ventricular fibrillation (VF), producing cardiac arrest and SCD that accounts for half of all the cardiac deaths and up to 15% of total mortality in United States.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0885066611402165">65</xref></sup> A high prevalence of SCD (more than 20% incidence within the ensuing 12 months) has been observed in patients with syncope from cardiovascular causes, suggesting that undiagnosed VT may be an underlying cause of SCD in patients with syncope that remains unexplained after a thorough appropriate workup. Ventricular tachycardia is classified as nonsustained and sustained. Nonsustained VT refers to 3 or more consecutive QRS complexes of uniform configuration of ventricular origin at a rate exceeding 100 bpm. Sustained VT lasts for more than 30 seconds and often requires intervention for its termination. Ventricular tachycardia is, in addition, classified as monomorphic VT (same QRS morphology in a given ECG lead) or polymorphic VT (beat-to-beat variation in QRS complex morphology in any given ECG lead). Polymorphic VT can be associated with a normal QT interval or a prolonged QT interval, in which case the rhythm is referred to as torsades de pointes.</p>
<p>The hemodynamic stability of VT depends on many factors, including rate, duration, ventricular function, the presence of concomitant coronary artery disease, baroreflex sensitivity, the presence or absence of cardioactive drugs, and even the patient’s posture at the time of onset. Hemodynamic tolerance of VT can, therefore, vary considerably in different situations; at times, it can vary in the same patient, and it is prudent not to exclude the diagnosis of VT on the basis of hemodynamic tolerance alone. The diagnosis of wide QRS complex tachycardia by ECG analysis has always been a challenge for clinicians. The differential diagnosis includes VT, SVT with aberrant intraventricular conduction delay (IVCD), and pre-excited tachycardia in patients with Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome (WPW). Pre-excited tachycardia is a rare cause of wide QRS complex tachycardia (5%-8% of cases); however, the QRS pattern of pre-excited QRS complex can be difficult to distinguish from VT because in both instances the QRS starts with muscle-to-muscle conduction. ECG artifact can also mimic wide QRS complex tachycardia and be misdiagnosed as VT, leading to expensive testing and even placement of implantable cardioverter-defibrillators (ICDs). Clues to the diagnosis of artifact include absence of hemodynamic deterioration, an unstable baseline, association with body movement and ability to march the normal QRS complexes through the artifact at the regular sinus interval (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0885066611402165">Figure 12</xref>). Specific ECG rhythms that can mimic VT in the intensive care unit (ICU) include sinus tachycardia with IVCD, hyperkalemia with wide QRS complex, and acute MI, with ST segment elevation being mistaken for part of the QRS complexes. A number of surface ECG criteria, including the atrioventricular (AV) relationship, the QRS complex duration, specific QRS morphologies, and the mean frontal plane QRS complex axes, have been established to distinguish VT from SVT with aberrant conduction. These criteria are helpful in arriving at an accurate diagnosis if they are used in a systemic fashion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table8-0885066611402165">Table 8</xref>
).</p>
<fig id="fig12-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 12.</label>
<caption>
<p>Artifact mimicking ventricular tachycardia. The QRS complexes are seen as notches that are marching at the regular sinus interval (*).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig12.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table8-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Table 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>ECG Criteria to Distinguish Ventricular Tachycardia (VT) From Supraventricular Tachycardia (SVT) During Wide QRS Complex Tachycardia (WCT)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table8-0885066611402165" xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-table8.tif"/>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>QRS axis: northwest axis with predominant positive QRS complex in aVR favors VT</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>AV dissociation: QRS rate faster than P wave rate is diagnostic of VT</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Narrow complex beat: narrow complex beat during WCT (fusion or capture beats) favor VT</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Brugada criteria: RS (measured from beginning of QRS to the nadir of S wave) in precordial leads <list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>Absence of RS in all precordial leads favors VT</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>RS &gt; 100 ms in any precordial lead favors VT</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Morphology criteria (V<sub>1</sub>, V<sub>2</sub>): classic bundle branch block morphology favors SVT</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<list list-type="alpha-lower">
<list-item>
<p>RBBB (rsR’): R’ &gt; r favors SVT</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>LBBB: Kindwall criteria favors VT</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>    R &gt; 30 ms, notch in S wave, QRS onset to S &gt; 60 ms</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>   Q wave in V<sub>6</sub>
</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0885066611402165">
<p>Abbreviations: AV, atrioventricular; LBBB, left bundle branch block; RBBB, right bundle branch block; SVT, supraventricular tachycardia; VT, ventricular tachycardia.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The mechanism of VT includes reentry, abnormal automaticity and triggered activity. Reentry involving an area of slow conduction is the basis of VT seen in patients with structural heart disease. Abnormal automaticity is associated with warm-up and warm-down phenomenon and usually causes monomorphic VT in patients without structural heart disease, and an accelerated ventricular rhythm seen in patients with coronary artery disease. Triggered rhythms can be caused by early (long QT syndrome) or late (digitalis toxicity) afterdepolarizations that usually lead to polymorphic VT.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section31-0885066611402165">
<title>Monomorphic VT in Specific Clinical Conditions</title>
<sec id="section32-0885066611402165">
<title>Coronary artery disease</title>
<p>Myocardial ischemia and infarction (MI) is associated with VT in 3 clinically distinct time periods: early, within the first few hours of the onset of symptoms (polymorphic VT); later, approximately 48 hours after onset of symptoms (monomorphic VT; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0885066611402165">Figure 13</xref>); and after coronary artery reperfusion (accelerated ventricular rhythm). The underlying substrate is usually an area of fibrosis (scar) that provides an anatomic obstacle around which a reentrant impulse can propagate. The extent and architecture of the scar may determine the propensity to VT in a given situation. For example, a homogeneous scar with no surviving conducting tissue is less likely to cause arrhythmias than is fibrosis interspersed with streaks of healthy myocardium. In some situations, acute myocardial ischemia or infarct can produce the conditions of slow conduction and block necessary for reentry. Although nonreentrant mechanisms (abnormal automaticity, triggered activity) can cause VT in these settings, reentry is the most common mechanism.</p>
<fig id="fig13-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 13.</label>
<caption>
<p>Monomorphic ventricular tachycardia in a patient with ischemic cardiomyopathy.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig13.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Accelerated ventricular rhythms (wide QRS complexes originating in ventricular tissue and occurring at a rate &lt;100 bpm) are observed in approximately 40% of patients undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0885066611402165">66</xref></sup> The mechanism is abnormal automaticity with classical ECG features of onset and offset with a fusion beat between the sinus-conducted QRS and the ventricular complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-0885066611402165">Figure 14</xref>). The development of accelerated ventricular rhythms has generally been considered to be a sign of reperfusion, although the recent studies have suggested that these rhythms in fact represent reperfusion injury and more extensive myocardial damage and delayed microvascular reperfusion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0885066611402165">5</xref></sup>
</p>
<fig id="fig14-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 14.</label>
<caption>
<p>Accelerated ventricular rhythm with fusion complex at the onset and the offset. (*)</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig14.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section33-0885066611402165">
<title>Dilated cardiomyopathy</title>
<p>Monomorphic VT associated with idiopathic (nonischemic) dilated cardiomyopathy and valvular disease is indistinguishable from VT due to coronary artery disease in over half the patients. Invariably, however, these patients have conduction slowing in the His-Purkinje system as a part of the diffuse myocardial disease process, and the baseline ECG shows a nonspecific intraventricular conduction defect. The resultant VT uses the bundle branches and the bundle of His for sustained reentry. Bundle branch reentry could manifest as either an LBBB or RBBB pattern. As ventricular myocardial activation occurs via the bundle branches, a typical LBBB or RBBB configuration is generally noted. Bundle branch reentry is also fairly common in patients with aortic and mitral valve disease. Owing to the close anatomic relationship between the proximal His-Purkinje system and the annuli of these valves, His-Purkinje system conduction delays can occur in association with valvular disease. Frequently, sustained bundle branch reentry is observed soon after valve surgery.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section34-0885066611402165">
<title>Idiopathic VT</title>
<p>Ventricular tachycardia is most commonly associated with structural heart disease; however, 15% to 20% of VT episodes reported in various series is seen in patients without structural heart disease and is referred to as idiopathic VT.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0885066611402165">67</xref></sup> These patients are usually seen as outpatients with hemodynamically stable sustained and nonsustained monomorphic VT, but occasionally can present with unstable rapid VT that requires admission to the ICU. This is broadly classified into left ventricular fascicular VT and outflow tract VT. In left ventricular fascicular VT, the VT arises from the fascicles in the left ventricle. Based on the QRS morphology and the site of origin, it can be classified as left posterior fascicular VT that has RBBB left axis morphology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-0885066611402165">Figure 15</xref>), left anterior fascicular VT that has RBBB right axis morphology and left upper septal VT that gives rise to a very narrow complex RBBB or LBBB morphology VT. The QRS duration in fascicular VT varies from 140 to 150 ms and the duration from the beginning of the QRS onset to the nadir of the S wave (RS interval) in the precordial leads is 60 to 80 ms, unlike VT associated with structural heart disease that is usually associated with longer duration of QRS and RS intervals. Outflow tract VT usually arises from the right ventricular outflow tract; rarely this can arise from left ventricular outflow tract or aortic cusp. This form of VT is associated with a characteristic ECG morphology of LBBB with inferior axis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig16-0885066611402165">Figure 16</xref>). It is important to differentiate right ventricular outflow tract VT from VT associated with arrhythmogenic right ventricular cardiomyopathy that also has LBBB morphology. In most situations, intravenous adenosine will terminate the VT, suggesting that triggered activity dependent on cyclic adenosine monophosphate may be the mechanism.</p>
<fig id="fig15-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 15.</label>
<caption>
<p>Left ventricular fascicular VT arising from the posterior fascicle in the LV. Typical RBBB pattern morphology is noted. Capture beat noted that proves diagnosis of VT(*).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig15.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig16-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 16.</label>
<caption>
<p>Right ventricular outflow tract VT showing LBBB morphology with inferior axis.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig16.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section35-0885066611402165">
<title>Management of Monomorphic VT</title>
<sec id="section36-0885066611402165">
<title>Immediate termination</title>
<p>The method of VT termination in the acute setting depends on the hemodynamic tolerance of the tachycardia. When the patient loses consciousness or has severe hypotension, a synchronized DC cardioversion should be attempted. Sedation prior to cardioversion is advised in patients who are awake. With hemodynamically well-tolerated VT, there is ample time to gather complete information, including a 12-lead ECG, before initiating therapy. Intravenous amiodarone is the drug of choice for treating VT. Ventricular tachycardia in association with acute MI may respond to lidocaine (2-3 mg/kg). Intravenous procainamide (10-15 mg/kg) at a rate of 50 to 100 mg/min is also effective, but it can lead to hypotension. When VT has been triggered or aggravated by exercise or increased sympathetic tone in the hospital, intravenous β-blockers may be tried as the initial therapy unless there are contraindications to their use. If there is any uncertainty regarding the safety of β-blockers in patients with VT, it is somewhat safer to use agents with a short half-life, such as esmolol. Immediate termination of right ventricular outflow tract VT can be achieved with carotid sinus massage, adenosine, β-blockers, and lidocaine. Left ventricular fascicular VT responds well to calcium channel blockers. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table9-0885066611402165">Table 9</xref>
gives a summary of intravenous drugs used for acute treatment of tachyarrhythmias.</p>
<table-wrap id="table9-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Table 9.</label>
<caption>
<p>Antiarrhythmic Drugs used in ICU</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table9-0885066611402165" xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-table9.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Drug</th>
<th>Indications</th>
<th>Dosage (Intravenous)</th>
<th>Elimination Half-Life</th>
<th>Adverse Effects</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Procainamide</td>
<td>VT, Pre-excited tachycardia</td>
<td>15-17 mg/kg at 20 mg/min, maintenance 1-4 mg/min</td>
<td>3-3.5 hours</td>
<td>Hypotension, lupus, wide PR or QRS, asthenia, apraxia, depression, bone marrow suppression, myopathy, nausea, vomiting, bitter taste, abdominal pain</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lidocaine</td>
<td>VT in setting of ischemia, torsades de pointes</td>
<td>1-1.5 mg/kg repeated in 5 minutes max 3 mg/kg, maintenance 1-4 mg/min</td>
<td>1.5-2 hours</td>
<td>Dizziness, nausea, drowsiness, speech disturbance, perioral numbness, muscle twitching, psychosis, seizures, sinus arrest, complete AV block</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Esmolol</td>
<td>Short-term rate control during SVT</td>
<td>500 μg/kg over 1 min (load), then 50 μg/kg/min (maintenance)</td>
<td>2 minutes</td>
<td>Hypotension, dizziness, somnolence, headache, bronchospasm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Amiodarone</td>
<td>VT, VF, AF</td>
<td>150 mg/min over 10 min, then 1 mg/min for 6 h, then reduce to 0.5 mg/min for 18 hours</td>
<td>40-60 days (long-term administration)</td>
<td>Elevated liver enzymes, nausea, vomiting, constipation, anorexia, dermatologic reactions, tremor, neuropathy, abnormal gait, parasthesias, pulmonary fibrosis, hypotension, hypo/hyperthyroidism, flushing, edema, corneal deposits</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diltiazem</td>
<td>Rate control of AF, AFL; treatment of SVT</td>
<td>0.25 mg/kg over 2 min; if no response in 15 min, 0.35 mg/kg over 2 min, then 5-15 mg/h (maintenance)</td>
<td>3.5-10 hours</td>
<td>Hypotension, dizziness, headache, nausea, bradycardia, AV block, syncope, gingival hyperplasia, peripheral edema</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ibutilide</td>
<td>Terminate AF, AFL</td>
<td>1 mg (&gt;60 kg) over 10 minutes; repeat after 10 min as needed, Less than 60 kg: 0.01 mg/kg</td>
<td>3-6 hours</td>
<td>Headache, bradycardia, hypotension, palpitations, QT prolongation, torsades, heart failure, heart block, nausea</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Digoxin</td>
<td>Rate control of AF, AFL</td>
<td>0.5 mg (initial), 0.25 mg q4-8 h to total of 1 mg (load)</td>
<td>30 minutes</td>
<td>Nausea, accelerated junctional rhythm, AV block</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Adenosine</td>
<td>Termination of AV node dependent SVT, some focal AT and RVOT VT</td>
<td>6-12 mg rapid bolus with flush peripherally, 3-6 mg centrally</td>
<td>9 seconds</td>
<td>Flushing, chest pain, dyspnea, headache, lightheadedness, jaw discomfort, bradycardia, bronchoconstriction, AV block, non sustained ventricular arrhythmias</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Magnesium</td>
<td>Torsades de pointes</td>
<td>2 g bolus followed by additional 2 g if arrhythmias persists</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>Cardiovascular collapse, respiratory paralysis, hypothermia, pulmonary edema, depressed reflexes, flushing, drowsiness, diaphoresis, hypocalcemia, hypophosphatemia, hyperkalemia, visual changes</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0885066611402165">
<p>Abbreviations: AT, atrial tachycardia; AF, atrial fibrillation; AFL, atrial flutter; RVOT, right ventricular outflow tract; SVT, supraventricular tachycardia; VT, ventricular tachycardia; VF, ventricular fibrillation.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>When pharmacologic intervention fails, overdrive termination can be tried. It does require insertion of a pacing catheter but can be quite useful in patients with frequent recurrent VT. Cardioversion is necessary in many situations, particularly if a prolonged VT episode is undesirable, such as in the setting of ischemic heart disease. It should also be emphasized that careful attention should be paid to other factors contributing to ventricular arrhythmogenesis, such as acidosis, hypoxia, electrolyte abnormalities, and the use of drugs. If such factors are involved, pharmacologic treatment alone may fail to control the VT.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section37-0885066611402165">
<title>Long-term drug therapy</title>
<p>For monomorphic VT in association with coronary artery disease or any other type of fibrosis, a variety of therapeutic options are now available. Among the antiarrhythmic drugs, class I agents have moderate efficacy; quinidine and procainamide (class IA) have been used extensively. In recent years, however, their use has progressively declined because of both excessive patient intolerance and lack of efficacy. Class IB drugs such as mexiletine are weak antiarrhythmic agents when used alone, but they seem more useful in combination with IA drugs. Class IC drugs have moderate efficacy but a significant proarrhythmic potential; they are mainly used in patients with idiopathic VT. Exercise-induced VT generally responds well to β-blockers, and serial exercise stress tests can be used to judge drug efficacy. As other forms of VT in patients with coronary artery disease may respond to β-blockers, they are frequently used alone or in combination with other antiarrhythmic drugs when the patient can tolerate them. At present, class III agents (amiodarone, sotalol, and azimilide) are the most widely used antiarrhythmic agents for control of VT and VF.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0885066611402165">68</xref></sup> After a loading dose of 1200 to 1800 mg/day for 1 to 2 weeks, amiodarone can be used in a maintenance dose of 200 to 400 mg/day. It is associated with long-term side effects that can affect the thyroid, lungs, gastrointestinal tract, eyes, skin, genitourinary system, and central nervous system. Baseline thyroid function tests, liver function tests, pulmonary function tests, and ophthalmologic examination (in selected patients) should be done in patients when amiodarone therapy is started, with repeat tests every 6 months.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0885066611402165">69</xref></sup> The usual daily dose of sotalol is 120 to 240 mg/day with monitoring of the ECG for QT prolongation during its administration or with any change in dosage. It should be noted that in high-risk patients with coronary artery disease and reduced left ventricular function, none of the antiarrhythmic agents, including amiodarone, has been shown to decrease mortality compared with placebo.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section38-0885066611402165">
<title>Implantable cardioverter-defibrillators (ICDs)</title>
<p>These devices provide the most effective form of therapy for preventing SCD in patients with VT. The ICD does not prevent VT from occurring; however; it is specifically designed to terminate the tachycardia or fibrillation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0885066611402165">68</xref></sup> Most episodes of VT can be terminated with overdrive pacing; a form of therapy usually not perceptible to the patient. There are relatively few contraindications to ICD treatment; these include incessant VT and VF secondary to reversible causes such as antiarrhythmic drugs, electrolyte abnormalities, and acute ischemia. Implantable cardioverter-defibrillators have demonstrated a remarkable effectiveness in prevention of SCD, with an overall 1-year survival rate of 92% in patients with documented life-threatening ventricular tachyarrhythmias. A recent meta-analysis of ICD trials showed that ICDs reduced all-cause mortality by 20% in adult patients with left ventricular systolic dysfunction.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0885066611402165">70</xref></sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section39-0885066611402165">
<title>Catheter-based ablation</title>
<p>In patients with VT due to structural heart disease who experience recurrent shocks from the ICD, radiofrequency catheter ablation can be used in an attempt to modify or eliminate the VT circuit and thereby reduce the number of shocks a patient experiences.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0885066611402165">71</xref></sup> The success rates for this therapy ranges from 50% to 80%. A randomized study showed the role of prophylactic substrate-based catheter ablation in decreasing VT occurrences in patients with history of MI undergoing ICD implantation for secondary prevention.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0885066611402165">72</xref></sup> Catheter ablation is almost always curative, however, for sustained VT from bundle branch reentry from any cause seen in patients with dilated cardiomyopathy. High success rates (85%-100%) make radiofrequency catheter ablation a good alternative to drug therapy in patients with idiopathic VT due to the focal origin of this form of VT.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0885066611402165">67</xref></sup> Radiofrequency catheter ablation is likely to play a greater role in management of VT in the future due to the development of advanced mapping systems, better catheter design, and incorporation of real time anatomy using echocardiogram, computer-tomographic and magnetic resonance imaging techniques.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section40-0885066611402165">
<title>Management of Polymorphic VT</title>
<p>Recognition of polymorphic VTs and their distinction from the monomorphic variety represent the crucial first step toward appropriate management. These tachycardias tend to be rapid; they generally produce symptoms of hypotension and can readily degenerate into VF.</p>
<sec id="section41-0885066611402165">
<title>Polymorphic VT associated with Prolonged QT Interval</title>
<p>This condition is often referred to as torsades de pointes. It can be congenital or acquired. Although the precipitating factor can differ between the two varieties, both show a prolonged QT and QTc interval (a 12-lead ECG should be obtained to determine the lead(s) showing the longest intervals) and slow, prominent, or unusual-looking and bizarre T or TU waves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig17-0885066611402165">Figure 17</xref>). Congenital long QT syndrome (LQTS) can occur with deafness (Jervell and Lange-Nielsen syndrome) or without deafness (Romano-Ward syndrome). It is characterized mainly by episodes of polymorphic VT often triggered by adrenergic stimulation, which can be brought about by physical exertion or mental or emotional stress. The QT interval prolongation may be subtle and can be unmasked by long pauses or adrenergic stimuli such as exercise. The electrophysiological mechanism is early after depolarization for initiation and reentry for maintenance. It is now clear that congenital LQTS is caused by ion channel defects; 12 different gene defects have so far been identified in this syndrome.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0885066611402165">73</xref></sup> LQT<sub>1</sub> and LQT<sub>2</sub> are K<sup>+</sup> channel abnormalities, but LQT<sub>3</sub> is a Na<sup>+</sup> channel mutation.</p>
<fig id="fig17-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 17.</label>
<caption>
<p>Polymorphic VT associated with prolonged QT interval (torsades de pointes) in a patient receiving quinidine.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig17.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Acquired LQTS can be caused by a variety of pharmacologic agents and metabolic factors (list of drugs to avoid is available at www.sads.org or www.qtdrugs.org). These patients have a partial defect in the K<sup>+</sup> channel I<sub>Kr</sub> that becomes a complete defect in the presence of the offending agents. The QT interval prolongation may not always be striking at the normal rates but should show a measurable increase after a pause (or slowing of sinus rate), for example, following a premature beat.</p>
<p>The key to managing torsades de pointes related to acquired prolonged QT interval is recognizing it. When the proper diagnosis is made, the treatment is withdrawal of the offending agent and replacement of electrolytes (potassium, magnesium, and calcium as needed). Intravenous magnesium has been shown to decrease early after depolarizations. Because hemodynamic stability is necessary to excrete the offending pharmacologic agent, the immediate suppression of torsades de pointes is desirable and can be accomplished with overdrive pacing or using such drugs as isoproterenol (if ischemic heart disease is not present) or atropine (if the rhythm is clearly related to bradycardia).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0885066611402165">68</xref></sup> When it is related to pauses and bradycardia, temporary transvenous pacemaker support may be needed; transcutaneous pacing is unstable over time and not indicated. The mainstay of long-term treatment in congenital LQTS is β-blockade, and up to 5 mg/kg per day of propranolol (or 1 mg/kg per day of nadolol) may be necessary in some situations. Because cardiac slowing can also be arrhythmogenic, permanent pacing is often performed and is the therapy of choice in LQT<sub>3</sub> where β-blockers are contraindicated. Left stellate sympathectomy has been carried out with variable success in difficult cases. In individuals with recurrent syncope or cardiac arrest, ICDs remain a viable option to prevent SCD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0885066611402165">68</xref></sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section42-0885066611402165">
<title>Polymorphic VT associated with normal QT interval</title>
<p>Recurrent polymorphic VT can occur without QT interval prolongation. The true nature of this problem can be readily appreciated by observation of this interval prior to the tachycardia and, more reliably, following the pause that ensues after VT termination. This rhythm can be seen in patients with acute ischemia, severe hypothermia, Brugada syndrome and the “early repolarization syndrome” that has recently been described in patients who present with sudden cardiac death.</p>
<p>Acute ischemia must be excluded in all patients with polymorphic VT in association with normal QT interval. The acute ischemia might be related to underlying coronary stenosis or coronary artery spasm.. The workup includes coronary arteriography and an assessment for coronary artery spasm. Treatment is directed toward eliminating myocardial ischemia. Polymorphic VT with normal QT interval can also occur in patients without substrates for myocardial ischemia but with chronic fibrosis or hypertrophy, as in patients with hypertrophic or dilated cardiomyopathy.</p>
<p>Brugada syndrome is characterized by ECG pattern of ST elevation in the right-sided precordial leads in the absence of structural heart disease or ischemia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig18-0885066611402165">Figure 18</xref>). This can lead to sustained VF and sudden death. Recently, idiopathic VF has been noted in patients with early repolarization pattern on the ECG (“early repolarization syndrome”). This syndrome has been classified as type 1 (J-point elevation in lateral leads), type 2 (J-point elevation in inferior and lateral leads) and type 3 (global J-point elevation in inferior, lateral, and right-sided precordial leads) that is associated with the highest risk of sudden death.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0885066611402165">73</xref></sup> Ventricular fibrillation storm associated with these syndromes can acutely be treated with quinidine and isoproterenol after making an accurate diagnosis. Long-term treatment would involve implantation of ICD. It has been proposed that these syndromes can be grouped together under the category of J-wave syndromes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0885066611402165">73</xref></sup>
</p>
<fig id="fig18-0885066611402165" position="float">
<label>Figure 18.</label>
<caption>
<p>Typical ECG pattern of ST elevation in V<sub>1</sub> to V<sub>3</sub> in a patient with Brugada syndrome.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611402165-fig18.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0885066611402165">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goldstein</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pica</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dixon</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>O'Neill</surname>
<given-names>WW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Patterns of coronary compromise leading to bradyarrhythmias and hypotension in inferior myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Coron Artery Dis</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0885066611402165">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Clemmensen</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bates</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Califf</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Complete atrioventricular block complicating inferior wall acute myocardial infarction treated with reperfusion therapy. TAMI Study Group</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0885066611402165">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goldberg</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zevallos</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yarzebski</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prognosis of acute myocardial infarction complicated by complete heart block (the Worcester Heart Attack Study)</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1135</fpage>–<lpage>1141</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0885066611402165">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harpaz</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Behar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Boyko</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kishon</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eldar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Complete atrioventricular block complicating acute myocardial infarction in the thrombolytic era. SPRINT Study Group and the Israeli Thrombolytic Survey Group. Secondary Prevention Reinfarction Israeli Nifedipine Trial</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1721</fpage>–<lpage>1728</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0885066611402165">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aplin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Engstrom</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vejlstrup</surname>
<given-names>NG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Clemmensen</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Torp-Pedersen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kober</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prognostic importance of complete atrioventricular block complicating acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>853</fpage>–<lpage>856</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0885066611402165">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rathore</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gersh</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Berger</surname>
<given-names>PB</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Acute myocardial infarction complicated by heart block in the elderly: prevalence and outcomes</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>141</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0885066611402165">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Epstein</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dimarco</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ellenbogen</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>ACC/AHA/HRS 2008 guidelines for device-based therapy of cardiac rhythm abnormalities: executive summary</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>934</fpage>–<lpage>955</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0885066611402165">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hohnloser</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kuck</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dorian</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prophylactic use of an implantable cardioverter-defibrillator after acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>351</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>2481</fpage>–<lpage>2488</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0885066611402165">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nagueh</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Spencer</surname>
<given-names>WH</given-names>
<suffix>3rd</suffix>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lakkis</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Complete heart block: determinants and clinical impact in patients with hypertrophic obstructive cardiomyopathy undergoing nonsurgical septal reduction therapy</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>296</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0885066611402165">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nee</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guttormsen</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gimelli</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Delayed complete heart block secondary to jailed first septal perforator</article-title>. <source>J Invasive Cardiol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>E338</fpage>–<lpage>E339</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0885066611402165">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Calvi</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Puzzangara</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pruiti</surname>
<given-names>GP</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Early conduction disorders following percutaneous aortic valve replacement</article-title>. <source>Pacing Clin Electrophysiol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>S126</fpage>–<lpage>S130</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0885066611402165">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huynh</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dalloul</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ghanbari</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Permanent pacemaker implantation following aortic valve replacement: current prevalence and clinical predictors</article-title>. <source>Pacing Clin Electrophysiol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1520</fpage>–<lpage>1525</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0885066611402165">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Koplan</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stevenson</surname>
<given-names>WG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Epstein</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aranki</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maisel</surname>
<given-names>WH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Development and validation of a simple risk score to predict the need for permanent pacing after cardiac valve surgery</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>795</fpage>–<lpage>801</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0885066611402165">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Glikson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dearani</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hyberger</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schaff</surname>
<given-names>HV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hammill</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hayes</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Indications, effectiveness, and long-term dependency in permanent pacing after cardiac surgery</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>80</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1309</fpage>–<lpage>1313</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0885066611402165">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Berdajs</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schurr</surname>
<given-names>UP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wagner</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seifert</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Turina</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Genoni</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Incidence and pathophysiology of atrioventricular block following mitral valve replacement and ring annuloplasty</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cardiothorac Surg</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0885066611402165">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tucker</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pyles</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bass</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Moller</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Permanent pacemaker for atrioventricular conduction block after operative repair of perimembranous ventricular septal defect</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1196</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0885066611402165">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Deeb</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eagle</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Complete atrioventricular block after valvular heart surgery and the timing of pacemaker implantation</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>649</fpage>–<lpage>651, A10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0885066611402165">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fletcher</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Amiodarone in patients with congestive heart failure and asymptomatic ventricular arrhythmia. Survival trial of antiarrhythmic therapy in congestive heart failure</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>333</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0885066611402165">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bongard</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marc</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Philippe</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jean-Louis</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Maryse</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Incidence rate of adverse drug reactions during long-term follow-up of patients newly treated with amiodarone</article-title>. <source>Am J Ther</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0885066611402165">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Essebag</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hadjis</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Platt</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pilote</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Amiodarone and the risk of bradyarrhythmia requiring permanent pacemaker in elderly patients with atrial fibrillation and prior myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0885066611402165">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Scheinman</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Levine</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cannom</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dose-ranging study of intravenous amiodarone in patients with life-threatening ventricular tachyarrhythmias. The Intravenous Amiodarone Multicenter Investigators Group</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3264</fpage>–<lpage>3272</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0885066611402165">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mattu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brady</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Robinson</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Electrocardiographic manifestations of hyperkalemia</article-title>. <source>Am J Emerg Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>721</fpage>–<lpage>729</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0885066611402165">
<label>23</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Parham</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Edelstein</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Unger</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mooney</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Therapeutic hypothermia for acute myocardial infarction: past, present, and future</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>7 suppl</issue>):<fpage>S234</fpage>–<lpage>S237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0885066611402165">
<label>24</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kandzari</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brodie</surname>
<given-names>BR</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Feasibility of endovascular cooling as an adjunct to primary percutaneous coronary intervention (results of the LOWTEMP pilot study)</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>636</fpage>–<lpage>639</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0885066611402165">
<label>25</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>DiNubile</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Calderwood</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Steinhaus</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Karchmer</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cardiac conduction abnormalities complicating native valve active infective endocarditis</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>1213</fpage>–<lpage>1217</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0885066611402165">
<label>26</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weisse</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>MY</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The relationship between new cardiac conduction defects and extension of valve infection in native valve endocarditis</article-title>. <source>Clin Cardiol</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0885066611402165">
<label>27</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Choussat</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Isnard</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Perivalvular abscesses associated with endocarditis; clinical features and prognostic factors of overall survival in a series of 233 cases. Perivalvular Abscesses French Multicentre Study</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>232</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0885066611402165">
<label>28</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Manzoor</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aftab</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Choksi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Lyme carditis: sequential electrocardiographic changes in response to antibiotic therapy</article-title>. <source>Int J Cardiol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>137</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0885066611402165">
<label>29</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pinto</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cardiac manifestations of Lyme disease</article-title>. <source>Med Clin North Am</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0885066611402165">
<label>30</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Khongphatthallayothin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chotivitayatarakorn</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Somchit</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mitprasart</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sakolsattayadorn</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thisyakorn</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Morbitz type I second degree AV block during recovery from dengue hemorrhagic fever</article-title>. <source>Southeast Asian J Trop Med Public Health</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>642</fpage>–<lpage>645</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0885066611402165">
<label>31</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Barold</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sischy</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Punzi</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kaplan</surname>
<given-names>EL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chessin</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Advanced atrioventricular block in a 39-year-old man with acute rheumatic fever</article-title>. <source>Pacing Clin Electrophysiol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>11 pt 1</issue>):<fpage>2025</fpage>–<lpage>2028</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0885066611402165">
<label>32</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Slade</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grover</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Benger</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Atropine-resistant bradycardia due to hyperkalaemia</article-title>. <source>Emerg Med J</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>612</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0885066611402165">
<label>33</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/NewsEvents/Newsroom/PressAnnouncements/2005/ucm108486.htm">http://www.fda.gov/NewsEvents/Newsroom/PressAnnouncements/2005/ucm108486.htm</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0885066611402165">
<label>34</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schuchert</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kuck</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of local steroid elution on chronic pacing threshold and impedance of endocardial pacemaker leads</article-title>. <source>Cardiology</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>240</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0885066611402165">
<label>35</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dohrmann</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goldschlager</surname>
<given-names>NF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Myocardial stimulation threshold in patients with cardiac pacemakers: effect of physiologic variables, pharmacologic agents, and lead electrodes</article-title>. <source>Cardiol Clin</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>527</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0885066611402165">
<label>36</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Surawicz</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chlebus</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reeves</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gettes</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Increase of ventricular excitability threshold by hyperpotassemia: possible cause of internal pacemaker failure</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>1965</year>;<volume>191</volume>:<fpage>1049</fpage>–<lpage>1054</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0885066611402165">
<label>37</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gettes</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shabetai</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Downs</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Surawicz</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of changes in potassium and calcium concentrations on diastolic threshold and strength-interval relationships of the human heart</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>. <year>1969</year>;<volume>167</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>705</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0885066611402165">
<label>38</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hughes</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
<name><surname>Tyers</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Torman</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name> 
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of acid-base imbalance on myocardial pacing thresholds</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>. <year>1975</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>743</fpage>–<lpage>746</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0885066611402165">
<label>39</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goldschlager</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Epstein</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Friedman</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gang</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krol</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Olshansky</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Environmental and drug effects on patients with pacemakers and implantable cardioverter/defibrillators: a practical guide to patient treatment</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>161</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>649</fpage>–<lpage>655</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0885066611402165">
<label>40</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tworek</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nazari</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ezri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bauman</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Interference by antiarrhythmic agents with function of electrical cardiac devices</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharm</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0885066611402165">
<label>41</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ben-Zur</surname>
<given-names>UM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gross</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goldberger</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tilkemeier</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weyman</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Furman</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Oversensing of pacemakers in the bipolar pacing configuration: paradoxic resolution with programming to unipolar sensing</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>128</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>617</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0885066611402165">
<label>42</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Secemsky</surname>
<given-names>SI</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hauser</surname>
<given-names>RG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Denes</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Edwards</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Unipolar sensing abnormalities: incidence and clinical significance of skeletal muscle interference and undersensing in 228 patients</article-title>. <source>Pacing Clin Electrophysiol</source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0885066611402165">
<label>43</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Barold</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ong</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Falkoff</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Heinle</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Inhibition of bipolar demand pacemaker by diaphragmatic myopotentials</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>4 pt 1</issue>):<fpage>679</fpage>–<lpage>683</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0885066611402165">
<label>44</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Thaker</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jongnarangsin</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liepa</surname>
<given-names>VV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thakur</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Electromagnetic interference with pacemakers caused by portable media players</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>538</fpage>–<lpage>544</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0885066611402165">
<label>45</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chatterjee</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sutton</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Davies</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Low intracardiac potentials in myocardial infarction as a cause of failure of inhibition of demand pacemakers</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>1968</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>7541</issue>):<fpage>511</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0885066611402165">
<label>46</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bertholet</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Materne</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dubois</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Artificial circus movement tachycardias: incidence, mechanisms, and prevention</article-title>. <source>Pacing Clin Electrophysiol</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3 pt 1</issue>):<fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>423</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0885066611402165">
<label>47</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mahmud</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Denker</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lehmann</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gilbert</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Akhtar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Functional characteristics of retrograde conduction in a pacing model of “endless loop tachycardia”</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1488</fpage>–<lpage>1499</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0885066611402165">
<label>48</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Porter</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Morton</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Denman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Influence of age and gender on the mechanism of supraventricular tachycardia</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>396</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0885066611402165">
<label>49</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chun</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liem</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sung</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of adenosine and verapamil in catecholamine-induced accelerated atrioventricular junctional rhythm: insights into the underlying mechanism</article-title>. <source>Pacing Clin Electrophysiol</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>6 pt 1</issue>):<fpage>866</fpage>–<lpage>870</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0885066611402165">
<label>50</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rosen</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reder</surname>
<given-names>RF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Does triggered activity have a role in the genesis of cardiac arrhythmias?</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>794</fpage>–<lpage>801</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0885066611402165">
<label>51</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Scheinman</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Atrial flutter: a review of its history, mechanisms, clinical features, and current therapy</article-title>. <source>Curr Probl Cardiol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0885066611402165">
<label>52</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Natale</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Newby</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pisano</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prospective randomized comparison of antiarrhythmic therapy versus first-line radiofrequency ablation in patients with atrial flutter</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1898</fpage>–<lpage>1904</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0885066611402165">
<label>53</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kistler</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roberts-Thomson</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Haqqani</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>P-wave morphology in focal atrial tachycardia: development of an algorithm to predict the anatomic site of origin</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1010</fpage>–<lpage>1017</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0885066611402165">
<label>54</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chugh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Oral</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lemola</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence, mechanisms, and clinical significance of macroreentrant atrial tachycardia during and following left atrial ablation for atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>464</fpage>–<lpage>471</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0885066611402165">
<label>55</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Miyasaka</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barnes</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gersh</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Secular trends in incidence of atrial fibrillation in Olmsted County, Minnesota, 1980 to 2000, and implications on the projections for future prevalence</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0885066611402165">
<label>56</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jespersen</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vaage-Nilsen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The significance of myocardial ischaemia and verapamil treatment on the prevalence of supraventricular tachyarrhythmias in patients recovering from acute myocardial infarction. Danish Study Group on Verapamil in Myocardial Infarction</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1427</fpage>–<lpage>1430</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0885066611402165">
<label>57</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pizzetti</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Turazza</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Franzosi</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Incidence and prognostic significance of atrial fibrillation in acute myocardial infarction: the GISSI-3 data</article-title>. <source>Heart</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>527</fpage>–<lpage>532</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0885066611402165">
<label>58</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rathore</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Berger</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weinfurt</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Acute myocardial infarction complicated by atrial fibrillation in the elderly: prevalence and outcomes</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>969</fpage>–<lpage>974</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0885066611402165">
<label>59</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Behar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zahavi</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goldbourt</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reicher-Reiss</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term prognosis of patients with paroxysmal atrial fibrillation complicating acute myocardial infarction. SPRINT Study Group</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0885066611402165">
<label>60</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sakata</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kurihara</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Iwamori</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical and prognostic significance of atrial fibrillation in acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>80</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1522</fpage>–<lpage>1527</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0885066611402165">
<label>61</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nielsen</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Andersen</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gram-Hansen</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sorensen</surname>
<given-names>HT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klausen</surname>
<given-names>IC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The relationship between ECG signs of atrial infarction and the development of supraventricular arrhythmias in patients with acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0885066611402165">
<label>62</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kyriakidis</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barbetseas</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Antonopoulos</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Skouros</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tentolouris</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Toutouzas</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Early atrial arrhythmias in acute myocardial infarction. Role of the sinus node artery</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>944</fpage>–<lpage>947</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0885066611402165">
<label>63</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>White</surname>
<given-names>HD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wilcox</surname>
<given-names>RG</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>New atrial fibrillation after acute myocardial infarction independently predicts death: the GUSTO-III experience</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>140</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>878</fpage>–<lpage>885</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0885066611402165">
<label>64</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zimetbaum</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Josephson</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McDonald</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Incidence and predictors of myocardial infarction among patients with atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1223</fpage>–<lpage>1227</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0885066611402165">
<label>65</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>ZJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Croft</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Giles</surname>
<given-names>WH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mensah</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Sudden cardiac death in the United States, 1989 to 1998</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>2158</fpage>–<lpage>2163</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0885066611402165">
<label>66</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Terkelsen</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sorensen</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kaltoft</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and significance of accelerated idioventricular rhythm in patients with ST-elevation myocardial infarction treated with primary percutaneous coronary intervention</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1641</fpage>–<lpage>1646</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0885066611402165">
<label>67</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Badhwar</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Scheinman</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Idiopathic ventricular tachycardia: diagnosis and management</article-title>. <source>Curr Probl Cardiol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0885066611402165">
<label>68</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zipes</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Camm</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Borggrefe</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>ACC/AHA/ESC 2006 Guidelines for management of patients with ventricular arrhythmias and the prevention of sudden cardiac death: a report of the American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Task Force and the European Society of Cardiology Committee for Practice Guidelines (writing committee to develop Guidelines for Management of Patients With Ventricular Arrhythmias and the Prevention of Sudden Cardiac Death): developed in collaboration with the European Heart Rhythm Association and the Heart Rhythm Society</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e385</fpage>–<lpage>e484</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0885066611402165">
<label>69</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goldschlager</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Epstein</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Naccarelli</surname>
<given-names>GV</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A practical guide for clinicians who treat patients with amiodarone: 2007</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1250</fpage>–<lpage>1259</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0885066611402165">
<label>70</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ezekowitz</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rowe</surname>
<given-names>BH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dryden</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Systematic review: implantable cardioverter defibrillators for adults with left ventricular systolic dysfunction</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>147</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0885066611402165">
<label>71</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aliot</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stevenson</surname>
<given-names>WG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Almendral-Garrote</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>EHRA/HRS Expert Consensus on Catheter Ablation of Ventricular Arrhythmias: developed in a partnership with the European Heart Rhythm Association (EHRA), a Registered Branch of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC), and the Heart Rhythm Society (HRS); in collaboration with the American College of Cardiology (ACC) and the American Heart Association (AHA)</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>886</fpage>–<lpage>933</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0885066611402165">
<label>72</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reddy</surname>
<given-names>VY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Neuzil</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prophylactic catheter ablation for the prevention of defibrillator therapy</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>357</volume>(<issue>26</issue>):<fpage>2657</fpage>–<lpage>2665</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0885066611402165">
<label>73</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Antzelevitch</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>GX</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>J wave syndromes</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>549</fpage>–<lpage>558</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>