<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IBE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spibe</journal-id>
<journal-title>Indoor and Built Environment</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1420-326X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1423-0070</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1420326X11420014</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1420326X11420014</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Quantitative Reduction Method of Draft in High-Rise Buildings, Using Revolving Doors</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Joonghoon</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1420326X11420014">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>Taeyon</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1420326X11420014">b</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1420326X11420014">c</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1420326X11420014"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Doosam</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1420326X11420014">d</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Jeong Tai</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1420326X11420014">c</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1420326X11420014"><label>a</label>Technology Research Center, Samsung C&amp;T Corporation, Seoul 137-857, Republic of Korea</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1420326X11420014"><label>b</label>Department of Architectural Engineering, Kyung Hee University, Yongin 446-701, Republic of Korea</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1420326X11420014"><label>c</label>Building Technologies Department, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, CA 94720, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff4-1420326X11420014"><label>d</label>Department of Architectural Engineering, Sungkyunkwan University, Suwon 440-746, Republic of Korea</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1420326X11420014">Dr. Taeyon Hwang, Department of Architectural Engineering, Kyung Hee University, Yongin 446-701, Republic of Korea, Building Technologies Department, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, CA 94720, USA. Tel. +82 31 201 2852, Fax +82 31 202 8181, E-Mail <email>hwang@khu.ac.kr</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue on: Sustainable Development for Future Building</issue-title>
<issue-title>Edited by: Jeong Tai Kim</issue-title>
<fpage>79</fpage>
<lpage>91</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s), 2011. Reprints and permissions:http://www.sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">International Society of the Built Environment</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Drafts in high-rise buildings caused by the stack effect can cause noise and reduce the performances of ventilation, cooling and heating systems as well as the building’s energy efficiency. Revolving doors are generally used as a method to reduce drafts; however, the effect would only be limited to the main entrance on the lobby floor.</p>
<p>Revolving doors have two main advantages; that their opening areas are seldom changed by people passing through the doors, and the doors do not have the pressure-related functional problems. Considering these advantages, this study examined a quantitative draft reduction method using revolving doors in high-rise buildings. This method would contribute to the design process to install revolving doors to buildings and consists of 10 steps with two key steps of selecting the installation locations of revolving doors and to calculate the air leakage area of revolving doors. Verification through simulations showed that, based on this process, the use of revolving doors could reduce the drafts in buildings by a quantified target value. Furthermore, the possibility of problems due to the stack effect in the other walls of buildings would decrease due to the pressure sharing of the additional walls fitted to revolving doors.</p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Stack effect</kwd>
<kwd>Revolving doors</kwd>
<kwd>Drafts</kwd>
<kwd>Simulations</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1420326X11420014" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>The construction of high-rise buildings inevitably brings about the strong stack effect. This, in turn, increases the strength of problems related to the stack effect. Thus, responses to the stack effect are emerging as an important technical item in high-rise buildings. Natural ventilation of building based on stack effect and mechanical ventilation is now an important design feature in high rise buildings in the Far East such as Hong Kong, China and Korea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1420326X11420014">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1420326X11420014">3</xref>]; also for low-rise buildings such as in the UK [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1420326X11420014">4</xref>].</p>
<p>The two major causes of the problems related to the stack effect are the unbalanced distribution of stack-effect pressure and the excessive generation of drafts.</p>
<p>The former refers to the case that the pressure difference between the inside and outside of a building, which is determined by the building’s height (distance from the neutral pressure level) and by the temperature difference between the inside and outside, is excessively concentrated on some walls inside the building. Stack-effect pressure is distributed to the building envelope and multiple interior walls, depending on the relative air leakage areas among the walls.</p>
<p>The latter refers to the case that, because the air-tightness of the building is low, the drafts through the walls of the building increase. In particular, as the increase in drafts can directly affect the performance of air-conditioning systems in high-rise buildings, drafts must be reduced for a comfortable interior environment through effective control of ventilation, cooling and heating systems. Moreover, increased drafts increase the energy load of the building.</p>
<p>Considering these facts, the characteristics on the two major causes of stack-effect problems are determined by the air leakage area distribution of the building. Many previous studies on the air leakage area distribution of buildings have been performed to better understand the stack effect and to search for effective countermeasures on the problems.</p>
<p>Tamura analyzed the stack effect to control smoke movement during a fire and demonstrated, using the thermal draft coefficient (TDC) concept, that the stack-effect pressure distribution was determined by the air leakage area distribution among the building envelope and interior walls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1420326X11420014">5</xref>]. The concept of smoke movement and stack effect has also been an important feature for air movement and heating in traditional houses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1420326X11420014">6</xref>]. By measuring three high-rise office buildings with open-floor plans, Tamura et al. found that the pressure difference shared by the exterior walls accounted for 60–80% of the total stack effect-pressure and that the interior walls of the buildings were not as airtight as the building envelope [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1420326X11420014">7</xref>]. Other studies measured the general range of air leakage volume through the building envelopes on multiple office buildings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1420326X11420014">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1420326X11420014">9</xref>]. Another study measured 23 buildings and found that the pressure differences at the main entrances on the first floor accounted for 30–70% of the maximum value of stack-effect pressure in the buildings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1420326X11420014">10</xref>].</p>
<p>The effect of south façade stack effect and their relative contribution to cooling through increased ventilation the cross-ventilation flow paths could satisfy most of the summer cooling ventilation requirements was investigated by BRE in the UK [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1420326X11420014">11</xref>]. Passive stacks can enhance the cooling ventilation of the space during warm and still days, as intended by the design, and may also have the potential to assist night-time cooling due to their thermally massive structure. The effect of balconies on the airflow movement and ventilation performance within buildings has also been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1420326X11420014">12</xref>].</p>
<p>Some studies classified the general air leakage performance of each component of buildings. First, Tamura et al. measured the air leakage volumes through the average width between doors and between doors and door frames for elevators and stairway doors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1420326X11420014">13</xref>], and they measured the air leakage volumes through the windows and walls of houses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1420326X11420014">14</xref>]. Klote et al. represented the airtightness of major components of office buildings, such as building envelopes and doors as the ratio between the air leakage area and the total area of a component [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1420326X11420014">15</xref>].</p>
<p>Taking the note that the airtightness of each building component (the air leakage area distribution of the building) is the key factor that determines the drafts of a building, some studies examined the variances of the stack effect according to the conditions of building components that act as the resistance to drafts. Yu et al. investigated the stack effects in high-rise buildings according to the layout of the lobby floor and the ratio of window area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1420326X11420014">16</xref>]. Koo et al. examined the effects of architectural plans on the stack effect for high-rise residential buildings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1420326X11420014">17</xref>].</p>
<p>Many studies have investigated the relationships between the stack effect and the air leakage area distribution of buildings and have recognised their importance. We cannot find any studies, however, that attempted to respond to stack-effect problems by adjusting quantitatively the air leakage areas of major building components.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, revolving doors are a typical countermeasure on the stack effect in high-rise buildings. Revolving doors are usually installed at the main entrance on the lobby floor. The original purpose for installing revolving doors was efficient heating of the lobby by minimising the infiltration of external air due to frequent access. The revolving doors’ greatest advantages are that they allow effective responses to drafts by minimising the variance of the door opening area when people pass through and that they have almost no pressure-related functional problems. However, the draft-reduction effect of revolving doors at the aspect of the whole building is limited because they are locally applied in general.</p>
<p>The purpose of this study is to maximise and quantify the draft-reduction effect of revolving doors as a stack-effect countermeasure. For this purpose, this study investigated a quantitative application method for revolving doors, taking into consideration their performance advantages and the relationships between the stack-effect characteristics and the air leakage area distribution of buildings. The effects of this application method were verified using a simulation analysis technique.</p></sec>
<sec id="sec2-1420326X11420014"><title>Quantitative Application Method for Revolving Doors</title>
<sec id="sec3-1420326X11420014"><title>Outline</title>
<p>The quantitative application method for revolving doors is a design process to install revolving doors in order to effectively reduce drafts in a building. Quantitative characteristics are given, in this method, to the conventional usage of revolving doors as a stack-effect countermeasure. It is possible to reduce drafts by the quantified target value using revolving doors in this design process.</p>
<p>Since revolving doors have no pressure-related functional problems, the additional walls connecting to revolving doors would share the pressure from the other walls of a building without any secondary problems. Sharing the pressure would reduce the possibility of problems by the unbalanced distribution of stack-effect pressure at the other walls.</p>
<p>The design process consists of 10 steps, including the precondition step and two key steps, which include selecting the installation locations for the revolving doors and to calculate their air leakage areas for the quantitative control of drafts. The design process is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1420326X11420014">Figure 1</xref>, and its characteristics are summarised as follows:
<list id="list1-1420326X11420014" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The design process is a quantified version of previous application method of revolving doors as a stack-effect countermeasure. The quantification is to reduce drafts inside a building by a target value compared with a value prior to the installation of revolving doors. The quantitative reduction of drafts would be carried out by adjusting the airflow resistance inside the building through the installation of revolving doors, which are applied as an additional wall.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The application of this countermeasure can be determined on the basis of whether there are stack-effect problems after completion and occupation of the building. This would prevent the excessive application of countermeasures for the stack effect, which can occur by predictions at the time of planning. Furthermore, this would also minimise the cost due to later supplementary countermeasures. For post-application of the countermeasure, however, care must be taken for the precondition of the design process.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The design process includes a stack-effect countermeasure targeting the scope of the whole building. Thus, the secondary problems due to the pressure transfer among the walls of buildings would not occur, and these are the general characteristics of the traditional countermeasures targeting the small parts of the building. Pressure transfer refers to the variance of the pressure distribution in each part of the building due to the movement of the neutral pressure level of the building or the changed pressure shares of walls by the application of the countermeasures targeting the small parts of the building.</p></list-item></list>
<fig id="fig1-1420326X11420014" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Process to apply revolving doors.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-fig1.tif"/></fig></p></sec>
<sec id="sec4-1420326X11420014"><title>Details of the Design Process</title>
<p>Each step of the design process is described in detail below (refer to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1420326X11420014">Figure 1</xref>).
<list id="list1-1420326X11420014" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Step 1: Spare spaces for installation of revolving doors would need to be secured during the planning phase of the building in order to install revolving doors selected through this design process in case stack-effect problems occur after completion and occupation of the building. This is a precondition in this design process.</p>
<p>In order to secure spare spaces, the selection of the installation locations of revolving doors, which is Step 5 of this design process, needs to be done first. The installation locations of revolving doors are finally determined in Step 5 after considering the actual building characteristics, such as the problem occurrence characteristics and the building usage patterns, etc., after completion and occupation of the building. Details of the selection method for the installation locations of revolving doors will be described in Step 5. Meanwhile, in order to prevent the quantitative control of drafts from being destroyed by opening the entrances, it would be more effective to design the entrances to face the outside as revolving doors, in advance. In addition, to improve the accuracy of quantitative control of drafts, airtight work would be needed for airflow paths other than the main airflow paths of the building on which revolving doors are installed as an additional wall. The airflow paths that would require airtight work include the slabs between floors and the access paths to the staircase and the emergency elevator shaft.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Step 2: The occurrence of stack-effect problems in the building and their levels are checked and the decision on whether or not to perform this design process is made.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Step 3: In this design process, to reduce drafts in the building by a target value, additional walls with revolving doors are installed on the main airflow paths of the building and the total air leakage area of each main airflow path consisting of multiple walls should be adjusted by the additional wall. Thus, to determine the appropriate air leakage areas of the additional walls with revolving doors, the air leakage area of each component on the main airflow paths, such as the building envelope and interior walls would need to be measured. Furthermore, to analyze the effect on the error occurrence of reduction goal, the air leakage areas of other components, such as the slabs between floors and the emergency staircase doors, would be measured. The air leakage area here signifies the equivalent air leakage area that is written as air leakage area for convenience.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Step 4: No established criteria exist to predict the possibility of problems caused by the stack effect. Furthermore, considering that the characteristics of the stack effect and related problems could vary depending on the combination of various items related to building performance, it would be practically impossible to establish general judgment criteria.</p>
<p>Therefore, in this design process, the draft reduction goal of the building is set based on the draft level before the implementation of the countermeasure, and the air leakage areas of the additional walls with revolving doors should be determined based on the reduction goal. The draft reduction goal would be determined considering the actual conditions of the building such as the cooling and heating energy reduction goal and the range of wind velocity inside the building about which complaints are raised.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Step 5: The draft reduction according to the reduction goal would be carried out by adjusting the total air leakage area of each main airflow path distributed within the building. In other words, assuming that <italic>Q</italic> in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1420326X11420014">Equation (1)</xref> is the draft that passes through each main airflow path, <italic>αA</italic> would be adjusted with the other items (<italic>g</italic>, <italic>γ</italic> and Δ<italic>P</italic>) that determine <italic>Q</italic> being fixed. For example, in order to reduce <italic>Q</italic> by 50%, <italic>αA</italic> would be reduced by 50%. Here, <italic>αA</italic> would be the total air leakage area for the entire scope of the relevant main airflow path to be adjusted by the air leakage area of the additional walls with revolving doors:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1420326X11420014"><label>(1)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>where, <italic>Q</italic> is the airflow rate (the draft rate) (m<sup>3</sup>/s), <italic>α</italic> is the airflow coefficient (−), <italic>A</italic> is the air leakage area (m<sup>2</sup>), <italic>αA</italic> is the equivalent air leakage area (m<sup>2</sup>), <italic>γ</italic> is the air density (kgf/m<sup>3</sup>), <italic>g</italic> is the gravitational constant (≒9.8 m/s<sup>2</sup>), and Δ<italic>P</italic> is the pressure difference (Pa).</p>
<p>In this process, the range between the elevator shaft and the outdoor on each floor is set as a main airflow path (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1420326X11420014">Figure 2</xref>), which has multiple walls, such as the building envelope and interior walls. Δ<italic>P</italic> in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1420326X11420014">Equation (1)</xref> is fixed by adjusting the total air leakage area of every main airflow path of the building at the same rate. Here, Δ<italic>P</italic> is the difference of absolute pressure between the elevator shaft and the outdoor air on each floor caused by the stack effect. To fix Δ<italic>P</italic> would mean that the neutral pressure level of the building does not change by the application of revolving doors. The neutral pressure level would change when the air leakage area distribution of the building was modified. In this process, in order to prevent the variance of the air leakage area distribution of the building, the total air leakage area of every main airflow path should be adjusted at the same rate. From this principle, the revolving doors should be basically installed on every main airflow path of the building.
<fig id="fig2-1420326X11420014" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Method of setting up the main airflow paths to install revolving doors.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Meanwhile, on the lobby floor and transfer floors on which elevators with different operating floors coexist, more complex main airflow paths than typical floors are formed. Thus, it is very difficult to adjust <italic>αA</italic> by simply setting the range between elevator shaft and outdoor air as one of the main airflow paths.</p>
<p>In these cases, multiple main airflow paths are set for each range between indoor space and each elevator shaft and then the <italic>αA</italic> of each range is adjusted (refer to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1420326X11420014">Figure 2</xref>). Since the draft through the building envelope is not considered here, the draft reduction ratios on the relevant floors become different from those of other typical floors and the neutral pressure level may move a little. This would be negligible, however, considering its effect on the whole building, and its effect would become smaller with an increase in building height.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1420326X11420014">Figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1420326X11420014">Equations (2)</xref>–(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8-1420326X11420014">8</xref>) show an example of calculating the required performance; that is to say, the air leakage area of an additional wall with a revolving door installed on a main airflow path. In the example shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1420326X11420014">Figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1420326X11420014">Equations (2)</xref>–(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8-1420326X11420014">8</xref>), the additional wall with a revolving door is installed on the main airflow path that passes through the two walls of the building envelope and one interior wall. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1420326X11420014">Equation (2)</xref> calculates the draft through the main airflow path before the installation of the revolving door, and <italic>αA</italic><sub>1</sub> is the total air leakage area for the entire range of the main airflow path (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1420326X11420014">Figure 3(a)</xref>). <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-1420326X11420014">Equation (4)</xref> calculates the draft through the main airflow path after installation of the revolving door, and <italic>αA</italic><sub>2</sub> is the adjusted total air leakage area for the entire range of the main airflow paths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1420326X11420014">Figure 3(b)</xref>). If the draft reduction goal is 50% of the present, the air leakage area C of the additional wall with a revolving door installed on the main airflow path is calculated from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula6-1420326X11420014">Equations (6)</xref>–(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8-1420326X11420014">8</xref>).
<fig id="fig3-1420326X11420014" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Methods to install revolving doors and to calculate the air leakage area of the additional wall</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-fig3.tif"/></fig></p>
<p><list id="list2-1420326X11420014" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>a : Air leakage area of envelope (m<sup>2</sup>)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>b : Air leakage area of shaft wall (m<sup>2</sup>)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>c : Air leakage area of additional wall with a revolving door (m<sup>2</sup>)</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>with revolving doors.</p>
<p>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-1420326X11420014"><label>(2)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-1420326X11420014"><label>(3)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-1420326X11420014"><label>(4)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-1420326X11420014"><label>(5)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-1420326X11420014"><label>(6)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-1420326X11420014"><label>(7)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8-1420326X11420014"><label>(8)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-eq8.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Steps 6–8: Simulations are conducted using the air leakage areas measured in Step 3 and the air leakage areas of the additional walls with revolving doors calculated in Step 5 to identify the error of the reduction goal, and the air leakage areas of the additional walls with revolving doors is adjusted if the error is large. The error of the reduction goal is determined by the draft through the building envelope on the lobby floor and transfer floors, the draft through the slabs between floors, and the draft through the emergency staircase door, etc.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Step 9: Revolving doors appropriate for the required performance are selected and installed. Secondary error may occur at the time of installation by the actual usage conditions of the building and the airflow coefficient of the opening of revolving doors. In these cases, the air leakage area of the additional wall with revolving doors would be fine-tuned using gaskets. Other parts of the additional wall, except the revolving doors, would need airtight work.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Step 10: The final draft reduction ratio would be determined through the measurement of the outdoor air infiltration volume, the wind velocity inside the building, etc. A building management method to maintain the reduction ratio is proposed.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec5-1420326X11420014"><title>Process Verification by Simulations</title>
<p>As stated above, the key steps of the design process are the selection method of the installation locations of revolving doors through identification of the main airflow paths in the building and the derivation method of the air leakage area of the additional walls with revolving doors. In this section, the usefulness of these methods is verified using a simulation analysis technique. The usefulness of these methods can be verified by the change of the location of neutral pressure level and the draft reduction ratio of the whole building.</p>
<sec id="sec6-1420326X11420014"><title>Outline of Simulation</title>
<p>
<list id="list1-1420326X11420014" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Target building</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>CONTAMW was used for the simulations. The target building has five floors underground and 30 floors above ground. The characteristics of the general office buildings were surveyed for use in the modelling simulations. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1420326X11420014">Table 1</xref> shows the outline of the target building. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1420326X11420014">Figure 4</xref> shows the plans and the elevation of the target building. The target building has a plan of the open-floor type with a central core, which consists of an emergency staircase, four passenger elevators, two shuttle elevators, and one emergency elevator. The passenger elevators are divided into two shafts run between the 1st floor and the 30th floor above ground. The shuttle elevators run between the 5th floor underground and the 1st floor above ground, and the emergency elevator runs on all the floors.
<fig id="fig4-1420326X11420014" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Plans and elevation of the target building.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-fig4.tif"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-1420326X11420014" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Outline of the target building</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1420326X11420014" xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<td>Items</td>
<td align="center">Contents</td>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Building type</td>
<td>Office.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Floors</td>
<td>30 floors above ground and 5 floors underground.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Plan type</td>
<td>Open-floor type with a central core.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Elevator plan</td>
<td>Four passenger (1F ∼ 30F, 2 per shaft).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Two shuttle (B5 ∼ 1F).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>One emergency (B5 ∼ 30F).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Staircase</td>
<td>Sharing a hall with the emergency elevator on every floor.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Setting a door to the emergency elevator hall and a door to the staircase on every floor.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Parking areas</td>
<td>B5 ∼ B1 (five floors underground connected by ramps).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1F main entrance</td>
<td>A vestibule type with a double swing door and a revolving door.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>The vestibule space that leads to the emergency staircase is also used as the emergency elevator hall on every floor. The main entrance on the lobby floor (1F) is a vestibule type with a double swing door and a revolving door. Underground parking areas are connected with the outdoor through the ramps.
<list id="list1-1420326X11420014" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Simulation conditions</p></list-item></list></p>
<p>The basic input conditions for simulations are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1420326X11420014">Table 2</xref>. The outdoor air was set to −11.9°C assuming the bitter-cold period when the stack effect could be severe, and the indoor temperature was set to 22°C. It was assumed that there was no change in the absolute pressures of the interior zones by air conditioning. The air leakage area of the building envelope was set to 200 mm<sup>2</sup> m<sup>−2</sup>. The air leakage areas of the 1F main entrance and the interior doors were set by referring to the CONTAMW library, measurement data and the ASHRAE data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1420326X11420014">18</xref>].
<table-wrap id="table2-1420326X11420014" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Basic input conditions for simulations</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1420326X11420014" xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th>Items</th>
<th>Contents</th>
<th/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Temperatures</td>
<td>Envelope</td>
<td>Outdoor: −11.9°C, Indoor: 22°C</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Air leakage  areas</td>
<td/>
<td>200mm<sup>2</sup> m<sup>−2</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Interior doors</td>
<td>Elevator doors:  4.8 × 10<sup>4</sup> mm<sup>2</sup>/item</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Doors to the emergency elevator  halls: 10 mm<sup>2</sup>/item</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Doors to the staircase:  1.6 × 10<sup>3</sup> mm<sup>2</sup>/item</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>1F main entrance</td>
<td>Double swing door:  3.2 × 10<sup>3</sup> mm<sup>2</sup>/item</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Revolving door:  1.088 × 10<sup>3</sup> mm<sup>2</sup>/item</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Since the main purpose of simulations was to verify the methods for the selection of the installation locations of revolving doors and for the derivation of the air leakage areas of revolving doors, the error-generating factors for the target reduction ratio were minimised in the basic conditions of <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1420326X11420014">Table 2</xref>. That is, they were designed in such a way that no draft through the slabs between floors will be generated and that the airtightness performance of the access door to the emergency elevator hall on every floor was reinforced. It was assumed that interior walls had no air leakage area, except the air leakage areas of doors. The simulation cases for verification of the design process were set to reduce the draft of the whole building by 10%, 20%, 30%, 40% and 50% of the draft before application of revolving doors.</p>
<p>The revolving doors were installed as an additional wall type at the shuttle elevator entrance on each underground floor, the shuttle elevator entrance on the lobby floor, the passenger elevator hall entrance on the lobby floor and the passenger elevator hall entrance on each typical floor. The revolving doors were installed on both sides of the elevator hall considering the plan characteristics for the passenger elevator halls on the lobby floor and the typical floors. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1420326X11420014">Table 3</xref> shows the air leakage areas of the revolving doors calculated to achieve the respective reduction goals. It was assumed that the additional walls with revolving doors had no air leakage areas, except those of the revolving doors.
<table-wrap id="table3-1420326X11420014" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Outline of the target building</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1420326X11420014" xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th rowspan="2">Cases</th>
<th rowspan="2">Draft reduction ratios (%)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Air leakage areas of revolving doors (mm<sup>2</sup>/item)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Entrances of shuttle elevators (B5∼1F)</th>
<th>Entrance of passenger elevator hall (1F, both sides)</th>
<th>Entrances of passenger elevator halls (2F∼30F, both sides)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Basic case</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>–</td>
<td>–</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Case 1</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>1.9822 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
<td>1.9822 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
<td>0.6960 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Case 2</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>1.2800 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
<td>1.2800 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
<td>0.4494 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Case 3</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>0.9410 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
<td>0.9410 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
<td>0.3304 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Case 4</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>0.7200 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
<td>0.7200 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
<td>0.2528 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Case 5</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>0.5543 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
<td>0.5543 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
<td>0.1946 × 10<sup>5</sup></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p></sec>
<sec id="sec7-1420326X11420014"><title>Simulation results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1420326X11420014">Figures 5</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1420326X11420014">8</xref> show the simulation results. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1420326X11420014">Figure 5</xref> shows the total airflow rate (total draft volume) of the whole building in each case and the draft reduction ratios based on the basic case. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1420326X11420014">Figure 6</xref> shows the correlation between the target reduction ratio and the actual reduction ratio. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1420326X11420014">Figure 7</xref> shows the locations of the neutral pressure levels in the passenger elevator shaft and the shuttle elevator shaft and shows the airflow rate through each elevator shaft. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1420326X11420014">Figure 8</xref> shows the pressure distribution of each wall on each floor of the target building.
<fig id="fig5-1420326X11420014" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Drafts of the whole building and draft reduction ratios.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-fig5.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig6-1420326X11420014" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Correlation between target reduction ratio and actual reduction ratio.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-fig6.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig7-1420326X11420014" position="float"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><p>Neutral pressure level in each shaft.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-fig7.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig8-1420326X11420014" position="float"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><p>Pressure distributions of the target building.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1420326X11420014-fig8.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1420326X11420014">Figure 5</xref>, the actual draft reduction ratios after the installation of revolving doors would be generally greater than the target draft reduction ratios, and the differences range would be from 2.1% at the minimum to 5.9% at the maximum. These differences are generated by the effect of drafts that occur on the airflow paths other than the main airflow paths and by the effect of drafts through the building envelopes not to be considered as the main airflow paths on some floors. In other words, the causes of these differences are the exclusion of drafts through the envelope when the main airflow paths are set for installation of revolving doors on the lobby floor, and the occurrence of drafts through the emergency elevator shaft and the staircase in all the floors. Considering the building height (30 floors), however, the differences are not large. The differences will decrease if the height of the target building increases. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1420326X11420014">Figure 6</xref> shows the high correlation between the actual and target draft reduction ratios.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1420326X11420014">Figure 5</xref> shows the tendency that the difference between the actual and target reduction ratios would become smaller when there were less air leakage area of the additional wall with revolving doors, in other words, when the target reduction ratio was enhanced. The reason for this phenomenon appears to be that as the airtightness of the additional wall with revolving doors increases, the stack-effect pressure shared by the additional wall would also increase thus increasing the relative influence of the additional wall compared with other walls. Because the pressure differences (Δ<italic>P</italic>) on other walls would decrease when there was a higher pressure share on the additional wall with revolving doors, the drafts (<italic>Q</italic>) through other walls would decrease as shown in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1420326X11420014">Equation (1)</xref>. Thus, after all, the effect of the error causing factors would become smaller.</p>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1420326X11420014">Figure 7</xref>, most of the drafts of the whole building would pass through the passenger elevator shafts, and the neutral pressure levels of the passenger elevator shafts and the shuttle elevator shafts practically would not change much by the installation of revolving doors. This means that there would not be any practical changes in air leakage area distribution of the building due to the installation of revolving doors, and this result has thus verified that the method to select the installation locations of revolving doors and the method to derive the air leakage areas of the revolving doors are valid.</p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1420326X11420014">Figure 8</xref>, the pressure differences on other walls are decreased by the application of the additional wall connected with revolving doors, and the reduction level of the pressure difference would be higher when the air leakage area of the additional wall becomes smaller. This suggests that as the airtightness in the additional wall connected with revolving doors becomes higher, the additional wall would share more of the pressure difference from other walls, thus the possibility of stack-effect problems in other walls would decrease. Consequently, because the pressure transfer occurs from other walls to the additional wall connected with revolving doors, secondary problems by pressure transfer are not expected considering the performance characteristics of revolving doors.</p></sec></sec>
<sec id="sec8-1420326X11420014" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In this study, in order to effectively reduce the drafts caused by the stack effect in high-rise buildings, the quantitative application method of revolving doors was investigated based on the performance characteristics of revolving doors and the relationships between the air leakage area distribution and the stack-effect generation characteristics of a building. The efficiency of this stack-effect countermeasure was verified using a simulation analysis technique. The important findings from this study are summarised below.
<list id="list1-1420326X11420014" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The drafts in the building could be effectively reduced by the quantified target value through the application of the proposed countermeasure including two key technical issues: the installation locations of revolving doors and the air leakage areas of revolving doors.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The air leakage area distribution of the building and the neutral pressure levels in the shafts would not practically change much, when the air leakage areas in these spaces was limited to the same ratio by checking the main airflow path between the elevator shaft and the outdoor and between the elevator shaft and the indoor space. In other words, there would not be secondary problems caused by the pressure transfer between the upper and lower parts of the neutral pressure level due to the movement of the neutral pressure level when the proposed countermeasure was applied.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>It was confirmed that, since the additional wall connected with revolving doors shares the pressure differences on other walls, there would not be any secondary problems by the pressure transfer between the walls of the building, and the possibility of stack-effect problems in other walls due to the unbalanced distribution of stack-effect pressure would decrease when the proposed countermeasure was applied.</p></list-item></list></p></sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><title>Acknowledgment</title>
<p>This work was supported by the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) grant funded by the Korea government (MEST), (No. 2011-0001031).</p></ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1420326X11420014"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yik</surname><given-names>FWH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lun</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Energy saving by utilizing natural ventilation in public housing in Hong Kong</article-title>. <source>Indoor Built Environ</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1420326X11420014"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Developments in strategies used for natural and mechanical ventilation in China</article-title>. <source>Indoor Built Environ</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1420326X11420014"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Seok</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A study on the application of a ceiling plenum ventilation system in an apartment house</article-title>. <source>Indoor Built Environ</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1420326X11420014"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mavrogianni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mumovic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On the use of windcatchers in schools: climate change, occupancy patterns, and adaptation strategies</article-title>. <source>Indoor Built Environ</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1420326X11420014"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Smoke movement and control in high-rise buildings: Quincy</source>. <publisher-loc>Massachusetts, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Fire Protection Association</publisher-name> <year>1994</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1420326X11420014"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Smoke flow in Chinese Kangs</article-title>. <source>Indoor Built Environ</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1420326X11420014"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pressure differences caused by chimney effect in three high buildings</article-title>. <source>ASHRAE Trans</source> <year>1967</year>; <volume>73</volume>(<issue>Part 2</issue>):<fpage>II.1.1</fpage>–<lpage>II.1.10</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1420326X11420014"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Studies on exterior wall airtightness and air infiltration of tall buildings</article-title>. <source>ASHRAE Trans</source> <year>1973</year>; <volume>82</volume>(<issue>Part 1</issue>):<fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1420326X11420014"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Persily</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Grot</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pressurization testing of federal buildings, Measured air leakage of buildings</article-title>. <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Trechsel</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagus</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group> <source>ASTM STP 904</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>. <publisher-name>American Society for Testing and Materials</publisher-name> <year>1986</year>, <fpage>184</fpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1420326X11420014"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>ASHRAE</collab><source>Infiltration and Ventilation; in Handbook of Fundamentals</source>. <publisher-loc>Atlanta, GA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Society of Heating, Refrigerating, and Air-Conditioning Engineers</publisher-name> <year>1993</year>, <fpage>23.1</fpage>–<lpage>23.23</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1420326X11420014"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ní Riain</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolokotroni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Littler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cooling effectiveness of south façade passive stacks in a naturally ventilated office building</article-title>. <source>case study: Indoor Built Environ</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1420326X11420014"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ai</surname><given-names>ZT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>The effect of balconies on ventilation performance of low-rise buildings</article-title>: <source>Indoor Built Environ</source> <month>May</month> <year>2011</year>; <comment>doi: 10.1177/1420326X11409457</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1420326X11420014"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Air leakage data for the design of elevator and stair shaft pressurization systems</article-title>. <source>ASHRAE Trans</source> <year>1976</year>; <volume>82</volume>(<issue>Part 2</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1420326X11420014"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Experimental studies on mechanical venting for smoke control in tall office buildings</article-title>. <source>ASHRAE Trans</source> <year>1978</year>; <volume>84</volume>(<issue>Part 1</issue>):<fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1420326X11420014"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klote</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Milke</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Design of smoke management systems. </source>. <publisher-loc>Atlanta, GA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Society of Heating, Refrigerating, and Air-Conditioning Engineers, Inc., and Society of Fire Protection Engineers</publisher-name> <year>1992</year>, <fpage>47</fpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1420326X11420014"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Evaluation of stack effect according to the shape and the window area ratios of lobby in high-rise buildings</article-title>: <source>Procceedings of CTBUH</source>, <month>October</month> <day>10–13</day>, <publisher-loc>Seoul, Korea</publisher-loc>, <year>2004</year>, <fpage>787</fpage>–<lpage>792</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1420326X11420014"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Influence of architectural elements on stack-effect problems in tall residential building</article-title>: <source>Proceedings of CTBUH</source>, <month>October</month> <day>10–13</day>, <publisher-loc>Seoul, Korea</publisher-loc>, <year>2004</year>, <fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>941</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1420326X11420014"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>ASHRAE</collab>. <source>Ventilation and infiltration; in Handbook of Fundamentals</source>. <publisher-loc>Atlanta, GA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Society of Heating, Refrigerating, and Air-Conditioning Engineers</publisher-name> <year>1997</year> <fpage>25.18</fpage>.</citation></ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>