<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjmo</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journalism &amp; Mass Communication Monographs</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1522-6379</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1522637913475792</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1522637913475792</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>From Realism to Reality</article-title>
<subtitle>The Advent of War Photography</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Borchard</surname><given-names>Gregory A.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1522637913475792">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>Lawrence J.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1522637913475792">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1522637913475792">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1522637913475792"><label>1</label>Hank Greenspun School of Journalism and Media Studies, University of Nevada, Las Vegas, Las Vegas, NV, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1522637913475792">Gregory A. Borchard, Hank Greenspun School of Journalism and Media Studies, University of Nevada, Las Vegas, 4505 Maryland Parkway, Box 455007, Las Vegas, NV 89154-5007, USA. Email: <email>gregory.borchard@unlv.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>66</fpage>
<lpage>107</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 AEJMC</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Association for Education in Journalism &amp; Mass Communication</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This monograph focuses on a selection of images displayed to audiences during the American Civil War era, based in two categories—illustrations and photographs. Illustrations include lithographs and handcrafted interpretations of events. Photographs include the mechanically based processes of the era that featured chemically captured images, or remnants of actual events. The chronological scope of this work is between the war’s outbreak in 1861 and its close in 1865. Using theoretical approaches generally applied by the social sciences, we interpret the content of images and place them in context with the origins of photography. We also compare both the common and dissimilar features of illustrated and photographic images from the era.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>photojournalism</kwd>
<kwd>media history</kwd>
<kwd>Civil War</kwd>
<kwd>illustrated press</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>During the American Civil War many citizens otherwise removed from the conflict witnessed the physical tolls of war for the first time. From the leading illustrated newspapers <italic>Harper’s Weekly</italic> and <italic>Frank Leslie’s Illustrated</italic>, from lithographs and woodcuts, and from Mathew Brady’s public galleries, images not only provided a compelling sample of a major event in American history but also captured a pivotal moment in the development of media.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1522637913475792">1</xref></sup> From this moment in history, popularly distributed visual items—from drawings to photographs—quite literally depict an ongoing interplay between art and technology, with the former influencing the latter and vice versa.</p>
<p>As well as marking a watershed moment in the history of the United States, the Civil War marked a pivotal event in the development of the American press. Before the war, American newspapers had operated primarily for political purposes, while serving as the primary source of information for nineteenth-century media consumers. While this emphasis remained the case throughout a war fought largely for political reasons, journalism changed rapidly at midcentury, with several technological innovations affecting the press dramatically. Major developments included improvements in the steam press, the diffusion of a telegraphic network, the inclusion of graphic arts and illustrations such as portraits, tables, and maps, and the advent of documentary photojournalism.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1522637913475792">2</xref></sup> The development of the steam press and the telegraph in the 1840s contributed to changes in the content of newspapers as technologies allowed for the faster reproduction of information. The means to transport it more quickly transformed the news industry—indeed, mass media as a whole. The use of graphics, illustrations, and photographic reproductions in the popular press in particular brought immediacy to daily events that transcended the symbolic abstractions of text alone.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1522637913475792">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>This monograph focuses on a selection of images displayed to audiences during the era, based in two categories. The first category, illustrations, includes lithographs and handcrafted, non–technologically based human interpretations of events. The second category, photographs, includes the mechanically based processes of the era that featured chemically captured images, or remnants of actual events. The authors recognize that these two categories can take on a number of different meanings and definitions given the historical context in which they we used. Based on the technologies available during the 1860s, we used a combination of contemporary and historical definitions for illustrated and photographic work to determine the selection of materials for study. This research does not intend to exclude from consideration other kinds of illustrations or photographs—from nineteenth-century paintings or abstract art to contemporary, moving, or digital images—as part of the universe of visual communication. For the sake of this study, we have limited the pool of possible visuals with these definitions, based on the materials produced during the Civil War.</p>
<p>The chronological scope of this monograph is the Civil War period, between its outbreak in 1861 and its close in 1865. It also provides a developmental account of the technologies that contributed to the formation of photojournalism. Using theoretical approaches generally applied by the social sciences, this work deconstructs individual images to interpret denotative and connotative levels of meaning. It puts the origins of photography into context with comparisons of both the common and dissimilar features of illustrated and photographic images.</p>
<sec id="section1-1522637913475792">
<title>Literature Review</title>
<p>Literature pertinent to this study includes scholarship on the cultural and developmental aspects of the illustrated press as a significant event in the history of communication, alongside the role of Mathew Brady in popularizing photography. Within Brady’s lifetime, scholars began studying the ways in which photographs can change how we understand events, and this monograph continues this line of research by combining intersecting interests in media studies, communication, and art. Among the more compelling approaches from early scholars of photography that still resonate in theories about representations of visual messages include the work of American philosopher and linguist Charles Sanders Peirce. Writing much of his research as a contemporary of the Civil War, Peirce interpreted images as a collection of symbols and combined the meanings of individual features in photographs to represent events larger than the moments they captured.</p>
<p>In his 1868 study “On a New List of Categories,” Peirce argued that three sets of signs (“qualisigns,” “sinsigns,” and “legisigns”) represented qualities of individual events, states, or habits.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1522637913475792">4</xref></sup> Among Peirce’s most notable deductions included his observation that the positioning of elements within a photographic frame could produce a symbolically inverse relationship between the subject and the viewer. Moreover, the way in which images were interpreted was not affected by the amount of information included in them, as long as the essential meaning of each symbol remained the same. His analysis can account for a number of the recurring patterns—some of which we feature here—that are found in the illustrated and photographic media of the 1860s and to the present day.</p>
<p>A number of subsequent sociological studies on the effect of photographic technologies on an audience’s interpretation of content have concentrated on the use of the camera as a device that communicates a particular time and moment without the use of written words. The mechanical reproduction of art—specifically, the use of negatives in the reproduction of prints—is another aspect of this technological evolution in media. Predating the popular culture theories of the late twentieth century, literary critic Walter Benjamin recognized, in part from his experiences as a broadcaster, that photography simplified the process of producing art by essentially making the final image dependent on the act of an eye looking through a lens. “Since the eye perceives more swiftly than the hand can draw,” he wrote, “the process of pictorial reproduction was accelerated so enormously that it could keep pace with speech.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1522637913475792">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>Benjamin referred specifically to the way moving pictures could reproduce actions and record a speaker as he spoke. In a similar way, the speed at which Civil War photographers could reproduce battlefield imagery of death and destruction far outpaced the painting or drawing arts. Addressing the comparison of art (or hand-produced imagery) and photographs, Benjamin suggested that viewers should not take time to determine whether photography itself is a form of art, but rather how photography transformed art. He noted that photography freed artistic forms such as painting and drawing from classic portraiture, and that it had a similar effect on the traditional written documentation of events. Similarly, when in 1839 French painter Paul Delaroche first saw in 1839 a daguerreotype (one of the first technologies of what we would call photography), he reportedly exclaimed, “Painting is dead!”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1522637913475792">6</xref></sup> He did not mean his remark to suggest painting would no longer exist, but rather that it was no longer necessary for recording external reality. The advent of Impressionism, Post-Impressionism, Cubism, and Surrealism in the following century reflects this change, but at the same time, whether or not the advent of photography influenced the birth of these new artistic forms is a matter of speculation and is beyond the scope of this study. The literature examined—and indeed the primary sources analyzed for this work—focused, rather, on “art” relative to the mechanical reproduction of messages communicated primarily through mass media, especially the printed text. While significant movements in fine art did exist in the United States at the time, notably the Hudson River School, the works by these artists generally did not receive wide exposure in the most popular newspapers and journals of the day.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1522637913475792">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>The overarching transformation in the media—from a text-driven form of communication to a visually based one—represents a significant moment in the development of social interaction, appropriately attracting the attention of scholars in a number of disciplines. While pictographs and hieroglyphics certainly predated photojournalism, media theorist Marshall McLuhan described the proliferation of visual messages in the contemporary world as a historical break from the past, a transition from “the age of Typographic Man” to “the age of Graphic Man.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1522637913475792">8</xref></sup> Like all technology, photographic technology is, in McLuhan’s conception, a form of human expression, with photographs—early photos in particular—as parts of the gesture and posture of the human body.</p>
<p>The way generals and their horses posed and how a photographer depicted a body, among other examples, were of paramount importance for Civil War photography. In fact, the position of bodies was so important that they were sometimes manipulated by the photographers—even dragged to new geographic positions and propped into various poses—to emphasize or highlight the nature of the battle or to improve the aesthetic look of the scene.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1522637913475792">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>From the twenty-first century, historians and readers of popular texts about the Civil War have more than 150 years of hindsight to evaluate in contemporary terms what these images represent. However, evaluating Civil War images realistically, in the terms of nineteenth-century audiences, depends on familiarity with the terms, themes, and cultural framework that would have influenced interpretations of both specific images and their unspecified use as a war-reporting device. One of the approaches used for this interpretation advocated by German theorist and literary critic Hans Jauss is to interpret the reception of media messages as part of the “horizon of expectations” of audiences. “The reconstruction of the horizon of expectations, in the face of which a work was created and received in the past, enables one,” Jauss wrote, “to pose questions that the text gave an answer to, and thereby to discover how the contemporary reader could have viewed and understood the work.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1522637913475792">10</xref></sup></p>
<p>For example, to understand a Shakespearean play appropriately, a scholar of English, or literature, or history, and so on, using Jauss’s approach, would need to research the kinds of expectations audiences held for entertainment and performances at the time. During the sixteenth century, a researcher would note, men played women’s roles, which today might seem odd but would easily explain both cultural norms and the individual nuances of the playwright’s works. Understanding photographs of the Civil War, similarly, requires familiarity with visual representations found elsewhere in society at the time they were made.</p>
<p>While scholars and artists alike have interpreted the stories told by Brady’s images at varying levels of depth and purpose, from the perspective of twenty-first-century media users, contemporary students have invariably seen his work through the lens of modern technology. Historians who have attempted to interpret Brady’s work in its appropriate context include Alan Trachtenberg, a leading American studies scholar who described in <italic>Photographs: Images as History</italic> the interplay between the technology used by Brady and the more commonly used media of the day, including illustrations, lithographs, and woodcuts. Brady’s photographs transmitted contradictory messages to audiences. Trachtenberg notes that the idea of history as a heroic action, as it had been historically understood, had become at odds with the events, from the mundane to the grotesque, as the photos clearly demonstrated.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1522637913475792">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>In a tension that persists through the development of contemporary technologies, the way photographers reconciled this contradiction for their audiences, Trachtenberg suggests, was to manipulate subjects in their photographs to resemble artistic renditions in popular illustrations. “The staged informality often adopted by Civil War photographers thus counted on association with handmade sketches by artists like Alfred Waud and Winslow Homer,” he wrote, “which were made into woodcuts and popularized in the periodical press.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-1522637913475792">12</xref></sup> While professional photographers have since taken the opportunity to criticize Brady and those he hired for manipulating subjects into more dramatic poses, the practice, at a time of unprecedented journalistic innovation, would have withstood at least the immediate scrutiny of his peers.</p>
<p>The same holds true for audiences of the mid-nineteenth century. While we today take for granted that popular Hollywood movies contain violent scenes—sometimes graphic and gratuitous—a visitor to a Mathew Brady studio, having not seen this type of medium or content before, may well have been shocked or would, at least, have to take time to make sense of it. Audiences of the early 1860s may have been more directly familiar with death than we are, but pictorial imagery was relatively new and images of violent death were without precedent. Moreover, at the time, viewers of the photographs, in Jauss’s terms, would have had a horizon of expectations about war that interpreted the act as something honorable. Indeed, the popular idea of war before 1860, as photography historian Richard Rudisill has observed, was that it was “a stylized and romantic conception provided by the sketch artist or the documentary painter, both of whom usually softened the ugliness of reality.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-1522637913475792">13</xref></sup> But the course of the Civil War, after four seemingly incessant years of bloodshed—as well as exposure to the gruesome scenes depicted in widely reproduced photographic accounts—changed both the public’s understanding of events and their expectations for future ones.</p>
<p>From a broader perspective, scholars have argued that the advent of photography changed the way people see the world in which they live. Looking at the role of art in general as a form of communication, the rise of the halftone illustration in magazines and newspapers after the Civil War, art historian Neil Harris contends, represented a communication shift comparable to the Gutenberg press, “an iconographical revolution of the first order,” producing “an experience of visual reorientation that had few earlier precedents.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-1522637913475792">14</xref></sup> The photographs of the era, more lucidly than paintings, drawings, and lithographs, reflected an unadorned reality that superseded interpretation or imagination.</p>
<p>Reflecting on the role photographs have played in our moment-by-moment understanding of reality, Susan Sontag, in a classic set of reflections, observed that they do not act as “statements about the world so much as pieces of it.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-1522637913475792">15</xref></sup> To Sontag, behind their appearance of authenticity and literalism, “photographs are as much an interpretation of the world as paintings and drawings are.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-1522637913475792">16</xref></sup> Defining the peculiarities of Civil War photography in a journalistic sense, including both lithographs and Brady’s public displays of his work as a form of journalism, has also gone beyond purely technological and mechanical aspects and into an understanding of the interplay between images and words. Although interpreting the levels of truth communicated by individual images or collections of them can challenge researchers, as literary and image studies scholar Graham Clarke notes, photographs have always had the capacity to reflect social conditions. “We can read a photograph within its own frame of reference,” he writes, “seeing it not so much as the reflection of a ‘real’ world as an interpretation of that world.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-1522637913475792">17</xref></sup></p>
<p>Among the more poignant contemporary attempts to describe the totality of violent imagery—specifically war-related photos—Susan Sontag surmises in <italic>On Photography</italic> that a photograph of violence or tragedy “cannot make a dent in public opinion unless there is an appropriate context of feeling and attitude.” She adds, “The photographs Mathew Brady and his colleagues took of the horrors of the battlefields did not make people any less keen to go on with the Civil War.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-1522637913475792">18</xref></sup> In a later work, <italic>Regarding the Pain of Others</italic>, Sontag puzzles over the purpose of war photography and asks if it stimulates the repudiation of war, or if it acts as a call for peace or a cry for revenge, or if it simply reminds viewers that terrible things happen.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-1522637913475792">19</xref></sup> In the end, despite her search for answers, she reaches none and admits that only those who experience war firsthand can understand its terror.</p>
<p>While Sontag suggests pictures may serve to normalize war and make it familiar, the internationally renowned war photographer James Nachtwey holds hope for the ability of war photography to evoke positive change. In the concluding remarks of a documentary about his work, he asks, “Why photograph war? Is it possible to put an end to human behavior which has existed throughout history by means of photography?” Nachtwey admits the suggestion that war photographs could somehow put an end to war is “ridiculously out of balance,” but the same idea has motivated him nonetheless. “For me the strength of photography lies in its ability to evoke a sense of humanity,” he says. “If war is an attempt to negate humanity, then photography can be perceived as the opposite of war and if it’s used well it can be a powerful ingredient in the antidote to war.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20-1522637913475792">20</xref></sup> These observations are also among the few to attempt a holistic understanding of the role of violent images in society, and they present a context for the interpretation of the impact and meaning of a number of the images featured in this monograph.</p>
<p>Indeed, understanding the historical context of how artists and photographers of the era produced their images can help contemporary students understand modern conditions that affect technologies, war, and our understanding of both. Actual participation in combat, as Sontag notes, remains at a level of removal not only by the participation of the photographer in battle but also by the slow exposure times and bulky equipment needed to reproduce reality through photographic means. Regardless, literature in general points to the ways photographic imagery has altered the interpretation of the meanings of events in a war by dissolving the dimensions of time and space for audiences.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21-1522637913475792">21</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1522637913475792">
<title>The Popularization of Sensationalism in the Illustrated Press</title>
<p>While modern technologies have helped to capture sharper depictions of actual events, the roots of the illustrated press stretch back centuries. Visual messages in general of course stretch back even farther—millennia—but in 1638, the <italic>Weekly News</italic> in Britain published one of the first modern engravings of a topical event, a volcano off the coast of France.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22-1522637913475792">22</xref></sup> On other occasions during the era, the American colonial press periodically published woodcuts and cartoons, such as Ben Franklin’s “Join or Die” snake.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23-1522637913475792">23</xref></sup> Later, during the era of the penny press of the 1830s and ’40s, drawings more frequently appeared on the front pages of leading newspapers, such as the <italic>New York Herald</italic>’s depiction of the aftermath of a downtown fire.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24-1522637913475792">24</xref></sup></p>
<p>Chronicling the history of American photography between the 1840s and 1880s, Michael Carlebach’s <italic>The Origins of Photojournalism in America</italic> reveals that illustrated journalism began well before the Civil War reporters and photographers experimented with ways to feature images of both important events and exotic scenery to a wide readership. As early as 1849, Carlebach notes, Canadian illustrator John Henry Walker christened a new era in journalism with the Montreal-based <italic>Punch in Canada</italic>. Although the publication was short-lived, the formula of issue-driven cartoons combined with biting, social commentary inspired imitators in the United States, such as T. W. Strong’s <italic>Illustrated American News</italic> two years later.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25-1522637913475792">25</xref></sup></p>
<p>Some engravings in the weeklies included labels that indicated they had been based on photographs.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26-1522637913475792">26</xref></sup> But engravings and photographs of the era were different entities. As the <italic>Times</italic> of London observed in 1862, long exposure times meant that photographers had to make do “with the still life which remains when the fighting is over,” and while engravings, by contrast, could depict action, Frank Leslie, in fact, referred to photographs as “corpse-like.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27-1522637913475792">27</xref></sup></p>
<p>Due in part to the expenses associated with the telegraph, the <italic>Herald</italic> and other leading newspapers had stopped publishing illustrations around 1850, opting to concentrate solely on text. However, during the Civil War, newspapers occasionally published maps of battles and portraits of generals.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28-1522637913475792">28</xref></sup> These woodcut illustrations appeared most frequently in two weeklies, <italic>Frank Leslie’s Illustrated Newspaper</italic> and <italic>Harper’s Weekly</italic>, both founded in the 1850s. With each publisher sending as many as a dozen artists to the field so they could capture Civil War scenes, the illustrations usually appeared about two weeks after the events depicted. <italic>Leslie’s</italic> was known to be the more sensational of the two.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29-1522637913475792">29</xref></sup></p>
<p>The general definition of what constitutes a sensationalized news story has changed for mass communication scholars from generation to generation, with each successive age having either a more or less expansive concept of it than the previous one. While it is true that almost any work can be sensationalized as long as it contains a certain rhetorical or visual edginess, sensationalized topics after the mid-nineteenth century took a different tone with the addition of the visual component in daily news.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30-1522637913475792">30</xref></sup></p>
<p>Sensational reporting of local crime news had become a staple of nineteenth-century journalism with the advent of the penny press as noted in stories such as those of a crooked mayor who embezzled money or a well-known doctor who went insane and murdered his entire family. Homicide in particular seemed to resonate with readers, with an example being the coverage of the April 10, 1836, murder of Ellen Jewett (also known as Helen Jewett), a prostitute in New York City whose death brought attention to a number of her customers who were among Manhattan’s elite. James Gordon Bennett’s <italic>New York Herald</italic> provided the most complete coverage of the event, emphasizing the sensational nature of the story and working to exploit the sexual, violent details of Jewett’s death for the newspaper’s gain.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31-1522637913475792">31</xref></sup></p>
<p>In a search for a historical precedent to identify the development of modern sensationalism, scholars have pointed to separate instances in which sensational content can be found in the literary or news texts of newspapers, but fewer—if any—have analyzed sensational images in particular. <italic>Inventing the Victorians</italic>, British journalist Matthew Sweet’s influential reinterpretation of nineteenth-century mores, attributes our understanding of the “sensation” in sensationalism to a nineteenth-century “mid-Victorian predilection for spectacular thrills.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32-1522637913475792">32</xref></sup> Dating the popularized usage of the word as an attributive noun to the early 1860s, sensationalism at the time—indeed, through today—implied both “a physical effect upon the body” and “a wide and swift circulation throughout culture,” presumably derived through either text or experiences independent of it.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33-1522637913475792">33</xref></sup></p>
<p>However, use of the word <italic>sensationalism</italic> relative to press endeavors most likely preceded Sweet’s understanding of it, at least in the United States. In 1856, the <italic>New York Times</italic> referred to “sensation novels,” and less than a year later, the <italic>Times</italic>, in response to the suggestions of “sensation” newspapers, remarked that “New-York City is still inhabitable,” in spite of “absurd exaggerations” of conditions in the metropolis.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34-1522637913475792">34</xref></sup> In an 1858 case, an accused murderer even complained to the <italic>Times</italic> that the press had tried him with reporters and journalists assuming his guilt: “Unfortunately for me,” he wrote, “these sensation-paragraphs are much more spicy and readable, and will, therefore, be much more widely copied than the dry legal investigation which will establish my innocence.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35-1522637913475792">35</xref></sup></p>
<p>While sensationalism in antebellum news may have relied at times on literary attributes, sensationalized content during the Civil War reflected the chaotic, violent nature of wartime events. Urban newspapers in particular exposed readers not only to horrific body counts and battle details but also to the dangerous world of industrial accidents and venal crime. In responding to the interests of readers, editors understood that they needed to supply a mix of national and local news, along with entertainment as a diversion, and the subject materials were often combined. In the most sensational instances, the subject matter was complemented with the woodcut versions of photographs to help illustrate man’s inhumanity to man.</p>
<p>Two publications were more consistently sensational in their coverage of crime and sex: the <italic>National Police Gazette</italic> and <italic>The Days’ Doings</italic>, which became the <italic>New York Illustrated Times</italic> in 1876. The <italic>Police Gazette</italic> in particular developed a reputation for sensationally violent images, as press historian Guy Reel wrote: “Pick up virtually any <italic>Gazette</italic> during the era and one will find violence, immorality, and/or alarm at such conduct.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36-1522637913475792">36</xref></sup> And although Anthony Comstock succeeded in securing an obscenity indictment over <italic>The Days’ Doings</italic> in 1873, Frank Leslie published the journal under a pseudonym. After Leslie promised to cut back on the more lurid elements of the weekly, the district attorney dropped the case.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37-1522637913475792">37</xref></sup></p>
<p>The first American daily newspaper to publish drawings regularly, the <italic>New York Daily Graphic</italic>, was founded in 1873. But its illustrations were, according to Don C. Seitz, generally “coarse sketches that really told a very poor story of events,” and the paper closed after sixteen years.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38-1522637913475792">38</xref></sup> Aside from the <italic>Graphic</italic> and the Civil War maps and portraits, few illustrations appeared in the daily press before 1880.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39-1522637913475792">39</xref></sup></p>
<p>In the early phases of a new publishing era—later dubbed “yellow journalism”—Joseph Pulitzer began publishing drawings in the <italic>New York World</italic> in 1883.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40-1522637913475792">40</xref></sup> Pulitzer at first felt the illustrations were unbecoming of his reputation as a publisher and instructed staff to cut them from editions. But when circulation of his newspaper dropped, he reversed his directive and ordered his editors to freely use illustrations.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41-1522637913475792">41</xref></sup> As with the <italic>Daily Graphic</italic>, the early images in the <italic>World</italic> were imprecise. Early in its experimentations with illustrations, the <italic>World</italic> published pictures of society women from Brooklyn. Glitches during printing caused a number of imperfections, including what appeared to be a beard on one of the women. A state prosecutor reportedly said that the humiliating images left Joseph Pulitzer vulnerable to prosecution for criminal libel, though nothing came of it.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42-1522637913475792">42</xref></sup></p>
<p>Starting in 1889, the <italic>New York Herald</italic> began publishing sketches; soon it and the <italic>World</italic> began competing heavily not only in circulation but also in what might be described as an illustration war, with one observer describing the result as “essentially an age of pictorial journalism.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43-1522637913475792">43</xref></sup> In 1893, the <italic>World</italic> added color illustrations, and in 1894, it began publishing an image-filled Sunday supplement.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44-1522637913475792">44</xref></sup> Other papers, including the <italic>New York Times</italic>, continued to publish few illustrations, but launched an image-heavy Sunday supplement in 1896 that was discontinued in 1899.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45-1522637913475792">45</xref></sup></p>
<p>The rise of illustrations was not without controversy. In 1893, <italic>Harper’s Weekly</italic> observed that discussions about how much content in the daily newspaper should be devoted to text versus illustration excited “more animated comment” than other matters of even greater importance, but the journal editors recognized that good pictorial work justified itself and that illustrations of little value would eventually disappear.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46-1522637913475792">46</xref></sup> By contrast, some condemned engravings in newspapers with arguments that preceded later denunciations of newspaper photographs. In 1893, the <italic>Nation</italic> called woodcuts in newspapers “infantile” and predicted that readers would soon demand “a rattle, or a colored India rubber balloon, or a bright ball of worsted, or a jack-in-the-box, with each year’s subscription.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47-1522637913475792">47</xref></sup> In 1899, the <italic>New York Times</italic> distinguished its upscale readers from “those whose interest in the news of the day can be awakened only by rough cuts and tawdry typographical display.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48-1522637913475792">48</xref></sup></p>
<p>In a book published in 1893, artist Max De Lipman said that news illustrators sometimes were obliged to confront unspeakable scenes, some tinged with sensationalism, including “ghastly sights of a holocaust, a collapse, mine-disasters, railway horrors, and the long chain of accidents which bring death in its most repulsive aspect to human beings.” He wrote of the illustrator as having to witness “terrible havoc,” “horribly-mutilated corpses,” “the terror of frantic survivors,” and “the heart-rending grief of those who find almost by intuition only the shapeless remains of their kin beneath the shattered timbers of a railway-train, or the smouldering fragments of a burned building.” “But the public demands of a newspaper that it show at least a suggestion of a horrible scene,” he wrote, “beyond the stirring accounts given in letter-press, and the artist must at those times be deaf to the pleadings of his heart, and work because it is his duty to his employers and to his family and to himself”.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49-1522637913475792">49</xref></sup></p>
<p>Photographs gradually edged out line drawings in newspapers and magazines. In 1880, the <italic>New York Graphic</italic> published one of the first halftones in an American newspaper, depicting a New York shantytown.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50-1522637913475792">50</xref></sup> The process remained primitive, however, and it was adopted only slowly, with <italic>Harper’s</italic> publishing just two halftones out of more than 700 illustrations in 1885.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51-1522637913475792">51</xref></sup> By the early 1890s, nearly half of the photos in <italic>Harper’s</italic> were halftones, and it took several more years for such photos to become regular features of daily newspapers.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52-1522637913475792">52</xref></sup> Only in 1897 did Stephen H. Horgan of the <italic>New York Tribune</italic>, earlier the art editor of the <italic>New York Daily Graphic</italic>, develop a process for reproducing halftones on rotary presses.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53-1522637913475792">53</xref></sup> Photojournalism use took off. Woodcuts accounted for a small minority of newspaper illustrations by 1900, and some commentators proclaimed their demise, though one author did insist, “the future of the black-and-white artist who illustrates current topics is absolutely assured.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54-1522637913475792">54</xref></sup></p>
<p>The rise of photography in newspapers demonstrated similar developmental characteristics as the rise of yellow journalism in the era of Pulitzer and Hearst, and in certain respects, the former contributed to the development of the latter.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55-1522637913475792">55</xref></sup> As cultural historian Karin E. Becker observed, newspaper writers and editors of the 1880s and 1890s viewed photography as a medium that bypassed the intellectual processes that journalism was intended to address and cultivate.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56-1522637913475792">56</xref></sup> Therefore, when the <italic>New York Times</italic> eliminated its Sunday illustrated supplement in 1899, it published an article quoting New York City luminaries who praised the move. One, a banker, said that “a pictorial supplement, it seems to me, does not pertain to journalism proper.” A former judge said, “I should be delighted to see illustrations banished from the newspapers altogether.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57-1522637913475792">57</xref></sup> In 1901, the <italic>Times</italic> declared that a new owner had “transformed <italic>The Philadelphia Times</italic> from a discredited freak to a sane newspaper” by means of a list of newsroom rules that included a ban on the use of pictures.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58-1522637913475792">58</xref></sup></p>
<p>Finally, it is important to note that newspapers and magazines were not the only sources of news images. In 1840, Nathaniel Currier sold his lithographs of the conflagration of the steamboat <italic>Lexington</italic> on Long Island Sound, though he evidently was not on the scene. With partner James Merritt Ives, Currier regularly produced lithographs of news events within a day or two and sold them in New York City. These images as well as portraits of public figures remained popular through the nineteenth century.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59-1522637913475792">59</xref></sup> Before photos became readily reproducible in newspapers and magazines, prominent photographers such as Mathew Brady exhibited their work publicly. In addition, stereocards and postcards of all sorts—featuring news stories such as earthquakes and hurricanes—were widely popular in the 1890s and well into the twentieth century.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60-1522637913475792">60</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1522637913475792">
<title>The Photography and Photojournalism of Mathew Brady</title>
<p>This transformation might not have happened without the photographic innovations of Mathew Brady, who began his pioneering work in the 1840s. Brady’s renown was such that he appeared in “Her Letter,” a popular poem by Bret Harte: “If you saw papa’s picture, as taken / By Brady, and tinted at that,— / You’d never suspect he sold bacon / And flour at Poverty Flat.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61-1522637913475792">61</xref></sup> However, like most great innovators, Brady built his accomplishments with the assistance of others. Robert Fenton, commissioned by the British government to photograph the Crimean War (1853–56), deserves recognition as an early war photographer—his work, conducted mostly in 1855, resulted in 360 photographs of that war and of the personnel involved.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62-1522637913475792">62</xref></sup> Even though the technology for photography was still in its infancy during the Civil War and photographs could not yet be mass produced, they were enormously popular. Evidence for the demand can be found in the 1860 U.S. census, which lists 2,650 daguerreotypists, plus more than 500 other photographers.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63-1522637913475792">63</xref></sup></p>
<p>By the time of the Civil War, and certainly in the decades following it, both Brady’s contemporaries and subsequent historians had recognized him as the leading producer of photographic images. In the mid-nineteenth century, Brady had attracted the attention of writers, such as James Fenimore Cooper, Charles Dickens, Nathaniel Hawthorne, Washington Irving, Edgar Allan Poe, and Walt Whitman, who visited his Manhattan studio to have their portraits taken. Such portraits led to the publication of <italic>A Gallery of Illustrious Americans</italic>, which issued only one edition because of lackluster sales. One image, however, of Lincoln (the first of many) became so well known that the president gave credit to it for his election to office. Taken before his February 27, 1860, speech at New York’s Cooper Union, the image showed a beardless Lincoln with features softened to make him appear more agreeable to a national audience.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64-1522637913475792">64</xref></sup></p>
<p><italic>Harper’s Weekly and Leslie’s Illustrated fueled the development. They first entertained readers and then shocked them with reproductions of images of the carnage</italic>. Major newspapers, including New York’s <italic>Herald</italic> and <italic>Tribune</italic>, increasingly followed suit, helping illustrations—at least later in the century—become a mainstay of daily news. The result was a press that depicted human events well beyond the scope of its predecessors.</p>
<p>During the early war years, the most popular individual photographs in circulation were made primarily for personal use and not for the news. These collector’s items included relatively long-distance views of full-length figures. During the later years, similar images were often vignettes, or headshots with surrounding detail and a blurred torso. The major photographic studios sold <italic>cartes de visite</italic>, photographs of famous persons, while owners valued the images as much as modern seekers of baseball cards. Many of the same carte de visite albumen images of Civil War generals still exist. In 1866, cabinet cards, a larger format medium, were introduced and rapidly replaced the cartes de visite as the major photographic format.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65-1522637913475792">65</xref></sup></p>
<p>With the increasing popularity of photographs among the public, leading magazines sought to capitalize on the phenomenon and, through the course of the war, began publishing illustrations, woodcuts, and other representations of pictures on the same pages that carried the news. <italic>Harper’s</italic> and <italic>Leslie’s</italic> led the trend and, as early as the 1850s, published large illustrations that were often based on woodcut versions of photographs. The center pages of these publications contained large pictorials, known a century later as “double-truck” artwork, which during the war often depicted panoramic prints of battle. They featured action, which made the prints far less static than portraits and maps. Both magazines also put a premium on portraits of Union officers.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>“Major Robert Anderson, U.S.A., in command of Fort Sumpter [sic], Charleston Harbor, S.C.,” photographed by Webster and Brothers, 1861, in <italic>Frank Leslie’s Illustrated Newspaper</italic> 11, no. 271 (February 2, 1861): 161, Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/2001699896">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/2001699896</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>The profile featured on the front page of this <italic>Frank Leslie’s Illustrated</italic> issue, published shortly before the outbreak of hostilities at Fort Sumter (or here, “Sumpter”) is based on a photograph by the Webster Brothers of Louisville, Kentucky. Although not as nationally prominent as Mathew Brady’s studios, Webster and Brothers, as the company here identifies itself, produced photographs—some published by <italic>Leslie’s</italic>—of major-generals, brigadier-generals, and colonels. According to a newspaper advertisement for the Webster Brothers, collectors of cartes de visite could order five cards for $1, twelve for $2, fifty for $7, or one hundred for $13 (the card sets were a pricey, $25, $62, $175, and $325 adjusted for inflation).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66-1522637913475792">66</xref></sup> In this head-and-shoulders portrait, Robert Anderson, whose image appeared regularly in print throughout April, wears his uniform and faces front.</p>
<p>Actual photographs of the Civil War appeared only in exhibitions, with the first formal presentation of war dead in Brady’s studio shortly after the 1862 Battle of Antietam, an event described by the <italic>New York Herald</italic> as “an invaluable service” that contributed to the historical record unlike any previous exhibit.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67-1522637913475792">67</xref></sup> The visual record of the conflict captured the horrors of war in a way never before seen, as illustrated magazines sometimes converted photographs into wood engravings for use in the mass production of images and other times dispatched their own artists to the scenes of battle. Enterprising photographers opened studios throughout the country, exhibiting their pictures and promoting this innovation, and soldiers and politicians routinely visited these photographers to have their pictures taken. Indeed, Lincoln’s use of photography gave him a major advantage historically over previous presidents, and in hindsight, it can be said that his presidency fared comparably better than those of his predecessors precisely because he was photographed while they were not. Brady, who was close to Lincoln and received permission to accompany Union troops to the front lines of battle, brought his so-called “Brady wagon,” which included a darkroom for developing plates in the field. However, humidity and dust often plagued the operation.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68-1522637913475792">68</xref></sup></p>
<p>Brady’s studio portraits produced clearer reproductions, and in some cases, depending on the subject, as remarkable in some respects as those from the field. As late as November 1864, for example, the <italic>Herald</italic> praised Brady for making available to the public the first circulated portrait of General Ulysses S. Grant, writing, “Now we know that Gen. Grant has given Mr. Brady the best opportunity in the world to secure a true and correct portrait.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn69-1522637913475792">69</xref></sup></p>
<p>While photographs such as these appeared only in exhibitions, the visual record of the conflict captured the horrors of war in a way never before seen. Illustrated publications did reproduce graphic renditions of horrific events, and audiences saw carnage in presentations of traveling art, such as Goodwin and Wilder’s “Polyorama of the War.” The exhibition promised to tell the story of the “First Dread Signal at Sumter down to the Last Grand Battle.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn70-1522637913475792">70</xref></sup> The owners said the polyorama would engulf the senses of its viewers with fire and smoke, as well as thunderous sounds.</p>
<p>The polyorama may have been short-lived, but the impact of the newly available imagery—photographs in Brady’s studios and in people’s homes, combined with the new wave of illustrations in the weekly press—had effects that endure today. When combined with the proliferation of visual media before the war, the institutional and cultural developments in the print industry led to a revolution—a revolution to which contemporary media is in a number of ways indebted. The general transformation of news from political purposes to informative ones made it a commodity unlike any time before the war, with the catastrophic events of the Civil War bringing a new emphasis to the purpose of the press and the images it disseminated.</p>
<p>Beyond Brady’s role as a portrait taker, the press also appreciated his contributions to revolutionizing the Fourth Estate. The <italic>New York Times</italic>, among others, admired the news value of his photographs. “Mr. Brady had done something to bring home to us the terrible reality and earnestness of war,” the <italic>Times</italic> editorialized after his 1862 display of images from the Battle of Antietam, images that resembled too closely “a few dripping bodies, fresh from the field, laid along the pavement. . . . If he has not brought bodies and laid them in our dooryards and along the streets, he had done something very like it.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn71-1522637913475792">71</xref></sup></p>
<p>Brady later sold much of his collection of negatives to the U.S. government, while others were given as payment for supplies. <italic>History of the Civil War</italic>, which Brady coauthored with Benson J. Lossing and which was first published in 1895 and again in 1905 and 1912, includes many of the photographs inherited by the War Department. As a history of the Civil War, it is among the many from those who experienced it firsthand, but as a primary source of visual material, it is remarkable in its inclusion of some of Brady’s best work. In this respect—and in spite of the numerous advances in technology, including color photographs, highly detailed moving images, and the rapid transmission of both—Brady was, as noted in the <italic>History of the Civil War</italic>’s biographical description of him, “fifty years in advance of his time, for many of his photographs compare favorably with the best quality of work to-day.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn72-1522637913475792">72</xref></sup></p>
<p>Brady’s documentation of the Civil War had, for the first time, given shape to photojournalism’s greater promise—that of transforming historic events into a coherent visual expression. But like so many artists, the significance of his Civil War work was not fully appreciated during his lifetime. Dying poor and destitute, Brady had a vision of making money from his Civil War photographs that never materialized. The eventual loss of his enterprises was caused by debts incurred from purchasing all the supplies and outfitting all the photographers he trained and sent out onto the various battlefields, along with the downfall of his political patrons and the slowing demand for photographic portraits because of the recession following the war.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>“Gettysburg, Pa. Alfred R. Waud, artist of <italic>Harper’s Weekly</italic>, sketching on battlefield,” Timothy H. O’Sullivan, photographer, July 1863, Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/cwp2003000198/PP">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/cwp2003000198/PP</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig2.tif"/></fig>
<p>On a number of levels, this photograph of Alfred Rudolph Waud, an important illustrator, by leading photographer Timothy H. O’Sullivan captures a metahistorical moment. Waud, who was born in England in 1828 and immigrated to the United States in 1850, drew illustrations for newspapers and periodicals as a “special correspondent,” a title used for contributors, such as artists, photographers, and writers. O’Sullivan, a Brady affiliate, took some of the era’s most famous photos. Here, Waud prepares a sketch of the Battle of Gettysburg for <italic>Harper’s Weekl</italic>y.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn73-1522637913475792">73</xref></sup></p>
<p>The photographer focuses on his subject, a sketch artist, in a virtually ironic juxtaposition of media—rather an intersection, or a convergence—an established and popular form (illustrations) with an emerging one (photographs). In a style reminiscent of traditional portrait painting, O’Sullivan seems to capture an unaware Waud in the act of drawing, but the production of such an image no doubt happened with the cooperation of Waud, who would have posed motionless. (For proper exposure of the photosensitive chemical emulsion of the glass plate—that is, without blurring resulting from inadvertent movement—exposures required about three to twenty seconds.) Some of this type of blurring effect appears on the bushes in the background, as any mild breeze caused branches to move (although some of the out-of-focus nature of the background could be from them falling beyond the camera’s depth of field).</p>
<p>Waud remains the central element within the photograph’s frame—slightly off center, but merely to a degree. His centrality within the image gives him heavy symbolic authority, but another primarily important symbolic figure—the photographer—is off frame, thus establishing an inverse symbolic relationship, the same kind of relationship described in Peirce’s theoretical work from the same time. The fact that the photograph itself depicts Waud at the Devil’s Den site on the Gettysburg battlefield brings an additional context for the viewer to consider, as on July 2, 1863, Devil’s Den—the site of some of the bloodiest fighting of the battle—would have undoubtedly triggered an association with the larger events of the war.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn74-1522637913475792">74</xref></sup></p>
<p>One character (Waud) is visible, the other (O’Sullivan) invisible; the former motionless, the latter active; the former in the light, the latter in the dark; the former oblivious (or at least seemingly so), the latter an aware observer. Meanwhile, beyond the scope of either the subject or the photographer lies an even larger event—the battle itself. And in this particular picture, the external event serves as a frame around a frame, putting into inverse the already inverse relationship depicted—again, the symbolic juxtapositions suggested by Peirce. While Waud and O’Sullivan appear to work peacefully, an epic battle—a pivotal moment in the Civil War—takes place at a distance unknown and invisible to the viewer.</p>
<p>Aesthetically, in terms of the relationship between light and dark, the sparse shadowing in the image indicates that it was exposed around midday. In fact, the only shadow seen in the work is that which is under the brim of Waud’s hat along his forehead, under his foreground leg along the ground, and at the base of the bushes in the background. Waud sits on the side of an elevated mound, or hillside, which places him at an eye-level angle to the photographer despite his seated posture. This posture, with his sketchbook steadied on his knee, also suggests the posed nature of the image, as it would have been difficult to hold the sketchbook with a poised writing instrument steady if he were in a standing position for any length of time. Interestingly, Waud glances to the right side of the frame. This adds an element of intrigue, serving to extend the scene and allow the viewer to imagine both the scene outside of O’Sullivan’s frame and the scene sketched on Waud’s papers—presumably intense action, including fighting and death. (Historians generally recognize the three days of conflict at Gettysburg, with more than fifty thousand casualties, as the costliest battle of the war.)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn75-1522637913475792">75</xref></sup></p>
<p>Waud would have sent a drawing such as this to his editors, who would then have converted it into a woodcut or a copperplate engraving for print publication. Leading illustrated newspapers during the war used woodcuts that were then impressed on paper to create images for mass reproduction in the press. These engravings, such as those of Winslow Homer, generally came from illustrations made by sketch artists in the field. Speed was increased by using a multiple-block system, in which a drawing was divided into four or five segments. A different engraver worked on each block, and then the blocks were locked into a frame. A master engraver cut the lines that crossed the various blocks.</p>
<p>The raw labor and artistic sensibility involved in creating the images, both for studio use as well as for reproduction as woodcuts, was neither lost nor unappreciated by publishers. While cost may have prohibited wide-scale publication of photographs until later in the century, newspaper editors began recognizing the transformative effect of visuals on news. Reflecting on the photographs of the Gettysburg battlefield—nearly all much more gruesome than the portrait of Waud—the industry-leading <italic>New York Herald</italic> praised Brady. “A better memorial of that sanguinary conflict cannot well be imagined; and in after years, when this war shall be spoken of only in the history of the past, these faithful sketches of Brady will be invested with an importance and patriotic beauty which at this moment can scarcely be sufficiently appreciated,” read the <italic>Herald</italic> just weeks after the battle. “[T]here is scarcely a doubt that his efforts to perpetuate the memories of the battle field of Gettysburg will meet with prompt and generous public approval.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn76-1522637913475792">76</xref></sup> In fact, the <italic>Herald</italic>, on several occasions during the war—as did other leading newspapers—remarked on Brady’s photographs not in terms of their content alone, but as newsworthy events for their own sake.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn77-1522637913475792">77</xref></sup></p>
<p>As a young man, Timothy O’Sullivan, a native New Yorker, found work with Mathew Brady, who sent him to Washington, D.C., to serve as an apprentice under Alexander Gardner in Brady’s studio. With the outbreak of the Civil War and soldiers wanting photographs in uniform before going to battle, demand for images from Brady’s studios increased. In July 1861, with the first major conflict of the war, Brady and Alfred Waud traveled to Bull Run to witness the disaster for the Union Army. In the wake of the battle, Brady decided to make a photographic record of the war and sent nearly two dozen men, including O’Sullivan, Alexander Gardner and his brother James Gardner, William Pywell, and George Barnard, to travel throughout the country and photograph subsequent battles over the following years. One of the most famous photographs to come from the endeavor was O’Sullivan’s “Harvest of Death,” an image of dead soldiers at Gettysburg.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn78-1522637913475792">78</xref></sup> With Brady claiming credit for the work taken by his employees and evidently unhappy with this policy, O’Sullivan—as did Alexander Gardner—left the project to establish his own photographic business.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn79-1522637913475792">79</xref></sup></p>
<p>Alexander Gardner was born in Paisley, Scotland, and in 1850, immigrated to the United States in an attempt to create a cooperative farm with a group of investors who purchased land near Monona, Iowa. He returned to Scotland to raise more money and in doing so became owner and editor of the <italic>Glasgow Sentinel</italic> in 1851. Later that year, he visited the Great Exhibition, a demonstration of industrial and technological developments, in Hyde Park, London, where he saw a display put together by Mathew Brady and formed an interest in photography.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn80-1522637913475792">80</xref></sup> Gardner brought his family to the United States in 1856 when he discovered that the cooperative in Iowa had failed to prosper and decided to stay in New York. Initiating contact with Brady, he began working with him in a partnership that lasted until 1862.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn81-1522637913475792">81</xref></sup></p>
<p>Gardner first specialized in making large prints known as “imperial” photographs, but as Brady’s eyesight began to fail, Gardner assumed additional responsibilities. In 1858, Brady put him in charge of the Washington, D.C., gallery. With Lincoln’s election in November 1860—and along with it the threat of war—Gardner was conveniently located to document the unfolding events. His relationship with Allan Pinkerton, who headed an intelligence operation that became the Secret Service, was instrumental in communicating Brady’s ideas about documenting the war to Lincoln, and Pinkerton recommended Gardner to the position of chief photographer under the jurisdiction of the U.S. Topographical Engineers. Following a short tenure with the title, Gardner became a staff photographer for George B. McClellan, commander of the Army of the Potomac. At this time, he ended his work in the Washington studio. Gardner received the honorary rank of captain, resuming photographic work after the bloody Battle of Antietam in September 1862. Gardner’s work was subsequently often misattributed to Brady, and despite his considerable output, historians have tended to give Gardner less than full recognition for his documentation of the Civil War. Regardless, when Lincoln dismissed McClellan from command of the Army of the Potomac in November 1862, Gardner’s role as chief army photographer diminished, and Gardner apparently ended his working relationship with Brady because of Brady’s practice of attributing his employees’ work as “Photographed by Brady.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn82-1522637913475792">82</xref></sup></p>
<p>Regardless of the reasons for the split, Gardner followed General Ambrose Burnside, photographing the Battle of Fredericksburg, and then followed General Joseph Hooker. In May 1863, his brother James and he opened their own studio in Washington, D.C., hiring many of Brady’s former staff. During this time, Gardner photographed the Battle of Gettysburg (July 1863) and the Siege of Petersburg (June 1864–April 1865).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn83-1522637913475792">83</xref></sup> Scholars, including Anne E. Peterson, have since noted that historians may have overattributed both Gardner’s and O’Sullivan’s departures from Brady’s studios to the latter’s crediting—or not crediting—individual photographers for their work, as Gardner (and others) apparently engaged in the practice as well.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn84-1522637913475792">84</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1522637913475792">
<title>Illustrations and Photos by Events and Themes</title>
<p>For this monograph, the following five sets of images featured in this section included visual items from two categories. The first category, “illustrations,” included handcrafted manually drawn, non–technologically based human interpretations of events, such as sketches, woodcuts, and lithographs; the second, “photographs,” included images produced by a mechanically based process featuring a chemically captured image, a remnant of an actual event.</p>
<p>In general, illustrations included visual artifacts that were drawn by hand—from simple sketches to more elaborate woodcuts and lithographic color paintings—and photographs included images taken by a camera, as archived by the Library of Congress in the Brady Collection. The sets of visuals each contain one illustration and one photograph paired together to demonstrate the relationship between art and technology. While secondary literature has described this relationship to some extent, the five sets demonstrate how the illustrated press of the Civil War captured particular events in a number of ways that for the first time epitomized the convergence of media, technology, and art at the time.</p>
<p>While the authors reviewed hundreds of illustrations and photographs in the online archives of the Library of Congress, those selected for this section matched an illustration with a picture based on the event they depicted, or on the theme depicted, or on both the event and the theme depicted. Undoubtedly, hundreds of other illustrations and photographs could have been selected for this section, but the following sets provide a representative sample that covers the general scope of the war years, also providing a sample of the general techniques and themes used by both illustrators and photographers of the era.</p>
<sec id="section5-1522637913475792">
<title>Sample Set 1: Fair Oaks</title>
<p>Unlike photographs, engravings can show movement in significant and almost surreal ways. In “The Battle of Fair Oaks,” Union soldiers demonstrate movement toward enemy lines through their arched backs as they move forward, all in nearly perfect regimentation and in a neat, straight line. Clearly visible in the background is a scouting balloon, an image that would have struck at least a few readers at the time as foreign. The image actually depicts two flanks: In the foreground, the battle is just beginning, with the Confederate soldiers seeming to be losing ground; further in the background, two sides march, not yet reaching each other. Based on the number of Union soldiers visible—especially because they are in the clear of the woods—the Confederates appear outnumbered.</p>
<p>Because of linear perspective and the concept of the vanishing point, which provides a sense of depth in a flat image, the eye is drawn toward the center of the picture where the vanishing point converges in a cloud of what we assume to be artillery smoke. The smoke from the artillery in the background is clearly visible, yet there is only a hint of its origin. Since we might assume that the cannons are aimed from the background toward the foreground, we may also assume that the devastation suggested by their long-range projectiles may not yet have reached the front lines. Beyond this suggested sense of motion, the illustration also provides a clear sense of movement from left to right, as the Union Army overwhelms the Confederates in a mighty surge, thus suggesting a Union victory. The men in blue carry the heavier visual weight in this image and seem to dominate the scene. Regardless, no side in the end could claim a victory in this particular battle. While McClellan publicly claimed victory, the lithographer apparently took the opportunity to illustrate the general’s claims for the purpose of Union propaganda, a luxury that photographs could not as easily provide.</p>
<fig id="fig3-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>“The Battle of Fair Oaks, Va. May 31st, 1862,” New York: Currier and Ives, 1862, Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/90709053">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/90709053</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig3.tif"/></fig>
<p>In a photograph of a Union battery at or near Fair Oaks, soldiers look to the left, unaware of the camera that captures them. Cannons in the foreground of the picture and in the center–left indicate heavy armament, and the foreground machinery weighs down the image. From the little smoke in the air and the tense stance of the soldiers, it would seem that this was taken before the battle. Unlike the sketch illustration of Fair Oaks with Union soldiers moving left to right and apparently defeating the Confederates, this photograph depicts a quiet, almost eerie setting. With Union soldiers to the right of the camera, the image was likely taken from the left flank. In the distance, some Union soldiers appear to march slowly to the left. Unlike the engraved image of the Fair Oaks battle, all subjects stand motionless.</p>
<p>As evidenced by this picture, as well as by others of troops on the battlefield, camera speeds at the time were too slow to take photos of active battle, and so photojournalists were left to document only the before and after of military action. Indeed, “the process required that the camera be planted, the lens focused, the plate coated, exposed, and developed while still wet, all within precious moments at the scene of the ‘view’ to be made.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn85-1522637913475792">85</xref></sup> Even in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1522637913475792">Figure 4</xref>, some blurring is noted, since not all the men in the frame remained stationary during the time of the exposure. “For photographers the problem of making sense of battles raging in woods and fields was compounded by problems of equipment as well as access to battlefields, which required permission, usually withheld until fighting ceased,” Trachtenberg writes. “Large cameras on tripods, lenses designed for landscape views, the necessity of preparing the glass plate in a portable darkroom, then rushing with it to the camera—all these physical barriers to spontaneous pictures of action encouraged a resort to easily applied conventions of historical painting, casual sketches, and even studio portraits.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn86-1522637913475792">86</xref></sup></p>
<fig id="fig4-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>“Fair Oaks, Va., Vicinity. Federal Battery,” June 1862, Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/cwp2003000074/PP">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/cwp2003000074/PP</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig4.tif"/></fig>
<p>Moreover, any problems with the accuracy of sketch artists, who sometimes were not actually at the scene of battle and instead relied on what observers told them, did not in a publisher’s mind outweigh the slowness of the photographic process. Drawings remained less expensive than photographs, and in any event, photographs could not be reproduced in magazines and newspapers at the time, so publishers of illustrated journals continued to rely on sketched engravings for illustrated depictions of action on the battlefield. At the same time, mass-marketed lithographs provided another outlet for battlefield images.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1522637913475792">
<title>Sample Set 2: Surgeons at Work</title>
<p>This Winslow Homer engraving, which was reproduced in <italic>Harper’s Weekly</italic> as a woodcut illustration, draws the viewer’s eyes to the center of the image; yet the subject at the focus of the illustration is the surgeon on the left corner. Also missing from this image is any of the actual battle carnage of the dead, dying, and wounded. One has to assume that the doctor, who wears an officer’s cap, works on a patient, but we see nothing of the actual procedure or the wounds. By leaving out such details, this engraving allows the image to be sanitized and likely more acceptable to the <italic>Harper’s Weekly</italic>’s consumer. While publishers did not hold back on visual content exclusively because of reader interest, they could more easily manipulate sketches, thus making them at times more popular than photographs.</p>
<fig id="fig5-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>“The Surgeon at Work at the Rear during an Engagement,” Winslow Homer, wood engraving, 1862, <italic>Harper’s Weekly</italic> 6 (July 12, 1862): 436, Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/97501512">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/97501512</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig5.tif"/></fig>
<p>The surgeon in the Homer engraving focuses on a patient underneath a tree. Another surgeon holding a small knife tends to a shirtless soldier who has a visible cut to the chest. Two soldiers in the center of the engraving appear to unload supplies, while another wounded soldier approaches the scene from the background, walking uphill. The smoke in the far background reveals a battle most likely in progress. The image demonstrates a determination among the subjects, as well as in the artist, to depict an order not found in other photographs depicting the conditions of hospitals. The focus on the surgeons working on the wounded soldiers brings attention away from the battlefield and to the activity under the tree.</p>
<fig id="fig6-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>“Savage Station, Va. Field Hospital after the Battle of June 27,” James F. Gibson, photographer, June 30, 1862, Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/cwp2003000090/PP">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/cwp2003000090/PP</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig6.tif"/></fig>
<p>James Gibson’s photograph of the hospital at Savage Station, Virginia, captures the atmosphere of postbattle surgical operations, but if the procedures were taking place at the time of the picture, they were hidden from the viewer behind the walls of the tent. A few faces, both Anglos and African Americans, look toward the camera, but most subjects are either asleep or unaware of the photographer. As with other photographs of such gruesome nature, there seems to be no focal point for the eye—no part of the picture pulls a reader’s eyes in some particular direction. In the foreground, one soldier apparently receives treatment in an open space. Another man, wearing a straw hat, appears to be operating on a soldier’s leg or a body part just outside the frame of the photograph. In the far background, three tents and one small building likely house the injured. Numerous soldiers outside these tents appear to wait for treatment of their wounds, or perhaps they are just resting after battle. Nowhere does a doctor actually appear to work on a patient. A few soldiers stand and some look toward the camera lens, while others are blurred; they probably happened to walk in front of the camera in the middle of an exposure. The faces of those who do appear in the frame neither smile nor frown; it is difficult to read their demeanor.</p>
<fig id="fig7-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>“Major General Ambrose E. Burnside (seated with legs crossed) and His Staff at Cold Harbor, Va., 9th Corps Headquarters,” June 11 or 12, 1864, Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/cwp2003001113/PP">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/cwp2003001113/PP</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig7.tif"/></fig>
<p>A contemporary viewer who may not have had the chance to see a battlefield hospital in person might have had the impression that soldiers experienced amputations with little or no terror or pain. Although the photograph shows general disorganization at the site, it does not capture the sights of blood and limbs. In this regard, the photograph—at least this one in particular—like the illustration, tended to sanitize warfare, as the photographer followed the approach of the illustrator and self-censored much of the horror experienced during an amputation. In addition, photography by its nature tended to sanitize such scenes by providing visual depictions that lacked the cries of pain and the smell of death.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1522637913475792">
<title>Sample Set 3: The General at War</title>
<p>Mathew Brady’s photograph of General Ambrose Burnside and his staff at Cold Harbor, which was also published as a woodcut version, typifies the portraits produced by Brady and his associates. His collection of Civil War photographs offers a sustained record of the events from that war, and like many others from his collection, it depicts the Union Army’s hierarchy posed before the camera.</p>
<p>As a portrait, it compares well with portraiture paintings done at the same time; yet, at the same time, the flaws of the new photographic technologies are evident here in that we see how much of the background fades because of overexposure. Much of the detail in the foreground is also overexposed. The contrast of the linear group in their dark uniforms framed by trees on either side is highlighted by the lighter foreground and background. Aesthetically, the photograph creates a frame within a frame—an overall flat, rectangular structure with a slight angle, suggesting a sense of instability (the trees form the sides of the rectangle and the top of the photograph frame is the top of the rectangle, with the line of men forming the bottom). This sense of instability is less pronounced in the woodcut.</p>
<fig id="fig8-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>“Cold Harbor, Va. Gen. Burnside and His Staff at 9th Corps Headquarters,” <italic>Harper’s Weekly</italic>, July 23, 1864, 469, Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/cwp2003001113/PP">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/cwp2003001113/PP</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig8.tif"/></fig>
<p>The features of Major General Burnside, in many ways the focus of both the photograph and the woodcut, communicate more than what is immediately apparent. Burnside’s unusual facial hair is repeated in differing forms on the faces of many of the others in the picture (Burnside’s muttonchops later were named “sideburns” in what is a simple inversion of his name). The facial hair becomes as much a subject in the image as the men themselves. Burnside is the center of attention, flanked on either side by his subordinates, and his position as leader is reinforced by the way the majority of the officers in the group defers to him (or not) and seemingly copy his facial grooming.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn87-1522637913475792">87</xref></sup> But he is also seated with legs crossed in a relaxed manner, suggesting a kind of lax leadership style, as some of his men are looking away and others looking toward the camera. In fact, history shows that Burnside was ill equipped intellectually and emotionally for military leadership but was personally friendly, always smiling, and affable. The aesthetic instability caused by the slanted rectangular look helps to reinforce Burnside’s somewhat specious leadership style.</p>
<p>To a certain extent, the illustrated version of this image corrects the imperfections of the photograph. The illustrator reinserted objects not even visible in the photograph, such as the building in the background and the detail of the tree branches. Here, the technologically produced image—and what a modern viewer might assume would be a more reliable depiction of reality—actually contains a less accurate depiction of the scene. As the reproduction of photographs as woodcuts became an increasingly common feature of news during the war, publishers sought to meet the demand with even more detailed and precise illustrations, which by the turn of the century included color.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1522637913475792">
<title>Sample Set 4: Jefferson Davis</title>
<p>Less than a month after the new president of the Confederate States of America took office, <italic>Leslie’s</italic> depicted Jefferson Davis based on a photograph by Mathew Brady. In both, Davis looks to the right, off camera, in a statesmanlike pose. The picture shows more of his body, with his left hand resting on books. The drawing faithfully recaptures Davis’s head and upper body from the photograph, though with darker hair, a darker shadow over his left eye, and perhaps a gentler set to his lips.</p>
<fig id="fig9-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 9.</label>
<caption>
<p>“Jefferson Davis, Three-Quarter Length Portrait, Facing Right,” Mathew Brady, photographer, between 1858 and 1860, Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/2004673617">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/2004673617</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig9.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig10-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 10.</label>
<caption>
<p>“Jefferson Davis, First President of the New Southern Confederacy,” in <italic>Frank Leslie’s Illustrated Newspaper</italic> 11, no. 276 (March 9, 1861): 241, Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/2001700451">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/2001700451</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig10.tif"/></fig>
<p>Notably, the drawing surrounds Davis with heroic garlands. It also appears on the front page of the issue, eclipsing a portrait of President-Elect Lincoln that appears inside. Frank Leslie initially hoped to hold onto his readers in both the North and the South, so he sought to remain neutral in the conflict—hence the noble portrait of Davis. “[W]e are essentially an Illustrated and not a Political Newspaper,” a <italic>Leslie’s</italic> editorial said in March 1860, before the outbreak of hostilities. “Our paper is not addressed to one class, to one political party, or to one section; it is intended for, and has gained a general circulation in every portion of the United States, of over one hundred and fifty thousand copies weekly.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn88-1522637913475792">88</xref></sup> When this neutrality proved off-putting to readers in both regions, Leslie sided with the Union, though the paper was often critical of what it saw as the North’s military ineptitude.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn89-1522637913475792">89</xref></sup></p>
<p><italic>Leslie’s</italic> reproduced portraits from photographs taken by Brady and others, as in the case of Jefferson Davis. But unlike some other illustrated periodicals of the time, <italic>Leslie’s</italic> rarely reproduced battlefield photos. Instead, it sent its own artists into the field—some fifty by mid–1861. When critics contended that <italic>Leslie’s</italic> illustrations did not match eyewitness accounts of a battle, Frank Leslie responded that the complaints were “grossly unjust” and that his artists were regularly risking their lives for the sake of informing <italic>Leslie’s</italic> readers.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn90-1522637913475792">90</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1522637913475792">
<title>Sample Set 5: Antietam</title>
<p>Photography could provide exactitude, and it proved ideal for portraits. But for two reasons, scenes of battle presented largely insuperable problems. First, photographic technology during the Civil War required near immobility on the part of the subjects, as movement would blur the image. Second, the technology demanded close proximity, as, at the time, no telephoto lenses existed. A photographer who planted himself in the middle of a battlefield would thus risk his life for action images that were at best fuzzy. Accordingly, many Civil War photographs show events before or after a battle. In this photograph by Alexander Gardner, a man sits on a rock, his binoculars trained to the right. The photograph is by some standards a poor depiction, with the man seen from the back at the extreme right of the image, looking outside the frame. Any fighting—and the picture may have been taken before the battle—is out of view. It is a motionless image, as all photographs are, but of a motionless scene.</p>
<fig id="fig11-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 11.</label>
<caption>
<p>“Antietam, Md. Battlefield on the Day of the Battle, September 17, 1862,” photograph by Alexander Gardner, September 17, 1862, Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/cwp2003000127/PP">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/cwp2003000127/PP</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig11.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig12-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 12.</label>
<caption>
<p>“The Battle of Antietam, Md. Sept. 17th 1862,” New York: Currier and Ives print, 1862 or 1863[?], Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/90709032">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/90709032</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig12.tif"/></fig>
<p>The Gardner photograph contrasts sharply with the Currier and Ives scene of the same battle, as the latter thrives with movement and action. In the foreground, Union forces on horseback are driving back Confederate soldiers, although one Union soldier appears to have been bayoneted; his rearing white horse is positioned near the center of the image. Smoke rises from the right, where the Confederates are positioned, and appears in the background as well. The caption speaks of a “splendid victory” in which General George B. McClellan’s Union forces were “utterly routing and compelling [the Confederates] to a precipitate retreat across the Potomac to save themselves from capture or annihilation.” Alexander Gardner could never hope to match such vivid depictions of an ongoing battle, even if, as was likely the case, the drawings were rooted more in the illustrator’s imagination than in reality.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section10-1522637913475792">
<title>Discussion and Conclusion</title>
<p>The images featured in this monograph, for a moment in time, captured both a sense of time and time itself, as the Civil War provided a backdrop for a critical moment in history when external events and the depictions of them combined to change the way people quite literally saw the world in which they lived. The interplay between artist and photographer depicted in this study, in a number of ways, reflected an ongoing relationship between the storyteller and the popular media of the day. This relationship is still a vital part of the development of new technologies and the ways audiences interact with them. Indeed, the moment in history we study in this monograph is critical for visual media—and for photojournalism specifically—and this period informs our understanding of visual messages today.</p>
<p>The dawn of photography was a moment of democratization of the visual, as soon such images become less expensive to make and available to a wider segment of the public. Writer Jonathan Crary goes further, arguing that the implication of photography was so vast that drawing similarities between it and older types of images, such as perspectival painting or drawings made with the aid of the camera obscura, is insignificant. “Photography is an element of a new and homogenous terrain of consumption and circulation in which an observer becomes lodged,” Crary writes. “To understand the ‘photographic effect’ in the nineteenth century, one must see it as a crucial component of a new cultural economy of value and exchange, not as part of a continuous history of visual representation.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn91-1522637913475792">91</xref></sup> In addition, photography created a new relationship between past and present because, for the first time, it was suddenly possible to record events with certainty and create archives for future generations. This moment in the history of visual messages can also be contrasted to what is happening today with the advent of digital image making and the computer. The rise of these technologies and the ways in which they made the manipulation of images easy and seamless (i.e., practically undetectable) spelled a new way in which we, today, understand them as no longer closely tethered to concepts such as veracity, objectivity, and reality.</p>
<p>It would be premature—at least for historians—to anticipate developments in media technologies based either on the precedent set by photographers of the 1860s or on more recent developments in digital technologies, but it may be fair to anticipate that a more refined and efficient medium will stem from the interplay of existing technologies and art, while for the public the ever-increasing speed at which photographs can reproduce images has sped the perceived sequence of events—in war or in everyday life. Happenings in a distant corner of the planet no longer seem to have happened in a different time or space.</p>
<p>This monograph examined a particular time in which journalism went through substantial changes in the way it presented events visually, a time of photojournalism’s infancy. The work of Mathew Brady, who extended and laid the groundwork for photojournalistic images of wartime events, were seen alongside woodcuts or drawings and sketches of the war. Some of his photographs were reproduced in illustrations for reproduction in the press. The transition from woodcut technologies to photography was not immediate. In fact, drawings and sketches continue to exist in editorial cartoons and other forms of hand-created artwork for journalistic purposes. However, photography would continue to evolve into new technologies such as the halftone, color imagery, and on to the digital imagery of today. These changes are important in that they all serve to alter the way we depict reality and continue to shape our understanding of events whether past or present.</p>
<p>The profundity of the changes in media can be measured in some ways by corresponding social changes, but this change in some respects is beyond the scope of this work. Additional research—to put into context the general effects of visual media on American culture—could examine, for example, the role of political cartoons during the Civil War. While Gary L. Bunker’s <italic>From Rail-Splitter to Icon: Lincoln’s Image in Illustrated Periodicals, 1860–1865</italic>, an examination of cartoons parodying Abraham Lincoln, provides a solid analysis of a specific kind of illustration, it does not do so in comparison with the photographic images of the era. Another area to explore for future studies is the role of images in both the North and South. While this particular study may provide a basis for understanding social changes in the North, given the materials studied, it cannot make claims about the way southern audiences interpreted Mathew Brady’s photos.</p>
<p>To summarize the tension between technology and art, given the kinds of photographs and illustrations featured here, two more visual artifacts from the era provide dramatically different interpretations of the world. The first, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-1522637913475792">Figure 13</xref>—unlike <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1522637913475792">Figure 6</xref>—went to a different extreme of desanitizing war; that is, it made it all too real. This iconic image of a burial party on the Cold Harbor battlefield captured a new reality that transcended a singular image, conveying a new vision—a haunting one—of life and death and, indeed, of freedom and slavery.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn92-1522637913475792">92</xref></sup> Unlike popular notions before the Civil War of the United States as a place where American culture would civilize the world through progressive advances in technology and wealth, the burial party at Cold Harbor exposed death, wildly uncontrolled and wreaking havoc on the idea that humans at the time had developed a more humane way to live.</p>
<fig id="fig13-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 13.</label>
<caption>
<p>“A Burial Party on the Battle-Field of Cold Harbor, April 1, 1865,” John Reekie, photographer, in <italic>Gardner’s Photographic Sketch Book of the War</italic>, Alexander Gardner (Washington, DC: Philip and Solomons, 1865–66), vol. 2, no. 94, 1866, Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/2002713100">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/2002713100</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig13.tif"/></fig>
<p>In this photograph, among the most harrowing from the battlefield—or what once was a battlefield—an African American sits with a stretcher full of skulls and partial corpses as he and other men reinter the dead, months after the battles of Gaines’ Mill and Cold Harbor.</p>
<p>The following excerpt from a caption for the picture originally published in Alexander Gardner’s <italic>Photographic Sketch Book of the War</italic> describes a “sad scene” in language that would have resonated with contemporary readers. “It speaks ill of the residents of that part of Virginia, that they allowed even the remains of those they considered enemies, to decay unnoticed where they fell. The soldiers, to whom commonly falls the task of burying the dead, may possibly have been called away before the task was completed. At such times the native dwellers of the neighborhood would usually come forward and provide sepulture for such as had been left uncovered.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn93-1522637913475792">93</xref></sup> The photograph exemplifies the limits of photography during the Civil War. Rather than depicting battles as they unfolded, Gardner, O’Sullivan, Brady, and others often had to content themselves with scenes of postbattle carnage—shocking, but literally and figuratively lifeless.</p>
<p>On a denotative, or descriptive, level we see a foreground that depicts the results of war: death, a stretcher (noting the handles on either side) on which rests broken bodies and the skulls of five men (with a sixth lying on the ground), and a seated African American man who might have been operating the stretcher. The body parts and skulls are rather haphazardly arranged, as if the men simply tossed them on the cart with little regard or ceremony. They may be Confederate soldier remains—former slave owners, perhaps, fighting to keep that institution alive. Thus, we might sympathize with these men and their profane treatment of these remains. We see a single disembodied boot lying in front of the stretcher. The five skulls atop the pile look as though they were placed purposely and possibly to keep a count of the number of bodies unearthed. With almost Hamlet-like similarity, the skull on the far left gazes out at the viewer along with the seated man—the man expressionless, the skull seemingly smiling at us. Although slightly angled downward from left to right, the composition of the photograph is balanced. In the background, four men, tools in hand, dig into the earth to recover more bodies and body parts.</p>
<p>On the symbolic or connotative level, we have the African Americans, possibly former slaves, performing the grim and thankless task of cleaning up the battlefield. In many ways, they are as dead as the remains they gather, their futures unclear, their lives as torn as the bodies on the stretcher. This image symbolically depicts a Holocaust—an American Holocaust—and like the Holocaust imagery from a later war, it documents the tragedy of war’s reality. Indeed, death and photography are intricately intertwined. Images of death, in many ways, took center stage in the photographic work coming out of the Civil War. We find this difficult to understand today, in part because modern governments have tried to suppress the dissemination of images of death to maintain control of public perception and maintain home-front morale. More generally, in addition, photographing bodies grew common later in the nineteenth century. To create a keepsake, Americans of the time often hired photographers to take pictures of a dead relative, sometimes surrounded by family members.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn94-1522637913475792">94</xref></sup></p>
<p>Today, by contrast, the practice is simply not acceptable in most cases, although the decentralized nature of the Internet—as well as some other media forms such as documentary film and surveillance video—have provided images of death and destruction that occasionally leak through controlling agents and agencies to shock the public. The practice of photographing the dead reflects an era’s familiarity with death, writes cultural historian Nicholas Mirzoeff. Photography’s beginnings came at a time of “profound social change in attitudes to the dead and to death. It thus participated in a new means of configuring death at the same time that it offered an everyday reminder of death.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn95-1522637913475792">95</xref></sup> Mirzoeff concludes that death was simply part of nineteenth-century everyday life in a way that is difficult for those of us in the modern West to imagine. Death did not take place so much in hospitals as it did in the home. Infant mortality rates were high, diseases easily cured today killed people in the prime of life, and surgical tools and techniques that today save the lives of victims of traumatic accidents and wartime wounds simply did not exist. As former slaves, the men in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-1522637913475792">Figure 13</xref> were probably well acquainted with death in its many forms.</p>
<p>At almost the other extreme—in both the medium and the message—<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-1522637913475792">Figure 14</xref> depicts a sense of profound optimism, one afforded by the same forms of technological innovation that also helped create the weapons of destruction used in the Civil War. The artist of “The Progress of the Century,” an 1876 Currier and Ives lithograph, depicts the technological innovations that influenced both the course of the Civil War and the development of the nineteenth-century press—with a man using the telegraph in the foreground, and a steam press, a steamboat, and a locomotive featured behind.</p>
<fig id="fig14-1522637913475792" position="float">
<label>Figure 14.</label>
<caption>
<p>“The Progress of the Century—The Lightning Steam Press, the Electric Telegraph, the Locomotive, [and] the Steamboat,” Currier and Ives lithograph, 1876, Library of Congress, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/90716345">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/90716345</ext-link>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1522637913475792-fig14.tif"/></fig>
<p>Although the “progress” depicted in the lithograph coincided with the terrible bloodshed of the Civil War, many Americans at the time believed that the Union victory made possible the continued advances in communications and transportation throughout the remainder of the century. The artist even invokes divine will as part of technological innovation, as evidenced by the telegraphic message sprawling to the floor: “Liberty and Union now and forever one and inseparable. Glory to God in the highest. On earth, peace, good will toward men.”</p>
<p>Nevertheless, important continuities exist. The sensational images of the Civil War, the Reconstruction, and the Gilded Age helped lay the groundwork for illustrated, photographic, and even color visual materials during the era of yellow journalism, as well as the sensational tabloids of the 1920s. As Tebbel and Zuckerman have noted, “Frank Leslie’s various illustrated papers had pictured society, scandal, civic problems, politics, and a variety of other matters in essentially the same way the tabloids and their supplements were doing half a century or more later. The difference, of course, was photography and the technology of reproducing pictures.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn96-1522637913475792">96</xref></sup> The technology changed, yet the nature of the depictions remained the same.</p>
<p>While the images studied in this monograph can gauge to some extent both the interests of readers and the trends in publishing at the time, the overall effect of these images should not be overstated. Just as with other forms of communication, an image can have myriad effects, some of which may include its ability to inform viewers, or serve a cathartic function, or to evoke, as Paul F. Lazarsfeld and Robert K. Merton suggested in terms more theoretical, an action-numbing effect similar to the narcotizing dysfunction.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn97-1522637913475792">97</xref></sup> Although images can clearly influence the understanding of events—both among contemporary viewers and among subsequent generations—broader social forces can overwhelm the impact of even the most potent images, leaving conclusions about their overall meaning the subject of continued historical inquiry.</p>
<p>Indeed, early photographers themselves pointed to these choices in defending their work as a new art form rather than as mere visual stenography.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn98-1522637913475792">98</xref></sup> In 1851, the first issue of the <italic>Photographic Art-Journal</italic> praised Brady for “elevating [the daguerreotype] into the dignity and beauty of an art of taste.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn99-1522637913475792">99</xref></sup> The pictorial record initiated during the Civil War, as declared by Henry Wysham Lanier in 1911, was “indisputably authentic, vividly illuminating, and the final evidence in any question of detail.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn100-1522637913475792">100</xref></sup></p>
<p>Regardless, photographs at best reflect one reality, often an incomplete one. Stated plainly, a photograph can be faked. A scene can be rearranged, as Brady was accused of doing in some of his pictures. Or a greater fraud can be perpetrated, as William H. Mumler notoriously did with his double-exposure “spirit photographs” in the years after the Civil War.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn101-1522637913475792">101</xref></sup> Even in the absence of staging and trick photography, a photograph reflects choices made by its creator, including choices of perspective, distance, and exposure time.</p>
<p>In sum, Americans of the nineteenth century had read about General Burnside, but for most of them, it took Brady’s portrait to put a face to him and make his persona at least in part a visual reality. In addition, many contemporary viewers approached the images with experiences that we lack. To take the most obvious case, we know how the Civil War ended; they did not. And while they did not know the trajectory of the rest of the nineteenth century, we can in hindsight assess what newspaper audiences found to be both shocking and entertaining.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1522637913475792">
<label>1</label>
<p>Gary L. Bunker, <italic>From Rail-Splitter to Icon: Lincoln’s Image in Illustrated Periodicals, 1860–1865</italic> (Kent, OH: Kent State University Press, 2001), 2, 4, 111–49; William E. Huntzicker, “Picturing the News: Frank Leslie and the Origins of American Pictorial Journalism,” in <italic>The Civil War and the Press</italic>, ed. David B. Sachsman, S. Kittrell Rushing, and Debra Reddin van Tuyll (New Brunswick, NJ: Transaction, 2000), 312; Naomi Rosenblum, <italic>A World History of Photography</italic> (New York: Abbeville Press, 1989), 155.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1522637913475792">
<label>2</label>
<p>Richard B. Kielbowicz, <italic>News in the Mail: The Press, Post Office, and Public Information, 1700–1860s</italic> (Westport, CT: Greenwood, 1989), 107; James M. McPherson, <italic>Ordeal by Fire: The Civil War and Reconstruction</italic> (Boston: McGraw-Hill, 2001), 19.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1522637913475792">
<label>3</label>
<p>David W. Bulla and Gregory A. Borchard, <italic>Journalism in the Civil War Era</italic> (New York: Peter Lang, 2010), 90–94.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1522637913475792">
<label>4</label>
<p>Charles S. Peirce, “On a New List of Categories,” <italic>Proceedings of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences</italic> 7 (1868): 287–98.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1522637913475792">
<label>5</label>
<p>Walter Benjamin, <italic>The Work of Art in the Age of Mechanical Reproduction</italic> (New York: Prism Key Press, 2010), 12.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1522637913475792">
<label>6</label>
<p><italic>Geoffrey Batchen, “Ghost Stories: The Beginnings and Ends of Photography,” Art Monthly Australia 76 (December 1994): 4–8.</italic></p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1522637913475792">
<label>7</label>
<p>Charles H. Caffin, <italic>A Short History of Art</italic> (New York: Dodd, Mead and Company, 1921), 660–65; Marilyn Stokstad, <italic>Art History</italic>, rev. ed., vol. 2 (New York: Harry N. Abrams, 1995), 973. The Hudson River School, a style of romantic painting during the early nineteenth century, captured prominent themes of discovery, exploration, and settlement. Thomas Cole, one of the movement’s most well-known artists, featured landscapes of upstate New York. Cole also produced thousands of sketches of various subjects.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1522637913475792">
<label>8</label>
<p>Marshall McLuhan, <italic>Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man</italic> (New York: McGraw-Hill, 1964), 190.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1522637913475792">
<label>9</label>
<p>The Library of Congress archives explains this practice, citing the Alexander Gardner photo “Gettysburg, Pa., Dead Confederate Soldier in the Devil’s Den” as a case study; accessed January 2, 2013, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/cwphtml/cwpcam/cwcam3c.html">memory.loc.gov/ammem/cwphtml/cwpcam/cwcam3c.html</ext-link>. Also see William Frassanito, <italic>Gettysburg: A Journey in Time</italic> (New York: Charles Scribner’s Sons, 1975), 186–92.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1522637913475792">
<label>10</label>
<p>Hans Robert Jauss, <italic>Toward an Aesthetic of Reception</italic>, trans. Timothy Bahit (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1982), 25, 28.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1522637913475792">
<label>11</label>
<p>Alan Trachtenberg, <italic>Reading American Photographs: Images as History, Mathew Brady to Walker Evans</italic> (New York: Hill and Wang, 1989), 84–85.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-1522637913475792">
<label>12</label>
<p>Ibid.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-1522637913475792">
<label>13</label>
<p>Richard Rudisill, <italic>Mirror Image: The Influence of the Daguerreotype on American Society</italic> (Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1971), 231.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-1522637913475792">
<label>14</label>
<p>Neil Harris, <italic>Cultural Excursions: Marketing Appetites and Cultural Tastes in Modern America</italic> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1990), 307–8; see Estelle Jussim, <italic>Visual Communication and the Graphic Arts: Photographic Technologies in the Nineteenth Century</italic> (New York: R. R. Bowker, 1983).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-1522637913475792">
<label>15</label>
<p>Susan Sontag, <italic>On Photography</italic> (1977; repr., New York: Anchor, 1989), 4.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-1522637913475792">
<label>16</label>
<p>Ibid., 6–7.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn17-1522637913475792">
<label>17</label>
<p>Graham Clarke, <italic>The Photograph</italic> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1997), 33.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn18-1522637913475792">
<label>18</label>
<p>Sontag, <italic>On Photography</italic>, 17.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn19-1522637913475792">
<label>19</label>
<p>Susan Sontag, <italic>Regarding the Pain of Others</italic> (New York: Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 2003), 8, 13; Barbie Zelizer, “When War Is Reduced to a Photograph,” in <italic>Reporting War: Journalism in Wartime</italic>, ed. Stuart Allen and Barbie Zelizer (London: Routledge, 2004), 115–35.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn20-1522637913475792">
<label>20</label>
<p>Christian Frei, <italic>War Photographer</italic> (First Run/Icarus Films, Christian Frei Filmproductions, 2001).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn21-1522637913475792">
<label>21</label>
<p>Sontag, <italic>Regarding the Pain of Others</italic>, 20.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn22-1522637913475792">
<label>22</label>
<p>Clement K. Shorter, “Illustrated Journalism,” <italic>Contemporary Review</italic> 75 (April 1899): 483. On the development of the illustrated press in Britain, see Gerry Beegan, <italic>The Mass Image: A Social History of Photomechanical Reproduction in Victorian London</italic> (New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2008); Beegan, “The Mechanization of the Image: Facsimile, Photography, and Fragmentation in Nineteenth-Century Wood Engraving,” <italic>Journal of Design History</italic> 8, no. 4 (1995): 257–74; Mason Jackson, <italic>The Pictorial Press: Its Origin and Progress</italic> (1885; repr., New York: Burt Franklin, 1969).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn23-1522637913475792">
<label>23</label>
<p>Robert B. Rhode and Floyd H. McCall, <italic>Press Photography: Reporting with a Camera</italic> (New York: Macmillan, 1961), 19; Frank Luther Mott, <italic>American Journalism</italic>, 3rd ed. (New York: Macmillan, 1962), 85, 97.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn24-1522637913475792">
<label>24</label>
<p>Joshua Brown, <italic>Beyond the Lines: Pictorial Reporting, Everyday Life, and the Crisis of Gilded Age America</italic> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2002), 12; Rhode and McCall, <italic>Press Photography</italic>, 19–21.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn25-1522637913475792">
<label>25</label>
<p>Michael L. Carlebach, <italic>The Origins of Photojournalism in America</italic> (Washington, DC: Smithsonian Institution Press, 1992), 63.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn26-1522637913475792">
<label>26</label>
<p>Stephen P. Rice, “Photography in Engraving on Wood: On the Road to the Halftone Revolution,” <italic>Common-Place</italic> 7, no. 3 (April 2007), accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://common-place.org">http://common-place.org</ext-link>.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn27-1522637913475792">
<label>27</label>
<p>Brown, <italic>Beyond the Lines</italic>, 48, 70.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn28-1522637913475792">
<label>28</label>
<p>Ibid., 14; Edwin Emery, <italic>The Press and America: An Interpretative History of the Mass Media</italic>, 3rd ed. (Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall, 1972), 340.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn29-1522637913475792">
<label>29</label>
<p>Andrea G. Pearson, “<italic>Frank Leslie’s Illustrated Newspaper</italic> and <italic>Harper’s Weekly</italic>: Innovation and Imitation in Nineteenth-Century American Pictorial Reporting,” <italic>Journal of Popular Culture</italic> 23, no. 4 (Spring 1990): 81–111; Mott, <italic>American Journalism</italic>, 332, 379; Rhode and McCall, <italic>Press Photography</italic>, 21.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn30-1522637913475792">
<label>30</label>
<p>John D. Stevens, “Sensationalism in Perspective,” <italic>Journalism History</italic> 12, nos. 3–4 (Autumn/Winter 1985): 78. News featuring local crime, accidents, and the bizarre, Stevens notes, could even be found in the city streets of Rome millennia ago with postings of events throughout the city and from around the empire on a white tablet with copied-out newsletters. For additional sources on the development of sensational content over the millennia, see David Copeland, <italic>Colonial American Newspapers: Character and Content</italic> (Newark: University of Delaware Press, 1997), 18, 19, 69; Warren Francke, “Sensationalism and the Development of 19th-Century Reporting: The Broom Sweeps Sensory Details,” <italic>Journalism History</italic> 12, nos. 3–4 (Autumn/Winter, 1985): 80, 84; David Paul Nord, “Teleology and News: The Religious Roots of American Journalism,” <italic>Journal of American History</italic> 77, no. 1 (June 1990): 10, 11, 14; Donald L. Shaw and John W. Slater, “In the Eye of the Beholder? Sensationalism in American Press News,” <italic>Journalism History</italic> 12, nos. 3–4 (Autumn/Winter 1985): 86, 87; Mitchell Stephens, <italic>A History of News</italic> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2007), 94, 102; Stephens, “Sensationalism and Moralizing in 16th- and 17th-Century Newsbooks and News Ballads,” <italic>Journalism History</italic> 12, nos. 3–4 (Autumn/Winter 1985): 92.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn31-1522637913475792">
<label>31</label>
<p>Patricia Cline Cohen, <italic>The Murder of Helen Jewett</italic> (New York: Knopf, 1998), 37.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn32-1522637913475792">
<label>32</label>
<p>Matthew Sweet, <italic>Inventing the Victorians</italic> (New York: St. Martin’s, 2001), 4–5.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn33-1522637913475792">
<label>33</label>
<p>Ibid., 7.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn34-1522637913475792">
<label>34</label>
<p>“The Third Regular Trade Sale,” <italic>New York Times</italic>, September 12, 1856; “State of the City,” <italic>New York Times</italic>, February 23, 1857.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn35-1522637913475792">
<label>35</label>
<p>Robert L. Willis, “Communication from Mr. Robert L. Willis,” <italic>New York Times</italic>, October 26, 1858.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn36-1522637913475792">
<label>36</label>
<p>Guy Reel, <italic>The National Police Gazette and the Making of the Modern American Man, 1879–1906</italic> (New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2006), 192.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn37-1522637913475792">
<label>37</label>
<p>Joshua Brown, “The Days’ Doings: The Gilded Age in the Profane Pictorial Press” (paper, American Studies Association annual meeting, Hartford, CT, October 17, 2003), accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://joshbrownnyc.com">http://joshbrownnyc.com</ext-link>.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn38-1522637913475792">
<label>38</label>
<p>Robert Taft, <italic>Photography and the American Scene: A Social History, 1839–1889</italic> (New York: Macmillan, 1938), 427; Don C. Seitz, <italic>Training for the Newspaper Trade</italic> (Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott, 1916), 126, 127; Rhode and McCall, <italic>Press Photography</italic>, 21.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn39-1522637913475792">
<label>39</label>
<p>Brown, <italic>Beyond the Lines</italic>, 14.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn40-1522637913475792">
<label>40</label>
<p>Valerian Gribayédoff, “Pictorial Journalism,” <italic>Cosmopolitan</italic> 11, no. 4 (August 1891): 474; Seitz, <italic>Training for the Newspaper Trade</italic>, 127; Emery, <italic>Press and America</italic>, 340; Taft, <italic>Photography and the American Scene</italic>, 427; Rhode and McCall, <italic>Press Photography</italic>, 22.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn41-1522637913475792">
<label>41</label>
<p>Mott, <italic>American Journalism</italic>, 438; Taft, <italic>Photography and the American Scene</italic>, 428.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn42-1522637913475792">
<label>42</label>
<p>Gribayédoff, “Pictorial Journalism,” 477.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn43-1522637913475792">
<label>43</label>
<p>Ibid., 480; Thomas Campbell-Copeland, <italic>The Ladder of Journalism: How to Climb It</italic> (New York: Allan Forman, 1889), 73; Mott, <italic>American Journalism</italic>, 502.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn44-1522637913475792">
<label>44</label>
<p>Seitz, <italic>Training for the Newspaper Trade</italic>, 128, 132.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn45-1522637913475792">
<label>45</label>
<p>“Praise the <italic>Times</italic>’s Move,” <italic>New York Times</italic>, September 7, 1899; Campbell-Copeland, <italic>Ladder of Journalism</italic>, 73; Taft, <italic>Photography and the American Scene</italic>, 447.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn46-1522637913475792">
<label>46</label>
<p>“Things Talked Of,” <italic>Harper’s Weekly</italic>, April 22, 1893.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn47-1522637913475792">
<label>47</label>
<p>“Newspaper Pictures,” <italic>Nation</italic> (April 27, 1893): 307.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn48-1522637913475792">
<label>48</label>
<p>“The <italic>Times</italic> at One Cent,” <italic>New York Times</italic>, April 10, 1899.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn49-1522637913475792">
<label>49</label>
<p>Max De Lipman, “The Newspaper Illustrator,” in <italic>The Making of a Newspaper: Experiences of Certain Representative American Journalists Related by Themselves</italic>, ed. Melville Phillips (New York: Putnam, 1893), 181.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn50-1522637913475792">
<label>50</label>
<p>Mott, <italic>American Journalism</italic>, 501; Rhode and McCall, <italic>Press Photography</italic>, 22.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn51-1522637913475792">
<label>51</label>
<p>Taft, <italic>Photography and the American Scene</italic>, 430, 437, 438, 441, 446.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn52-1522637913475792">
<label>52</label>
<p>Rhode and McCall, <italic>Press Photography</italic>, 22; John Tebbel and Mary Ellen Zuckerman, <italic>The Magazine in America, 1741–1990</italic> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1991), 75.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn53-1522637913475792">
<label>53</label>
<p>Emery, <italic>Press and America</italic>, 341; Mott, <italic>American Journalism</italic>, 501, 502.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn54-1522637913475792">
<label>54</label>
<p>Shorter, “Illustrated Journalism,” 553; Taft, <italic>Photography and the American Scene</italic>, 444, 445. On the demise of woodcuts, see Thomas J. Lindsey, “Type-Making, Stereotyping, Picture-Making,” in <italic>Triumphs and Wonders of the 19th Century: The True Mirror of a Phenomenal Era</italic>, ed. James P. Boyd (Philadelphia: A. J. Holman, 1899), 568.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn55-1522637913475792">
<label>55</label>
<p>Rhode and McCall, <italic>Press Photography</italic>, 22, 23.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn56-1522637913475792">
<label>56</label>
<p>Karin E. Becker, “Photojournalism and the Tabloid Press,” in <italic>Journalism and Popular Culture</italic>, ed. Peter Dahlgren and Colin Sparks (London: Sage, 1992), 130.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn57-1522637913475792">
<label>57</label>
<p>“Praise the <italic>Times</italic>’s Move,” <italic>New York Times</italic>, September 7, 1899.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn58-1522637913475792">
<label>58</label>
<p>“A New Code for Dailies,” <italic>New York Times</italic>, June 29, 1901, A10; Taft, <italic>Photography and the American Scene</italic>, 448. Similar assertions were common during the heyday of the tabloids in the 1920s, when photographs were widely viewed as exemplifying sensationalism, with a commentator, in one such example, predicting photo-filled tabloids would “enfeeble” the minds of readers, dulling their thinking and robbing them “of any remnant of intellectual initiative, and worse—even make them forget how to read.” Historian Robert Taft wrote in 1938 that “mention of the term ‘photograph’ in journalism has come to mean <italic>sensational</italic> journalism.”</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn59-1522637913475792">
<label>59</label>
<p>Rhode and McCall, <italic>Press Photography</italic>, 21; on the popularity of lithographed portraits, see Brown, <italic>Beyond the Lines</italic>, 10.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn60-1522637913475792">
<label>60</label>
<p>Amy Louise Wood, <italic>Lynching and Spectacle: Witnessing Racial Violence in America, 1890–1940</italic> (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 2009), 107.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn61-1522637913475792">
<label>61</label>
<p>Bret Harte, <italic>Her Letter, His Answer, and Her Last Letter</italic> (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1905), 18.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn62-1522637913475792">
<label>62</label>
<p>Rosenblum, <italic>World History of Photography</italic>, 178–84.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn63-1522637913475792">
<label>63</label>
<p>Rudisill, <italic>Mirror Image</italic>, 197.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn64-1522637913475792">
<label>64</label>
<p>Rosenblum, <italic>World History of Photography</italic>, 191.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn65-1522637913475792">
<label>65</label>
<p>“Cabinet Portraits,” <italic>Photographic News: A Weekly Record</italic> 10 (May 18, 1866): 239. This particular issue of <italic>Photographic News</italic> documented the advent of the cabinet portrait, devoting several columns to the new pictographic form. One ad reads, “We have commenced issuing to our customers a cabinet picture 5.5 inches by 4 inches, and we find that they give very great satisfaction, and are greatly preferred to the carte-de-visite; as, while they are equally pretty pictures, they are, from their increased size, necessarily better portraits.”</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn66-1522637913475792">
<label>66</label>
<p>“Webster’s Photograph Gallery,” in <italic>Louisville in the Civil War: Lithographers and Photographers</italic>, ed. Kraig McNutt, 6, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scribd.com/kraigm">http://scribd.com/kraigm</ext-link>.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn67-1522637913475792">
<label>67</label>
<p>“Incidents of the War—The Battles of South Mountain and Antietam,” <italic>New York Herald</italic>, October 5, 1862. The <italic>Herald</italic> praised Brady on several occasions for both contributing valuable documents for historical purposes as well as advancing the artistic depictions of the war—see, for example, “Photographic Chef d’Ouvre—Brady’s ‘Sanitary Commission,’” April 18, 1864; “Brady’s New Photographs,” May 31, 1864.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn68-1522637913475792">
<label>68</label>
<p>Bulla and Borchard, <italic>Journalism in the Civil War Era</italic>, 94–105, 213–14.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn69-1522637913475792">
<label>69</label>
<p>“General Grant at Brady Photographic Gallery,” <italic>New York Herald</italic>, November 24, 1864.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn70-1522637913475792">
<label>70</label>
<p>For primary press accounts, see Cleveland <italic>Plain Dealer</italic>, May 12, 1863; Fort Wayne (IN) <italic>Dawson’s Daily Times &amp; Union</italic>, May 23, 1863.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn71-1522637913475792">
<label>71</label>
<p>“Brady’s Photographs; Pictures of the Dead at Antietam,” <italic>New York Times</italic>, October 20, 1862.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn72-1522637913475792">
<label>72</label>
<p>Benson J. Lossing and Mathew B. Brady, <italic>A History of the Civil War, 1861–65, and the Causes That Led Up to the Great Conflict</italic> (New York: War Memorial Association, 1912), 2.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn73-1522637913475792">
<label>73</label>
<p>Roy Meredith, <italic>Mr. Lincoln’s Camera Man, Mathew B. Brady</italic> (Mineola, NY: Dover, 1974), 3.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn74-1522637913475792">
<label>74</label>
<p>McPherson, <italic>The Battle Cry of Freedom</italic> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), 659–69.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn75-1522637913475792">
<label>75</label>
<p>Ibid., 664.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn76-1522637913475792">
<label>76</label>
<p>“The Late Battle of Gettysburg: Brady’s Photographs of the Scene of Conflict,” <italic>New York Herald</italic>, August 6, 1863.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn77-1522637913475792">
<label>77</label>
<p>“Incidents of the War,” <italic>New York Herald</italic>, October 5, 1862; “Photographic Chef d’Ouvre,” <italic>New York Herald</italic>, April 18, 1864; “Brady’s New Photographs,” <italic>New York Herald</italic>, May 31, 1864; “General Grant at Brady Photographic Gallery,” <italic>New York Herald</italic>, November 24, 1864.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn78-1522637913475792">
<label>78</label>
<p>“A Harvest of Death, Gettysburg, Pennsylvania,” T. H. O’Sullivan, photographer, published July 1863, accessed May 15, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/2006685384">http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/2006685384</ext-link>; also see <italic>Gardner’s Photographic Sketch Book of the War</italic>, vol. 1 (New York: Dover, 1959), no. 36; James David Horan, <italic>Timothy O’Sullivan: America’s Forgotten Photographer</italic> (New York: Doubleday, 1966), 30.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn79-1522637913475792">
<label>79</label>
<p>Trachtenberg, <italic>Reading American Photographs</italic>, 71–118.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn80-1522637913475792">
<label>80</label>
<p><italic>Gardner’s Photographic Sketch Book of the War</italic>, Introduction.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn81-1522637913475792">
<label>81</label>
<p>Joseph M. Wilson, “A Eulogy on the Life and Character of Alexander Gardner,” accessed January 2, 2013, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tinyurl.com/aqtlvdh">http://tinyurl.com/aqtlvdh</ext-link>; Meredith, <italic>Mr. Lincoln’s Camera Man</italic>, 54; Anne E. Peterson, “Alexander Gardner in Review,” <italic>History of Photography</italic>, 34, 4 (November 2010): 356–67.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn82-1522637913475792">
<label>82</label>
<p>Trachtenberg, <italic>Reading American Photographs</italic>, 71–118.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn83-1522637913475792">
<label>83</label>
<p><italic>Gardner’s Photographic Sketch Book of the War</italic>, vol. 1, images 35 to 44 feature Gardner’s work at Gettysburg, among the most remarkable of his career.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn84-1522637913475792">
<label>84</label>
<p>Peterson, “Alexander Gardner in Review.”</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn85-1522637913475792">
<label>85</label>
<p>Trachtenberg, <italic>Reading American Photographs</italic>, 72.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn86-1522637913475792">
<label>86</label>
<p>Ibid., 73.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn87-1522637913475792">
<label>87</label>
<p>Clarke, <italic>The Photograph</italic>, 35.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn88-1522637913475792">
<label>88</label>
<p>Quoted in Donald Christian Peterson, “Two Pioneer American Picture Magazines” (MS thesis, University of Wisconsin, 1953), 116.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn89-1522637913475792">
<label>89</label>
<p>Pearson, “<italic>Frank Leslie’s Illustrated Newspaper</italic> and <italic>Harper’s Weekly</italic>,” 132–33.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn90-1522637913475792">
<label>90</label>
<p>Peterson, “Two Pioneer American Picture Magazines,” 118, 123, 134.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn91-1522637913475792">
<label>91</label>
<p>Jonathan Crary, <italic>Techniques of the Observer: On Vision and Modernity in the Nineteenth Century</italic> (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1992), 13.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn92-1522637913475792">
<label>92</label>
<p>Ian Frederick Finseth, “Bring Out Your Dead: Improper Burial in American Civil War Literature” (paper, 17th Annual Symposium on the 19th Century Press, the Civil War and Free Expression, Chattanooga, TN, November 12–14, 2009); Lindsey H. Gregory, “Depictions of Death on the Battlefield: Press Use of Photography during the American Civil War, 1861–1865” (paper, 17th Annual Symposium on the 19th Century Press, the Civil War and Free Expression, Chattanooga, TN, November 12–14, 2009). Two papers presented at the 2009 Symposium on the 19th Century Press, the Civil War and Free Expression explored this photograph in some detail. Finseth’s “Bring Out Your Dead” examined the impact of Civil War mortality on the development of late-nineteenth-century American popular literature. Gregory’s “Depictions of Death on the Battlefield” reviewed a genre of war photos that depicted death on the battlefield.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn93-1522637913475792">
<label>93</label>
<p><italic>Gardner’s Photographic Sketch Book of the War</italic>, vol. 2, no. 94.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn94-1522637913475792">
<label>94</label>
<p>See Barbara P. Norfleet, <italic>Looking at Death</italic> (Boston: David R. Godine, 1993).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn95-1522637913475792">
<label>95</label>
<p>Nicholas Mirzoeff, <italic>An Introduction to Visual Culture</italic> (New York: Routledge, 1999), 75.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn96-1522637913475792">
<label>96</label>
<p>Tebbel and Zuckerman, <italic>Magazine in America</italic>, 229; on sensationalism and <italic>Leslie’s</italic>, see Mott, <italic>American Journalism</italic>, 379.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn97-1522637913475792">
<label>97</label>
<p>Paul F. Lazarsfeld and Robert K. Merton, “Mass Communication, Popular Taste, and Organized Social Action,” in <italic>Communication of Ideas</italic>, ed. Lyman Bryson (New York: Harper, 1948), 95–118.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn98-1522637913475792">
<label>98</label>
<p>Harris, <italic>Cultural Excursions</italic>, 310.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn99-1522637913475792">
<label>99</label>
<p>C. Edwards Lester, “M. B. Brady and the Photographic Art,” <italic>Photographic Art-Journal</italic> 1, no. 1 (January 1851): 37.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn100-1522637913475792">
<label>100</label>
<p>Henry Wysham Lanier, “Photographing the Civil War,” <italic>American Review of Reviews</italic> 43, no. 3 (March 1911): 302.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn101-1522637913475792">
<label>101</label>
<p>See Louis Kaplan, <italic>The Strange Case of William Mumler, Spirit Photographer</italic> (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2008).</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Gregory A. Borchard</bold> is an associate in the Hank Greenspun School of Journalism and Media Studies at the University of Nevada, Las Vegas (UNLV). His research has focused on the nineteenth century press and includes <italic>Abraham Lincoln and Horace Greeley</italic>, a book published by Southern Illinois University Press (2011), and the co-authored book <italic>Journalism in the Civil War Era</italic> for Peter Lang (2010). He teaches classes in journalism history, reporting, and research methods.</p>
<p><bold>Lawrence J. Mullen</bold> is a professor in the Hank Greenspun School of Journalism and Media Studies at the University of Nevada, Las Vegas (UNLV). His research and teaching interests include the study of visual aesthetics, and media and community. His publications have explored the phenomenon of visual communication in several settings including the nexus between community and visuality. His courses feature the subjects of visual studies, research methods, social media, games, and virtual environments.</p>
<p><bold>Stephen Bates</bold> is an associate professor in the Hank Greenspun School of Journalism and Media Studies at the University of Nevada, Las Vegas (UNLV). He is the author, coauthor, or editor of four books. He has been a fellow of the Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars and the Joan Shorenstein Center for the Press, Politics and Public Policy at Harvard University. He teaches First Amendment law and political communication courses.</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>