<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PAA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppaa</journal-id>
<journal-title>Pacifica</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1030-570X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1839-2598</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1030570X13489647</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1030570X13489647</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Vatican II and the history of Vatican II</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Melloni</surname><given-names>Alberto</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1030570X13489647"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1030570X13489647">Bologna, Italy</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1030570X13489647">Alberto Melloni, Fondazione per le scienze religiose Giovanni XXIII, via san Vitale 114, Bologna, 1-40125, Italy. Email: <email>melloni@fscire.it</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>26</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>134</fpage>
<lpage>154</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Pacifica Theological Studies Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article provides a critical account of the historical reception of Vatican II, identifying key questions that relate to the question of the history of the Council and its ongoing meaning and significance. A description of the five-volume <italic>History of Vatican II</italic> is followed by consideration of the critical responses to that work and subsequent phases of Vatican II historical scholarship. The article argues that this ongoing historical work is an essential dimension of the wider task of discerning the Council’s meaning and significance today.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Giuseppe Alberigo</kwd>
<kwd>hermeneutics</kwd>
<kwd>history</kwd>
<kwd>reception history</kwd>
<kwd>Vatican II</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1030570X13489647" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Vatican II, as with each and every church Council, has a peculiar profile. History may see different things in it.</p>
<p>Vatican II was a surprise. One may say that it was totally unexpected. No one in the college of cardinals elected Patriarch Roncalli for this purpose. When John XXIII said to his Secretary of State that he wanted to gather a Council, Domenico Tardini did not understand that the old man was serious and he was shocked, as were many others, when six days after the Pope announced a Council he invited ‘the other churches to take part with us in this banquet of grace’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1030570X13489647">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>Vatican II was also an achievement: it was long awaited.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1030570X13489647">2</xref></sup> Generations had been waiting, not for a new Council, but for a session to properly close Vatican I, which was simply interrupted in 1870.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1030570X13489647">3</xref></sup> Others were waiting for a Council of condemnation, like the one envisaged by Pacelli in the early 1940s,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1030570X13489647">4</xref></sup> a sort of ‘super-Denzinger’ that would be a summation of all the condemnations of the ‘Pius Popes’, from Pius IX to Pius XII.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1030570X13489647">5</xref></sup> Many hoped for a Council of unity, as sketched out in the encyclical published by Constantinople in 1921 and absorbed in the work for the World Council of Churches or elsewhere.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1030570X13489647">6</xref></sup></p>
<p>Vatican II was pastoral, where ‘pastoral’ did not mean something less than dogmatic, but a new way of understanding the truth, or even a reform of the very idea of revelation. So this says that Vatican II was an event.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1030570X13489647">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>For decades, scholars thought that to understand Vatican II, all one had to do was to validate a corpus or to ‘print’ the documents. This refers not to the corpus prepared by the Roman Curia (69 useless documents that were cast aside without discussion, in the very first moment of the Council) but to a corpus prepared in order to satisfy theologians and their hermeneutical efforts. From the perspective of the historian, however, Vatican II was an event that has to be studied not for what it produced, but for what it meant.</p>
<p>One of the most striking differences between the Council of Trent and Vatican II is the role of the papacy.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1030570X13489647">8</xref></sup> After Trent the Pope kept the documents on the Council as a closely guarded secret reserved for a special commission of the Roman Curia for its interpretation. After Vatican II, Paul VI decided to open all the archives to historical research. This choice, however, did not mark the first phase of the reception of Vatican II. The concern of the faithful, the bishops and the theologians was to implement Vatican II or to hope for Vatican III. And the risk – very visible around the mid-1980s – was to discuss empty ideas of the Council and to struggle with false dichotomies.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1030570X13489647">9</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1030570X13489647"><title>The history of Vatican II</title>
<p>Since 1988, a programme to develop a history of Vatican II was implemented in Bologna.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1030570X13489647">10</xref></sup> Professor Giuseppe Alberigo and an international team started the research project based on the idea that the historical core of the Council was the only object of the research. Indeed, this very core was capable of interpreting the event in all its potential.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1030570X13489647">11</xref></sup> Five volumes were published between 1995 and the 2000s in Italian, and later in English, German, Spanish, Portuguese, French, Russian (and hopefully Chinese and Polish), based on thousands of archives, journals, diaries, diplomatic reports, TV sources, newspapers and memoirs.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-1030570X13489647">12</xref></sup> The result of this research was closely commented upon by several journals, and it deserved much reflection: all this is now a <italic>corpus</italic> constantly monitored by the ‘Bollettino’ published by Massimo Faggioli in <italic>Cristianesimo nella Storia</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-1030570X13489647">13</xref></sup></p>
<p>In what follows I describe the history of that history of Vatican II. I will try to understand the reactions of distress and fear caused in some specific circles by the history of Vatican II. Immediately after the publication of the first volume in 1995, the daily newspaper <italic>L’Osservatore Romano</italic> published two full pages dedicated to the <italic>History of Vatican II</italic>. Longer than an encyclical, the review was signed by an ex-nuncio, who was originally from Vicenza and a student of monsignor Michele Maccarrone, lecturer in ecclesiastical history at the Lateran University. The author, Agostino Marchetto, was a name that only the most faithful readers of <italic>Apollinaris</italic> could recall. His critical review of the historical work takes the form of a warning, a sort of <italic>ne audeatur</italic> or a Clint Eastwood-style ‘go ahead, make my day’ phrasing. The concern was not with the basic documentation of episodes, conflicts, decisions and events, but for having ‘ignored’ the necessary identity between Councils and papal teachings, and having described Vatican II as an ‘event’. This indignation, for having avoided a presumed ‘obligation’, remained almost identical in analogous reviews published by the Vatican newspaper following the issue of volumes 2, 3 and 4, in which the reviewer presented a presumed ‘official’ defence of the Holy See and proposed, in essence, a type of Council ‘Docetism’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-1030570X13489647">14</xref></sup> Similar to those doctrines that claimed the illusory nature of the passion of Christ, the reality of Vatican II was reduced to an illusory appearance. According to Marchetto, the dialectics, the conflicts, the turning points had never existed, neither in the preparation (1959–62) nor afterwards. To evoke, with documentation at hand, its semblance, philologically narrate its pragmatics, and to underline the <italic>intention</italic> of John XXIII of a Council speaking without condemnation, created indignation for the polemicist: how could a history book dare say that what occurred in the Council actually occurred? With what level of audacity could it claim that Vatican II should not be interpreted as a deed in which the bishops deliberated upon that which the pope desires (and vice versa), without ripples and in any case without events of any significance? Such insolence, from his perspective, demonstrated the low level of quality of almost all scholars of the Council; liable to errors, prejudices, faults, for which the ‘school of Bologna’, i.e. Giuseppe Alberigo and his colleagues, were the origin and the synthesis.</p>
<p>The attack of 1995 and its iterations retained, however, significance that went beyond the grotesque style and gratuitous verbal violence that were utilized. Those who sympathized with the historiographical operation that was underway could not fail to be astonished at the emergence of a polemic of such strength and persistence (‘not even Hitler’ deserved such a treatment, commented an important reader of the Vatican newspaper in 2003). Those who did not appreciate such a brutal approach became immediately aware of the fact that reconstructing the history of the Vatican II Council was, <italic>ipso facto</italic>, a problem. What kind of history was the history of Vatican II to be? A biography of leaders? A history of ideas? All these operations are needed but the history of a synodical event is more than this. It is the understanding of its collective identity as a body.</p>
<p>All of this was at stake in the reception of Vatican II: the abandoning of the Lefebvrian gamble that, in 1988, had deluded itself that it could recruit John Paul II in the ‘anti-Council’ faction; the revision of the Code of Canon Law that assumed the communion ecclesiology as a standard hermeneutic criterion;<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-1030570X13489647">15</xref></sup> and the Extraordinary Synod of 1985 that resumed, through the Walter Kasper report, a (reductive) ecclesiology of the church as a universal sacrament of salvation.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-1030570X13489647">16</xref></sup> In the light of all the above, the bare historical work became intolerable to those who thought they mastered Vatican II. The full and integral historicization of the conciliar works – more than any possible systematization – supplied a key for a more severe interpretation of the event than the commentary on the texts.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-1030570X13489647">17</xref></sup></p>
<p>The simple act of preparing a history of Vatican II with first-hand sources was an attempt to mark a step from the generation of bishops of the Council to the generation of bishops who had been priests during it and who, in some cases, became disillusioned with hindsight. The very idea of recovering the overall doctrinal complexity and institutional structure of the Council, based on a documentary foundation, instigated a reaction of unforeseable violence amongst those in power.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1030570X13489647"><title>Open questions</title>
<p>The volumes of the <italic>History of Vatican II</italic> were based on a series of studies of the sources, the editorial aspects of the major documents, the wider environmental factors and key groups. This historical work highlighted several research questions that were still unresolved.</p>
<p>The first issue pertains to Paul VI’s role. The decision of John Paul II to proceed with the beatification of John XXIII, separately from that of Pacelli, contributed, between 1993 and 1999, to creating a dramatic disparity in documentation between the two popes of Vatican II.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-1030570X13489647">18</xref></sup> Access to the Roncalli papers was always more extensive and made available, to all parties, materials of enormous importance for the history of the Council: texts of Papal speeches and even the personal diaries of the Pope. The situation for Paul VI was reversed. An Institute in Brescia, had hidden the papers of the pope for years, yet, in a sign of bitter irony, had made available to all the documentation on Vatican II. Submerged by a level of discretion without rules, the sources on and about Montini in fact remained marginalized from scientific work. This exceptional situation led historians to evaluate a body of information on the attitude of Paul VI derived from collaborators, correspondence, hearing notes, the articles of Don Carlo Colombo, who was his trusted theologian, as well as the correspondence with the major leaders of the Council.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-1030570X13489647">19</xref></sup> This effort yielded significant results despite the gap that separates a first-hand source from individual rumours.</p>
<p>A second issue that became fundamental in the preparation of the final volumes of the <italic>History of Vatican II</italic> related to the reception of Vatican II before its completion. The approval, in 1963, of major liturgical reforms – the new Mass, the use of the vernacular, the desire for intercommunion, the desire of assemblies to be in the limelight,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20-1030570X13489647">20</xref></sup> adoption of new musical and artistic languages – contributed towards understanding the breaking of the majority that marked the year 1965. The issue was raised, with a certain degree of historiographical success, that the completion of Vatican II certainly did not result in the victory of a majority over an aggrieved minority, as had occurred with Vatican I.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21-1030570X13489647">21</xref></sup> The end of the Council, on the contrary, resulted in the emergence of tensions within the majority itself: partly disappointed by the lack of binding decisions; partly tired of that search for unanimous consent that Paul VI had required in the hope of counteracting the conservative subversion; and partly worried about an unrest in which an uncontrollable rebellious spirit seems inherent. The capacity for mutual listening, which was the key to Vatican II, was broken when theologians and bishops resumed following their own path. Some theologians feared the transformation of the Council reforms into a superficially interpreted breakdown with past. For others the lack of courage with respect to decisive themes (collegial institutions, reform of the curia, contraception, celibacy of the clergy, nuclear deterrence), which Paul VI deferred and which crushed him, was enough to diminish the value of Vatican II.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22-1030570X13489647">22</xref></sup></p>
<p>A third issue is that during the course of Vatican II, the internal cracks and antagonisms within the Holy See became increasingly clear. They are perhaps only perceived in the first volumes of the <italic>History of Vatican II,</italic> or perhaps highlighted by the development of Council events, for which historical/critical narration serves as a sensor.</p>
<p>A fourth issue concerns the role of local churches. I totally disagree with the idea that the role of the churches is established by the simple fact of their existence. The purpose of the historian is not only to document what really existed, but also to give weight and meaning, and this is vital for the reception of Vatican II as well as for the event as such.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1030570X13489647"><title>The attempted ‘Sarpization’ of Alberigo</title>
<p>The intellectual vigour of the discussion that was generated by Vatican II and by its historicization was consistent with the expectations of those who had worked on it. Even the polemical violence triggered by the specific ecclesiastical aspects cited above had a target that was not related to the historical/critical work, but had to do with the intrinsic connection between Vatican II and its history.</p>
<p>The aim of the type of assault mentioned above was to attempt an assimilation of Alberigo’s work with the earlier <italic>History of the Council of Trent</italic> by Brother Paolo Sarpi. The work by the Venetian Servite, who was the victim of an assassination attempt in which he recognized the <italic>stiletto</italic> of the Roman Curia (‘<italic>agnosco stylum romanæ curiæ</italic>’ was his notorious phrase), had been stored as a pro-Lutheran work that deserved loathing as a negative example of ‘political use’ of history. Against Sarpi – slightly after the mid-17th century (following the deaths of Terenzio Alciati and Felice Contelori) – the Jesuit Paolo Sforza Pallavicino was called upon to react. In a similar way, Marchetto aimed to be a modern-day Pallavicino in order to introduce Alberigo as a new Sarpi. The ‘Sarpization’ of Alberigo and of the five volumes that were incorrectly identified as the ‘school of Bologna’ had only been explicitly invoked once, on 22 June 2005, by Cardinal Camillo Ruini.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23-1030570X13489647">23</xref></sup> No rational person would argue for a link between Alberigo and Sarpi, but the ‘sarpization’ was not a historiographical theory and had nothing to do with the history of the 16th–17th or 20th centuries. The not always explicit, and perhaps not even conscious, plan was to render the event of the Council as entirely evanescent; a machine of disciplinary standing, and a body for decree-making that was, by necessity, ideologically superfluous and bearer of a <italic>quantité négligeable</italic> in theological terms.</p>
<p>In this process of oblivion, the preferred line of argumentation is that of introducing false dichotomies: those relative to the Council itself (dogmatic versus pastoral Council); those relative to the container of their meanings (letter of the Council versus spirit of the Council); that relative to the type of sources of historical work (acts vs. diaries) and trends (celebration vs. reception); and that relative to intentions (beginning vs. the end).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1030570X13489647"><title>A Second Quest?</title>
<p>The supreme and most recent dichotomy was obtained by stripping the 2005 speech by Benedict XVI, an exchange of Christmas wishes with the Holy See, of all subtleties of meaning. Despite the fact that the pope, when speaking of the single church entity from an ontological perspective, had created an exchange between the double concept of continuity and reform with that of discontinuity and rupture, a group of uneducated individuals vulgarized the continuity/discontinuity dichotomy in a manner that was inconceivable from a historical perspective and incompatible with the theological point that was so specific to Ratzinger’s ecclesiology and that underlies that statement.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24-1030570X13489647">24</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although the polemic aimed to request an ‘authentic’ interpretation of the Council from the supreme authority (an action that was not even contemplated by the popes of the 20th century) the result was not attained in a useful time period. The ecclesiastical bitterness that wanted to burden the research on the ‘Council of history’, obtained an ephemeral result. In practice, the first years of the 21st century resulted in what could be generously defined as a type of problematic Second Quest. The Second Quest was recognizable because it recommended an interpretation of the ideological polemic on the basis of that which can and cannot be said, and of historical/critical work on the basis of sources, as two equivalent polarities from which one should dissociate with equal levels of grace.</p>
<p>In this ‘middle way’ are included works that are primarily secondary sources and studies that are significantly more solid, but which end up granting the ‘occurrence’ of the Council to one side and allowing the others to move the dialectics of reception outside of Vatican II. The Canadian scholar Gilles Routhier was a protagonist of this idea: of a fragmented reception amongst the multiple players and playing fields, as well as amongst the multiple entities that are all legitimate targets for study, and cases that are obviously unique.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25-1030570X13489647">25</xref></sup> The risk is of making receptions of opposite types equivalent from a historical perspective, and of making choices between them on principle, or on the basis of a ‘theory’ of what the reception should be, rather than on the basis of what the Council itself was.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26-1030570X13489647">26</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1030570X13489647"><title>Moving towards a Third Quest?</title>
<p>The scholarly discussion of the <italic>History of Vatican II</italic> therefore created the foundation for what was beginning to be depicted as a <italic>Third Quest</italic> for Vatican II: a historicization that was capable of integrating the doctrinal shifts within historical reconstruction, without being intimidated by the technicalities of theological language, and remaining firmly set on its objective. Its meaning, in fact, goes beyond formulas in both realms. The problem was not to label the Council as an event in a nominalistic manner. This would not have required much work, nor even any historical research: it would have been enough to recall Canon 218 of the Pio-Benedictine code in order to remember that, according to Catholic doctrine (and more generally for Christian experience), the Council is the seat of <italic>full and supreme power</italic> given that, according to Christian tradition, it is the assistance of the Holy Spirit in the event that supports the decisions, and not the other way around. In 1909, the encyclopedia <italic>Catholicisme</italic> wrote that no new Council was necessary to the Roman Catholic Church, after the approval of the constitutions on infallibility and primacy of the Roman Pontiff, at Vatican I. Vatican II proved that <italic>Catholicisme</italic> was wrong. The <italic>History of Vatican II</italic> says why.</p>
<p><italic>De facto</italic> the publication of <italic>The History of Vatican II</italic> opened the way to a real change in how the Council was interpreted and played a major role in shaping the condition of the Church of Rome today. Strange as it may seem, there has not been a single dispute in the past 10 years that was not a consequence of Vatican II, which shows how its potential and effectiveness have endured. The idea of Vatican II as, on the one hand, an event, and its pastoral meaning on the other, are at the core of the research presented here. Recent publications by John O’Malley, Christoph Theobald, Peter Hünermann, and Giuseppe Ruggieri have brought out different aspects of Vatican II, and a new type of Ecumenical Council is now easier to contemplate than it used to be. But until we have come to fully know the potential of Vatican II, the ‘updating’ undertaken by John XXIII cannot yet be said to have played itself out in the church’s present and future.</p>
<p>The very category of <italic>événement</italic> has a historicity of its own. If we want to evoke it without running the risk of falling into the generic, we always need to specify what takes place, where, and for whom. Seeing Vatican II as an event only has meaning for the historian to the extent that it helps us to understand the dynamism of the real, within the limits of the information obtainable from the sources. Precisely this dynamism itself points those who hold that mandate to consider the church as though it were a subject in itself; but it is not the task of this church-as-subject to reflect on its own persistence. In the case of Vatican II its task is to give substance to what the Holy Spirit was saying to the churches between 1959 and 1965.</p>
<p>It is on this point that the part of the scholarly debate that came into existence after the publication of <italic>The History of Vatican II</italic>, and thanks to it, has taken a number of significant steps forward, of which the evidence can be seen in new inventories (which in historiographical terms are the building blocks without which nothing can be constructed), and in new editions of the source documents that make known the results of new investigations into the different sectors and problems of the assembly. In my view these publications include three particularly important works.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-1030570X13489647"><title>Did the Council happen?</title>
<p>In the late 1980s John O’Malley, a scholar of the Council of Trent who has for a long time been professor at the Weston School of Theology, had already drawn attention to the historicity of the nexus between transition and tradition at Vatican II; a topic to which he returned with even greater incisiveness after the end of Wojtyla’s pontificate.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27-1030570X13489647">27</xref></sup> In 2006 he wondered whether anything actually took place at Vatican II.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28-1030570X13489647">28</xref></sup> This was not his sarcastic way of settling a controversy between prelates, but of asking a question that had become historically decisive, comparable to the question Hubert Jedin asked himself (<italic>warum so spät</italic>?) in relation to the delay in starting the Council of Trent. Not long afterwards, O’Malley’s question was to become the guiding thread of a seminal book in which he discussed what did happen at Vatican II.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29-1030570X13489647">29</xref></sup> Taking the long view, he situates Vatican II within the history of the Council as an instrument of church government and reform, and brings the reader up to date on the variety of forms these Councils have taken and the modifications that some of their traditional aspects – such as the participation of princes – underwent during the centuries of modernity. He devotes particular attention to exploring the ‘long 19th century’ of the church: the struggle of the papacy against modernity and the ecclesiological consequences that the battle had for the image of the papacy, the appointment of bishops and the spiritual life. In O’Malley’s view Vatican II responded to this by renouncing definitive condemnations and final judgments; an approach that compelled the entire episcopate to begin the proceedings without any defined agenda, meeting as they did in a hall where the shadows of Popes Pius IX and XII, of Marx and Freud, Lagrange and Rosmini, De Maistre and Lamennais were lurking in the background. So the approach of Vatican II became one of seeking and, as O’Malley rightly says, this explains why the majorities and minorities were unstable during the preparatory phase and during the initial part of the Council itself. After 1962, when the first period of Vatican II was over, work began on preparing for the adoption of an epideictic form of rhetoric, which had to gain the consensus of the listener from within.</p>
<p>In his account of the phases of Vatican II, O’Malley suggests a periodization that is not the same as that given in Alberigo’s <italic>History of Vatican II</italic>. Alberigo presents the second period, which took place in the autumn of 1963, as the affirmation of a ‘Council that had reached maturity’; but only a year later during the tempestuous days that led to <italic>De Ecclesia</italic> it experienced a profound rift. O’Malley discovered that those two moments were a unique amalgam of ‘triumphs and tribulations’. Although liturgical and ecclesiological reform remained interdependent, there was still a minority that was anything but placated by the approval of <italic>Sacrosanctum Concilium</italic> and the five guiding votes on ecclesiology in October 1963, which explains why, in the months that followed, taking advantage of the possibilities of filibustering that were allowed by the regulations, it mounted a siege against Paul VI and the Council. According to O’Malley, this tactic of resistance on the part of a small minority was a gamble based on the fact that even though Paul VI was in favour of several changes, it was not his intention to make structural modifications to the centre of government of the Church of Rome itself. Yet for both Roncalli and Montini it was the three undisputed pillars of the Council – updating, development and <italic>ressourcement</italic> – that determined the physiognomy of Vatican II, which manifested itself in the form of a new language of humility and reciprocity in which the concrete experience of the bishops also had a place. Well acquainted as he is with Tridentine dynamics, O’Malley thus ferrets out the commonplaces about the Council and its aftermath that influenced the debate. Without bitterness he shows how the 20th-century Council can be rendered incomprehensible by ignorance of the 16th-century Council: for instance, the so-called protagonism of the theologians (who actually appear to have been much less influential at Vatican II than they were at Trent) or the role of the minority (which far more than at any time during the previous four centuries of Council history was capable of mounting a challenge to some points of the ecclesiological discussion and, I would add, to the doctrine of the poverty of the church and the question of peace).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1030570X13489647"><title>Back to the source</title>
<p>A year after O’Malley, Christoph Theobald, in a weighty tome, showed that the interpretations of Vatican II had been incisively affected by the work of the historians. According to Theobald the great transformations brought about by the globalization of Christianity, which Vatican II wanted to take upon itself, affected its very understanding of revealed truth. Its effort to be seen to perform the act of embracing tradition was determinant on how the Council was conducted and on its after-effects. This was the challenge it had to face.</p>
<p>As Theobald sees it, the question of what came after Vatican II is not a matter of extrinsic periodization, of material geographies, or of locating what happened between significant dates, one of which, 1968, hangs like a nightmare (or a complex) over the heads of those who are unable to say what Vatican II actually was.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30-1030570X13489647">30</xref></sup> The issue should be seen as closely related to the ‘power to shape’ that marks the whole great tradition of the Councils and the intention of John XXIII. Roncalli was not simply a tired pope bringing to an end the long centuries of waiting for Vatican II to happen. Nor was he a lucky gambler at the table of history who by sheer good luck had spotted the right moment at which to play the winning numbers. By virtue of his role as <italic>primus</italic> he posed the questions: what was the theological identity of the Council itself, and what was the meaning of its existence as an institution?</p>
<p>So Vatican II was not a workshop in which to manufacture an ecclesiology left unfinished by Vatican I, but a way for the church to ‘be’ in the light of revealed truth; a question that concerns the very nature of the Council as such and that as early as 1961 had been at the centre of a dispute between the Swiss theologian Hans Küng and the Bavarian cardinal Joseph Ratzinger. Theobald recalls that in order to determine the physiognomy of Vatican II, Küng demanded that the church should state what a council is, whilst Ratzinger stressed that, unlike the church-as-subject, the council is an historical instrument whose nature is intermittent. It was the wise Karl Rahner who cut through this knot. According to Rahner, since it seems evident from history that it is not <italic>necessary</italic> that a council take place, the very fact that a council is convocated acquires a decisive position, facing towards the truth. Each council has its own changing connotations precisely because it occurs at this hermeneutic level: it sets itself the problem of receiving the Word and making it audible for its own day.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31-1030570X13489647">31</xref></sup> So, for Theobald the central theological point of John XXIII’s Vatican II ‘was to bring out this radicalization of the theological identity of the Council as an institution, because now that the Church has become globalized and plural, the identity and truth of Revelation, and how to receive and transmit that identity and truth, are both brought into question’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32-1030570X13489647">32</xref></sup></p>
<p>If this is true then the reception accorded to Vatican II is neither an issue restricted to the post-conciliar period nor is it an experience that only began after Vatican II started, but a <italic>premise</italic>. Vatican II decentralized the theological experience of hearing the Word of God in the liturgical assembly by implicating and involving those who were the direct receptors of that experience, before the textual outcomes of Vatican II were published (and whilst the Council was actually in session). In Theobald’s view, <italic>this</italic> is why we must ask what is the historicity that is immanent in the body of texts, and what is its theological status. The body of texts produced by Vatican II is in fact a <italic>corpus</italic> that is both open and closed: ‘open’ because it presupposes that the churches, and Christians, do have a living future; and ‘closed’ because it marks one particular stage in the long history of Christianity and of the living faith in tradition. So the ‘hermeneutics of reform’ – a formulation that became fashionable after 2005 – does help us to understand the meaning of Vatican II, on condition that we include in that definition a reform of the hermeneutics of tradition.</p>
<p>In Theobald’s view it is not enough to talk about how Vatican II was received, as though this were a process in which its decisions were accepted and assimilated, because the ‘kerygmatic and practical’ level that this connotes does not appear in the Montinian phase (which on the one hand sees the institutional figure of Catholicism transformed, and on the other sees the manifestation of a reflection of synodal life in the local branches of the church), not in the Wojtylian phase (in which relationships with others experience sudden drops and unexpected accelerations), and not in the Ratzinger phase (in which the position of the pontiff has a weight that is not at all ‘conservative’).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33-1030570X13489647">33</xref></sup> It could be said – and this is the most provocative thesis of Theobald, at least so far as the historian is concerned – that the reception of Vatican II is to be understood not by tallying up a profit-and-loss account of its outcomes, but because from a strictly historical point of view, therefore, the Council-in-itself does not exist; it is always situated in an unsurpassable hermeneutic circuit between the historian and the conciliar intrigue that constructs it. This strengthens the argument, several times defended by scholars, that it is impossible to separate the identity of the Council itself from the historical process of its reception.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34-1030570X13489647">34</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1030570X13489647"><title>The Council as a ‘constitutional text’ of faith</title>
<p>In the case of Peter Hünermann, his position was related to the work of historicizing Vatican II, at which he had been a participant. Not only that, Hünermann was the editor of the great Herder commentary and author of a number of important theological writings. For Hünermann it is precisely knowledge of the dynamics of the event that makes essential a ‘global’ interpretation of the <italic>corpus</italic> produced by it. Far from supposing that it possesses a homogeneity (which does not in fact exist), it is constituted as a system of relations. This question of the ‘global’ interpretations of Vatican II had already intrigued the distinguished canonist Giuseppe Dossetti in 1965.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35-1030570X13489647">35</xref></sup> More than 40 years after Dossetti, Hünermann identifies only four interpretations. The most ideological was upheld with schismatic determination by the traditionalists, who thought they saw a ‘modernism’ creeping into the Council’s dictums, that in their view had to be eradicated by an act of the ordinary magisterium – whether interpretive, by replacement, or both – renouncing the statute that Vatican II possessed and that it claimed to possess. The second of Hünermann’s four ‘global’ readings was historiographical. As in Alberigo<italic>’s History</italic>, it saw the Council as an event. Alongside this reading and in relation to the fourth way, expressed by Theobald, is the reading of Vatican II as a ‘constituting’ text of the faith.</p>
<p>As Paolo Pombeni suggested, in a 1996 essay, that there was a possible analogy between that formulation and the relationship between constitution and ordinary legislation,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36-1030570X13489647">36</xref></sup> Hünermann insisted on it. For him, this analogy helps to understand two turning points: the relationship between reforming acts of the churches and their fundamentally important ‘chart’ on the one hand, and the way in which Vatican II is situated within the aspiration to freedom of which constitutionalism is the effect and the characteristic attribute on the other.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37-1030570X13489647">37</xref></sup> This thesis ran up against the immediate resistance of Alberigo himself, who, having known and fought against the prospect of a <italic>Lex Ecclesiæ fundamentalis</italic>, saw in the very assumption of this language a dangerous return to that ghost of the 1970s. In response to Alberigo’s objection, Hünermann showed how it helps to understand the dynamism of liberty that the Council aims to express in the here and now. For his part, Benedict XVI, in his oft-quoted 2005 Christmas discourse to the Roman Curia, also attacked Hünerman’s thesis because he saw in it the outlines of that ‘historic value’ of Vatican II that, according to an old theory of his, could not be affirmed until holy persons, exercising a ‘free and personal commitment’, had created something ‘vital and new’. Hünermann responded by explaining that the ‘constitutional’ character of the text does not limit its authority and does not negate the previous (and even dogmatic) magisterium, but simply puts it in the correct order in relation to those texts that propose to take on that ordering task themselves.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38-1030570X13489647">38</xref></sup></p>
<p>It seems to me that in this case, too, we see how a theological reading is made possible by the historian using the historian’s methods and tools to work on the sources, and also how theological reflection, opened up by global hypotheses of interpretation that are in competition with each other can suggest new and purely historical directions of inquiry.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-1030570X13489647"><title>The church ‘in actu’ and the Council</title>
<p>In a series of interventions that were recently summarized in a book on the Council as Pentecost, Giuseppe Ruggieri offers another perspective on Vatican II that builds on the previous historical work and, in my view, opens up a new area.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39-1030570X13489647">39</xref></sup> Along with Hünermann and Theobald, Ruggieri was one of those who contributed to <italic>The History of Vatican Council II</italic>. However, his book does not retrace that history and does not theoretically address the question of the statute – of tradition, revelation, or text – which is centrally important for both Hünermann and Theobald.</p>
<p>For Ruggieri there is one constituent fact about Vatican II, written into the very fact of its convocation and present in the intention of Pope John XXIII: to hold a Council that is ‘new’ in a very specific sense. As was perfectly obvious, and as has been repeated here more than once, Vatican II had to have a physiognomy. Each event of the Council, as a whole and in every detail, presents specificities that differentiate it from the other Councils. So whatever its future destiny might turn out to be, Vatican II would also have to have its own character. So John XXIII adopted terminologies that were anything but infantile: pastorality; the nexus between the book and the chalice; the signs of the times; unity as a banquet of grace shared by the churches; the dialectic between substance and form; the icon of the new Pentecost. This language had an effect on the process of giving Vatican II its own character and orientated the Council to be an act of re-presentation of the gospel, in the time that makes the church manifest <italic>in actu</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40-1030570X13489647">40</xref></sup> In <italic>this</italic> opening to history that the Council, as an event, experienced, it transcended the language of the modern and the language of ‘dialogue’ and came face to face with the overarching need for the church to receive all revelation and all tradition. Benedict XVI has rightly said that ‘Vatican II embraces the entire doctrinal history of the Church’ because it adopts a living conception of tradition itself that is exposed to the signs of the times, and deciphers those signs within the actual human condition.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41-1030570X13489647">41</xref></sup> The traditions of the other churches, which were represented at Vatican II by their own voices, are fully entitled to enter this living conception of tradition. And with a weight never known before, public opinion in its widest sense also enters, along with the actual life of the communities, whose role certainly cannot be underestimated. Underlying this way of being of the church <italic>in actu</italic> in Vatican II are the individual decisions taken by the Council, which do not constitute a <italic>corpus</italic> that is rendered monolithic because they are given formal approval, but are a complex structure of more or less mature thoughts whose theological weight cannot be determined a priori or temporalized mechanically, but are destined to develop and come to completion over time.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42-1030570X13489647">42</xref></sup></p>
<p>According to Ruggieri, the study of the source documents relating to Vatican II shows that (historically, in the awareness of those who were present and who left in it some trace of themselves) it was an event for listening to the gospel, in the expectation of a communication of the Word itself that would be appropriate for the needs of the time. It is precisely this double polarity that constitutes the Council as a liturgical act that, as in an offertory, brings forth the consensus that sanctions its deliberations.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43-1030570X13489647">43</xref></sup> This perspective has immediate repercussions for historical interpretations of Vatican II because it bars the way to any possibility that there might be a return to political machinery or engineered documents. It is banal and obvious that a Council does possess a political machinery and that its process of engineering documents has to adhere to criteria of compromise and negotiation that need to be analytically reconstructed. But just as the historian does not attempt to explain the meaning of Michelangelo’s <italic>Pietà</italic> by talking about the route taken by the block of marble from a particular point in the quarry to a particular point in Rome, so the historian of Vatican II knows that the existence of this path does not exempt them from their obligation to have another understanding, in which theological intentions inscribed in the real life of people and time have a weight that is not secondary and that must be traced by putting the sources, in the fullness of their substance, back at the centre. So in the end, a perspective of this kind also redounds on how the post-conciliar period is to be interpreted and exists where the need to represent the gospel is received; not where some issue or other, or an abstract hermeneutics, is debated with or without vigour.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44-1030570X13489647">44</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-1030570X13489647" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Earlier I mentioned the dense historical work that, in the form of inventories, essays and monographs, is continuing with great intensity, re-editing the major documents of Vatican II and investigating the major issues underlying the debates,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45-1030570X13489647">45</xref></sup> the participation of the protagonists who were part of the organs, of the assembly, or of the vast world surrounding the hall.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46-1030570X13489647">46</xref></sup> The ‘preparatory’ weight of the great Catholic renewal movements and of extremely small intellectual ferments in even tiny places such as Dombes or Seelisberg are not to be overlooked.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47-1030570X13489647">47</xref></sup> Nor are the meaning of diaries,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48-1030570X13489647">48</xref></sup> the impact of communication via periodicals or newspapers, and the political action to which the diplomatic source documents contain pointers.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49-1030570X13489647">49</xref></sup> In sum, there is now a new generation of historians and new publications that are taking their place in the bibliographies, to which some conferences in 2012 have already begun to give a voice that will continue to be heard, at least up until the celebration of the fiftieth anniversary of the conclusion of the Council in 2015 under a new pope. These studies enjoy a solid position and even if, whether out of weakness or goodness, the magisterium were to bend to the blackmail of those who demand an ‘authentic’ interpretation of the Council, the historical case that Paul VI decided to incorporate into Vatican II can no longer be amputated from it. Thanks to these studies and the access to the sources they have enjoyed, we are better able to see that the problems underlying the interpretation of Vatican II are the same as, or at least similar to, those that the Council itself experienced while it was in session.</p>
<p>In its great conciliar debates – on ecclesiology, ecumenism, religious freedom, revelation, Judaism, and the other religions – the assembly had in fact experienced dramatic hesitations. Listening to the discussions in St Peter’s, there was a danger of thinking that the opposing positions were essentially balanced, almost as though the bishops who endorsed Pope Roncalli’s update plan were balanced by a comparable number of other bishops who associated themselves with the culture of intransigence. It was precisely to reject this illusion that Paul VI in 1963 adopted new regulations and decided to install moderators with delegated authority who could bring the Council out of an impasse that was theologically intolerable. One might sometimes get the impression, historiographically speaking, that something like this was bound to transpire, and it almost does appear that the historical-critical work and the disparaging expressions of sententiousness had been given equal weight. Again, however, it is clear that no tyranny can place ideological limits, or worse, on the fallible but honest craft of historians. And no legitimation can equate the judgement on the significance of Vatican II for the life of faith with the doubts of those who feel they have a duty to minimize its significance and even its existence. This is not merely an historiographical matter, and one does have to ask whether, in the reception given to Vatican II, there really did exist dynamics that were not the same as those that moved the Council itself and that brought agitation to its deliberations. In other words, whether the question of the reception of Vatican II is inseparable from that of the Council itself, or whether there were hermeneutics of the Council that had not already revealed themselves. In this mutual overlapping between the Council and its reception, the cultural dislocation in which Christianity is immersed, and the succession of one generation after another, become decisive.</p>
<p>To sum up, it is evident that whatever new may have been said (and was actually voiced) at Vatican II can be now be identified, thanks in no small measure to the work of historians. Traces of that work can even be found in the efforts of those who think they need to elaborate a history ‘that has never been written’, seen from the point of view of the opponents of the Council. By patient work the sources themselves are once again placed at the centre. By finding the papers and comparing them, and interpreting them whilst refining as much as possible the doctrinal sensitivities needed to grasp their implications, we broaden the diachronic and synchronic horizons in which the Council does not <italic>have to be</italic> situated, but actually <italic>is</italic> situated.</p>
<p>This is no different from any other ordinary work of the historian who, as a visitor to a different ‘present’ set in another time, is always limited by only being able to rely on the documentary sources and who is also aware that, after the inrush of that gospel whose urgency is felt by whoever lives it, without ever neglecting its weight and without ever being able to know where it originated, one can only measure the footprints that remain. This backward gaze cannot fail to note that ‘betraying the Council’ (a betrayal either perpetrated by the Council or, vice-versa, perpetrated by the ‘restorers’ to which the Council must succumb) is a leitmotif that comes back into fashion every 10 years. Nor can it fail to note that, despite all the prophecies of doom, Vatican II remains and still returns as a tool for a colloquium with the future, similar to the colloquium with the future that was generated by all the great Councils, and that is destined to endure until a new Council comes about. Vatican II remains and returns because it was intended to position itself in a specific location, not in front of the whole tradition as though contemplating a library, or in the heart-wrenching ruins of some lost pre-Romantic Christianity, but in the manner desired by Pope John: moving towards ‘the encounter with the face of Christ’, having retraced the whole tradition until it arrives at an appointed meeting place that marks the necessary beginning of a new pilgrimage.</p>
<p>It is another question as to whether Vatican II has so far succeeded in this task. But the necessarily nuanced judgement on its outcomes does not alter one <italic>fact</italic>: that this task, which by a primatial act was defined as ‘pastoral’ in a very substantial sense, has the same value that the formulation <italic>Spiritu Sancto legitime congregata, ecclesiam universalem repræsentans</italic> implied in the 15th century. Faced with this <italic>fact</italic>, it is more than obvious that the Council does not belong to the everyday ordinariness of the church, and that when a Council takes place, its significance cannot be diminished by the liturgical impermanence that is a necessary part of its constitution.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50-1030570X13489647">50</xref></sup></p>
<p>Exactly like the act of worship, when a Council ‘takes place’ it measures itself <italic>ipso facto</italic> against a history. In the awareness of the 17th-century controversialist this meant that a serial progression had to be constructed so that the Council as an event could be strengthened by setting it within a chain of events that legitimated it.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51-1030570X13489647">51</xref></sup> But for the historian of today it is sufficient to know that Vatican II, like every other great Council, was not exempt from the challenge that led it to confront a problem that the proliferation of metaphors (the beginning of a beginning, the turning point, the end of an age, the epochal transition) can scarcely circumscribe. The work of the researcher does have need of simple knowledge in order to advance, but, <italic>numquid Deus indiget vestro mendacio?</italic>, the magisterium of the theologian and of authority also needs exactly the same knowledge.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52-1030570X13489647">52</xref></sup></p>
<p>Vatican II, therefore, must be included as part of this listening to what the Spirit says to the church, and what time whispers to the church about the gospel. So inevitably, the Council consists of what is gradually received of <italic>those things</italic>, in a dynamism from which not even those who ask for it to be rejected or downgraded can absent themselves; a dynamism that by now has become overlaid on the decades that separate us from Vatican II and its history, and is now already implicit in the decades that separate the Christians from a future in which conciliarity will return, and will once again propose itself as a contemporary of its own time, of the <italic>traditio</italic> and of the future, as a summons to create the correct conditions in which the kerygmatic event can take place in all its dimensions, and with all its consequences.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1-1030570X13489647"><label>1</label><p>A. Melloni, ‘Prodromi e preparazione del discorso d’annuncio del Vaticano II (‘Questa Festiva Ricorrenza’, 25 gennaio 1959)’, <italic>Rivista di Storia e Letteratura Religiosa</italic> 28 (1992), 607–643.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn2-1030570X13489647"><label>2</label><p>H. J. Sieben, <italic>Katholische Konzilsidee im 19. und 20. Jahrhundert</italic>, (Paderborn: F. Schöningh, 1993).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn3-1030570X13489647"><label>3</label><p>G. Caprile, ‘Pio XI e la ripresa del concilio Vaticano’, <italic>Civiltà Cattolica</italic> 117 (1966), 27–39 and ‘Pio XI, la Curia romana e il concilio’, <italic>Civiltà Cattolica</italic> 120 (1969), 121–133, 563–575.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn4-1030570X13489647"><label>4</label><p>G. Butturini, ‘Per un concilio di riforma: una proposta inedita (1939) di C.Costantini’, <italic>Cristianesimo nella Storia</italic> 7 (1986), 87–139.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn5-1030570X13489647"><label>5</label><p>G. Caprile, ‘Pius XII. und das zweite Vatikanische Konzil’, in H. Schambeck (ed.), <italic>Pius XII. zum Gedachtnis</italic> (Berlin: Duncker and Humblot, 1977), 649–691. The subject is also mentioned in the reports on the Council by Civiltà Cattolica, gathered by G. Caprile in <italic>Il Concilio Vaticano II</italic> (4 vols; Roma: 1966–68).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn6-1030570X13489647"><label>6</label><p>For the most recent research, see A. Mainardi (ed.),<italic> Il Concilio di Mosca del 1917–1918</italic> (Bose: Qiqajon, 2004).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn7-1030570X13489647"><label>7</label><p>For an example of the ways in which rumours of a possible Council circulated at this time, see the conversation between Cardinal Frings and his secretary, which took place on the return voyage from the conclave, in J. Kard. Frings,<italic> Für die Menschen bestellt: Erinnerungen des Alterzbischofs von Köln</italic> (Köln: J. P. Bachem, 1973), 247. For other references see Melloni, ‘Questa festiva ricorrenza’.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn8-1030570X13489647"><label>8</label><p>See A. Melloni, ‘Vaticano I, Vaticano II. L’edizione dei concili in età contemporanea’,<italic> Annali dell’Istituto storico italo-germanico in Trent /Jahrbuch des italienisch-deutschen Instituts in Trient</italic> 29 (2003), 495–510; V. Carbone, ‘Genesi e criteri della pubblicazione degli Atti del Concilio Vaticano II’, <italic>Lateranum</italic>, 44 (1978), 579–595, ‘L’Archivio del Concilio Vaticano II’, <italic>Archiva Ecclesiæ</italic> 34/35 (1991/92), 57–67; cf. G. Lefebvre, ‘Les Actes du Concile du Vatican’, <italic>Revue Théologique de Louvain</italic>, 11 (1980), 186–200, 325–351.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn9-1030570X13489647"><label>9</label><p>M. Böhnke, ‘Wider die falschen Alternativen: Zur Hermeneutik des Zweitens Vatikanischen Konzils’, <italic>Catholica</italic> 65 (2011), 169–183; M. Faggioli, <italic>Vatican II. The Battle for Meaning</italic> (New York: Paulist, 2012), 125–133. Cf. a semi-lefebvrian point of view in B. Gherardini, <italic>Quod et tradidi vobis: La Tradizione, vita e giovinezza della Chiesa</italic> (Frigento: Casa Mariana, 2010), and a warning against oversimiplification in É. Fouilloux, ‘Histoire et événement: Vatican II’, <italic>Cristianesimo nella Storia</italic> 13 (1992), 515–538, and J. Komonchak, ‘Interpreting the Council: Catholic Attitudes toward Vatican II’, in M. J. Weaver and R. Scott Appleby (eds),<italic> Being Right: Conservative Catholics in America</italic> (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1995), 17–36.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn10-1030570X13489647"><label>10</label><p>I will refrain from constantly referring to the <italic>Storia del concilio Vaticano II</italic> (5 vols.; Bologna: Mulino, 1995–2001), mandatory reading for an exhaustive reconstruction of the Council and its historiography. In this preliminary overview I will provide only the more essential or recent bibliographic references.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn11-1030570X13489647"><label>11</label><p>S. Schloesser, ‘Against Forgetting: Memory, History, Vatican II’, <italic>Theological Studies</italic> 67 (2006), 275–319; Komonchak, ‘Interpreting the Council’.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn12-1030570X13489647"><label>12</label><p>A. Melloni, ‘Les journaux privés dans l’histoire de Vatican II’, in M.-D. Chenu (ed.), <italic>Notes quotidiennes au Concile</italic> (Paris: Cerf, 1995), 7–54. The principal edition is Y. Congar, <italic>Mon journal du Concile</italic> (Paris: Cerf 2002). Collections of letters written by Lercaro and Camara during the Council have also been published, see G. Lercaro, <italic>Lettere dal concilio 1962–1965</italic> (Bologna: Dehoniane, 1984), and Helder Camara, <italic>Vaticano II: Correspondência conciliar. Circulares á família do São Joaquim</italic>, ed. Luiz Carlos Marques (Recife: Editora Universitaria UFPE, 2004). Other diaries have also been published, see n. 48 below. On the sources see C. Soetens, J. Famerés, L. Hulsbosch and E. Louchez (eds),<italic> Concile Vatican II et église contemporaine - Archives de Louvain-la-Neuve</italic> (4 vols; Louvain-la-Neuve,: Peeters, 1989–95); A.-M. Abel and J.P. Ribaud (eds.), <italic>Documents pour une histoire du Concile Vatican II. Inventaire du Fonds J. Le Cordier</italic> (Paris: Institut Catholique, 1993); L. Lazzaretti (ed.), <italic>La documentazione bolognese per la storia del concilio Vaticano II. Inventario dei fondi G. Lercaro e G. Dossetti</italic> (Bologna, 1995); P. Lafontaine, <italic>Inventaire des Archives conciliaire et du Fonds Paul-Émile Léger</italic> (Montréal: Ed. des Parternaires, 1995); R. Desreumaux and A.-M. Abel, <italic>Inventaires du Fonds Henri Dupon et Adrien Grand</italic> (Paris: Institut Catholique, 2001); L. Declerck and W. Verschooten (eds),<italic> Inventaires des papiers conciliaires de mgr Gérard Philips, sécretaire ad. de la Commission docitrinale</italic> (Leuven: Peeters, 2001); F. Álvarez Alonso, ‘Claretiani al Concilio. Arcadio M. Larraona, Arturo Tabera e Anastasio Gutiérrez. Inventario dei fondi documentari sul Concilio Vaticano II’, <italic>Centro Vaticano II. Ricerche e documenti</italic> 2 (2002), 85–186; Peter Pfister-Guido Treffler (ed.), <italic>Schriften des Archivs des Erzbistums München und Freising, Bd. 6: Erzbischöfliches Archiv München – Julius Kardinal Döpfner. Archivinventar der Dokumente zum Zweiten Vatikanischen Konzil</italic> (München–Freising: Schnell and Steiner, 2004).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn13-1030570X13489647"><label>13</label><p>M. Faggioli, ‘Concilio Vaticano II: bollettino bibliografico’,<italic> Cristianesimo nella Storia</italic> 24 (2003), 335–360, on the years 2000–02; 26 (2005), 743–767, on the years 2002–05; 29 (2008), 567–610, on the years 2005–07; 31 (2010), 755–791, on the years 2007–10. Cf. the broader synthesis in M. Faggioli, <italic>Vatican II: Battle for the Meaning</italic> (Maryknoll: Orbis, 2012).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn14-1030570X13489647"><label>14</label><p>His reviews are gathered in A. Marchetto, <italic>Il Concilio Ecumenico Vaticano II. Contrappunto per la sua storia</italic> (Città del Vaticano: Editrice Vaticana, 2005).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn15-1030570X13489647"><label>15</label><p>E. Corecco, ‘Aspetti della ricezione del Vaticano II nel Codice di Diritto Canonico’, in G. Alberigo and J.-P. Jossua (eds), <italic>Il Vaticano II e la chiesa</italic> (Brescia: Paideia, 1985), 333–397; L. Orsy, <italic>Receiving the Council. Theological and Canonical Insights and Debates</italic> (Collegeville MN: Liturgical, 2009).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn16-1030570X13489647"><label>16</label><p>W. Kasper, <italic>Theologie und Kirche</italic> (Mainz: Matthias-Grünewald, 1987).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn17-1030570X13489647"><label>17</label><p>O. Rush, <italic>Still Interpreting Vatican II: Some Hermeneutical Principles</italic> (New York: Paulist, 2004); M. Bredeck, <italic>Das Zweite Vatikanum als Konzil des Aggiornamento</italic> (Paderborn: F. Schöningh, 2007); G. Routhier and G. Jobin (eds),<italic> L’Autorité et les Autorités. L’hermenéutique théologique de Vatican II</italic> (Paris: Cerf, 2010).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn18-1030570X13489647"><label>18</label><p>E. Galavotti, <italic>La Causa di Canonizzazione di A. G. Roncalli (1965–2000)</italic> (Bologna: Mulino 2005).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn19-1030570X13489647"><label>19</label><p>F. G. Brambilla, ‘Il Card. Montini e l’inizio del Concilio Vaticano II. Una Ricostruzione Storico-teologica. I-II’, <italic>La rivista del clero italiano</italic> 83 (2002), 504–519, 600–614, and ‘Carlo Colombo e G. B. Montini alle Sorgenti del Concilio’, <italic>La Scuola Cattolica</italic> 130 (2002), 221–260.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn20-1030570X13489647"><label>20</label><p>J. Lamberts, ‘L’évolution de la Notion de “Participation Active” dans le Mouvement Liturgique du XXe Siècle’, <italic>La Maison-Dieu</italic> 241 (2005), 77–120.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn21-1030570X13489647"><label>21</label><p>For the particular situation of the Church in Latin America, S. Scatena, <italic>In Populo Pauperum. La Chiesa Latinoamericana dal Concilio a Medellín (1962–1968)</italic> (Bologna: Mulino, 2008).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn22-1030570X13489647"><label>22</label><p>J. A. Komonchak, ‘Augustine, Aquinas or the Gospel sine glossa: Divisions over Gaudium et Spes’, in Austen Ivereigh (ed.), <italic>Unfinished Journey: The Church 40 Years after Vatican II. Essays for John Wilkins</italic> (New York: Continuum, 2003), 102–118.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn23-1030570X13489647"><label>23</label><p>G. Ruggieri, ‘Ricezioni e Interpretazioni del Vaticano II: Le ragioni di un Dibattito’, in A. Melloni and G. Ruggieri (eds), <italic>Chi ha Paura del Vaticano II?</italic> (Roma: Carocci, 2009), 17–44.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn24-1030570X13489647"><label>24</label><p>A. Melloni, ‘Breve Guida ai Giudizi sul Vaticano II’, in Melloni and Ruggieri, <italic>Chi ha Paura?</italic>, 107–145, and J. A. Komonchak, ‘Benedict XVI and the Interpretation of Vatican II’, <italic>Cristianesimo nella Storia</italic> 28 (2007), 323–337. Cf. N. Ormerod, ‘Vatican II: Continuity or Discontinuity? Toward an Ontology of Meaning’, <italic>Theological Studies</italic> 71 (2010), 609–636.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn25-1030570X13489647"><label>25</label><p>G. Routhier (ed.),<italic> Réceptions de Vatican II: Le Concile au Risque de l’Histoire et des Espaces Humains</italic> (Leuven: Peeters 2004), and <sc>G.</sc> Routhier, ‘Le Réseau Dominicain: Vecteur de la Réception de Vatican II au Canada’, <italic>Science et Esprit</italic> 63 (2011), 385–408.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn26-1030570X13489647"><label>26</label><p>G. Routhier, <italic>Vatican II: Herméneutique et Reception</italic> (Montréal: Fides, 2006).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn27-1030570X13489647"><label>27</label><p>J. W. O’Malley, <italic>Tradition and Transition: Historical Perspectives on Vatican II</italic> (Wilmington, DE: Michael Glazier, 1989).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn28-1030570X13489647"><label>28</label><p>J. W. O’Malley, ‘Vatican II: Did Anything Happen?’, <italic>Theological Studies</italic> 67 (2006), 3–33, and D. G. Schultenover (ed.), <italic>Vatican II: Did Anything Happen?</italic> (New York: Continuum, 2007).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn29-1030570X13489647"><label>29</label><p>J. W. O’Malley, <italic>What Happened at Vatican II?</italic> (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2008).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn30-1030570X13489647"><label>30</label><p>C. Theobald, <italic>La Réception du Concile Vatican II, I: Accéder à la Source</italic> (Paris: Cerf, 2009), 514–515, 666–667. On Revelation at Vatican II see C. Theobald, <italic>‘Dans les traces …’ de la constitution ‘Dei Verbum’ du concile Vatican II: Bible, Théologie et Pratiques de Lecture</italic> (Paris: Cerf, 2009).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn31-1030570X13489647"><label>31</label><p>K. Rahner, ‘Zur Theologie des Konzils’, <italic>Stimmen der Zeit</italic> 169 (1962), 321–339.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn32-1030570X13489647"><label>32</label><p>Theobald, <italic>La Réception</italic>, 265.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn33-1030570X13489647"><label>33</label><p>Theobald, <italic>La Réception,</italic> 512 in dialectic with with P. Hünermann, ‘Der “Text”: Eine Ergänzung zur Hermeneutik des II. Vatikanischen Konzils’, <italic>Cristianesimo nello Storia</italic> 28 (2007), 339–358.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn34-1030570X13489647"><label>34</label><p>Theobald, <italic>La Réception</italic>, 532.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn35-1030570X13489647"><label>35</label><p>G. Dossetti, <italic>Il Vaticano II: Frammenti di una Riflessione</italic> (Bologna: Mulino 1996).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn36-1030570X13489647"><label>36</label><p>P. Pombeni, ‘La Dialettica tra Evento e Decisioni nella Ricostruzione delle Grandi Assemblee: I Parlamentari e le Assemblee Costituenti, in Maria Teresa Fattori, A. Melloni (eds.), <italic>L’Evento e le Decisioni: Studi sulle Dinamiche del Concilio Vaticano II</italic> (Bologna: Mulino, 1997), 17–49.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn37-1030570X13489647"><label>37</label><p>Hünermann, ‘Der Text’<italic>.</italic></p></fn>
<fn id="fn38-1030570X13489647"><label>38</label><p>P. Hünermann, ‘Quo Vadis? Au Sujet de l’importance du Concile Vatican II pour l’Église, l’œcuménisme et la Société aujourd’hui’, <italic>Recherches de science religieuse</italic> 100 (2012), 27–44.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn39-1030570X13489647"><label>39</label><p>G. Ruggieri, <italic>Ritrovare il Concilio</italic> (Turin: Einadi, 2012).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn40-1030570X13489647"><label>40</label><p>G. Ruggieri, ‘L’Esdeveniment Conciliar com Ecclesia in actu’, in <italic>La relació entre Església i món d’avui a la llum del Concili Vaticà II</italic> (Barcelona: Facultat de Teologia de Catalunya, 2011), 15–41.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn41-1030570X13489647"><label>41</label><p>Benedict XVI, Letter to the Bishops, 3 March 2009, para. 4. Online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/benedict_xvi/letters/2009/documents/hf_ben-xvi_let_20090310_remissione-scomunica_en.html">http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/benedict_xvi/letters/2009/documents/hf_ben-xvi_let_20090310_remissione-scomunica_en.html</ext-link>.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn42-1030570X13489647"><label>42</label><p>G. Ruggieri, <italic>Das II. Vatikanum: Ereignis von Weltkirche</italic>, in P. Hünermann (ed.), <italic>Das II. Vatikanum: Christlicher Glaube im Horizont globaler Modernisierung</italic> (Paderborn: Schöningh, 1998), 31–44.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn43-1030570X13489647"><label>43</label><p>G. Ruggieri, ‘L’Officina Bolognese et Vatican II’, <italic>Recherches de Science Religieuse</italic> 100 (2012), 11–25, here p. 22.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn44-1030570X13489647"><label>44</label><p>Ch. Theobald, ‘L’Hermeneutique de Réforme Implique-t-elle une Réforme de l’Hermeneutique?’, <italic>Recherches de Science Religieuse</italic> 100 (2012), 65–84.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn45-1030570X13489647"><label>45</label><p>For example, M. Faggioli, <italic>Il Vescovo e il Concilio: Modello Episcopale e Aggiornamento al Vaticano II</italic> (Bologna: Mulino, 2005); S. Scatena, <italic>La fatica della Libertà</italic> (Bologna: Il Mulino, 2008; N. Lamdan and A. Melloni (eds), <italic>Nostra Aetate: Origins, Promulgation, Impact on Jewish-Catholic Relations</italic> (Münster: LIT 2007); M. Attridge (ed.), <italic>Jews and Catholic Together: Celebrating the Legacy of Nostra Aetate</italic> (Ottawa: Novalis, 2007); G. Routhier and G. Jobin (eds),<italic> L’Autorité et les Autorités: L’Hermeneutique Théologique de Vatican II</italic> (Paris: Cerf, 2007); K. Schelkens, <italic>Catholic Theology of Revelation on the Eve of Vatican II: A Redaction History of the Schema ‘De Fontibus Revelationis’ (1960–1962)</italic> (Leiden: Brill, 2010); C. Antonelli, <italic>Il Dibattito su Maria nel Concilio Vaticano II: Percorso Redazionale sulla Base di Nuovi Documenti d’Archivio</italic> (Padova: Messaggero di Sant’ Antonio, 2009); C. Lorefice, <italic>Dossetti e Lercaro: La Chiesa Povera e dei Poveri nella Prospettiva del Concilio Vaticano II</italic> (Cinisello B: Paoline, 2011).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn46-1030570X13489647"><label>46</label><p>For example, D. Donnelly, J. Famerée, M. Lamberigts, et al. (eds), <italic>The Belgian Contribution to the Second Vatican Council</italic> (Leuven: Peeters, 2008); T. Eggensperger and U. Engel (eds), <italic>‘Mutig in die Zukunft’: Dominikanische Beiträge zum Vatikanum II</italic> (Leipzig: Benno, 2007); B. Xibaut, <italic>Mgr. Léon-Arthur Elchinger. Un Evêque Français au Concile</italic> (Paris: Cerf, 2009); M. Perroni, A. Melloni and S. Noceti (eds), <italic>Tantum Aurora Est: Le Donne al Vaticano II</italic> (Berlin: LIT, 2012).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn47-1030570X13489647"><label>47</label><p>For example, G. Routhier, P. J. Roy and K. Schelkens (eds), <italic>La Théologie Catholique entre Intransigeance et Renouveau: La Réception des Mouvements Préconciliaire à Vatican II</italic> (Leuven: Peeters, 2011); F. Bousquet, P. Gibert, É. Fouilloux, M. Fédou and B. Cholvy, ‘Les théologiens français et la preparation de Vatican II’, <italic>Gregorianum</italic> 92 (2011), 737–827; S. Scatena, <italic>Taizé: Le Origini della Comunità e l’Attesa del Concilio</italic> (Berlin: LIT, 2011).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn48-1030570X13489647"><label>48</label><p>Beside the Congar diary (whose annex remains unpublished!) see: H. Câmara, <italic>Vaticano II: Correspondência Conciliar. Circulares á Família do São Joaquim</italic>, ed. L. C. Marques (Recife: Universitária da UFPE, 2004) and <italic>Circulares Conciliares</italic>, ed. L. C. Marques and R. Faria (Recife: Universitária da UFPE, 2008); L. Declerck (ed.),<italic> Carnets conciliaires de Mgr Gérard Philips: Secrétaire adjoint de la Commission Doctrinale</italic> (Leuven: Peeters, 2006), and <italic>Carnets conciliaires de l’êvéque de Namur A.-M. Charue</italic> (Leuven: Peeters, 2001); N. Edelby, <italic>Il Vaticano II nel Diario di un Vescovo Arabo</italic>, ed. R. Cannelli (Cinisello B: Paoline, 1996); U. Betti, <italic>Diario del Concilio: 11 Ottobre 1962–Natale 1978</italic>, ed. V. Occhipinti (Bologna: Mulino, 2003); P. Poswick, <italic>Un Journal du Concile Vatican II par un Diplomate Belge: Notes Personnelles de l’Ambassadeur de Belgique près la Saint-Siège (1957–1968)</italic>, ed. R. F. Poswick and Y. Juste (Paris: Cerf, 2005)<italic>;</italic> J. Döpfner, <italic>Tagebücher, Briefe und Notizen zum Zweiten Vatikanischen Konzil</italic>, ed. Guido Treffler (Regensburg: Schnell-Steiner, 2006); H. de Lubac, <italic>Carnets du Concile</italic>, ed. L. Figoureux (Paris: Cerf 2007); T. Salemink (ed.),<italic>‘You will be Called Repairer of the Breach’: The Diary of J. G. M. Willebrands, 1958–1961</italic> (Leuven: Peeters, 2009), and <italic>Les Agendas Conciliaires de Mgr J. Willebrands, Secrétaire du Sécretariat pour l’Unité des Chrétiens</italic>, trans. and annotated by L. Declerck (Leuven: Peeters, 2009); S. Siliberti (ed.), <italic>Mons. Carlo Ferrari ‘Padre del Concilio’: Diario (1962–1965)</italic> (Mantova: Arti Grafiche Grassi, 2010); K. Schelkens (ed.),<italic> The Council of Edward Schillebeeckx</italic> (Leuven: Peeters, 2011), and<italic> The Second Vatican Council Diaries of Met. Maxim Hermaniuk, C.Ss.R. (1960–1965)</italic>, trans. Jaroslav Z. Skira (Leuven: Peeters, 2012); O. Semmelroth, <italic>Das Konzilstagebuch</italic>, ed. G. Wassilowsky (forthcoming); P. Giorgi (ed.), <italic>Il Diario Conciliare di Ermenegildo Florit. L’Esperienza di un Vescovo Italiano al Vaticano II</italic>. Online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.amiciziacristiana.it/diario.pdf">http://www.amiciziacristiana.it/diario.pdf</ext-link>; N. Egender<italic>,</italic> ‘Cinquante Ans de Vatican II’, <italic>Irénikon</italic> 83 (2010), 41–91; K. Loussouarn, ‘État des Sources sur le Concile Vatican II dans les Fonds Conservés au Centre National des Archives de l’Église de France (CNAEF)’, <italic>Chrétiens et Sociétés, XVI<sup>e</sup>–XXI<sup>e</sup> siècles: Bulletin de l’Équipe RESEA</italic>, no. 17 (2010), 195–214.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn49-1030570X13489647"><label>49</label><p>F. Ruozzi, <italic>Il Concilio in Diretta: Il Vaticano II in TV</italic> (Bologna: Mulino, 2012); P.-W. Scheele, <italic>Als Journalist beim Konzil: Erfahrungen und Erkenntisse in der 3. Session. [Mit einem Beitrag von Karl Hillenbrand: Das Konzil und seine Folge]</italic> (Würzburg: Echter Verlag, 2010); ‘Kirche und Leben’ is studied by M. Hartmann, <italic>Bistumpresse während des Zweitens Vatikanischen Konzils</italic>, ed. Thomas von Flammer, and Hubert Wolf (Münster: Dialogverlag, 2009); for the subsidia addressed to the preachers N. Weigl<italic>, Liturgische Predigt seit dem Zweiten Vatikanischen Konzil: Eine Untersuchung zur Messfeier in der Sonntagspredigt anhand der Zeitschrift ‘Der Prediger und Katechet’</italic> (Regensburg: Pustet, 2009).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn50-1030570X13489647"><label>50</label><p>K. Lehmann, ‘Hermeneutik für einen künftigen Umgang mit dem Konzil’, in<italic> Zweites Vatikanum – vergessene Anstöße, gegenwärtige Fortschreibungen</italic> (Freibugr i.Br.: Herder, 71–89, and ‘Das II. Vatikanum – ein Wegweiser: Verständnis – Rezeption – Bedeutung’, in P. Hünermann (ed.), <italic>Das Zweite Vatikanische Konzil und die Zeichen der Zeit Heute</italic> (Freiburg: Herder, 2006), 11–26.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn51-1030570X13489647"><label>51</label><p>A. Melloni, ‘Concili, Ecumenicità e Storia: Note di Discussione’, <italic>Cristianesimo nella Storia</italic> 28 (2007), 509–542.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn52-1030570X13489647"><label>52</label><p>Job 13 : 77 was quoted by Leo XIII in <italic>Depuis le Jour</italic>, 8 September 1899. See C. Semeraro (ed.),<italic> Leone XIII e gli Studi Storici: Atti del Convegno Internazionale Commemorativo (Città del Vaticano, 30–31 Ottobre 2003)</italic> (Città del Vaticano: Editrice Vaticana, 2004).</p></fn></fn-group>
<bio><title>Author biography</title>
<p><bold>Alberto Melloni</bold> is Director of the John XXIII Foundation for Religious Studies in Bologna, Italy, and Professor of the History of Christianity at the University of Modena and Reggio Emilia. He is the author of numerous books on the history of Vatican II.</p></bio>
</back>
</article>