<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GCT</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spgct</journal-id>
<journal-title>Gifted Child Today</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1076-2175</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1076217511427432</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1076217511427432</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Features</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Teachers as Advocates</article-title>
<subtitle>If Not You—Who?</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>Julia Link</given-names></name>
<degrees>EdD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1076217511427432">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Siegle</surname><given-names>Del</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1076217511427432">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1076217511427432"><label>1</label>Western Kentucky University</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1076217511427432"><label>2</label>University of Connecticut</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1076217511427432">Julia Link Roberts, Western Kentucky University Center for Gifted Studies, 1906 College Heights Blvd., Bowling Green, KY 42101-1301; email: <email>julia.roberts@wku.edu</email>.</corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-1076217511427432">
<p>Julia Link Roberts, EdD, is the Mahurin Professor of Gifted Studies at Western Kentucky University. She is Executive Director of The Center for Gifted Studies and the Carol Martin Gatton Academy of Mathematics and Science in Kentucky. She co-chairs the National Association for Gifted Children Legislative and Advocacy Committee, and is president-elect of The Association for the Gifted (TAG/CEC).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio2-1076217511427432">
<p>Del Siegle, PhD, is a professor of gifted education and head of the Educational Psychology Department in the Neag School of Education at the University of Connecticut. He is a past president of the National Association for Gifted Children and currently serves as co-chair of the NAGC Legislative and Advocacy Committee.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>35</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>58</fpage>
<lpage>61</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Teachers, including teachers of children and young people who are gifted and talented, care about educational issues; and, consequently, they need to advocate for issues impacting their students. Strategies for advocating are described—strategies for advocating with colleagues at the school level, in the community for district-wide issues, and at the state and national levels for policy and legislative issues.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>advocacy</kwd>
<kwd>gifted education</kwd>
<kwd>leadership</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1076217511427432-img1.tif"/>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Never doubt that a small group of thoughtful committed citizens can <italic>change the world</italic>. Indeed it’s the only thing that ever has.</p>
<attrib>—Margaret Mead</attrib></disp-quote></p>
<p>An emerging trend in education is the important role that teachers can and should play in advocacy. For many years, teachers have been an underutilized voice on how to improve schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1076217511427432">Flom, 2010</xref>). As the federal and state governments move to improve the strengths of various education programs and address the weaknesses of others, educators should become part of the process. Such reform movements are too important for educators, with their years of firsthand experience, to sit on the sideline. It is equally too important for educators who understand the educational needs of gifted students to stand by and watch these students’ educational needs go unmet. When individuals care about issues, they act. Educators who care about children need to be active in the decisions that will shape children’s lives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1076217511427432">Horton, 2010</xref>). This action translates into becoming advocates. Too often the population of gifted children has been overlooked in education reform movements. The No Child Left Behind mandate set minimal proficiency standards below those already met by most gifted children. The outcome was a decade of educational neglect as gifted and talented students often sat ignored in their classrooms, waiting to be taught by teachers who were preoccupied with the mandate to bring low-achieving students to proficiency, an admirable goal unless the children are beyond that point in their learning. The outcome has been stagnated growth for many gifted and talented students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1076217511427432">Duffett, Farkas, &amp; Loveless, 2008</xref>). Schools can do better for their top-achieving students, and educators must join forces to advocate for excellence for all. After all, every child deserves to learn new concepts and skills each day, including the child who is gifted and talented.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>“Schools can do better for their top-achieving students, and educators must join forces to advocate for excellence for all.”</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Teachers and parents can advocate for services for gifted students along a broad continuum of support that begins with advocacy at home and ends with advocacy on a national level. This includes</p>
<list id="list1-1076217511427432" list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>advocating with grade-level teachers to differentiate instruction to meet the wide range of student needs,</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>advocating with all educators and parents for specific services and best practices for gifted students at the school level,</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>advocating within the community for greater school district-wide services for gifted children,</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>advocating for state support in legislation and policy with funding for gifted education, and</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>advocating for national attention on gifted education (both legislatively and with the general public).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<sec id="section1-1076217511427432">
<title>Three Ps of Advocacy</title>
<p>Success as an advocate in each of the above venues depends on three Ps: <italic>purpose, preparation</italic>, and <italic>persistence</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1076217511427432">Burney &amp; Sheldon, 2010</xref>). Advocates must have a clear understanding of what they want or their purpose for advocating. Simply complaining about the status quo does little to move causes forward. Advocates need clear goals and a clear understanding of what is possible.</p>
<p>Advocates must also be well informed. This preparation is essential because policy makers will want data that support advocates’ requests. For example, policy makers will want to see data showing that gifted students’ educational needs are not being met (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1076217511427432">Burney &amp; Sheldon, 2010</xref>). A big part of advocacy is developing relationships. Preparation also involves incubating and nurturing these relationships. It is through these relationships that support and, ultimately, change occur. Building relationships takes time. Local, state, and national officials need to be aware of educators,’ as well as parents,’ concern for gifted children, and they need to trust that they can turn to them for accurate information about the educational needs of gifted children. Advocates need to be sure that decision makers know their names and, better still, recognize their faces. Waiting until a crisis occurs is often too late to find support.</p>
<p>Preparation also can include setting the climate for change. For example, a long-term plan that includes placing letters to the editor in key newspapers and having stories appear on local television news and in newspapers about the needs of gifted children or the positive impact of existing programs helps develop a positive climate about gifted education that facilitates contact with key policy makers and creates a friendly climate for key policy makers to support services for gifted education. (For information on public relations ideas, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1076217511427432">Besnoy, 2005</xref>.) Persistence is also key in advocacy. Building relationships takes time, and advocates need to be in it for the long haul. Advocacy is a continual process using interpersonal relationships and various forms of communication to promote and gain support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1076217511427432">Besnoy, 2005</xref>). There will be roadblocks to overcome. Using a warrior analogy,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>(a) all battles are local; (b) resistance and support can come from unexpected corners; (c) timing is critically important and frequently beyond your control; (d) expect to be attacked and wounded; (e) do not burn any bridges; (f) know that you will eventually want to live and work alongside your present enemies in peace; and (g) remember your efforts are for social justice and the future of gifted children. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1076217511427432">Burney &amp; Sheldon, 2010</xref>, p. 20)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Purpose, preparation, and persistence are important words for advocates if they want their advocacy efforts to be effective.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1076217511427432">
<title>Advocacy With Colleagues</title>
<p>At its core, advocacy is simply sharing information, and no one is better positioned to share the information about the educational needs of gifted students than the teachers who work with them every day. This sharing can begin with peers who may not be aware of the educational needs of gifted students. In fact, many educators still hold on to the myths about gifted children—myths like “gifted children will make it on their own.” This sharing might include providing basic strategies for teaching gifted students that peers can implement in their classrooms. It may be as simple as sharing the rationale and steps for curriculum compacting or strategies to tier an assignment to meet different students’ learning needs. It can also focus on accurate information about gifted children to whittle away at the mythology.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1076217511427432">
<title>Advocacy for a Schoolwide Plan</title>
<p>Advocacy also involves building support within one’s community for services for gifted students. This support includes helping school and community leaders understand the importance of providing educational services for gifted and talented students. This includes sharing the academic needs of gifted students, which involves a continuum of possible services that could be offered from simple differentiation in the classroom to whole-grade acceleration and special schools. It may include documenting how minimal adjustments in curriculum and instruction can have dramatic effects on gifted students’ academic achievement and attitude toward school and learning. Although community advocates traditionally have been parents of gifted students, educators in their role are more able to selflessly share their gifted expertise. This advocacy may be as simple as sharing with a neighbor or relative what one knows about gifted education. It also may be providing correct information when hearing a myth about gifted children, a myth spoken as a truth.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1076217511427432">
<title>Advocacy at the State Level</title>
<p>Whether a local school offers services for gifted students is often dependent on state regulations. Ideally, states mandate that students be identified, that those who are identified receive services, and that state funds are available to provide those services. Some states have all of these components; others have some or none. State legislators and department of education personnel must understand that gifted students, like all students, have a right to learn something new every day. Advocacy is necessary to maintain these three components if a state currently has them; advocacy is even more crucial to adopt them if they are not available.</p>
<p>One of the best ways to advocate at the state level is to become a member of the state gifted organization. State organizations provide <italic>impact</italic> through multiple advocates working together to make change happen, up-to-date <italic>information</italic> about the field of gifted education, and <italic>involvement</italic> with other passionate individuals who share an interest in gifted education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1076217511427432">Roberts &amp; Inman, 2009</xref>). Because advocates are information providers, the first step in becoming an advocate is educating oneself on the nature and needs of gifted students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1076217511427432">Wiskow, Fowler, &amp; Christopher, 2010</xref>). The state association is an excellent resource for information.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1076217511427432">
<title>Advocacy at the National Level</title>
<p>Finally, teacher and parent support is needed to ensure that giftedness and high potential in youth are nationally recognized, universally valued, and actively supported and developed. To that end, the National Association for Gifted Children (NAGC) is committed to sharing three key messages with the public and policy makers:</p>
<list id="list2-1076217511427432" list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Our nation’s ability to compete tomorrow depends on how well schools challenge advanced students today.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>When gifted students from disadvantaged backgrounds lose ground year after year, our nation is leaving a national treasure behind.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Every child deserves to maximize his or her potential.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<p>Collaborating with a national organization is much more efficient than “going it alone.”</p>
<p>NAGC is committed to helping the public understand these themes and implement federal legislation to support them. Jane Clarenbach in the NAGC office has organized a Legislative Action Network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nagc.org/index.aspx?id=970">http://www.nagc.org/index.aspx?id=970</ext-link>) that provides the latest information about gifted and talented legislative issues at the nati]onal level. Teachers need to be part of that network. Parents need to be part of that network. Grandparents need to be part of that network. Friends need to be part of that network. The dream of every child learning something new every day becomes a reality only if everyone joins together.</p>
<p>Another national organization that focuses on advocacy for exceptional children, including children who are gifted and talented, is the Association for the Gifted (TAG), a division of the Council for Exceptional Children. This organization places a priority on gifted children from diverse backgrounds and advances an advocacy agenda often in partnership with NAGC.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Advocacy opportunities abound:</p>
<p>There is definitely a place for advocacy for gifted children in every conversation about new standards, RtI, and Race to the Top, because within each of those initiatives are common goals that are a perfect fit for gifted learners—1. Increased rigor that will make our students globally competitive; 2. Focus on growth; 3. High Quality Teaching and Learning; and 4. Individual Accountability. These goals can and will support quality education for gifted students, but it is important for gifted advocates to “be in the room.” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1076217511427432">Lanham, 2010</xref>, p. 7)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>A common phrase among advocates is, “If you are not at the table, you are on the menu.” Educators must be at the table advocating for the needs of gifted students. Change within education happens, and educators can either be recipients of it or agents in it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1076217511427432">Horton, 2010</xref>). Part of being a professional is having one’s voice heard and being part of the process.</p>
<p>For many teachers, the role of advocate is a new one. Getting educators involved in advocating at the school, school district, state, and national levels will raise awareness of the needs of gifted children as well as legislation, policies, and best practices to address those needs. Educators have an important role to play in advocating for children who are gifted and talented. A key question for teachers is, “If not you, then who?”</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author(s) declare no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the authorship and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1076217511427432">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Besnoy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Using public relations strategies to advocate for gifted programming in your school</article-title>. <source>Gifted Child Today</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>32</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1076217511427432">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burney</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>, <month>March</month>). <article-title>Warrior advocates</article-title>. <source>Parenting for High Potential</source>, <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1076217511427432">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Duffett</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loveless</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>High-achieving students in the era of No Child Left Behind</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Thomas S. Fordham Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1076217511427432">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flom</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Emerging trends: Teachers as advocates</article-title>. <source>Cooperative Catalyst</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://coopcatalyst.wordpress.com/2010/06/11/emerging-trend-teachers-as-advocates/">http://coopcatalyst.wordpress.com/2010/06/11/emerging-trend-teachers-as-advocates/</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1076217511427432">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Calling teachers to action beyond SB 6</article-title>. <source>Ecology of Education</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ecologyofeducation.net/wsite/?p=2311">http://ecologyofeducation.net/wsite/?p=2311</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1076217511427432">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lanham</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>CHALLENGE—The key message for gifted advocacy</article-title>. <source>KAGE Update</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1076217511427432">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Inman</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>, <month>December</month>). <article-title>Advocacy: The importance of joining your state gifted organization</article-title>. <source>Parenting for High Potential</source>, <fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1076217511427432">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wiskow</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christopher</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A call to action: Advocacy at all levels</article-title>. <source>Tempo</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>