<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ECL</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">specl</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Early Childhood Literacy</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1468-7984</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-2919</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1468798411417378</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1468798411417378</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>‘They tell a story and there's meaning behind that story’: Indigenous knowledge and young indigenous children's literacy learning</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Hare</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1468798411417378"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1468798411417378">University of British Columbia, Canada</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1468798411417378">Jan Hare, Department of Language and Literacy Education, University of British Columbia, 2125 Main Mall, Vancouver, British Columbia, V6T 1Z4, Canada Email: <email>jan.hare@ubc.ca</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>389</fpage>
<lpage>414</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This research draws on the reflections from group discussions with indigenous families and interviews with early childhood educators and community stakeholders from five First Nations reserve communities in Canada whose young children participate in the national aboriginal Head Start On Reserve (AHSOR) programme. The purpose of the study was to examine the contributions of indigenous knowledge to young indigenous children's literacy learning. In the course of this examination what became clear is that there is a greater set of literacy activities in these families than is recognized by early learning settings. Further, there is a literacy orientation within their indigenous knowledge systems that, draws on oral tradition, land-based experiences and ceremonial practices that, when linked to the discourses of schooling and literacy, provide the basis for improving educational outcomes for indigenous children and families, whose relationship with schooling has been historically troubled.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>early literacy</kwd>
<kwd>early childhood programmes and services</kwd>
<kwd>indigenous children and families</kwd>
<kwd>indigenous knowledge</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1468798411417378" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Indigenous people have not been served well by schools in many areas of the world. Indigenous children do not experience the same success in literacy as their non-indigenous counterparts. For example, in British Columbia, Canada, more than 40% of aboriginal children failed the province-wide reading tests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1468798411417378">Cowley and Easton, 2004</xref>). In New Zealand, young Maori and Pasifika students at the end of year one in English schools had a lower level of literacy than any other ethnic group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1468798411417378">Ministry of Education, 2009</xref>). And in Australia, young aboriginal children score significantly below average in literacy benchmarks, and dismally so in rural areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1468798411417378">Frigo et al., 2004</xref>). The result has been a troubling disparity in academic achievement between indigenous and non-indigenous learners, as seen in Canada where nearly half the aboriginal youth fail to attain a high school diploma. The situation is similar in the USA where the academic outcomes for Native Indian and Alaskan Native youth are significantly lower than for European Americans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1468798411417378">Freeman and Fox, 2005</xref>). Many indigenous people, then, do not have the literacy knowledge and skills necessary to participate fully in society. For example, more than 60% of Canadian aboriginal people, aged 16 years and over, who took part in the International Adult Literacy Survey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1468798411417378">Statistics Canada, 2003</xref>) failed to meet the basic standard Level 3, a level considered necessary for participation in everyday work and life in a developed country. In Australia and New Zealand, indigenous adults perform similarly, as reflected in the low social, economic and health indicators observed among indigenous peoples.</p>
<p>There is converging evidence that young children's early literacy development is crucial for their later success in school and life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1468798411417378">Dickinson and Tabors, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1468798411417378">Roberts et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1468798411417378">Senechal et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1468798411417378">Snow et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1468798411417378">Sulzby and Teale, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-1468798411417378">Whitehurst and Lonigan, 2002</xref>). There is also compelling evidence that children familiar with the knowledge and skills associated with the dominant literacy practices of schooling tend to have an advantage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1468798411417378">Purcell-Gates, 2001</xref>). Early literacy experiences have been found to influence children's learning opportunities positively in later school years. And so while families play a central role in children's early literacy development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1468798411417378">Cairney, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1468798411417378">Purcell-Gates, 1996</xref>), the literacy experiences of children from lower socioeconomic and minority backgrounds are often not consistent with the literacy practices they encounter in formal early learning settings and in school, resulting in their lack of success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1468798411417378">Arnold and Doctoroff, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1468798411417378">Heath, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1468798411417378">MacNaughton, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1468798411417378">Makin et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1468798411417378">Marsh, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1468798411417378">Neuman, 2006</xref>). The seminal work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1468798411417378">Heath (1983)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1468798411417378">Taylor and Dorsey Gaines (1988)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1468798411417378">Valdes (1996)</xref> demonstrates that when children's language and literacy experiences within their families and communities are different from the literacy expectations and practices of formal school, children do not do well. Despite consistent calls for educators to build on the literacy practices of children from diverse backgrounds, home and community literacy contributions to children's language and literacy development still tend to be ignored as educators struggle to move beyond dominant literacy paradigms, particularly in this age of high-stakes testing and outcomes-based accountability measures. For indigenous children, the need to bridge indigenous family and community cultural and linguistic experiences with school-based literacy expectations and practices is critical to improving their educational outcomes and future success and well-being. Early learning settings can play an important role in helping children become familiar with the literacy expectations of schooling.</p>
<p>While the diverse literacy practices of cultural and linguistic communities have received attention in the literature, there is a limited body of research addressing the practices and programmes that contribute to young indigenous children's literacy development. This study draws on focus group sessions with First Nations<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1468798411417378"/>1</sup> families and interviews with early childhood educators and community stakeholders from five First Nations reserve communities in western Canada, whose children participate in the national aboriginal Head Start On Reserve (AHSOR) programme. The purpose of this study was to examine the contributions of indigenous knowledge to young First Nations children's literacy learning. This paper describes the literacy experiences of First Nations children as framed by their local and culturally specific practices, learning processes and values, and suggests how educators can draw on these indigenous-specific experiences to equip indigenous children better for the process of schooling and enhance the literacy learning opportunities for all children. Developing an awareness of and appreciation for indigenous approaches to living and learning will provide the basis for improving the home-school connections that begin with early childhood for indigenous families and communities whose relationship with schooling has, historically, been troubled.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1468798411417378"><title>Indigenous knowledge: Theoretical perspective and analytical framework</title>
<p>This study is situated within an indigenous knowledge framework and has the goal of providing indigenous-informed perspectives to promote culturally appropriate frames of reference relevant to indigenous children, families and communities served by early childhood and school programmes. Indigenous peoples have their own ways of knowing, being, valuing and living in this world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1468798411417378">Brayboy and Maughan, 2009</xref>). Indigenous knowledge represents the local and culturally specific knowledge of a people that is dynamic, adapting over time and place (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1468798411417378">Battiste, 2005</xref>). It comprises their practices, values and beliefs, and is intimately linked to their worldview, their way of seeing and making sense of the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1468798411417378">Barnhardt and Kawagley, 2005</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1468798411417378">Battiste and Henderson (2000</xref>: 41) describe indigenous knowledge as a ‘complete knowledge system with its own epistemology, philosophy, and scientific and logical validity’.</p>
<p>Indigenous knowledge systems include learning processes that are social, inter-generational, holistic, oral- and narrative-based, and experiential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1468798411417378">Battiste, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1468798411417378">Canadian Council of Learning, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1468798411417378">Castellano, 2000</xref>). As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1468798411417378">Barnhardt and Kawagley (2005</xref>: 10) explain:<disp-quote>
<p>… education processes were carefully crafted around observing natural processes, adapting modes of survival, obtaining sustenance from the plant and animal world, and using natural materials to make their tools and implements. All of this was made understandable through demonstration and observation accompanied by thoughtful stories in which the lessons were imbedded.</p></disp-quote>Stories were the primary medium used to convey cultural knowledge. According to Castellano (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1468798411417378">2000</xref>: 31): ‘Stories inform and entertain; they hold up models of behaviour; and they sound warnings. Recounted in ceremonial settings and confirmed through many repetitions, they record the history of a people.’ Oral tradition gives authority to the spoken word and to the status of the person sharing knowledge in this form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1468798411417378">Dunn, 2001</xref>). In the indigenous learning context, knowledge is viewed as holistic, and attempts to fragment knowledge in order to achieve understanding only undermine the relationship between knowledge and social and cultural contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1468798411417378">Nakata et al., 2005</xref>). Further, knowledge is contained within cultural practices, where songs, dances and symbolic representations are repositories for the history, genealogies, thoughts and beliefs about the world and the relationships within it. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1468798411417378">Battiste (2002)</xref> underscores the relationship of indigenous languages to indigenous knowledge, asserting that those languages, and their symbolic, verbal and unconscious orders, give structure to indigenous knowledge.</p>
<p>Integral to indigenous knowledge are values that emphasize the relationship between one's self with others and the natural world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1468798411417378">Cajete, 2000</xref>). For example, indigenous knowledge is inherently tied to land, where meaning and identity are constructed through landscapes, territory and land formations. Land and community serve as sources of knowledge and authority, where meaning is constructed through relationships and experiences with a particular place (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1468798411417378">Michell et al., 2008</xref>). Indigenous people highly value relationships of family and community. Traditional learning emphasizes the role of parents and extended family, such as grandparents, aunts and cultural teachers, who include elders and spiritual leaders. Elders are highly regarded in the community and have the responsibility for ensuring the preservation and transmission of knowledge. Knowledge and languages are taught through social relationships, thus emphasizing the role of family and community as important sources of knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1468798411417378">Canadian Council of Learning, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>This study complements sociocultural theories of literacy with theories of indigenous knowledge. As a theoretical framework, indigenous knowledge is aligned with emergent theories of multiliteracies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1468798411417378">Cope and Kalantzis, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1468798411417378">New London Group, 1996</xref>) and multi-modality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1468798411417378">Jewitt and Kress, 2003</xref>) that suggest meaning is made through a range of communicative and repre- sentational modes including, but extending beyond, reading and writing. Proponents of these theories recognize images, movement, music, speech and digital forms as meaning-making modes. In this study, I draw on an indigenous knowledge framework to interpret and represent the cultural and specific ways that ‘meanings are made, distributed, received, interpreted and remade in interpretation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1468798411417378">Jewitt and Kress, 2003</xref>: 1) within indigenous communities.</p>
<p>Focusing on indigenous knowledge as a theory for understanding the literacy experiences of indigenous children and families helps us to theorize and describe the range of semiotic modes in use in a particular society (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1468798411417378">Kress, 2000</xref>). A Maori scholar, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1468798411417378">Smith (1999)</xref>, tells us that the privileging of Western knowledge is implicated in the struggle for the validity and legitimacy of indigenous knowledge. An indigenous knowledge framework allows us to link indigenous-specific cultural practices, learning processes and values with school-based literacy. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1468798411417378">Siegal (2006)</xref> says that more studies are needed to document what happens when multi-literacies and multi-modalities meet school-based literacy. By using indigenous knowledge as a theoretical framework, we are able to find educational advantages and opportunities in specific meaning-making practices, such as those of indigenous peoples. Moreover, an indigenous knowledge framework ‘creates a new balanced center and fresh vantage point’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1468798411417378">Battiste, 2005</xref>: 3) from which to examine the literacy experiences of indigenous children and families.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1468798411417378"><title>Relevant literature</title>
<p>Research suggests that children's literacy is shaped by the social and cultural contexts in which they live (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1468798411417378">Heath, 1983</xref>). Children from diverse family backgrounds experience literacy in different ways. Indigenous children draw on their rich cultural traditions and ancestral languages to provide them with meaning-making experiences that shape how they make sense of their world and to contribute to their socialization in early literacy practices. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1468798411417378">Hohepa and McNaughton (2002)</xref> describe how Maori teaching approaches focus on memorization and multiparty interactions, as young Maori children in New Zealand learn shared tribal knowledge contained in songs, narratives and genealogies. This orientation leads to interactions with written texts that differ from the dialogic method that is typically promoted in early childhood education and family literacy. Aboriginal children in Australia who are frequently raised in an oral culture are less likely to have experience with book-based literacy activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1468798411417378">Dunn, 2001</xref>). First Nations children in Canada learn to inscribe meaning onto landscapes through stories and land-based experiences, shaping their understanding of the centrality of land to their identity and way of life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1468798411417378">Hare, 2005</xref>). For young Pueblo children in the USA, learning the literacy they need in the Pueblo world requires cultural and linguistic interactions with their extended families, demonstrating the role of inter-generational learning in the transmission of indigenous knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1468798411417378">Romero, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Early childhood programmes can be valuable spaces in which to familiarize children and families from diverse backgrounds with the literacy of formal schooling. Assessing literacy and numeracy achievements of a group of Australian aboriginal children in each of their first three years of school, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1468798411417378">Frigo et al. (2004)</xref> observed that most of the children had attended preschool prior to formal schooling. Those who did well on early tests also did well on later tests of academic achievement. Chadwick (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1468798411417378">2004</xref>) interviewed a small group of Native American (Pima) parents about their children's participation in a Head Start programme in the USA. Parents viewed the programme as helpful in getting children ready for kindergarten, yet they were unaware of the specific literacy practices that took place in the programme. In their group interview with aboriginal parents from a preschool, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1468798411417378">Makin et al. (1999)</xref> found that these parents wanted their children to gain specific literacy skills, including print and book knowledge. In their review of children learning to read in northern Canada, where 64% of children aged five to nine years are aboriginal, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1468798411417378">O'Sullivan and Goosney (2007)</xref> reported that access to early childhood programmes can be a challenge. Yet, the literacy benefits for children attending programmes that include aboriginal content and reflect aboriginal culture are encouraging. Some children attending an aboriginal Head Start preschool programme maintained reading and language achievement gains made in the programme up to grade five. Another Canadian study indicated that 18% of six- to eleven-year-old First Nations children living on reserves had repeated a grade. The proportion dropped to 12% for children who had attended a preschool aboriginal Head Start programme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1468798411417378">Canadian Council of Learning, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1468798411417378">First Nations Centre, 2005</xref>). The benefits of quality early childhood programming for indigenous children include improved intellectual, economic and social outcomes.</p>
<p>While early childhood education programmes can foster young children's literacy development, the living and learning experiences of indigenous children are not always consistent with the literacy practices they encounter in early childhood education settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1468798411417378">Makin et al., 1999</xref>). Many literacy programmes delivered in indigenous early childhood settings have been developed based on research with mainstream families without appropriate adaptation for indigenous children and families, and where pedagogical strategies by early childhood educators may be inappropriate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1468798411417378">Hohepa and McNaughton, 2002</xref>). For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1468798411417378">Simpson and Clancy (2005)</xref> found that non-aboriginal educators in an Australian early childhood setting used forms of questioning that were not consistent with the language patterns of aboriginal children and families. Further, many early childhood educators are unfamiliar with indigenous culture, traditions, values and languages, making it difficult for them to make literacy learning relevant to the lives of indigenous children. Indigenous parents value the literacy practices associated with schooling, but want to ensure that their children are oriented towards their own cultural and linguistic practices in their early learning experiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1468798411417378">Chadwick, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1468798411417378">Hare, 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>Indigenous families are likely to approach early learning environments with caution. Their concerns are grounded in colonial practices, which introduced government-legislated child removal in countries such as Canada, the USA, New Zealand and Australia. Mission, boarding and residential schools were set up in these countries where the state took control of the care and education of indigenous children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1468798411417378">Armitage, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1468798411417378">Prochner, 2009</xref>). Children were removed from the influences of their families and communities to be indoctrinated into Christianity and to take up lifestyles based on newcomer ways. In Canada, children as young as four were taken from their families to attend residential schools across the country run by various religious denominations between 1850–1950. The systematic denigration of the indigenous knowledge embedded in their cultural practices, values and languages was the most destructive feature of those schools, which were then thought to be necessary as part of the ‘civilizing’ agenda of governments and missionaries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1468798411417378">Beresford and Partington, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1468798411417378">Miller, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1468798411417378">Milloy, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1468798411417378">Trafzer et al., 2006</xref>). It is a historical narrative of which many educators are unaware. The legacy of mission, residential and boarding schools taints the experiences that indigenous parents bring to formalized learning environments today (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1468798411417378">Hare and Anderson, 2010</xref>), and their participation in early childhood education cannot be viewed in isolation from this colonial history (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1468798411417378">Walker and Rodriguez de France, 2007</xref>). Schooling has been a site of rejection of indigenous knowledge, and has been charged with continuing to assimilate and integrate indigenous people peoples into the dominant society (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1468798411417378">May and Aikman, 2003</xref>). In her review of early childhood education programmes and services in Canada, Greenwood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1468798411417378">2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1468798411417378">2006</xref>) makes clear that early learning settings for aboriginal children must be developed and delivered based on aboriginal ways of knowing. Indigenous knowledge reflected in early learning settings offers the promise that indigenous children and families will find success in connecting with school-based literacy and enhances the learning opportunities for non-indigenous educators and learners.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1468798411417378"><title>Knowledge-gathering</title>
<p>This study explores the perspectives of First Nations family and community members on: (1) the literacy learning goals for young First Nations children; (2) literacy practices in the home and community; (3) literacy practices in the AHSOR programme; and (4) the role of language and culture in supporting First Nations children's literacy development. Parents, extended family, caregivers and community stakeholders from five aboriginal AHSOR programmes from western Canada took part in this study. AHSOR is an aboriginal early childhood intervention programme based on the US Head Start model. The federally funded national programme was developed based on consultation with aboriginal groups across Canada. It focuses on language and culture, nutrition, health promotion, education and school readiness, social support and parent and family involvement as its operating principles. Currently, AHSOR forms part of the early childhood programming in just over 350 First Nations reservation communities across Canada. This study was not an evaluation of the AHSOR programme. Rather, in keeping with protocols of respect and reciprocity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1468798411417378">Kovach, 2009</xref>) that are essential in indigenous research, this researcher collaborated with the AHSOR programmes to investigate the early literacy experiences of young First Nations children and their families living on reserves in Canada. Administrators of the AHSOR programme were particularly interested in how they might enhance support for the language and literacy experiences of young First Nations children so as to prepare their children better for schooling.</p>
<p>Five AHSOR projects sites were visited. Two of the sites were in remote locations (AH and K), accessible only by boat, plane or dirt-logging roads. The other three programmes (AL, P, and C) were located in close proximity to small urban centres. Interviews were conducted with at least two staff members and two community stakeholders from each of the five programmes. Staff included the coordinator of the programme; interestingly, only one of the five coordinators identified herself as having First Nations ancestry and being a member of the First Nations community where she worked. Four of the five early childhood educators, or caregivers as they are often referred to in an indigenous context, identified First Nations. Community stakeholders were defined as those who are associated with the programme through volunteer work or who provide indirect support to the programme. Stakeholders taking part in this study included two elders, a language teacher, three schoolteachers, three community administrators of the programme and a community-elected education counsellor. Of the stakeholders interviewed, all but two of the teachers identified First Nations. Interviews were approximately one to two hours in length.</p>
<p>With family members, a less formal focus/discussion group format was used. Family members included parents, grandparents, aunts or uncles and primary caregivers, such as foster parents. Extended family is highly valued in indigenous communities and children's well-being is a collective responsibility. The number of family members taking part in focus group discussions varied in each programme, with a total of 62 family members in all taking part in this study. Focus group/discussions ranged from one and a half to three hours in length. The discussion groups were framed as sharing circles. This form of gathering knowledge is based on tribal traditions, where the sharing circle represents the act of the community coming together to share collectively and where each person has an opportunity to be heard through turn taking. Kovach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1468798411417378">2009</xref>: 124–5) suggests that this method is more elastic: ‘It becomes less about research participants responding to research questions, and more about the participants sharing their stories in relation to the question.’</p>
<p>The researcher and research assistant also spent time observing programme settings and attending events in each of the communities, taking field notes along the way. This approach was not intended to represent an ‘ethnographic’ account of the literacy practices within the community, but allowed the researcher to get a sense of the distinct language, cultures and traditions within each of these small homogenous communities. The events, activities and documents observed in each of the five project sites could then be situated within a specific cultural context. Cultural practices and learning processes taking place in the programme could be observed, such as dance, song, storytelling, drumming and alternative expressions, and understood in relation to family, programmatic and community expressions of indigenous knowledge.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1468798411417378"><title>Analysis of data</title>
<p>Interviews and focus/discussion group sessions were transcribed and sent to participants for verification and accuracy. Two levels of analysis were conducted of the resulting transcripts. Focus/discussion group sessions and interviews were first analysed to identify comments that related to the four areas of focus for the interviews and sharing circles (literacy goals for their children; literacy practices in the home and community; literacy practices in AHSOR; the role of culture and language in supporting children's literacy). The transcripts were read for themes in the responses related to the focus areas across all the conversations. A second level of analysis coded participants' responses within an indigenous knowledge framework represented by five features that are relatively common across indigenous societies. These features include: (1) culturally specific practices that children and families take part in; (2) examples of values inherent within indigenous knowledge systems; (3) processes that reflect indigenous approaches to learning; (4) artefacts of the local culture; and (5) the role of indigenous languages in the lives of children and families. While used as discrete categories for the analysis of responses, these features operate as complete and interrelated systems of meaning. What emerged from the conversations with participants focused mainly on cultural practices, values and learning processes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1468798411417378"><title>Themes and findings</title>
<sec id="sec7-1468798411417378"><title>Theme 1: Family and community perspectives on early literacy</title>
<p>The central theme emerging from the conversations with family, caregivers and community stakeholders was that these First Nations families engaged in a greater set of literacy practices than were recognized by those working and associated with the AHSOR project sites. I first describe the kinds of literacy practices that First Nations families reported that they take part in with their children, and then share the perceptions of caregivers and community stakeholders that suggested families are limited in the literacy experiences they provide. In each of the sharing circles, there were many parents and family members who reflected on the value of literacy learning in the early years. Literacy for their children was more than ‘reading and learning their letters'. Definitions of literacy included ‘learning to communicate, they're learning how to interact’, ‘learn[ing] to touch things and stuff. Crawl, eating’, ‘use[ing] the computers’ and ‘playing games’. They recognized that literacy learning began very early in life, as noted by one parent: ‘You can start right from the time that they're born even, you know, reading to them, talking to them’ (site P).</p>
<p>Parents and family members were able to describe a range of activities they engage in their homes and in the community with their children to support literacy learning. Most of their conversations focused on reading or having books in the home. ‘I think they start learning when they're babies, when you read a book to them,’ said one parent (site K). Another parent said: ‘I started reading to my daughter when she was a baby and now she's at a point where she's doing make-up stories' (site AH). They also described ‘playing music to them’, ‘having toys that teach’, ‘use[ing] the computer’ and ‘at home [I] teach them to count. It's teaching them how to interact.’</p>
<p>In each of the five sharing circles, there was at least one parent who voiced challenges associated with reading to their child or engaging their child in some of the literacy activities that other parents described. As one parent said: ‘I like to read to him, but I am not very good at it’ (site AL). Another parent also shared: ‘I don't know how to read to my kids’ (site AL). Interestingly, in some instances, others in the discussion group would try to help parents overcome their concerns by suggesting strategies or approaches to try. As one parent suggested, it is a matter of ‘accept[ing] you have that limitation or a bit of a disability or something [not reading] and finding a different way’ (site AL). When one young woman at a programme described how she did not like to read to her child, another in the discussion group encouraged her and others to think about ‘the courage and strength it takes some people to overcome the issues they may have in the home, in their life, their past’ (site AH).</p>
<p>Although all parents reported engaging in literacy activities with their children at home, caregivers and stakeholders consistently called for more parental involvement in children's literacy learning. Describing parental support for children's learning, one caregiver expressed:<disp-quote>
<p>We need to get them [parents] in the [pre]school. We need to help them strengthen their skills for the long run. More books in the home at their level and educating parents on the importance of literacy. Reassuring them that being able to read and being educated is also important. (site AH)</p></disp-quote>Unsure of what might account for the perceived limited parental engagement in young children's literacy learning, the education counsellor at one programme felt that they ‘need to do some kind of survey’ (site AH). At another programme, a caregiver acknowledged that parents are able to support their children's literacy learning, saying: ‘Some of our parents do read to their children and it's quite obvious because of the way the children are with books and listening to stories’ (site C). But this caregiver also noted:<disp-quote>
<p>I think they’re [parents] all able to do it, but do they understand the importance of it and do they know how to go about it. I don’t know that all parents understand that… You know, they may not realize what value their child may receive by reading a book to them. (site C)</p></disp-quote>An administrator for one of the programmes explained:<disp-quote>
<p>What I also see going on in the houses, a lot of the skills are learned unfortunately through the television. I see a lot of parents, young parents, frustrated and it’s easier to throw a Barney video in than sit down with the child and read or talk to them. (site K)</p></disp-quote>Some parents were also described as simply too busy in their lives. ‘I think a lot of parents are quite busy as far as upgrading. That's been a huge responsibility with upgrading education and a lot of parents are involved in adult ed[ucation]’ (site K).</p>
<p>Caregivers and community stakeholders gave several explanations for what they saw as parents' limited involvement in young children's literacy development. The first was the historical legacy of schooling for aboriginal people in Canada. One caregiver stated:<disp-quote>
<p>I know lots of parents, they just kind of get shy… or they might have had a bad experience with school so it’s hard to make sure that they get that friendly atmosphere. And people experienced residential school and just weren’t comfortable in the school setting. [We’re] working to change that so they can support their children and feel valued in their education as well. (site P)</p></disp-quote>Speaking about the inter-generational impacts of residential schooling, one caregiver noted:<disp-quote>
<p>Not only are they [parents] not ready, they just might not know how. They might not know the value [of reading to their children]. It might not have been part of their upbringing to value that. It might be something that they don’t know anything about. It hadn’t been part of their life and it’s because we tend to do what we have learned as we go along and because it was something they never experienced they don’t pass it on to their kids either. (site C)</p></disp-quote>An administrator at another project talked about the early childhood programme needing to build trust with the parents: ‘For us at this point in time with some of the dysfunction that's been happening with the consumption of alcohol and the effects of the residential schooling, these were priorities for us  …  Let's deal with these first’ (site K). Negative experiences with schooling may justify what one parent describes: ‘We're just about 100% dependent on the education system to teach our children and that's a really unfair advantage’ (site AH).</p>
<p>Cultural priorities were described as another reason why some parents or family members may not support school-based literacy practices. An elder from one of the project sites explained: ‘I think it's [literacy learning] important, but there is a lack of it. There's a lack of support I think from families. Other things are more important to them  …  They spend a lot of time preparing for the ceremonies’ (site C). Several parents at the project sites confirmed this. One parent explained about needing to be away from home at times: ‘When they [children] don't come with me [to the Longhouse], I explain where I am going and that it [the ceremony] might take long  …  ’ (site C). At another programme, an administrator explained that cultural priorities on the part of families led to different forms of literacy learning:<disp-quote>
<p>Every home is unique in that way because there’s some homes you have a lot of readers and in some homes you don’t. One big way here might be the reliance on oral tradition. A lot of storytelling by the Elders. (site K)</p></disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1468798411417378"><title>Theme 2: Indigenous children learning from indigenous knowledge</title>
<p>Participants were asked to consider the role of aboriginal culture and language in supporting young First Nations children's literacy development. They identified a range of cultural practices that children took part in. These included drumming, singing, dancing, picking medicines (e.g. herbs and plants) or berries, fishing and hunting, gathering food and preparing traditional foods. At three of the project sites, it was shared that children take part in cultural ceremonies held in the community. One elder said:<disp-quote>
<p>They teach the ceremonies that they have to do and when they’re going to be. And how to listen to and learn the ways of what they do for ceremonies. And they say that these kids are still too young but I say they’re not. (site C)</p></disp-quote>‘When there's a funeral our program's closed just to teach them respect,’ shared one staff member (site AH). Several of the projects described a ‘graduation’ for young children who would be moving on to kindergarten. At such an event these projects would adhere to traditional cultural protocols and practices, such as gift giving, songs, drumming or dance, elder participation, wearing traditional regalia, and witnessing.</p>
<p>Children engaged in learning that was experiential, land based, narrative and inter-generational. In two project sites, children regularly took part in traditional camps, where community programmes and schools were closed and children and families went out on the land to learn and carry out traditional activities, such as hunting, fishing, plant gathering, storytelling and communal practices associated with traditional life. Sharing the role of oral storytelling and its connection to its present-day context, one parent described: ‘I make up stories, like when we're walking in the woods  …  [I] keep their main character Wild Woman [cultural character] but I just put a slight modern twist on it’ (site C). At three sites, elders regularly visit to tell children local stories and show them how to do traditional activities, such as preparing medicines, berries and fish, demonstrating how knowledge is passed on through the generations. At another site, where access to cultural knowledge posed challenges as there were few elders and language speakers in the community, children went for daily walks on the land. Their visits to the sea and bush inspired conversations about landscape, traditional food sources and stories about traditional life. As one of the caregivers told the children on the walk, ‘long ago our people used to gather [name of plant in First Nations language] at this place’ (site AH). Then she told them when and how the plant was gathered and its medicinal purposes. Children came back to the centre and would then visit their ‘writing’ table, drawing pictures of their outings on the land. Caregivers would print their story beneath the pictures, usually just a few words or sentences. The programme coordinator commented: ‘We build on the culture and the local ways of living’ (site AH). At another site, the children and caregivers took walks through their First Nations community. One of the caregivers explained that this was a regular part of the programme. Their walks were not only along the few roads that went through this reserve, but to the bush, where children learned about their local environment. On one particular walk, caregivers pointed out to children the bark on the cedar trees and how it could be stripped and used to make baskets, hats and other artefacts of their culture. More importantly, she talked to the children about ‘giving thanks to all living things’, recognizing Mother Earth, the trees, rocks and plants as animate objects possessing spirit and life. All but one of the project sites framed their cultural curriculum around the seasonal living of First Nations peoples. For example, one coordinator pointed out: ‘This month we'll be getting salmonberries [spring season]  … In the fall  … everything you wanted to learn about herring roe’ (site K).</p>
<p>When asked how these cultural practices and learning processes might support children's literacy learning, some participants recognized the literacy orientations within indigenous knowledge. ‘My husband sings his traditional songs to our daughter in his language and they [songs] tell stories so he sings with her everyday,’ said one parent (site K). One mother explained about the tribal dancing the children watch and participate in: ‘They [dances] tell a story and there's meaning behind that story,’ (site AH). An administrator, talking about the oral storytelling shared with the children in her project site and the teachings within those stories, said: ‘It's different than sitting down and reading a book. But it's all got real meaning’ (site C). Speaking of the experiential approaches to learning, where children take part in cultural activities, one parent described:<disp-quote>
<p>There’s a variety of other experiences which might be a little bit better for him because he’s not so into the literacy part… It’s not handwriting and in the books. It’s like hands on and right there in front of you. (site P)</p></disp-quote>The opportunities for meaning-making within the worldview of indigenous peoples are conveyed by a non-First Nations caregiver:<disp-quote>
<p>I think the [First Nations] teach their children about things that are far more worth being valued than the things in my world that are valued as far as thanking a tree for giving its branches, to respecting their elders, to being part of a huge family that supports each other when there’s anything like the Big House [Longhouse]… There’s reading and writing and books and all that. But I think these kids got something way more because they’ve got a sense of who they are. (site C)</p></disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1468798411417378" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>To reiterate, some of the First Nations parents and family members we spoke with clearly value early literacy learning for their children, acknowledging that children's literacy development begins early in life. While parent and family members tended to emphasize reading books to their children, they also described a broader range of literacy activities they participate in with their children. For example, they: provide educational toys; use the computer with their children; sing, talk and play games with them; provide writing materials; and through direct instruction, teach children colours, numbers and letters. Interestingly, caregivers and stakeholders involved with the five project sites held very different perceptions of the kinds of literacy experiences that these First Nations parents were providing to their children. They suggested that parents had limited knowledge and skills about how best to support children's learning or that cultural priorities were the reasons parents may not engage in literacy learning with their children. It is important to note that their perceptions of parent's limited engagement with early literacy activities were situated within a historical context, acknowledging that child-removal policies and efforts at cultural revitalization may constrain the ways parents are able to contribute to young First Nations children's literacy learning. They are able to ‘read’ the families taking part in their programmes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1468798411417378">Whitehouse and Colvin, 2001</xref>) to move beyond their expectations for how indigenous parents and families should support their children's learning and consider the social and cultural conditions that bear upon indigenous families’ literate activities. This might be due, in part, to how early learning programmes and services need to establish parental trust to engage indigenous families effectively. This requires knowledge of the history, culture and languages of indigenous families and communities achieved through understanding and dialogue with indigenous peoples.</p>
<p>There is a growing body of literature that asserts that indigenous knowledge contributes positively to a coherent identity for indigenous children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1468798411417378">Ball, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1468798411417378">Beresford and Partington, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1468798411417378">Bergstrom et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1468798411417378">Canadian Council of Learning, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1468798411417378">Grande, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1468798411417378">Royal Commission on aboriginal Peoples, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1468798411417378">Smith, 2000</xref>). What has been overlooked are the ways in which indigenous knowledge can build on the skills and knowledge associated with school-based literacy practices. Participants in this study acknowledge a literacy orientation within the cultural practices, learning processes and values, where song, dance and landscape convey meaning to children. The meanings derived from these cultural, social and visual practices foster identity as these young First Nations children gain knowledge of their histories, stories and languages, affirming who they are and their place in their world. Further, they come to understand the significance, context and protocols associated with their long-standing knowledge traditions. Alongside these critical cultural learning opportunities, young indigenous children and their families can be apprenticed into the world of school-based literacy. In their response to the National Early Literacy Panel (NELP) in the USA, Orellana and D'warte (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1468798411417378">2010</xref>: 297) argue that ‘we should be looking at the skills that are demanded and developed through the very experience of being a member of nondominant social groups’, especially since we need to prepare children for the broad, flexible and transcultural language and literacy skills that will be demanded in the future. The authors take issue with the narrow set of precursor skills that lead to the development of conventional literacy skills, suggesting that we need to examine and value other kinds of ‘head starts’ that children experience in coming to early literacy.</p>
<p>Oral tradition is the primary means by which indigenous knowledge is stored and transmitted. Despite the devastating impact of colonialism in the First Nations communities visited for this study, there remains a strong oral tradition within several of them, as observed in the storytelling practices in the programme, where elders shared local stories in circle time or when the language was being taught and caregivers and community members shared stories while on land-based outings. Further, the cultural curriculum within three of the project sites emphasized local stories. Oral tradition as a cultural resource can be applied to young indigenous children's language and literacy development. Oral narrative skills have been found to be predictors of literacy skills that include story knowledge, increased vocabulary and comprehension (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1468798411417378">Snow et al., 2001</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1468798411417378">Francis and Reyhner (2002)</xref> suggest that the under-utilization of this cultural resource is a missed opportunity for educators, especially since oral tradition in its various forms fulfils the requirements for high-quality literature and is rich in literacy learning opportunities. They point out that oral storytelling in the indigenous context promotes oral language development, comprehension and listening skills, as well as introducing young indigenous children to different forms of narrative and story structure, and the literary strategies of metaphor, prediction, foreshadowing and contradiction. Drawing on the particular cultural narrative of trickster stories, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1468798411417378">Francis and Reyhner (2002)</xref> demonstrate how this story form lends itself to the development of literacy-related language abilities that underlie reading comprehension and written expression. Coyote is a main cultural character for many tribal groups. As a trickster figure, it is through his foolish or selfish antics that children come to understand cultural teachings. Indigenous storytelling draws on repetition of language as both a narrative and a memory device (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1468798411417378">Archibald, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1468798411417378">Hayne and MacDonald, 2003</xref>). This artful repetition, say <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1468798411417378">Francis and Reyhner (2002)</xref>, introduces indigenous children to elements and patterns in literature, especially those that characterize their community. They further explain that the rich use of metaphor and wordplay within themes of trickster stories, such as deceit, cleverness and wisdom, calls attention to how language can be used to create meaning, produce effect and provoke a reaction. A precursor to reading and writing, storytelling serves as a traditional teaching method and is particularly relevant to indigenous children and families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1468798411417378">McKeough et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1468798411417378">Timmons et al., 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>The use of indigenous narrative was extended to land-based experiences, where caregivers shared cultural practices, values and teachings as young First Nations children in the various project sites experience and observe their natural surroundings. The daily land-based outings, such as those observed in some of the programmes, reinforced for children their relationship with the land. As Tewe scholar, Cajete (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1468798411417378">2000</xref>: 178), explains:<disp-quote>
<p>[Indigenous] peoples understood that all entities of nature – plants, animals, stones, trees, mountains, rivers, lakes, and a host of other living entities – embodied relationships that must be honored. Through the seeking, making, sharing, and celebrating of these natural relationships, they came to perceive themselves as living in a sea of relationships.</p></disp-quote>It is through these intimate relationships with the natural world, that knowledge is accumulated. Young indigenous children learn to interpret their environment and understand the significance of place, territory and landscape through land-based pedagogies, which emphasize stories, specific teachings, observation and experiential learning. They are ‘reading their world’ and, in doing so, learning their histories, ideologies and identities. Furthermore: ‘Geography is not only a matter of location, distance, and elevation, but is additionally permeated with meaning and cultural significance’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1468798411417378">Riggs, 2005</xref>: 303). Young children's experiences on the land help them make connections between how the natural world works and their own lives. They come to know the life cycles and behaviours of animals, the weather patterns and plants that emerge in the seasons, and the particular uses of flora and fauna, which demonstrate how symbolic systems are deeply encoded across many dimensions of their environment. As Hare (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1468798411417378">2005</xref>) asserts, approaches to literacy need to include indigenous people's connection to the natural world as a legitimate ‘text’ from which to learn alongside the print traditions learned in educational settings, particularly as indigenous people attempt to define new traditions of living on the land.</p>
<p>The First Nations children in this study experience ceremony through participation in the AHSOR programme and community events. At these important cultural observances, children and families experience a wide range of linguistic and literate practices. There are likely to be forms of oral tradition that include speeches, stories, prayers of thanks and witnessing. They may also experience dances and songs, which one participant described as ‘telling a story and there's meaning behind that story’ (site AH). Their dances combine bodily forms, facial expressions and movement of the hands to tell ‘that story’. The cultural expression of dance can bring together a range of modes, where gestures accompany a mythic mask figure and song accompanies the drum, rattle or shells, linking meaningful sign forms in a cultural context. Meaning-making then becomes multiplied across these modes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1468798411417378">Pahl, 2003</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1468798411417378">Baquedano-Lopez (2004)</xref> suggests that cultural practices associated with ceremony or ritual reveal the complex nature of community-learning opportunities and local interpretive practices and that it may be useful for educators to understand how these cultural and local literacy practices are organized by members of a community, how they work for them and how they can be useful for interpreting new material.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-1468798411417378" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>This study of First Nations children's early literacy learning opportunities in five AHSOR project sites recognizes that there are many practices that constitute literacy. The parents and caregivers taking part in sharing circles and interviews viewed local cultural practices and particular values as serving cultural and social functions, but also recognized the meaning-making contributions within indigenous knowledge and the potential and promise for young children's early literacy development for both participation in community and schooling. Young First Nations children taking part in AHSOR programmes have opportunities to experience their cultural heritage and ancestral languages, given the goals of this national programme. They learn ways of knowing and being specific to their communities and Nations, drawing on the repositories of indigenous knowledge that include land, ceremony, oral tradition and elders, families and community members. This acquired valuable knowledge needs to be taken up in early learning programmes and services that support indigenous children and families and linked with the discourses of schooling and literacy. Rather than seeing indigenous knowledge and its various forms as an anthropological curiosity or even entertainment, places of learning should come to see indigenous knowledge as a legitimate source of knowledge. That knowledge must be respected and honoured if children and families, particularly those from diverse cultural and linguistic communities, are to bridge the gap between the literacy of home and community and school.</p>
<p>The challenge for educators who work with indigenous children, then, is to create space for indigenous knowledge so as to support indigenous children and families. This requires caregivers and educators to familiarize themselves with the families and communities with whom they work. The most effective means for achieving this are through relationship building and dialogue with indigenous families and communities which, at times, may require special outreach efforts, given indigenous people' prior negative experiences with schools and other mainstream institutions. Special outreach may take the form of: meeting families outside the early learning setting within their own familiar spaces of home and community; enhancing collaboration with families on the part of service providers such as speech-language pathologists, family support workers and cultural enrichment programmes; new forms of professional development that inform educators about indigenous knowledge and history; and attending community events to become familiar with the social and cultural contexts of families’ lives. These opportunities allow caregivers and educators to make connections between indigenous knowledge and the curriculum and pedagogies of early learning and literacy. So, for example, they can learn about the kinds of stories relevant to indigenous families, the themes, different styles and basic organizational structures of traditional oral stories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1468798411417378">Francis and Reyhner, 2002</xref>). They may come to see outdoor spaces ‘on the land’ as appropriate learning settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1468798411417378">Greenwood and Shawana, 1999</xref>), that ‘the land is the first teacher’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1468798411417378">Haig-Brown and Dannenmann, 2008</xref>: 248).</p>
<p>As this study demonstrates, caregivers and educators need to listen closely to the literacy learning goals and educational aspirations that indigenous families and communities articulate for their young children. Indigenous families want their children to become successful in the dominant literacy practices of schooling and early learning programmes offer families that opportunity. But as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1468798411417378">Noll (1998)</xref> reminds us in her case study of two Native American youths, validating expressions of cultural knowledge through language, arts, dance and music, the literacy strengths that exist for indigenous learners outside of school might be clearly revealed within the school. Literacy pedagogies that are effective in the early years and most appropriate for local contexts ‘work productively and sensitively with indigenous forms of knowledge, and  … draw on children's multiple semiotic resources in combination with other forms of knowledge [and] are equally important and powerful’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1468798411417378">Prinsloo and Stein, 2005</xref>: 138–9). That orientation would certainly provide a more balanced and holistic approach to supporting indigenous children and families, both in continuing to pass on their own traditional knowledge while learning the knowledge and skills necessary for success in school and to participate fully in society.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back><notes>
<title>Note</title>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1-1468798411417378"><label>1</label><p>First Nations people make up almost 60% of the aboriginal population. While the First Nations people are equally divided, living on reserves and in rural/urban centres, the First Nations participants of this study reside on reserve communities. Reserves are land-based communities negotiated through treaties between First Nations groups and the federal government. There are over 615 First Nations reserve communities across Canada. I use the term First Nations when referring to the participants and programmes of this study.</p></fn></fn-group></notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Archibald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Indigenous Storywork: Educating the Heart, Mind, Body and Spirit</source>, <publisher-loc>Vancouver, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UBC Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Comparing the Policy of Aboriginal Assimilation in Australia, Canada and New Zealand</source>, <publisher-loc>Vancouver, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UBC Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Doctoroff</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The Early Education of Socioeconomically Disadvantaged Children</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Psychology</source> <volume>54</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>517</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Supporting Young Indigenous Children's Language Development in Canada: A Review of Research on Needs and Promising Practices</article-title>. <source>The Canadian Modern Language Review</source> <volume>66</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baquedano-Lopez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Literacy Practices across Contexts</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Duranti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Companion to Linguistic Anthropology</source>, <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnhardt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawagley</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Indigenous Knowledge Systems and Alaska Ways of Knowing</article-title>. <source>Anthropology and Educational Quarterly</source> <volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Battiste</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Maintaining Aboriginal Identity, Languages and Culture in Modern Society</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Battiste</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Reclaiming Indigenous Voice and Vision</source>, <publisher-loc>Vancouver, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UBC Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Battiste</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Indigenous Knowledge: Foundations for First Nations</article-title>. <source>World Indigenous Nations Higher Education Consortium Journal</source>. <comment>4 January, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.win-hec.org/docs/pdfs/Journal/Marie%20Battiste%20copy.pdf">http://www.win-hec.org/docs/pdfs/Journal/Marie%20Battiste%20copy.pdf</ext-link> (consulted August 2011</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Battiste</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Protecting Indigenous Knowledge and Heritage: A Global Challenge</source>, <publisher-loc>Saskatoon, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Purich</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Beresford</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Partington</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Reform and Resistance in Aboriginal Education: The Australian Experience</source>, <publisher-loc>Crawley, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Western Australia Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergstrom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>The Seventh Generation: Native Students Speak about Finding the Good Path</source>, <publisher-loc>Charleston, WV</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ERIC Clearinghouse on Rural Education and Small Schools</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brayboy</surname><given-names>BMJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maughn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Indigenous Knowledges and the Story of the Bean</article-title>. <source>Harvard Educational Review</source> <volume>79</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cairney</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Developing Parent Partnerships in Secondary Literacy Learning</article-title>. <source>Journal of Reading</source> <volume>38</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>520</fpage>–<lpage>526</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cajete</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Native Science. Natural Laws of Interdependence</source>, <publisher-loc>Santa Fe, NM</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Clear Light Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Canadian Council of Learning</collab> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Redefining How Success is Measured in First Nations, Inuit and Metis Learning</source>, <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Canadian Council of Learning</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Canadian Council of Learning</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <source>The State of Aboriginal Learning in Canada</source>, <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Canadian Council of Learning</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castellano</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Updating Aboriginal Traditions of Knowledge</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dei</surname><given-names>GJS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Indigenous Knowledges in Global Contexts: Multiple Readings of our World</source>, <publisher-loc>Toronto, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Chadwick, D. (2004) ‘Structuring Classroom Literacy Learning: Perspectives of Parents, Staff and Community in an Indigenous Head Start Center’, paper presented at the American Educational Research Association, San Diego, CA, April</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Cope</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalantzis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Multiliteracies: Literacy Learning and the Design of Social Futures</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cowley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Easton</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Report Card on Aboriginal Education in British Columbia</source>, <publisher-loc>Vancouver, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fraser Institute</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Department of Indian Affairs and Northern Development Canada</collab> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Our Children – Keepers of the Sacred Knowledge: Final Report of the Minister's National Working Group on Education</source>, <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Indian and Northern Affairs Canada</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabors</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Early Literacy: Linkages between Home, School and Literacy Achievement at Age Five</article-title>. <source>Journal of Research in Childhood Education</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Aboriginal Literacy: Reading the Tracks</article-title>. <source>The Reading Teacher</source> <volume>54</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>678</fpage>–<lpage>687</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>First Nations Centre</collab> (<year>2005</year>) <source>First Nations Regional Longitudinal Health Survey (RHS): 2002/2003</source>, <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Aboriginal Health Organization</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyhner</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Language and Literacy Teaching for Indigenous Education: A Bilingual Approach</source>, <publisher-loc>Clevedon, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Multilingual Matters</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Status and Trends in the Education of American Indians and Alaska Natives</source>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>US Government Printing Office</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frigo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Corrigan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Supporting English Literacy and Numeracy for Indigenous Students in the Early Years</source>, <publisher-loc>Camberwell, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Australian Council for Educational Research</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grande</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Red Pedagogy: Native American Social and Political Thought</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>An Overview of the Development of Aboriginal Early Childhood Services in Canada</source>. <comment>Retrieved from ERIC database (ED456954)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Children Are a Gift to Us: Aboriginal-Specific Early Childhood Programs and Services in Canada</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Native Education</source> <volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shawana</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Whispered Gently through Time: Quality Aboriginal Childcare in Canada</source>, <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Human Resources Development Canada, Government of Canada</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haig-Brown</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dannenmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The Land is the First Teacher: The Indigenous Knowledge Instructor’s Program</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bekerman</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopelowitz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Cultural Education and Cultural Stability: Minority, Diaspora, Indigenous and Ethnoreligious Groups in Multi-Cultural Societies</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Hare, J. (2001) ‘Aboriginal Literacy. Making Meaning across Three Generations in an Anishinaabe Community’, unpublished doctoral dissertation, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, Canada</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hare</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2005</year>) <article-title>To Know Papers: Aboriginal Perspectives on Literacy</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kendrick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Smythe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Portraits of Literacy across Families, Communities and Schools</source>, <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hare</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Transitions to Early Childhood for Indigenous Children and Families in Canada: Historical and Social Realities</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Early Childhood</source>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The Socialization of Autobiographical Memory in Children and Adults: The Roles of Culture and Gender</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Fivush</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haden</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Autobiographical Memory and the Construction of a Narrative Self: Developmental and Cultural Perspectives</source>, <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <source>Ways with Words</source>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hohepa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McNaughton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Indigenous Literacies: The Case of Maori Literacy</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Makin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Literacies in Early Childhood: Changing Views, Challenging Practice</source>, <publisher-loc>Sydney, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MacLennand and Petty</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jewitt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Multimodal Literacy</source>, <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Peter Lang</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Indigenous Methodologies: Characteristics, Conversations, and Contexts</source>, <publisher-loc>Toronto, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Early Spelling: Between Convention and Creativity</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKeough</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tourignay</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Romaine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ottmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Storytelling as a Foundation to Literacy Development for Aboriginal Children: Culturally and Developmentally Appropriate Practices</article-title>. <source>Canadian Psychology/Psychologie Canadienne</source> <volume>49</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacNaughton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Considering Culture in Research Based Interventions to Support Early Literacy</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Handbook of Early Literacy Research, Vol. 2</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Mapping Literacy Practices in Early Childhood Services</source>, <publisher-loc>Sydney, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New South Wales Department of Education and Training and New South Wales Department of Community Services</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>One-Way Traffic? Connections between Literacy Practices at Home and in the Nursery</article-title>. <source>British Educational Research Journal</source> <volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aikman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Indigenous Education: Addressing Current Issues and Developments</article-title>. <source>Comparative Education</source> <volume>39</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michell</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vizina</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Augustus</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Learning Indigenous Science from Place: Research Study Examining Indigenous-Based Science Perspectives in Saskatchewan First Nations and Metis Community Contexts</source>, <publisher-loc>Saskatoon, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Saskatchewan</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Singwauk's Vision: A History of the Native Residential Schools</source>, <publisher-loc>Toronto, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milloy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>A National Crime: The Canadian Government and the Residential School System, 1879 to 1986</source>, <publisher-loc>Winnipeg, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Manitoba Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Ministry of Education</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Nga haeta matauranga: The Annual Report on Maori Education 2001/08</source>, <publisher-loc>Wellington, New Zealand</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ministry of Education</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakata</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Indigenous Knowledge, the Library and Information Service Sector, and Protocols</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Nakata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Langton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Australian Indigenous Knowledge and Libraries</source>, <publisher-loc>Kingston, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Australian Academic and Research Libraries</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The Knowledge Gap: Implications for Early Education</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Handbook of Early Literacy Research</source> <volume>Vol. 2</volume>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><collab>New London Group</collab> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>A Pedagogy of Multiliteracies: Designing Social Futures</article-title>. <source>Harvard Educational Review</source> <volume>66</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noll</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Experiencing Literacy in and out of School: Case Studies of Two American Indian Youths</article-title>. <source>Journal of Literacy Research</source> <volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orellana</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>D'warte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Recognizing Different Kinds of “head starts”</article-title>. <source>Educational Researcher</source> <volume>39</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Sullivan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Goosney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Get Ready, Get Set, Get Going: Learning to Read in Northern Canada</source>, <publisher-loc>Thunder Bay, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Centre of Excellence for Children and Adolescents with Special Needs</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pahl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Children's Text-Making at Home: Transforming Meaning across Modes</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Jewitt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Multimodal Literacy</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Peter Lang</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prinsloo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2005</year>) <article-title>‘Down, up and around’: Setting Children up as Readers and Writers in South African Classrooms</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kendrick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Smythe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Portraits of Literacy across Families, Communities and Schools: Intersections and Tensions</source>, <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prochner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>History of Early Childhood Education in Canada, Australia and New Zealand</source>, <publisher-loc>Vancouver, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UBC Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell-Gates</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Stories, Coupons, and the “TV Guide”: Relationships between Home Literacy Experiences and Emergent Literacy Knowledge</article-title>. <source>Reading Research Quarterly</source> <volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>406</fpage>–<lpage>428</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell-Gates</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Emergent Literacy is Emergent Knowledge of Written, not Oral, Language</article-title>. <source>New Directions for Child and Adolescent Development</source> <volume>2001</volume>(<issue>92</issue>): <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riggs</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Field-Based Education and Indigenous Knowledge: Essential Components of Geoscience Education for Native American Communities</article-title>. <source>Science Education</source> <volume>89</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>296</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurgens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Burchinal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The Role of Home Literacy Practices in Preschool Children's Emergent Literacy Skills</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language &amp; Hearing Research</source> <volume>48</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>345</fpage>–<lpage>359</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Cultural Literacy in the World of Pueblo Children</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Volk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Many Pathways to Literacy: Young Children Learning with Siblings, Grandparents, Peers and Communities</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge Falmer</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Royal Commission on Aboriginal Peoples</collab> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Report of the Royal Commission on Aboriginal Peoples</source>, <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Canada Communications Group</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senechal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouellette</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodney</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The Misunderstood Giant: On the Predictive Role of Early Vocabulary to Future Reading</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kickinson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Handbook or Early Literacy Research, Vol. 2</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siegal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>“Radical” Pedagogy Requires “Conservative” Epistemology</article-title>. <source>Journal of Philosophy of Education</source> <volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr68-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Clancy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Enhancing Opportunities for Australian Aboriginal Literacy Learners in Early Childhood Settings</article-title>. <source>Childhood Education</source> <volume>81</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>342</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr69-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Maori Education: Revolution and Transformative Action</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Native Education</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr70-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Deocolonizing Methodologies: Research and Indigenous Peoples</source>, <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Zed Books</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr71-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Preventing Reading Difficulties in Young Children</source>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academy Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr72-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabors</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Language Development in the Preschool Years</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabors</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Beginning Literacy with Language: Young Children Learning at Home and School</source>, <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brookes</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr73-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Statistics Canada</collab> (<year>2003</year>) <source>International Adult Literacy Survey</source>, <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Statistics Canada</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr74-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sulzby</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Teale</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Emergent Literacy</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamil</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosenthal</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Handbook on Reading Research</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Longman</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr75-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorsey-Gaines</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <source>Growing up Literate: Learning from Inner-City Families</source>, <publisher-loc>Portsmouth, NH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Heinemann</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr76-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Timmons</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Keefe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>MacGillivary</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>A Family Literacy Program for the Mi'kmaq Community in Atlantic Canada: Final Report</source>, <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Literacy Secretariat</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr77-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trafzer</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sisquoc</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Boarding School Blues: Revisiting American Indian Educational Experiences</source>, <publisher-loc>Lincoln, NE</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Nebraska Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr78-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valdes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Con Respeto: Bridging Distances between Culturally Diverse Families and Schools</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Teachers College Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr79-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriquez de France</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Historical Look at Early Childhood Education in the Light of the Importance of the Treaty of Waitangi and the Maori Self-Determination Movement</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Native Education</source> <volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr80-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitehouse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Colvin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Reading Families: Deficit Discourse and Family Literacy</article-title>. <source>Theory into Practice</source> <volume>40</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>212</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr81-1468798411417378"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitehurst</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lonigan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Emergent Literacy: Development from Prereaders to Readers</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Handbook of Early Literacy Research</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>