<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppij</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part J: Journal of Engineering Tribology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1350-6501</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-305X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1350650112439659</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1350650112439659</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Study on the influence of critical shear stress on wall slip of spiral oil wedge journal bearing</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Li-Li</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Chang-Hou</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1350650112439659"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>Pei-Qi</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Shu-Jiang</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1350650112439659">School of Mechanical Engineering, Shandong University, People’s Republic of China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1350650112439659">Chang-Hou Lu, School of Mechanical Engineering, Shandong University, Jinan, People’s Republic of China. Email: <email>luchh@sdu.edu.cn</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>226</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>362</fpage>
<lpage>376</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>With the application of sleeve bearing in high speed, super-high speed and narrow-gap conditions, and the emergence of non-metallic bearing materials, the conventional no-slip boundary condition can be broken down. Critical shear stress is a main parameter in the numerical computation of wall slip. The four modified Reynolds equations for the two-dimensional spiral oil wedge sleeve bearing is established based on the critical shear stress model, in which the circumferential and axial wall slip of the sleeve and axial surface are considered. The shear stress angle is used to compute the circumferential and axial shear stress component and slip velocity. The results show the special structure of spiral oil wedge and the increase of eccentricity ratio make slip more difficult to occur. With the decrease of initial limiting shear stress, pressure, carrying capacity and friction drag decrease. Wall slip has an effect on the oil film rupture position, positive pressure area, and pressure peak. Wall slip occurs first in the large shear stress, the small clearance, and the envelop zone. The slip position and area influence each other in the sleeve and axial surface.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>High speed</kwd>
<kwd>spiral oil wedge</kwd>
<kwd>wall slip</kwd>
<kwd>critical shear stress</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1350650112439659" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Hybrid journal bearing has been widely applied to high speed and precise spindle systems, due to the advantage of high load capacity, excellent keeping, and stability. The classical Reynolds equation assumes that the liquid molecules adjacent to the solid are stationary relative to the solid, which states that fluid at a solid surface has no relative velocity to it. With the use of sleeve bearings in high speed, ultra-high speed and the narrow-gap conditions, the application of non-metallic material bearing and the emergence of special lubricants, wall slip is a common phenomenon in lubrication. Recently, researchers have observed the occurrence of slip by theory and experiment. Choo et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1350650112439659">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1350650112439659">2</xref></sup> tested the friction coefficient with hydrophobic and hydrophilic surfaces and revealed that the lubricant slipped against the hydrophobic surface by a reduction in friction, but the slip did not occur against the hydrophilic surface. Their results have proved that hexadecane can show apparent slip against sapphire surfaces with critical shear stress of 30 Pa and slip length of 4 µm. Watanabe et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1350650112439659">3</xref></sup> learned the drag drop of tap water and an aqueous solution of glycerin flowing in pipes with highly water-repellent walls, the slip velocity that measured using a hot-film anemometer was directly proportional to the shear stress, sliding coefficient for fluids was a constant value, and the slip length of tap water flowing in a pipe was about 0.25–0.92 mm. Recently, it has been demonstrated that slip occurred on mica and glass surfaces, and the degree of slip was found to increase with surface roughness.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1350650112439659">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1350650112439659">5</xref></sup> Cho et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1350650112439659">6</xref></sup> examined the slip behavior for 13 categories of polar and non-polar liquids at alkylsilane-coated solid surfaces using the colloidal probe atomic force microscope technique. The results found that the slip length was not influenced by the contact angle and viscosity for polar liquids, but the slip length decreased with the decrease of contact angle for non-polar liquid. Craig et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1350650112439659">7</xref></sup> Du et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1350650112439659">8</xref></sup> and Ellis and Hayward<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1350650112439659">9</xref></sup> demonstrated that the slip degree of aqueous solutions of sucrose, hydrophilic liquids, and water at the gold surfaces was different, and the slip length was measured. For hexadecane flowing on a lyophobic smooth surface, slip lengths of the order of 400 nm were obtained by Pit R et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1350650112439659">10</xref></sup> Zhu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1350650112439659">11</xref></sup> implied that partial slip occurred when shear stress (shear rate) exceeded a critical level, slip occurred for deionized water on octadecyltriethoxysilane-coated partially wetting surfaces.</p>
<p>The critical shear stress model that proposes originally in the rheological behavior study of elastohydrodynamic lubrication problem<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1350650112439659">12</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1350650112439659">14</xref></sup> is introduced to describe the boundary slip, and it assumes that wall slip occurs when shear stress exceeds the limiting shear stress at the solid–liquid interface. Kaneta et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1350650112439659">15</xref></sup> implied that wall slip and wall shear strength were closely related, and the liquid molecules will slip along the surface when the interfacial shear stress reached the critical shear stress. Salant and Fortier<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1350650112439659">16</xref></sup> assumed that fluid slip occurred when a critical shear stress was exceeded, the resulting slip velocity was proportional to the difference between the shear stress and the critical value. The results showed that the slip region was the same as the effect of a recess, which reduced the resistance to flow. Spikes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1350650112439659">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1350650112439659">18</xref></sup> implied that fluid slip occurred when shear stress exceeded the limiting shear stress, and carrying capacity, friction drag of finite and infinite length slider bearing considering the wall slip were computed. Based on the limiting shear stress model and the corresponding finite element parametric quadratic programming method, Ma et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1350650112439659">19</xref></sup> studied the influence of wall slip on the hydrodynamic lubrication performance of a two-dimensional (2D) journal bearing. Reference has given the detailed numerical analyses on the boundary slip and hydrodynamics for different gap flows and revealed some new physical phenomena and rules. Especially, it was found that a heterogeneous boundary slip improved the hydrodynamic effects. Jin et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1350650112439659">20</xref></sup> proved the possibility of boundary slip between oil and surface of polymer of low surface energy by comparative experiments and implied that boundary slip occurred when shear stress up to a critical value. The results showed that the slip effect increased with the increase of shear stress and the decrease of field pressure. Spikes and Granick<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1350650112439659">21</xref></sup> and Fatu Aurelian et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1350650112439659">22</xref></sup> implied that wall slip occurred when shear stress exceeded a critical level and the slip length was a constant value. The influence of wall slip over the load carrying capacity and power loss in hydrodynamic fluid bearings were studied. Comparing with the textured bearings, wall slip conditions leaded to better power loss improvements and higher carrying capacity. To study the boundary slippage effect on squeeze film, Guo and Wong<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1350650112439659">23</xref></sup> presented that the pressure gradient can be discontinuous at the border of the slip and no-slip regions and the critical shear stress significantly affected the squeeze behavior.</p>
<p>From the numerical point of view, there are two slip models: the slip length model states that shear stress varies in proportion to the slip velocity, and the critical shear stress model states shear stress varies with local pressure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1350650112439659">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1350650112439659">18</xref></sup> Although many literatures prove the existence of slip, but few measure the specific critical shear stress. Based on the slip length model <inline-formula id="ilm1-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math1-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the critical shear stress of hexadecane at lyophobic surfaces was 5 kPa, and the critical shear stress of deionized water on octadecyltriethoxysilane-coated partially wetting surfaces was 0.1 Pa.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1350650112439659">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1350650112439659">18</xref></sup> Ma et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1350650112439659">19</xref></sup> demonstrated that the critical shear stress was 0.3 kPa for aqueous solutions of sucrose flowing on a 15.1 nm thickness of gold film coated the sphere and flat walls, the critical shear stress was 6 Pa for tetradecane to which 0.2% of hexadecylamine was added flowing on the mica wall. The critical shear stress of oil at EMP journal bearing surfaces was 1.12694 kPa, which was obtained by Jin et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1350650112439659">20</xref></sup> So the study on the influence of critical shear stress on wall slip is very necessary.</p>
<p>Most slip analysis is based on 1D circumferential direction slip, but the wall slip analysis of 2D and complex flow is seldom. The values of critical shear stress are also different if work environment, friction materials, and lubricants are different. In this article, spiral oil wedge hybrid sleeve bearing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1350650112439659">Figure 1</xref>) is studied, its outstanding features of the bearing are as follows: three arc oil recesses on whole circumference are titled and the bearing has oil feed holes and oil return holes at both ends of each recess. So the different structures of this new bearing make its static and dynamic characteristics and slip properties different from conventional bearings. By means of the finite differential methods, the influence of critical shear stress on slip characteristics of 2D journal bearing considering the circumferential and axial wall slip is studied.
<fig id="fig1-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>The structural diagram of spiral oil wedge hydrodynamic bearing.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1350650112439659"><title>The 2D hydrodynamic model with slip</title>
<sec id="sec3-1350650112439659"><title>Velocity boundary conditions</title>
<p>Wall slip occurs when shear stress exceeds the critical shear stress at the solid–liquid interface. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1350650112439659">Figure 2</xref> illustrates that the flow of liquid can be regarded as an infinite number of very thin liquid layer and the internal friction of the liquid can be expressed using the shear stress that is caused by relative sliding of the liquid layer. Wall slip occurs when shear stress of sleeve surface exceeds the critical shear stress at the solid–liquid interface, then shear stress and slip velocities in the <italic>x-</italic> and <italic>z</italic>-directions can be expressed as <italic>τ<sub>yx</sub></italic> = <italic>τ</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>x</sub></italic>, <italic>u</italic> = <italic>u</italic><sub>sb</sub> and <italic>τ<sub>y</sub><sub>z</sub></italic> = <italic>τ</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>z</sub></italic>, <italic>w</italic> = <italic>w</italic><sub>sb</sub>, respectively<sub>.</sub><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1350650112439659">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1350650112439659">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1350650112439659">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1350650112439659">19</xref></sup> In addition to sleeve interface, shear stress <italic>τ<sub>yx</sub></italic> in the <italic>x</italic>-direction can be expressed as <inline-formula id="ilm2-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math2-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>yx</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, shear stress <italic>τ<sub>yz</sub></italic> in the <italic>z</italic>-direction can be expressed as <inline-formula id="ilm3-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math3-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>yz</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for the rest of the thin layer interface.
<fig id="fig2-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Shear stress.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1350650112439659">Figure 3</xref> shows that the liquid molecules adjacent to the solid are not stationary relative to the solid when wall slip occurs on sleeve surface, while they move with speeds <italic>u</italic><sub>sb</sub> and <italic>w</italic><sub>sb</sub> in the <italic>x-</italic> and <italic>z</italic>-directions, respectively. Considering the slip region on the stationary surface of the journal bearing, the boundary conditions for the steady flow at the axis surface (<italic>y</italic> = 0) and the sleeve surface (<italic>y</italic> = <italic>h</italic>) are as follows<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1350650112439659">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1350650112439659">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1350650112439659">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1350650112439659">19</xref></sup>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1350650112439659"><label>(1)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>z</italic> is the axial coordinate, <italic>x</italic> the circumferential coordinate, <italic>y</italic> the radial coordinate, <italic>u</italic><sub>sb</sub>, <italic>w</italic><sub>sb</sub> the slip velocity of sleeve surface in <italic>x-</italic> and <italic>z</italic>-directions, <italic>τ</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>x</sub></italic>, <italic>τ</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>z</sub></italic> the critical shear stress of sleeve surface in the <italic>x-</italic> and <italic>z</italic>-directions, <italic>τ<sub>yx</sub></italic>, <italic>τ<sub>yz</sub></italic> the shear stress in the <italic>x-</italic> and <italic>z</italic>-directions, and <italic>β</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>x</sub></italic>, <italic>β</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>z</sub></italic> the sign function.
<fig id="fig3-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Slip velocity at the sleeve surface.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig3.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1350650112439659"><title>Generalized Reynolds equation considering wall slip</title>
<p>It is assumed that the flow is incompressible, constant viscosity, laminar, and the lubricant inertia effect is small. Substituting equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1350650112439659">1</xref>) into simplified Navier–Stokes equation, the velocity equation can be expressed as follows
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-1350650112439659"><label>(2)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>A similar expression can be derived for the <italic>z</italic>-direction
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-1350650112439659"><label>(3)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>The volumetric flow rate through per unit width on film cross-section as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-1350650112439659"><label>(4)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>The shear stress equation in the <italic>x</italic>-direction is equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1350650112439659">2</xref>) differential
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-1350650112439659"><label>(5)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>A similar expression can be derived for the <italic>z</italic>-direction
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-1350650112439659"><label>(6)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>Substituting equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-1350650112439659">4</xref>) into continuity of flow, the Reynolds equation is then modified to account for the wall slip of sleeve surface as follows
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-1350650112439659"><label>(7)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>For equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula7-1350650112439659">7</xref>), the satisfied condition is as follows<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1350650112439659">14</xref></sup>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula18-1350650112439659"><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq18.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>A similar expression can be derived for the Reynolds equation considering the wall slip of axis surface
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8-1350650112439659"><label>(8)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq8.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>For equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8-1350650112439659">8</xref>), the satisfied condition is as follows τ<sub>b</sub> &lt; τ<sub>cdl</sub>, <inline-formula id="ilm4-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math4-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&lt;τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cul</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1350650112439659">Figure 4</xref> shows that wall slip occurs on sleeve surface and axis surface, then velocities of sleeve surface in the <italic>x-</italic> and <italic>z</italic>-directions are <italic>u</italic><sub>sb</sub> and <italic>w</italic><sub>sb</sub>, respectively; velocities of axis surface in the <italic>x-</italic> and in the <italic>z</italic>-directions are <italic>u</italic><sub>a</sub> + <italic>u</italic><sub>sa</sub> and <italic>w</italic><sub>sa</sub>, respectively. The Reynolds equation is then modified to account for the wall slip of sleeve and axis surfaces as follows
<disp-formula id="disp-formula9-1350650112439659"><label>(9)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq9.tif"/></disp-formula>
<fig id="fig4-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Slip velocity at the sleeve and axis surface.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig4.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>For equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula9-1350650112439659">9</xref>), the satisfied condition is as follows τ<sub>a</sub> &lt; τ<sub>cdl</sub>, <inline-formula id="ilm5-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math5-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&gt;τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cul</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p>
<p>When wall slip cannot be considered, the Reynolds equation can be expressed as follows
<disp-formula id="disp-formula10-1350650112439659"><label>(10)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq10.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>For equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula10-1350650112439659">10</xref>), the satisfied condition is as follows τ<sub>a</sub> &lt; τ<sub>cdl</sub>, <inline-formula id="ilm6-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math6-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&lt;τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cul</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p>
<p>where <italic>p</italic> is the oil film pressure, <italic>η</italic> the fluid dynamic viscosity, <italic>h</italic> the oil film thickness, <italic>u</italic><sub>a</sub> the journal speed, <italic>u</italic><sub>sa</sub>, <italic>w</italic><sub>sa</sub> the slip velocity in the <italic>x-</italic> and <italic>z</italic>-directions at axial surface, <italic>β</italic><sub>cdl</sub><italic><sub>x</sub></italic>, <italic>β</italic><sub>cdl</sub><italic><sub>z</sub></italic> the sign function, <italic>τ</italic><sub>a</sub> the shear stress at axial surface, <italic>τ</italic><sub>b</sub> the shear stress at sleeve surface, <italic>τ</italic><sub>cu</sub>, <italic>τ</italic><sub>cd</sub> the initial shear stress for slip at sleeve and axis surface, <italic>k</italic><sub>cu</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>cd</sub> the pressure constant, <inline-formula id="ilm7-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math7-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Rk</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,<inline-formula id="ilm8-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math8-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cd</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Rk</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cd</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,<inline-formula id="ilm9-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math9-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,<inline-formula id="ilm10-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math10-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cd</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the 0.17 based on the results of literatures,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1350650112439659">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1350650112439659">19</xref></sup> <italic>c</italic> the bearing clearance, <italic>R</italic> the bearing radius, <italic>τ</italic><sub>cdl</sub>, <italic>τ</italic><sub>cul</sub> the critical shear stress for slip at axial and sleeve surface.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1350650112439659"><title>Slip velocity</title>
<p>For equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula7-1350650112439659">7</xref>) to (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula9-1350650112439659">9</xref>), the slip velocity is an unknown term, it can be obtained by the following formula
<disp-formula id="disp-formula11-1350650112439659"><label>(11)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq11.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula12-1350650112439659"><label>(12)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq12.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>The similar expression can be derived for the slip velocity <italic>u</italic><sub>sa</sub> and <italic>w</italic><sub>sa</sub>. So equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula11-1350650112439659">11</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula12-1350650112439659">12</xref>) convert the solution of slip velocity into the solution of critical shear stress.</p>
<p>The resultant force of shear stress can be expressed as follows<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1350650112439659">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1350650112439659">19</xref></sup>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula13-1350650112439659"><label>(13)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq13.tif"/></disp-formula>
The critical shear stress can be expressed as follows
<disp-formula id="disp-formula14-1350650112439659"><label>(14)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq14.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1350650112439659">Figure 5</xref>(c) shows the shear stress angular <italic>ξ</italic><sub>cul</sub>, <italic>ξ</italic><sub>cdl</sub> considering the wall slip is the same as the angular reckoning without the wall slip, so wall slip do not affect relationship of the shear stress in <italic>x-</italic> and <italic>z-</italic>directions and the accuracy of the results. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1350650112439659">Figure 5</xref>(c), the critical shear stress component can be expressed as follows
<disp-formula id="disp-formula15-1350650112439659"><label>(15)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq15.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>τ</italic><sub>cdl</sub><italic><sub>x</sub></italic>, <italic>τ</italic><sub>cdl</sub><italic><sub>z</sub></italic> is the critical shear stress in the <italic>x-</italic> and <italic>z</italic>-directions for slip at axial surface, <italic>ξ</italic><sub>cul</sub>, <italic>ξ</italic><sub>cdl</sub> the shear stress angular at sleeve and axial surface.
<fig id="fig5-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Shear stress vector.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig5.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>In the 2D flow, both the magnitude and the direction of the slip velocity cannot be known in advance, which brings some difficulties in numerical calculation. Since the direction of slip velocity cannot be known in advance, the front of scalar <italic>u</italic><sub>sb,</sub> <italic>w</italic><sub>sb</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>sa</sub>, and <italic>w</italic><sub>sa</sub> multiplies the corresponding coefficient <italic>β</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>x</sub></italic>, <italic>β</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>z</sub></italic>, <italic>β</italic><sub>cdl</sub><italic><sub>x</sub></italic>, and <italic>β</italic><sub>cdl</sub><italic><sub>z</sub></italic> when the formula is derived. The regulation of positive sign for fluid shear stress is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1350650112439659">Figure 5</xref>(a), negative sign is in the opposite direction. If <italic>τ<sub>yx</sub></italic> and <italic>τ<sub>yz</sub></italic> are greater than 0, <italic>β</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>x</sub></italic> and <italic>β</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>z</sub></italic> are 1. If <italic>τ<sub>y</sub><sub>x</sub></italic>, <italic>τ<sub>y</sub><sub>z</sub></italic> is less than 0, <italic>β</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>x</sub></italic> and <italic>β</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>z</sub></italic> are −1.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1350650112439659"><title>Oil film thickness equation</title>
<p>Because the surface of the spiral oil wedge hybrid sleeve bearing consists of two parts, the common surface same as conventional bearing and the circular recess surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1350650112439659">Figure 1</xref>) caused by three oil recesses, the oil film thickness must be calculated, respectively.</p>
<p>Film thickness at the common cylinder surface is written as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula16-1350650112439659"><label>(16)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq16.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>Film thickness at the eccentric arc surface is written as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula17-1350650112439659"><label>(17)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-eq17.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>e</italic> is the eccentricity, <italic>α</italic> the position angle of the eccentric arc, <inline-formula id="ilm11-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math11-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ztg</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic>θ</italic> the attitude angle, <italic>R</italic><sub>1</sub> the radius of the arc surface, <italic>e</italic><sub>1</sub> the eccentricity of the eccentric arc, and <italic>φ</italic> the angular coordinate, <italic>φ</italic> = <italic>x</italic>/<italic>R</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-1350650112439659"><title>Boundary condition</title>
<p>At the regions of inlet holes 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1350650112439659">Figure 1</xref>), the pressure is taken to be equal to the feed lubricant pressure <italic>p</italic><sub>in</sub>; at both ends of the bearing and the region of outlet holes 1, the pressure is taken to be equal to the ambient pressure that is defined as being zero; at the point of film rupture, the pressure boundary condition accords with the Reynolds boundary condition, that is <italic>p</italic> = 0,<inline-formula id="ilm12-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math12-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1350650112439659"><title>Numerical calculation verification</title>
<p>In the same state and calculation conditions of Ma et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1350650112439659">19</xref></sup> it is proved whether the numerical results of 2D spiral oil wedge bearing based on critical shear stress model are right. The primary parameters of the bearing are given as follows:<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1350650112439659">19</xref></sup> width-diameter ratio <italic>L</italic>/<italic>D</italic> is 1, eccentricity ratio <italic>ε</italic> is 0.8. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1350650112439659">Figure 6</xref>, the method results are in general consistent with the reference results except that there are some errors in small dimensionless initial critical shear stress <inline-formula id="ilm13-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math13-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Globally, error is in the permissible range, which validates that this calculation method and the results are correct.
<fig id="fig6-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>The carrying capacity and friction for literature and theoretical computation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig6.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1350650112439659"><title>Numerical solution and results</title>
<p>The finite difference method, the iteration method with over relaxation and Reynolds boundary conditions are used in solving corresponding Reynolds equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula7-1350650112439659">7</xref>) to (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula10-1350650112439659">10</xref>) that is determined according to four slip states of the grid points as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1350650112439659">Figure 7</xref>, pressure distribution, carrying capacity, and flow velocity of the spiral oil wedge bearing are computed considering the wall slip. In numerical calculation, the shear stress is related with the pressure and varies over the whole bearing calculation region, so it can not be extracted from equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula7-1350650112439659">7</xref>) to (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula10-1350650112439659">10</xref>). However, solution of generalized Reynolds equation is quite straightforward using successive over-relaxation iteration method, which is consistent with references.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1350650112439659">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1350650112439659">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1350650112439659">17</xref></sup> The bearing within whole circumference was expanded to a plane and divided into many rectangle grids. Because, the spiral oil wedge sleeve bearing is not symmetrical in axial direction, the grids must cover the whole bearing width. With these grids, the first and second-order partial derivatives can be expressed using second order, centered finite differences around each grid.
<fig id="fig7-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Flow chart.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig7.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The primary parameters of the bearing are given as follows: rotational speed <italic>n</italic> is 10,000 r/min, bearing diameter <italic>D</italic> is 100 mm, bearing clearance <italic>c</italic> is 0.02 mm, width-diameter ratio <italic>L</italic>/<italic>D</italic> is 1.1, depth of the arc recess <italic>h</italic><sub>0</sub> is 0.12 mm, inlet oil pressure <italic>p</italic><sub>in</sub> is 1 MPa, oil viscosity <italic>η</italic> is 0.02 Pa·s, oil density <italic>ρ</italic> is 876.5 kg/m<sup>3</sup>. Using the equation <inline-formula id="ilm14-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math14-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for journal bearing, the Reynolds number <italic>R</italic><sub>e</sub> is about 45.87 that is much lower than the critical Reynolds number 1000 for the transition from laminar flow to turbulent flow. So the calculation is in the condition of laminar flow.</p>
<sec id="sec10-1350650112439659"><title>The influence of the bearing structure on wall slip</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1350650112439659">Figure 8</xref> shows the graphical comparison of the threshold of dimensionless initial critical shear stress for spiral oil wedge bearing and conventional bearing at spiral angle <italic>β</italic> = 0.6 rad and different eccentricities. With the decrease of initial critical shear stress, bearing surfaces begin to slip and carrying capacity begins to decrease (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-1350650112439659">Figure 10</xref>) in the threshold of dimensionless initial critical shear stress. For example, the threshold of dimensionless initial critical shear stress <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> for spiral oil wedge bearing is 2.4, but the threshold for conventional bearing is 2 at <italic>ε</italic> = 0.4, <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> = <italic>T</italic><sub>cd</sub>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1350650112439659">Figure 8</xref> indicates that the threshold of the critical initial shear stress increases with the eccentricity increasing; at the same eccentricity, the threshold of critical shear stress for spiral oil wedge sliding bearing is higher compared with the general bearing. So the special spiral oil wedge structure and the increase of eccentricity make slip more difficult to occur, which leads to a better understanding for wall slip.
<fig id="fig8-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>The initial shear stress for spiral oil wedge and conventional journal bearing.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig8.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig9-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Pressure for different initial shear stresses: (a) <italic>λ</italic> = 0.2; (b) <italic>λ</italic> = 0.5; and (c) <italic>λ</italic> = 0.7.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig9.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig10-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Carrying capacity for different initial shear stresses.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig10.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-1350650112439659"><title>The influence of initial critical shear stress on bearing performance</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-1350650112439659">Figure 9</xref> is the distributions of dimensionless circumference pressure in the case of <italic>T</italic><sub>cd</sub> = 0.84, <italic>ε</italic> = 0.6, different dimensionless initial shear stresses of sleeve surface and dimensionless axial coordinates <italic>λ</italic> = 0.2, <italic>λ</italic> = 0.5, and <italic>λ</italic> = 0.8. The figures show that: sleeve surface begins to slip when initial shear stresses <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> of sleeve surface is 2.75, and the oil film pressure decreases obviously with the initial shear stress decreasing; the oil film pressure considering wall slip (<italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> ≤ 2.75) is lower compared with reckoning without wall slip (<italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> &gt; 2.75); the wall slip has effect on the oil film rupture location, for example, the oil film rupture location in the case of <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> = 0.38 is in advance compared with reckoning without wall slip. So the cavitation area at <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> = 0.38 increases, which affects the lubrication quality of bearing. The area of the positive pressure zone decreases and the position of pressure peak migrates along the <italic>x</italic>-negative direction when wall slip is considered, which is consistent with the decrease of carrying capacity considering wall slip.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-1350650112439659">Figures 10</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-1350650112439659">11</xref> are the influence of initial critical shear stress on carrying capacity and friction drag in the case of <italic>ε</italic> = 0.6 and five cases. The five cases are as following: case a, slip is only allowed to occur at the sleeve surface; case b, slip is only allowed to occur at the axis surface; case c, slip can occur at both surfaces and the initial shear stress is equal; case d, the initial shear stress of the axis surface is only fixed at 0.25, but the initial shear stress of the sleeve surface is discussed; case e, the initial shear stress of the axis surface is only fixed at 0.84, but the initial shear stress of the sleeve surface is discussed:
<list id="list1-1350650112439659" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>With the initial shear stress decreasing, slip begins to occur at sleeve surface and axis surface, and carrying capacity and friction drag decrease. According to the equation <inline-formula id="ilm15-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math15-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the increase of journal speed and the decrease of the radial clearance can lead to the decrease of <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> when the initial shear stress is fixed at constant (the surface property remains unchanged), so wall slip can occur drastically in the high speed and ultra high speed conditions.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>In general, the carrying capacity and friction drag are maximum in case a, and the carrying capacity and friction drag are minimum in case d, so the value of carrying capacity and friction drag is too large when slip is considered only on the surface of the sleeve surface or axial surface. Slip should be considered at the both surfaces in numerical calculation of bearing performance; 3. Sleeve surface begins to slip at <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> = <italic>T</italic><sub>cd</sub> = 3.18 in case c, when curves c and a coincide with each other. Axial surface begins to slip at <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> = <italic>T</italic><sub>cd</sub> = 3.1, when curves c and b coincide with each other. Curves c and e coincide with each other at <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> = <italic>T</italic><sub>cd</sub> = 0.84, curves c and d coincide with each other at <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> = <italic>T</italic><sub>cd</sub> = 0.25.</p></list-item>
</list>
<fig id="fig11-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>Friction for different initial shear stresses.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig11.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-1350650112439659"><title>Slip starting and expanding of different initial critical shear stresses</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-1350650112439659">Figures 12</xref>(a), <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-1350650112439659">13</xref>(a) and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-1350650112439659">14</xref>(a) show the graphical comparisons of <italic>T</italic><sub>b</sub>, <italic>T</italic><sub>a</sub>, <italic>T</italic><sub>cul</sub>, <italic>T</italic><sub>cdl</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>sb</sub>, <italic>w</italic><sub>sb</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>sa</sub>, and <italic>w</italic><sub>sa</sub> at <italic>ε</italic> = 0.6, <italic>β</italic> = 0.6, <italic>λ</italic> = 0.5, <italic>T</italic><sub>cd</sub> = 0.84 and <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> varies at 3, 0.38, and 0. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-1350650112439659">Figure 12</xref>(a) indicates <italic>T</italic><sub>b</sub> &lt; <italic>T</italic><sub>cul</sub> at <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> = 3, so wall slip can not occur (<italic>w</italic><sub>sb</sub> = <italic>u</italic><sub>sb</sub> = 0) at the sleeve surface in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-1350650112439659">Figure 12</xref>(b). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-1350650112439659">Figure 12</xref>(c) shows that wall slip occurs at narrow gap, circumference slip velocity is opposite to rotation direction and the axial slip velocity is obvious at larger gap.
<fig id="fig12-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 12.</label><caption><p><italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> = 3, <italic>T</italic><sub>cd</sub> = 0.84: (a) shear stress and slip velocity; (b) slip velocity at the sleeve surface; and (c) slip velocity at the axis surface and oil film thickness contours.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig12.tif"/></fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-1350650112439659">Figure 13</xref>(a) shows that <italic>T</italic><sub>cul</sub> = <italic>T</italic><sub>b</sub> in the area 1, 2, 3, at <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> = 0.38, when the sleeve surface can slip and axial slip velocity is smaller compared with the circumferential slip velocity. So in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-1350650112439659">Figure 13</xref>(b), the slip velocity is about circumferential, wall slip occurs in the envelop zone, the end slip velocity is outward, the end leakage increases, carrying capacity decreases and temperature rise decreases. The axial surface can slip in the area of 4 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-1350650112439659">Figure 13</xref>(a), when <italic>T</italic><sub>cdl</sub> = <italic>T</italic><sub>a</sub> and <italic>u</italic><sub>sa</sub> &gt; <italic>w</italic><sub>sa</sub>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-1350650112439659">Figure 13</xref>(c) shows that the axial slip velocity is more obvious in the start slip position, the slip velocity is about circumferential in the other position, wall slip occurs in the small clearance position and the slip area of both ends is larger. The slip velocity direction changes into the axial rotation direction, the emergence of wall slip is beneficial to the increase of carrying capacity in this sense, but the general capacity is reduced considering the large area slip of sleeve surface.
<fig id="fig13-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 13.</label><caption><p><italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> = 0.38, <italic>T</italic><sub>cd</sub> = 0.84: (a) shear stress and slip velocity; (b) slip velocity at the sleeve surface; and (c) slip velocity at the axis surface and oil film thickness contours.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig13.tif"/></fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-1350650112439659">Figure 14</xref>(a) shows that the oil wedge can slip at <italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> = 0 and the direction of <italic>u</italic><sub>sb</sub> and <italic>w</italic><sub>sb</sub> changes with different positions. And in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-1350650112439659">Figure 14</xref>(b), the general slip velocity is about <italic>x</italic>-direction in the envelop surface, the overall slip velocity of oil wedge flows to the outlet position, so the flow rate of outlet increases and the pressure decreases. Compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-1350650112439659">Figure 14</xref>(c) with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-1350650112439659">Figure 13</xref>(c), and it will be seen that the slip position of axis surface migrates along <italic>x</italic>-direction and the general slip zone changes little. In general, the bearing and shaft material has an impact on the initial shear stress, and the slip position and area influence each other in the sleeve and axial surface.
<fig id="fig14-1350650112439659" position="float"><label>Figure 14.</label><caption><p><italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub> = 0, <italic>T</italic><sub>cd</sub> = 0.84: (a) shear stress and slip velocity; (b) slip velocity at the sleeve surface; and (c) slip velocity at the axis surface and oil film thickness contours.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1350650112439659-fig14.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-1350650112439659" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>
<list id="list2-1350650112439659" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The special structure of spiral oil wedge and the increase of eccentricity make slip more difficult to occur.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>With the decrease of initial limiting shear stress, pressure, carrying capacity and friction drag decrease; the oil film rupture position is affected, the area of the positive pressure zone decreases and the position of pressure peak migrates along the <italic>x</italic>-negative direction when wall slip is considered; the increase of journal speed and the decrease of the radial clearance can lead to the decrease of initial shear stress, so wall slip can occur drastically in the high speed and ultra high speed conditions; the value of carrying capacity and friction drag is too large when slip is considered only on the surface of the sleeve surface or axial surface, so slip should be considered at the both surfaces in numerical calculation of bearing performance.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Wall slip occurs first in the large shear stresses, the small clearance and the envelop zone; the axial slip velocity is more obvious in some positions, so the circumferential and axial wall slip is considered in numerical calculation; the slip position and area influence each other in the sleeve and axial surface.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec14-1350650112439659"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This study was supported by a grant from the Major State Basic Research Development Program of China (973 Program) (grant no. 2009CB724404) and National Nature Science Foundation of China (grant no. 51075242).</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1350650112439659"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Spikes</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratoi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Friction reduction in low-load hydrodynamic lubrication with a hydrophobic surface</article-title>. <source>Tribol Int</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1350650112439659"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Glovnea</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A low friction bearing based on liquid slip at the wall</article-title>. <source>J Tribol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>620</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1350650112439659"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Udagawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Udagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Drag reduction of Newtonian fluid in a circular pipe with a highly water-repellent wall</article-title>. <source>J Fluid Mech</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>381</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1350650112439659"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonaccurso</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Butt</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hydrodynamic force measurements: boundary slip of water on hydrophilic surfaces and electrokinetic effects</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev Lett</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>88</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>076103/1</fpage>–<lpage>076103/4</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1350650112439659"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonaccurso</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Butt</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>VSJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Surface roughness and hydrodynamic boundary slip of a Newtonian fluid in a completely wetting system</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev Lett</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>90</volume>(<issue>14</issue>): <fpage>144501/1</fpage>–<lpage>144501/4</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1350650112439659"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J-HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieutord</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dipole-dependent slip of Newtonian liquids at smooth solid hydrophobic surfaces</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev Lett</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>92</volume>(<issue>16</issue>): <fpage>166102/1</fpage>–<lpage>166102/4</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1350650112439659"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>VSJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DRM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Shear-dependent boundary slip in an aqueous Newtonian liquid</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev Lett</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>87</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>054504</fpage>–<lpage>054504</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1350650112439659"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Goubaidoulline</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Johannsmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of laterally heterogeneous slip on the resonance properties of quartz crystals immersed in liquids</article-title>. <source>Langmuir</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>10617</fpage>–<lpage>10624</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1350650112439659"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interfacial slip on a transverse-shear mode acoustic wave device</article-title>. <source>J Appl Phys</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>94</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>7856</fpage>–<lpage>7867</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1350650112439659"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pit</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hervet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Direct evidence of slip in hexadecane: solid interfaces</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev Lett</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>980</fpage>–<lpage>983</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1350650112439659"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Granick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rate-dependent slip of Newtonian liquid at smooth surfaces</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev Lett</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>87</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>096105/1</fpage>–<lpage>096105/4</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1350650112439659"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamrock</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Non-Newtonian fluid model incorporated into elastohydrodynamic lubrication of rectangular contacts</article-title>. <source>J Tribol</source> <year>1984</year>; <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1350650112439659"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Study on influence of the boundary slip of visco-plastic lubrication on the lubrication properties</article-title>. <source>Acta Mech Sin</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>31</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>745</fpage>–<lpage>752</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1350650112439659"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An analysis of elastohydrodynamic lubrication with limiting shear stress: part I-theory and solutions</article-title>. <source>Tribol Trans</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1350650112439659"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaneta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kameishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Observation of wall slip in elastohydrodynamic lubrication</article-title>. <source>J Tribol</source> <year>1990</year>; <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1350650112439659"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salant</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortier</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Numerical analysis of a slider bearing with a heterogeneous slip/no slip surface</article-title>. <source>Tribol Trans</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>328</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1350650112439659"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spikes</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The half-wetted bearing. Part 1: extended Reynolds equation</article-title>. <source>Proc IMechE Part J: J Engineering Tribology</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>217</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1350650112439659"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spikes</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The half-wetted bearing. Part 2: potential application in low load contacts</article-title>. <source>Proc IMechE Part J: J Engineering Tribology</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>217</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1350650112439659"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Wall slip and hydrodynamics of two-dimensional journal bearing</article-title>. <source>Tribol Int</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1056</fpage>–<lpage>1066</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1350650112439659"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Experiment and simulations on lubrication performance of EMP journal bearing</article-title>. <source>J Shanghai Univ (English Ed)</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1350650112439659"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spikes</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Granick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Equation for slip of simple liquids at smooth solid surfaces</article-title>. <source>Langmuir</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>19</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>5065</fpage>–<lpage>5071</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1350650112439659"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aurelian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Wall slip effects in (elasto) hydrodynamic journal bearings</article-title>. <source>Tribol Int</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>44</volume>(<issue>7–8</issue>): <fpage>868</fpage>–<lpage>877</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1350650112439659"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Full and partial boundary slippage effect on squeeze film bearings</article-title>. <source>Tribol Int</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>997</fpage>–<lpage>1004</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-1350650112439659"><title>Appendix</title>
<sec id="sec15-1350650112439659"><title/>
<sec id="sec16-1350650112439659"><title>Notation</title><p><def-list id="duolist3-1350650112439659">
<def-item><term><italic>c</italic></term><def><p>bearing radial clearance</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>D</italic></term><def><p>bearing diameter</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>e</italic></term><def><p>eccentricity</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>e</italic><sub>1</sub></term><def><p>eccentricity of the eccentric arc</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>F</italic></term><def><p>friction drag, <inline-formula id="ilm16-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math16-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>cF</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mi>RL</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>h</italic></term><def><p>oil film thickness</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>k</italic><sub>cu</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>cd</sub></term><def><p>pressure constant at sleeve and axial surface</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>L</italic></term><def><p>width of bearing</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>n</italic></term><def><p>rotating speed</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>p</italic></term><def><p>oil film pressure, <inline-formula id="ilm17-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math17-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>p</italic><sub>in</sub></term><def><p>oil supply pressure</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>R</italic></term><def><p>bearing radius</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>R</italic><sub>1</sub></term><def><p>radius of the arc surface</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>T</italic><sub>cu</sub>, <italic>T</italic><sub>cd</sub></term><def><p>dimensionless initial shear stresses of sleeve, axis surface</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>u</italic></term><def><p>circumferential velocity of oil film</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>u</italic><sub>a</sub></term><def><p>journal speed</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>u</italic><sub>sa</sub>, <italic>u</italic><sub>sb</sub></term><def><p>slip velocity in the <italic>x</italic>-direction at axial and sleeve surface</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>w</italic></term><def><p>axial velocity of oil film</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>w</italic><sub>sa</sub>, <italic>w</italic><sub>sb</sub></term><def><p>slip velocity in the <italic>z</italic>-direction at axial, sleeve surface</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>W</italic></term><def><p>carrying capacity, <inline-formula id="ilm18-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math18-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>x</italic></term><def><p>circumferential coordinate</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>y</italic></term><def><p>radial coordinate</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>z</italic></term><def><p>axial coordinate</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>α</italic></term><def><p>position angle of the eccentric arc, <inline-formula id="ilm19-1350650112439659"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math19-1350650112439659"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ztg</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>β</italic></term><def><p>spiral angle</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>β</italic><sub>cdl</sub><italic><sub>x</sub></italic>, <italic>β</italic><sub>cdl</sub><italic><sub>z</sub></italic></term><def><p>sign of critical shear stress in the <italic>x</italic>- and <italic>z</italic>-directions for slip at axial surface</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>β</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>x</sub></italic>, <italic>β</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>z</sub></italic></term><def><p>sign of critical shear stress in the <italic>x</italic>- and <italic>z</italic>-directions for slip at sleeve surface</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>ε</italic></term><def><p>eccentricity ratio</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>η</italic></term><def><p>fluid viscosity</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>θ</italic></term><def><p>attitude angle</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>λ</italic></term><def><p>dimensionless axial coordinate</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>ξ</italic><sub>cul</sub>, <italic>ξ</italic><sub>cdl</sub></term><def><p>shear stress angular at sleeve, axial surface</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>τ</italic></term><def><p>resultant force of shear stress</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>τ</italic><sub>a</sub>, <italic>τ</italic><sub>b</sub></term><def><p>shear stress at axial, bearing surface</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>τ</italic><sub>cdl</sub><italic><sub>x</sub></italic>, <italic>τ</italic><sub>cdl</sub><italic><sub>z</sub></italic></term><def><p>critical shear stress in the <italic>x-</italic> and <italic>z</italic>-directions for slip at axial surface</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>τ</italic><sub>cu</sub>, <italic>τ</italic><sub>cd</sub></term><def><p>initial critical shear stress for slip at sleeve, axial surface</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>τ</italic><sub>cul</sub>, <italic>τ</italic><sub>cdl</sub></term><def><p>critical shear stress for slip at sleeve, axial surface</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>τ</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>x</sub></italic>, <italic>τ</italic><sub>cul</sub><italic><sub>z</sub></italic></term><def><p>critical shear stress in the <italic>x-</italic> and <italic>z</italic>-directions for slip at sleeve surface</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>τ<sub>yx</sub></italic>, <italic>τ<sub>yz</sub></italic></term><def><p>shear stress in the <italic>x-</italic> and <italic>z-</italic>directions</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>φ</italic></term><def><p>angular coordinate</p></def></def-item></def-list></p>
</sec>
</sec></app></app-group>
</back>
</article>