<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="letter" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JHS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjhs</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Hand Surg Eur Vol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Hand Surgery (European Volume)</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1753-1934</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2043-6289</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753193412449579</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1753193412449579</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Short report letters</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Iatrogenic injury to the ulnar nerve during primary repair of medial ulnar collateral ligament in complex elbow fracture dislocations</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Mughal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>H.</given-names><suffix>II</suffix></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1753193412449579">Indiana Hand to Shoulder Center, Indiana, USA. Email: <email>philster_1@me.com</email></aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>38</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>686</fpage>
<lpage>687</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The British Society for Surgery of the Hand</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Dear Sir,</p>
<p>We present two cases of primary ulnar collateral ligament repair in association with the treatment of complex fracture/dislocations of the elbow that were referred to the Indiana Hand to Shoulder centre post-operatively with evidence of complete ulnar nerve palsy. They were clinically examined, investigated and subsequently explored operatively. The findings are reported here.</p>
<p><italic>Case 1.</italic> A 43-year-old right-hand dominant actuary sustained a closed postero-lateral dislocation of her left elbow following a fall while roller skating. This involved a proximal Monteggia variant comminuted fracture of the olecranon, radial head fracture and an associated coronoid fracture. At the primary hospital, she had had a midline posterior approach to fix the olecranon. A Kocher approach was used to explore the radial head (small fragment removed/no fixation) and repair an attenuated lateral collateral ligament. An additional medial approach was used to explore the coronoid fracture, which could not be fixed and the partially torn ulnar collateral ligament (UCL) was repaired with Ethibond (braided polyester) sutures. The ulnar nerve was visualized but not formally explored. She was referred two weeks later for a persistent dislocation and complete ulnar nerve palsy with clawing. During operative exploration, an ethibond suture was found encircling and damaging a segment of the ulnar nerve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1753193412449579">Figure 1</xref>) with no conduction across the segment. Resection of the injured segment and neurorrhaphy was required. At most recent review, 5 months post-op, she still has persistent clawing and a positive Froment’s sign and poor recovery of function.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1753193412449579" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Suture around ulnar nerve.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412449579-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p><italic>Case 2.</italic> A 50-year-old sales executive fell down a flight of stairs sustaining an open fracture dislocation of her right elbow with radial head and coronoid fractures. At the primary hospital, the radial head and coronoid fractures were treated with open reduction and internal fixation. The lateral and UCLs were repaired and the ulnar nerve was again not formally examined. The elbow was stable. The patient was referred a month later with ulnar-sided numbness and motor weakness, and chronic regional pain syndrome. At operative review, a suture was found ligating one-third of the ulnar nerve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1753193412449579">Figure 2</xref>), resulting in a complete palsy that did not recover with release of the suture and anterior transposition of the nerve. This then required an anterior interosseous nerve-to-ulnar motor transfer. At most recent review, she has slow recovery of intrinsic function.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1753193412449579" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Suture through ulnar nerve.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412449579-fig2.tif"/></fig>
<p>With evolution of surgical techniques, improved outcomes have been reported with decreased handling of the ulnar nerve during reconstruction of the UCL of the elbow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193412449579">Langer et al., 2006</xref>). This, however, differs from the acute complex elbow fracture dislocations where direct repair or reconstruction of the UCL may be required to restore elbow stability. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412449579">Shin and Ring, 2007</xref>)</p>
<p>The ulnar nerve is predisposed to iatrogenic injury by its close proximity to the distal aspect of the UCL and medial coronoid, by traction, by implant insertion or, as in this case, by suture entrapment. Both patients incurred severe functional deficits.</p>
<p>A clear knowledge of the anatomy, careful identification and protection of the ulnar nerve distal to the cubital tunnel during the procedure is required to prevent this debilitating iatrogenic injury. The surgeon must carefully document ulnar nerve function at every patient visit.</p>
<p>We thus recommend identifying the nerve and performing an in-situ decompression to permit full visualization and protecting the nerve throughout when attempting exploration and repair of the UCL in the unstable elbow following trauma.</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interests</label>
<p>None declared.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1753193412449579">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fadale</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hulstyn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evolution of the treatment options of ulnar collateral ligament injuries of the elbow</article-title>. <source>Br J Sports Med</source>. <year>2006</year>, <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>499</fpage>–<lpage>506</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1753193412449579">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The ulnar nerve in elbow trauma</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2007</year>, <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>1108</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>