<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MCR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmcr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Med Care Res Rev</journal-id>
<journal-title>Medical Care Research and Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1077-5587</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6801</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1077558712468490</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1077558712468490</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Empirical Research</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Racial and Ethnic Disparities in the Surgical Treatment of Acute Myocardial Infarction</article-title>
<subtitle>The Role of Hospital and Physician Effects</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Daifeng</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1077558712468490">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Mellor</surname><given-names>Jennifer M.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1077558712468490">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Jankowitz</surname><given-names>Eytan</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1077558712468490">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1077558712468490"><label>1</label>College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, VA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1077558712468490"><label>2</label>Edgeworth Economics, Washington, DC, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1077558712468490">Jennifer M. Mellor, Department of Economics and Schroeder Center for Health Policy, College of William and Mary, PO Box 8795, Williamsburg, VA 23187-8785, USA. Email: <email>jmmell@wm.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>70</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>287</fpage>
<lpage>309</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>18</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>25</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Many studies document disparities between Blacks and Whites in the treatment of acute myocardial infarction on controlling for patient demographic factors and comorbid conditions. Other studies provide evidence of disparities between Hispanics and Whites in cardiac care. Such disparities may be explained by differences in the hospitals where minority and nonminority patients obtain treatment and by differences in the traits of physicians who treat minority and nonminority patients. We used 1997-2005 Florida hospital inpatient discharge data to estimate models of cardiac catheterization, percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty, and coronary artery bypass grafting in Medicare fee-for-service patients 65 years and older. Controlling for hospital fixed effects does not explain Black–White disparities in cardiac treatment but largely explains Hispanic–White disparities. Controlling for physician fixed effects accounts for some extent of the racial disparities in treatment and entirely explains the ethnic disparities in treatment.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>race and ethnicity</kwd>
<kwd>disparities</kwd>
<kwd>cardiac care</kwd>
<kwd>acute myocardial infarction</kwd>
<kwd>hospital</kwd>
<kwd>physician</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1077558712468490" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Racial and ethnic disparities, often defined as utilization differences that exist on controlling for patient age, gender, access-related factors, and health conditions, have been identified in dozens of studies on the treatment of heart disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1077558712468490">Ford &amp; Cooper, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1077558712468490">Geiger, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1077558712468490">Kressin &amp; Petersen, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1077558712468490">Lillie-Blanton, Rushing, Ruiz, Mayberry, &amp; Boone, 2002</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1077558712468490">1</xref></sup> Recent studies continue to report racial disparities in diagnostic tests and treatments for heart disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1077558712468490">Basu &amp; Mobley, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1077558712468490">Bertoni et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1077558712468490">Brown, Ross, Lopez, Thornton, &amp; Kiros, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1077558712468490">Cram, Bayman, Popescu, &amp; Vaughan-Sarrazin, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1077558712468490">Jha, Fisher, Li, Orav, &amp; Epstein, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1077558712468490">Vaccarino et al., 2005</xref>). Additional recent studies also document significant Hispanic–White disparities in heart disease treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1077558712468490">Bertoni et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1077558712468490">Cram et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1077558712468490">Guzman et al., 2012</xref>). These findings are of particular importance since minorities are at greater risk than nonminorities for cardiovascular disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1077558712468490">Heron et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1077558712468490">Mensah &amp; Brown, 2007</xref>), the leading cause of death in the United States.</p>
<p>Racial and ethnic disparities in heart disease treatment may be explained in part by differences in the hospitals where minority and nonminority patients obtain treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1077558712468490">Ehlenbach et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1077558712468490">Groeneveld, Kruse, Chen, &amp; Asch, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1077558712468490">Liu et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1077558712468490">Popescu, Nallamothu, Vaughan-Sarrazin, &amp; Cram, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1077558712468490">Weeks &amp; Fisher, 2007</xref>). Black patients are more likely than Whites to be treated in hospitals that are of lower quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1077558712468490">Popescu, Cram, &amp; Vaughan-Sarrazin, 2011</xref>), provide lower volume (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1077558712468490">Liu et al., 2006</xref>), and have less technologically advanced facilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1077558712468490">Cram, Bayman, Popescu, &amp; Vaughan-Sarrazin, 2010</xref>). High-proportion Hispanic hospitals are more likely to be for-profit, have lower nurse-to-patient ratios, and have lower quality measures than low-proportion hospitals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1077558712468490">Jha, Orav, Zheng, &amp; Epstein, 2008</xref>). If hospital traits such as quality, volume, staffing levels, and facility availability are associated with the propensity to use certain treatments for heart disease, then accounting for these traits in models of procedure use could help to explain the estimated Black–White or Hispanic–White gaps in surgical utilization.</p>
<p>Likewise, physician traits may explain some of the observed racial and ethnic disparities in cardiac care utilization. Among patients admitted to hospitals with acute myocardial infarction (AMI), Black patients are less likely to be treated by attending physicians who are cardiologists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1077558712468490">Funk, Ostfeld, Chang, &amp; Lee, 2002</xref>) than are White patients; AMI patients treated by cardiologists are more likely to undergo invasive coronary procedures, such as angiography (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1077558712468490">Funk et al., 2002</xref>) and revascularization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1077558712468490">Ayanian, Guadagnoli, McNeil, &amp; Cleary, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1077558712468490">Chen, Radford, Wang, &amp; Krumholz, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1077558712468490">Jollis et al., 1996</xref>). Physician practice style, quality, and other traits may also affect the tendency to employ certain cardiac treatments, and these traits may differ in physicians who treat minority patients compared with those who treat Whites. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1077558712468490">Mukamel, Murthy, and Weimer (2000)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1077558712468490">Castellanos et al. (2011)</xref> found that minority patients who undergo bypass surgery are more likely than Whites to be treated by surgeons with higher risk-adjusted mortality rates, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1077558712468490">Bach, Pham, Schrag, Tate, and Hargraves (2004)</xref> found that Blacks are more likely than Whites to be seen by physicians who report difficulties providing their patients with access to high-quality specialists and diagnostic imaging. Additional studies show that yet other physician traits are also related to treatment decisions: patients treated by male physicians are more likely to undergo catheterization after AMI than those treated by female physicians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1077558712468490">Rathore et al., 2001</xref>) and board-certified physicians have higher rates of clinical guideline recommended therapies following AMI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1077558712468490">Chen, Rathore, Wang, Radford, &amp; Krumholz, 2006</xref>). If Black or Hispanic patients are seen more often by physicians who are less likely to employ invasive procedures in the treatment of AMI, then adjusting for physician traits could help to explain observed racial and ethnic disparities in treatment.</p>
<sec id="section2-1077558712468490">
<title>New Contribution</title>
<p>This study makes two contributions. First, we build on prior studies by investigating whether the addition of hospital fixed effects to regression models of invasive treatments for heart disease can explain racial and ethnic disparities in treatment. Hospital fixed effects control for all persistent hospital-specific traits, including those that are unobserved by the researcher, and have been employed by multiple studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1077558712468490">Barnato et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1077558712468490">Barnato, Lucas, Staiger, Wennberg, &amp; Chandra, 2005</xref>). We contribute to the literature by examining a longer and more recent time period (1997 to 2005) than prior work and by examining both Black–White <italic>and</italic> Hispanic–White differences in the treatment of AMI. Ethnic disparities in cardiac care have received relatively less attention than racial disparities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1077558712468490">Lillie-Blanton et al., 2002</xref>). More attention is beneficial since Hispanics represent the largest minority group and one of the fastest growing populations in the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1077558712468490">U.S. Census Bureau, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Second, we also estimate models that include fixed effects for attending physicians, those physicians with the primary and final responsibility for the patient’s medical care and treatment. Since patients choose their physicians and physicians can to some extent select which patients they treat, this mutual selection process may lead to nonrandom matches between attending physicians and patients. Furthermore, this process may result in matches where minority patients are treated by physicians with different traits on average than the physicians treating nonminority patients. We add physician fixed effects to treatment models to examine whether the control of fixed physician traits helps to explain racial and ethnic disparities in treatment. Physician fixed effects are able to control for all fixed physician traits, such as specialty, gender, board certification, and practice style, including those that are unobserved to the researcher. To the best of our knowledge, our study is the first to incorporate physician fixed effects in a model that estimates the associations between Black race and Hispanic ethnicity and the likelihood of undergoing invasive cardiac treatments. We build on a small number of studies that include physician fixed effects in models of other surgical procedures (such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1077558712468490">Katz et al., 2010</xref> on mastectomy) and in models of process and quality of care (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1077558712468490">Brookhart et al., 2006</xref> on osteoporosis screening, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1077558712468490">Sequist et al., 2008</xref> on diabetes care, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1077558712468490">Huesch, 2011</xref> on coronary artery bypass grafting [CABG] mortality).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1077558712468490">
<title>Conceptual Framework</title>
<p>The conceptual framework underlying our analysis is that decisions to use surgical procedures in the treatment of individuals with cardiovascular disease are affected by patient-specific factors, physician-specific factors, and health care system factors, as described in a model presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1077558712468490">Kressin and Petersen (2001)</xref>. Patient factors include age, sex, race, and ethnicity, and socioeconomic status (SES). Factors influencing the physician include patient clinical characteristics as well as physician specialty, training, and certification. Finally, factors associated with the health care system might include hospital ownership (nonprofit, for-profit, government), teaching status, quality, volume, and facility availability, and broader measures of the local health system, such as practice patterns or physicians per capita in the community.</p>
<p>Our study examines two main research questions. First, we examine how the inclusion of hospital fixed effects affects both Black–White and Hispanic–White disparities in models of three surgical treatments of AMI. We hypothesize that including hospital fixed effects will explain some extent of racial and ethnic disparities, given the evidence that Black and Hispanic patients are more likely than Whites to be treated in hospitals marked by lower quality, lower volume, and less technologically advanced facilities. Our second research question examines the effect of including attending physician fixed effects in models that estimate racial and ethnic disparities in the surgical treatment of AMI. If minority patients are more likely than Whites to be seen by physicians who are less likely to employ invasive procedures in the treatment of AMI, then this could explain some of the observed Black–White or Hispanic–White disparities in cardiac care.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1077558712468490" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section5-1077558712468490">
<title>Data</title>
<p>We used data on hospital inpatient discharges from 1997 to 2005 from the Florida Agency for Health Care Administration. To construct the sample and study variables, we used information from the discharge record on the patient’s race/ethnicity, age, gender, as well as the principal payer, admission source, the principal diagnosis, and up to nine secondary diagnoses, and the principal procedure and up to nine other procedures. We used the patient’s county of residence to merge each discharge record to county-level measures of SES, such as county-level household median income and poverty rates, which serve as proxies for patient SES since personal income data are not available. County-level socioeconomic data were obtained from the U.S. Census Bureau.</p>
<p>We linked the discharge records to other sources of data to construct health care system factors. We used the hospital identification code to merge various hospital-level traits, such as ownership type, number of acute beds, rural location, and teaching status, to each discharge record. For each year in the sample, hospital traits were obtained from annual issues of the <italic>Florida Hospital Beds and Services List</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1077558712468490">Agency for Health Care Administration, various years</xref>). We also merged county-level measures of physician supply constructed from counts of active nonfederal physicians in patient care from the Area Resource File and population data from the Census Bureau.</p>
<p>We constructed controls for factors that influence physician decision making. Since patient clinical characteristics affect physician decisions about treatment, we constructed indicators of several comorbidities from the discharge record, as described below. We also employed information on the attending physician’s identification code to model physician fixed effects. A particular strength of the Florida discharge data is that the attending physician license is reported on each discharge record in a consistent manner over time from 1997 to 2005.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1077558712468490">2</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1077558712468490">
<title>Study Sample</title>
<p>We restricted our focus to Black, White, and Hispanic patients with a principal diagnosis of an initial episode of care for AMI. The determination of initial episode of care for AMI was based on the presence of International Classification of Diseases, Ninth Revision, Clinical Modification (ICD-9) codes 410.x1 in the principal diagnosis field. We selected only those patients admitted to the hospital from the emergency room since patients admitted through physician referrals or hospital transfers may differ in the propensity to undergo surgical treatment or in the determination of hospitals/ physicians. About three quarters of initial AMI discharges are admitted through the emergency room.</p>
<p>We also restricted the sample to patients aged 65 years and older at the time of admission and patients for whom the principal payer was traditional fee-for-service Medicare. These restrictions yielded a more homogenous set of patients in which to examine the role of hospital and physician fixed effects. By examining patients with the same type of insurance coverage, we sidestep the effects of different provider payment policies on treatment decisions and by selecting only age-eligible Medicare patients, we sidestep the effects of younger age and/or disability on treatment decisions in Medicare patients younger than than 65 years. A small number of patients who resided in a state other than Florida were excluded, and we excluded less than 0.15% of AMI discharges where the attending physician was a resident, unlicensed medical doctor in training, or physician assistant as opposed to a medical doctor or osteopathic physician. Finally, to avoid the effects of outlier physicians with low numbers of AMI admissions, we excluded cases where the attending physician was listed on fewer than 30 total discharges over the sample period.</p>
<p>The restrictions have the following effects on sample size. We started with a total of 444,840 AMI discharges between 1997 and 2005, where the patient was a Florida resident and the attending physician was a licensed medical doctor or osteopathic physician. Restricting the sample to Whites, Blacks, and Hispanics resulted in a loss of 15,717 observations. Of the remaining 429,123 patients, 73.6% were admitted through the emergency room, and for just more than half (52%) of these, Medicare fee-for-service was the principal payer. Of the 165,045 observations, we dropped less than 7% who were younger than age 65 years. The restriction that attending physicians be associated with a minimum of 30 discharges of any patient type or admission source reduced the sample by 33,557 observations and missing data on covariates resulted in a modest loss of 160 observations. We also excluded 457 observations from the small number of hospitals (three) that experienced changes in their rural status.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1077558712468490">3</xref></sup> The final sample consisted of 119,386 observations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1077558712468490">
<title>Study Variables</title>
<p>We defined dependent variables for three surgical procedures used in the treatment of AMI based on the presence of specific ICD-9 procedure codes in any of the 10 procedure code fields on the discharge record (the principal procedure and up to nine other procedures). Cardiac catheterization is identified by ICD-9 procedure codes 37.21-37.23 and 88.52-88.58; percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty (PTCA) is identified with codes 36.01-36.05, and CABG is identified with codes 36.10-36.19.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1077558712468490">4</xref></sup> The key explanatory variables of interest, the patient’s race and ethnicity, are identified from a combined race/ethnicity field included on the discharge record. An indicator for Black race equals 1 if the patient is non-Hispanic Black, and 0 otherwise, and an indicator for Hispanic ethnicity equals 1 if the patient is either White Hispanic or Black Hispanic, and 0 otherwise. The omitted category is non-Hispanic White.</p>
<p>We employed various control variables in our multivariate analysis. Patient sex was measured with an indicator variable for female, and we defined a continuous measure of age in years. To account for nonlinearities in the relationship between age and procedure use, we also included age squared. We controlled for comorbid conditions using a set of indicator variables defined from diagnosis codes reported in the nine secondary diagnoses fields on the discharge record. These include indicators for a prior myocardial infraction, peripheral vascular disease, dementia, chronic pulmonary disease, rheumatologic disease, mild liver disease, moderate or severe liver disease, diabetes, chronic diabetes, hemiplegia or paraplegia, and renal disease. These controls were defined using the ICD-9 diagnosis codes for each condition as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1077558712468490">Deyo, Cherkin, and Ciol (1992)</xref>. We proxied for patient SES with dummies for quartiles in the distribution of annual real median household income in the patient’s county of residence and with indicator variables representing the fraction of persons in poverty by county and year. Observable hospital traits included measures of hospital ownership, teaching status, rural status (defined by the state legislature), and bed size. We also included the ratio of active nonfederal physicians in patient care to 1,000 residents by county-year. Finally, we included indicator variables for the year of discharge to account for trends in procedure use.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1077558712468490">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>We used Stata/SE software Version 12.0 to analyze the data. We compared means of dependent and explanatory variables across samples of Whites and Blacks and Whites and Hispanics using <italic>t</italic> tests (for continuous variables) and chi-squared tests (for binary indicators). In our multivariate analysis, we first estimated the linear probability model illustrated by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1077558712468490">Equation (1)</xref> for each of our three dependent variables:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1077558712468490">
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-1077558712468490">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>Black</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>Hispanic</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>H</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>ε</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-1077558712468490" xlink:href="10.1177_1077558712468490-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula></p>
<p>The dependent variable <italic>y<sub>icht</sub></italic> indicates whether individual <italic>i</italic> living in county <italic>c</italic> treated in hospital <italic>h</italic> in year <italic>t</italic> received a particular surgical procedure used in the treatment of AMI. We estimated the equation for three separate dependent variables representing cardiac catheterization, PTCA, and CABG. <italic>Black</italic> and <italic>Hispanic</italic> are binary variables indicating whether individual <italic>i</italic> is Black or Hispanic; <italic>X<sub>it</sub></italic> is a set of patient characteristics, including age, gender, and 11 indicator variables for whether individual <italic>i</italic> has any of the comorbid conditions shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1077558712468490">Table 1</xref>. Hospital characteristics <italic>H<sub>ht</sub></italic> include time-invariant rural status and time-varying teaching status, ownership status (nonprofit and for-profit indicators with publicly owned being the omitted category), and the number of acute care beds.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1077558712468490">5</xref></sup> County characteristics <italic>C<sub>ct</sub></italic> include indicators for quartiles in the distribution of real median household income (the omitted category is the lowest quartile), and indicators for whether the percent of households at or below 100% of the federal poverty line is from 10% to less than 12.5%, from 12.5% to less than 15%, or 15% or more (the omitted category is less than 10%), and the number of physicians per 1,000 county residents.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1077558712468490">6</xref></sup> Model (1) also controls for year fixed effects (λ<sub><italic>t</italic></sub>), which are dummy variables absorbing all time-varying factors that are common to all AMI patients in Florida in a given year, such as potential nationwide changes in practice style and technology advancement. Finally, ϵ<sub><italic>it</italic></sub> is the mean-zero idiosyncratic error term. β<sub>1</sub> and β<sub>2</sub> are our coefficients of interest.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1077558712468490">7</xref></sup></p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1077558712468490" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Descriptive Statistics for Full Sample and by Patient Race/Ethnicity.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1077558712468490" xlink:href="10.1177_1077558712468490-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="center">Full Sample (<italic>n</italic> = 119,386)</th>
<th align="center">Whites (<italic>n</italic> = 103,899)</th>
<th align="center">Blacks (<italic>n</italic> = 5,556)</th>
<th align="center">Hispanics (n = 9,931)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Treatment</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cardiac catheterization</td>
<td>0.399</td>
<td>0.411</td>
<td>0.362<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.295<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PTCA</td>
<td>0.165</td>
<td>0.169</td>
<td>0.142<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.133<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> CABG</td>
<td>0.061</td>
<td>0.064</td>
<td>0.045<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.045<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Patient characteristics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black (non-Hispanic)</td>
<td>0.047</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>0.083</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age</td>
<td>78.83</td>
<td>78.93</td>
<td>76.84<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>78.96</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(7.91)</td>
<td>(7.85)</td>
<td>(8.11)</td>
<td>(8.22)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>0.46</td>
<td>0.59<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Previous myocardial infarction</td>
<td>0.081</td>
<td>0.084</td>
<td>0.058<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.059<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Peripheral vascular disease</td>
<td>0.073</td>
<td>0.075</td>
<td>0.081<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">*</xref></td>
<td>0.053<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Dementia</td>
<td>0.016</td>
<td>0.016</td>
<td>0.019<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">*</xref></td>
<td>0.013<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Chronic pulmonary disease</td>
<td>0.257</td>
<td>0.258</td>
<td>0.227<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.269<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rheumatologic disease</td>
<td>0.017</td>
<td>0.018</td>
<td>0.011<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.012<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mild liver disease</td>
<td>0.004</td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>0.006<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Moderate/severe liver disease</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.002</td>
<td>0.003<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Diabetes</td>
<td>0.239</td>
<td>0.224</td>
<td>0.329<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.344<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Chronic diabetes</td>
<td>0.034</td>
<td>0.032</td>
<td>0.061<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.037<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hemiplegia or paraplegia</td>
<td>0.005</td>
<td>0.005</td>
<td>0.010<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Renal failure</td>
<td>0.021</td>
<td>0.021</td>
<td>0.026<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.023<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Hospital characteristics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Teaching status</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>0.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Number of acute beds</td>
<td>305.35</td>
<td>298.47</td>
<td>341.49<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>357.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(176.10)</td>
<td>(173.46)</td>
<td>(195.42)</td>
<td>(181.02)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rural designation</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>0.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Nonprofit</td>
<td>0.50</td>
<td>0.51</td>
<td>0.48<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> For profit</td>
<td>0.41</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>0.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Public hospital</td>
<td>0.09</td>
<td>0.09</td>
<td>0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">County characteristics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Household income second quartile</td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td>0.26</td>
<td>0.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Household income third quartile</td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td>0.26</td>
<td>0.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Household income fourth quartile</td>
<td>0.24</td>
<td>0.26</td>
<td>0.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Poverty rate from 10.0% to 12.5%</td>
<td>0.43</td>
<td>0.46</td>
<td>0.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Poverty rate from 12.5% to 15.0%</td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>0.20</td>
<td>0.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Poverty rate 15% or more</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>0.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.69<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Physicians per 1,000 population</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>1.94</td>
<td>2.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>2.59<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.70)</td>
<td>(0.68)</td>
<td>(0.93)</td>
<td>(0.54)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1077558712468490">
<p>Note: PTCA = percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty; CABG = coronary artery bypass grafting. Standard deviations of continuous variables are reported in parentheses. Statistically significant differences in means between Blacks and Whites and Hispanics and Whites are indicated by *** for .01 level, ** for .05 level, and * for .10 level. For continuous variables we report results from <italic>t</italic> tests; for binary variables we report results from chi-square tests.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>We then estimated a set of linear hospital fixed effects models as shown by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1077558712468490">Equation (2)</xref>:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula2-1077558712468490">
<mml:math display="block" id="math2-1077558712468490">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>Black</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>Hispanic</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>H</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>δ</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>ε</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-1077558712468490" xlink:href="10.1177_1077558712468490-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula></p>
<p>The hospital fixed effects are represented by α<sub><italic>h</italic></sub>. These models also control for all the patient characteristics (<italic>X<sub>it</sub></italic>), county characteristics (<italic>C<sub>ct</sub></italic>), and year fixed effects (λ<sub><italic>t</italic></sub>), as defined in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1077558712468490">Equation (1)</xref>. We also include a set of hospital characteristics (<italic>H<sub>ht</sub></italic>), as in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1077558712468490">Equation (1)</xref>, but unlike <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1077558712468490">Equation (1)</xref> we do not include the rural indicator in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1077558712468490">Equation (2)</xref>. This is because the hospital fixed effects α<sub><italic>h</italic></sub> absorb <italic>all</italic> time-invariant hospital characteristics, including rural status. Examples of other time-invariant traits picked up by the hospital fixed effects include hospital management style and efficacy, the nurse-to-patient ratio, the number and/or quality of competitors in the local market, the conditions of devices and equipment, the capital-to-labor ratio, and, in particular, hospitals’ potential preferences for types of patients or the possibility that a given hospital is used by patients with certain characteristics that are relevant to the outcomes of interest.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1077558712468490">8</xref></sup> The power of hospital fixed effects is that they control for all time-invariant hospital factors affecting all patients admitted to a given hospital, including factors unobservable to the researcher. The coefficients of interest in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-1077558712468490">Equation (2)</xref> are δ<sub>1</sub> and δ<sub>2</sub>; as in the baseline models, we report the marginal effects of the explanatory variables.</p>
<p>We next estimated a similar set of linear fixed effects models without the hospital fixed effects but with physician fixed effects, as shown by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-1077558712468490">Equation (3)</xref>:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula3-1077558712468490">
<mml:math display="block" id="math3-1077558712468490">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>Black</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>Hispanic</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>H</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>∗</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>ε</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-1077558712468490" xlink:href="10.1177_1077558712468490-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula></p>
<p>The subscript p indicates physician, and the physician fixed effects are represented by θ<sub><italic>p</italic></sub>. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-1077558712468490">Equation (3)</xref> controls for the full set of patient, hospital, and county characteristics, as well as year fixed effects. In addition, it controls for both the time-invariant and time-variant hospital characteristics (rural status, as well as ownership, teaching status, and bed size) because physicians treat patients in multiple hospitals (in other words, physicians are not nested within a hospital). Importantly, the physician fixed effects capture all time-invariant physician characteristics that are unobservable to the researcher and similarly affect the treatment of all the patients seen by a given physician. These include, for example, the physicians’ race, gender, educational background, experience, skill, and the physicians’ potential preference for certain types of patients or the possibility that physicians may be preferred by patients of certain characteristics. In this model, the coefficients of interest are α<sub>1</sub> and α<sub>2</sub>, and again, marginal effects are reported.</p>
<p>In all regressions, we adjusted the standard errors of the reported coefficients for the clustering of observations; we did so by hospital in the baseline and the hospital fixed effect models and by physician in the physician fixed effect models. Clustering adjusts for potential correlations in the error terms among patients treated in the same hospital or by the same doctor.</p>
<p>After estimating the three sets of models, we compared the marginal effects for Black race and Hispanic ethnicity obtained from the linear probability models without fixed effects to those obtained from the linear fixed effects models to ascertain whether control for the hospital or the attending physician can explain Black–White and Hispanic–White disparities in cardiac care utilization. Since our goal is to examine how the inclusion of hospital fixed effects or physician fixed effects changes the size of the marginal effects of race and ethnicity, linear probability models offer several conceptual and computational advantages over nonlinear models.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1077558712468490">9</xref></sup> Importantly, fixed effects logit models (also known as conditional logit models) do not allow researchers to obtain marginal effects because they do not estimate the group-specific intercepts that are necessary for calculating the marginal effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1077558712468490">Wooldridge, 2010</xref>, pp. 619-622).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1077558712468490">10</xref></sup></p>
<p>Finally, we examined the robustness of our findings to a number of variations in our empirical analysis. First, we estimated our models using alternate measures of two dependent variables since prior studies sometimes differ in their definition of cardiac catheterization and revascularization. We defined an alternate measure of cardiac catheterization that used codes 37.21-37.23 and excluded codes 88.52-88.58 (similar to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1077558712468490">Hall, DeFrances, Williams, Golosinskiy, &amp; Schwartzman, 2010</xref>), and we broadened the measure of PTCA to all types of PCI with the addition of codes 36.07, 36.09 and 00.66 (similar to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1077558712468490">Epstein, Polsky, Yang, Yang, &amp; Groeneveld, 2011</xref>). Second, we estimated our models using larger samples of patients admitted both though the emergency department and through other means and patients treated by physicians who treat any number of patients in the sample period. Third, we excluded large teaching hospitals (those with more than 300 beds) and residents of Miami-Dade county. Large teaching hospitals might differ from other hospitals in the assignment of attending physician. We excluded Miami-Dade since it accounts for a large share of Hispanic and Black residents in the state. Finally, we estimated our models on subsets of years in the study period (1997-1999 and 2003-2005).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1077558712468490" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section10-1077558712468490">
<title>Descriptive Statistics</title>
<p>As shown in the first three rows of <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1077558712468490">Table 1</xref>, the full sample consists of 103,899 Whites (87%), 5,556 Blacks (4.7%), and 9,931 Hispanics (8.3%). The unadjusted rates of all three surgical procedures show evidence of Black–White differences and Hispanic–White differences in cardiac catheterization, PTCA, and CABG. Across all years, rates of cardiac catheterization are 41.1% for Whites, 36.2% for Blacks, and 29.5% for Hispanics. Rates of PTCA are 16.9% for Whites, 14.2% for Blacks, and 13.3% for Hispanics, and rates of CABG are 6.1% for Whites, 4.5% for Blacks, and 4.5% for Hispanics. For all three procedures, the Black–White and Hispanic–White differences in unadjusted rates are statistically significant according to chi-squared tests. These differences exist in almost every year of the study period, although Black–White differences in cardiac catheterization and CABG and the Hispanic–White difference in CABG decrease over time. Utilization rates for the individual procedures generally increase over time.</p>
<p>The remaining rows in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1077558712468490">Table 1</xref> show significant differences in patient and hospital characteristics by race and ethnicity. For example, Black patients are on average slightly younger than White patients, and Black and Hispanic patients are more likely than Whites to be female. Black and Hispanic patients are less likely than Whites to have had a prior AMI listed among the other diagnoses on the discharge records, but they are more likely than Whites to have diabetes. Compared with Whites, Black and Hispanic patients are more likely to be treated in teaching hospitals, larger hospitals, and hospitals with a rural designation. Several racial and ethnic differences emerge in the ownership of the hospital where patients are seen. Black and Hispanic patients are less likely than Whites to be treated at nonprofit hospitals. Hispanics are more likely than Whites to be seen at for-profit hospitals and less likely than Whites to be seen at public hospitals, while Blacks are more likely than Whites to use public hospitals.</p>
<p>To illustrate the differences between the use of hospital fixed effects and physician fixed effects in our models, we report descriptive statistics on the numbers of hospitals and physicians in our sample. In the full estimation sample, a total of 202 unique hospitals and 3,955 unique physicians are represented; at the average hospital, there are 47 different physicians treating AMI patients. Thus, the hospital fixed effects capture the provider effect at a more aggregated level than do the physician fixed effects. Furthermore, while some physician fixed effects capture differences within the hospital (because multiple physicians may see patients in the same hospital), in most cases, the effects are common to patients treated at different hospitals by the same physician because physicians are not nested within hospitals. In our data set, two thirds (69%) of physicians treat patients at more than one hospital; the average physician treats patients at 2.4 hospitals and the number of hospitals per physician ranges from 1 to 14.</p>
<p>The distinctions between hospital and physician fixed effects apply to White, Black, and Hispanic subsamples of patients. White patients are treated at all 202 hospitals, while Black and Hispanic patients are treated at slightly fewer hospitals (190 and 173, respectively). In terms of physicians, White patients are treated by 3,859 physicians whereas Black and Hispanic patients are treated by 1,977 and 1,665 physicians, respectively. Most physicians (66%) treat patients from more than one racial or ethnic group. Among physicians who treat minority patients, almost all also treat nonminority patents: all but seven of the physicians who treat Black patients also treat Whites, and 96% of the physicians who treat Hispanic patients also treat Whites.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1077558712468490">11</xref></sup> As in the full sample, physicians are observed at multiple hospitals for all three groups of patients. About two thirds (65%) of physicians treating Whites, one fifth (20%) of physicians treating Blacks, and one third (33%) of physicians treating Hispanics are observed at more than one hospital in the data set.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1077558712468490">
<title>Regression Analysis</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1077558712468490">Table 2</xref> reports the results from estimating <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1077558712468490">Equation (1)</xref>, which specifies the association between Black race and Hispanic ethnicity and surgical procedure use while controlling for patient traits and observable hospital traits, but without controlling for hospital or physician fixed effects. These models serve as our baseline specification, and we refer to the estimated effects of race and ethnicity in this specification as disparities in treatment. We report marginal effects for all variables included in each model. The key findings from this set of regressions are threefold. First, Black–White disparities in all three surgical procedures persist on controlling for patient age, gender, and comorbidities, county-based proxies for SES, and observable hospital characteristics. Black race lowers the likelihood of undergoing cardiac catheterization by 8.5 percentage points and lowers the likelihood of revascularization by 2.7 percentage points (for CABG) to 6.6 percentage points (for PTCA), relative to White race. Second, Hispanic ethnicity similarly is associated with a significantly lower incidence of cardiac catheterization and PTCA compared with White race. Hispanics are 7.2 percentage points less likely to undergo PTCA and 10.5 percentage points less likely to undergo cardiac catheterization. The Hispanic–White disparity in CABG remains sizeable (1.4 percentage points relative to a mean of 6%), and the estimate is statistically significant at the 10% level. Third, we find that certain hospital traits have significant associations with procedure use. For example, patients treated at larger hospitals (those with more acute care beds) are more likely to undergo surgical treatment for AMI, and relative to patients treated at public hospitals, patients treated at for-profit or nonprofit hospitals are more likely to undergo catheterization or angioplasty.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1077558712468490" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Baseline Linear Probability Models of Surgical Treatment of AMI.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1077558712468490" xlink:href="10.1177_1077558712468490-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Explanatory Variables</th>
<th align="center">Cardiac Catheterization</th>
<th align="center">PTCA</th>
<th align="center">CABG</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Patient characteristics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black</td>
<td>−0.085<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.066<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.027<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.017)</td>
<td>(0.012)</td>
<td>(0.005)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>−0.105<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.072<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.014<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.037)</td>
<td>(0.023)</td>
<td>(0.008)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age</td>
<td>0.048<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.006)</td>
<td>(0.003)</td>
<td>(0.002)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age squared</td>
<td>−0.0004<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.00007<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.00004<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.00004)</td>
<td>(0.00002)</td>
<td>(0.00001)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td>−0.027<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.012<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.023<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td>(0.003)</td>
<td>(0.003)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Previous myocardial infarction</td>
<td>−0.021<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.013<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.017<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.006)</td>
<td>(0.003)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Peripheral vascular disease</td>
<td>−0.009</td>
<td>−0.017<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
<td>−0.008<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.007)</td>
<td>(0.004)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Dementia</td>
<td>−0.169<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.067<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.030<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.013)</td>
<td>(0.009)</td>
<td>(0.004)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Chronic pulmonary disease</td>
<td>−0.087<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.063<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.006)</td>
<td>(0.007)</td>
<td>(0.003)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rheumatologic disease</td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>−0.004</td>
<td>−0.016<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.011)</td>
<td>(0.009)</td>
<td>(0.006)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mild liver disease</td>
<td>−0.157<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.083<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.026<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.021)</td>
<td>(0.016)</td>
<td>(0.010)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Moderate/severe liver disease</td>
<td>−0.193<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.081<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.022</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.029)</td>
<td>(0.020)</td>
<td>(0.016)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Diabetes</td>
<td>−0.046<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.030<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.010<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.005)</td>
<td>(0.004)</td>
<td>(0.002)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Chronic diabetes</td>
<td>−0.117<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.075<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.024<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.010)</td>
<td>(0.009)</td>
<td>(0.005)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hemiplegia or paraplegia</td>
<td>−0.167<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.083<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.017)</td>
<td>(0.013)</td>
<td>(0.009)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Renal failure</td>
<td>−0.152<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.062<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.019<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.011)</td>
<td>(0.009)</td>
<td>(0.004)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Hospital characteristics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Teaching</td>
<td>0.005</td>
<td>0.023</td>
<td>0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.042)</td>
<td>(0.038)</td>
<td>(0.027)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Number of acute beds</td>
<td>0.0008<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.0006<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.0002<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.00007)</td>
<td>(0.00005)</td>
<td>(0.00003)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rural</td>
<td>−0.161<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.012</td>
<td>−0.008</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.038)</td>
<td>(0.025)</td>
<td>(0.013)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Nonprofit</td>
<td>0.104<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
<td>0.069<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
<td>0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.046)</td>
<td>(0.032)</td>
<td>(0.015)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> For profit</td>
<td>0.111<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
<td>0.098<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.014</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.048)</td>
<td>(0.032)</td>
<td>(0.015)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">County characteristics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Household income second quartile</td>
<td>−0.014</td>
<td>−0.009</td>
<td>0.005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.033)</td>
<td>(0.030)</td>
<td>(0.010)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Household income third quartile</td>
<td>−0.065<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">*</xref></td>
<td>−0.009</td>
<td>0.010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.039)</td>
<td>(0.035)</td>
<td>(0.013)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Household income fourth quartile</td>
<td>−0.096<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
<td>0.018</td>
<td>0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.042)</td>
<td>(0.036)</td>
<td>(0.013)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Poverty rate from 10.0% to 12.5%</td>
<td>−0.055<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
<td>0.002</td>
<td>−0.010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.023)</td>
<td>(0.022)</td>
<td>(0.006)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Poverty rate from 12.5% to 15.0%</td>
<td>−0.091<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>0.008</td>
<td>−0.013</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.031)</td>
<td>(0.030)</td>
<td>(0.010)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Poverty rate 15% or more</td>
<td>−0.170<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.005</td>
<td>−0.021<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.042)</td>
<td>(0.034)</td>
<td>(0.011)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Physicians per 1,000 population</td>
<td>−0.010</td>
<td>−0.007</td>
<td>−0.010<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1077558712468490">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.016)</td>
<td>(0.011)</td>
<td>(0.005)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1077558712468490">
<p>Note: AMI = acute myocardial infarction; PTCA = percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty; CABG = coronary artery bypass grafting. The sample consists of 119,386 observations, and is restricted to individuals aged 65 years and older, in Medicare FFS (fee-for-service), and treated by a physician who discharged at least 30 AMI patients between 1997 and 2005. All models also include year fixed effects. The omitted categories are White non-Hispanics, males, those with no comorbid conditions, nonteaching hospitals, urban hospitals, public hospitals, counties falling into the lowest quartile of household income, and counties with poverty rates below 10%. Robust standard errors clustered at the hospital level are reported in parentheses. Statistical significance is indicated by *** for .01 level, ** for .05 level, and * for .10 level.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Before turning to the fixed effects models, we note that the associations between procedure use and several of the control variables are as expected. Female patients are less likely to receive each of the treatments, consistent with previous research by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1077558712468490">Redberg (2005)</xref>. In most instances, the presence of a comorbid condition significantly decreases the chance of receiving one of the three cardiac procedures, as expected. Patients treated in rural hospitals are less likely to undergo cardiac catheterization.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1077558712468490">Table 3</xref> presents the main results of our analysis and allows us to address the main study questions. Panel A of <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1077558712468490">Table 3</xref> reproduces the marginal effect estimates for Black race and Hispanic ethnicity from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1077558712468490">Table 2</xref>, allowing for an easy comparison of the Black–White and Hispanic–White disparities in the baseline model to those from models that include fixed effects. Panel B reports the marginal effects from hospital fixed effects models and Panel C reports the marginal effects from physician fixed effects models. In Panel C, the models include the full set of controls reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1077558712468490">Table 2</xref>, including year indicator variables; in Panel B, we include all these controls except the rural indicator variable. For ease of presentation, the coefficients of the controls are not shown but are available on request.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1077558712468490" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Effects of Patient Race and Ethnicity in Linear Probability Models, With and Without Adjustment for Provider Fixed Effects.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1077558712468490" xlink:href="10.1177_1077558712468490-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Explanatory Variables</th>
<th align="center">Cardiac Catheterization</th>
<th align="center">PTCA</th>
<th align="center">CABG</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Panel A: Baseline models</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black</td>
<td>−0.085<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.066<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.027<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.017)</td>
<td>(0.012)</td>
<td>(0.005)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>−0.105<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.072<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.014<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1077558712468490">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.037)</td>
<td>(0.023)</td>
<td>(0.008)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Panel B:With hospital fixed effects</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black</td>
<td>−0.077<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.068<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.026<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.011)</td>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.004)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>−0.004</td>
<td>−0.014<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1077558712468490">**</xref></td>
<td>0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.008)</td>
<td>(0.007)</td>
<td>(0.005)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Panel C:With physician fixed effects</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black</td>
<td>−0.059<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.052<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
<td>−0.017<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1077558712468490">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.006)</td>
<td>(0.005)</td>
<td>(0.003)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>−0.00003</td>
<td>−0.007</td>
<td>0.00001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>(0.007)</td>
<td>(0.005)</td>
<td>(0.003)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1077558712468490">
<p>Note: PTCA = percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty; CABG = coronary artery bypass grafting. The sample consists of 119,386 observations, and is restricted to individuals aged 65 years and older, in Medicare FFS (fee-for-service), and treated by a physician who discharged at least 30 acute myocardial infarction patients between 1997 and 2005. Models in Panels A and C include the full set of controls reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1077558712468490">Table 2</xref> as well as year dummy variables; models in Panel B include all of these controls except the rural dummy variable. In Panels A and B, robust standard errors clustered at the hospital level are reported in parentheses. In Panel C, robust standard errors clustered at the physician level are reported in parentheses. Statistical significance is indicated by *** for .01 level, ** for .05 level, and * for .10 level.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>A comparison of Panels A and B in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1077558712468490">Table 3</xref> answers our first study question, which asks how the inclusion of hospital fixed effects in models of surgical procedure use affects both Black–White and Hispanic–White disparities in the surgical treatment for cardiac care. We expect that including hospital fixed effects will lessen these disparities given the evidence that minority patients are more likely than Whites to be treated in lower quality hospitals with less technologically advanced facilities. Panel B of <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1077558712468490">Table 3</xref> offers limited support for this hypothesis in regard to racial disparities. For both catheterization and CABG, there is a slight decline in the coefficient of Black race on the inclusion of hospital fixed effects.</p>
<p>In contrast, the Hispanic–White disparity is largely explained by the inclusion of hospital fixed effects. In the case of cardiac catheterization and CABG, the inclusion of hospital fixed effects renders the Hispanic coefficient statistically insignificant. In all three models, the magnitude of the Hispanic marginal effect is greatly reduced; it falls by 96% for cardiac catheterization and by 81% for PTCA, and it changes sign in the model of CABG surgery. Our results show that, in general, the inclusion of hospital fixed effects helps to explain disparities in cardiac care, but important differences exist between Blacks and Hispanics. The marginal effects of race in the within-hospital models are only somewhat smaller than the race effects overall, while the marginal effect of Hispanic ethnicity is greatly reduced, and in the case of cardiac catheterization and CABG, rendered statistically insignificant by including hospital fixed effects.</p>
<p>A comparison of results shown in Panels A and C answers our second study question concerning the effect of adjusting for attending physician fixed effects. For all three procedures, the results show that the inclusion of physician fixed effects accounts for a large portion of the Black–White disparity in procedure use. For example, in the baseline model, Black patients had an 8.5 percentage point lower chance of undergoing cardiac catheterization compared with Whites. Adding physician fixed effects to this model reduces the gap to 5.9 percentage points (or by 31%). Similarly, the addition of physician fixed effects to the model for CABG procedure use lowers the Black marginal effect from 2.7 percentage points to 1.7 percentage points (a drop of 37%). The decline in the racial disparity in PTCA on control of physician fixed effects is smaller, going from 6.6 to 5.2 percentage points (a decline of 21%). This change is still notable given that the inclusion of hospital fixed effects <italic>does not account</italic> for the race gap.</p>
<p>We see a similar pattern from a comparison of the Hispanic coefficient across Panels A and C; namely, controlling for attending physician fixed effects reduces the Hispanic–White disparities and does so to a somewhat greater degree than the control of hospital fixed effects in Panel B. For cardiac catheterization, the Hispanic coefficient falls from a significant negative 10.5 percentage points to nearly 0; for PTCA, the Hispanic coefficient falls from a significant negative 7.2 percentage points to an insignificant negative 0.7 percentage points (a drop of 90%). In the case of CABG, the Hispanic coefficient changes sign to a positive value, albeit very small and highly insignificant.</p>
<p>Our results are robust to the specification changes described earlier. We obtain similar results using slightly different definitions for two dependent variables and including patients admitted from all sources or treated by all medical or osteopathic physicians. Excluding large teaching hospitals or residents of Miami-Dade County also yields results similar to our main analysis, as does using data from shorter time periods within our 12-year sample (1997-1999 and 2003-2005). The results of these robustness checks are available from the authors on request.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1077558712468490" sec-type="discussion|conclusions">
<title>Discussion and Conclusion</title>
<p>The findings of this study help to identify hospital- and physician-level sources of racial and ethnic disparities in the surgical treatment of AMI. We find that disparities in procedure use between Hispanics and Whites in our sample are largely explained by differences in the hospitals where patients seek treatment. Hospital traits may matter greatly for Hispanics because, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1077558712468490">Jha et al. (2008)</xref> note, hospital care for elderly Hispanics is highly concentrated, with 90% of elderly Hispanic patients being treated at 25% of Americans hospitals, hospitals that on average were of lower quality. Similar patterns within Florida may explain why much of the Hispanic–White disparity is accounted by hospital fixed effects. Our findings also are consistent with prior evidence that hospital fixed or random effects explain some portion of disparities in the treatment of AMI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1077558712468490">Hasnain-Wynia et al., 2010</xref>) or in other types of health care, such as intensive care unit use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1077558712468490">Barnato et al., 2006</xref>) and reperfusion therapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1077558712468490">Bradley et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>In contrast, we find that disparities between Black and White patients are not explained by hospital traits. This suggests that Black patients are not systematically sorted to those Florida hospitals with a lower propensity to use intensive surgical treatments for AMI. Instead, physician fixed effects explain more of the Black–White disparities in utilization than do hospital fixed effects. For example, about one third of the Black–White gap in CABG is explained by physician fixed effects, but less than 5% of the gap is explained by hospital fixed effects. Thus, the sorting of patents to physicians explains a sizeable portion of racial disparities in treatment. On average, Blacks appear more likely than Whites to be treated by physicians who have a low propensity to employ surgical treatment in the use of cardiac care. Nonetheless, within-physician differences by race remain and are statistically significant, just smaller. The importance of physician effects in explaining disparities in health care has also been noted in by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1077558712468490">Rodriguez, von Glahn, Grembowski, Rogers, and Safran (2008)</xref> who estimated physician fixed effects models of patient experiences. They found that physician fixed effects largely explained the differences patient experience between minority and nonminority patients. While we find that physician fixed effects also explain ethnic disparities in utilization, we find that the largest reduction is driven by the sorting of Hispanics to different hospitals. Regardless, when we examine differences within-hospitals or differences within-physicians, treatment differences between Whites and Hispanics are not statistically significant.</p>
<p>Several limitations of our analysis should be noted. Like other studies that employ administrative data,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-1077558712468490">12</xref></sup> we are unable to include complete information on patients’ prior medical histories or patient risk factors, such as smoking, and we also lack data on individual-level measures of SES. We addressed this by including comorbid conditions, by focusing on a more homogenous population (seniors with Medicare fee-for-service), and by controlling for county-level socioeconomic measures. However, comorbidities and county-level SES may be insufficient controls, and if there are correlations between unobserved SES and health traits and race/ethnicity, we may be overestimating or underestimating race/ethnic disparities depending on the nature of these underlying correlations. Our findings are also limited to the Medicare population aged 65 years and older and may not generalize to preretirees.</p>
<p>Furthermore, our study is limited to discharge data from Florida hospitals, so questions about representativeness may arise. It is reassuring that recent data from the Dartmouth Atlas of Health Care show that for Medicare fee-for-service enrollees aged 65 to 99 years, national rates of CABG, PTCA/PCI, and cardiac catheterization are quite similar to rates in Florida, for both Blacks and non-Blacks. For cardiac catheterization, for example, the Florida rate for Blacks was 18.2 per 1,000 persons, and the national rate was 18 per 1,000 persons, and the rate for non-Blacks in Florida was 20.3 per 1,000, close to the national rate of 19 per 1,000 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1077558712468490">The Dartmouth Atlas of Health Care, 2011</xref>). That said, Florida Hispanics face different socioeconomic and political circumstances than minorities nationwide. Nearly a third of Hispanics in Florida are of Cuban origin, compared with only 3.5% of Hispanics nationwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1077558712468490">U.S. Census Bureau, 2001</xref>). U.S. immigration has also long-favored Cubans seeking residency and citizenship, and compared with all U.S. Hispanics, Cubans have higher levels of educational attainment and median family income (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1077558712468490">U.S. Census Bureau, 2004</xref>). Thus, the circumstances faced by Hispanics in our sample may be better than those of Hispanics nationwide.</p>
<p>Our findings suggest that attempts to lessen ethnic disparities in care should focus on the facilities available in Hispanic areas, perhaps by improving hospital quality and access to revascularization facilities. In the case of Black–White disparities in cardiac care treatment, our results suggest a different strategy. Rather than focusing solely on hospital traits, policy makers and practitioners might consider the traits of physicians who treat patients admitted through the emergency room with AMI. Our results show that differences between physicians who treat White and Black patients may explain about 21%-37% of the difference in treatment propensity. Beyond that, our results suggest that it would be beneficial to policy makers and practitioners if future research were to examine the sources of within-hospital and within-physician differences and effective ways to target them in order to address racial disparities in cardiac care.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors are grateful for valuable research assistance by Elizabeth Vestal and for financial support from the Schroeder Center for Health Policy at the College of William and Mary.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This study received financial support from the Schroeder Center for Health Policy at the College of William and Mary.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1077558712468490">
<label>1.</label>
<p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1077558712468490">Geiger (2003)</xref>, racial and ethnic disparities in surgical and medical treatments of AMI and coronary artery disease have been the focus of almost 200 publications since 1983.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1077558712468490">
<label>2.</label>
<p>The Florida Agency for Health Care Administration (AHCA) performs extensive auditing and validation of all variables in the inpatient discharge data. For the attending physician ID variable in particular, the AHCA verifies the IDs against state physician licensure information; if a discharge record has a missing or invalid ID, the record is sent back to the hospital for further review and correction. The Florida AHCA also checks the overlap between operating physician ID and attending physician ID for each hospital and flags those hospitals where more than 75% of the discharge records have the same operating and attending physician ID. These hospitals must verify that the accuracy of the data and rule out any errors.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1077558712468490">
<label>3.</label>
<p>We drop these hospitals because the hospital fixed effects models that we describe below control for all time-invariant hospital specific traits and because rural is time invariant for the remaining 199 hospitals in the sample. In a separate robustness check, we include these three hospitals; estimates of the race and ethnicity effects are almost identical.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1077558712468490">
<label>4.</label>
<p>These definitions are the same as those used in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1077558712468490">Bertoni et al. (2005)</xref> for cardiac catheterization and percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1077558712468490">Epstein et al. (2011)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1077558712468490">Cram, Pham, Bayman, and Vaughan-Sarrazin (2008)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1077558712468490">Cram, Bayman, Popescu, and Vaughan-Sarrazin (2010)</xref> for coronary artery bypass grafting.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1077558712468490">
<label>5.</label>
<p>We use data on the hospital’s statutory rural designation, which is determined by the state of Florida. As noted earlier, only three hospitals in our sample underwent changes in the statutory rural designation during the sample period, and we excluded these three hospitals from our analysis. Twelve hospitals in the sample switched teaching status, and 18 hospitals changed ownership status. The number of acute beds changed for 125 hospitals in the sample.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1077558712468490">
<label>6.</label>
<p>Note that median household income controls for the income level in the county and the percentage poverty serves as a proxy for inequality in the income distribution.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1077558712468490">
<label>7.</label>
<p>We also estimated the logit model equivalent of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1077558712468490">Equation (1)</xref>. Since the marginal effect estimates from this model (available on request) are similar to those from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-1077558712468490">Equation (1)</xref>, we use linear probability models as our main analysis models throughout the article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1077558712468490">
<label>8.</label>
<p>Note that we perform a patient-level analysis with hospital fixed effects; that is, the fixed effects are at a level that is more aggregated than the unit of analysis. This analysis captures all of the time-invariant hospitals factors that are faced by <italic>all</italic> acute myocardial infarction patients admitted to the same hospital and that may affect the treatment decision in the same way for all admitted patients.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1077558712468490">
<label>9.</label>
<p>Other drawbacks to nonlinear models are the stronger functional and distributional assumptions of logit and probit models compared with linear probability models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1077558712468490">Wooldridge, 2010</xref>, pp. 610-622), and, in the case of the unconditional logit model, the incidental parameters problem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1077558712468490">Wooldridge, 2010</xref>, p. 495). The main drawback of the linear probability models is, of course, the potential of generating a predicted probability larger than one or smaller than zero. But given that we are not interested in predicting probabilities <italic>per se</italic>, we do not consider this drawback as a serious limitation, especially given that our main variables of interest and the majority of our control variables are indicator variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1077558712468490">Wooldridge, 2010</xref>, pp. 563-565).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1077558712468490">
<label>10.</label>
<p>Fixed effects logit models estimate odds ratios conveniently; however, marginal effects have a clearer behavioral interpretation and also are measured in the metric of direct interest—the probability of the outcome event occurring. To illustrate, let the probability of outcome D (say hand-washing) occurring under an intervention (say a large-scale public campaign on the benefits of hand-washing) be <italic>p</italic><sub>1</sub> and the probability of D occurring with no intervention be <italic>p</italic><sub>0</sub>. If <italic>p</italic><sub>1</sub> = .8 and <italic>p</italic><sub>0</sub> = .2, the marginal effect of the intervention is 0.6 while the odds ratio is 16 and the relative risk is 4. All three estimates might lead to the conclusion that the intervention substantially changed the probability that the outcome of interest occurred. If, however, <italic>p</italic><sub>1</sub> = .0008 and <italic>p</italic><sub>0</sub> = .0002, then the marginal effect is 0.0006, which is a small difference from a public policy point of view; this might lead researchers and policy makers to conclude that the funding for the intervention is better used elsewhere. But the odds ratio is now 4.002 and the relative risk remains 4. Both may lead to the conclusion that the intervention effect is large and intervention is warranted. For an in-depth discussion of the advantages of marginal effects relative to odds ratios and relative risks, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1077558712468490">Lance (2008)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1077558712468490">
<label>11.</label>
<p>Black and Hispanic discharges are not evenly distributed across attending physicians, but large numbers of physicians are still involved in treating the bulk of minority patients. For example, about half of all discharges involving Black patients are among 323 or 16% of the total number of physicians treating Black patients, and about two thirds of all discharges involving Hispanic patients are among 231 or 14% of the total number of physicians treating Hispanic patients.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-1077558712468490">
<label>12.</label>
<p>Examples include <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1077558712468490">Epstein et al. (2011)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1077558712468490">Cram et al. (2010)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1077558712468490">Brown et al. (2008)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>Agency for Health Care Administration</collab>. (<year>various years</year>). <source>Hospital beds and services list</source>. Certificate of Need Office. <publisher-loc>Tallahassee, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ayanian</surname><given-names>J. Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guadagnoli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNeil</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Treatment and outcomes of acute myocardial infarction among patients of cardiologists and generalist physicians</article-title>. <source>Archives of Internal Medicine</source>, <volume>157</volume>, <fpage>2570</fpage>-<lpage>2576</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schrag</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hargraves</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Primary care physicians who treat blacks and whites</article-title>. <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>, <volume>351</volume>, <fpage>575</fpage>-<lpage>584</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barnato</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Staiger</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wennberg</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Hospital-level racial disparities in acute myocardial infarction treatment and outcomes</article-title>. <source>Medical Care</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>308</fpage>-<lpage>319</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barnato</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berhane</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weissfeld</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C. C. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Linde-Zwirbe</surname><given-names>W. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Angus</surname><given-names>W. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Racial variation in end-of-life intensive care use: A race or hospital effect?</article-title> <source>Health Services Research</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>2219</fpage>-<lpage>2237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mobley</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Trends in racial disparities among the elderly for selected procedures</article-title>. <source>Medical Care Research and Review</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>617</fpage>-<lpage>637</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bertoni</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goonan</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bonds</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whitt</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brancati</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities for acute myocardial infarction in the United States, 1995-2001</article-title>. <source>Journal of the National Medical Association</source>, <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>317</fpage>-<lpage>323</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Herrin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Magid</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krumholz</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Racial and ethnic differences in time to acute reperfusion therapy for patients hospitalized with myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source>, <volume>292</volume>, <fpage>1563</fpage>-<lpage>1572</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brookhart</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glynn</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Avorn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schneeweiss</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Explained variation in a model of therapeutic decision making is partitioned across patient, physician, and clinic factors</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Epidemiology</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kiros</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Disparities in the receipt of cardiac revascularization procedures between blacks and whites: An analysis of secular trends</article-title>. <source>Ethnic Disparities</source>, <volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>, <supplement>Suppl. 2</supplement>), S2-<fpage>112</fpage>-<lpage>117</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Castellanos</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhongmin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ayanian</surname><given-names>J. Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amsterdam</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Relation of race, ethnicity and cardiac surgeons to operative mortality rates in primary coronary artery bypass grafting in California</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Cardiology</source>, <volume>107</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Radford</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krumholz</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Care and outcomes of elderly patients with acute myocardial infarction by physician specialty: The effects of comorbidity and functional limitations</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Medicine</source>, <volume>108</volume>, <fpage>460</fpage>-<lpage>469</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rathore</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Radford</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krumholz</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Physician board certification and the care and outcomes of elderly patients with acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Journal of General Internal Medicine</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>238</fpage>-<lpage>244</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cram</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bayman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Popescu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaughan-Sarrazin</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Racial disparities in revascularization rates among patients with similar insurance coverage</article-title>. <source>Journal of the National Medical Association</source>, <volume>101</volume>, <fpage>1132</fpage>-<lpage>1139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cram</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bayman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Popescu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaughan-Sarrazin</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>AMI and CABG outcomes in specialty and general hospitals: Analysis of SID all-payor data</article-title>. <source>Health Services Research</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>62</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cram</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bayman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaughan-Sarrazin</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Insurance status of patients admitted to specialty cardiac and competing general hospitals</article-title>. <source>Medical Care</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>467</fpage>-<lpage>475</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>The Dartmouth Atlas of Health Care</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>CABG, PCI, and catheterization (per 1,000), by race, 2007</source>. <publisher-loc>Dartmouth, NH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Dartmouth Institute for Health Policy and Clinical Practice</publisher-name>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dartmouthatlas.org/data/topic/all.aspx">http://www.dartmouthatlas.org/data/topic/all.aspx</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deyo</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cherkin</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ciol</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Adapting aclinical comorbidity index for use with ICD-9-CM administrative databases</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Epidemiology</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>613</fpage>-<lpage>619</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ehlenbach</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barnato</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kreuter</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koepsell</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stapleton</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Epidemiologic study of in-hospital cardiopulmonary resuscitation in the elderly</article-title>. <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>, <volume>361</volume>, <fpage>22</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Polsky</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Groeneveld</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Coronary revascularization trends in the United States, 2001-2008</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source>, <volume>305</volume>, <fpage>1769</fpage>-<lpage>1776</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Implications of race/ethnicity for health and health care use: Racial/ethnic differences in health care utilization of cardiovascular procedures: A review of the evidence</article-title>. <source>Health Services Research</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>252</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ostfeld</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Racial differences in the use of cardiac procedures in patients with acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Nursing Research</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>148</fpage>-<lpage>157</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities in diagnosis and treatment: A review of the evidence and a consideration of causes</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Smedley</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stith</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Unequal treatment: Confronting racial and ethnic disparities in health care</source> (pp. <fpage>417</fpage>-<lpage>454</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Groeneveld</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kruse</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Asch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Variation in cardiac procedure use and racial disparity among Veterans Affairs Hospitals</article-title>. <source>American Heart Journal</source>, <volume>153</volume>, <fpage>320</fpage>-<lpage>327</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T. Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daviglus</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Exaire</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Differences in treatment patterns and outcomes between Hispanics and non-Hispanic whites treated for ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction: Results from the NCDR ACTION Registry GWTB</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American College of Cardiologists</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>630</fpage>-<lpage>631</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeFrances</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Golosinskiy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwartzman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>National Hospital Discharge Survey: 2007 summary</source> (National Health Statistics Rep. No. 29). <publisher-loc>Hyattsville, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Center for Health Statistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hasnain-Wynia</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Landrum</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vogeli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities within and between hospitals for inpatient quality of care: an examination of patient-level hospital quality alliance measures</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Care for the Poor and Underserved</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>629</fpage>-<lpage>648</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heron</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoyert</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J. Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kochanek</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tejada-Vera</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Deaths: Final data for 2006</article-title>. <source>National Vital Statistics Reports</source>, <volume>57</volume>(<issue>14</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>134</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huesch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Provider-hospital “fit” and patient outcomes: Evidence from Massachusetts cardiac surgeons, 2002-2004</article-title>. <source>Health Services Research</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orav</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Racial trends in the use of major procedures among the elderly</article-title>. <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>, <volume>353</volume>, <fpage>683</fpage>-<lpage>691</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orav</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The characteristics and performance of hospitals that care for elderly Hispanic Americans</article-title>. <source>Health Affairs</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>528</fpage>-<lpage>537</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jollis</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muhlbaier</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fortin</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Califf</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Outcome of acute myocardial infarction according to the specialty of the admitting physician</article-title>. <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>, <volume>335</volume>, <fpage>1880</fpage>-<lpage>1887</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hawley</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abrahamse</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Friese</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alderman</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Does it matter where you go for breast surgery? Attending surgeon’s influence on variation in receipt of mastectomy for breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Medical Care</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>892</fpage>-<lpage>899</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kressin</surname><given-names>N. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Racial differences in the use of invasive cardiac procedures: Review of the literature and prescription for future research</article-title>. <source>Annals of Internal Medicine</source>, <volume>135</volume>, <fpage>352</fpage>-<lpage>366</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lance</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Odds ratios</source>. Unpublished manuscript. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aging-disgracefully.com/notes/">http://www.aging-disgracefully.com/notes/</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lillie-Blanton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rushing</surname><given-names>O. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mayberry</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boone</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Racial/ethnic differences in cardiac care: The weight of the evidence: Summary report</source>. <publisher-loc>Menlo Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Henry J. Kaiser Family Foundation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zingmond</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGory</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>SooHoo</surname><given-names>N. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ettner</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brook</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Disparities in the utilization of high-volume hospitals for complex surgery</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source>, <volume>296</volume>, <fpage>1973</fpage>-<lpage>1980</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mensah</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>An overview of cardiovascular disease burden in the United States</article-title>. <source>Health Affairs</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>38</fpage>-<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mukamel</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Racial differences in access to high-quality cardiac surgeons</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source>, <volume>90</volume>, <fpage>1774</fpage>-<lpage>1777</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Popescu</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cram</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaughan-Sarrazin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Differences in admitting hospital characteristics for black and white Medicare beneficiaries with acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>, <volume>123</volume>, <fpage>2710</fpage>-<lpage>2716</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Popescu</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nallamothu</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaughan-Sarrazin</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cram</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Racial differences in admissions to high-quality hospitals for coronary heart disease</article-title>. <source>Archives of Internal Medicine</source>, <volume>170</volume>, <fpage>1209</fpage>-<lpage>1215</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rathore</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Radford</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vaccarino</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krumholz</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Sex differences in cardiac catheterization: The role of physician gender</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source>, <volume>286</volume>, <fpage>2849</fpage>-<lpage>2856</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Redberg</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Gender, race, and cardiac care</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American College of Cardiology</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>1852</fpage>-<lpage>1854</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>H. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>von Glahn</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grembowski</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Safran</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Physician effects on racial and ethnic disparities in patients’ experiences of primary care</article-title>. <source>Journal of General Internal Medicine</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1666</fpage>-<lpage>1672</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sequist</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fitzmaurice</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaykevich</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Safran</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ayanian</surname><given-names>J. Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Physician performance and racial disparities in diabetes mellitus care</article-title>. <source>Archives of Internal Medicine</source>, <volume>168</volume>, <fpage>1145</fpage>-<lpage>1151</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vaccarino</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rathore</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wenger</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frederick</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abramson</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barron</surname><given-names>H. V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krumholz</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Sex and racial differences in the management of acute myocardial infarction, 1994 through 2002</article-title>. <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>, <volume>353</volume>, <fpage>671</fpage>-<lpage>682</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Characteristics of VA patients who use low-quality private-sector CABG centers in New York</article-title>. <source>Medical Care Research and Review</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>691</fpage>-<lpage>705</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wooldridge</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Econometric analysis of cross section and panel data</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>U.S. Census Bureau</collab>. (<year>2001</year>). <source>The Hispanic population: Census 2000 brief</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>U.S. Census Bureau</collab>. (<year>2004</year>). <source>We the people: Hispanics in the United States. Census 2000 special report, CENSR-18</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1077558712468490">
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>U.S. Census Bureau</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>2010 Census data</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://2010.census.gov/2010census/data/">2010.census.gov/2010census/data/</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>