<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JEA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjea</journal-id>
<journal-title>The Journal of Early Adolescence</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0272-4316</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-5449</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0272431612450949</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0272431612450949</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Predicting Achievement in Mathematics in Adolescent Students</article-title>
<subtitle>The Role of Individual and Social Factors</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Levpušček</surname><given-names>Melita Puklek</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0272431612450949">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Zupančič</surname><given-names>Maja</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0272431612450949">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sočan</surname><given-names>Gregor</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0272431612450949">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0272431612450949"><label>1</label>University of Ljubljana, Ljubljana, Slovenia</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0272431612450949">Melita Puklek Levpušček, Department of Psychology, University of Ljubljana, Aškerčeva 2, 1000 Ljubljana, Slovenia. Email: <email>melita.puklek@ff.uni-lj.si</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>33</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>523</fpage>
<lpage>551</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The study examined individual factors and social factors that influence adolescent students’ achievement in mathematics. The predictive model suggested direct positive effects of student intelligence, self-rated openness and parental education on achievement in mathematics, whereas direct effects of extraversion on measures of achievement were negative. Indirect positive effects of intelligence, self-rated conscientiousness, student-perceived mathematics teacher’s press for understanding and mastery goal, and a negative effect of student-rated parental academic pressure on course achievement were mediated through the students’ self-efficacy in mathematics. The findings highlight the important role that individual differences in ability and personality, as well as student perceptions of parent and teacher academically related variables, play in the students’ performance in mathematics.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>adolescents</kwd>
<kwd>individual differences</kwd>
<kwd>parental involvement</kwd>
<kwd>teachers’ classroom behavior</kwd>
<kwd>achievement in mathematics</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Academic achievement is of an exceptional importance for individuals in postindustrial societies. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0272431612450949">Vitaro, Trembley, Brendgen, and Larose (2005)</xref> summarized that adults who do not complete, at least, an upper secondary school use social services more frequently, have more health problems, are more prone to abuse psychoactive substances, and engage in illegal acts. They are also less likely to be involved in community life and their children are at a higher risk for poor educational attainment. Poor academic achievement in early adolescence is an important antecedent of low educational levels in young adulthood, and precedes long-term unemployment; at the same time adolescents’ school success is known to mediate the effects of early personality risk factors on unemployment in adulthood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0272431612450949">Kokko, Bergman, &amp; Pulkkinen, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>Academic achievement reflects the extent to which students attain learning objectives as defined in curricula and syllabuses for specific subjects. It is usually evaluated by grades in particular academic courses, GPA or scores at national examination tests. Academic achievement in mathematics seems to be of special significance in information societies that require their workforce to be mathematically literate. Therefore, success in mathematics is treated as an admission criterion at the level of upper secondary and postsecondary education across many countries. It is worth noting that, from the learning perspective, mathematics is sequential; achievement in mathematics is largely dependent on accomplishments in arrays of preceding mathematics courses. Thus, students who do not effectively attain learning standards in mathematics at the end of compulsory education, are less likely to complete general mathematics courses in upper secondary school and beyond, successfully (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0272431612450949">Singh, Granville, &amp; Dika, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>Despite the important role of mathematics in a students’ progress through the upper levels of education, there is very little research that combines individual and social factors in predicting achievement in mathematics. Only recently, has research focused on analyzing the contribution of motivation, family and culture to individual differences in mathematical knowledge, as assessed by large-scale international studies such as “Program for International Student Assessment (PISA)” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0272431612450949">Chiu &amp; Klassen, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0272431612450949">Chiu &amp; Xihua, 2008</xref>). Although these studies were very thoroughly designed and well executed, in addition to being informative, they do not include student intelligence and personality traits which, some authors define as key individual factors contributing to academic achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0272431612450949">Ackerman &amp; Haggestad, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0272431612450949">Bratko, Chamorro-Premuzic, &amp; Saks, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0272431612450949">Chamorro-Premuzic &amp; Furnham, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0272431612450949">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0272431612450949">Laidra, Pullmann, &amp; Allik, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0272431612450949">Watkins, Lei, &amp; Canivez, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>This study jointly investigated several social and individual factors that, as indicated by previous research, contribute to adolescents’ academic achievement in mathematics. We focused on Slovene students in their last year of compulsory basic school education (Grade 9). For the study we selected the following social factors: education level of parents, student-perceived parental academic pressure and support, and student assessments of the mathematics teacher’s behavior in the classroom. Among individual factors, general intelligence of the student, personality traits, and self-efficacy in mathematics were included. The two indicators of achievement in mathematics were final grades as assessed by the teacher and student scores on the National Examination Test (NET) in mathematics. A path model of the direct and indirect effects (through students’ self-efficacy in mathematics) of predictors on achievement in mathematics was proposed and examined.</p>
<sec id="section1-0272431612450949">
<title>Intelligence and Personality</title>
<p>Intelligence has been clearly demonstrated to play an important role in predicting students’ academic achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0272431612450949">Deary, Strand, Smith, &amp; Fernandes, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0272431612450949">Mackintosh, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0272431612450949">Rinderman &amp; Neubauer, 2004</xref>). This is certainly not surprising, as predicting school performance was the main objective in constructing the first psychometric intelligence tests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0272431612450949">Ackerman &amp; Heggestad, 1997</xref>). Concurrent and longitudinal associations between intelligence and academic achievement are substantial with the magnitude of correlation ranging from 0.4 to 0.7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0272431612450949">Jensen, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0272431612450949">Mackintosh, 1998</xref>). A longitudinal study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0272431612450949">Deary et al. (2007)</xref> suggested that general intelligence at age 11 contributes to achievement in national examinations, across academic subjects five years later, with intelligence explaining the largest part of variance in mathematics (almost 60%). Using a cross-lagged research design, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0272431612450949">Watkins et al. (2007)</xref> even provided convincing evidence that psychometric intelligence precedes future academic achievement measures; whereas previous achievement does not significantly influence intelligence scores in adolescent students. Similar relationships between general intelligence and achievement in mathematics were also reported across a variety of measures and samples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0272431612450949">Alarcón, Knopik, &amp; DeFries, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0272431612450949">Little et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0272431612450949">Lynn, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0272431612450949">Rohde &amp; Thompson, 2007</xref>). Based on these research findings, a direct effect of students’ general intelligence on their mathematical achievements was proposed in our inquiry.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, cognitive ability alone is not sufficient to account fully for individual differences in academic success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0272431612450949">Chamorro-Premuzic &amp; Furnham, 2006</xref>). Along with intelligence, personality traits appear to be among the most promising predictors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0272431612450949">Bratko et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0272431612450949">Chamorro-Premuzic &amp; Furnham, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0272431612450949">Laidra et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0272431612450949">O’Connor &amp; Paunonen, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0272431612450949">Steinmayr, Bipp, &amp; Spinath, 2011</xref>), explaining unique variance in academic achievement beyond intelligence. Recent explorations of the links between personality and academic achievement (mostly defined in terms of GPA) tend to operate under the framework of the Five-Factor Model (FFM) of personality trait structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0272431612450949">O’Connor &amp; Paunonen, 2007</xref>). The FFM, which posits robust traits of extraversion, agreeableness, conscientiousness, neuroticism, and openness at the top level of the personality hierarchy, has been replicated across different countries in samples of adolescents (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0272431612450949">Knyazev, Zupančič, &amp; Slobodskaya, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0272431612450949">Mervielde &amp; De Fruyt, 2002</xref>) and adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0272431612450949">McCrae &amp; Costa, 1997</xref>).</p>
<p>Some of the FFM traits appear to be more predictive of school success than others. Conscientiousness is most consistently identified as relevant to academic achievement in adolescent students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0272431612450949">Barbaranelli, Caprara, Rabasca, &amp; Pastorelli, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0272431612450949">Bratko et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0272431612450949">Laidra et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0272431612450949">Smrtnik Vitulić &amp; Zupančič, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0272431612450949">Steinmayr et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0272431612450949">Trautwein, Lüdtke, Roberts, Schnyder, &amp; Niggli, 2009</xref>). Investigating predictive relations of the FFM traits with an adolescents’ domain specific achievement in mathematics suggests a similar conclusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0272431612450949">Marsh, Trautwein, Lüdtke, Köller, &amp; Baumert, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0272431612450949">Trautwein et al., 2009</xref>), though such research is scarce. Students who are persistent, achievement oriented, show effort, are orderly, responsible, are good at planning and are well organized are likely to more effectively manage academic assignments and learning (including mathematics) in a structured academic context. Likewise, openness usually accounts for academic success across grade levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0272431612450949">Barbaranelli et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0272431612450949">Laidra et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0272431612450949">Mervielde, Buyst, &amp; De Fruyt, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0272431612450949">Steinmayr et al., 2011</xref>). Students who are quick and eager to learn, curious, interested in new ideas, and tend to seek novel educational experiences manage academic-related problems in school successfully and consequently do well academically (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0272431612450949">Chamorro-Premuzic &amp; Furnham, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0272431612450949">Smrtnik Vitulić &amp; Zupančič, 2010</xref>). When defined in terms of fantasy, aesthetics, feelings, actions, ideas, and values, openness correlates with adolescent school grades in languages but not with mathematics grades and test scores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0272431612450949">Marsh et al., 2006</xref>). However, the openness factor measured in our study also included intellect (need for cognitive experience, knowledge acquisition, ease of learning and understanding), the specific constituent trait of openness that appears clearly related to school-age children’s mathematics grades and test scores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0272431612450949">Zupančič &amp; Kavčič, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0272431612450949">Zupančič &amp; Vidmar, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Extraversion seems to be negatively related to grades in adolescents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0272431612450949">Bratko et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0272431612450949">Furnham, Chamorro-Premuzic, &amp; McDougall 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0272431612450949">Laidra et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0272431612450949">Smrtnik Vitulić &amp; Zupančič, 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0272431612450949">2011</xref>), possibly because extraverted students spend less time on studying and more on socializing (Chamorro-Premuzic, 2005; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0272431612450949">Smrtnik Vitulić &amp; Zupančič, 2010</xref>). Neuroticism either shows low negative relations (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0272431612450949">Steinmayr et al., 2011</xref>) or no associations (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0272431612450949">Bratko et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0272431612450949">Smrtnik Vitulić &amp; Zupančič, 2010</xref>) with school grades, while agreeableness is not related to academic outcomes in adolescent students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0272431612450949">Bratko et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0272431612450949">Laidra et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0272431612450949">O’Connor &amp; Paunonen, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0272431612450949">Steinmayr et al., 2011</xref>). Thus, we expected positive effects of conscientiousness and openness and negative effects of extraversion, on the students’ performance in mathematics.</p>
<p>In addition, we were looking for the indirect effects of FFM traits on performance in mathematics. Self-efficacy in mathematics seems to be particularly relevant to this relationship because of its powerful effect on mathematical outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0272431612450949">Fast et al., 2010</xref>). When explaining academic success in mathematics, the predictive power of self-efficacy in mathematics was found to be similar to that of cognitive ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0272431612450949">Pajares &amp; Kranzler, 1995</xref>) and it even exceeded the predictive power of previous performance in mathematics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0272431612450949">Pajares &amp; Miller, 1995</xref>). Concerning personality traits, the association of conscientiousness with academic achievement has often been interpreted in terms of academic motivation, including academic competence beliefs (e.g., self-efficacy) and study habits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0272431612450949">Chamorro-Premuzic &amp; Furnham, 2005</xref>). Conscientious students may be, relative to their less conscientious peers, more motivated to perform well at academic tasks because of their dutiful nature, effective study habits, confidence in self-perceived academic competence, attentiveness in the classroom and commitment to academic courses, and are more likely to invest effort into learning, to persist, and consequently, to succeed academically. Indeed, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0272431612450949">Trautwein et al. (2009)</xref> found a moderate association between conscientiousness and competence beliefs in mathematics. Both variables predicted the adolescent students’ academic effort in the course, which mediated their positive effect on achievement in mathematics.</p>
<p>Based on this summary of findings and suggestions, we expected that conscientiousness mainly affects students’ self-efficacy beliefs in mathematics which, in turn, influences achievement in the course. Openness (defined as openness to experience and self-perceived intelligence in our study) was further proposed to be related to achievement in mathematics, both directly and indirectly. On the one hand, curiosity and the need for cognitive experience may lead to higher intellectual investment and knowledge acquisition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0272431612450949">Chamorro-Premuzic &amp; Furnham, 2006</xref>), representing a direct link between openness and achievement. On the other hand, self-perceived intelligence and self-efficacy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0272431612450949">Bandura, 1986</xref>) both refer to subjective evaluations rather than objectively measured characteristics and are believed to affect performance because of their self-fulfilling effects, even when intelligence test scores are controlled (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0272431612450949">Chamorro-Premuzic &amp; Furnham, 2006</xref>). In a related study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0272431612450949">Steinmayr et al. (2011)</xref>, an effect of openness on academic achievement in adolescents, which was partially mediated by the students’ learning goals (focus to increase one’s academic competence), was also demonstrated. Besides its direct effect on achievement in mathematics, we assumed openness to indirectly relate to achievement in mathematics, through the students’ self-efficacy beliefs. However, we had no evidence to propose a mediating effect of self-efficacy in the predictive relationship between extraversion and achievement.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0272431612450949">
<title>Parental Involvement and SES</title>
<p>The role of parental involvement in their children’s education has been well documented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0272431612450949">Fan &amp; Chen, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0272431612450949">Grolnick &amp; Slowiaczek, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0272431612450949">Marchant, Paulson, &amp; Rothlisberg, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0272431612450949">Steinberg, Lamborn, Dornbusch, &amp; Darling, 1992</xref>). Students whose parents participate in school activities, support their children’s intellectual and academic work, and convey the value of education have stronger academic motivation (self-efficacy, internal locus of control, educational aspirations) and do better in school than their peers who have less involved parents. However, parental academic involvement is a multidimensional construct (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0272431612450949">Gonzalez-DeHass, Willems, &amp; Doan Holbein, 2005</xref>). Therefore, the direction and size of associations with student’s academic achievement depend on a domain of parental involvement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0272431612450949">Fan &amp; Chen, 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>Our study examined how students perceive parental academic pressure and support. A consistent negative effect, of the perceived parental academic pressure (unrealistic expectations, constantly reminding children of their school duties, distrusting their school work) on students’ academic motivation and achievement in mathematics, was previously demonstrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0272431612450949">Campbell &amp; Mandel, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0272431612450949">Koutsoulis &amp; Campbell, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0272431612450949">Puklek Levpušček &amp; Zupančič, 2009</xref>). The negative effect on achievement was also displayed indirectly through students’ motivational beliefs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0272431612450949">Koutsoulis &amp; Campbell, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0272431612450949">Puklek Levpušček &amp; Zupančič, 2009</xref>). In contrast, student-reported parental academic support (interest in children’s learning, encouraging their academic efforts, showing pride and having realistic expectations concerning their future education) was suggested to be beneficial in both academic motivation and achievement in mathematics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0272431612450949">Campbell &amp; Mandel, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0272431612450949">Koutsoulis &amp; Campbell, 2001</xref>). However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0272431612450949">Puklek Levpušček and Zupančič (2009)</xref> established, in Slovene eighth-grade students, a direct negative effect of their perception of parental academic support (interest in adolescents’ school work, support of their effort placed in learning) on performance in mathematics. This may, however, reflect an adolescent-to-parent-effect, as parents usually become more involved in response to their child’s academic problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0272431612450949">Grolnick, Ryan, &amp; Deci, 1991</xref>). In addition, adolescents may also perceive high levels of parental support as being overprotective and intrusive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0272431612450949">Puklek Levpušček &amp; Zupančič, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Meta-analytic reviews on SES-achievement relation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0272431612450949">Sirin, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0272431612450949">White, 1982</xref>) indicate that family SES is one of the strongest correlates of academic achievement. Parents with higher SES are usually well educated, have the financial resources that allow them to offer learning opportunities that foster their children’s education and pay more attention to their child’s intellectual growth than parents with lower SES. Accordingly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0272431612450949">Chiu and Xihua (2008)</xref> studied the effect of family SES across 41 countries participating in the PISA study. Students with higher family SES scored significantly higher on the mathematics test in 95% of the countries. Parental education is usually used as a SES measure across studies. It is considered “one of the most stable aspects of SES because it is typically established at an early age and tends to remain the same over time” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0272431612450949">Sirin, 2005</xref>, p. 419). It also relates to other SES components such as family income, social prestige and economic status based on the parents’ professional occupation. Therefore, parental education was included in the current study as one of the social factors of adolescents’ achievement in mathematics.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0272431612450949">
<title>Teacher Behavior</title>
<p>Significant associations between teacher classroom behavior and student academic performance have been demonstrated over the past decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0272431612450949">Brekelmans, Webbels, &amp; Levy, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0272431612450949">Kaplan &amp; Midgley, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0272431612450949">Marchant et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0272431612450949">Urdan &amp; Midgley, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0272431612450949">Wentzel, 1997</xref>). Teachers’ academic support, academic press and mastery goal consistently related to how their adolescent students engaged in academic work, coped with academic difficulty, and academic achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0272431612450949">Fast et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0272431612450949">Goodnow, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0272431612450949">Kaplan &amp; Midgley, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0272431612450949">Middleton &amp; Midgley, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0272431612450949">Patrick, Ryan, &amp; Kaplan, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0272431612450949">Urdan &amp; Midgley, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>The three teacher behavioral dimensions were also considered in our study. The teacher academic support refers to students’ observations that the teacher cares about their learning, offers help when they experience learning difficulties, and encourages them to demonstrate their full learning potential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0272431612450949">Patrick et al., 2007</xref>). The teacher mastery goal reflects students’ perceptions that the teacher emphasizes in-depth learning, understanding of course contents, and development of mathematics competence and skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0272431612450949">Midgley et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0272431612450949">Urdan &amp; Schoenfelder, 2006</xref>). Finally, the teacher academic press involves students’ beliefs about demand and press for cognitive engagement in the classroom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0272431612450949">Middleton &amp; Midgley, 2002</xref>). Although the quality of teaching and classroom management was suggested as being beneficial in student learning and performance, less is known about whether the effects are direct, indirect or both. To our knowledge, only <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0272431612450949">Puklek Levpušček and Zupančič (2009)</xref> investigated the direct and indirect effects of the mathematics teacher behavior, as assessed by the students (among other social factors), on their achievement in mathematics. Student-perceived mathematics teachers’ academic press and mastery goal contributed to the final grades, by indirectly enhancing student self-efficacy. However, the perceptions of the mathematics teacher classroom behaviors were unique and substantial contributors to students’ motivational beliefs in mathematics, displaying significant effects above and beyond the contribution of adolescent-assessed parental involvement in their education. It seems that teachers have a significant role in promoting self-efficacy in students which, in turn, contributes to academic achievement.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0272431612450949">
<title>Academic Self-Efficacy</title>
<p>According to the social cognitive theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0272431612450949">Bandura, 1986</xref>), an individual’s belief about his/her own abilities and skills, and about the value and likelihood of success in an activity, plays an important part in human motivation. Self-efficacy reflects the individuals’ context-specific belief, about their abilities or effectiveness in achieving specific goals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0272431612450949">Bandura, 1997</xref>). These beliefs relate to decisions regarding one’s own performance in specific domains (e.g., a particular school subject) or in carrying out certain tasks.</p>
<p>Individuals’ self-beliefs, including self-efficacy, contribute to academic achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0272431612450949">Bandura, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0272431612450949">Schunk &amp; Pajares, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0272431612450949">Valentine, Dubois, &amp; Cooper, 2004</xref>). Students who are confident about their own effectiveness in achieving the learning objectives will invest effort in studying and will not give up despite a current failure. Moreover, self-efficacy is related to goal setting: perception of higher self-efficacy leads to setting higher goals; the individual is less afraid of failure and is willing to explore new approaches to solve the problem when previous ones prove to be unsuccessful (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0272431612450949">Woolfolk, 2001</xref>). Students with positive self-beliefs, in a given academic domain, are also more active in their respective field. Consequently, they gain experience and feedback which help them perform a task or activity better in the future. In his self-efficacy theory, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0272431612450949">Bandura (1997)</xref> assumed that among equally capable students those higher in academic self-efficacy will be more successful.</p>
<p>Encouragement and supportive messages received by students from parents, teachers, and peers are important sources of academic self-efficacy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0272431612450949">Usher &amp; Pajares, 2009</xref>). Parents who invest effort in their child’s education, put value on academic endeavor and achievement, and do not exert unrealistic expectations on the child’s educational progress have children with higher self-efficacy beliefs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0272431612450949">Marchant et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0272431612450949">Puklek Levpušček &amp; Zupančič, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0272431612450949">Schunk &amp; Pajares, 2002</xref>). The encouragement obtained through teachers’ positive feedback on standards of school work attained by students and their perception of teachers as respectful and supportive may also help shape positive beliefs about academic self-efficacy in a particular learning area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0272431612450949">Patrick et al., 2007</xref>). Accordingly, eighth graders’ self-efficacy in mathematics was found to be a significant motivational predictor of their final mathematics grade, and a mediator of the effect of student-perceived parental and mathematics teacher behavior on the course achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0272431612450949">Puklek Levpušček &amp; Zupančič, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Self-efficacy beliefs are created and developed by an individual’s interpretation of prior experiences, social support and personal qualities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0272431612450949">Bandura, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0272431612450949">Schunk &amp; Pajares, 2002</xref>). Beside social factors we thus assumed that stable personality traits (conscientiousness and openness) and intelligence contribute to students’ self-efficacy in mathematics.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0272431612450949">
<title>Aims—Hypotheses</title>
<p>Our goal was to determine if selected individual factors (general intelligence, self-rated FFM personality traits) and social factors (parental education, student-perceived parental academic involvement and the classroom behavior of the mathematics teacher) were predictive of academic outcomes in mathematics (self-efficacy, final grades and NET scores) in adolescents. Direct and indirect effects (mediated through students’ self-efficacy) of these factors on achievement in mathematics were investigated. The following hypotheses were proposed:</p>
<list id="list1-0272431612450949" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1</italic>: Students’ intelligence, conscientiousness and openness have a positive effect on self-efficacy in mathematics;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 2</italic>: This self-efficacy has a positive effect on achievement in mathematics;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 3</italic>: Extraversion has a direct and negative effect on achievement in mathematics;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 4</italic>: Intelligence and openness show both direct and indirect positive effects (through self-efficacy) on achievement;</p></list-item> <list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 5</italic>: Conscientiousness positively predicts achievement but only indirectly through self-efficacy in mathematics;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 6</italic>: Among student perceptions of parent-related variables, academic support was expected to predict self-efficacy in a positive direction, whereas academic pressure was proposed to be associated with self-efficacy negatively;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 7</italic>: Parental education and student perceptions of parental academic support were expected to directly affect achievement in mathematics, with parental education having a positive influence and parental support exerting a negative effect on achievement; both a direct and an indirect negative effect of the perceived parental academic pressure on mathematics achievement was also proposed;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 8</italic>: Self-efficacy in mathematics was suggested to mediate the positive effect of student-reported academic support from their mathematics teachers, academic press, and mastery goal on mathematics achievement.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0272431612450949" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section7-0272431612450949">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>The initial sample consisted of 416 eighth graders (216 girls, 200 boys) for whom a written parental consent was assured. The students attended one of 13 randomly selected public schools (eight urban, five rural) in different regions of the country. As the data was collected over 2 academic years at four time points, the sample size varied somewhat across the measurement occasions. The variation was due to the absence of the students from the classroom at the time of the data collection, for various reasons.</p>
<p>At the beginning of Grade 8 (the first wave of the study), 386 students (51.7% girls) participated (92.8% of the initial sample). Their age ranged from 12.9 years to 14.0 years (<inline-formula id="inline-formula1-0272431612450949">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math1-0272431612450949">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>¯</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>age</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> = 13.46, <italic>SD</italic><sub>age</sub> = .33); 49% of the students were from 12.9 to 13.5 years old. Also, the students’ mothers (<italic>N</italic> = 323) and fathers (<italic>N</italic> = 313) provided data on their education. The average years of completed schooling were 12.7 and 12.4 for mothers and fathers, respectively. We did not restrict the educational level (EL) of parents to a few categories (e.g., finished elementary school, vocational school graduates, high school graduates etc.) but rather used the continuous EL variable in years as restrictively defined SES measures decrease the correlation between SES and academic achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0272431612450949">Sirin, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Six months later, in the second wave of the study, 372 students (52.8% girls) representing 89.4% of the initial sample took part. In the first school term of Grade 9 (the third wave of the study), 373 students (51.2% girls) participated (89.7% of the initial sample) and at the end of Grade 9 the students’ final mathematics grades (<italic>N</italic> = 400; 96.1% of the initial sample) and scores on the NET in mathematics (<italic>N</italic> = 399; 95.9% of the initial sample) were collected.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0272431612450949">
<title>Measures</title>
<sec id="section9-0272431612450949">
<title>Intelligence</title>
<sec id="section10-0272431612450949">
<title>Nonverbal general intelligence</title>
<p>Raven’s Standard Progressive Matrices (SPM; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0272431612450949">Raven, Raven, &amp; Court, 1999</xref>) were used to assess students’ intellectual ability (<italic>g</italic>-factor). The SPM includes five sets of 12 incomplete patterns and the individual’s task is to select the missing piece that would complete the pattern, from a number of options presented beneath. Split-half reliability coefficients of the SPM scores in Slovene adolescents ranged between .92 and .95; mean internal consistency was high (α = .93) and correlations of the SPM with WISC-R ranged from .83 to .92 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0272431612450949">Raven et al., 1999</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0272431612450949">
<title>Personality</title>
<sec id="section12-0272431612450949">
<title>Five robust dimensions of personality</title>
<p>The Slovene adapted and standardized version (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0272431612450949">Zupančič &amp; Kavčič, 2009</xref>) of the Inventory of Child Individual Differences (ICID; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0272431612450949">Halverson et al., 2003</xref>) was completed in a self-report format by the students. The ICID is designed to be an age and culture neutral instrument and it is based on parental free descriptions of their children across seven countries. It includes 108 items which form 15 midlevel personality scales. Each item is rated using a 7-point Likert-type scale (1 = <italic>much less than the average peer or not at all</italic>; 7 = <italic>much more than the average peer</italic>).</p>
<p>Exploratory and confirmatory factor analyses of scores on the Slovene ICID suggested five robust personality scales that are invariant across age groups, and method of assessment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0272431612450949">Knyazev et al., 2008</xref>). Extraversion (capturing midlevel scales of positive emotionality, sociability, activity), conscientiousness (achievement orientation, organized behavior, low distractibility), and openness (openness to experience, intelligence) scales were used for the purpose of the present study. Adolescent self-ratings (ages 12 through 18) for these robust scales show good internal consistency (αs from .83 to .95; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0272431612450949">Zupančič &amp; Kavčič, 2009</xref>), temporal stability over 2 years (mean <italic>r</italic> = .61), interrater agreement (adolescent—mother, adolescent—peer; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0272431612450949">Smrtnik Vitulić &amp; Zupančič, 2010</xref>), links with temperament (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0272431612450949">Halverson at al., 2003</xref>), social behavior, and adjustment problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0272431612450949">Slobodskaya, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0272431612450949">Zupančič &amp; Kavčič, 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0272431612450949">
<title>Student Perceptions of Parental Involvement</title>
<sec id="section14-0272431612450949">
<title>Parental academic pressure and support</title>
<p>The Inventory of Parental Influence (IPI-child version; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0272431612450949">Campbell, 1994</xref>) measures student perceptions of parental involvement in their academic development. In this study, the IPIPart I was used to assess parental academic pressure and parental academic support. Students were asked to rate the parent whom they perceive to be more involved in their academic activities. The items were rated on a 5-point scale (1 = <italic>strongly disagree</italic>; 5 = <italic>strongly agree</italic>). The Slovene student ratings suggested a two-component structure of the IPI Part I (details can be found in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0272431612450949">Puklek Levpušček &amp; Zupančič, 2009</xref>). Followed by a varimax rotation, the inspection of the item loadings revealed that six of the original items of the Parental Support scale did not have satisfactory component loadings. Therefore, the reduced scales were employed. The composition of both IPI scales applied in the present study is described below.</p>
<p>Parental Pressure contains 13 items describing student perceptions of an academically demanding home atmosphere, wherein they experience lots of pressure to maintain high standard of performance at school (e.g., “My parent is never satisfied with my grades”). With the current data, the internal reliability of the scale was high (α = .87).</p>
<p>Parental Support includes seven items of the original scale capturing student-perceived parental interest in adolescents’ school learning and parental encouragement of academic effort (e.g., “My parent takes a big interest in my school work”). Using the current data, the internal reliability appears satisfactory (α = .75).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0272431612450949">
<title>Student Perceptions of the Behavior of Mathematics Teachers</title>
<sec id="section16-0272431612450949">
<title>Academic support</title>
<p>A five-item measure, the Mathematics Teacher’s Academic Support Scale was redesigned from an earlier version of the Teacher Support Scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0272431612450949">Puklek, 2001</xref>). For the purpose of the current study, the items were rephrased in order to describe the teachers’ classroom behavior. The items refer to student perceptions of the teacher’s emotional support, responsiveness, help, and verbal praising when a student does well in mathematics. The introductory sentence “To what extent does your mathematics teacher” is followed by five statements, for example, “offer you help when you face difficulties with your schoolwork in mathematics.” Students responded on a 4-point scale (1 = <italic>not at all</italic>; 4 = <italic>a lot</italic>). The internal reliability of the scale in the present study was good (α = .80).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0272431612450949">
<title>Academic press and teacher mastery goal</title>
<p>Two scales of the Patterns of Adaptive Learning Scale (PALS; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0272431612450949">Midgley et al., 2000</xref>) describing student perceptions of the teacher’s pressure for understanding and the teacher’s mastery goal orientation in a given classroom were used. The items were rephrased in order to assess student perceptions of the mathematics teacher’s behavior. The students responded along a 5-point scale (1 = <italic>not at all</italic>; 5 = <italic>very true</italic>).</p>
<p>Academic Press (five items) refers to student perceptions of the mathematics teacher’s demand for understanding, thorough thinking and for putting full effort into learning (e.g., “My teacher doesn’t let me do just easy work, but makes me think”). The internal consistency estimate of the scale with the current data was good (α = .80) and similar to the estimate reported by the authors of the scale (α = .79; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0272431612450949">Midgley et al., 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Teacher Mastery Goal (seven items) captures the student perceptions of the mathematics teacher’s effort to develop their competence (e.g., “My teacher gives us time to really explore and understand new ideas”). The scale demonstrated considerable internal consistency with middle school and high school US students (α = .83; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0272431612450949">Midgley et al., 2000</xref>) and with the current data on Slovene students (α = .78).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0272431612450949">
<title>Motivational Beliefs About Mathematics</title>
<sec id="section19-0272431612450949">
<title>Academic self-efficacy</title>
<p>The Academic Self-Efficacy scale of the PALS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0272431612450949">Midgley et al., 2000</xref>) was employed, with the original items rephrased to relate specifically to the students’ self-efficacy in mathematics. The five items were responded on a 5-point scale (1 = <italic>not at all true</italic>; 5 = <italic>very true</italic>) and they referred to students’ perceptions of their capability to do class work (e.g., “I can do even the hardest work in mathematics class if I try”). The authors of the original scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0272431612450949">Midgley et al., 2000</xref>) reported on its good internal reliability (α = .78) which was also established using the current data (α = .87).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0272431612450949">
<title>Mathematics Achievement</title>
<p>Final grades and NET scores in mathematics served as indicators of the student’s academic success at the end of their 9-year compulsory basic schooling. Slovene students are graded through oral and written exams from 1 (<italic>fail</italic>) to 5 (<italic>excellent</italic>) by their course teacher, several times over the school year. The grades can be considered as standard criterion-referenced indicators of performance and they constitute a final grade at the end of the academic year. The NET, constructed by the National Testing Committee, offers a summative assessment of knowledge comprising tasks over different mathematics domains which are supposed to be mastered by the students at the end of compulsory basic education. The students’ NET scores (given in percentages) as well as their final grades in mathematics were among selection criteria to enroll in upper secondary education at the time of the study. Both indicators of achievement in mathematics were accounted for because they represent different ways of assessing mathematical knowledge. Also, while teachers use a 5-level grading scale to evaluate academic outcomes, the NET scores are distributed on a 100-point scale and thus provide a more sensitive measure of a student’s performance.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0272431612450949">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>The participating students and their parents were fully informed of the purpose and method of study. Those who did not wish to participate were free to decline despite their parents’ consent. Data were collected at different time points due to the specificity of some measures: Self-efficacy in mathematics and perceptions of the mathematics teacher’s classroom behavior were measured in the middle of the eighth school year to ensure that students had enough experience with learning mathematics and with their mathematics teacher in that particular school year; students’ final grades and NET scores in mathematics were available at the end of the Grade 9. Also, we received permission from school authorities to apply the intelligence test only in Grade 9.</p>
<p>At the beginning of Grade 8, the students filled in questionnaires on personality and parental academic involvement. These questionnaires were completed during the class time (about 45 min) and in the presence of two research assistants. A similar procedure which took about 30 minutes was carried out in the second school term (6 months later) when the students reported on self-efficacy in mathematics and assessed their mathematics teacher’s classroom behavior. In the first school term of Grade 9 (1 year after the beginning of the study) the intelligence test was administered collectively in classrooms during the first school class (about 40 minutes). The procedure was performed by two trained research assistants, according to instructions of the test manual. The students’ final mathematics grades and scores on the NET in mathematics were reported by school administrators at the end of Grade 9, i.e., 22 months after the beginning of the study.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0272431612450949" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section23-0272431612450949">
<title>Descriptive Results and Correlations</title>
<p>The means, standard deviations, and correlations of individual and social variables with students’ academic outcomes (self-efficacy and achievement in mathematics) are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0272431612450949">Table 1</xref>. Paired samples <italic>t</italic> test showed no significant difference between the years of schooling for mothers and fathers, <italic>t</italic>(304) = 1.65. We used an aggregated parental education score (mother’s years of schooling + father’s years of schooling)/2) in further analyses. A few gender differences in the mean levels of variables under study were revealed. Girls perceived a slightly stronger academic support from their mathematics teachers, than boys, <italic>F</italic>(1, 369) = 17.60, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, <inline-formula id="inline-formula2-0272431612450949">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math2-0272431612450949">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>η</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> = .05, who reported on slightly more parental academic pressure than girls, <italic>F</italic>(1, 364) = 7.56, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01, <inline-formula id="inline-formula3-0272431612450949">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math3-0272431612450949">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>η</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> = .02. Considering academic achievement in mathematics, the girls received slightly higher final grades than boys <italic>F</italic>(1, 368) = 8.83, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01, <inline-formula id="inline-formula4-0272431612450949">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math4-0272431612450949">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>η</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> = .023.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0272431612450949" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Descriptive Statistics of All Variables and Correlations With Academic Outcomes.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0272431612450949" xlink:href="10.1177_0272431612450949-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center"><inline-formula id="inline-formula5-0272431612450949">
<mml:math display="inline" id="math5-0272431612450949">
<mml:mover accent="true">
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>¯</mml:mo>
</mml:mover>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center">Self-efficacy</th>
<th align="center">Final grade</th>
<th align="center">NET Grade 9</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">General intelligence</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> SPM</td>
<td>47.52</td>
<td>6.58</td>
<td>.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.51<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Personality</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Extraversion</td>
<td>4.94</td>
<td>.86</td>
<td>.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">**</xref></td>
<td>−.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">**</xref></td>
<td>−.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Conscientiousness</td>
<td>4.77</td>
<td>.73</td>
<td>.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">*</xref></td>
<td>.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Openness</td>
<td>4.93</td>
<td>.73</td>
<td>.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Parental dimensions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Educational level<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0272431612450949">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>12.55</td>
<td>2.51</td>
<td>.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Academic pressure</td>
<td>2.52</td>
<td>.80</td>
<td>−.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>−.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>−.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Academic support</td>
<td>3.88</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>−.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>−.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Math teaching dimensions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Academic support</td>
<td>3.14</td>
<td>.61</td>
<td>.32<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Academic press</td>
<td>3.71</td>
<td>.69</td>
<td>.50<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mastery goal</td>
<td>4.00</td>
<td>.76</td>
<td>.42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Motivational beliefs in math</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Self-efficacy</td>
<td>3.94</td>
<td>.71</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>.41<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
<td>.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Math achievement</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Final Grade</td>
<td>3.55</td>
<td>1.10</td>
<td/>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>.78<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0272431612450949">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> NET Grade 9</td>
<td>61.90</td>
<td>20.18</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0272431612450949">
<p>Note: NET Grade 9 = National Examination Test results in Grade 9.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0272431612450949">
<label>a.</label>
<p>A combined parental educational level score (average years of schooling).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0272431612450949">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Students’ general intelligence was moderately associated with their self-efficacy in mathematics, and it correlated substantially with the two indicators of achievement in mathematics (final grades and NET scores). Among personality traits, extraversion related positively to the students’ self-efficacy in mathematics, but negatively to both measures of achievement in mathematics (all correlations were modest); conscientiousness and openness were moderately associated with academic self-efficacy but modestly with final grades, and openness also displayed modest links with the students’ test scores in mathematics (NET).</p>
<p>Parental education was modestly related to students’ self-efficacy and moderately to their mathematics achievement. Student perceptions of parental academic pressure and support were negatively linked with both indicators of achievement in mathematics, with medium and small-sized correlations, respectively. Student-reported parental pressure showed a moderate and negative relation with students’ self-efficacy in mathematics but parental academic support was not significantly related to self-efficacy beliefs. Three student-perceived classroom behaviors of their teachers (academic support, academic press and mastery goal) were all positively associated with the students’ academic outcomes, moderately with self-efficacy in the course, and modestly with both measures of achievement in mathematics. Students’ self-efficacy in mathematics showed positive relations of a medium size with their final grades and NET scores. Last, final mathematics grades and NET Grade 9 strongly correlated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0272431612450949">
<title>Path Model of Relationships of Intelligence, Personality, Student-Perceived Parental and Teaching Dimensions With Self-Efficacy in Mathematics, and Achievement in Mathematics</title>
<p>A path analysis using structural equation modeling techniques (Mplus 6, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0272431612450949">Muthén &amp; Muthén, 1998-2010</xref>) was applied to determine the proposed (a) direct effects of the students’ general intelligence, self-ratings of personality (extraversion and openness), parental education and student-perceived parental behavior on their achievement in mathematics, and (b) indirect effects of the predictors (intelligence, conscientiousness, openness, student-perceived parental pressure and teacher behaviors) on achievement in mathematics, as mediated by the student self-efficacy in mathematics.</p>
<p>The paths were set according to the hypotheses stated in section, “Aims-hypotheses.” Both the final grade and the NET score were the outcome variable, self-efficacy was the mediating variable, while the remaining variables were included as exogenous variables.</p>
<p>The model parameters were estimated by means of the WLSMV estimator. This robust weighted least squares estimator presents the default estimation method for multilevel data with categorical dependent variables (final grade in our case) in the Mplus program. A clustered (“complex”) analysis was performed to account for the dependencies caused by the fact that several students were taught by a single teacher. Only the student-level model was of interest, thus we neither performed a multilevel modeling in the strict sense nor computed intraclass correlations for the variables in the model. However, the use of the clustered mode of analysis ensured correct estimates of the model coefficients and their standard errors.</p>
<p>In the first step we used the multiple-group modeling to test the hypothesis that the model parameters were the same for both female and male students. Constraining the parameters to equality did not lead to a significant deterioration of the model fit (χ<sup>2</sup> = 35.2, <italic>p</italic> = .05). Since the <italic>p</italic> value barely exceeded the 5% criterion value, we inspected the pattern of path coefficients in both gender groups. The average difference between the standardized path coefficients was .02 and the congruence coefficient between both sets of coefficients exceeded .99. Due to the high similarity of both profiles we decided not to split our sample based on gender, in further analyses.</p>
<p>The fit of the model was acceptable: RMSEA = .056, CFI = .96, WRMSR = .78. The path model explained 43% of the variance in self-efficacy in mathematics, 52% of the variance in final grades, and 47% of the variance in NET scores. However, a high correlation (.62) between residuals still remained, indicating that our predictors did not fully account for the correlation between both measures of achievement in mathematics.</p>
<p>Path model showing the relationship of student intelligence and personality traits, parental education, student-perceived parental and teachers’ behaviors to self-efficacy, and achievement in mathematics is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0272431612450949">Figure 1</xref>. The measures of general intelligence, self-ratings of extraversion, openness, self-efficacy and the three, student-assessed parental variables showed significant direct effects on at least one indicator of achievement in mathematics; intelligence displayed the largest effect, while the effects of student-perceived parental academic support and parental academic pressure, respectively, were the smallest. Standardized indirect effects due to mediation through student-rated academic self-efficacy in mathematics are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0272431612450949">Table 2</xref>. General intelligence, self-ratings of conscientiousness, student perceptions of parental academic pressure and mathematics teacher’s academic press and mastery goal orientation had statistically significant indirect effects on the achievement variables.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0272431612450949" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Path model of relations between intelligence, personality, parental and teaching dimensions, self-efficacy in mathematics, and mathematics achievement.</p>
<p>Note: Only statistically significant standardized path coefficients are reported (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05); NET = National Examination Test. The horizontal position of variables in the path diagram reflects the time of measurement.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0272431612450949-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table2-0272431612450949" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Standardized Indirect Effects.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0272431612450949" xlink:href="10.1177_0272431612450949-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">GI</th>
<th align="center">C</th>
<th align="center">O</th>
<th align="center">EL</th>
<th align="center">PAP</th>
<th align="center">PAS</th>
<th align="center">AS</th>
<th align="center">AP</th>
<th align="center">MG</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Grade</td>
<td>0.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0272431612450949">*</xref></td>
<td>0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0272431612450949">*</xref></td>
<td>0.02</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>−0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0272431612450949">*</xref></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0272431612450949">*</xref></td>
<td>0.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0272431612450949">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NET</td>
<td>0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0272431612450949">*</xref></td>
<td>0.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0272431612450949">*</xref></td>
<td>0.01</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>−0.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0272431612450949">*</xref></td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>0.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0272431612450949">*</xref></td>
<td>0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0272431612450949">*</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0272431612450949">
<p>Note: GI = General intelligence, C = Conscientiousness, O = Openness, EL = Parental educational level, PAP = Parental academic pressure, PAS = Parental academic support, AS = Mathematics teacher’s academic support, AP = Mathematics teacher’s academic pressure, MG = Mathematics teacher’s mastery goal orientation, Grade = Final grade in mathematics, NET = National Examination Test.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0272431612450949">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>More specifically, the path analysis results showed that student intelligence and self-ratings of conscientiousness (but not openness) positively predicted academic self-efficacy in mathematics, as expected in Hypothesis 1. According to Hypothesis 2, self-efficacy in students positively influenced their achievement in mathematics, as measured by either final grades or NET scores. Self-rated extraversion and openness, and intelligence, directly predicted both the final grades and NET scores in mathematics. As proposed by Hypotheses 3 and 4, extraversion showed a direct and negative effect on achievement in the course, and intelligence (but not openness) showed both direct and indirect positive effects on achievement in mathematics. As suggested by Hypothesis 5, conscientiousness had an indirect effect on the two measures of achievement in mathematics (through self-efficacy in mathematics). Student-rated parental academic pressure had a negative effect on the students’ academic self-efficacy but parental academic support, as perceived by the students was not significantly related to their self-efficacy in mathematics (Hypothesis 6 partly rejected). A direct, negative effect of perceived parental academic support, and the direct and indirect negative effects of perceived parental academic pressure on the students’ final grades and NET scores in mathematics were demonstrated; whereas parental education directly and positively affected both indicators of students’ achievement in mathematics (in support to Hypothesis 7).</p>
<p>The student-rated teaching dimensions of academic press and mastery goal (but not academic support) were associated with the students’ academic outcomes, showing the indirect effect on achievement in mathematics, through the students’ self-efficacy. This was as suggested by Hypothesis 8, and thus partially supported.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, indirect effects were small relative to direct effects of the respective variables, indicating that the effects of the predictors under our study, mediated through students’ self-efficacy in mathematics are not among the most important ones in predicting achievement in mathematics.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-0272431612450949" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The study jointly investigated several individual and social factors that are known to contribute to a students’ academic outcome in mathematics, at the end of compulsory basic school education. The predictive model showed a good fit to the data with 43% of the variance explained in academic self-efficacy, 52% of the variance in final mathematics grades and 47% of the variance in NET scores. The model was successful in explaining the final grades which are a reflection of the mathematics teachers’ grading of the students’ knowledge, more so than the NET scores, which represent an external assessment of the students’ mathematical knowledge.</p>
<p>Students’ general intelligence (<italic>g</italic>) and self-ratings of conscientiousness were predictive of their academic self-efficacy in mathematics, which predicted each of the two measures of achievement in mathematics. The effect of <italic>g</italic> on course achievements was mainly direct and it was, in part, mediated through the students’ self-efficacy in mathematics. As proposed, the contribution of self-rated conscientiousness to achievement in mathematics was mediated by the students’ self-efficacy in mathematics, whereas self-ratings of openness and extraversion directly predicted both the final grades and NET scores in mathematics. Among all the predictors considered, achievement in mathematics was most strongly linked to intelligence. This is not surprising given that the learning process at school is <italic>g</italic>-demanding and that <italic>g</italic> is an empirically well-established predictor of academic achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0272431612450949">Jensen, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0272431612450949">Laidra et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0272431612450949">Mackintosh, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0272431612450949">Watkins et al., 2007</xref>), especially in the mathematics domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0272431612450949">Deary et al., 2007</xref>) where analytical and logical abilities, and grasping abstract relations are of particular importance.</p>
<p>Consistent with research suggesting that acquisition and consolidation of academic knowledge depends on ability and personality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0272431612450949">Bratko et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0272431612450949">Chamorro-Premuzic &amp; Furnham, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0272431612450949">Laidra et al., 2007</xref>), our analysis demonstrated the value of FFM traits in predicting academic outcomes in mathematics. Moreover, our findings provide evidence for using personality variables to predict achievement in mathematics, even if intelligence and several academically related social measures are available. It seems likely that less extraverted students may benefit from being less sociable and outgoing, and may perform well in quiet school settings, imposing demands on individual work. Students perceiving themselves as intellectually oriented, quick to understand and learn, may tend to acquire academic content effectively and thus perform better at school tests. Conscientious students, who due to their persistence, effective study habits, attentiveness in the classroom and willingness to put effort into learning, may have an advantage over their less conscientious peers in developing positive academic self-efficacy, which in turn, affects academic achievement.</p>
<p>Among parent-related variables, parents’ education directly affected both indicators of their adolescent children’s achievement in mathematics. The effects of parental education on students’ achievement may be due to more favorable environmental conditions created for children by parents with higher education, relative to those with lower education, e.g., parents’ involvement in teaching mathematics, buying educational supplies, modeling and supporting the child’s intellectual activities, promoting educational values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0272431612450949">Chiu &amp; Xihua, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0272431612450949">Huntsinger, Jose, Liaw, &amp; Ching, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0272431612450949">Sirin, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Negative effects of student-perceived parental academic pressure, on academic self-efficacy and final grades in mathematics were further demonstrated in the present study. Consistent with previous research on adolescents in the domain of mathematics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0272431612450949">Campbell &amp; Mandel, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0272431612450949">Koutsoulis &amp; Campbell, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0272431612450949">Puklek Levpušček &amp; Zupančič, 2009</xref>), students who reported higher parental academic pressure, in our study had lower self-efficacy and were given lower grades by their mathematics teachers. In general, Slovene parents are strongly involved in their children’s education, yet they put more emphasis on the student’s grades rather than his/her knowledge itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0272431612450949">Japelj Pavešić, 2004</xref>). This may reflect the fact that grades, at the end of compulsory education are important criteria for entry academically demanding upper secondary schools. In an attempt to ensure good educational opportunities for their children, parents of poor achievers may exert more pressure on adolescents, than parents of high achievers. According to our expectations in the present study, a detrimental effect of student perceptions of parental dissatisfaction, criticism and unrealistic expectations about their achievement in mathematics, was also mediated through the students’ negative self-beliefs about their own ability to perform mathematical tasks.</p>
<p>Contrary to most studies that suggest a beneficial role of student-perceived parental supportive involvement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0272431612450949">Campbell &amp; Mandel, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0272431612450949">Koutsoulis &amp; Campbell, 2001</xref>), parental academic support, as rated by our students was not significantly related to self-efficacy beliefs about their mathematical ability, but it was significantly and negatively linked to their achievement in mathematics. However, the latter is consonant with findings on the same sample of eighth grade Slovene adolescents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0272431612450949">Puklek Levpušček &amp; Zupančič, 2009</xref>). Parental enthusiasm experienced by students about their education, pride and trust in their schoolwork, and parental aspirations and values placed on education, may present the most proximal variables related to adolescents’ positive academic outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0272431612450949">Fan &amp; Chen, 2001</xref>). These aspects of student-perceived parental involvement are captured by the original IPI Parental Support scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0272431612450949">Campbell, 1994</xref>); however not all aspects, such as aspirations and values, of parental involvement were replicated to belong to the corresponding scale used in the Slovene cultural/educational setting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0272431612450949">Puklek Levpušček &amp; Zupančič, 2009</xref>). As described in the Method section, the Parent Support scale employed in the present study was confined to parental interest in students’ academic work and support of the effort put into learning. Our findings thus imply that parental academic support should not be treated as a uniform construct, because its dimensions appear to contribute to students’ academic achievement in different ways. At least in a Slovene home atmosphere that is on the whole academically supportive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0272431612450949">Japelj Pavešić, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0272431612450949">Puklek Levpušček &amp; Zupančič, 2009</xref>), student perceptions of strong parental interest in their schoolwork and encouragement of intensive learning, do not contribute to better academic outcomes in mathematics, as demonstrated by our present analysis. Rather, when experienced intensely, this kind of student-perceived parental support might be counterproductive in enhancing students’ academic achievement and/or may also reflect a student-to-parent effect, proposing that those who experience problems with school performance evoke more parental support and attention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0272431612450949">Grolnick et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0272431612450949">Pomerantz, Moorman, &amp; Litwack, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Two of the three student-rated teaching dimensions under our study were associated with students’ outcomes in mathematics, showing indirect effects on both measures of achievement in mathematics through students’ self-efficacy. In support of our findings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0272431612450949">Puklek Levpušček &amp; Zupančič, 2009</xref>) on the important role teachers play in promoting the students’ self-efficacy in mathematics which, in turn, influenced achievement in mathematics at the eighth grade, the present study indicates that, student-perceived mathematics teachers’ mastery goal and academic press for understanding the course content, continue to affect adolescents’ performance in mathematics one year later, by enhancing their self-efficacy in mathematics.</p>
<p>A significant mediating role of self-efficacy in mathematics on course achievement suggests that individual factors (intelligence and conscientiousness), and student-assessed social factors of classroom behavior exhibited by the mathematics teacher, may create positive beliefs in students about their own ability to learn and/or perform mathematical tasks. In turn, students’ self-efficacy in mathematics enhances their achievement in mathematics. However, an effect in the opposite direction may not be precluded. Underachievers in mathematics may, for example, perceive their efforts as less effective than their peers who do better in mathematics. Consequently, the former are more likely to receive negative social feedback about their capabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0272431612450949">Usher &amp; Pajares, 2009</xref>). Nevertheless, the mathematical achievements of our students were mainly predicted directly and the mediated effects were rather small.</p>
<p>While we recognize our contribution to the extant knowledge about the role that individual differences in students, and their perceptions of parental and teacher academically related characteristics play in an adolescents’ academic performance, we are also aware of limitations to this study that require further investigation. First, the data on student personality traits and self-efficacy in mathematics, parental academic involvement, and mathematics teachers’ classroom behavior were provided by the adolescents themselves and may therefore include the same-rater bias. Other sources of information (e.g., parent, teacher, peers) will therefore be appreciated in further inquiries. However, we collected the same-informant reports at different time points which, at least partly, decreased the “within-occasion informant” bias. Relying on two different measures of achievement in mathematics was also an advantage of our analysis.</p>
<p>Second, although our study was designed prospectively, the findings do not allow implications of causality. We only tested the extent to which the observed relations among variables can be predicted from the proposed model. Student-to-parent/teacher effects should also be addressed in future research. Poor academic achievement could contribute to low academic self-efficacy and both could, for example, increase student-perceived parental pressure on adolescents to do better in school and/or decrease teachers’ pressure on the students for understanding beyond the levels of basic knowledge. Longitudinal studies, designed to account for bidirectionality of the effects using a cross-lagged design still await future inquiry.</p>
<p>Third, our exploration focused on student perceptions of parental and teacher behaviors representing direct involvement by the adults in the academic life of the adolescents. Simultaneously accounting for other relevant factors such as school-level variables, peer characteristics, and parenting style, would provide a more complex and comprehensive explanation of adolescents’ academic achievement. Whether our findings are confined to specific cultural/educational contexts also calls for additional examination.</p>
<p>In conclusion, this study supports the important role of the students’ general intelligence and personality traits, parental education, student-perceived parental academic involvement and teacher classroom behavior on performance in mathematics. Student intelligence, extraversion and openness, and parental education displayed substantial direct effects on achievement in mathematics, while the effect of student perceptions of parental academic involvement was smaller. Furthermore, course specific self-efficacy had an important mediating role in students’ achievement in mathematics. Intelligence, conscientiousness, lower levels of perceived parental academic pressure, and positive perceptions of the teacher’s press for understanding and mastery goal in mathematics may engender positive beliefs in students about their own ability to learn or perform mathematical tasks. In turn, self-efficacy in mathematics enhances achievement in mathematics. The findings certainly do not rule out an effect in the opposite direction, especially with regard to the influence of students’ success and self-efficacy in mathematics on the perceived parental and teacher behavior.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Melita Puklek Levpušček</bold>, PhD, is an associate professor in educational psychology at the Department of Psychology at the University of Ljubljana. Her research focus is on psychosocial development in adolescence: social anxiety, individuation in relation to parents and peers, and academic motivation. She is also interested in the effects of multiple social contexts (family, peers, school) on adolescent development.</p>
<p><bold>Maja Zupančič</bold>, PhD, is full professor of developmental psychology at the Department of Psychology, University of Ljubljana. Her recent research work is in the development of child and adolescent personality traits.</p>
<p><bold>Gregor Sočan</bold>, PhD, is an assistant professor in psychological methodology at the Department of Psychology at the University of Ljubljana.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ackerman</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haggestad</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Intelligence, personality and interests: Evidence for overlapping traits</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>121</volume>, <fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>245</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alarcón</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Knopik</surname><given-names>V. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeFries</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Covariation of mathematics achievement and general cognitive ability in twins</article-title>. <source>Journal of School Psychology</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <source>Social foundations of thought and action. A social cognitive theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Self-efficacy: The exercise of control</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Freeman</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barbaranelli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caprara</surname><given-names>V. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rabasca</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pastorelli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>A questionnaire for measuring the Big Five in late childhood</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>645</fpage>-<lpage>664</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bratko</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chamorro-Premuzic</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saks</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Personality and school performance: Incremental validity of self- and peer-rating over intelligence</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>-<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brekelmans</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wubbels</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Student performance, attitudes, instructional strategies and teacher-communication style</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wubbels</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Do you know what you look like? Interpersonal relations in education</source> (pp. <fpage>56</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palmer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Developing cross-cultural/cross-national instruments: Cross-national methods and procedures</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Educational Research</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>775</fpage>-<lpage>784</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mandel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Connecting math achievement to parental influences</article-title>. <source>Contemporary Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>64</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chamorro-Premuzic</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Furnham</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Personality and intellectual competence</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chamorro-Premuzic</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Furnham</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Intellectual competence and the intelligent personality: A third way in differential psychology</article-title>. <source>Review of General Psychology</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>251</fpage>-<lpage>267</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klassen</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Relations of mathematics self-concept and its calibration with mathematics achievement: Cultural differences among fifteen-year-olds in 34 countries</article-title>. <source>Learning and Instruction</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>2</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xihua</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Family and motivation effects on mathematics achievement: Analyses of students in 41 countries</article-title>. <source>Learning and Instruction</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>321</fpage>-<lpage>336</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deary</surname><given-names>I. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strand</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Intelligence and educational achievement</article-title>. <source>Intelligence</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Parental involvement and students’ academic achievement: A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Educational Psychology Review</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fast</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bocian</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cardullo</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rettig</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Does math self-efficacy mediate the effect of the perceived classroom environment on standardized math test performance?</article-title> <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>102</volume>, <fpage>729</fpage>-<lpage>740</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Furnham</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chamorro-Premuzic</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McDougall</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Personality, cognitive ability, and beliefs about intelligence as predictors of academic performance</article-title>. <source>Learning and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goodnow</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Classroom belonging among early adolescent students: Relationships to motivation and achievement</article-title>. <source>Journal of Early Adolescence</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gonzalez-DeHass</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>P. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doan Holbein</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Examining the relationship between parental involvement and student motivation</article-title>. <source>Educational Psychology Review</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grolnick</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>The inner resources for school performance: Motivational mediators of children’s perceptions of their parents</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>508</fpage>-<lpage>517</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grolnick</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slowiaczek</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Parental involvement in children’s schooling: A multidimensional conceptualization and motivational model</article-title>. <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>252</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Halverson</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Havill</surname><given-names>V. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Victor</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pavlopoulos</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Wen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Personality structure as derived from parental ratings of free descriptions of children: The Inventory of Child Individual Differences</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality</source>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>995</fpage>-<lpage>1026</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huntsinger</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jose</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liaw</surname><given-names>F.-R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ching</surname><given-names>W.-D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Cultural differences in early mathematics learning: A comparison of Euro-American, Chinese-American, and Taiwan-Chinese Families</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Behavioral Development</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>371</fpage>-<lpage>388</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Japelj Pavešić</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>. (<year>2004</year>). <article-title xml:lang="sl">Znanje, ocene in učenje v osemletki in devetletki</article-title> [<trans-title>Knowledge, grades and studying in the 9-year and 8-year elementary schools</trans-title>]. <source>Šolsko polje</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>5/6</issue>), <fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>130</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>The g factor: The science of mental ability</source>. <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Praeger</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Midgley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The relationship between perceptions of classroom goal structure and early adolescents’ affect in school: The mediating role of coping strategies</article-title>. <source>Learning and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>212</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Knyazev</surname><given-names>G. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zupančič</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slobodskaya</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Child personality in Slovenia and Russia: Structure and mean level of traits in parent and self-ratings</article-title>. <source>Journal of Cross Cultural Psychology</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>317</fpage>-<lpage>334</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kokko</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pulkkinen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Child personality characteristics and selection into long-term unemployment in Finnish and Swedish longitudinal samples</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Behavioral Development</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>134</fpage>-<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koutsoulis</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Family processes affect students’ motivation, and science and math achievement in Cypriot high schools</article-title>. <source>Structural Equation Modelling</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>108</fpage>-<lpage>127</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laidra</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pullmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allik</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Personality and intelligence as predictors of academic achievement: A cross-sectional study from elementary to secondary school</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>441</fpage>-<lpage>451</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miyashita</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karasawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mashima</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oettingen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Azuma</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baltes</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The links among action-control beliefs, intellective skill, and school performance in Japanese, US, and German school children</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Behavioral Development</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>High IQ is sufficient to explain the high achievements in math and science of the East Asian peoples</article-title>. <source>Learning and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>567</fpage>-<lpage>568</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mackintosh</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>IQ and human intelligence</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marchant</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paulson</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rothlisberg</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Relations of middle school students’ perceptions of family and school contexts with academic achievement</article-title>. <source>Psychology in the School</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>505</fpage>-<lpage>519</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trautwein</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lüdtke</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Köller</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baumert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Integration of multidimensional self-concept and core personality constructs: Construct validation and relations to well-being and achievement</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality</source>, <volume>74</volume>, <fpage>403</fpage>-<lpage>456</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCrae</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Personality trait structure as human universal</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>-<lpage>516</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mervielde</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Fruyt</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Assessing children’s traits with the Hierarchical Personality Inventory for Children</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>De Raad</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perugini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Big Five Assessment</source> (pp. <fpage>129</fpage>-<lpage>146</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Gottingen, Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hogrefe &amp; Hoger</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mervielde</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buyst</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Fruyt</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The validity of the Big-Five as a model for teachers’ ratings of individual differences among children aged 4-12 years</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>525</fpage>-<lpage>534</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Middleton</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Midgley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Beyond motivation: Middle school students’ perceptions of press for understanding in math</article-title>. <source>Contemporary Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>-<lpage>391</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Midgley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maehr</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hruda</surname><given-names>L. Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderman</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderman</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Urdan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Manual for the Patterns of Adaptive Learning Scales</source>. <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Michigan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muthén</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muthén</surname><given-names>B. O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998-2010</year>). <source>Mplus user’s guide</source> (<edition>6th ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Muthén &amp; Muthén</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paunonen</surname><given-names>S. V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Big Five personality predictors of post-secondary academic performance</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>971</fpage>-<lpage>990</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pajares</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kranzler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Self-efficacy beliefs and general mental ability in mathematical problem solving</article-title>. <source>Contemporary Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>426</fpage>-<lpage>443</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pajares</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Mathematics self-efficacy and mathematics outcomes: The need for specificity of assessment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Counselling Psychology</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>190</fpage>-<lpage>198</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Early adolescents’ perceptions of the classroom social environment, motivational beliefs, and engagement</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>99</volume>, <fpage>83</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pomerantz</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moorman</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Litwack</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The how, whom, and why of parents’ involvement in children’s academic lives: More is not always better</article-title>. <source>Review of Educational Research</source>, <volume>77</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>-<lpage>410</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Puklek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source xml:lang="sl">Razvoj psihološkega osamosvajanja mladostnikov v različnih socialnih kontekstih</source> [<trans-source>The development of adolescent psychological individuation in different social contexts</trans-source>] (Unpublished doctoral dissertation). <publisher-name>University of Ljubljana</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Ljubljana, Slovenia</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Puklek Levpušček</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zupančič</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Math achievement in early adolescence: The role of parental involvement, teachers’ behavior, and students’ motivational beliefs about math</article-title>. <source>Journal of Early Adolescence</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>541</fpage>-<lpage>570</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Court</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source xml:lang="sl">Priročnik za Ravenove progresivne matrice in besedne lestvice</source> [<trans-source>Raven’s Progressive matrices and verbal scales. Manual</trans-source>]. <publisher-loc>Ljubljana, Slovenia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychological Test Publishing, Assessment, and Consultancy</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rinderman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neubauer</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Processing speed, intelligence, creativity, and school performance: Testing of causal hypothesis using structural equation models</article-title>. <source>Intelligence</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>573</fpage>-<lpage>589</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Predicting academic achievement with cognitive ability</article-title>. <source>Intelligence</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>83</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schunk</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pajares</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The development of academic self-efficacy</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wigfield</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Development of achievement motivation</source> (pp. <fpage>16</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>). <publisher-loc>San Diego, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Slobodskaya</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The associations among the big five, behavioural inhibition and behavioural approach systems and child and adolescent adjustment in Russia</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>913</fpage>-<lpage>924</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Granville</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dika</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Mathematics and science achievement: Effects of motivation, interest, and academic engagement</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Research</source>, <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>323</fpage>-<lpage>332</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sirin</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Socioeconomic status and academic achievement: A meta-analytic review of research</article-title>. <source>Review of Educational Research</source>, <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>417</fpage>-<lpage>453</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smrtnik Vitulić</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zupančič</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Robust and mid-level personality traits as predictors of adolescents’ academic achievement in secondary school</article-title>. <source>Suvremena psihologija</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>203</fpage>-<lpage>219</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smrtnik Vitulić</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zupančič</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Personality traits as a predictor of academic achievement in adolescents</article-title>. <source>Educational Studies</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lamborn</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dornbusch</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Darling</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Impact of parenting practices on adolescent achievement: Authoritative parenting, school involvement, and encouragement to succeed</article-title>. <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>1266</fpage>-<lpage>1281</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steinmayr</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bipp</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spinath</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Goal orientations predict academic performance beyond intelligence and personality</article-title>. <source>Learning and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>196</fpage>-<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trautwein</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lüdtke</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schnyder</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niggli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Different forces, same consequence: Conscientiousness and competence beliefs are independent predictors of academic effort and achievement</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>1115</fpage>-<lpage>1128</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Urdan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Midgley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Changes in the perceived classroom goal structure and patterns of adaptive learning during early adolescence</article-title>. <source>Contemporary Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>524</fpage>-<lpage>551</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Urdan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schoenfelder</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Classroom effects on student motivation: Goal structures, social relationships, and competence beliefs</article-title>. <source>Journal of School Psychology</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>331</fpage>-<lpage>349</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Usher</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pajares</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Sources of self-efficacy in mathematics: A validation study</article-title>. <source>Contemporary Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>89</fpage>-<lpage>101</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DuBois</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The relation between self beliefs and academic achievement: A meta-analytic review</article-title>. <source>Educational Psychologist</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>111</fpage>-<lpage>133</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vitaro</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trembley</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brendgen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larose</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Kindergarten disruptive behaviors, protective factors, and educational achievement in early adulthood</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>617</fpage>-<lpage>629</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Canivez</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Psychometric intelligence and achievement: A cross-lagged panel analysis</article-title>. <source>Intelligence</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wentzel</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Student motivation in middle school: The role of perceived pedagogical caring</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>89</volume>, <fpage>411</fpage>-<lpage>419</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>The relation between socioeconomic status and academic achievement</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>461</fpage>-<lpage>481</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Woolfolk</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Educational psychology</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Allyn &amp; Bacon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zupančič</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kavčič</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source xml:lang="sl">Vprašalnik medosebnih razlik pri otrocih in mladostnikih VMR-OM: Priročnik</source> [<trans-source>Inventory of child and adolescent individual differences ICID: Manual</trans-source>]. <publisher-loc>Ljubljana, Slovenia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychological Test Publishing, Assessment, and Consultancy</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zupančič</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kavčič</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Predicting early academic achievement: The role of higher- versus lower-order personality traits</article-title>. <source>Psihologija</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>-<lpage>306</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0272431612450949">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zupančič</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vidmar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title xml:lang="sl">Osebnostne poteze v otroštvu; vzdolžna in sočasna napoved spoznavnih značilnosti pri prvošolcih</article-title> [<trans-title>Personality traits in childhood: Longitudinal and contemporaneous prediction of cognitive characteristics in firstgraders</trans-title>]. <source>School Field</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>