<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjce</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Contemporary Ethnography</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0891-2416</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-5414</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0891241611429943</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0891241611429943</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Ringing the Chord</article-title>
<subtitle>Sentimentality and Nostalgia among Male Singers</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>Jeffrey Eugene</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0891241611429943">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0891241611429943"><label>1</label>University of Arkansas, Little Rock, AR, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0891241611429943">Jeffrey Eugene Nash, University of Arkansas, 2801 South University Ave, Little Rock, AR 72204 Email: <email>jenash@ualr.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>581</fpage>
<lpage>606</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Singing in barbershop choruses and quartets evokes sentimentality and nostalgia as a means of interpreting the present and establishing an identity as a barbershop singer. In choruses devoted to the preservation of a highly stylized form of singing, a gendered social context shapes the acquisition of identities in the development of relationships. An analysis of the barbershop experience reveals that men, particularly those with common backgrounds, are routinely involved in expressing deep emotions through ritualized means, allowing them to maintain a version of traditional masculine identity.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>barbershop music</kwd>
<kwd>nostalgia</kwd>
<kwd>sentimentality</kwd>
<kwd>masculinity</kwd>
<kwd>identities</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>What do men accomplish when they devote significant portions of their leisure time to learning songs with sentimental lyrics, standing close to, singing in close harmony, and even dancing with other men? Is this hobby, called barbershop singing, at odds or congruent with members’ sense of masculinity? Is emotional involvement with the sentimental music that characterizes barbershop singing outside the conventional template for manly activities? I address these questions in this article, as I explore my own emotional experiences as a barbershop singer and those of my fellow singers.</p>
<p>When I first visited a barbershop chorus chapter meeting, I was asked to stand in front of the chorus as a visitor. I did not know what to expect. The chorus, on the director’s cue, sang to me: “You’re as welcome as the flowers in May . . . Come along and sing your cares away.” “Flowers in May?” I felt embarrassed and wondered what is going on here? This chorus composed of white, conservative, middle-aged men exhibited uncharacteristic warmth and openness. How can such obviously masculine men be so devoted to a leisure time activity that fosters the preservation of a form of music dripping with emotions of loss, sadness, grief, and, at the other end of the emotional continuum, joy, hope, and excitation? This musical hobby, so oddly and purposefully out of the mainstream, affords an opportunity to observe and understand masculine identity and expressivity. Through a thick description of the barbershop world, I characterize ways that conventional masculinity frames and expresses emotions, thereby adding depth to sociological understandings of the relationship between men’s emotions and their gendered relationships.</p>
<sec id="section1-0891241611429943" sec-type="methods">
<title>My Method: A Long and Winding Road</title>
<p>My study is participatory and ethnographic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0891241611429943">Spradley 1980</xref>). I rely extensively, however, on my personal experiences as a barbershop singer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0891241611429943">Anderson 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0891241611429943">Kleinman and Copp 1993</xref>). I am also opportunistic in that I take advance of naturally occurring events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0891241611429943">Riemer 1977</xref>), and I am autoethnographic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0891241611429943">Anderson 2006</xref>) in that I made purposeful attempts to interpret my own experiences conceptually.</p>
<p>My method for conducting research emerged from my immersion in the world of barbershop singing. For example, at particularly poignant moments when a chorus member revealed something personal, such as an illness or a family tragedy, I was both sympathetic and observant. I empathized, yet I remained analytic. For example, later in the article, I analyze the way a chorus member turns his own divorce into a way of “feeling” the separation that the lyrics he is singing depict.</p>
<p>Autoethnography, as I employ the method, highlights the emotional aspects of everyday life settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0891241611429943">Dieser 2008</xref>). Recalling experiences, telling stories, and reflecting on what being a barbershopper means created opportunities to interpret “a culture or social group by producing highly personalized and revealing texts; it examines social phenomena holistically and underscores how social histories influence identity development” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0891241611429943">Dieser 2008</xref>, 293-94).</p>
<p>Much of the descriptive information in this analysis consists of recollected or “delayed” observations. I preserve in my accounts and narratives both my feelings and thoughts in order to depict the world of barbershop singing. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0891241611429943">Vasconcelos (2011)</xref> points out, autoethnography covers a wide variety of ways to convert autobiography into a method for doing research. She writes:
<disp-quote>
<p>Autoethnographers do not lose sight of their aim to explore and investigate the self. Since this research method makes room for various analytical lenses and understandings, the autoethnographic hybrid product can assume multifarious shapes and scopes, on a continuum ranging from researchers sharing personal experiences with their respondents, which then become part of the larger research narrative, to wholly autobiographical projects, to those that explicitly combine autobiographical data and fiction. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0891241611429943">Vasconcelos 2011</xref>, 417)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>My autoethnography falls more on the analytic side of a continuum from self-revelation to analysis. I provide “observational evidence” for how the particular experiences of barbershoppers relate to larger concerns of understanding self in social context; in this case, the self is situated in emotional expressivity. Because I suspected that announcing that I am conducting research would alter the naturally occurring interaction among members, I conducted my research covertly, that is, as a regular chorus member (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0891241611429943">Lugosi 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>However, I have made no effort to conceal my desire to write about my experiences, and chorus members with whom I sing know that I am a sociologist. Furthermore, I have revealed to several chorus members that I have presented papers on barbershop singing at professional sociology meetings.</p>
<sec id="section2-0891241611429943">
<title>Documentation</title>
<p>To supplement my experiences and observations, I gathered printed materials on barbershopping, and I took extensive notes at workshops and sessions with judges who evaluated our chorus performances. After rehearsals, I wrote notes recording my reactions to things said, times when I laughed uncontrollably at jokes and gestures, and times when my feelings were hurt, when I was especially touched by the lyrics of a song, or the special way that song was performed. I attempted to record remarks <italic>verbatim</italic>, from recollection. I also collected several years of the Barbershop Harmony Society magazine, <italic>The Harmonizer</italic>, handouts from workshops, a small library of books about barbershop music and a satchel full of sheet music.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0891241611429943">
<title>My Journey</title>
<p>My personal motivation for joining such a group began with nostalgic memories of my father’s quartet rehearsing in our family living room in Tulsa, Oklahoma. On my sixtieth birthday, for reasons I cannot fully recall, I decided to see if there was a barbershop chorus in my town. I had always found solace and comfort listening to ballads on the record album of the 1964 International quartet competition I purchased when I was an undergraduate student. Listening to that album constituted my main exposure to the barbershop world for more than thirty years. I did, however, sing in a calypso quartet in high school, and my father taught us one barbershop song, which we performed on a talent show.</p>
<p>While looking for a barbershop chorus to join, I ran across a badly out of date web page. After several unsuccessful attempts to find a rehearsal, I located two members of the local chorus. They invited me to visit their regular weekly rehearsal. A couple of rehearsals later, I was invited to audition with the chorus director, and I was asked to become a member of the chapter. Membership, it turns out, entailed more than learning, practicing, and performing music. Instead, it became a socialization process by which I eventually sounded and felt like a barbershopper.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0891241611429943">
<title>Acquiring a Barbershop Habitus</title>
<p>Over the course of eight years, I became aware that I have acquired a barbershop habitus—a set of distinctive social, cognitive, and physical competencies associated with being part of social structures and organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0891241611429943">Bourdieu 1984</xref>). Habitus, in this incidence, refers to “the practical sense,” or the ability to function effectively within a given social field—knowing how, rather than knowing what (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0891241611429943">Lovell 2000</xref>, 27). Throughout this article, I rely on my habitus to produce realistic accounts of the barbershop experience. Because of my socialization, I can produce examples of verbal expressions, depict the details of chorus rehearsals, and reproduce the feelings of fellow barbershoppers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0891241611429943">Agar 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0891241611429943">Spradley 1980</xref>).</p>
<p>I began singing with a barbershop chorus to connect with memories of my father, to find a hobby that would allow escape from my ordinary routines, and to engage in an activity that I really enjoy, namely singing with men with whom I shared a passion for a particular style of music. After several years of participation, I became intrigued by my own emotional experiences, my reactions to singing sentimental songs and to my responses to expressing emotions through vocalization and gesturing.</p>
<p>When I decided to write about these experiences, I was instructed by an editor of a journal to secure approval from my local Institutional Review Board. I decided to ask for an exemption on the grounds that (1) that my work is observational, conducted in an open, public, impersonal setting; and (2) members of choruses I sing with are aware that I am writing articles about barbershopping, and they are supportive of my efforts; and (3) my topics of study deal with abstract matters such as the sentimentality of the music and rituals of barbershop singing. Finally, (4) I gathered the observations I use following standard practices for conducting ethnographic research; that is, I use pseudonyms, disguise place and personal identities, and protect the confidentiality of my informants.</p>
<p>The first chorus I joined was in a Midwestern city where I was living, and after I moved from that location, I joined another chorus in the capital of a Southern state. I have traveled hundreds of miles to sing with my chorus in competition with other choruses. During rehearsals and performances, I have experienced a wide range of emotions from pride to embarrassment, and I have observed others experiencing and expressing strong feelings. While I intentionally avoided formal interviews with chorus members in order to maintain the “public and open” aspects of my observations, I have participated in hundreds of naturally occurring conversations about barbershop singing and performances.</p>
<p>In one chorus, I served as an officer, and in the other, as a board member, and in each chorus, I volunteered in a number of other supportive roles, such as putting up and taking down risers for rehearsals, selling tickets to performances, managing our annual scholarship competitions, or selling barbershop paraphernalia at district competitions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0891241611429943">
<title>Discovering Manly Singing</title>
<p>I set for myself an analytic task of understanding how conventionally masculine males could be preoccupied with sentimentality and nostalgia in this hobby, and how they bond without crossing into gay identities. In order to frame feelings and versions of the past in a masculine context, I turned to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0891241611429943">Kimmel (2006)</xref>, who contends that as society changes, older versions of manhood are challenged and new versions emerge. The new versions are often portrayed as aligned and consistent with the realities of existing social structure, in that they reflect changes in larger society such as employment patterns and trends in dating and marriage, while the older versions are seen as anachronistic, dissonant with the requirements of intimate relationships, and resistant to egalitarian societal trends (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0891241611429943">Anderson 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>According the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0891241611429943">Kimmel (2008)</xref>, men who resist change are often portrayed as remote, distant, angry, and potentially violent. Even the bonds that tie men together (masculine solidarity) are said to emerge from the crucibles of competition, sports teams (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0891241611429943">Messner 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0891241611429943">2002</xref>), the experience of combat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0891241611429943">Hodgson 1999</xref>), and corporate liaisons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0891241611429943">Beasley 2008</xref>). Hence, these ties are themselves potentially destructive, derisive of others, and emotionally flat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0891241611429943">Connell 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>The men of the barbershop hobby are not destructive. They resist social change, however, especially in their choice to participate in an organization with the explicit goal of preserving an “out-of date” musical form. And from my discussions with wives and friends of barbershoppers, in their everyday lives these men were more often than not emotionally restrained and curtailed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0891241611429943">Scheff 1997</xref>). My assumptions about how they hid their emotions within conventional expression of masculinity seemed well founded. However, I began to see that masculinity might be expressed in many different forms and with varying contents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0891241611429943">Connell and Messerschmidt 2005</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section6-0891241611429943">
<title>The Christian Connection</title>
<p>Since approximately 80 percent of the men in the barbershop choruses that I studied are self-identified protestant Christians, I thought that understanding how conservative Christian versions of masculinity adapt to context might provide clues to understanding how barbershoppers think about manly singing. In their study of what counts as “manly” among conservative Christians, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0891241611429943">Gallagher and Wood (2005)</xref> interviewed both men and women about what a male Christian should be according to their reading of a popular Christian book (<italic>Wild at Heart</italic> by John Elridge, 2001). They discovered that the slightly dangerous, aggressive, and adventuresome masculinity that the book advocates represents a revival of the older versions of the Christian self-made man. The <italic>Wild at Heart</italic> version of masculinity that the book presents is a reaction against “the rationalized nature of paid employment, as well as the responsible and ‘feminized’ expectations of Promise Keepers’ ideal of servant leadership and involved fatherhood” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0891241611429943">Gallagher and Wood 2005</xref>, 135).</p>
<p>Studies such as those of the conservative Promise Keepers movement pertain to my experiences with barbershop singing since they reveal the complicated and resilient character of deeply held belief systems. These studies reveal conservative Christian movements to be, in large measure, attempts to maintain conventional meanings of masculinity in the face of profound changes in employment that threaten the central role of men as breadwinners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0891241611429943">Donovan 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0891241611429943">Heath 2003</xref>). Furthermore, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0891241611429943">Gallagher and Smith (1999)</xref> illustrate that conservative men are willing to make changes in their lives on an interactional and personal level when these changes do not challenge the foundations of their sense of masculinity. They change, but they do not
<disp-quote>
<p>grapple with the structural conditions that undergird their privilege. Their worldview follows from a tradition of American Evangelical Christianity that focuses on individuals rather than social structure. Concentrating on individual spirituality may not be a conscious attempt to maintain power. Yet the lack of attention to structural inequality does, in fact, reinforce existing power relations. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0891241611429943">Heath 2003</xref>, 440)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Conservative men adapt to social change in many ways. For instance, in the pursuit of understanding underlying forces in antigay campaigns among conservative Christians, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0891241611429943">Stein (2005)</xref> shows that images of masculinity result in new forms of homophobia that are amalgams of traditional Christian beliefs and values and feminist criticisms. For example, Christian men may condemn blatant discrimination of gay people, yet hold tenaciously to values about the authority of men over their own families. Stein depicts the genesis of homophobias as evolving from resistance to challenges to traditional Christian beliefs and values about masculinity. Her research underscores the fluid nature of traditional images of masculinity, alongside the persistence of certain core attributes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0891241611429943">
<title>Mutable Masculinity</title>
<p>My survey of recent literature on masculinity suggests that interpretations of masculinity accommodate a wide range of variant meanings within the framework of “traditional masculinity” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0891241611429943">Copes and Hochstetler 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0891241611429943">Kaplan 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0891241611429943">Leyser 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0891241611429943">Schwalbe 1996b</xref>). Core masculine values such as emotional detachment and patriarchic attitudes persist through and can even strengthen during participation in organizations and interactional settings that seem contradictory to these values. Conservative Christian men, it seems, adapt to threats to their worldviews in ways that allow them to maintain their foundational beliefs and continue to function in contemporary society.</p>
<p>As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0891241611429943">Kimmel (2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0891241611429943">2008</xref>) points out, men may learn how to accommodate social change and remain masculine within all-male spaces. In these spaces, men play out their versions of manhood without having to defend them. The male space, then, can be both a refuge from and a defense against perceived social change. I learned that barbershopping could be such a space in which conventional men may experience deep emotions consistent with their senses of manhood. Within that space, I discovered a social form that the Christian men I sang with called “manly singing.”</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0891241611429943">
<title>Doing Manly Singing</title>
<p>Barbershop singers, and particularly chorus directors, repeatedly refer to barbershop singing as “manly singing,” by which they mean a full, rich blend of voices with a dominant bass component, and a particular stress on the ringing chord, which I will discuss later. To understand fully what “manly” means, I will describe the context in which the phrase is typically used.</p>
<p>Truck drivers, carpenters, and brick masons stood at my sides at rehearsals and performances. Bantering, ritualized insults, handshaking, and an occasional mildly off-color word play (not fit to do when wives visit) are common in the weekly rehearsals. For example, when practicing chorography for a song, learning when to “clap” in a song, nearly always elicits some snicker from a chorus member—an allusion to the sexually transmitted disease. Or, a ginger snap cookie becomes a “gender snap” in an elliptical allusion to sexual intercourse. As described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0891241611429943">Connell (2005)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0891241611429943">Connell and Messerschmidt (2005)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0891241611429943">Messner (1993)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0891241611429943">Ross and Mirowsky (1984)</xref>, the choruses in which I sang were composed of men with traditional masculine identities.</p>
<p>In their appearances, barbershop singers would never be mistaken for avant-garde musicians: no earrings, flamboyant tattoos, or grungy fashion. Rehearsals often start with the singing of the “Old Songs,” which depicts a bygone place where even the police say, “How do you do?” Sentimental expressions abound in the lyrics of songs and in the affable greetings extended to visitors and members alike. The music itself has a predominant bass (manly) sound, and men who sing the high tenor parts are often kidded about using their “girlie” voices (a reference to singing in falsetto).</p>
<p>Barbershop singing is a highly stylized form of four-part harmony, sung <italic>a cappella</italic>. While there are several sounds that characterize the style, the “ringing chord” is the most important. The ring in a barbershop chord is an acoustical effect, referred to variously as expanded sound, the angel’s voice, the fifth voice, or the overtone. It occurs when the upper harmonics in the individual voice notes, combined with heard voices, reinforce each other, strengthening it so that the ringing overtone stands out separately above the blended sound. The effect is audible only on certain kinds of chords, and only when all voices blend precisely. Hearing the overtone is often taken as sign that a singer has become a “barbershopper.”</p>
<p>While the origins of barbershop singing are debatable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0891241611429943">Averill 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0891241611429943">Henry 2001</xref>), this style of singing enjoyed its greatest popularity when sheet music was the primary means of distributing popular songs. With the advent of the radio, in the 1930s, older forms of entertainment waned and barbershop singing became a hobby supported by a national organization (The Barbershop Harmony Society).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0891241611429943">1</xref></sup> Since the 1980s, membership in the society has declined and barbershop officials have pointed to a variety of reasons such as harried lifestyles, the serious commitment of time the hobby demands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0891241611429943">Stebbins 1996</xref>), and changing musical tastes.</p>
<p>While declining participation in all sorts of volunteer activities is well documented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0891241611429943">Putnam 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0891241611429943">2007</xref>), the trend has not affected community chorus singing in general (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0891241611429943">Chorus Impact Study 2009</xref>). Currently, according to the Barbershop Harmony Society headquarters’ website, membership is holding steady at about 25,000, and initiatives are underway to attract new members, including major efforts to reach younger singers. I mention declining membership and efforts to recruit new members to underscore the anachronistic nature of the hobby. Anachronisms are intrinsic to the barbershop habitus, and concealed within them is a worldview.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0891241611429943">
<title>Joe Barbershopper’s Worldview</title>
<p>Joe Barberhopper is the moniker frequently used in Barbershop Harmony Society (BHS) literature (see <italic>The Harmonizer</italic> 2011) to refer to the typical barbershopper. I use it here to depict my fellow barbershoppers. While the BHS strives for a wide appeal, there can be no denying that the typical barbershop singer is middle- to old-aged, middle income, a church member, white, and he is decidedly conservative, politically and socially. Although BHS’s code of ethics prohibits political discussions, casual occurrences reveal the conservatism of the hobby. For example, during the 2004 presidential campaign, one chorus member circulated a joke about John Kerry’s military service on the list server for the chorus. The chorus director quickly reminded members about the prohibition against politicking, and the culprit quickly apologized, saying that the posting was an accident of cyberspace.</p>
<p>Still, given the patriotic songs that elicit strong emotions from singers, the backgrounds of the men in business occupations, engineering, construction and independent contracting, and the relatively large numbers of military veterans and church members, I learned to think of my fellow singers as socially conservative. I collected prayers that were given to commence the proceedings at annual installation banquets. One such prayer aptly illustrates my conclusion. In it, we thanked the Lord for living in a country where “the police would not break up a meeting such as ours.” I learned to appreciate the “no politics” and “no religion” prohibition, as a way to avoid confrontation with fellow singers over what I saw as a mixture of religiosity and politics in songs such as <italic>God Bless the USA</italic>, and in some of the misogynistic and racist lyrics of songs written in the early twentieth century and late nineteenth. For example, “husbands tie their wives up with a ball and chain” (from, <italic>Sentimental Gentleman from Georgia</italic>), or “ “the people are gay,” originally “darkies are gay” (from <italic>My Old Kentucky Home</italic>). The phrase “darkies are gay,” which is Stephen Foster’s original lyric, seems to live in the barbershop collective memory. Whenever the song is rehearsed, I would often hear someone in the chorus refer to the original lyric—”you know that used to be ‘darkies.’”</p>
<p>No doubt many singers are drawn to fellowship with men who share their conservative predilections, even if the values and points of views they espouse remain, for the most part, tacit. I draw this conclusion from the numbers of singers who belong to the same church, play golf together, and discuss off-limit subjects in these settings.</p>
<p>However, the conservative milieu of barbershopping does not, in itself, account for the lure of the hobby. One workshop leader suggested that the emotional reaction to the commonly used harmonic structure in this music, the “ringing chord,” is something genetic, implying that a kind of biological tie exists among barbershop singers. “We all hear the ‘fifth’ voice,” he said, “And, we all respond emotionally to it.” While not all barbershoppers agree with such biological determinism, most will attest to the thrill that comes from ringing a chord. Emphasis on the ringing chord shapes the selection of songs, and these are mostly songs from the 1920-1940s, though there is a trend to include a few more “contemporary songs” (1960-1980), such as Beatles and Beach Boy selections.</p>
<sec id="section10-0891241611429943">
<title>Doing Nostalgia and Sentimentality</title>
<p>
<disp-quote>
<p>Some folks say I’m sentimental—that I can’t deny,</p>
<p>I can’t help feeling sentimental and here’s the reason why.</p>
<p>I wish they’d write songs again the way they wrote them back in Dad and Mother’s day. . . . Songs with a smile. . . . Songs with a tear. (“Back In Dad And, Mother’s Day,” as performed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0891241611429943">Boston Common (n.d.)</xref>. Sheet Music 2M73 Barbershop Harmony Society)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p><italic>Prima facie</italic>, the barbershop world is nostalgic, even anachronistic, but for what purposes is the past revered and preserved? <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0891241611429943">Davis (1979)</xref> wrote that what most forms of nostalgia seem to have in common is dissatisfaction with the present in service of some end, about which there is consensus. Nostalgic feelings, moods, and social activities, he suggested, range from restoring automobiles to, in extreme cases, reactionary political movements. In the case of barbershoppers, while they share a general malaise about contemporary society, they are particularly dissatisfied with the popular music scene.</p>
<p>Barbershop, then, shares this characteristic with other “retro” forms of music, such as bluegrass or old-timey music. Intricate melody, harmony, and lyrics with several verses comprise the core of the barbershop sound, in contrast to popular music, which is often lyrically simple and rhythmically driven. Furthermore, while nostalgic popular song lyrics do exist, most popular music engages the present. Blau demonstrated that popular music is “related to forms of social dislocation and alienation and is largely a reflection of prevailing economic inequalities” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0891241611429943">Blau 1988</xref>, 883).</p>
<p>One show of which I was a part featured a quartet doing a parody of a rap song. While skillfully performed, audience and chorus members alike seemed relieved when the song was finished, and that number was dropped from the chorus repertory. Rap and even most popular music is dissonant with the cognitive and emotional processes that use senses of time for imagining the past in terms of the present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0891241611429943">Flaherty and Fine 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0891241611429943">Mead 1932</xref>). In other words, the present is too imminent—even as a parody—in the rap form.</p>
<p>Participation in the barbershop hobby creates a space between contemporary society and actually being in that society. Through their music, barbershoppers distinguish between their interpretation of society and their membership in it. They are obviously in society, but they are able to maintain distance from what they see as “negatives” such as popular music, fashion trends, politics, and news headlines through singing nostalgic songs. One chapter member put it this way:
<disp-quote>
<p>I just don’t listen to popular music. When I was young, I was a fan of the Beatles, The Eagles, Chicago, even the Kingston Trio and the Beach Boys. I could tell you the titles of songs on the top ten list. Today, I don’t even know if there is a “top ten list.” Seems like the really popular songs are rap, or hip hop. . . . I don’t know, I guess I’d be pretty lost in today’s music world. Good thing I have my barbershop. I have barbershop CDs in my car and that’s pretty much what I listen to. (field notes, 2008)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>During times of social transition, nostalgia assists people in their understandings of what is happening to their place in a changing social world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0891241611429943">Davis 1979</xref>). By constructing a version of what the past was like, people can sharpen and define meanings that they want to make important in the present. Similar to Davis, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0891241611429943">Wilson (2005)</xref>, who studied a variety of efforts to resurrect the past, agrees with Davis that nostalgia can help facilitate the continuity of identity. When people perceive threats and obstacles to constructing and maintaining coherent and consistent senses of self, they can shore up their identities through remembering, recalling, reminiscing, and having other emotional experiences associated with doing an imagined past. Individually and collectively, the past is remembered and, in this act of recall, it is re-created. The lyrics of a barbershop arrangement of the Peter Allen song <italic>Everything Old Is New Again</italic> (1974) capture this function of nostalgia: “Don’t throw the past away, you might need it some rainy day . . . everything old is new again.”</p>
<p>Nostalgia may embody contradictions created by technologically driven social change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0891241611429943">Davis 1979</xref>). A goal of the international organization is the preservation of a style of music that had its golden age one hundred years ago during Vaudeville. That effort has resulted in the world’s largest archive of sheet music through the Barbershop Harmony Society, which ironically, is now available online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.barbershop.org">www.barbershop.org</ext-link>). Practicing one’s part at home, assisted by listening to a CD or an electronic file of the song, has become the primary way that new songs are learned in a chorus or quartet. With these technological aids, singers hear their part emphasized—tenor, lead, baritone, or bass—as they sing along.</p>
<p>Much of the old music, including barbershop arrangements of newer music (typically 1950s Do Wop), consists of love songs, songs of love lost and, most importantly, songs of sentimentality. Some songs, such as <italic>Friends</italic> (composed by Michael W. Smith, contemporary Christian musician and song writer), are religious, and impart meanings to life events, such as the death of a friend or loved one: “But, we’ll keep you close as always, it won’t even seem you’re gone, because our hearts . . . will keep the love strong.” Another example, <italic>If the Rest of the World Don’t Want You</italic>, a song from the 1920s (Gerber and Dreyer, Irving Berlin, Inc.), offers reassurance to the prodigal son that home and family are always a safe haven:
<disp-quote>
<p>When you’ve lost all your pride and they’ve cast you aside. When you’ve lost every friend you had. If the rest of the world don’t want you, then go back to your mother and dad. . . . You will always be welcome back home, welcome home.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Such lyrics, sung with facial expressions embracing both joy and sorrowful empathy, are sung by men whose own children are grown, living their lives separate from their parents, or in some cases, by men whose adult children have returned to the “nest.” In this context, the lyrics of this song seem incongruent with actual circumstances of everyday life, at best, and tragically poignant, at worst.</p>
<p>Some barbershop singers relate that certain songs carry such strong emotions that they have difficulty singing through them without a cracking voice or even a tear in their eye. For example, my quartet sang <italic>Lean on Me</italic> to our chorus, and one member related that the song was especially emotional for him, given the help that members of the chorus gave him and his family during his period of unemployment. Or, during my own divorce, rehearsing the barbershop version of <italic>It Is Well with My Soul</italic> (Horatio Spafford, circa 1873) required constraint to kept tears from falling.</p>
<p>Nostalgic sentiment then reconciles feelings that are in discord into a harmonic form. Men who appreciate emotion, but may not have found ways to blend it into everyday life, may discover in music an instrument of emotional expressivity—a sharp contrast with their quotidian existence. Songs about days gone by allow men a safe distance from the subjects of loss, joy, and romantic love. The lack of contemporariness further depersonalizes the feelings in the songs and, hence, becomes a device for controlling emotions through their ritualized expression. One barbershopper put it this way:
<disp-quote>
<p>I come to sing with my friends, to a place where I know I am supported and where I can just have fun. I feel a real connection with my brothers in the society. I have depression and anxiety, but not when I’m with the chorus. Singing about feelings makes me feel good. (field notes, 2009)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0891241611429943">
<title>Creating a Manly Space</title>
<p>Barbershop singing creates a space in which men can be sentimental, loving, and even sensitive without violating the ideologies of masculinity. Touching another man can be part of the warm up routine. For example, as part of a warm-up exercise, directors often have men on the risers turn to massage the neck of a neighboring singer, and then they direct the chorus to turn the other way to reciprocate the massage. Choruses also choreograph their performances, which requires them to move, gesture, and even dance. Barbershoppers also often wear make-up for performances (lipstick, rouge, and eyeliner). In all of these activities, remarks intended to reassert masculinity are common. For example, touching might be accompanied by remarks that distance the touching from a “gay” gesture: “Careful there young man,” or “Don’t get too used to this.” And, jokes about wearing make-up for performances are also commonly heard: “My, don’t you look nice” [voiced in a sarcastic tone].</p>
<p>Social space conducive to masculine emotional expressivity, minimally, should have characteristics that allow for both expressivity and masculine ideology. Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0891241611429943">Oldenburg (1999)</xref> referred to physical locations and locales in describing the third place, that is, places between home and work, he does point out that gender mixing has changed the character of previously all-male third places between work and family. These all-male places often served as a refuge within which men could express their emotions to one another. Today, barbershop singers preserve the all-male place by gathering in churches, retirement homes, schools, or virtually anywhere they can rehearse and store risers, wardrobes, and music. These are not third places like a neighborhood bar, but they function as such. For example, while visitors are always welcome at rehearsals, whenever women (wives, daughters, granddaughters, or friends) are present, behavior changes, almost as if one were in a men’s locker room and someone yells, “woman in the house!”</p>
<p>I have attended coaching sessions with female leaders, and discovered that female directors (allowed by BSH rules) and voice and performance coaches attest to the creed of “manly” singing, just as do male directors. Chorus directors model the way men express emotions through voice and gesture. They demand a full, rich blend of voices with a dominant bass component, and barbershop songs, whether ballads or up-tunes, will include a full (loud) ringing chord here and there in the song. Barbershop songs typically end with ring, achieved by arranging chords into a “tag.”</p>
<p>In other contexts, such as choral music, these same musical components might be referred to as rich or full. In the barbershop world, the “manly” designation serves to compensate for the suspicion that singing might be unmanly. Men who are unsure about the way they might be perceived as singers can reassure themselves of their traditional masculinity by thinking of what they do as “manly” singing.</p>
<p>Whatever a director or coach may intend, singers understand manly singing as a kind of folk model of the way men sing. Barbershop singers hear, <italic>post hoc ergo propter hoc</italic>, in their training, a masculine form for the expression of emotions. This habitus is, of course, composed of directors’ and singers’ understandings of masculinity, and the ways they impute meanings to their singing. Singers are taught that barbershop singing is emotional, and that emotion must be communicated to audiences. Hence, they must learn to match their facial expressions and body posture with the sentiments of the music they sing, which further creates a situation conducive to sharing feelings, even if it is highly ritualized. The barbershop chorus or quartet becomes, then, a safe haven for the expression of a surprisingly wide range of emotions, especially if a director makes that safe by rewarding expressiveness with praise. Emotions, however, are embedded in the songs, and may or may not be shared conversationally with fellow barbershoppers. The songs become a kind of safe conduit through which emotions may be expressed without identifying ties to an individual singer.</p>
<p>While emotional meanings become specific to place and inclusive of others, they retain an overall theme of masculinity. I have seen men cry, and I have cried, myself, as we sing songs, which elicit “real world” recollections such as divorce, financial problems, and death of a family member. In this context, “men do cry,”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0891241611429943">2</xref></sup> and eliciting sufficient emotional content to evoke crying may be expected in learning a song. Of course, crying must be controlled and suppressed in order to perform a song and carry out a rehearsal or a performance. This is accomplished primarily through part-by-part practice and repetition (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0891241611429943">Haiman 1998</xref>). Too much repetition can, of course, deprive a performance of emotional depth. Therefore, a balance between elicited emotions and control of them is the goal of an accomplished singer. Singing songs about times gone by, for instance, allows men a safe distance from the subjects of loss, joy, and romantic love. The lack of contemporariness depersonalizes the feelings in the songs so that an audience knows that the song is about something or someone else, not the singers themselves.</p>
<p>Making music together, then, creates a fairly predictable, safe form through which men connect in ways that allow them to express emotions prohibited by traditional masculinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0891241611429943">Schutz 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0891241611429943">Vannini and Waskul 2006</xref>). Even the simple choreography that singers learn for concerts can be opportunity for men who “don’t dance” to step lively and playfully with other guys.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0891241611429943">
<title>Serious Leisure and Serious Emotions</title>
<p>Barbershop singing as a hobby can impart meaning to otherwise boring and routine habits of everyday life. Serious leisure time activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0891241611429943">Stebbins 1976</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0891241611429943">1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0891241611429943">2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0891241611429943">2009</xref>) may function as organizational foundations for imparting meaning to ordinary activities. There can be little doubt that barbershopping is serious leisure. It requires a significant commitment of time and finances (practice, membership fees, and travel costs). And it serves as an organizing principle for daily life, often encroaching on time normally allocated to family and even work.</p>
<p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0891241611429943">Stebbins (2007)</xref>, the role that serious leisure plays in modern society approaches institutional portions. Whereas foundational institutions such as family and religion may be less effective in defining and clarifying transformative meanings and anchoring identities, leisure time pursuits may provide and generate complementary and even novel interpretive processes.</p>
<p>For example, in their description of how men deal with competition in choral singing, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0891241611429943">Faulkner and Davidson (2006)</xref> stress what they refer to as “homo-social” behaviors, that is, specifically masculine ways to compete and cooperate. They write, “Men’s perception of singing in harmony implies that this vocal behavior is not only a metaphor for human relationships, but an essential and enriching way of relating to others, fulfilling basic needs for vocal and social connectedness” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0891241611429943">Faulkner and Davidson 2006</xref>, 219). Barbershoppers, similarly, feel affinity for fellow members, particularly during times of hardship and illness. Their relationships may be like family in some incidents, yet they are rooted in participating in a hobby.</p>
<p>Participation in serious leisure has implications for senses of belonging or community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0891241611429943">Stebbins 2007</xref>). Leisure time organizations are often seen as a way to escape or, at least mitigate, negative forces outside of the chorus. In a gender-polarized setting where participation requires constant evaluations of one’s own and one’s fellow singers’ performances, emotions can become raw. I have seen men who have been criticized walk out of a rehearsal. I have been criticized myself to the point of questioning whether my efforts to sing perfectly are worthwhile. Once, when I was asked to stand off the risers, because I had not passed my session leader’s audition to assess my mastery of a song, I felt so ashamed that I just left the rehearsal. I seriously considered quitting the chorus, but I decided that I needed to accept being criticized in order to continue learning about barbershopping.</p>
<p>Accepting criticism is not easy for conventionally masculine individuals, and criticism takes on many forms. I have witnessed members criticizing fellow members for their lack of commitment, unreliability, and unwillingness to work toward perfection in singing. These negative characterizations can always find their way back to the singer by way of rumor and innuendo. And, singers rather quickly develop a reputation as a quick learner, a quartet perfectionist, a good guy but not a particularly good singer, and infrequently, “a hard guy to get along with.” However, while these factors can be contributing to declining memberships and inactivity, they are only a part of total emotional context of barbershop singing. That context includes deeply instilled senses of membership that transcend evaluations of performance.</p>
<p>For example, a long-time member of a local chorus stands in front of the chorus and relates the story of his fall from a ladder while he was trimming trees at his home. He was hospitalized for several days and suffered considerable pain. He finished his story in this way.</p>
<p>
<disp-quote>
<p>Why am I telling you guys this? Because I want to thank you for calling to see how I’m doing, for visiting me, and for me knowing that my buddies are thinking about me. You know I’m 84 years old. Going through this ordeal has made me think more about my death. I have decided I don’t want to be displayed and look nothing like myself. I want to be cremated, and I want you guys to sing at my funeral. I want you to sing <italic>Amazing Grace</italic> and <italic>The Lord’s Prayer</italic> (my recollection of the story).</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>There was a short silence after Gene finished his talk. Then, one member retorted, “Hey, Gene, when should we schedule you in?” Laughter filled the rehearsal room, as Gene sat down. Still, we all knew that a solemn commitment had just been made to Gene, a commitment that was kept two years later.</p>
<p>In another example of the emotional ties that singers develop through their interpretations of barbershop songs, Allen, a section leader, explained to the chorus how we could evoke emotions within ourselves to enliven our performance of a particularly sentimental song. “Selling” your song to the audience involves achieving symmetry between the meanings of the lyrics and facial and bodily expressions of the singers. Allen started to talk about his first divorce and his return to his parents’ home for comfort and recovery. His narrative was to prepare us for singing “If the Rest of the World Don’t Want You,” by thinking of personal experiences in which we were welcomed home after a difficult time. As he spoke, he lost his composure and began to weep. He returned to the risers, while others sat in silence (one member quietly snickered to another that he, himself, has been divorced three times and is quite used to it). Then, the director of the chorus explained how barbershoppers are a close-knit group of men who are accepting of the expression of emotion.</p>
<p>A particularly telling display of barbershop emotional expressivity occurred when a longtime director of my chorus announced he was moving to another town to accept a better job. To us all, he wrote the following email:
<disp-quote>
<p>There is no way to convey how much I love you and how much my life and passion for singing have been enhanced by your friendship, encouragement, and joy of singing together over these past 27 years. You are my friends and family . . . I can tell you as a fact that there is no place on earth, no joy like being in front of you, my friends, as we kid around together, tell stories and jokes (even the bad ones, Frank), sing tags together, learn new things together, and then sing and perform like champions together. (email from the director, Herman, to chorus members, 2011)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>A farewell cerebration of his tenure as director was hastily arranged for the last hour of his last rehearsal with us. Chorus members gave testimonies to how Herman had enriched their singing and their lives. While farewell events such as this one are rituals of appreciation, this one simply gushed with effusiveness. Men proclaimed publicly that they loved each other, that they had established bonds of deep emotional connection. “I love you guy,” followed by a hug, was the order of the event.</p>
<p>I doubted the sincerity of some of the testimony, as I thought of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0891241611429943">Goffman’s (1959)</xref> dramaturgic metaphor, which unpacks such displays as staged role-playing. Knowing that relationships between Herman and members of his quartets had been strained by misunderstandings and broken commitments and that members of the chorus often stifled negative reactions to grueling practices in search of the “perfect” sound, I was aware of a feigned sincerity in what I observed.</p>
<p>Still, within the barbershopper identity, two functions were accomplished during this event: showing appreciation for the director’s devotion to and energy expended on the chorus, and doing this in a way fully consistent with a barbershop habitus. Sentimentality framed the narratives of Herman’s biography through the frequent use of “love,” and references to friendships and ongoing commitments to the barbershop community provided the nostalgia.</p>
<p>As my review of literature showed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0891241611429943">Gallagher and Wood 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0891241611429943">Schwalbe 1996a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0891241611429943">1996b</xref>), masculine identities may encompass a considerable range of emotions. They do this by framing the emotions within larger value structures. In the context of the barbershop hobby, effusive praise and feigned sincerity create relationships that are mostly limited to the barbershop world. Just as facial expressions, bodily posturing, and ringing chords enliven sappy lyrics, feigned sincerity and practiced display animate appreciation and praise.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0891241611429943">
<title>Varieties of Barbershop Identities</title>
<p>Involvement in the barbershop world inevitably results in an individual acquiring a sense of a singer’s self. When a singer learns to think about himself as capable of making judgments and generating performances that embody the ways of barbershopping, he acquires a habitus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0891241611429943">Bourdieu 1984</xref>). For example, as I learned to see differences between qualities of barbershop singing, I acquired a kind of capital that enabled me to judge others and myself according to a practical logic. An official BSH coach explained to one of my choruses that singers can be classified according to their progress toward becoming an ideal barbershop singer. He introduced a model that illustrates the process whereby a singer acquires skills to perform songs without errors and with a high degree of confidence (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0891241611429943">Table 1</xref>). Of course, this model is an idealization, but it captures the distinct judgments, style and, particularly, the capital of the barbershop habitus.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0891241611429943" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Idealized Model of Singer</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0891241611429943" xlink:href="10.1177_0891241611429943-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Aspects</th>
<th align="center">Error-Free Singing</th>
<th align="center">Errors in Singing</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Self-aware</td>
<td>Journeyman</td>
<td>Apprentice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Natural (nonreflexive)</td>
<td>Master</td>
<td>Novice</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>According to the model, novice singers have a desire to sing but they have acquired neither skills nor the necessary self-awareness. An apprentice has acculturated the style, adopted the values of barbershopping, heard the ringing chord, and even been a part of producing it, but his competency is incomplete. He still sings with errors (wrong notes, rhythms, or words). The journeyman singer gets notes and words correct and even manages the theatricality of singing with emotion, but he does so in a self-conscious fashion, always thinking ahead to the next bar or the next gesture. One director, in admonishing the journeyman-like performance of his chorus, said that he could see singers “reading the words, notes, and moves from the back of their eyeballs.” Finally, the mastersinger performs the particulars of a song, error free, without awareness of his agency, that is, nonreflexively. His competency causes his performance to seem natural and effortless.</p>
<p>Of course, this formal way of describing the singer’s habitus does not cover the distinctions that individual chorus members make about themselves and others as barbershoppers. The idealized model glosses the informal distinctions, judgments, and categorizations that singers impute to one another. For example, here are some terms that men use to characterize one another as well as themselves. A “mush mouth” singer sings with a “dead mouth,” that is, he fails to articulate or clearly shape his sounds. The resulting sound seems “mushed.” A “scooper” tends to find the right note by rising to it; that is, beginning notes to phrases, verses, or choruses of a song are sung initially slight flat. The effect is to scoop the note. A “bottom-sider” sings consistently at the bottom of a note, and has to work to “get on top” of the note. Some men have a “harsh” voice, which means that their voices stand out from the chorus or quartet. “Harsh” voices must be muted to blend into a unit sound so that a chord may ring. There are “warblers,” or men who have difficulty controlling the vibrato of their voices. Some singers are “clowns,” continually cracking jokes, making snide remarks, and often in return, being the brunt of jokes.</p>
<p>One member, named Ernie, played this role for so long that corny jokes, any retort, any pun, or “bad” joke would be referred to as an “Ernie.” For example, whenever the director would critique a performance for lacking emotion, we could expect someone to say, “You mean you want us to sing it with feeling,” to which the chorus would collectively respond with, “Ernie.”</p>
<p>Barbershop identities are fluid, but sometimes they become, within this small world, fixed. Singers who are “journeymen” may retain that identity for decades, never becoming a master, rarely given an opportunity to sing in a quartet with the best voices in the chorus. “Clowns” may be so for an entire career. “Scoopers” may find that they have a hard time joining a quartet, and “bottom-siders” discover that they are always placed on the riser in front of a mastersinger. As long as these men accept and practice within the identity they have acquired, they remain members with a barbershop habitus.</p>
<p>Within the fraternity, there are several forms of friendship, ranging from intimate to distant, but all are within the context of sentimentality. Members may be known only by their first name on a nametag, but they are greeted warmly at the beginning of rehearsals, chatted with at break-time, and they may even receive a telephone call as a reminder of a performance date or practice time. Such relationships do not penetrate into the private lives of the members, but they function as entry to further conversation and deeper relational bonds. Most importantly, they are framed as masculine friendships, shaped by jokes, stories of life events such as illnesses, work stresses, what happened at the office today, and so on. Complaining about life is not expected to elicit any specific kind of response—merely a listening ear. Such is the social capital of barbershopping.</p>
<p>Another aspect of barbershop capital is the deeply ingrained custom of the “afterglow.” The afterglow is an informal get together following a performance, usually an annual show, that takes place at a local restaurant. Members, their spouses, friends, and family eat together, and quartets sing some of their repertoire they did not sing on the show. When these after-the-show events happen, they “take over” the restaurant by unashamedly singing for the entire clientele, whether said group likes it or not.</p>
<p>Some barbershoppers stay engaged in their hobby for decades (one particular barbershopper had been a member of the Society for more than sixty years) and barbershop singing often is intergenerational, as in my case. Deep, sincere bonds may develop among those who have sung together for such a long time. During periods of illness, chorus members may visit each other, and the wives of the older members may extend a network of caring that could include food brought to the member’s house. These circles of helping friends are common, and resemble the caring networks found in mainstream American churches.</p>
<p>Some singers establish friendships that extend into their private lives. They may socialize, dine at one another’s homes, join the same golf clubs, and attend the same churches. However, establishing close friendships is not necessarily a consequence of longtime barbershopping. The bonds they form often symbolize a commitment to the style of singing, and a sense of brotherhood, but not necessarily a compatibility of lifestyles.</p>
<p>More often than not, the deepest bonds form from the practice of quartetting: the formation of quartets from members of a chorus. Managing a quartet over time involves a great deal of emotional work. Singers have senses of their own competencies and voices, and, of course, these sensibilities may be at odds with the judgments of their peers. Some quartets sing together for years and even decades, while others endure for only a few months. Barring uncontrollable events such as a job transfer, job loss, death or illness of the singer or a member of his family, a quartet has a life span that is dictated by the emotional work that goes on within it.</p>
<p>Usually, a quartet will have a dominant member who has taken the initiative to form the quartet in the first place. In one chorus I sang with, these leaders were referred to as “alpha males.” Of course, two alpha males in one quartet can result in struggles for control over when rehearsals are scheduled, where they are held, song selections, and vocal and lyrical interpretations. Some quartets are more egalitarian than others, but most adhere to the leader’s tastes and sense of order.</p>
<p>Quartets must register with the Barbershop Harmony Society. Their members must be BSH members, and pay a nominal registration fee for a unique name, that is, one that is not currently in use. Quartet names are not unlike the names of racehorses. They must be unique, catchy, and if possible, share some theme with the chorus from which they were formed. For example, Gem Tones formed out of the Diamond State Chorus (from Arkansas, the Diamond State), and MO-Sound from the Sho-Me Statesmen of Missouri (The Show Me state). However, most names are idiosyncratic, as in The Noise, or they may be a play on names, as in Vocal Spectrum, derived from the highly successful chorus, Vocal Majority from Dallas, Texas.</p>
<p>As a part of emotional work, quartets develop means of coping with the hurt feelings of its members. Each decision made about song selection, interpretation of a lyric, or sound production can be a flash point for hurt feelings, conflicts of opinion, and differing tastes. Examples of such means are emails of apology, and public apologies in front of the chorus. However, the typical way those feelings are dealt with is by ignoring them, joking about them, or leaving the quartet, claiming with claims of being too busy to continue quartetting.</p>
<p>While there are emotional difficulties and dynamics in quartetting, deep friendships often form that involve quartet members in the details of each other’s lives. Wives, family members, and even employers may become involved in a quartet’s social life. Airplane flights, automobile trips, time off from work, commitments to singing, as in rehearsal time, gigs, etc. all can create opportunities for friendships that are deep, but distinctively male: that is, they are in the context of accomplishing a task (doing barbershop music) and they are framed mostly by lighthearted banter, jokes at others’ expense, and self-deprecating humor.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0891241611429943" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Relying on my own experiences and my observations of others, I offer descriptions and analysis that show that within the distinctive context of the barbershop hobby, conventionally masculine men learn to be sentimental and nostalgic. They find in the gendered space that their hobby affords them a way to express emotions that accommodates their conventional understandings of masculinity, while permitting them a range of expressivity not found in their daily lives. By acquiring a habitus, men create avenues for expressing emotions that would otherwise be curtailed as incongruent with conventional masculinity. For barbershoppers, their hobby takes on significance for them because it serves as platform for interpreting their location in society. Through the use of nostalgic lyrics and a theory of harmony, they construct a social world and acquire identities.</p>
<p>For mostly conservative, middle-aged men morphing masculine values into emotionally sensitive performances is no mean accomplishment. This ironic transition is accomplished through several devices that are part of the barbershop habitus: that is, men learn in the barbershop world how to be sentimental and nostalgic, and they use these performances to establish a sense of identity for themselves and their relationships with other barbershoppers. First, the formulaic nature of barbershop singing is conducive to emotional responses. The way dissonances resolve, the way harmonics are constructed for hearing four parts most of the time, the ringing of chords at the ends of phrases, and the addition of “tags” to the body of songs, all contribute to the singer’s sense of emotionality. The form provides a comfortable distance between the emotions expressed in a song and those felt or lived through emotions of the singer. Second, self-awareness about the emotionality of the songs and performances is achieved through a theatrical framing of the emotions: that is, singers are trained to feign emotions (smiles on faces). This further separates singers from the emotions elicited by the music they sing. Finally, songs about the past create a distance that protects the singer from self-revelation.</p>
<p>Barbershopping affords men opportunities to connect emotionally with each other in ways that are perceived as masculine, even if these perceptions are specific to the hobby and revolve around emotions not typically understood as masculine. The rituals, traditions, and customs of the hobby provide the structure within which men may be sentimental and nostalgic, and this, it turns out, is manly singing.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0891241611429943">
<label>1.</label>
<p>In 1938, two lawyers founded the whites-only Society for the Preservation and Encouragement of Barbershop Quartet Singing in America, Inc. The awkward acronym, SPEBQSA, was intended to be a satirical comment on the proclivity of New Dealers to use acronyms to describe programs and policies. A rather complete history of the society, its goals, and philosophy of its music can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.barbershop.org">http://www.barbershop.org</ext-link> and in several books and articles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0891241611429943">Stebbins 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0891241611429943">Henry 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0891241611429943">Averill 2003</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0891241611429943">
<label>2.</label>
<p>In their report of findings from survey research, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0891241611429943">Ross and Mirowsky (1984)</xref> discovered that men with traditional male values and beliefs were less likely to cry than those with higher level of education and income. Their experimental findings fit with the frequency of crying observed in this group: it is rare. However, when it does occur, it is accepted, if in a manly fashion. Men on the risers ignore the display, and, therefore, accommodate emotionality through the lack of ridicule and shaming.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Bio</title>
<p><bold>Jeffrey Eugene Nash</bold> is professor and chair of the sociology and anthropology department at the University of Arkansas at Little Rock. He has held positions at University of Tulsa, Macalester College in Saint Paul Minnesota and at Missouri State University. His research interests include urban public spaces, race and ethnicity and sociolinguistics.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Agar</surname><given-names>Michael H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1996</year>. <source>The professional stranger: An informal introduction to ethnography</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>Edward</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <source>Inclusive masculinity: The changing nature of masculinities</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>Leon</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <article-title>Analytic autoethnography</article-title>. <source>Journal of Contemporary Ethnography</source> <volume>35</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>373</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Averill</surname><given-names>Gage</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <source>Four parts, no waiting: A social history of American barbershop harmony</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beasley</surname><given-names>Christina</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>Rethinking hegemonic masculinity in a globalizing world</article-title>. <source>Men &amp; Masculinities</source> <volume>11</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>86</fpage>-<lpage>103</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blau</surname><given-names>Judith</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1988</year>. <article-title>Music as social circumstance</article-title>. <source>Social Forces</source> <volume>66</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>883</fpage>-<lpage>902</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Boston Common</collab>. <comment>No date</comment>. <source>Back in dad and, mother’s day</source>, <comment>Sheet Music 2M73</comment>. <publisher-loc>Nashville, TN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Barbershop Harmony Society</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bourdieu</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1984</year>. <source>Distinction: A social critique of the judgment of taste</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Chorus Impact Study</collab>. <year>2009</year>. <source>How children, adults, and communities benefit from choruses</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chorus America</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Connell</surname><given-names>Raewyn W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2005</year>. <source>Masculinities</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Connell</surname><given-names>Raewyn W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Messerschmidt</surname><given-names>James E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2005</year>. <article-title>Hegemonic masculinity: Rethinking the concept</article-title>. <source>Gender &amp; Society</source> <volume>19</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>829</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Copes</surname><given-names>Heith</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hochstetler</surname><given-names>Andy</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>Situational construction of masculinity among male street thieves</article-title>. <source>Journal of Contemporary Ethnography</source> <volume>32</volume> (<issue>June</issue>): <fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>305</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Fred</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1979</year>. <source>Yearning for yesterday: A sociology of nostalgia</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dieser</surname><given-names>Rodney B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2008</year>. <article-title>Tales from grades 1 through 12: Understanding the complex web of multiple life forces located in schools</article-title>. <source>Alberta Journal of Educational Research</source> <volume>54</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>292</fpage>-<lpage>308</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1998</year>. <article-title>Political consequences of private authority: Promise keepers and the transformation of hegemonic masculinity</article-title>. <source>Theory and Society</source> <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>817</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Faulkner</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>Jane W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2006</year>. <article-title>Men in chorus: Collaboration and competition in homo-social behavior</article-title>. <source>Psychology of Music</source> <volume>34</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flaherty</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>Gary Alan</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2001</year>. <article-title>Present, past, and future: Conjugating George Herbert Mead’s perspective of time</article-title>. <source>Time and Society</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>Sally K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Carol</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1999</year>. <article-title>Symbolic traditionalism and pragmatic egalitarianism</article-title>. <source>Gender &amp; Society</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>211</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>Sally K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>Sabrine L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2005</year>. <article-title>Godly manhood going wild? Transformations in conservative Protestant masculinity</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Religion</source> <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>135</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goffman</surname><given-names>Irving</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1959</year>. <source>The presentation of self in everyday life</source>. <publisher-loc>Garden City, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Doubleday Anchor</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haiman</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1998</year>. <source>Talk is cheap: Sarcasm, alienation, and the evolution of language</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>Melanie</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>Soft-boiled masculinity: Renegotiating gender and racial ideologies in the Promise Keeper’s Movement</article-title>. <source>Gender &amp; Society</source> <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>423</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>Jim</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2001</year>. <article-title>Historical roots of barbershop harmony</article-title>. <source>The Harmonizer</source> <month>July/August</month>, <fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>Dorothy L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1999</year>. <article-title>Once intrepid warriors: Modernity and the production of Maasai masculinities</article-title>. <source>Ethnology</source> <volume>38</volume> (<issue>Spring</issue>): <fpage>121</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>Danny</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <article-title>Folk models of dyadic male bonds in Israeli culture</article-title>. <source>Sociological Quarterly</source> <volume>48</volume> (<issue>Winter</issue>): <fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kimmel</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <source>Manhood in America: A cultural history</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kimmel</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <source>Guyland: The perilous world where boys become men</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>HarperCollins</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kleinman</surname><given-names>Sherryl</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Copp</surname><given-names>Martha</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1993</year>. <source>Emotions and fieldwork</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>Ophra</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>Doing masculinity in a mental hospital</article-title>. <source>Journal of Contemporary Ethnography</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>336</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lovell</surname><given-names>Terry</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2000</year>. <article-title>Thinking feminism with and against Bourdieu</article-title>. <source>Feminist Theory</source> <volume>1</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lugosi</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <article-title>Between overt and covert research concealment and disclosure in an ethnographic study of commercial hospitality</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Inquiry</source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>541</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>George Herbert</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1932</year>. <source>The philosophy of the present</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Messner</surname><given-names>Michael A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1990</year>. <article-title>Boyhood, organized sports and the construction of masculinities</article-title>. <source>Journal of Contemporary Ethnography</source> <volume>18</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>416</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Messner</surname><given-names>Michael A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1993</year>. <article-title>Changing men and feminist politics in the United States</article-title>. <source>Theory &amp; Society</source> <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>723</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Messner</surname><given-names>Michael A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2002</year>. <source>Taking the field: Women, men and sports</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oldenburg</surname><given-names>Raymond</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1999</year>. <source>The great good place</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Paragon House</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>Robert D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2000</year>. <source>Bowling alone: The collapse and revival of American community</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Simon &amp; Schuster</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>Robert D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2007</year>. <article-title><italic>E Pluribus Unum</italic>: Diversity and community in the twenty-first century</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian Political Studies</source> <volume>30</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>137</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Riemer</surname><given-names>Jeffrey W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1977</year>. <article-title>Varieties of opportunistic research</article-title>. <source>Journal of Contemporary Ethnography</source> <volume>5</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>467</fpage>-<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>Cathrine E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mirowsky</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1984</year>. <article-title>Men who cry</article-title>. <source>Social Psychological Quarterly</source> <volume>47</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>138</fpage>-<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scheff</surname><given-names>Thomas J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1997</year>. <source>Emotions, the social bond and human reality</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schutz</surname><given-names>Alfred</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1977</year>. <article-title>Making music together: A study in social relationship</article-title>. In <source>Symbolic anthropology: A reader in the study of symbols and meanings</source>. Edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dolgin</surname><given-names>Janet L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kemnitzer</surname><given-names>David S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>David M.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>42</lpage>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schwalbe</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1996a</year>. <article-title>The mirrors in men’s faces</article-title>. <source>Journal of Contemporary Ethnography</source> <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>-<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schwalbe</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1996b</year>. <source>Unlocking the iron cage: The men’s movement, gender politics, and American culture</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spradley</surname><given-names>James P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1980</year>. <source>Participant observation</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Holt, Rinehart &amp; Winston</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stebbins</surname><given-names>Robert A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1976</year>. <article-title>Music among friends: The social networks of amateur musicians</article-title>. <source>International Review of Sociology</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>-<lpage>73</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stebbins</surname><given-names>Robert A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1982</year>. <article-title>Serious leisure: A conceptual statement</article-title>. <source>Pacific Sociological Review</source> <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>251</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stebbins</surname><given-names>Robert A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1996</year>. <source>The barbershop singer: Inside the social world of a musical hobby</source>. <publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stebbins</surname><given-names>Robert A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2007</year>. <source>Serious leisure: A perspective for our time</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stebbins</surname><given-names>Robert A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2009</year>. <source>Personal decisions in the public square: Beyond problem solving into a positive sociology</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>Arlene</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <article-title>Make room for daddy: Anxious masculinity and emergent homophobias in neopatriarchal politics</article-title>. <source>Gender &amp; Society</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>601</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vannini</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waskul</surname><given-names>Dennis</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <article-title>Symbolic interaction as music: The esthetic constitution of meaning, self and society</article-title>. <source>Symbolic Interaction</source> <volume>24</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>Erika Franca de Souza</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>“I can see you”: An autoethnography of my teacher-student self</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Report</source> <volume>16</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>415</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0891241611429943">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Janelle L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2005</year>. <source>Nostalgia: Sanctuary of meaning</source>. <publisher-loc>Lewisburg, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bucknell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>