<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PDJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppdj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Progress in Development Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1464-9934</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-027X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage India: New Delhi, India</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/146499341201200409</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_146499341201200409</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: McDonald, B.L. 2010: <italic>Food Security</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Alfranca</surname><given-names>Oscar</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-146499341201200409">Pennsylvania State University, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>359</fpage>
<lpage>360</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2010</year>: <source>Food Security</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge and Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>. <page-count count="200"/> pp. <price>£15.99</price> paper, ISBN-10: <isbn>0745648088</isbn>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Malthus foresaw inevitable social problems emerging from the tension he believed existed between the differing rates of increase in human population and food supply. Following from this fundamental social and economic argument, the main objective of this book is the illustration of the value of considering policies related to food security from a broad human security perspective that takes into account both the sudden and chronic sources of food insecurity. Therefore, food security is considered to be a fundamental component of human security’s effort to ensure safety from both chronic threats and sudden disruptions.</p>
<p>A number of ways in which individual and household choices about food have significant impacts on food security are presented and discussed. One of the aims of these policy solutions should be to educate people to better understand the implications of their food choices. For instance, the growing prominence of displays of nutritional information about foods, or the publicizing of concepts such as the ecological and climate footprint which help people to estimate the environmental impacts of food choices.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, while these educational efforts could improve understanding of the relationship of individual choices to food security, such tools could also lead to an oversimplification of environmental impacts from food if they do not take into account differing impacts related to production and transportation methods. According to the author, one way to address the shortcomings of such efforts is to increase the sophistication of environmental impact information.</p>
<p>A remarkable point of this book is that food security problems are discussed from a global multidisciplinary perspective, in which the creation of a global food system has happened as the result of amalgamated decisions in a wide variety of locations including farm fields, scientific and commercial laboratories, governmental agencies and international negotiations.</p>
<p>In spite of the fact that the debate on food security is developed for quite a number of issues (such as nutrition, the incidence on food supplies by infectious diseases or the disappearance of local food traditions), two central points are at the core of discussion: the influence of genetically modified food on production and the relevance of climatic change.</p>
<p>One main outcome of the debates over genetically modified food is the emergence of a new, more complex form of naturalism that links concerns about environmental degradation with concerns about social justice and human security. This discussion appears in many developed countries expressing growing interest in foods produced using organic or sustainable methods.</p>
<p>So, discussion is developed under the main hypothesis that one of the most pressing challenges confronting the global food system is the need to compare impacts on food and agricultural production from global climatic change. Arguments on climate change effects are mainly based on published data from official sources, and take into account that while agriculture and food production are often discussed as drivers of climate change, they could also play an important role in efforts to mitigate climate change. In this book, climate change presents both direct and indirect effects on food production and food security. Some examples are presented of direct effects, such as increased water scarcity, biodiversity losses to animal and fish populations (that provide key sources of nutrition), sea level rise or trade flows. The impact of such trade flows, which often only seem profitable by failing to consider the externalities that accrue from the costs of transportation, could be dramatically altered by efforts such as the European Union announcement that it would begin requiring all freight-carrying flights to participate in emissions-trading programmes by 2012.</p>
<p>While global change processes may make the effort to develop a sustainable global food system more difficult in some ways, advances in technology and communications could also open new pathways through strategic decoupling from global networks and the creation of sustainable local food systems. Then, it is necessary to point out that these activities could have significant (although sometimes unintentional), impacts on the global environment.</p>
<p>Regarding indirect effects on food security, they could be produced through impacts on the availability of resources such as oil (and therefore increasing the costs of transportation), and also changing the relative prices of inputs such as synthetic pesticides and fertilizers.</p>
<p>It is interesting to point out that discussions are developed under the perspective that while agriculture and food production are often considered to be drivers of climate change, it is also accepted that they could also play an important role in mitigating climate change, and even that agricultural practices could have positive impacts on the environment, by reducing environmental impacts through sustainable intensification of food production.</p>
<p>An essential point in this book is the relevance of ethical principles, such as health, ecology, fairness and care, on food production. An interesting hypothesis suggested is that these principles can be applied not only to some specific forms of agriculture but also to agriculture in the broadest sense, including the way people take care of soil, water, plants and animals in order to produce, prepare and distribute food and other goods.</p>
<p>This book is about an innovative and motivating subject. Bryan L. McDonald distils the conclusions for a fairly wide number of relevant issues related to food security. The book proves to be a stimulating work for those researchers interested in alternative methodologies for political and economic analysis, and very specially, for food policy analysis.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig><italic>Oscar Alfranca</italic><break/>
<italic>Pennsylvania State University, USA</italic></sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>