<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DHG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdhg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Dialogues in Human Geography</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2043-8206</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2043-8214</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2043820613490131</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2043820613490131</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>ARTICLE FORUM 1</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Commentaries</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Where in the (capitalist) world (economy) are regional narratives?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Flint</surname>
<given-names>Colin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2043820613490131"/>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-2043820613490131"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-2043820613490131">University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-2043820613490131">Colin Flint, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 220 Davenport Hall M/C 150, Urbana, IL 61801, USA. Email: <email>flint@illinois.edu</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>170</fpage>
<lpage>173</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>General support is given for the call by Alexander Murphy for a study of regions to enable geographers to engage in public debates. However, Murphy’s emphasis upon narrative is challenged and an argument is made for a theoretical framework within which to situate analysis of regions. Moreover, the “meso” scale of the region demands consideration of a larger, or “macro,” scale. World-systems theory is advanced as a framework that defines the global scale as the capitalist world-economy in a way that situates regions and gives meaning to their form and interaction. The empirical approach offered by world-systems theory enhances Murphy’s call for regional narratives and enables geographers to engage in public debates.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>capitalist world-economy</kwd>
<kwd>regions</kwd>
<kwd>scale</kwd>
<kwd>world-systems theory</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-2043820613490131">Murphy (2013)</xref> has advanced an important argument about the appropriate and relevant scale of analysis. Generally, I agree with the three major premises: (1) geographers should analyze larger scales; (2) such analysis should be empirical; and (3) the product of the analysis should be made accessible and relevant to nonacademic audience<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-2043820613490131">s. Murphy (2005</xref>) has made a similar argument before in his discussion of mesolevel typologies to understand nationalism and conflict. He has also made important arguments, for which the whole discipline should be truly grateful, for presenting knowledge in a manner that can inform the wider public, a service tied to his past role as President of the Association of American Geographers.</p>
<p>However, and in the spirit of dialogue that is the raison d’etre of this journal, I would like to take issue with the content and sequence of his argument. I get the impression that the primary intent of Murphy’s argument is to advance a form of public geography that can contend with public figures such as Robert Kaplan and Samuel Huntington. A public geography, in other words, that has the ear of, if not the Prince himself, then the broad strata of foreign policy elite managers in government and nongovernmental organizations that largely set and execute (literally in the case of drone attacks and other military actions) policies of US-led global intervention. The sequence of Murphy’s argument rather backs in to this, when this goal is essential for choosing the three types of regional narratives discussed. Specifically, the characterization, comparison, and usage of regions beg the questions by and for whom.</p>
<sec id="section1-2043820613490131">
<title>Critique</title>
<p>My central issue with Murphy’s presentation is that there is no theoretically informed understanding of how to generate broad regional narratives and hence no criteria for what the content is, on what basis comparisons can be made, and what sort of knowledge is constructed that could then be used by different public constituencies. Perhaps the problem lies, or is best addressed, in identifying two terminological inconsistencies I see in Murphy’s argument.</p>
<p>First, there is an inconsistency in calling for narratives and an empirically grounded approach to regions. Though “empirically grounded” is consistently employed in the definition of the regional approach more weight is actually given to the term narrative as a form of geopolitical representation in the manner commonly employed by critical geopoliticians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-2043820613490131">Ó Tuathail, 1996</xref>). The weight of the argument is about representations, and especially the mythical and intentionally biased narratives mobilized to enable US-led policies of global intervention and rule. The important point to emerge from this inconsistency is that the role of empirics is moved into the background and so the need to identify theoretical frameworks (and please note the plural) to allow for rigorous characterization, comparison, and usage is not given the emphasis it deserves.</p>
<p>The second inconsistency lies in the usage of the terms meso and broad/grand. Though Murphy takes time and care to distinguish between meso or grand and meta, the concentration is upon theory and not scale. The result is that the region is identified not just as the most important or imperative unit of analysis but also the ultimate or highest. No theoretical justification is made for this limitation. To put it more bluntly, no social theory is presented to explain regions as a particular social feature or more accurately a historical–geographical social feature.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-2043820613490131">
<title>Narratives need theories</title>
<p>
<italic>Warning:</italic> the rest of this article is likely to contain a strong dosage of world-systems theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-2043820613490131">Wallerstein, 1983</xref>). Though geographers may find this approach exotic or unusual please do not be alarmed. The reader can be reassured that they have recently been exposed to world-systems theory in Murphy’s essay, both in implicit and explicit dosages, but curiously no acknowledgment was given. Younger readers should also note that the current vitality of the subdiscipline of political geography is a relatively recent phenomenon, and the revival that we are currently benefiting from owes much to the adoption and usage of world-systems theory by an array of political geographers in the 1980s (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-2043820613490131">Flint, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Though I will use world-systems theory to continue the dialogue with Murphy in this essay, I am sincere in my earlier claim that empirically grounded regional approaches require a plurality of theoretical frameworks. The broad-term geoeconomics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-2043820613490131">Mercille, 2008</xref>) would certainly appear relevant, as would approaches emphasizing comparative sovereignty regimes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-2043820613490131">Kuus and Agnew, 2008</xref>), to name just a couple. However, I see the use of world- systems to be particularly apt in studying regions, and follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-2043820613490131">Taylor (1991</xref>) in this claim. Not only is world-systems theory implicitly present in Murphy’s essay, I see it as being especially well-suited to provide a theoretical framework that enables the characterization, comparison, and, only subsequently, the usage or dissemination of knowledge of regions to a variety of audiences.</p>
<p>The first step in the argument is to present a reason why emphasis upon narrative is inadequate and problematic. In the discussion of competing regional narratives, there is a notable absence in Murphy’s list of references, Edward <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-2043820613490131">Said’s (1979)</xref> seminal text <italic>Orientalism</italic>. Another interesting absence is the more controversial geopolitical analysis of Saul <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-2043820613490131">Cohen (1963</xref>). Cohen develops a theory of the regionalization of the world that provides a basis for discussing the content (or characterization) of regions and their relationship to each other. I do not agree with Cohen’s theoretical approach, but the key point here is that he has one, and a framework specifically designed to make sense of the world as a system comprised of politically constructed regions that interact through the geopolitics of conflict and cooperation.</p>
<p>The identification of regions is a political act, and if it is done mainly through a sense of narrative, it becomes a matter of representation rather than being empirically grounded. If narrative is the key, then geographers are the contemporary foot soldiers of Edward Said; nobly challenging representations, such as those of Kaplan and Huntington, deemed “bad” and “up to no political good.” I suspect Murphy thinks empirics will challenge these poor and politically motivated representations. My point is that unless they are to be challenged by something other than other representations (ones deemed “good”), then empirics is needed; but you cannot have empirics without a theoretical framework.</p>
<p>The particular benefits of world-systems theory as a means to situate regional narratives rest in the purpose and content of the approach. One motivation of the theory was to change the ontology of social science (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-2043820613490131">Wallerstein, 1983</xref>), a similar goal to Murphy’s. Instead of a regional focus, the purpose was to define the unit of analysis as the historical social system; the contemporary system being the capitalist world-economy. Hence, as with Murphy’s approach, the state is not seen as the primary unit of analysis, but is situated within a broader social system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-2043820613490131">Wallerstein, 1979</xref>). Regions are, indeed, the mesoscale of analysis, situated within the global geographic scope of the capitalist world-economy.</p>
<p>The capitalist world-economy is differentiated, as Murphy would like us to recognize. According to world-systems theory, the dominant processes of differentiation are economic and result in a structure of inequality. The dual operation of core processes (high value-added and high wages) and peripheral processes (low value-added and low wages) is manifest in multiple geographies of capital accumulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-2043820613490131">Wallerstein, 1983</xref>). Though many studies have, erroneously, territorialized and reified core and peripheral processes as homogeneous state entities (i.e. “the US is a core country”), the manifestation of core and peripheral processes occurs at a variety of scales, from neighborhoods to regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-2043820613490131">Terlouw, 1992</xref>). Such differentiation means that a simple regional narrative (i.e. Western Europe as core) would be too simplistic. On the other hand, understanding the narrative of Western Europe as a region of the capitalist world-economy in which core processes dominate is one that is theoretically informed and can serve as a guide for empirical analysis. It is a narrative but one that is given purpose, expression, and clarity within a theoretical framework.</p>
<p>Another aspect of world-systems theory relevant to regional narratives is the idea of <italic>one logic</italic> in which what are usually defined as separate political and economic processes and entities are seen as components of the imperative of ceaseless capital accumulation. This means that states are not given ontological primacy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-2043820613490131">Chase-Dunn, 1989</xref>). Instead, the processes of empire, state construction, and the dissolution of both states and empires are driven by the logic of capitalism. Continual construction of such political entities produces the dynamism of the extent and nature of regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-2043820613490131">Taylor, 1991</xref>). To emphasize the last point, dynamics play an important role in world-systems theory and hence the changing nature of regions can be identified and explained.</p>
<p>The final benefit of using world-systems theory to frame regional narratives is its rationale and ability to make connections between geographical spaces. One set of roots for world-systems theory is the dependency school and the notion of the “development of underdevelopment” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-2043820613490131">Frank, 1978</xref>). The axiom that wealth accumulation requires exploitation that results in socioeconomic inequalities is given geographic expression in spaces with varying mixtures of core and peripheral processes. Geographic differentiation, including at the regional scale, is a product of the core–periphery connections that span the globe; connections that are ever changing, creating new regional expressions and linkages. The global scope of the processes of the capitalist world-economy is a macroframework in which dynamic and interconnected regional narratives can be situated and understood.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-2043820613490131">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>I reiterate my main points. First, I support Murphy’s call for a geography that is grounded in creating knowledge of regions. However, the claim that this approach is focused on “narrative” at a “meso” scale is problematic and requires clarification. Second, knowledge construction requires a theoretical framework to organize and interpret analysis. I believe that a plurality of theoretical frameworks is the most fertile way forward. In this essay, I have promoted world-systems theory as a framework in which regional mesonarratives can be situated and connected to each other through the dynamism and logic of the capitalist world-economy. Third, a theoretically informed empirical analysis of regions can be disseminated to nonacademic audiences to counter dominant geopolitical narratives; and this approach is an effective way to challenge misrepresentations and their policy implications. My final thought is that though I have some criticisms of Murphy’s approach, I wholeheartedly support the notion that the contribution geographers make is best illustrated by an empirical engagement with the real spatial diversity of the world and its impact upon everyday life chances.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chase-Dunn</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>Global Formation</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1963</year>) <source>Geography and Politics in a World Divided</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Random House</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Flint</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Geographic perspectives on world-systems theory</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>R</surname>
<given-names>Denemark</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed) <source>International Studies Compendium</source>. <publisher-loc>Malden, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>2828</fpage>–<lpage>2845</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frank</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <source>Dependent Accumulation and Underdevelopment</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Monthly Review Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kuus</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Agnew</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Theorizing the state geographically: sovereignty, subjectivity, territoriality</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>KR</surname>
<given-names>Cox</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>M</surname>
<given-names>Low</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>J</surname>
<given-names>Robinson</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>SAGE Handbook of Political Geography</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles and London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mercille</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The radical geopolitics of U.S. foreign policy: Geopolitical and geoeconomic logics of power</article-title>. <source>Political Geography</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>570</fpage>–<lpage>586</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murphy</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Territorial ideology and interstate conflict: Comparative considerations</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>C</surname>
<given-names>Flint</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed) <source>The Geography of War and Peace</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murphy</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Advancing geographical understanding: Why engaging grand regional narratives matters</article-title>. <source>Dialogues in Human Geography</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>). <comment>doi: 10.1177/2043820613490253</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ó Tuathail</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Critical Geopolitics</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Said</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <source>Orientalism</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Vintage Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>A theory and practice of regions: the case of Europes</article-title>. <source>Environment and Planning D: Society and Space</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Terlouw</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <source>The Regional Geography of the World-System: Periphery, Semi-Periphery, and Core</source>. <publisher-loc>Utrecht, The Netherlands</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nederlandse Geografische Studies</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wallerstein</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <source>The Capitalist World-Economy</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-2043820613490131">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wallerstein</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <source>Historical Capitalism</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>