<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JLS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjls</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Language and Social Psychology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0261-927X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6526</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0261927X12462696</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0261927X12462696</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Elements of Meaning in Gesture</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lavoie</surname><given-names>Dusty</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0261927X12462696">University of Maine, Orono, ME, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>32</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>110</fpage>
<lpage>114</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Calbris</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Elements of Meaning in Gesture</source> (<person-group person-group-type="translator">
<name><surname>Copple</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, Trans.). <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Benjamins</publisher-name>. <page-count count="378"/> pp. ISBN <isbn>978-90-272-2847-5</isbn></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Calbris’s (2011) <italic>Elements of Meaning in Gesture</italic> is a gripping rumination on the study of gesture as a socially symbolic act. When we communicate, she writes, we use “parallel sensory pathways, audio-oral and visual-gestural, that interact in multimodal communication, that is, the ensemble of spoken linguistic, prosodic, intonational, gestural, postural, and facial activity [in which] participants engage [. . .] when they ‘talk’” (p. 5). Treading respectfully on the groundbreaking framework lain by structuralists and poststructuralists alike (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0261927X12462696">Austin, 1962</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0261927X12462696">Derrida, 1981</xref>; Goffman, 1956/<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0261927X12462696">1959</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0261927X12462696">Knapp &amp; Hall, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0261927X12462696">Lakoff &amp; Johnson, 1980</xref>; de Saussure, 1916/<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0261927X12462696">2006</xref>), this book looks at the production of socially significant memes in contemporary culture as expressed through gesture. In general, gestural processes are slightly oversimplified by those outside linguistics, speech communication, and pathology: A wave means “hello” or “goodbye,” and a nod of the head indicates understanding, agreement, or the equivalent “yes.” Here, though, the reader progressively comes to understand the complex production of meaning through gesture in four stages of the book: Part 1 (the functions of gesture in relation to speech), Part 2 (the systematic organization of gestural signs), Part 3 (the symbolic relations between gestures and notions), and Part 4 (the gestural sign in utterance). Thus, the organization of Calbris’s work presents a meditation on gestures in terms of function, organization, symbolism, and signification.</p>
<p>“‘Utterance,’” Series Editor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0261927X12462696">Kendon (2011)</xref> writes in the book’s Foreword, “is a <italic>polymodal</italic> activity” (p. xv, italics original): It involves the head, face, eyes, posture, and hand movements at least. But rather than being considered as a mere by-product of the speech process itself, researchers in the field have increasingly become attuned to how the production of gesture contributes to and coexists with meaning making through the medium of speech. This is a radical flipping of the linear thought-speech-action paradigm that has been taken as “natural” by previous scholars since the 19th century. That outdated paradigm must now be reconsidered in terms of its relevance to the new understanding of the atemporal contingencies between utterance, gesture, and meaning. In ancient Greece, of course, bodily gestures were thought of as inherent properties of any good rhetor or orator. Since Darwin and Freud, though, the emphases on mammalian generalization and on psychoanalytic desires, respectively, in the social sciences have pushed gestures into a realm of niche studies with mostly ignored or disregarded theories. Even Calbris’s own work, a more Francocentric version derived from her four-volume dissertation in the early 1980s, was initially ignored by most academicians until later in the decade.</p>
<p>But steadily since the 1970s—not coincidentally alongside the rise of performance studies—researchers interested in communication, semiotics, linguistics, social psychology, and performance studies have increasingly returned to the concepts of bodies and gestures as visual metaphors formed concomitantly with the ideas expressed through their very representation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0261927X12462696">Barthes, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0261927X12462696">Langellier &amp; Peterson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0261927X12462696">Mirzoeff, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0261927X12462696">Rose, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0261927X12462696">Sturken &amp; Cartwright, 2009</xref>). “Speakers do this quite commonly and as an integral part of how they convey meaning,” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0261927X12462696">Kendon (2011</xref>, p. xvii) writes. He tells us that Calbris’s research shows how “gesture is a kind of pivot between the concrete and the abstract. It can suggest the process by which abstract conceptions are formed out of concrete perceptions and actions” (p. xvii). In other words, gesturing is not simply an add-on or afterthought to meaning making; it is inherently constitutive of it.</p>
<p>Calbris is adept at fusing the major conventions of communication, linguistics, and social psychology while maintaining a close connection with the reader to present a case that may appear to be a “given” but is in actuality a departure from the traditional understanding of gestures as byproducts of meaning making. For example, the book mentions how the corpus of Jean Piaget’s educational theories of comprehension, mimesis, and learned skills made him one of the main catalysts that quickly supplanted orthodox homeschooling with the enterprise of public schooling as the nation made its entry into modernity. And although some see a linear progression from imitation to mimesis and finally to gesturing, Calbris argues that “kinesic representational expression frequently precedes verbal expression during the process of utterance production” (p. 3, italics added). Moreover, such gesture making is not arbitrary; on the contrary, it has a specific “<italic>motivated</italic> origin” (p. 4, italics original) that “anticipates the verbal formulation of the thought to be expressed” (p. 5).</p>
<p>This relatively new inter-discipline therefore seeks to spark the potential for the undertaking of promising, intersectional, and transdisciplinary lines of inquiry by authors such as Calbris. By providing such a deft hand to her objects of study, she manages to convincingly rethematize several disciplines. For its close observation of the communicative aspects of ideas, bodies, and gestures, this book should be encouraged reading for the people who actually comprise the “scholarly elite.” Regardless, scholars of Gesture Studies should feel empowered to have had the opportunity to successfully influence their fields instead of the usual other way around. In this way, Gesture Studies can lend a helping hand, as it were, in the inevitability of the rebuilding of its crumbling mothership, but this will only happen if, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0261927X12462696">Moylan (1986)</xref> insists, we “demand the impossible.” Calbris’s work suggests we do so.</p>
<p>Bureaucratically, various levels of disciplinary walls that have been long-standing and unquestioned have just recently been breached by scholars such as Calbris: intellectuals with aspirations more than the mere capacity to survive and reproduce. In a span of the 30 years between when she began her dissertation and its official publication just last year, Calbris writes that she became more intimately acquainted with the unemployed, undernourished, and destitute—conditions of the social existence of the working poor or the homeless that persist. In light of the contemporary cultural, political, and financial predicament within academia, it would be excellent if scholars and nonscholars alike were to take seriously the epistemic, self-destructivist divisiveness that continues to separate us and instead look for opportunities of unity. As one particularly persuasive example, Gesture Studies is now on the cutting edge of scholarly research in communication that—rather than necessarily seeking out the latest fad or most provocative “new idea”—instead respectfully yet playfully toys with its disciplines’ most sacred, normative, and sometimes nonproductive conventions to effect positive change or, at the very least, to try to encourage the system to fall into disrepair or even to implode from within. To combat submission, regimentation, and depersonalization, this field offers subversion, hybridity, and personality.</p>
<p>The structure of <italic>Elements of Meaning in Gesture</italic> feels natural and unforced, indicating a firm grasp of the most salient details of the field. The book is quartered into groups under Calbris’s four-tier description of Gesture Studies as a field that is interested in the making and disseminating of meaning through the use of vocal, facial, or bodily inflections. Thus, just as academia is itself categorized into compartmental groups based on their natural (or unnatural) paradigms, so too is this treatment of Gesture Studies, but here it works. Calbris’s book tries to bridge the gap between qualitative and quantitative methodologies as well as those inherent among the various disciplines for which it can be illuminating. In this way, Gesture Studies appears to lie just to the left of the center of the political spectrum in its hybridized capabilities and in its potential to provoke and reproblematize disciplinary boundaries. This seems healthy for an institution that is ostensibly opposed to significant change.</p>
<p>The four sections of the book are prefaced by a useful Introduction and a terminology section (Chapter 1) for those who are new to the field. Then, in Part 1 (functions), Chapter 2 presents the demarcative function of gestures wherein the distinguishing between one and another gesture sets the stage for the context that co-constitutes it. Gestures’ referential function is described in Chapter 3, in which temporal, vocal, and kinesic instantiations all become significant in the meaning-making process as performed through gesture. Next, Part 2 (organization) contains two chapters addressing the issue of categorization of gestures into priority components, the first of which (Chapter 4) provides “a panoramic view of how gestures can be classified according to the different physical elements [that] are semantically relevant” (p. 100). It then delves into the classification of gestures based on localization, movement, and the use of body parts. In Chapter 5 comes useful analysis of the characteristics of gesture as based on their “physico-semantic derivation” (p. 166) and as categorized and described by the coding system customarily used by contemporary Gesture Studies scholars.</p>
<p>Part 3 (symbolism) presents the relationship between gestures and notions in three chapters. First, in Chapter 6, Calbris demonstrates how one notion can be expressed in several ways through the use of various gestures in certain tenses, ratios, and frequencies. Second, Chapter 7 conversely shows how one gesture may be perceived and interpreted in a variety of polysemic ways, including through the use of variants, multiple symbols, plural motivation, and indeterminacy. That is to say nothing about simple gazes, metagestures (gestures about gestures), and the gesture that may anticipate forthcoming speech or action. The result in these cases may be clear to those involved, though ambiguity and miscommunication seem more likely within this complex web than it would be if there were a way to get outside it. Chapter 8 rounds out this part of the book with a discussion centered on distinguishing the analogical links between gestures and notions. Here especially, the inclusion and integration of sketches and comic strips help keep the reader grounded amid all the terminology; they also provide additional learning opportunities for those whose primary learning style is not linguistic.</p>
<p>Finally, Part 4 (signification) teases out the chicken-and-egg scenario of the gesture and the speech that both vocalizes and co-constitutes meaning through utterance production. Chapter 9 delves into the murky waters of double meanings, intentional ambiguity, socioeconomic status, change across subjectivities, and gestural interaction. It provides “more evidence of the multifunctionality of the gestural sign serving referential, expressive, pedagogical, phatic, and predictive functions” (p. 285). In Chapter 10, Calbris brings the study full circle by thematizing the triangulation of gesture, thought, and speech, though she never goes so far as to claim definitively which necessarily comes first, if any. She does discuss abstractness versus concreteness as well as iconicity versus metaphor as represented via gesture. Put shortly, the alternately named “flower/seed” scenario can be understood as an unexplainable phenomenon akin to an experience some readers may have had at department stores in the 1980s and 1990s. The infinity of mirrors facing each other seems to represent the impossible simultaneity of the simplistic Cartesian split between body and mind, a dualism that in some ways is still paradigmatic in some departments of communication and other related fields in the social sciences and the humanities, despite its widely accepted outmodedness.</p>
<p>Overall, <italic>Elements of Meaning in Gesture</italic> presents a robust Derridean <italic>supplément</italic> to Gesture Studies begun in earnest by so many men so many years ago. Thirty years after its inception, <italic>Elements of Meaning in Gesture</italic> now includes English and French translations of almost all of the hundreds of examples used herein; it is deeply and thoroughly researched; and it is aimed at educated readers with a useful overview of the transdisciplinary subfield known as Gesture Studies. In doing so, it also provides diagrams, appendices, and people and subject indices. These qualities—along with its opening up of a space for potential future research into Gesture Studies’ relationships to representation, to ideological apparatuses, to computer-mediated communication, and to the relevant work of Barthes and Kristeva—give the book opportunities to “serve as an inspiration for psychological, ethnographical, and linguistic studies on gestures with speech” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0261927X12462696">Müller, 2011</xref>, p. 367).</p>
<p>Today, Calbris argues “that a gestural sign only ever exists in a given context” (p. 6). Her presentational thesis becomes clear through the use of numerous examples; countless sketches, diagrams, charts, tables, and flowcharts; and the technological augmentation of our understanding of the examples of audio-video clips available online. Additionally, consideration of gestural meaning making in this book takes into account its beholder’s speed of talking, the space surrounding him or her, as well as the combinations of various gestures at various rates in various spaces. In sum, the book highlights “the importance of gesture in the utterance of thought and how gesture expresses deep perceptual schemas via spontaneous, non-conscious iconicity, thus confirming the existence of spatial metaphors underlined by cognitive linguistics. Furthermore,” as Calbris summarizes in the Conclusion, Gesture Studies “brings to light [other metaphors that] are even less conscious and just as fundamental” (p. 353). In a few words, Calbris summarizes the book’s overarching thesis that contextual qualities of our surroundings become “abstractions in our minds [that] are thus made visible as they re-emerge in our bodies” (p. 354), and so on, it seems.</p>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<title>Bio</title>
<p><bold>Dusty Lavoie</bold> (PhD, University of Maine, 2011) is an independent scholar. His interests include language and composition, communication and media, literary theory and critical/cultural theory, semiotics and rhetoric, and ideological and performative analysis.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1962</year>). <source>How to do things with words</source> (<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Urmson</surname><given-names>J. O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sbisà</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, Eds.; <edition>2nd. ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barthes</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <source>A Barthes reader</source> (<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Sontag</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, Ed.). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hill &amp; Wang</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Derrida</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <source>Dissemination</source> (<person-group person-group-type="translator">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, Trans.). <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goffman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1959</year>). <source>The presentation of self in everyday life</source>. <publisher-loc>Garden City, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Doubleday</publisher-name>. (Original work published 1956)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kendon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Foreword</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Calbris</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.) &amp; <person-group person-group-type="translator">
<name><surname>Copple</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group>(Trans.), <source>Elements of meaning in gesture</source> (pp. <fpage>xv</fpage>-<lpage>xviii</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Benjamins</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Nonverbal communication in human interaction</source>. <publisher-loc>Independence, KY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wadsworth</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lakoff</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <source>Metaphors we live by</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Langellier</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Storytelling in daily life: Performing narrative</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Mirzoeff</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.). (<year>2002</year>). <source>The visual culture reader</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moylan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <source>Demand the impossible: Science fiction and the utopian imagination</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Postscript</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Calbris</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.) &amp; <person-group person-group-type="translator">
<name><surname>Copple</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Trans.), <source>Elements of meaning in gesture</source> (pp. <fpage>367</fpage>-<lpage>368</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Benjamins</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Visual methodologies: An introduction to the interpretation of visual materials</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>de Saussure</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Writings in general linguistics</source> (<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bouquet</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Engler</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weil</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, Eds.; &amp; <person-group person-group-type="translator">
<name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, Trans.). <publisher-loc>Oxford, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>. (Original work published 1916)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0261927X12462696">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sturken</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cartwright</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Practices of looking: An introduction to visual culture</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>