<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">WMR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spwmr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Waste Manag Res</journal-id>
<journal-title>Waste Management &amp; Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0734-242X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1096-3669</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0734242X12471098</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0734242X12471098</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Removal of chloride from fly ash produced in hazardous waste incineration by leaching and displacement washing in a vertical filter press</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Kinnarinen</surname><given-names>Teemu</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0734242X12471098">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Huhtanen</surname><given-names>Mikko</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0734242X12471098">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Penttilä</surname><given-names>Mika</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0734242X12471098">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Häkkinen</surname><given-names>Antti</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0734242X12471098">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0734242X12471098"><label>1</label>LUT Chemistry, Lappeenranta University of Technology, Lappeenranta, Finland</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0734242X12471098"><label>2</label>Ekokem-Service, Riihimäki, Finland</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0734242X12471098">Teemu Kinnarinen, LUT Chemistry, Lappeenranta University of Technology, P.O. Box 20, FI-53851 Lappeenranta, Finland. Email: <email>teemu.kinnarinen@lut.fi</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>31</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>178</fpage>
<lpage>186</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">International Solid Waste Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Fly ash is generated in large quantities by waste incineration processes. Chloride is commonly present in the fly ash produced by the incineration of hazardous materials, such as polyvinylchloride plastic. Major difficulties related to the disposal and handling of fly ash include the high concentration of easily leachable chlorides, heavy metals and toxic compounds. In order to avoid adverse environmental effects from the disposal of fly ash, the content of soluble chlorides must be reduced. One of the most effective options for chloride removal is leaching and displacement washing in a filter press. The primary aim of this study was to obtain efficient removal of chloride from fly ash by utilizing a leaching and displacement washing process, carried out in a filter press. The secondary objective was to obtain high filtration capacities and low filter cake moisture contents. The slurry was prepared by mixing fly ash with water at an ash:water ratio of 1:2 and filtered to separate the solids from the liquid. After solid–liquid separation, most of the dissolved residual chloride was removed from the filter cake by washing the cake with fresh water in the second stage of separation. It was possible to remove up to 98% of the total chloride and to obtain sufficient filtration capacities. The residual moisture content of the filter cakes varied from 22 to 35 wt%, which meant that the cakes could be disposed of in landfill, or possibly utilized as a construction material.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Fly ash</kwd>
<kwd>hazardous waste incineration</kwd>
<kwd>chloride removal</kwd>
<kwd>filter press</kwd>
<kwd>leaching</kwd>
<kwd>cake washing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0734242X12471098" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The increasing use of waste materials for energy production by incineration has reduced the unnecessary disposal of combustible waste in landfills. However, waste incineration always produces ash fractions, which may contain a large variety of contaminants. Some fly ashes are characterized by their high chloride and heavy metal content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0734242X12471098">Aguiar del Toro et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0734242X12471098">Pan et al., 2008</xref>), which sets challenges for their utilization and disposal from the technical and environmental points of view. Local groundwater pollution, for instance, can be caused by fly ash landfill leachates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0734242X12471098">Nzihou and Sharrock, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>The chloride content in fly ash varies greatly, depending on the type of the material incinerated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0734242X12471098">Kumar et al., 2007</xref>). Other soluble and insoluble salts are also present. Many of the chlorides produced, such as alkali metal chlorides and alkaline earth metal chlorides, have a high solubility in water. Therefore, chloride removal by leaching, also referred to as water extraction, or dissolution, can be technically feasible. The washed solid fraction can be then separated from the salt-containing liquid using filtration technology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0734242X12471098">Wilewska-Bien et al., 2007</xref>). As a result of successful fly ash washing and filtration, the leaching tendency of the solid cakes should be low. Squeezing of the cakes in a filter press at high pressures, after leaching at proper conditions, may help to achieve this requirement.</p>
<p>Residual chloride reduces the potentiality of ash utilization for applications such as cement and concrete production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0734242X12471098">Poon et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0734242X12471098">Zhu et al., 2010</xref>) and road construction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0734242X12471098">Ahmaruzzaman, 2010</xref>) by its erosive effects. Treatment of the saline liquid after leaching is also an important issue as, although it is outwith the scope of this study. For instance, chloride could be removed from the filtrate using ion-exchange resins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0734242X12471098">Brown et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X12471098">Jemaa et al., 1999</xref>). Concentration of the liquids using membrane technology, as well as stabilization of the heavy metals in the filter cake, are among the most promising technologies for alleviating the environmental impacts of the process. Fly ash has been recognized as a potential adsorbent for acid wastewater neutralization and heavy metal removal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0734242X12471098">González et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0734242X12471098">Wang and Wu, 2006</xref>). It has also been used as a soil ameliorant for improving crop production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0734242X12471098">Jala and Goyal, 2006</xref>). Irrespective of the end use of the solids, it is important to obtain an acceptable washing result, with minimal wash water consumption. The objective of this experimental study was to obtain a high degree of chloride removal using a filter press for the treatment of fly ash obtained from a hazardous waste incineration plant. A relatively similar process, comprising leaching of municipal solid waste incinerator (MSWI) fly ash followed by displacement washing, has been studied earlier by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0734242X12471098">Wilewska-Bien et al. (2007)</xref>. In their study, washing and dewatering of filter cakes was performed using both laboratory-scale and pilot-scale filters. Unlike the previous studies on this subject, the present study had main focus on the pressure filtration stage. The effect of important operational variables of the vertical filter press on the washing result were investigated and modeled.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0734242X12471098" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="section3-0734242X12471098">
<title>Process description</title>
<p>The idea of the fly ash handling process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0734242X12471098">Figure 1</xref>) was to mix fly ash with water so as to dissolve soluble chlorides and to separate the washed solids from the saline waste liquid using a pressure filter. The fly ash sample was obtained from a Finnish hazardous waste incineration plant. Cake-washing tests with different washing ratios were carried out for most filter cakes.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0734242X12471098" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The fly ash washing process, with an approximate mass balance for the treatment of 100 kg fly ash.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12471098-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0734242X12471098">
<title>Slurry preparation</title>
<p>The fly ash sample for the washing experiments was received from Ekokem, a company that operates a hazardous waste incineration plant in Finland. The main types of waste and hazardous waste incinerated at the plant include solid waste, solvents, paste-like waste, wastewater handling residues and oils. Slurry batches of approximately 100 dm<sup>3</sup> were prepared by mixing dry ash with water in a constant mass ratio of 1:2. The average density of the slurry was 1230 kg m<sup>–3</sup>. The chloride concentrations in the dry ash and in the slurry were 22.5% and 7.5% respectively. The slurry was mixed in a 120 dm<sup>3</sup> tank overnight to ensure that there was equilibrium between the chloride content of the solid and the liquid. Additionally, dissolution of ash salts into water, together with mixing friction, generated heat, which raised the slurry temperature rapidly to about 40°C. A constant slurry temperature of 30°C was obtained during the mixing time of about 20 h. Based on measurements carried out during the leaching period, chloride is dissolved almost completely within minutes. This means that the solid–liquid separation should be performed optimally very soon after the leaching, when the temperature of the slurry is still high and, consequently, the liquid viscosity is lower.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0734242X12471098">
<title>Test equipment</title>
<p>The filtration and washing experiments were conducted using a Larox PF 0.1 pressure filter unit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0734242X12471098">Figure 2</xref>). The filter system comprised a slurry tank, a diaphragm pump for feeding the slurry into the filter, a filter chamber (<italic>A</italic> = 0.1 m<sup>2</sup>) with a height of 45 mm and a pressurized wash water tank. The wash water was distributed over the filter cake at a pressure of 1 bar, driven by compressed air. The mass of the filtrate, the pressure in the slurry feed pipe and the pressing pressure were recorded continuously.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0734242X12471098" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Larox PF 0.1 pressure filter. The mixing tank (1), the wash water tank (2) and the filter chamber (3).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12471098-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0734242X12471098">
<title>Filtration and cake-washing experiments</title>
<p>All stages of the fly ash washing process including leaching, filtration and cake-washing were performed using the filter shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0734242X12471098">Figure 2</xref>. Five stages of operation were included in a typical filtration sequence in the pressure filter:</p>
<list id="list1-0734242X12471098" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>filtration</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>first cake pressing</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>displacement washing of the cake</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>second cake pressing</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>air dewatering.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The test variables included (i) the filtration time, (ii) pressing pressure after cake-washing, and (iii) air drying time. The ranges of these variables were (i) 100–300 s, (ii) 10–13 bar, and (iii) 0–240 s. The filtration pressure (6 bar), pressing pressure before cake washing (12 bar), washing pressure (2 bar) and air drying pressure (6 bar) were held constant. The duration of cake-pressing varied from 50 to 100 s in the first pressing stage and from 140 to 250 s in the second pressing stage. The duration of the pressing was determined by the <italic>X-point</italic> that was reached at the point in time when a significant drop was observed in the feed line pressure due to blocking of the slurry feed port by the compression diaphragm. Additionally, three experiments were conducted without cake-washing in order to obtain reference values for the chloride content in the unwashed cake. The liquid/solid by weight (L/S) ratio (2:1) was kept constant during the experiments. Statistical design of experiments was utilized to create the experimental plan shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0734242X12471098">Figure 3</xref>. The value ranges of the variables were included into the experimental plan according to an augmented full factorial design. This kind of experimental design enabled good applicability of the results for regression modeling. Three reference tests in which the filter cakes were not washed were performed in addition to the plan.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0734242X12471098" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>An illustration of the experimental plan comprising 19 tests.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12471098-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The wash water consumption varied between 1.6 and 2.6 dm<sup>3</sup> per experiment, depending on the volume of the empty space above the filter cake after the first pressing. However, this volume was dependent on the duration of the filtration stage. Feeding of the wash water was stopped immediately when the pressure in the filter chamber was equal to the feed pressure (2 bar).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0734242X12471098">
<title>Analysis methods</title>
<p>Prior to the experiments, the slurry characteristics were determined. The analyses included particle size analysis, determination of the chloride content, electrical conductivity, and determination of the density and solid content of the slurry. Concentrations of heavy metals were determined from the liquid phase after leaching (L/S = 10) at the incineration plant using inductively coupled plasma optical emission spectroscopy, with the exception of mercury, which was assayed with AAS. However, the representativeness of the heavy metal concentrations for the ash sample used for the experiments in the laboratory cannot be guaranteed because the materials to be incinerated may vary considerably. Therefore, only approximate ranges for heavy metal concentrations are reported.</p>
<p>The particle size distribution of the fly ash, after the dissolution stage, was measured using a Beckman Coulter LS 13320 laser diffraction analyzer (Beckman Coulter, Brea, CA, USA). The average values obtained from three parallel analyses were <italic>D<sub>mean</sub></italic> = 79.9 μm, <italic>D<sub>median</sub></italic> = 50.9 μm, <italic>D<sub>10</sub> =</italic> 2.2 μm and <italic>D<sub>90</sub> =</italic> 205.5 μm. The size reduction of the solid particles during mixing, caused by mechanical forces and dissolution of soluble compounds, was also measured using the same particle size analyzer.</p>
<p>The settling velocity of ash particles in the slurry was determined in a graduated glass cylinder at 22°C.</p>
<p>The cakes were analyzed for moisture content, chloride concentration and conductivity. When determining the chloride concentration and conductivity, the cakes were suspended in Millipore water (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA) using a ratio of 1:9. The cake samples prepared this way were shaken occasionally and kept at 22°C for 48 h to dissolve the soluble chlorides from the cake samples. A Sherwood 926 chloride analyzer (Sherwood Scientific Ltd., Cambridge, UK) was used to determine the chloride concentration. The operation of such a robust, but reliable, chloride analyzer is based on coulometric titration and formation of an insoluble silver chloride precipitate. According to the manufacturer, the accuracy of analysis is 1 mg l<sup>–1</sup>. The conductivity of each sample was measured by using a Knick 702 conductivity meter.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0734242X12471098">
<title>Equations</title>
<p>In the equations shown, <italic>m</italic> represents the mass and <italic>V</italic> represents the volume. The moisture contents <italic>MC</italic> in the filter cakes were determined by drying the cake samples (average dry weight of 270 g) to constant weight at 105°C:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0734242X12471098">
<label>(1)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-0734242X12471098">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0734242X12471098" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12471098-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>In cases when the cakes are fully saturated, the average porosity <italic>ϵ<sub>av</sub></italic> of the filter cakes can be determined by drying and calculating the pore volume from the loss of weight. Inversely, the average porosity can be calculated from the volumes of solids after determining the density of solids. The cake volume is calculated based on cake dimensions.</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0734242X12471098">
<label>(2)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math2-0734242X12471098">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>ε</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0734242X12471098" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12471098-eq2.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>There are two common ways to define the washing ratio, namely the mass of wash water per mass of dry solids (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-0734242X12471098">equation (3)</xref>) and the volume of wash water per pore volume of the cake (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-0734242X12471098">equation (4)</xref>). For cake washing by leaching, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-0734242X12471098">equation (3)</xref> is more commonly used, whereas <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-0734242X12471098">equation (4)</xref> is more frequently used for displacement washing.</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0734242X12471098">
<label>(3)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math3-0734242X12471098">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-0734242X12471098" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12471098-eq3.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0734242X12471098">
<label>(4)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math4-0734242X12471098">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula4-0734242X12471098" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12471098-eq4.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0734242X12471098" sec-type="results|discussion">
<title>Results and discussion</title>
<sec id="section10-0734242X12471098">
<title>General observations</title>
<p>The average particle size of solids in the slurry reduced while the slurry was mixed to dissolve the chloride. The median particle size, <italic>D<sub>median</sub></italic> decreased from 72 µm to 51 µm in 24 h. As the reduction of particle size is not favorable when considering filterability (because of increasing cake resistance and clogging of the filter medium) the leaching time should be kept as short as possible. Regarding the dissolution of soluble components, such as chloride, similar observations have been reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0734242X12471098">Wilewska-Bien et al. (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0734242X12471098">Wang et al. (2010)</xref>.</p>
<p>The average cake resistance, <italic>α<sub>av</sub></italic>, in the filtration tests at 6 bar was about 4.10<sup>10</sup> m kg<sup>–1</sup>. The suspended solid concentration in the filtrate ranged from 0.10 to 0.20 g l<sup>–1</sup>, the majority of which was observed to accumulate during the first seconds of each filtration experiment, i.e. before any filter cake was formed.</p>
<p>Even though heavy metals were out of the scope of this study, their concentrations in the non-washed fly ash were determined. The analyses were performed for water-leached samples, which gave information about easily leachable heavy metal salts. The quality of the hazardous waste incinerated varies by time. Therefore, only approximate values for this type of fly ash are given: arsenic, chromium, molybdenum, antimony, mercury &lt;1 ppm; barium, nickel &lt;10 ppm; cadmium, lead &lt;150 ppm; zinc &gt;1000 ppm.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0734242X12471098">
<title>Settling properties of the slurry</title>
<p>Prior to the filtration tests, two settling experiments were carried out. Thickening of the slurry, for instance, by gravity settling would help to enhance the filtration capacities. A graduated glass (V = 1000 ml, h = 330 mm) was filled with the slurry at 25 °C and the height of the clarified layer was measured at certain time intervals. It was observed that a significant reduction (over 30 %) of the slurry volume can be obtained within 1–2 hours, even without flocculants or coagulants. The settling rate was slightly accelerated with the help of ferrous sulfate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0734242X12471098">Figure 4</xref>), which is typically used as an immobilization agent for trace elements. The mass of ferrous sulfate (FeSO4) added was 4.2% of the mass of the fly ash. However, the action of FeSO<sub>4</sub> may have been impeded by the high salt concentration of the slurry.</p>
<fig id="fig4-0734242X12471098" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Settling of fly ash particles in water at 25°C.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12471098-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0734242X12471098">
<title>Cake-washing</title>
<p>The remaining chloride concentration after displacement washing was strongly dependent upon the washing ratio that ranged from 0 to 1.85 (water:dry cake by mass). However, leaching followed by filtration accounted for most chloride removal, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0734242X12471098">Figure 5</xref>. Leaching using the L/S (water/ash) ratio of 2:1, followed by filtration without cake-washing, resulted in 87–88% chloride removal efficiency, while up to 98% of the chloride was removed by the combination of leaching and cake-washing. The most effective chloride removal was achieved when air drying of a filter cake was applied after the second pressing of the cake to remove the residual liquid from the pores in the cake.</p>
<fig id="fig5-0734242X12471098" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Measured and modeled scaled values for the residual chloride concentration in the filter cakes.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12471098-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The optimum S/L ratio in the leaching stage depends on the cost of fresh water, possibility to use countercurrent washing and the cost of treatment or regeneration of the wash water. From another point of view, the optimum S/L ratio is determined by the environmental regulations related to fly ash reuse and/or disposal.</p>
<p>There has been some research activity on fly ash handling issues in the recent years. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0734242X12471098">Mulder (1996)</xref> obtained a 92% decrease in the chloride concentration of MSWI fly ash by leaching at pH 4 (L/S = 10), vacuum filtration, two-stage cake washing (L/S = 2) prior to the second and third vacuum filtration steps. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0734242X12471098">Zhu et al. (2010)</xref> investigated the presence of chlorides in MSWI fly ash. They found that calcium chloride, sodium chloride and potassium chloride were the most important water-soluble chlorides, whereas insoluble chlorides were mainly in the form of Friedel’s salt (calcium chloroaluminate). Chloride removal of about 90% was achieved by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0734242X12471098">Wilewska-Bien et al. (2007)</xref>, who used leaching and subsequent cake-washing in a filter press for the treatment of MSWI fly ash.</p>
<p>As statistical design of experiments was utilized, the results were highly suitable for modeling purposes. The empirical model used for fly ash washing is linear with regard to filtration time <italic>x<sub>1</sub></italic>, pressing pressure <italic>x<sub>2</sub></italic> and air drying time <italic>x<sub>3</sub></italic>. The exponential term <italic>x<sub>4</sub></italic> represents the wash liquid volume. The model function is of the form</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0734242X12471098">
<label>(5)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math5-0734242X12471098">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula5-0734242X12471098" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12471098-eq5.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <italic>β<sub>1</sub>, β<sub>2</sub>, β<sub>3</sub></italic> and <italic>β<sub>4</sub></italic> are the coefficients of the variables (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0734242X12471098">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0734242X12471098" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Coefficients of the variables in the cake-washing model.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0734242X12471098" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12471098-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable <italic>x<sub>i</sub></italic></th>
<th align="left">Coefficient <italic>β<sub>i</sub></italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><italic>x<sub>1</sub></italic> (filtration time)</td>
<td>–2.056⋅10<sup>−4</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>x<sub>2</sub></italic> (pressing pressure)</td>
<td>–5.874⋅10<sup>−4</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>x<sub>3</sub></italic> (air drying time)</td>
<td>–3.048⋅10<sup>−4</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>x<sub>4</sub></italic> (volume of wash liquid)</td>
<td>5.734⋅10<sup>−1</sup></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The coefficient of determination (R<sup>2</sup>) for this model is 97.5%. The measured versus modeled plot is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0734242X12471098">Figure 5</xref>.</p>
<p>Based on <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0734242X12471098">Table 1</xref>, it can be expected that the best washing result is obtained when the filtration and air drying times are long, pressing pressure is high and a high volume of wash liquid is used.</p>
<p>The empirical model is a combination of the exponential decay model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X12471098">Marecek and Novotny, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0734242X12471098">Rhodes, 1934</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0734242X12471098">Salmela and Oja, 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X12471098">2006</xref>) and linear terms. Combining linear terms and exponential decay model in cake-washing processes is more comprehensively discussed in the article by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0734242X12471098">Huhtanen et al. (2012)</xref>.</p>
<p>The volume of water used in the cake-washing step was measured after each experiment, based on the volume needed for complete re-filling of the wash water tank. Measured and modeled results as a function of the wash water volume are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0734242X12471098">Figure 6A</xref>. The dimensionless Cl– concentration is defined as the ratio of the Cl<sup>–</sup> content in a washed sample to the Cl<sup>–</sup> content in a non-washed sample. Most of the deviation of the values in the washing curve is caused by the variation in the experimental conditions. The wash water consumption was not actually a variable in this study, but it was a function of the filtration time (height of the cake).</p>
<fig id="fig6-0734242X12471098" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>(A) Dimensionless scaled chloride concentration in dry fly ash in the filter cakes after leaching and pressure filtration (wash water volume = 0 l) and leaching followed by displacement washing and pressure filtration (wash water volume &gt; 0.6 l). Both measured and modeled results are shown. (B) Chloride content of the re-slurried cake samples as a function of electrical conductivity.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12471098-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Displacement washing proved to be an efficient method for chloride removal, even at low washing ratios. About 85% of the chloride remaining after the leaching, filtration and cake-pressing could be removed by displacement washing using a washing ratio of 1.6 (water:dry cake by mass), which resulted in up to a 98% reduction of soluble chloride concentration in the fly ash.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0734242X12471098">
<title>Electrical conductivity and chloride concentration</title>
<p>A strong correlation was observed between the electrical conductivity and the chloride concentration in the samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0734242X12471098">Figure 6B</xref>). However, the relationship was not linear. Conductivity of the filtrate is a commonly used measure of the performance of the cake-washing stage.</p>
<p>Therefore, it is extremely important to be aware of the possible non-linear correlation between the conductivity and the chloride concentration. When the washing process is evaluated based on conductivity data, a plot similar to that shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0734242X12471098">Figure 6B</xref> should always be created because the electrical conductivity depends on the total quantity of dissolved compounds, not only on chlorides, and is also influenced by suspended solids.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0734242X12471098">
<title>Residual moisture and filtration capacity</title>
<p>The residual (dimensionless) chloride content had quite a clear correlation with the cake moisture content (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0734242X12471098">Figure 7A</xref>). The significant difference between the chloride contents of washed and unwashed cakes is also seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0734242X12471098">Figure 7A</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig7-0734242X12471098" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>(A) Dependence of the residual chloride content on the moisture content in the filter cakes. (B) Moisture content and the residual proportion of chloride in the filter cakes at different dry solids capacities.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12471098-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>An important aim of any filtration process is to obtain a sufficient production capacity. In this study, solid fly ash was washed in a vertical filter press and the main focus was on the final purity of the cakes. The importance of high enough filtration capacities in the fly ash washing process should not be underestimated because the cost of such a waste treatment process depends largely on the required size of the filter. Both the moisture content and the chloride content of the filter cakes increased with the capacity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0734242X12471098">Figure 7B</xref>). This is simply explained by the differences in the filtration cycle times and especially by the fact that higher cake moisture contents were obtained without air drying.</p>
<p>The moisture content of the filter cakes varied from 22 to 35%. Both cake pressing at higher pressure and longer air drying were observed to reduce the moisture content and therefore also the chloride content.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0734242X12471098" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Removal of chloride from fly ash obtained from a hazardous waste incineration process was investigated in this study. The results show that a filter press can be used effectively for the solid–liquid separation after the leaching step. Significant reduction in the chloride contents of the filter cakes can be obtained at moderate water consumption. Dissolution of chlorides from fly ash was observed to be a rapid process. Based on the results, a dissolution time of 15 min would suffice. The relationship between the chloride concentration and the electrical conductivity was non-linear, which should be kept in mind when evaluating the washing results based on the conductivity of the filtrate. Thickening or centrifugation prior to filtration should be considered because the solid particles can be sedimented readily.</p>
<p>Washing of the filter cakes may be performed in order to further reduce the chloride content. Higher capacities could be obtained by thickening of the slurry after the leaching step before filtration. About 87–88 % of the chloride content from the slurry was removed by leaching (L/S = 2/1) followed by filtration. The maximum reduction of the chloride content in the fly ash was 98%—obtained using a washing ratio of 1.85 (water:dry cake by mass). Filter cakes contained 22–35% water and the filtration capacities ranged from 70 to 290 kg<sub>dry solids</sub> m<sup>–2</sup>h<sup>–1</sup>. Belt filter with countercurrent washing could be used to minimize the wash water consumption, but the main drawback would be the increase in the cake moisture contents.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aguiar del Toro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Calmano</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ecke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Wet extraction of heavy metals and chloride from MSWI and straw combustion fly ashes</article-title>. <source>Waste Management</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>2494</fpage>–<lpage>2499</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ahmaruzzaman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A review on the utilization of fly ash</article-title>. <source>Progress in Energy and Combustion Science</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Russel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paleologou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jemaa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Chloride removal from kraft liquors using ion exchange technology</article-title>. In: <conf-name>TAPPI Environmental Conference</conf-name>, <conf-date>5–8 April 1998</conf-date>, <conf-loc>Vancouver, BC, Canada</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>González</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Navia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Querol</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Development of a non-conventional sorbent from fly ash and its potential use in acid wastewater neutralization and heavy metal removal</article-title>. <source>Chemical Engineering Journal</source> <volume>166</volume>: <fpage>896</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huhtanen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salmimies</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kinnarinen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Häkkinen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ekberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kallas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Empirical modelling of cake washing in a pressure filter</article-title>. <source>Separation Science and Technology</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>1102</fpage>–<lpage>1112</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Fly ash as a soil ameliorant for improving crop production – a review</article-title>. <source>Bioresource Technology</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>1136</fpage>–<lpage>1147</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jemaa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paleologou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sheedy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Chloride removal from the kraft recovery boiler ESP dust using the precipitator dust purification (PDP) system</article-title>. <source>Pulp &amp; Paper Canada</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mehrotra</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Towards sustainable solutions for fly ash through mechanical activation</article-title>. <source>Resources, Conservation and Recycling</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marecek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Novotny</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Optimizing the performance of leaf filters</article-title>. <source>Filtration and Separation</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>, <fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>, <fpage>50</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Pre-treatment of MSWI fly ash for useful application</article-title>. <source>Waste Management</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nzihou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharrock</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Calcium phosphate stabilization of fly ash with chloride extraction</article-title>. <source>Waste Management</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Recycling MSWI bottom and fly ash as raw materials for Portland cement</article-title>. <source>Waste Management</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1113</fpage>–<lpage>1118</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A study on high strength concrete prepared with large volumes of low calcium fly ash</article-title>. <source>Cement and Concrete Research</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>–<lpage>455</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1934</year>) <article-title>Washing in filtration</article-title>. <source>Industrial &amp; Engineering Chemistry</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1331</fpage>–<lpage>1333</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salmela</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Washing and dewatering of different starches in pressure filters</article-title>. <source>Fluid/Particle Separation Journal</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>134</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salmela</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Monitoring and modelling of starch cake washing</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Food Science &amp; Technology</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>688</fpage>–<lpage>697</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Environmental-benign utilization of fly ash as low-cost adsorbents</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hazardous Materials</source> <volume>B136</volume>: <fpage>482</fpage>–<lpage>501</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Recycling of Municipal solid waste incineration fly ash for ordinary Portland cement production : A real-scale test</article-title>. <source>Resources, Conservation and Recycling</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>1428</fpage>–<lpage>1435</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilewska-Bien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lundberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steenari</surname><given-names>B-M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Theliander</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Treatment process for MSW combustion fly ash laboratory and pilot plant experiments</article-title>. <source>Waste Management</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1213</fpage>–<lpage>1224</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0734242X12471098">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takaoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oshita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kitajima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Inada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morisawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsuno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Chlorides behaviour in raw fly ash washing experiments</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hazardous Materials</source> <volume>178</volume>: <fpage>547</fpage>–<lpage>552</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>