<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HHC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphhc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Home Health Care Management &amp; Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1084-8223</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6739</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1084822312468136</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1084822312468136</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>University of Tennessee – Knoxville College of Nursing: Perspectives on Home Health</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Evaluating a Community-Based Family Caregiver Training Program</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Janet Witucki</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD, RN, CNE</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1084822312468136">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Shu-li</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD, RN, CNE, NEA-BC</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1084822312468136">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Pratsani</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD, RN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1084822312468136">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1084822312468136"><label>1</label>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1084822312468136"><label>2</label>South College, Knoxville, TN, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1084822312468136"><label>3</label>Boromarajonani College of Nursing, Bangkok, Thailand</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1084822312468136">Janet Witucki Brown, PhD, RN, CNE, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville, College of Nursing, 1200 Volunteer Blvd, Knoxville, TN 37996-4180, USA. Email: <email>jwitucki@utk.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>25</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>76</fpage>
<lpage>83</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This mixed-methods, time series study investigated the effectiveness of a Family Caregiver Training Program offered by a community-based agency. The training program and the impact of the training program on the family caregivers of older community dwelling adults were evaluated using quantitative and qualitative measures. Program evaluation results were used to revise and develop a Family Caregiver Training Program responsive to needs of the caregivers. There was a significant difference on the overall Adapted Revised Caregiving Appraisal Scale that measured caregiver burden, satisfaction, mastery, impact, and demand among three survey points. These positive results demonstrated effectiveness of the Family Caregiver Training Program. An added benefit was the socialization that occurred through meeting with other family caregivers who shared the same experiences.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>caregiving</kwd>
<kwd>family</kwd>
<kwd>training</kwd>
<kwd>older adults</kwd>
<kwd>evaluation</kwd>
<kwd>community dwelling</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1084822312468136" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Informal and family caregivers are unpaid individuals such as family members, friends, and neighbors who provide care and assistance to someone else who needs help. In the year 2008, there were an estimated 65.7 million family caregivers in the United States.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1084822312468136">1</xref></sup> Family caregivers spend an average of 20 hours per week providing care to loved ones and the value of the services that they provided has an estimated value of US$375 billion dollars a year.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1084822312468136">1</xref></sup> This trend is expected to increase exponentially as the population of the United States ages. By the year 2030, the population of those 65 years of age and older in the United States is projected to be 72.1 million.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1084822312468136">2</xref></sup> Many of these older adults will have chronic health conditions and require some assistance to remain in their own homes.</p>
<p>Care of an older family member with multiple needs at home can be challenging. Multiple skills are needed. Many family caregivers provide some type of “nursing care” for their loved ones, such as giving medications, changing bandages, managing machinery, and monitoring vital signs, often with no training.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1084822312468136">3</xref></sup> Information needs identified by caregivers include dealing with forgetfulness and confusion, handling mobility problems, and dealing with stress.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1084822312468136">4</xref></sup> Family caregiver training programs can provide an essential support to these informal caregivers. The importance of such programs is supported by the fact that the US Department of Health and Human Services in its Healthy People 2020 agenda focuses on increasing support for caregivers and identifies the importance of identifying minimum levels of training for people who care for older adults and the need for research and analysis of appropriate training to equip providers with the tools they need to meet needs of older adults.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1084822312468136">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>Family caregiver training programs can be offered in a variety of venues and vary in the topics covered and the length of the program. However, evaluation is essential to determine if they are meeting the needs of family caregivers. The purpose of this mixed-methods, time series study was to investigate the effectiveness of a Family Caregiver Training Program (FCTP) offered by Senior Citizens Home Assistance Services (SCHAS) Inc, a nonprofit community-based agency in Knoxville, Tennessee. Both the actual training program itself and the impact of the training program on family caregivers of older adults were evaluated.</p>
<p>Informal caregivers, at great cost to themselves, save taxpayers in the United States countless dollars yearly. Research using data from the Health and Retirement Study estimating the economic impact of informal caregiving provided during the final year of life for older adults who were able to continue to live in their communities found that the economic value of the informal care provided by these caregivers ranged from US$22,514 to US$42,351 <italic>for each caregiver</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1084822312468136">6</xref></sup> The figures demonstrate the importance of family caregivers in keeping health care expenditures for older adults at home under control.</p>
<p>The majority of FCTP evaluation research studies demonstrate effectiveness for caregivers. The largest caregiver intervention study was the multisite research program funded by the National Institute on Aging and the National Institute of Nursing Research: Resources for Enhancing Alzheimer’s Caregiver Health (REACH). The study was performed in two phases. REACH I tested several interventions to decrease caregiver burden and depression at six US sites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1084822312468136">7</xref></sup> REACH II studies tested the effects of the intervention on quality of life and clinical depression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1084822312468136">8</xref></sup> and self-reported health, burden, and bother.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1084822312468136">9</xref></sup> REACH II included dementia caregivers from different ethnic and racial groups at five different sites. Improvement in health, burden, perception of bother, and depression were demonstrated as a result of the interventions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1084822312468136">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1084822312468136"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1084822312468136">9</xref></sup> Another interesting study arising from the REACH II data examined cost-effectiveness of the home-based intervention and concluded that the intervention resulted in less time spent in providing care by caregivers translating into lower cost of caregiving.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1084822312468136">10</xref></sup> Other caregiver training studies utilized well-validated scales to measure stress, burden, quality of life, perceived health, and depression. Findings were consistent with those found in the REACH studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1084822312468136">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1084822312468136"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1084822312468136"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1084822312468136"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1084822312468136"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1084822312468136">16</xref></sup></p>
<p>An intervention study based on the progressively lowered stress threshold model used an earlier version of the Caregiving Appraisal Scale<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1084822312468136">17</xref></sup> than the instrument utilized in this study. Findings indicated that the intervention positively affected impact, burden, and satisfaction, but had no effect on mastery when measured against a comparison group.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1084822312468136">18</xref></sup></p>
<p>The current study expands knowledge in the area of family caregiver training by involving dementia and nondementia caregivers of older adults and by using a mixed-methods, time series approach to evaluate the program and its effect on family caregivers. This knowledge can lead to FCTPs that are more responsive to caregivers’ needs and help lessen caregiver stress and burden.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1084822312468136" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>This pilot study was a mixed-methods, time series study with data triangulation of both quantitative and qualitative data. Data were collected at three time points: immediately before the series of classes began; immediately after a series of classes ended; and 1 month after the classes ended. This methodology allowed for both confirmation and completeness of data. Triangulation methods are used when the researchers value convergent and consensual validity and “in which it is deemed appropriate to use information from one source to corroborate another.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1084822312468136">19</xref>(p573)</sup></p>
<p>The goal of this research was the evaluation of outcomes as defined by Donabedian,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1084822312468136">20</xref></sup> which requires that identified outcomes be clearly linked to the process that caused the outcome and the need for dialogue between providers of care (SCHAS) and subjects of care (family caregivers) to clarify what desirable outcomes are. Feedback obtained from participants’ evaluation of the FCTP was important in clarifying what desirable outcomes were from the family caregivers’ perspectives.</p>
<sec id="section3-1084822312468136">
<title>Training Program Content</title>
<p>This family caregiver training program named HOPE for <italic>Helping Others to Provide Exceptional Care</italic>, consisted of four once weekly class sessions (revised from six sessions based on early feedback from caregivers) meeting for 2 hours. Based on the Minnesota Family Workshop,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1084822312468136">21</xref></sup> main aims of the FCTP were to increase caregivers’ knowledge; increase the family’s insight; help caregiver develop new skills; increase caregivers’ sense of self-efficacy; help family members understand the caregiving situation, and increase awareness of community resources. Specific content included self-care and stress reduction; older adult nutrition and hydration; planning for incapacity—advance directives and long-term care planning; understanding Alzheimer’s Disease-dealing with behavior problems; home modifications and durable medical equipment; senior exercise and activity for healthy aging; community resources; talking with your physician; and managing medications. Guest speakers were frequently utilized. Content was modified as feedback was obtained from participants to meet expressed need.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1084822312468136">
<title>Instruments</title>
<p>Both quantitative and qualitative instruments were used to collect data for this study. Each instrument added a dimension that assisted in the overall evaluation of the program and the caregiver impact. Study instruments were administered at three different times via self-report survey method. Time 1 and Time 2 instruments were administered at the training sites. Time 3 instruments were mailed through the US mail along with a postage-paid self-addressed envelope for return. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1084822312468136">Table 1</xref> is provided to illustrate the survey timeline and instruments used.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1084822312468136" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Survey Points &amp; Instruments.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1084822312468136" xlink:href="10.1177_1084822312468136-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Survey points</th>
<th align="center">Time</th>
<th align="center">Survey instruments</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Time 1</td>
<td>Prior to beginning the FCTP class</td>
<td>Caregiver demographic questionnaire, Care recipient demographic questionnaire, and <italic>Adapted Revised Caregiving Appraisal Scale</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Time 2</td>
<td>Immediately following the completion of the FCTP</td>
<td><italic>Adapted Revised Caregiving Appraisal Scale</italic> and <italic>Postprogram Evaluation Survey</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Time 3</td>
<td>Approximately 1 month after completion of the FCTP</td>
<td><italic>Adapted Revised Caregiving Appraisal Scale</italic>, and <italic>Follow-up Postprogram Survey</italic></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section5-1084822312468136">
<title>Demographic and characteristic forms</title>
<p>Two demographic and characteristic forms were utilized in this study. A caregiver questionnaire included age, gender, ethnicity, education level, occupation, employment status, health status, residence, relationship with the care recipient, availability of help, and the extent of care provided. A care recipient questionnaire included age, gender, ethnicity, education level, dementia diagnosis, level of impairment, and ability of the recipient to perform Activities of Daily Living (ADLs) and Instrumental Activities of Daily Living (IADLs), both of which are frequently utilized measures of elder functioning.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1084822312468136">
<title>Adapted Revised Caregiver Appraisal Scale (ARCAS)</title>
<p>An adaptation of the <italic>Revised Caregiving Appraisal Scale</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1084822312468136">22</xref></sup> was used to evaluate caregiver burden, satisfaction, mastery, demands, and impact. The scale was initially developed in 1989 consisting of four subscales: impact, burden, satisfaction, and mastery<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1084822312468136">23</xref></sup> and was later revised to include five subscales and 27 total items with Likert-type scale response sets.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1084822312468136">22</xref></sup> This revised scale was used in a study of daughter caregivers and confirmed the internal consistency reliability of the five subscales, including caregiving burden (nine items; α = .89), caregiving satisfaction (six items; α = .87), caregiving mastery (six items; α = .73), caregiving demand (three items; α = .79) and environmental impact (three items; α = .78).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1084822312468136">22</xref></sup></p>
<p>The <italic>Revised Caregiving Appraisal Scale</italic>, however, was originally designed to be administered verbally, which did not meet the needs of this study. Therefore, we retained the 5-point Likert-type scale format but adapted the instrument through grouping of items with similar response sets and changed specific language regarding the care recipient to more general language using the term “loved one” to obtain a paper-and-pencil survey instrument. Higher scores indicated more caregiver satisfaction, sense of mastery, burden, demand, or impact. The ARCAS used in this study demonstrated internal consistency reliability in Time 1 (α = .94), Time 2 (α = .92), Time 3 (α = .92), and the entire study period (α = .94). The internal consistency reliability for all five subscales was also established, including caregiving burden (α = .95), caregiving satisfaction (α = .87), caregiving mastery (α = .93), caregiving demand (α = .82), and environmental impact (α = .87).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1084822312468136">
<title>Postprogram evaluation survey</title>
<p>A short <italic>Postprogram Evaluation Survey</italic> included both quantitative measures and open-ended questions. Open questions included (a) What part of the training program was MOST helpful? (b) What part of the training program was LEAST helpful? (c) Should something be included in the training program that wasn’t there? What is it? What helped make it possible for you to attend this training program? (d) How do you think that completing this program will help you in caring for your family member? (e) Any additional comments? These items evaluated the program itself in terms of content, delivery, convenience, and usefulness.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1084822312468136">
<title>Follow-up postprogram survey</title>
<p>A <italic>Follow-up Postprogram Survey</italic> consisting of open-ended questions was used to determine what portions of the FCTP were most helpful and how the FCTP impacted caregiver life. Questions included (a) Has the training program helped you in caring for your family member? If so, in what way(s)? If not, why not? (b) What specific part(s) of the training knowledge or skills have you used in your caring for your loved one thus far? (c) Have you come across situations or tasks that you were not prepared for in the training program? If so, what were they? (d) Please recall your caregiving experience in the last month, and tell us about the main difference before you attended the training and after the training in caring for your loved one. (e) Any additional comments?</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1084822312468136">
<title>Data Collection</title>
<p>After obtaining university IRB approval, the study commenced. Participants were family caregivers who took the FCTP offered by SCHAS from August 2009 through August 2010. Five classes were held. Potential participants received information regarding the study from the PI and an invitation to participate the first day of the training Individuals who consented to participate signed a consent form and completed the instruments for Time 1 data collection. Participation was voluntary and individuals deciding not to participate in the study still received the training. Confidentiality of all participants was preserved throughout the study and after. No identifiers were used on any survey or questionnaires, which were only identified by a numeric code. The PI met again with participants completing the classes immediately on the last day after the class and asked participants to complete Time 2 instruments. At this time participants were asked to provide mailing information for Time 3 instruments that were mailed 1 month after class completion.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1084822312468136">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>Data collection, coding, entry, and analysis were conducted over the duration of the study. Findings from the <italic>Postprogram Evaluation Survey</italic> were shared after completion of each training class with the agency for the purposes of program revision and refinement for the next class. Descriptive statistics such as frequencies and percentages were utilized to report the aggregate demographic data and to report the quantitative portion of the <italic>Postprogram Evaluation Survey</italic>. To evaluate caregiver’s change in patterns over time on the ACRAS, the Friedman test was used to examine the distribution of changes between time points. The researchers hypothesized that skills learned and information received would result in less caregiving burden, more satisfaction, more mastery, and lower perception of demands, and impact.</p>
<p>Content analysis was used to analyze the qualitative portion of the <italic>Postprogram Evaluation Survey</italic> at Time 2 and the <italic>Follow-up Postprogram Survey</italic> at Time 3. Concrete categories were used to gather and organize the qualitative program evaluation data by grouping related concepts to facilitate the coding process. Based on Krippendorff’s method for content analysis,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1084822312468136">24</xref></sup> data from the open ended questions were coded, categorized, collapsed, and eventually organized into five groups, which are discussed in the findings section. Findings from qualitative data analysis were compared to the quantitative findings to add another dimension to the quantitative data findings.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1084822312468136" sec-type="results">
<title>Results and Discussion</title>
<sec id="section12-1084822312468136">
<title>Sample</title>
<p>Fifty-eight participants began FCTP classes. The majority were female (81%), married (76%), and White (91%). Age range of family caregiver participants was 42 to 90 years of age. Thirteen caregivers were providing care to more than one care recipient, and one caregiver was providing care for three family members. Thirty caregivers completed the Time 2 evaluations (Time 2 n = 30), and nineteen caregivers completed the Time 3 instruments (Time 3 n = 19). See <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1084822312468136">Table 2</xref> for Caregiver demographics and characteristics.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1084822312468136" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Caregivers’ Demographic/Characteristic Data.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1084822312468136" xlink:href="10.1177_1084822312468136-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Frequency</th>
<th align="center">Percent</th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Gender</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>19.0</td>
<td rowspan="2">58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>81.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Marital status</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Married</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>75.9</td>
<td rowspan="4">58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Widowed</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>6.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Divorced or separated</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>6.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Single (never married)</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>10.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Race</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> White or Caucasian</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>91.4</td>
<td rowspan="4">58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Asian or Pacific Islander</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Education</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> High school graduate</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>19.0</td>
<td rowspan="6">57</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Some college</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>32.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Bachelor’s degree</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>31.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Master’s degree</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>10.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PhD degree</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Employment status</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Full-time employed</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>12.1</td>
<td rowspan="4">58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Part-time</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>13.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Retired</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>58.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Unemployed</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>15.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Relationship with care recipient</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Spouse</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>36.2</td>
<td rowspan="3">58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Child</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>46.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>17.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Frequency of Care/week</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Alternatives (&lt;1 hour/week)</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>14.3</td>
<td rowspan="4">56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> About once a week</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Two to three times/week</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>23.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> More than six times/week</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>58.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Other helpers</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>39.7</td>
<td rowspan="2">58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>60.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age (years)</td>
<td colspan="3">Mean = 64.2, SD = 11.8, Range 42-90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Duration of care (years)</td>
<td colspan="3">Mean = 4.0, SD = 4.5, Range 0-16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Care hours/wk</td>
<td colspan="3">Mean = 55.1, SD = 67.8, Range 0-168</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The family caregiver participants provided care to 70 care recipients. These care recipients (n = 70) were mostly female (63%), married (50%), and White (96%). Ages of care recipients ranged from 46 to 105 years of age. There was one care recipient who was not an older adult, but rather a daughter with spina bifida. The caregiving father was caring for both the daughter and his aged wife. Slightly more than one half of care recipients had a diagnosis of dementia (51.7%). See <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1084822312468136">Table 3</xref> for care recipient demographics and characteristics.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1084822312468136" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Care Recipient Demographic/Characteristic Data.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1084822312468136" xlink:href="10.1177_1084822312468136-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">First care recipient<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Second care recipient<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1084822312468136">a</xref><hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">n</th>
<th align="center">%</th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
<th align="center">n</th>
<th align="center">%</th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Gender</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>45.6</td>
<td rowspan="2">57</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td rowspan="2">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>54.4</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Marital status</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Married</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>55.2</td>
<td rowspan="4">58</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>38.5</td>
<td rowspan="4">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Widowed</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>39.7</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>46.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Divorced or separated</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>7.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Single (never married)</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3.4</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>7.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Race</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> White or Caucasian</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>93.1</td>
<td rowspan="4">58</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>100</td>
<td rowspan="4">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3.4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Asian or Pacific Islander</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Dementia Diagnosis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>48.3</td>
<td rowspan="2">58</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>61.5</td>
<td rowspan="2">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>51.7</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>38.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Level of impairment</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> None</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>21.1</td>
<td rowspan="4">57</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>7.7</td>
<td rowspan="4">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mild</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>29.8</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>53.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Moderate</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>36.8</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>30.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Severe</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>12.3</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>7.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age (years)</td>
<td colspan="3">Mean 80.1, SD = 7.6</td>
<td colspan="3">Mean 83.2, SD = 13.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td colspan="3">Range 61-95</td>
<td colspan="3">Range 46-105</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1084822312468136">
<label>a</label>
<p>One caregiver was providing care for three family members.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1084822312468136">
<title>Program Evaluation</title>
<p>The <italic>Postprogram Evaluation Survey</italic> results showed that more than 95% of the participants either agreed or strongly agreed with all the statements reflecting positive evaluation of the FCTP. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1084822312468136">Table 4</xref> for these findings.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1084822312468136" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Postprogram Evaluation Survey (Time 2 n = 30).</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1084822312468136" xlink:href="10.1177_1084822312468136-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Agree</th>
<th align="center">Strongly agree</th>
<th align="center">Agree and strongly agree total<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1084822312468136">a</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1. I feel that I have more knowledge as a caregiver</td>
<td>41.4%</td>
<td>55.2%</td>
<td>96.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2. I feel more confident as a caregiver</td>
<td>55.2%</td>
<td>41.4%</td>
<td>96.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3. I learned skills that will help me as a caregiver</td>
<td>48.3%</td>
<td>48.3%</td>
<td>96.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4. The material was important to me as a caregiver</td>
<td>26.7%</td>
<td>70%</td>
<td>96.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5. The material was easy to understand</td>
<td>36.7%</td>
<td>60%</td>
<td>96.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6. The material was clear</td>
<td>36.7%</td>
<td>60%</td>
<td>96.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7. There was enough time spent on important materials</td>
<td>55.2%</td>
<td>31%</td>
<td>96.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8. The instructor encouraged discussion</td>
<td>30%</td>
<td>66.7%</td>
<td>96.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9. Time in class was well spent</td>
<td>36.7%</td>
<td>60%</td>
<td>96.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10. My questions and opinion were valued</td>
<td>36.7%</td>
<td>60%</td>
<td>96.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11. I expect to use the information that I received</td>
<td>40%</td>
<td>56.7%</td>
<td>96.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12. The timing of the program was convenient for me</td>
<td>46.7%</td>
<td>53.3%</td>
<td>100%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13. I would recommend this program to other caregivers</td>
<td>20%</td>
<td>80%</td>
<td>100%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1084822312468136">
<label>a</label>
<p>One participant selected “disagree” on all items and did not answer Items 12 and 13.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Comments from participants in response to the open-ended questions from the <italic>Postprogram Evaluation Survey</italic> included suggestions regarding timing of classes: “The lawyer needed more time”; content of classes: “Council on Aging representative gave too much information for me to absorb it all” and “Include when they should be put in the nursing home, more about cost and nursing homes in our area”; and presentation of content: “Could all speakers have outlines to give us so we could write on them and they could stop on topic and on time.” Feedback was presented to the agency after every class and the next class was modified to make classes more responsive to caregivers’ needs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1084822312468136">
<title>Program/Caregiver Evaluation</title>
<p>Qualitative data from the <italic>Follow-up Postprogram Survey</italic> was analyzed using Krippendorffs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1084822312468136">24</xref></sup> content analysis methods and organized into five categories: applicability/usefulness, satisfaction, barriers/facilitators, caregiver effect, and planning ahead. This qualitative data not only included comments regarding the program itself but also the effects of the program on the family caregivers. Often it was impossible to separate the two since they were inextricably linked.</p>
<sec id="section15-1084822312468136">
<title>Applicability/usefulness</title>
<p>Participants made numerous comments regarding the applicability and usefulness of the training program. These comments were clustered around three main areas: information, skills, and socialization.</p>
<p>Comments regarding information included information about resources, nutrition, medications, and medical conditions. Some comments included “Finding out about services available at county and state levels that I was unaware of” and “Information presented by the nurse regarding nutrition, recovery from broken hip, and drug interactions.”</p>
<p>Comments about skills encompassed areas of physical and behavioral management techniques such as “I am more cognizant of the importance of keeping mom flexed and exercised” and “Have used some of the techniques to divert conversations or responding to the emotion.”</p>
<p>The socialization aspect of the classes was greatly appreciated by the participants and indicated that the class sessions provided social support. This is supported by statements like “Makes one feel that they are not alone as well as making one feel that where a problem might be difficult, it can be taken care of” and “Also seeing other folks and realizing my problems are universal and there is help out there.”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1084822312468136">
<title>Satisfaction</title>
<p>Participants were highly satisfied with the training program. Comments demonstrated the value they received and included “I think this training is invaluable for everyone caring for ailing loved ones”; “You gave me a boost to keep going” and “I felt that the program was a very much needed program—that so many people are in my shoes and these shoes are very uncomfortable.”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1084822312468136">
<title>Barriers/facilitators</title>
<p>Participants were asked what caused problems in their attendance at the classes and what assisted. Responses were coded as barriers or facilitators. Barriers included lack of knowledge regarding the training program, “Most people are not aware of this program. I saw the article in the newspaper or I might never know.” Timing of classes acted as both a facilitator and a barrier depending on which class the participant took. One participant stated, “Timing . . . If I were working, I would not have been able to attend”, while others said, “Our evenings are mostly free which made our evening class perfect” and “The time during the day was convenient.” Another facilitator was location: “The location was close to my home”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1084822312468136">
<title>Caregiver effect</title>
<p>The main caregiver effect expressed by participants was confidence. The family caregivers described their confidence in their abilities to carry out the caregiver role because of the training program. Statements included “I have a little more confidence in certain areas after taking the training in regard to caring for mom” and “We have so much more confidence in our ability to find the help we need.”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1084822312468136">
<title>Planning ahead</title>
<p>An unexpected finding was that some of the participants were not actively caring for a family member at the time of the classes. Some participants anticipated a future need to do so and they took the class to prepare for the time when they would need to assume the caregiver role. This was exemplified in the statement, “I found the information very helpful in case I find myself caring for a relative and have saved the information for my sons if they have to care for me.” Other participants used information from the classes to plan ahead for themselves, not only for their family members. One couple stated, “We are changing and updating wills, living wills, and POAs to meet Tennessee requirements.”</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-1084822312468136">
<title>Caregiver Outcomes</title>
<p>The ARCAS was completed by participants at three survey points. Friedman’s test examined the effects of the FCTP on the caregivers. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1084822312468136">Table 5</xref> summarizes the findings. Based on the findings from the Friedman’s test, there was a significant difference among the three survey points with regard to the overall effects of the FCTP on caregivers (χ<sup>2</sup> = 10.21, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). Friedman’s test was further used to examine the effects of the FCTP on the caregivers within each subscale of the ARCAS. Caregiving satisfaction was the only subscale that had significant changes over three survey points (χ<sup>2</sup> = 8.09, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05), supporting our qualitative findings (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1084822312468136">Table 5</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-1084822312468136" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Effects of the FCTP on the Caregivers Measured by ARCAS.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1084822312468136" xlink:href="10.1177_1084822312468136-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Adapted Revised Caregiving Appraisal Scale</th>
<th align="center">Time 1 (n = 58) Mean</th>
<th align="center">Time 2 (n = 30) Mean</th>
<th align="center">Time 3 (n = 19) Mean</th>
<th align="center">χ<sup>2</sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Overall Scale</td>
<td>2.97</td>
<td>2.96</td>
<td>3.01</td>
<td>10.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1084822312468136">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Burden Subscale</td>
<td>2.56</td>
<td>2.68</td>
<td>2.59</td>
<td>2.39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Satisfaction Subscale</td>
<td>3.74</td>
<td>3.71</td>
<td>3.82</td>
<td>8.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1084822312468136">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mastery Subscale</td>
<td>3.55</td>
<td>3.62</td>
<td>3.74</td>
<td>0.28</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Demands Subscale</td>
<td>2.45</td>
<td>2.27</td>
<td>2.27</td>
<td>0.12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Impact Subscale</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.06</td>
<td>1.90</td>
<td>2.51</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1084822312468136">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>P</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>To determine when the changes occurred with regard to the effects of the FCTP on the caregivers, Friedman’s test was used to compare two survey points’ overall scores and the five subscale scores, including Time 1 versus Time 2, Time 1 versus Time 3, and Time 2 versus Time 3. There was no difference between any two survey points for the overall score, caregiving burden, caregiving mastery, caregiving demand, and environmental impact scores. Caregiver participants did report a significant increase in caregiving satisfaction from Time 1 to Time 3 (χ<sup>2</sup> = 6.25, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) and from Time 2 to Time 3 (χ<sup>2</sup> = 6.25, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05). <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-1084822312468136">Table 6</xref> summarizes the results of examining the difference between two survey points for individual subscales and the overall scale.</p>
<table-wrap id="table6-1084822312468136" position="float">
<label>Table 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Effects of the FCTP on the Caregivers across Three Survey Points.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-1084822312468136" xlink:href="10.1177_1084822312468136-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"><italic>Revised Caregiving Appraisal Scale</italic></th>
<th align="center">Time 1 (n = 58) Mean</th>
<th align="center">Time 2 (n = 30) Mean</th>
<th align="center">Time 3 (n = 19) Mean</th>
<th align="center">χ<sup>2</sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Overall Scale</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 1 vs. Time 2</td>
<td>2.99</td>
<td>2.96</td>
<td/>
<td>1.58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 1 vs. Time 3</td>
<td>2.88</td>
<td/>
<td>3.01</td>
<td>3.36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 2 vs. Time 3</td>
<td/>
<td>3.01</td>
<td>3.00</td>
<td>0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Burden Subscale</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 1 vs. Time 2</td>
<td>2.69</td>
<td>2.68</td>
<td/>
<td>0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 1 vs. Time 3</td>
<td>2.55</td>
<td/>
<td>2.59</td>
<td>0.53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 2 vs. Time 3</td>
<td/>
<td>2.62</td>
<td>2.69</td>
<td>0.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Satisfaction Subscale</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 1 vs. Time 2</td>
<td>3.64</td>
<td>3.71</td>
<td/>
<td>0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 1 vs. Time 3</td>
<td>3.56</td>
<td/>
<td>3.82</td>
<td>6.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1084822312468136">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 2 vs. Time 3</td>
<td/>
<td>3.89</td>
<td>3.70</td>
<td>6.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1084822312468136">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Mastery Subscale</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 1 vs. Time 2</td>
<td>3.57</td>
<td>3.62</td>
<td/>
<td>0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 1 vs. Time 3</td>
<td>3.62</td>
<td/>
<td>3.74</td>
<td>1.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 2 vs. Time 3</td>
<td/>
<td>3.67</td>
<td>3.70</td>
<td>0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Demands Subscale</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 1 vs. Time 2</td>
<td>2.42</td>
<td>2.27</td>
<td/>
<td>0.67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 1 vs. Time 3</td>
<td>2.30</td>
<td/>
<td>2.27</td>
<td>0.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 2 vs. Time 3</td>
<td/>
<td>2.18</td>
<td>2.34</td>
<td>0.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Impact Subscale</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 1 vs. Time 2</td>
<td>1.98</td>
<td>2.06</td>
<td/>
<td>1.67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 1 vs. Time 3</td>
<td>1.65</td>
<td/>
<td>1.89</td>
<td>0.82</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Time 2 vs. Time 3</td>
<td/>
<td>1.84</td>
<td>1.90</td>
<td>0.40</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1084822312468136">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>P</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-1084822312468136" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Findings from this study support previous findings such as those in the REACH I and II studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1084822312468136">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1084822312468136"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1084822312468136">9</xref></sup> that family caregiver intervention programs, such as this FCTP can have positive effects on caregivers. Furthermore, our findings support previous research findings that caregivers can experience feelings of accomplishment competence and that mastering complexity of caring, which can result from caregiver training, can result in a greater sense of satisfaction with the caregiving role.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1084822312468136">25</xref></sup> Caregiver responses to evaluation measures of the actual classes provided for revision and development of a FCTP that was responsive to needs of the caregivers. It is essential that any FCTP be flexible and responsive to caregiver needs.</p>
<p>A concern of this study was the number of family caregivers who did not complete the series of classes. It is unknown why the loss occurred. Both caregiver and care recipient demographics will be correlated with caregivers who completed versus those who did not in an attempt to explain the loss of participants. Respite care was provided by the agency during the time of the classes to enable the caregivers to attend, but only two caregivers took advantage of this service. This service may need to be emphasized more and may assist in retaining caregivers for the entire sequence of classes.</p>
<p>Some limitations of this study include lack of ethnic diversity in the sample and small sample size. It is also not possible to determine the length of time of the positive caregiver effects. More research is needed with diverse caregivers and larger sample sizes. Longitudinal studies that would include use of the ARCAS at 6 and 12 months and add measures of service utilization and caregiver health would also provide much needed information. Also, longitudinal care recipient measures such as number of hospitalizations and long-term care placement would be useful.</p>
<p>The <italic>Revised Caregiving Appraisal Scale</italic> offers an advantage of being one instrument that measures the five frequently studied areas of caregiver impact, burden, satisfaction, mastery, and caregiving demand in a 27-item format. This greatly reduces time needed to complete and avoids imposing further burden on already overwhelmed caregiver participants. Yet, despite having good psychometric properties, this instrument has only been utilized in one other reported intervention study.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1084822312468136">18</xref></sup> Perhaps this is due to the fact that the instrument was designed to be administered verbally, thereby increasing time needed for administration. Our adaptation of the scale made this instrument easier to administer, especially in the 1-month follow up phase (Time 3) because it could be mailed to participants.</p>
<p>Thirteen of our participants were caring for more than one family member and one was responsible for three older adults. It would appear that there are unique needs and concerns of this subset of the caregiver population that need to be researched.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-1084822312468136" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Qualitative findings in the form of statements by participants of increased satisfaction, confidence in abilities (mastery), confidence and feelings of support, add richness and explanation to the quantitative data. Family caregivers in this study benefited from the FCTP in all areas evaluated. These positive results persisted to the 1-month postcompletion point demonstrating effectiveness of the FCTP.</p>
<p>As our population ages, greater numbers of family caregivers will be needed to provide care to maintain older adults in their homes. These family members will need support and education to manage their caregiving roles. Ongoing evaluation of these educational programs is essential to determine if they are meeting the needs of the family caregivers. Additionally, research is essential on interventions such as the FCTP to improve caregiver health and well-being.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article from the University of Tennessee, Health Science Center.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1084822312468136">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>National Alliance for Caregiving in collaboration with AARP</collab>. <source>Caregiving in the U.S. 2009</source>. <publisher-loc>Bethesda, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.caregiving.org/data/Caregiving_in_the_US_2009_full_report.pdf">http://www.caregiving.org/data/Caregiving_in_the_US_2009_full_report.pdf</ext-link>. <access-date>Accessed September 27, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1084822312468136">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>Administration on Aging</collab>. <source>Profile of Older Americans: 2011:Future Growth</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aoa.gov/aoaroot/aging_statistics/Profile/2011/4.aspx">http://www.aoa.gov/aoaroot/aging_statistics/Profile/2011/4.aspx</ext-link> <access-date>Accessed September 26, 2012</access-date></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1084822312468136">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>National Family Caregivers Association</collab>. <article-title>Random Sample Survey of Family Caregivers</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Kensington, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>, Summer. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nfcacares.org/who_are_family_caregivers/2000_survey.cfm">http://www.nfcacares.org/who_are_family_caregivers/2000_survey.cfm</ext-link> <access-date>Accessed September 27, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1084822312468136">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Information needs of family caregivers of persons with cognitive versus physical deficits</article-title>. <source>Gerontol Geriatr Educ</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>396</fpage>-<lpage>413</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1084822312468136">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>US Department of Health and Human Services</collab>. <article-title>Healthy People 2020</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.healthypeople.gov/2020/topicsobjectives2020/overview.aspx?topicid=31">http://www.healthypeople.gov/2020/topicsobjectives2020/overview.aspx?topicid=31</ext-link>
<access-date>Accessed September 20, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1084822312468136">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Degenholtz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Losasso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Emanuel</surname></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Estimating the quantity and economic value of family caregiving for community-dwelling older persons in the last year of life</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>1654</fpage>-<lpage>1659</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1084822312468136">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gitlin</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Belle</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burgio</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of multicomponent interventions on caregiver burden and depression: the REACH multisite initiative at 6-month follow up</article-title>. <source>Psychol Aging</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>361</fpage>-<lpage>374</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1084822312468136">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Belle</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burgio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Enhancing the quality of life of dementia caregivers from different ethnic or racial groups</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>145</volume>:<fpage>727</fpage>-<lpage>738</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1084822312468136">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burgio</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeCoster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Enhancing caregiver health: findings from the Resources for Enhancing Alzheimer’s Caregiver Health II intervention</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1084822312468136">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lummus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The cost effectiveness of a behavior intervention with caregivers of patients with Alzheimer’s Disease</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>413</fpage>-<lpage>420</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1084822312468136">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hepburn</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tornatore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Center</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ostwald</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dementia family caregiver training: affecting beliefs about caregiving and caregiver outcomes</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>450</fpage>-<lpage>457</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1084822312468136">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gavrilova</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mikhaylova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sokolova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Helping carers to care—The 10/66 dementia research groups randomized control trial of a caregiver intervention in Russia</article-title>. <source>Int J Geriatr Psychiatry</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>347</fpage>-<lpage>354</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1084822312468136">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hepburn</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tornatore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The Savvy Caregiver Program: developing and testing a transportable dementia caregiver training program</article-title>. <source>Gerontologist</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>908</fpage>-<lpage>915</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1084822312468136">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martin-Carrasco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Valero</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of a psychoeducational program in the reduction of caregiver burden in Alzheimer’s disease patients’ caregivers</article-title>. <source>Int J Geriatr Psychiatry</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>489</fpage>-<lpage>499</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1084822312468136">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gallagher-Thompson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Japanese American caregivers of individuals with dementia: an examination of Japanese cultural values and dementia caregiving</article-title>. <source>Clin Gerontol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>102</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1084822312468136">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lorig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson-Gallagher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Traylor</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Building better caregivers: a pilot online support workshop for family caregivers of cognitively impaired adults</article-title>. <conf-name>J Appl Gerontol</conf-name>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>423</fpage>-<lpage>437</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1084822312468136">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>Polisher Research Institute</collab>. <source>Caregiver Appraisal Scale</source>. <publisher-loc>North Wales, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.abramsoncenter.org/pri/documents/caregiver.pdf">http://www.abramsoncenter.org/pri/documents/caregiver.pdf</ext-link>
<access-date>Accessed March 10, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1084822312468136">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stolley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buckwalter</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Caregiving and interventions based on the progressively lowered stress threshold model</article-title>. <source>Am J Alzheimers Dis Other Dementias</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage>-<lpage>120</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1084822312468136">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sandelowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Triangles and crystals: on the geometry of qualitative research</article-title>. <source>Res Nurs Health</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>569</fpage>-<lpage>574</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1084822312468136">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donabedian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Five Essential Questions Frame the Management of Quality in Health Care</article-title>. <source>Health Manage Q</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1084822312468136">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ostwald</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hepburn</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Training family caregivers of patients with dementia</article-title>. <source>J Gerontol Nurs</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1084822312468136">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perkinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Two transitions in daughters’ caregiving careers</article-title>. <source>Gerontologist</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>-<lpage>448</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1084822312468136">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kleban</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rovine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glickman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Measuring caregiver appraisal</article-title>. <source>J Gerontol B Ppsychol Sci</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1084822312468136">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krippendorff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Content Analysis: An Introduction to Its Methodology</source>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1084822312468136">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Markle-Reid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hawranik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leipert</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The positive aspects of the caregiving journey with dementia: using strengths-based perspectives to reveal opportunities</article-title>. <source>J Appl Gerontol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>640</fpage>-<lpage>659</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>