<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SOC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsoc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Sociology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0038-0385</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1469-8684</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0038038512464441</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0038038512464441</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Dave Elder-Vass, <italic>The Causal Power of Social Structures: Emergence, Structure and Agency</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Huijg</surname><given-names>Dieuwertje Dyi</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0038038512464441">University of Manchester, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>207</fpage>
<lpage>208</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elder-Vass</surname><given-names>Dave</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>The Causal Power of Social Structures: Emergence, Structure and Agency</source> <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>, <price>£58</price> hbk (ISBN: <isbn>9780521194457</isbn>), <page-count count="234"/> pp.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">BSA Publications Ltd.</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In <italic>The Causal Power of Social Structures: Emergence, Structure and Agency</italic>, Dave Elder-Vass presents an emergentist theory of social structure as a reconciliatory solution from a critical realist perspective to problems within the agency-structure debate. The central argument in the book is that social structures should best be ‘understood as the causal powers of social groups’ (p. 115). Emergence is the ‘synchronic relation amongst the parts of an entity that gives the entity as a whole the ability to have a particular (diachronic) causal impact’ (p. 23); it refers to an entity that has [emergent] properties that affect the world, but whose causal impact on the world is ‘not just the sum of the impacts its parts would have if they were not organised into this kind of whole’ (p. 5). Accordingly, a social structure is an entity, a ‘thing’ or ‘whole’ that is more than the sum of its parts or of the causal powers, also emergent properties, of its individual members. The question, then, is how social structures – Elder-Vass offers as exemplars norm circles and normative institutions, associations and organisations, and social events – can be accurately understood. He suggests a <italic>method of social ontology</italic> that should shed light on how entities and causal properties actually operate. To do so, one must identify the entity, strip it down to its parts, their relations, its emergent properties or causal powers, the mechanisms that produce the entity’s emergent properties, the morphogenetic and, subsequently, morphostatic causes and, last, the modes through which entities ‘<italic>interact to cause the events</italic> we seek to explain in the discipline’ (p. 69, italics in original). The application of this method occurs via various tests, i.e. the local complementarity tests, downward recursion and the retroduction test, emergence level test and the metatheory test – which must fall, unfortunately, beyond the scope of this review. According to Elder-Vass, we have to think of this model hierarchically, which constitutes both upward and downward causal powers; the entity and its parts are understood as ‘levels’ and its causal powers can belong to both levels in the same action (p. 74) that, in turn, impact upwards on the social world, or impact downward on the individual. Not surprisingly, considering the critical realist foundation, it is worth noting that the individual has been assigned quite some agency; though individuals’ dispositions and beliefs are influenced by structure, etc., via internalisation (p. 125) and downward causation, the individual agentically mediates these via intra-action and interaction (see, for example, pp. 170–8).</p>
<p><italic>The Causal Power of Social Structures</italic> responds to a social scientific lack of ‘ontological rigour’ (p. 64). The social sciences, Elder-Vass opines, ‘consistently lack plausible, well-defined and locally consistent scientific ontologies’ and, unlike the natural sciences, are not examples of a ‘well-developed science’ (pp. 69–70). He attempts to support the theoretical underpinnings of his book with examples from the natural sciences, as H<sub>2</sub>0 molecules, physical particles and chimpanzees or, for example, the ‘case of photosynthesis by a plant’ that is converted into ‘carbon dioxide from the atmosphere into oxygen’ (p. 51). My understanding of photosynthesis or H<sub>2</sub>0 molecules is not very sophisticated, so I presume that Elder-Vass has got these examples right. However, since the book aims at responding to the agency-structure debate with a workable solution that can be picked up by those researchers that theoretically engage with the social world, or with the theoretical foundations for a social ontology if you will, an effort to illustrate his general framework with examples from the social world that the theory says to address would have been appreciated. This is so, not only to facilitate reading or comply with questions of rigour and accountability that the framework of the natural sciences brings in, but because this framework permeates throughout the book and contributes to an understanding of the social world in terms of materiality (individuals and groups of individuals that form the basis for organisations, social structures, etc.) and bi-directional hierarchy (upward and downward causation). This, in turn, clarifies why it was not possible to engage with themes such as language, discourse, culture and knowledge (pp. 10, 203); these differentiate the natural from the social world and would have required a response to, first, the complex <italic>fuzziness</italic> that is actually out there and, second, to the extra-individual immaterial world that cannot be captured by studying structures as social groups.</p>
<p>Theory-oriented academics engaging with the agency-structure debate, specifically those who are interested in the critical realists Archer, Mouzelis and Baskar and/or the work of Giddens and Bourdieu, as well as researchers of ontology and possibly causation theory, could find <italic>The Causal Power of Social Structures</italic> a useful read. Though at this stage I would not recommend it as such, the book does propose a method for research; I would be curious to see how this might work empirically.</p>
</body>
</article>