<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DIJ</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdij</journal-id>
         <journal-title>Drug Information Journal</journal-title>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">0092-8615</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0092861512456839</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0092861512456839</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Regulatory Commentaries</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Join FDA/PhUSE Working Groups to Help Harness the Power of Computational Science</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Rosario</surname>
                  <given-names>Lilliam A.</given-names>
               </name>
               <degrees>PhD</degrees>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0092861512456839">1</xref>
               <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0092861512456839"/>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kropp</surname>
                  <given-names>Timothy J.</given-names>
               </name>
               <degrees>PhD</degrees>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0092861512456839">1</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wilson</surname>
                  <given-names>Stephen E.</given-names>
               </name>
               <degrees>PhD</degrees>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0092861512456839">1</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cooper</surname>
                  <given-names>Charles K.</given-names>
               </name>
               <degrees>MD</degrees>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0092861512456839">1</xref>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff1-0092861512456839">
               <label>1</label>Office of Translational Sciences, Center for Drug Evaluation and Research, US Food and Drug Administration, Silver Spring, MD, USA</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <author-notes>
            <corresp id="corresp1-0092861512456839">Lilliam A. Rosario, PhD, United States Food and Drug Administration, 10903 New Hampshire Avenue, WO 21 RM4512, Silver Spring, MD 20993, USA Email: <email xlink:type="simple">Lilliam.Rosario@fda.hhs.gov</email>
            </corresp>
         </author-notes>
         <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
            <month>9</month>
            <year>2012</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>46</volume>
         <issue>5</issue>
         <fpage>523</fpage>
         <lpage>524</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder content-type="society">Drug Information Association</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Consumers are often pleased by the accuracy with which online shopping websites are able to recommend new products they may be interested in.  For example, how did the favorite shopping website of your wine-enthusiast neighbor, who recently purchased a highly durable dog crate for her separation anxiety–stricken canine, know that she would also be interested in 2 items not typically bought together: a do-it-yourself wine cork bulletin board kit and canine calming herbal supplements?</p>
      <p>Amazon.com, Pandora Radio, and Netflix, to name a few, have developed innovative means to weed through and translate the heaps of data generated from a consumer’s search and “purchase” history into precise product recommendations.  Advances in information technology that have been extremely successful for consumer information delivery have also provided effective solutions to data-heavy projects in translational science, genomics, and business analytics.  These advances have engendered fields and businesses that regulatory stakeholders can leverage against the mountains of data that accompany each medical product application in order to speed review time, reduce and refine clinical trial requirements, pinpoint postmarket safety signals, and facilitate regulatory science efforts, to name a few potential benefits.  </p>
      <p>Increasingly complex informatics and data challenges must first be addressed in order to harness the potential of medical product development data.  Aggregation and curation of data collected from various sources, in various forms, are heavy tasks in existing scientific environments.  Data standards and associated tools can make the job of transforming data into knowledge a fast, efficient, and highly repeatable process.  The first step, increasing the accessibility of data with standards, is only an enabling step. The full benefit of standardized data can only be actualized when combined with systems, tools, and procedures that allow the user to easily find answers to the scientific and regulatory questions that they face.</p>
      <p>The FDA and Pharmaceutical Users Software Exchange (PhUSE) have teamed up to tackle these challenges using collaboration, crowd sourcing, and innovation, a strategy similar to one used in 2011 by scientists who were unable to solve the crystal structure of a key retroviral protein.  These innovative scientists cast a wide net in order to reach a solution by challenging nonscientist gamers to model the protein’s structure using their intuition and a protein folding game.  In 3 weeks, gamers were able to accomplish what biochemists had been unable to achieve for more than a decade and provided the field with new insights for the design of antiretroviral drugs.<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0092861512456839">1</xref>
         </sup>  Similar examples are now becoming more prevalent as we try to harness technical and human resources to address complex scientific and health-related issues.  </p>
      <p>Earlier this year, the FDA and PhUSE cast their own wide net to solve common informatics needs and challenges by calling on all interested parties from across the pharmaceutical industry, government, and technology sectors to bring their innovative ideas to the Computational Science Symposium held on March 19 and 20, 2012.<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0092861512456839">2</xref>
         </sup>  The symposium, cohosted by PhUSE and the FDA’s Center for Biologics Evaluation and Research (CBER) and Center for Drug Evaluation and Research (CDER), was designed to create a space where experts could work collaboratively to identify issues, discuss possible solutions, and ultimately devise and execute solutions by participating in any of the 6 working groups.</p>
      <p>Working groups were created based on the priorities of CBER and CDER and on interests of other stakeholders identified at previous meetings.  All working groups have multiple representatives from both the FDA and industry and will hold virtual meetings throughout the year to address the objectives and next steps generated during the symposium.  All working groups are welcoming and encouraging new participants to join.  The requirements for joining any working group are simple: just participate and contribute to the discussion and ongoing projects.  Brief descriptions of all working groups are below; please visit their websites and Wikis to learn more and join in the discussion.<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0092861512456839">3</xref>
         </sup>
      </p>
      <p>The goal of working group 1, Data Validation and Quality Assessment, is to facilitate joint development of a robust process to rapidly validate and assess data quality as data. moves through the product life cycle across industry and regulatory review.  The group has embarked on 3 initial projects to support this goal: Assess and Improve Existing Validation Rules, Develop Guidelines for Validation Rule Developers, and Develop and Support Change Management Process.</p>
      <p>Working group 2, Standardizing Data within the Inspection Site Selection Process, is focused on initiating an effort to develop data standards to support continued development and implementation of a risk model that aids in selecting the clinical sites that should be inspected during a clinical trial.  The group members are discussing ways to incorporate the variables necessary to support the risk model into existing standards and are working to identify standardization methods for both the industry and the FDA to use in order to generate future data sets in a specified format.</p>
      <p>The members of working group 3, Challenges of Integrating and Converting Data across Studies, are addressing the semantic and operational challenges faced by industry and regulatory stakeholders when attempting to integrate data for the purposes of supporting analysis across studies.  The goal of this group will be to generate best practice recommendations for when and how to integrate data as well as how to make data more capable of supporting integration.  The group has initiated 4 projects to address these issues: provide a succinct, inclusive, and understandable definition of “data integration,” provide guidance on when data integration is appropriate, examine the requirements for the ability to trace integrated data back to its source, and provide guidance on the mechanics of data integration.</p>
      <p>The goal of working group 4, Standards Implementation Issues with the CDISC Data Models, is to reach a more unified understanding of the impact of standards by learning how industry and FDA reviewers are interpreting the current data standards models and by identifying the specific challenges to standards implementation.  Projects including the development of a standardized data guide to support product submission and an assessment of which elements of data sets are not required for standardized submissions are underway with participation by CDER, CBER, and the. industry to develop best practices recommendations.</p>
      <p>The goal of working group 5, Development of Standard Scripts for Analysis and Programming, is to begin the process of creating a common library of scripts to support analytic and programming needs for the drug development and regulatory communities.  The industry and FDA representatives participating in this group will outline recommended analyses for common tables, figures, and listings for phase 2 to 4 clinical trial study reports and integrated summary documents with the intention of creating code for recommended analyses. This group also will develop technical requirements for an information-sharing platform that will house the scripts and serve as a tool for collaborative script development.</p>
      <p>Working group 6, Non-clinical Road-map and Impacts on Implementation, is focused on supporting and moving regulatory science and review forward by first identifying key nonclinical informatics needs and challenges and then establishing an innovative framework for prioritizing and addressing these needs in an open and innovative manner.  Regulators, pharmaceutical industry representatives, and technology vendors are all present at the table to discuss various approaches to using nonclinical data and available informatics approaches to solve shared challenges and provide the tools for improved regulatory science.  This group has several projects well underway including the development of a strategic road map to prioritize and maximize data standardization efforts across nonclinical research, strategies for applying informatics to nonclinical/clinical prediction assessment, historical controls, and projects to support and encourage sponsor use of the Standard for Exchange of Non-Clinical Data (SEND) for submission of nonclincial toxicology data.</p>
      <p>All medical product development stakeholders have a responsibility to protect and enhance the public health.  In the context of product application review, this includes performing effective and efficient reviews while helping move regulatory science forward.  To support this vision, the power of computational science must be harnessed using innovative approaches and bringing the ideas of all stakeholders to the table; the more stakeholders present to provide innovative ideas that address regulatory informatics challenges, the better the outcomes will be. Help shape the solutions of the future.  For more information on how to join ongoing efforts, please visit the FDA/PhUSE Collaboration website.<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0092861512456839">3</xref>
         </sup>
      </p>
   </body>
   <back>
      <fn-group>
         <fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-0092861512456839">
            <label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
            <p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-0092861512456839">
            <label>Funding</label>
            <p>The statement is accurate, the authors wrote this article as part of their regular duties.</p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="bibr1-0092861512456839">
            <label>1</label>
            <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
               <collab collab-type="author" xlink:type="simple">FDA/PhUSE Annual Computational Science Symposium</collab>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phuse.edu/css" xlink:type="simple">http://www.phuse.edu/css</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed July 24, 2012</comment>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr2-0092861512456839">
            <label>2</label>
            <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
               <collab collab-type="author" xlink:type="simple">FDA/PhUSE Working Groups</collab>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phuse.eu/Get-InvolvedCSS.aspx" xlink:type="simple">http://www.phuse.eu/Get-InvolvedCSS.aspx</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed July 24, 2012</comment>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr3-0092861512456839">
            <label>3</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Khatib</surname>
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>DiMaio</surname>
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>, <collab collab-type="author" xlink:type="simple">Foldit Contenders Group</collab>
               <etal/>. <article-title>Crystal structure of a monomeric retroviral protease solved by protein folding game players</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1175</fpage>–<lpage>1177</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>