<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSW</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sprsw</journal-id>
<journal-title>Research on Social Work Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1049-7315</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7581</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049731512453208</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1049731512453208</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Credit Building in IDA Programs</article-title>
<subtitle>Early Findings of a Longitudinal Study</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Birkenmaier</surname>
<given-names>Julie</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049731512453208">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1049731512453208"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Curley</surname>
<given-names>Jami</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049731512453208">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kelly</surname>
<given-names>Patrick</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1049731512453208">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1049731512453208">
<label>1</label>School of Social Work, Saint Louis University, St. Louis, MO, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1049731512453208">
<label>2</label>Doisy College of Health Sciences, Saint Louis University, St. Louis, MO, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1049731512453208">Julie Birkenmaier, School of Social Work, Saint Louis University, 3550 Lindell Blvd, St. Louis, MO 63103, USA Email: <email>birkenjm@slu.edu</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>22</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>605</fpage>
<lpage>614</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Objective: This article reports on the impact of the Individual Development Account (IDA) program on credit. Method: Using a convenience sample of IDA participants (<italic>N</italic> = 165), data were analyzed using paired sample <italic>t</italic> tests, independent sample <italic>t</italic> test, one-way analysis of variance, Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic> Tests, and Wilcoxon Signed Rank Tests. Results: Results indicate that participants improved their credit history and score, as compared with nonparticipants, and those who completed the program within a year experienced the most positive change in credit score. Conclusion: IDAs facilitate improvement in credit score and history.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>financial education</kwd>
<kwd>financial credit</kwd>
<kwd>asset development</kwd>
<kwd>individual development account (IDA)</kwd>
<kwd>credit score</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Credit plays an increasingly important role in the lives of Americans, to include a central role in purchasing assets. A myriad of asset development programs, including Individual Development Account (IDA), assist low-income families to gain wealth through asset purchase and/or maintenance. The IDA program is a unique asset development program in that it provides matched savings toward the goal of asset purchase. For many IDA asset purchases, a combination of personal savings and loans is needed. Lenders use credit history and score in their decisions to set the pricing and terms of borrowed funds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1049731512453208">Loonin, 2010</xref>). Therefore, the credit history and score, an indicator of risk of nonrepayment to potential lenders, are crucial to the success of asset purchase and long-term ownership. Many low-income families, including those seeking to gain assets, struggle with low credit scores. Given the importance of strong credit, many asset development programs, including most IDA programs, provide assistance to participants to improve their financial capability by helping them to improve their credit histories, save, and gain access to appropriate financial products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1049731512453208">Beverly et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1049731512453208">Mills, Lam, DeMarco, Rodger, &amp; Kaul, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1049731512453208">Pinder, Yagely, Peck, &amp; Moore, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>This article reports on the early findings of the impact of IDA programs on credit. Using a convenience sample of IDA participants recruited from the St. Louis, MO area, this study presents Year 1 findings of a longitudinal, 4-year study of participant credit within an IDA program. Results provide a snapshot of credit health for those who completed the program within a year, and various subgroups of participants, which are those who participated and completed the program within a year, those who participated and dropped out after opening an account, and those who participated and are still saving in the program after 1 year. Practice, policy, and research implications are provided.</p>
<sec id="section1-1049731512453208">
<title>Literature Review</title>
<sec id="section2-1049731512453208">
<title>Asset Development and IDAs</title>
<p>Assets, such as an education, a home, land, a business, financial investments, and savings, are vitally important to family development and wealth creation, as well as increasing independence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1049731512453208">Moser, 2008</xref>). Assisting low-income families to build wealth by building assets promotes economic advancement and self-sufficiency and compliments efforts that assist families in gaining income to meet daily needs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1049731512453208">Sherraden, 2009</xref>). The IDA program is an asset development program available across the United States. Various types of IDA providers offer financial education, support, and matched savings accounts for low-income families. The features of programs vary, but generally the program: (1) matches savings, typically by one-to-one, two-to-one, or three-to-one; (2) offers general and asset-specific financial education; and (3) provides additional support in the form of peer support, crisis management, employment support, mentoring, and/or structured planning exercises. Allowable expenses for the matched savings vary, but generally include secondary education, home ownership and home repair, and start or expansion of a small business (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1049731512453208">United States Department of Health and Human Services, 2010</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1049731512453208">
<title>Credit and the IDA Program</title>
<p>Low-income families generally have less financial knowledge than do middle- and high-income families and may benefit the most from financial education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1049731512453208">Campbell, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049731512453208">Sherraden, Schreiner, &amp; Beverly, 2003</xref>). Most IDA programs require and provide group and/or individual general financial education, as well as credit counseling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1049731512453208">United States Department of Health and Human Services, 2010</xref>) to assist participants to gain needed financial education and improve their credit. The majority of IDA participants who purchase an asset utilize financial credit in addition to their savings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1049731512453208">Huang, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1049731512453208">United States Department of Health and Human Services, 2010</xref>). Therefore, review of participant credit history and score has become institutionalized within IDA programs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1049731512453208">Johnson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1049731512453208">Mills et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1049731512453208">Pinder et al., 2006</xref>)</p>
<p>Poor credit has been shown to impede success in IDA programs. Unpaid or late bills from unsecured debt (i.e., credit card or medical debt) are often the cause of poor credit, and can inhibit asset development due to the difficulty in saving funds while also paying large debts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049731512453208">Birkenmaier, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1049731512453208">Nam &amp; Huang, 2009</xref>). For example, those with credit card debt are 4.7% more likely to drop out of the program than are those without debt due to factors such as insufficient financial sophistication, discouragement, and lack of automatic savings devices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1049731512453208">Schreiner &amp; Sherraden, 2005</xref>). For many IDA programs, credit history and scores are gathered at intake and used to tailor individual savings and asset purchase plans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049731512453208">Loibl, Grinstein-Weiss, Zhan, &amp; Red Bird, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1049731512453208">Rohe, Gorham, &amp; Quercia, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>The improvement of financial credit is essential both to prepare participants for IDA participation and to use credit for their future IDA asset purchase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1049731512453208">Carpender, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1049731512453208">Johnson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1049731512453208">Mills et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1049731512453208">Pinder et al., 2006</xref>). Beyond screening and educating, programs are focusing on credit in a variety of ways, to include: (1) allowing IDA funds to be used for paying off debt to increase credit scores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1049731512453208">Mills et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1049731512453208">Pinder et al., 2006</xref>); (2) providing referrals to or having partnerships with lending institutions and credit counselors, such as nonprofit credit counseling agencies and volunteer lawyers, to deliver credit counseling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1049731512453208">Carpender, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1049731512453208">Johnson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1049731512453208">Mills et al., 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1049731512453208">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1049731512453208">Pinder et al., 2006</xref>); and (3) gathering information about the fees associated with and the rates set on loans used for IDA purchases, such as home mortgages and mortgage insurance, and personal loans, which may be used for postsecondary education and business purposes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1049731512453208">Hendricks, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1049731512453208">United States General Accountability Office, 2004</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section4-1049731512453208">
<title>Credit</title>
<p>The three national Credit Reporting Agencies (CRAs), Equifax, Trans Union, and Experian, utilize scores from the Fair Isaac Corporation (FICO), which is the company that created the standard for credit scores. The FICO scores are used to rank borrowers according to the likelihood of default. These scores are widely used to assess credit worthiness and influence lenders’ decisions to grant credit and the terms of the credit. Credit scores are derived from information provided to the credit bureaus about active trade lines, which are revolving (i.e., credit card), or installment (i.e., a fixed loan amount, such as a home mortgage or an auto loan), and public judgments (i.e., bankruptcies, etc.). The CRAs compile creditor and public information into credit reports sold to businesses and consumers. The general range of scores is 300–850, with those below 620 deemed to be higher risk for default. A score of zero is given to those with no credit history. The scores are dynamic and fluctuate, depending on current information. Scoring is based on payment history, amounts owed, length of history of credit, new credit, and types of credit used. Although designed to be bias-free and rate only on financial information, the system has been faulted for many flaws, including a high likelihood of inaccurate information, and bias against the low-income families due to the types of information not regularly reported to the CRAs unless delinquent (i.e., rent, child care, and utility payments). In addition to asset development efforts, credit scores impact quality of life for low-income families because they are increasingly used for screening purposes regarding employment, housing options, setting insurance rates, and other related purposes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1049731512453208">Loonin, 2010</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1049731512453208">
<title>Participant response</title>
<p>Indebtedness to creditors is identified as a major concern of IDA participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1049731512453208">Carpender, 2008</xref>). Some participants take steps to reduce their problem debt prior to participating in the IDA program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1049731512453208">Sherraden, McBride, &amp; Beverly, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1049731512453208">Shockey &amp; Seiling, 2004</xref>). Other participants take steps to lower debt while also saving during the program using such strategies as mental accounting (i.e., coding, categorizing, and evaluating economic activity), maintaining a focus on their savings goal, tracking and reducing expenses, increasing their efficiency and income, and/or moving assets or savings around. Other strategies to deal with problem debt includes delaying bill payments, generating extra income, using tax refunds, reducing household expenses, limiting the use of credit cards, declaring bankruptcy, consolidating debt, working more hours, and borrowing from family. The most common is to limit number and the use of credit cards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1049731512453208">Sherraden et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1049731512453208">
<title>Financial Education</title>
<p>Reducing problem debt and increasing credit scores require knowledge and skills in a variety of financial areas. The financial education offered through IDA programs covers a variety of areas of financial knowledge, to include saving, budgeting, setting goals, and planning finances. Financial education may occur prior to opening an IDA account, or while participants are saving. Financial education typically involved 11–12 hr of general education, and 5–10 hr of asset-specific education (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1049731512453208">Mills et al., 2008</xref>)</p>
<p>In addition to a wide range of financial topics, IDA programs seek to impact participant credit by including credit as a topic in required financial education. Participants learn about the advantages and disadvantages of credit use, different types of credit and ways to access it, the cost of credit, and comparison of credit terms. Participants also learn about credit reports, CRAs, ways to protect their credit, and the best uses of credit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1049731512453208">Mills et al., 2008</xref>). Through these education efforts and one-on-one meetings focused on participant credit, IDA programs encourage problem debt reduction and careful resolution of old debts, which is key to improving credit scores and gaining access to affordable financial products for asset purchase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049731512453208">Fishelson-Holstine, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1049731512453208">Grinstein-Weiss et al., 2008</xref>). To improve their credit, participants often need to (1) pay off or resolve delinquent tradelines (i.e., lines of credit); (2) close tradelines; (3) open new tradelines through the use of such products as a secured credit card; (4) dispute questionable items; and/or (5) establish a consistent record of paying monthly bills on time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1049731512453208">Grinstein-Weiss et al., 2008</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1049731512453208">
<title>Outcomes</title>
<p>Many positive financial outcomes of the IDA program have been reported, including positive intangible outcomes (i.e., fiscal prudence, expanded social networks, future orientation, and sense of security), additional financial knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1049731512453208">Im &amp; Busette, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049731512453208">Scanlon &amp; Adams, 2009</xref>), savings outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1049731512453208">Carpender, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049731512453208">Grinstein-Weiss, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1049731512453208">Grinstein-Weiss, Yeo, Despard, Casalotti, &amp; Zhan, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049731512453208">Hogan, Solheim, Wolfgram, Nkosi, &amp; Rodrigues, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049731512453208">Loibl et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1049731512453208">Schreiner &amp; Sherraden, 2007</xref>), and reducing debt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1049731512453208">Grinstein-Weiss, 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1049731512453208">Shockey and Seiling (2004)</xref> found that the financial actions of IDA participants improved through the course of the program, with “setting aside money for unplanned spending” as the largest behavior change, and “reducing debt” as the smallest behavior change, because participants were already working to reduce debt at the program outset. Other research has demonstrated program impact on income, economic security (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1049731512453208">Lerman &amp; McKernan, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1049731512453208">Page-Adams, Scanlon, Beverely, &amp; McDonald, 2001</xref>), financial assets (i.e., all liquid and near-liquid assets, excluding home, other real estate, business, and vehicles; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1049731512453208">Huang, 2010</xref>), and real assets and total assets (i.e., total financial assets plus the value of all real assets, including home, other real estate, business, and vehicles; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1049731512453208">Han, Grinstein-Weiss, &amp; Sherraden, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Other studies have found unchanged or mixed financial outcomes associated with IDA programs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1049731512453208">McKernan, Ratcliffe, &amp; Nam, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1049731512453208">Mills et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1049731512453208">Richards &amp; Thyer, 2011</xref>). Neither the unique impact of the program on financial well-being, as measured by net worth (i.e., financial assets, home equity, and consumer debt), savings, nor the ability to purchase assets has been shown, although future evaluation data and longitudinal studies that use experimental designs may permit a more comprehensive study of these questions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1049731512453208">Grinstein-Weiss, Sherraden, Gale, Rohe, &amp; Key, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1049731512453208">Mills et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1049731512453208">Richards &amp; Thyer, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1049731512453208">Sherraden, 2009</xref>). Regarding credit, research has demonstrated no significant difference with regard to credit card debt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049731512453208">Loibl et al., 2010</xref>) or a significant difference in the credit scores of participants as compared to nonparticipants after program participation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1049731512453208">Loibl &amp; Red Bird, 2009</xref>). No studies were located that evaluated the impact of IDA program on credit scores during program delivery.</p>
<p>In sum, little research has been undertaken to study the impact of the program on credit during or after program participation. Such research would aid in understanding the credit well-being of families while in the program, and add to the body of research about the financial health of families after the program and the long-term impact of the program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1049731512453208">Birkenmaier, Curley, &amp; Kelly, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049731512453208">Loibl et al., 2010</xref>). Participants leaving the program with strong credit history and assets purchased with affordable credit would provide a strong foundation for long-term affordability and ownership of the asset (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1049731512453208">Christy-McMullin, Shobe, &amp; Wills, 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1049731512453208">
<title>Objective</title>
<p>The current study reports on 1-year findings of a 4-year longitudinal study on financial credit outcomes of asset development activities. The study provides an early look at the credit well-being of IDA program participants as one measure of their overall financial well-being. The following research questions are addressed: (1) Has there been a significant change in IDA participant credit score after 1 year as compared to nonparticipants? (2) Are there significant differences in change in credit score among participant subgroups? (3) Has there been a significant change in participant credit history elements after 1 year as compared to nonparticipants? and (4) Are there significant differences in change in credit history elements for participant subgroups after 1 year? It is hypothesized that those who complete the IDA program will have higher credit scores and a better credit history than those who do not complete the IDA program.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1049731512453208" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section10-1049731512453208">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>Permission was obtained from the United Way of Greater St. Louis and three IDA programs in St. Louis, Missouri, that participate in an IDA collaborative facilitated by the United Way of Greater St. Louis to conduct this study. The study received approval from the Institutional Review Board. Researchers utilized a convenience sample for data collection. Similar to most IDA programs around the country, the participants were employed with income levels of 200% or below the federal poverty line at the time of the study. A total of 281 clients from the three organizations were recruited to participate, and 188 consented, for a response rate of 67%. Of the total sample size of 188, 167 had a credit score above zero at both baseline and Year 1. Two cases were eliminated due to the initial zero credit score (i.e., no credit) for both cases. The final sample size was 165 (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1049731512453208">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1049731512453208" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Participant flowchart.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1049731512453208-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1049731512453208">
<title>Agency Setting</title>
<p>The sample (<italic>N</italic> = 165) was obtained through three community-based agencies that offered other programs besides IDAs. These agencies included (a) a housing counseling agency that provides prepurchase and postpurchase housing counseling, which recruited 88% of the participants (<italic>n</italic> = 146); (b) a domestic violence agency that provides family literacy, economic education, and other related programs, which recruited 9% of the participants (<italic>n</italic> = 15); and (c) a homeless service provider that provides referrals to area shelters, assistance with rent, and other related services, which recruited 2% of the participants (<italic>n</italic> = 4). The three recruitment sites collect identical demographic data in one web-based administrative database (i.e., VistaShare Outcome Tracker), teach financial education that addresses identical core financial education competencies (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1049731512453208">Table 1</xref>), and permit similar allowable purchases with IDA funds (i.e., home, home improvement, microenterprise, postsecondary education, and vehicle).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1049731512453208" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>General Financial Education Core Competencies</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1049731512453208" xlink:href="10.1177_1049731512453208-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<bold>Financial Plan</bold> Participants will:<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Become aware that attitudes and values affect how they view and use their money</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Learn how to set realistic and measurable financial goals</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Understand how to calculate monthly income and expenses</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Learn how to develop a spending plan that includes savings and goals and emergencies</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Learn how to manage regular monthly payments and savings</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Become aware of strategies for bringing income and expenses into balance</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<bold>Keeping Records, Taxes, and Contracts</bold> Participants will:<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Understand how planning their finances and keeping good records can reduce their taxes</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Identify what records to keep and where to keep them</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Understand what creates a legal contract</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Learn about types of contracts that exist, types of contract terms, and how to evaluate whether or not to sign a contract</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Become aware of consumer rights and lender rights under repossession, foreclosure, and the collections process</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<bold>Credit</bold> Participants will:<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Learn about the advantage and disadvantages of using credit</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Learn about different types of credit and how to get credit</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Become aware of the cost of credit</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Learn how to compare credit terms and evaluate their own credit situation</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Become aware of wise ways to use credit</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Learn about credit reports, credit reporting agencies, and how to protect their credit</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<bold>Financial services</bold> Participants will:<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Become aware of the benefits of using a financial institution</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Learn about the different types of financial institutions and services offered</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Learn ways to evaluate and compare institutions and services to choose those that best fit their needs</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Learn how to write checks and manage their checking and savings accounts</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Become aware of procedures used to address and resolve problems related to their accounts</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<bold>Insurance</bold> Participants will:<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>Learn ways to evaluate insurance policies and companies</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Learn basic insurance terms</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1049731512453208">
<title>Research Design</title>
<p>Between February 2008 and June 2009, community-based agencies screened low-income people for the IDA program and invited those who were eligible to an orientation. Those attending the orientation were then asked to participate in the study. Participants gave written permission for researchers to utilize data routinely collected by IDA program staff in the IDA database, as well as for the researchers to access their credit report annually over 4 years, and use the data for the study. Subjects had a range of number of contacts with IDA program staff: Some subjects only had contact with IDA staff during the orientation session, while others had contact with the IDA program throughout their financial education curriculum, during one individual session of credit assessment and IDA account opening, and prior to asset purchase, depending on their level of involvement and participation in the program (see below for clarification). Data presented here are baseline and Year 1 data for the 4-year study (<italic>N</italic> = 165). Participants are those who completed financial education, enrolled in the program, opened a bank account, and began saving. Nonparticipants are those who attended an orientation, but chose to cease their participation prior to any other step in the program; therefore, they did not complete financial education, enroll in the program, open a bank account, or save. To measure for differences between types of participants, three subgroups of participants were created: those who completed the program within a year (<italic>Completed</italic>), those who dropped out without completing (<italic>Dropouts</italic>), and those who are still saving in the program (<italic>Still Saving</italic>). FICO credit scores used are those calculated by the TransUnion credit bureau.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1049731512453208">
<title>Analysis</title>
<p>Descriptive statistics were computed on participant demographics and data obtained from the credit reports for baseline and Year 1. Paired sample <italic>t</italic> tests were completed to compare mean score changes in credit scores for participant and nonparticipant groups. An independent sample <italic>t</italic> test was used to compare the Year 1 credit scores between the participant and nonparticipant groups. A one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was conducted to explore whether or not there were significant changes in credit score attributable to participant program status (i.e., three participant subgroups and one group of nonparticipants). Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic> Tests, a nonparametric equivalent of independent sample <italic>t</italic> tests, was conducted to test for differences between credit history elements on the change score for participant and nonparticipant groups and the three participant subgroups. Wilcoxon Signed Rank Tests, a nonparametric equivalent of paired sample <italic>t</italic> tests, were conducted to test for significance between differences in credit history element medians from baseline to Year 1 within each group. Nonparametric tests were used for those variables that were not normally distributed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1049731512453208">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section15-1049731512453208">
<title>Descriptive Data</title>
<p>Descriptive statistics on the participants (<italic>n</italic> = 78), nonparticipants (<italic>n</italic> = 87), and the participant subgroups <italic>Completed</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 30 or 18% of the overall sample), <italic>Dropouts</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 13, 8% of the overall sample), and <italic>Still Saving</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 35, 21% of the overall sample) are provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1049731512453208">Table 2</xref>. Of the 78 participants, 30 (39%) closed and completed the program, 13 (17%) closed but did not complete the program, and 35 (45%) are still saving in the program after 1 year.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1049731512453208" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Demographic Statistics for Participants and Nonparticipants, and Participant Subgroups</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1049731512453208" xlink:href="10.1177_1049731512453208-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th rowspan="2">Variable</th>
<th rowspan="2">Nonparticipants (<italic>n</italic> = 87, 53%)</th>
<th rowspan="2">Participants (<italic>n</italic> = 78, 47%)</th>
<th colspan="3">Participant Subgroups<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Completed (<italic>n</italic> = 30, 18%)</th>
<th>Dropouts (<italic>n</italic> = 13, 8%)</th>
<th>Still Saving (<italic>n</italic> = 35, 21%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="6">Age</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 30 and younger</td>
<td>25 (29%)</td>
<td>25 (32%)</td>
<td>11 (37%)</td>
<td>0 (0%)</td>
<td>14 (40%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 31–40</td>
<td>32 (37%)</td>
<td>29 (37%)</td>
<td>15 (50%)</td>
<td>8 (62%)</td>
<td>6 (17%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 41 and older</td>
<td>30 (34%)</td>
<td>28 (31%)</td>
<td>4 (13%)</td>
<td>5 (31%)</td>
<td>15 (43%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Female</td>
<td>72 (83%)</td>
<td>66 (85%)</td>
<td>26 (87%)</td>
<td>12 (92%)</td>
<td>28 (80%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Single</td>
<td>48 (55%)</td>
<td>49 (63%)</td>
<td>17 (57%)</td>
<td>9 (69%)</td>
<td>22 (63%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Higher education</td>
<td>72 (83%)</td>
<td>68 (87%)</td>
<td>27 (90%)</td>
<td>12 (92%)</td>
<td>29 (83%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>African American</td>
<td>64 (74%)</td>
<td>56 (72%)</td>
<td>21 (70%)</td>
<td>11 (85%)</td>
<td>24 (69%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Caucasian and other</td>
<td>21 (24%)</td>
<td>28 (24%)</td>
<td>8 (26%)</td>
<td>2 (13%)</td>
<td>8 (23%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Baseline mean # of children</td>
<td align="center">1.8</td>
<td align="center">1.34</td>
<td align="center">1.5</td>
<td align="center">1.7</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Baseline high income/debt ratio</td>
<td>16 (18%)</td>
<td>17 (22%)</td>
<td>7 (23%)</td>
<td>3 (23%)</td>
<td>6 (17%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Baseline household bills past due, mean amount</td>
<td align="center">47 (53%), $562.31</td>
<td align="center">35 (44%), $1,529</td>
<td align="center">15 (50%), $1,362</td>
<td align="center">7 (54%), $5,154</td>
<td align="center">13 (37%), $295</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Baseline EITC recipients</td>
<td>26 (30%)</td>
<td>28 (35%)</td>
<td>12 (40%)</td>
<td>6 (46%)</td>
<td>9 (26%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Baseline % poor credit score</td>
<td>68 (77%)</td>
<td>46 (58%)</td>
<td>20 (67%)</td>
<td>10 (77%)</td>
<td>15 (43%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Positive change in credit score</td>
<td>51 (59%)</td>
<td>48 (62%)</td>
<td>23 (77%)</td>
<td>3 (23%)</td>
<td>22 (63%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1049731512453208">
<p>
<italic>Note</italic>. EITC: Earned Income Tax Credit Program.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Participants (<italic>n</italic> = 78) are predominately 31–40 years old (37%), female (85%), single (63%), and have enrolled in higher education (87%). They are also predominately African American (72%), with a mean number of 1.34 children. Nonparticipants (<italic>n</italic> = 87) are also predominately 31–40 years old (37%), 83% female, 55% single, and 83% enrolled in higher education. Similar to participants, 74% of the nonparticipants are African American (74%), with a mean number of 1.8 children. The participant groups (<italic>Completed</italic>, <italic>Dropouts</italic>, and<italic> Still Saving</italic>) had similar profiles. There were no significant differences between the participants from the three agencies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1049731512453208">
<title>Change in Credit Score</title>
<p>Results of a series of paired sample <italic>t</italic> tests to compare the differences between baseline and Year 1 credit scores for various groups are seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1049731512453208">Table 3</xref>. As the outcomes show, there is a significant improvement in credit score for participants (with a moderate effect size), and the Completed subgroup of participants (with a large effect size). Results of the Still Saving group neared significance (<italic>p</italic> = .07). Negative movement in credit score was experienced by the nonparticipants, and the Drop-out participant group.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1049731512453208" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Paired Sample <italic>t</italic> Tests for Change in Credit Score, Nonparticipant and Participant Group, and Participant Subgroups</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1049731512453208" xlink:href="10.1177_1049731512453208-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Variable</th>
<th>Baseline Mean</th>
<th>Year 1 Mean</th>
<th>Mean Diff.</th>
<th>95% CI</th>
<th>
<italic>t</italic>
</th>
<th>
<italic>r</italic>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Participant</td>
<td>598.4 (104.13)</td>
<td>613.92 (102.77)</td>
<td>15.53</td>
<td>[3.41, 27.64]</td>
<td>(77)* 2.55</td>
<td>.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Non-participant</td>
<td>561.34 (80.66)</td>
<td>560.41 (78.01)</td>
<td>−0.93</td>
<td>[−10.31, 8.45]</td>
<td>(86) −.20</td>
<td>.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Completed</td>
<td>590.6 (107.38)</td>
<td>620.37 (90.08)</td>
<td>29.77</td>
<td>[11.78, 47.76]</td>
<td>(29)** 3.38</td>
<td>.28</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dropout</td>
<td>570.46 (108.21)</td>
<td>550.62 (122.79)</td>
<td>−19.85</td>
<td>[−55.55, 15.86]</td>
<td>(12) 1.21</td>
<td>.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Still Saving</td>
<td>615.46 (99.67)</td>
<td>631.91 (98.87)</td>
<td>16.46</td>
<td>[−1.29, 34.21]</td>
<td>(34) 1.88</td>
<td>.04</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1049731512453208">
<p>
<italic>Note</italic>. **<italic>p</italic> ≤ .01. *<italic>p</italic> ≤ .05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The results of a two-tailed, nonpooled independent samples <italic>t</italic> test comparing participant group and nonparticipant group on Year 1 credit score indicated a significant difference, <italic>t</italic>(143.02) = −3.72, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. This indicates that the average credit score of nonparticipants (<italic>M</italic> = 560.41, <italic>SD</italic> = 78.08) was statistically significantly lower (MD = −53.51, CI [−81.85, −25.17]) than for participants (<italic>M</italic> = 613.92, <italic>SD</italic> = 102.77). The η<sup>2</sup> value of .08 indicates a moderate effect. For the one-way between-groups ANOVA to explore the impact of program status after 1 year on the change in credit score, participants were divided into four groups (Group 1: Nonparticipants; Group 2: Completed [Participants]; Group 3: Still Saving [Participants]; and Group 4: Dropout [Participants]). There is a statistically significant difference at the <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 level in change scores for the four groups: <italic>F</italic>(3, 161) = 4.91, <italic>p</italic> = .003. The effect size, calculated using η<sup>2</sup>, is .08, which is a medium effect. Post hoc comparisons using the Tukey HSD test indicated that the mean difference for Group 1 (Nonparticipants; <italic>M</italic> = −.93, <italic>SD</italic> = 44) is statistically different from Group 2 (Completed; <italic>M</italic> = 29.77, <italic>SD</italic> = 48.18). Group 2 (Completed) is statistically different from Group 4 (Dropout; <italic>M</italic> = −19.85, <italic>SD</italic> = 59.08).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1049731512453208">
<title>Change in Elements in Credit History for Participants and Nonparticipants</title>
<p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1049731512453208">Table 4</xref> reports the results of Wilcoxon Signed Rank Tests for the participant group. As the results indicate, there are significant differences in a number of credit history elements for participants: the age of oldest tradelines, the number of active tradelines, the number of revolving tradelines, the number of tradelines 6 months old with no collections, the number of tradelines 12 months old with no collections, and the number of bankruptcies. Effect sizes for all were small. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1049731512453208">Table 4</xref> also reports the results for the nonparticipants, which indicate significant differences in the age of the oldest tradeline, the number of tradelines with late pays 60–89 days, and the number of inquiries.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1049731512453208" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Wilcoxon Signed Rank Test, Participants, Nonparticipants, and Still Saving Participant Group</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1049731512453208" xlink:href="10.1177_1049731512453208-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th colspan="2">Participants (<italic>n</italic> = 78)<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Nonparticipants (<italic>n</italic> = 87)<hr/></th>
<th colspan="2">Still Saving (<italic>n</italic> = 35)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Variable</th>
<th>
<italic>d</italic>
</th>
<th>
<italic>r</italic>
</th>
<th>
<italic>d</italic>
</th>
<th>
<italic>r</italic>
</th>
<th>
<italic>d</italic>
</th>
<th>
<italic>r</italic>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age of oldest tradeline</td>
<td>0.50**</td>
<td>.23</td>
<td>0**</td>
<td>.19</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of active tradelines</td>
<td>1.00*</td>
<td>.15</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>1.00*</td>
<td>.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of revolving tradelines</td>
<td>0.00**</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>1.00*</td>
<td>.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of installment tradelines</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of tradelines 6 months old, no collections</td>
<td>1.00**</td>
<td>.23</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>1.00*</td>
<td>.18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of tradelines with late pays 30–59 days</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of tradelines with late pays 60–89 days</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>0*</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of tradelines 12 months old, no collections</td>
<td>0.00*</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Amount of collection debt</td>
<td align="center">−$936</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td align="center">$1,387</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td align="center">−574</td>
<td>.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of public judgments</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Defaults/foreclosures</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bankruptcies</td>
<td>0.00*</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Delinquencies</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tax liens</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>0.00</td>
<td>.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Inquiries</td>
<td>−2.00</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>−4**</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>.15</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1049731512453208">
<p>
<italic>Note</italic>. **<italic>p</italic> ≤ .01. *<italic>p</italic> ≤ .05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1049731512453208">Table 5</xref> provides results of the Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic> Test for participants and nonparticipants. Significant differences between the participant and nonparticipant groups are seen in the following credit history elements: age of oldest tradeline, number of active tradelines, number of revolving tradelines, number of tradelines 6 months old with no collections, amount of collection debt, and number of tradelines 12 months old with no collections, number of defaults/foreclosures, and number of tax liens.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-1049731512453208" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic> Test, Year 1 Credit History</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1049731512453208" xlink:href="10.1177_1049731512453208-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Variable</th>
<th>Mean Rank Participants (<italic>n</italic> = 78)</th>
<th>Mean Rank Nonparticipants (<italic>n</italic> = 87)</th>
<th>
<italic>U</italic>
</th>
<th>
<italic>z</italic>
</th>
<th>
<italic>r</italic>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age of oldest tradeline</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2785.50</td>
<td>−2.00*</td>
<td>.16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of active tradelines</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2522.00</td>
<td>−2.78**</td>
<td>.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of revolving tradelines</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2322.00</td>
<td>−3.73**</td>
<td>.29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of installment tradelines</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3139.50</td>
<td>−0.87</td>
<td>.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of tradelines 6 months old, no collections</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2563.50</td>
<td>−2.78**</td>
<td>.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Amount of collection debt</td>
<td>823</td>
<td>4,853</td>
<td>2224.00</td>
<td>−3.84**</td>
<td>.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of tradelines with late pays 30–59 days</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3327.00</td>
<td>−0.28</td>
<td>.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of tradelines with late pays 60–89 days</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3261.50</td>
<td>−0.62</td>
<td>.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of public judgments</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3045.00</td>
<td>−1.23</td>
<td>.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of tradelines 12 months old, no collections</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2690.00</td>
<td>−2.39*</td>
<td>.19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Defaults/foreclosures</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3003.00</td>
<td>−3.01**</td>
<td>.23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bankruptcies</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3289.50</td>
<td>−0.44</td>
<td>.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Delinquencies</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3311.00</td>
<td>−0.33</td>
<td>.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tax liens</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3123.00</td>
<td>−2.24*</td>
<td>.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Inquiries</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>3002.00</td>
<td>−1.16</td>
<td>.09</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1049731512453208">
<p>
<italic>Note</italic>. **<italic>p</italic> ≤ .01. *<italic>p</italic> ≤ .05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1049731512453208">
<title>Change in Elements in Credit History for Participant Groups</title>
<p>Wilcoxon Signed Rank Tests are conducted for the Completed, Dropout, and Still Saving participant subgroups. Results indicate that only the Still Saving participant group experienced significant changes to the elements of their credit history (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1049731512453208">Table 4</xref> displays these results). The Still Saving group experienced significant improvements in the number of active tradelines, the number of revolving tradelines, and the number of tradelines 6 months old with no collections, with small effect sizes.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1049731512453208">
<title>Discussion and Applications to Social Work</title>
<p>This study provides insight into the credit well-being of participants 1 year after beginning the IDA program. These preliminary results indicate that the IDA program participation has a positive impact on credit scores and credit history. While both participants and nonparticipants experienced positive changes, participants experienced more positive impacts than nonparticipants. Participants experienced an increase in their credit score, the age of oldest tradelines (i.e., an indication of maintenance of the credit line over time), the number of active tradelines, the number of revolving tradelines, the number of tradelines 6 months old with no collections, the number of tradelines 12 months old with no collections, and a decrease in the number of bankruptcies. Participants who completed the program within 1 year experienced a significant increase in their credit score, while those who are still saving in the program experienced an increase in the number of active tradelines, the number of revolving tradelines, and the number of tradelines 6 months old with no collections. Regarding the change in credit score, participants who completed the program had significantly higher credit scores than those who did not participate and those who participated and dropped out. As compared to nonparticipants, participants also experienced significant differences in the age of oldest tradeline, number of active tradelines, number of revolving tradelines, number of tradelines 6 months old with no collections, amount of collection debt, and number of tradelines 12 months old with no collections, number of defaults/foreclosures, and the number of tax liens.</p>
<p>With few exceptions, taken together, these changes indicate support for the hypothesis that the IDA program provides positive benefits for credit scores and credit history, particularly for participants who complete the program. For those who completed the program in the first year, results indicate that they graduated from the program with a purchased asset, significantly better credit scores, and improved credit history. The Still Saving subgroup of participants experienced a small, nonsignificant increase in their scores, and the Drop-out subgroup of participants and nonparticipants experienced a decline in credit scores. The Still Saving subgroup of participants experienced improvements in the elements of their credit history, with moderate and large (respectively) effect sizes. While the nonparticipant group also experienced some positive changes, their credit scores did not increase.</p>
<p>These IDA participants, like many IDA participants, began the program with low credit scores, and poor credit history (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1049731512453208">Birkenmaier et al., 2011</xref>) due to, among other factors, a lack of sufficient income, unexpected events that require spending and accumulation of unsecured (or problem) debt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1049731512453208">Grinstein-Weiss, Chowa, &amp; Casalotti, 2010</xref>), lack of financial education, and other factors. The participants who are able to complete the program and stay in the program after 1 year benefit from the financial education and support and experience significant improvements in their credit scores and histories. This benefit is important beyond the ability to purchase an asset, and could prove to be life-changing for IDA participants, many of whom struggle with significant credit problems, such as high debt. For example, almost half of those who enrolled in Rhode Island’s IDA program the first year had debt burdens of more than $10,000 (Christner, 2003, as cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1049731512453208">Carpender, 2008</xref>). While families from all income levels struggle with financial problems associated with a range of situations that negatively impact income, such as unexpected loss of employment, overindulgence, addictions, poor decisions, and miscalculations that contribute to problem debt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1049731512453208">Warren &amp; Tyagi, 2003</xref>), low-income families have little room for error. Events such as job loss, health emergency, divorce, and death in the family, situations for which there is little control, are the origins for the majority of problem debt for IDA participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1049731512453208">Sherraden et al., 2010</xref>). Despite these challenges, these results provide support for the notion that the IDA program can assist participants to improve some elements that contribute to the improvement of their credit score.</p>
<p>These results are particularly striking and provide evidence of the positive impact of IDA programming regarding credit, including financial education and support. Therefore, asset development programming should continue to institutionalize tailored approaches to financial capability by providing financial education, facilitating and encouraging participants to engage in strategies to improve credit, and assist in the acquisition of appropriate loan products so the credit improvements can be sustained (Grinstein-Weiss, Chowa, et al., 2010; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1049731512453208">Zhan, Anderson, &amp; Scott, 2006</xref>). Policy makers and program administrators may wish to expand the allowable uses of the IDA savings to include credit improvement through debt reduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1049731512453208">Grinstein-Weiss et al., 2008</xref>). The challenges of improving credit scores through addressing debt and using credit wisely, in combination with education and assistance to avoid high-risk, high-cost credit, can assist participants to build good credit and financial capability.</p>
<p>This research has implications for policy and research. Asset development policy must also consider and promote credit building as both a stand-alone asset and essential to building assets. Research with nationally representative samples is needed to determine the effectiveness of various aspects of financial education and other IDA programming on credit so that program elements can best be targeted toward credit building efforts. Research is also needed on the effectiveness of various types of partnerships between IDA programs and types of financial providers from which participants obtain loan products to determine the outcomes of these partnerships. Future research, including this longitudinal study, is needed to examine the long-term effects of IDA program participation on credit, including the incidence of asset forfeiture or foreclosure. Although anecdotal evidence suggests that IDA participants utilize affordable mortgage products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1049731512453208">Grinstein-Weiss et al., 2010</xref>), longitudinal research is needed to determine whether participants are able to maintain their improved credit scores and histories, as well as asset ownership, over many years. While the hope is that IDA participants are more likely to utilize safe loan products because of their improved knowledge of credit terms, subprime credit, and their ability to repay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1049731512453208">Grinstein-Weiss et al., 2008</xref>), research is needed about the loan products utilized by IDA participants when purchasing other types of assets (i.e., secondary education, etc.).</p>
<p>While the participants were drawn from the population of those seeking IDAs, the sample may not represent the national IDA population, nor a random draw of all low-income households. Therefore, the results may not apply to all IDA participants nor the employed low-income population. The study also should not be generalized to the national IDA population. An earlier report on this study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1049731512453208">Birkenmaier, Curley, and Kelly (2011)</xref> reported that the sample differed from other national samples of IDA participants (i.e., in the levels of education, homeownership rate, and number who have a transaction account; [<italic>are banked</italic>]). Additionally, credit information provided is cross-sectional and may not be an accurate description of the lifetime credit histories of IDA participants. Several threats to internal validity, including subject selection and maturation, experimental mortality and persistence, were described earlier. Regarding additional threats to internal validity, there were no perceptible effects of history (i.e., the economic climate remained relatively unchanged), the program delivery was consistent with no major changes during the study, and there were no major changes to the ways in which credit bureaus collect and score credit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1049731512453208">Campbell &amp; Standley, 1963</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1049731512453208">Cook &amp; Campbell, 1979</xref>). Therefore, the results are suggestive of the credit history and scores of IDA participants. Future research should include a larger, more diverse, nationally representative sample. Mixed-method research that included the view of the participants about their efforts to improve credit would contribute to the body of knowledge about credit and IDAs. Use of additional variables that may explain variance in credit score change may be useful.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-1049731512453208">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>This research adds to the evidence of the positive benefits of the IDA program. Participants who complete the program within a year or remain in the program, rather than drop out, experience significant gains in their credit. Through financial education, guidance, and support, IDA programs hold the potential to address the targeting of minority and low-income communities by high-cost credit providers, which has resulted in disproportionate share of high-cost loans in these types of communities and disproportionate foreclosure rates during the recent recession (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049731512453208">Rugh &amp; Massey, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1049731512453208">Squires, Hyra, &amp; Renner, 2009</xref>). IDA programs can build financial capability of participants by highlighting and focusing on credit score gains as a financial asset, and assisting participants to locate affordable financial products.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The authors also thank Katie Terrell, Hannah Shanks, Natalie Alcorn, Cassandra Kaufman, Debbie Irwin, Eric Zegel, Emily McGinnis, and Jane Schoeck for their contributions to this research and publication.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-1049731512453208">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1049731512453208">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors of this study would like to thank the United Way of Greater Saint Louis and U.S. Bankcorp Foundation for supporting this study.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beverly</surname>
<given-names>S. G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sherraden</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhan</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Williams Shanks</surname>
<given-names>T. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nam</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cramer</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Determinants of asset building</source>. <publisher-loc>St. Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New American Foundation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Birkenmaier</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Curley</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Financial credit: Social work's role in empowering low-income families</article-title>. <source>Journal of Community Practice</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Birkenmaier</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Curley</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kelly</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The financial credit profile of low-income families seeking assets</article-title>. <source>Journal of Financial Therapy</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stanley</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1963</year>). <source>Experimental and quasi-experimental designs for research</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rand-McNally</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>J. Y.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Household finance</source> <comment>(working paper no. 12149)</comment>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Bureau of Economic Research</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carpender</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Major findings from IDA research on the United States</source>. <publisher-loc>St. Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Center for Social Development, Washington University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Christy-McMullin</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shobe</surname>
<given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wills</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Arkansas IDA programs: Examining asset retention and perceptions of well-being</article-title>. <source>Journal of Social Service Research</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cook</surname>
<given-names>T. D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>D. T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <source>Quasi-experimentation: Design and analysis issues for field settings</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Houghton Mifflin Company</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fishelson-Holstine</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Credit scoring’s role in increasing homeownership for underserved populations</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Retsinas</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Belsky</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Building assets, building credit: Creating wealth in low-income communities</source> (pp. <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brookings Institution</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grinstein-Weiss</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Curley</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Charles</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Asset building in rural communities: The experience of individual development accounts</article-title>. <source>Rural Sociology</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grinstein-Weiss</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>J.-S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Greeson</surname>
<given-names>J. K. P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>C.-K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yeo</surname>
<given-names>Y. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Irish</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Fostering low-income homeownership through individual development accounts: A longitudinal, randomized experiment</article-title>. <source>Housing Policy Debate</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>711</fpage>–<lpage>739</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1080/10511482.2008.9521653</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grinstein-Weiss</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sherraden</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gale</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rohe</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Key</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Ten-year impacts of individual development accounts on homeownership: Evidence from a randomized experiment</source>. <publisher-loc>St. Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Center for Social Development, Washington University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grinstein-Weiss</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yeo</surname>
<given-names>Y. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Despard</surname>
<given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Casalotti</surname>
<given-names>A. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhan</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Does prior banking experience matter? Differences of the banked and unbanked in individual development accounts</article-title>. <source>Journal of Family and Economic Issues</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>212</fpage>–<lpage>227</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1007/s10834-010-9184-5</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grinstein-Weiss</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yeo</surname>
<given-names>Y. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zahn</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Charles</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Asset holding and net worth among households with children: Differences by household type</article-title>. <source>Children and Youth Services Review</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grinstein-Weiss</surname>
<given-names>M. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chowa</surname>
<given-names>G. A. N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Casalotti</surname>
<given-names>A. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Individual development accounts for housing policy: Analysis of individual and program characteristics</article-title>. <source>Housing Studies</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>C.-K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grinstein-Weiss</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sherraden</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Assets beyond savings in individual development accounts</article-title>. <source>Social Service Review</source>, <volume>83</volume>, <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>. <comment>doi</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/SSR/">http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/SSR/</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hendricks</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>How the system really works and what you can do</source>. <publisher-loc>Cabin John, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Privacy Times</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hogan</surname>
<given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Solheim</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wolfgram</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nkosi</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rodrigues</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The working poor: From the economic margins to asset building</article-title>. <source>Family Relations</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Effects of individual development accounts (IDAs) on household wealth and saving taste</article-title>. <source>Research on Social Work Practice</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>582</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Im</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Busette</surname>
<given-names>C. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>What motivates low income earners to save money?</article-title> <source>EARN Research Brief</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>EARN Research Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>A. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Growing the united way of king county individual development account program to scale</source>. <publisher-loc>Seattle</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Washington Daniel J. Evans School of Public Affairs</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lerman</surname>
<given-names>R. I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McKernan</surname>
<given-names>S.-M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Benefits and consequences of holding assets</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>McKernan</surname>
<given-names>S.-M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sherraden</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Asset building and low-income families</source> (pp. <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Urban Institute Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Loibl</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grinstein-Weiss</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhan</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Red Bird</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>More than a penny saved: Long-term changes in behavior among savings program participants</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Affairs</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>98</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Loibl</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Red Bird</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Survey of former IDA program participants: How do they fare</article-title>. <source>Journal of Extension</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Loonin</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Guide to surviving debt</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Consumer Law Center</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McKernan</surname>
<given-names>S-M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ratcliffe</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nam</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The effects of welfare and IDA program rules on the asset holdings of low-income families</article-title>. <source>This report is part of a series entitled <italic>Poor Finances: Assets and Low-Income Households</italic>, produced in a partnership between the Urban Institute, Center for Social Development, and New America Foundation</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Health &amp; Human Services, Office of the Assistant Secretary for Planning and Evaluation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mills</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Campos</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ciurea</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>DeMarco</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Michlin</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Welch</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Evaluation of asset accumulation initiatives</source> <comment>(Final report)</comment>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Abt Associates</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mills</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>DeMarco</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rodger</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kaul</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Impact study: Final report. Assets for independence act evaluation</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Abt Associates</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Moser</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Assets and livelihoods: A framework for asset-based social policy</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Moser</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dani</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Assets, livelihoods, and social policy</source> (pp. <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Bank</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nam</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Equal opportunity for all? Parental economic resources and children's educational attainment</article-title>. <source>Children and Youth Services Review</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Page-Adams</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Scanlon</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beverely</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McDonald</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Assets, health, and well-being: Neighborhoods, families, children, and youth</source> <comment>(Vol. Background paper 01-9)</comment>. <publisher-loc>St. Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Center for Social Development, Washington University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pinder</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yagely</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peck</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Moore</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Designing and implementing rural individual development account programs</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Housing Assistance Council</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Richards</surname>
<given-names>K. V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thyer</surname>
<given-names>B. A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Does IDA participation help the poor?</article-title> <source>Research on Social Work Practice</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>348</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rohe</surname>
<given-names>W. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gorham</surname>
<given-names>L. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Quercia</surname>
<given-names>R. G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Individual development accounts: Participants’ characteristics and success</article-title>. <source>Journal of Urban Affairs</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>520</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rugh</surname>
<given-names>J. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Massey</surname>
<given-names>D. S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Racial segregation and the American foreclosure crisis</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>651</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Scanlon</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Matched savings account: A study of youth's perceptions of program and account design</article-title>. <source>Journal of Social Service Research</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schreiner</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sherraden</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Drop-out from individual development accounts: Prediction and prevention</article-title>. <source>Financial Services Review</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schreiner</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sherraden</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Can the poor save? Saving and asset building in individual development accounts</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sherraden</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Individual development accounts and asset-building policy: Lessons and directions</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Blank</surname>
<given-names>R. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barr</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Insufficient funds: Savings, assets, credit, and banking among low-income households</source> (pp. <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>217</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Russell Sage Foundation</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sherraden</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schreiner</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beverly</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Income, institutions, and saving performance in individual development accounts</article-title>. <source>Economic Development Quarterly</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sherraden</surname>
<given-names>M. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McBride</surname>
<given-names>A. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beverly</surname>
<given-names>S. G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Striving to save: Creating policies for financial security of low-income families</source>. <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shockey</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seiling</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Moving into action: Application of the transtheoretical model of behavior change to financial education</article-title>. <source>Journal of Financial Counseling and Planning</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Squires</surname>
<given-names>G. D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hyra</surname>
<given-names>D. S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Renner</surname>
<given-names>R. N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Segregation and the subprime lending crisis</article-title>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the Federal Reserve System Community Affairs Research Conference</conf-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">United States Department of Health and Human Services</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>Assets for independence program: Status at conclusion of the tenth year</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">United States General Accountability Office</collab>. (<year>2004</year>). <source>Highlights of a GAO forum: The federal government's role in increasing financial literacy</source> <comment>(GAO-05-93SP)</comment>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gao.gov/cgi-bin/getrpt?GAO-05-93SP">http://www.gao.gov/cgi-bin/getrpt?GAO-05-93SP</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Warren</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tyagi</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>The two-income trap: Why middle class mothers and fathers are going broke</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1049731512453208">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhan</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>S. G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Financial knowledge of the low-income population: Effects of a financial education program</article-title>. <source>Journal of Sociology and Social Welfare</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>