<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcrx</journal-id>
<journal-title>Communication Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0093-6502</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3810</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0093650211420136</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0093650211420136</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Explaining the Process of Resistance to Persuasion</article-title>
<subtitle>A Politeness Theory-Based Approach</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>Mikayla</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0093650211420136">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Dragojevic</surname><given-names>Marko</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0093650211420136">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0093650211420136"><label>1</label>University of California, Davis, Davis, CA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0093650211420136">Mikayla Jenkins, Department of Communication, University of California, Davis, One Shields Ave., Davis CA 95616. Email: <email>mhughes@ucdavis.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>559</fpage>
<lpage>590</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Two experiments are conducted to test a politeness theory-derived process model of resistance to persuasion. Experiment 1 demonstrates that messages with more forceful language, compared to messages with less forceful language, produce an overall threat to face (i.e., negative and positive face). A second experiment was conducted to replicate the findings of Experiment 1 and to extend the process model by testing the hypothesis that controlling language produces a threat to face because of the meta-communicative content (i.e., unsubstantiated claim of relative power) implied by the language selected by the source. Overall, the data provide support for a politeness theory based understanding of resistance to persuasion.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>resistance</kwd>
<kwd>persuasion</kwd>
<kwd>face threat</kwd>
<kwd>relative power</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0093650211420136">
<title>Explaining the Process of Resistance to Persuasion: A Politeness Theory-Based Approach</title>
<p>On occasion, compelling and convincing arguments do not garner persuasion. One explanation for this finding is that recipients of the persuasive message are exhibiting resistance to persuasion. Resistance to persuasion may be observed as no change in attitude, a boomerang effect (i.e., attitude change in the direction opposite of what is desired by the message source), and derogation of the message source. Of the theories employed to explain the phenomenon of resistance to persuasion, recently the theory of psychological reactance appears to be the most frequently employed approach. One reason for this resurgence of reactance theory may be <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0093650211420136">Burgoon, Alvaro, Grandpre, and Voulodakis’ (2002)</xref> assertion that the theory has potential for a message feature centered approach to understanding resistance to persuasion.</p>
<p>The theory of psychological reactance posits that people have a fundamental need for autonomy and when their free behaviors are threatened, they experience an aversive emotional state called reactance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0093650211420136">Brehm, 1966</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0093650211420136">Brehm &amp; Brehm, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0093650211420136">Jones &amp; Brehm, 1970</xref>). Further, because persuasive messages, by definition, advocate that people hold a particular opinion, perform some behavior, or even refrain from performing some behavior, persuasive messages are an inherent threat to autonomy. To induce reactance and increase perceived threat to autonomy, reactance studies commonly use forceful language.</p>
<p>Politeness theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">Brown &amp; Levinson, 1987</xref>), however, can be employed to understanding resistance to persuasion, as well. Although politeness theory has been applied and even refined in the context of the production and reception of compliance gaining tactics, the theory has not been employed to predict why and when people may demonstrate resistance to persuasive messages. Like the theory of psychological reactance, politeness theory posits that people have a fundamental need for autonomy, or negative face. In addition, politeness theory suggests that people also have a fundamental need for approval and acceptance, or positive face. Working from this framework, we suggest that the language features employed to induce perceived threat to autonomy (i.e., negative face), such as forceful language, also impact the need to be liked and accepted (i.e., positive face). Given the potential for both positive and negative face threat in the persuasion context, the propositions posited by politeness theory appear to be germane to the task of understanding resistance antecedents and the underlying process associated with resistance to persuasive messages.</p>
<p>Moreover, one of the central claims of politeness theory is that language has meta-communicative value. Specifically, the language selected to encode a persuasive message is an expression of the source’s perception of the social relationship between source and receiver (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0093650211420136">Brown &amp; Levinson, 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0093650211420136">Goldsmith, 2008</xref>). Although people tend to encode their messages in a manner that maintains their face and the face of others, if message recipients believe that the language employed by the source implies a source-receiver relationship that is unjustified (i.e., the source does not have the right to command the recipient because the source does not have more power relative to the recipient), then the recipient will not only view the message as a threat to face but will respond to the attack on their face in a defensive manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0093650211420136">Brown &amp; Levinson, 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0093650211420136">Trees, Kerssen-Griep, &amp; Hess, 2009</xref>). Stated differently, a politeness theory approach to resistance to persuasion characterizes resistance to persuasion as a defensive reaction to an unjustified relational claim.</p>
<p>In order to test our politeness theory-derived process of resistance, we conducted two experiments. In the first experiment, we aim to test the applicability of a politeness theory based explanation of the process of resistance to persuasion by demonstrating that (a) forceful language produces an overall threat to face, not just an autonomy threat, and (b) face threatening messages prompt a defensive reaction in recipients. In the second experiment, we further investigate our claim that people resist persuasive messages that make unjustified meta-communicative claims by positing that implied relative power mediates the relationship between the degree of controlling language in a message and perceptions of overall face threat. We aim to test the applicability of a politeness theory-based explanation of the process of resistance to persuasion. This task will be accomplished by first pointing out the commonalities between reactance theory and politeness theory and discussing a frequently employed resistance inducing message feature, forceful language. A presentation of politeness theory and its application to persuasion will follow. Further, it will be argued that forceful language not only threatens autonomy (i.e., negative face) but also impacts the need to be accepted and approved (i.e., positive face). Next, a politeness theory-based process model of resistance to persuasion will be presented and subsequently tested.</p>
<sec id="section2-0093650211420136">
<title>Need for Autonomy and Forceful Language</title>
<p>Both the theory of psychological reactance and politeness theory acknowledge that people have a general need for autonomy and independence. People desire to be unencumbered and have the freedom to behave as they choose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0093650211420136">Brehm, 1966</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0093650211420136">Brehm &amp; Brehm, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">Brown &amp; Levinson, 1987</xref>). The theory of psychological reactance asserts that perceived threat to psychological freedom induces reactance. Reactance is a negative, aversive motivational state that people wish to avoid or reduce. In order to reduce reactance people can derogate the source of a persuasive message, advocate a stance that is contrary to the one advocated by the persuasive message, and/or perform behaviors that are contrary to the stance advocated by the persuasive message. Ultimately, a reactance based explanation of resistance to persuasion characterizes resistance as an outcome due to reactance arousal and subsequent reactance reduction.</p>
<p>Although any attempt to persuade can be viewed as a threat to psychological freedom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0093650211420136">Burgoon et al., 2002</xref>), reactance theory-based research has outlined message features that are more likely to induce resistance to persuasion. For instance, the language used in the presentation of a persuasive message can produce resistance to persuasion. Forceful language, a language feature frequently used by scholars employing reactance theory, can attenuate the persuasive impact of compelling arguments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0093650211420136">Dillard &amp; Shen, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0093650211420136">Quick &amp; Considine, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0093650211420136">Rains &amp; Turner, 2007</xref>). Forceful language contains two basic elements: controlling language and demeaning language. Controlling language uses imperatives, such as commands and orders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0093650211420136">Miller, Lane, Deatrick, Young, &amp; Potts, 2007</xref>). When controlling language is used, advocated behaviors are presented as something that must be done. However, messages that employ less controlling language emphasize recipients’ freedom to choose as they please and suggest people perform the advocated behavior by frequent use of qualifiers, such as “maybe” and “possibly.” Additionally, forceful language includes statements that demean anyone who does not agree with the advocated stance. Examples of statements that demean people who hold views contrary to the advocated stance include, “stop living in denial” and “no other conclusion makes sense.” In sum, forceful language presents the advocated stance as something that must be agreed with and demeans anyone who does not agree with the advocated stance. Notice that forceful language includes commands and orders, which are not only viewed as a threat to psychological freedom but also as impolite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0093650211420136">Dillard, Wilson, Tusing, &amp; Kinney, 1997</xref>). These perceptions of the degree of politeness may be more than just a byproduct of autonomy threatening language. It may be that the degree to which a persuasive message threatens recipients’ positive and negative face wants influences subsequent resistance behaviors, such as message and source derogations and postmessage attitudes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0093650211420136">
<title>Politeness Theory Applied to Resistance to Persuasion</title>
<p>Politeness theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0093650211420136">Brown &amp; Levinson, 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">1987</xref>) is a theory of language use that posits the systematic use of politeness strategies. Politeness theory asserts that, during a conversation, interactants are concerned with both the wants of self and their conversational partner(s) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0093650211420136">Brown &amp; Levinson, 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">1987</xref>). There are two types of wants, negative face wants and positive face wants. Negative face wants, just like reactance theory’s construct of need for autonomy, concern people’s desire to be autonomous agents who are free of constraints and obligations. Positive face wants pertain to the desire to be liked, respected, and viewed as competent. Messages that support positive and negative face wants are viewed as polite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0093650211420136">Dillard et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0093650211420136">Holtgraves, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0093650211420136">Lim &amp; Bowers, 1991</xref>). To the extent that a message threatens one or both aspects of face, the message will be viewed as impolite. Given that we are applying politeness theory to the process of resistance to persuasion, our application will focus only on potential face threats to message recipients due to exposure to a persuasive message.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0093650211420136">Brown and Levinson (1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">1987</xref>) outline speech acts that they claim are inherently face threatening. Although their discussion of face threatening acts (FTAs) focuses on how different acts primarily affect only one aspect of face, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">Brown and Levinson (1987</xref>; p. 67) concede that some FTAs threaten both negative and positive face. In general, all persuasive messages fall under the general speech act classification of directives, which are speech acts intended to produce some behavior or opinion in another. Even though Brown and Levinson assert that directives are an inherent threat to the desire to be autonomous, directives can produce a threat to recipients’ positive face (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0093650211420136">Craig, Tracy, &amp; Spisak, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0093650211420136">Penman, 1990</xref>). We maintain, however, that not all directives are equally threatening. For instance, all other things being equal, commanding, compared to suggesting, a relative to stop eating fast food is more face threatening. Further, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0093650211420136">Wilson, Aleman, and Leatham (1998)</xref> point out that compliance gaining messages contain additional speech acts beyond those considered to fall in the general class of directives. We contend that persuasive messages, like compliance gaining messages, may contain multiple speech acts, including acts beyond those that fall under the general class of directives, and some of these speech acts may threaten both the negative and positive face of message recipients. For example, revisiting the goal of ending a relative’s fast food habit, attempts to persuade the relative to not eat fast food may include expressions of disapproval of past behavior and challenges to the relative’s opinions concerning food, in addition to directives.</p>
<p>Although prior research has demonstrated that inclusion of forceful language in a persuasive message is viewed as a threat to the need for autonomy (i.e., negative face), resistance scholars have not acknowledged that the use of this language feature can make message recipients feel disrespected and that their competence to make their own decisions is being questioned (i.e., positive face threat). Consider the use of commands and instructions in a persuasive message, which is an element of forceful language. To be sure, use of these particular imperative forms in a persuasive message threatens the negative face of recipients but also has the potential to threaten positive face. When commands or instructions are used in a persuasive message, people may feel that (a) their judgment is being challenged and/or (b) their competence to make good decisions without the source’s intervention is being questioned. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0093650211420136">Brown and Levinson (1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">1987</xref>) assert that statements that challenge people’s competence or challenge their opinions or behaviors are among the acts that threaten positive face.</p>
<p>Demeaning language, another component of forceful language, criticizes message recipients for failing to adopt the advocated stance. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0093650211420136">Brown and Levinson (1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">1987</xref>) identify criticism as an act that threatens positive face. Moreover, implicit in the criticism is the assumption that all message recipients hold opinions and perform behaviors contrary to the advocated stance. Therefore, even if people may agree with the advocated stance of the persuasive message, they are being unjustly criticized and grouped with people who have opinions and behaviors contrary to their own, which threatens positive face. Accordingly forceful language, because of its use of demeaning statements, threatens positive face regardless of whether or not the persuasive message is contrary or consistent with recipients’ preexisting opinions and behaviors. Given that politeness theory predicts that the components that comprise forceful language (i.e., controlling and demeaning language) threaten both negative and positive face, we predict the following:</p>
<list id="list1-0093650211420136" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1</italic>: Recipients who read a message with more forceful language will perceive a greater overall threat to face (i.e., positive and negative) compared to those who read a message with less forceful language (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0093650211420136">Figure 1</xref>).</p></list-item>
</list>
<fig id="fig1-0093650211420136" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Predicted path model of politeness theory-based process of resistance to persuasion.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0093650211420136-fig1.tif"/></fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0093650211420136">
<title>Resistance to Persuasion as a Defensive Reaction to Face Threatening Language</title>
<p>As stated previously, all persuasive messages, by definition, include some form of directives, therefore persuasive messages have the potential to threaten the face of recipients. According to politeness theory, face maintenance is a cooperative endeavor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0093650211420136">Brown &amp; Levinson, 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">1987</xref>). This perspective is shared by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0093650211420136">Cupach and Metts (1994)</xref> who assert “mutual cooperation in the maintenance of face is so ordinary and pervasive that it is considered a taken-for-granted principle of interaction” (p. 4). Consequently, people assume that their face wants will be adequately addressed by those with whom they interact. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0093650211420136">Brown and Levinson (1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">1987</xref>) outline several strategies that people use to reduce face threat that may occur when performing acts. Usually, people will attempt to minimize the threat of an act by going off record (e.g., hinting) or using a politeness strategy such as positive politeness (e.g., in-group markers) and negative politeness (e.g, hedges).</p>
<p>Failure to include redressive language in a persuasive message commensurate to the weightiness (i.e., seriousness of the potential harm to face) of the particular message threatens the face of recipients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0093650211420136">Brown &amp; Levinson, 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">1987</xref>). Politeness theory, however, outlines the circumstances under which a potentially weighty FTA will not be viewed as a threat to face. For instance, when the source of the message has greater power relative to recipients (e.g., a doctor instructing a patient on methods of pain management) or the situation requires maximum efficiency (e.g., commanding another to move so they will escape bodily harm), recipients will experience diminished face threat in response to a FTA without redress. When the source is not perceived as having greater relative power or there is no apparent need for efficiency, however, FTAs without redress may be viewed as affront on the face of recipients and may lead recipients to derogate the source.</p>
<p>Additionally, politeness theory asserts that sources may deviate from the assumption of mutual cooperation of face maintenance as a method of attempting to claim relative power over recipients. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">Brown and Levinson (1987)</xref> point out that sources can imply that they have power over message recipients by conveying a FTA without redress (p. 228). In employing this strategy (i.e., using language to imply greater power relative to message recipients), however, the source risks retaliation from message recipients. This retaliation will be in the form of a defensive reaction toward the source.</p>
<p>Across interpersonal contexts, such as instructional feedback and workplace reproach, recipients of messages that include weighty FTAs without redress, compared to those who receive messages that redress potential face threat, have more negative feelings toward the source (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0093650211420136">Carson &amp; Cupach, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0093650211420136">Trees et al., 2009</xref>). For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0093650211420136">Trees et al. (2009)</xref> found that when students perceived their teacher’s feedback on a public speaking assignment as inattentive to their face wants (i.e., degree of redressive language was not commensurate to the potential threat of the FTA), they reported more negative perceptions of the teacher’s character and competence. It may be that negative evaluations of a source who conveys a weighty FTA without redress is because of recipients’ perception that the source is violating basic principles of interaction. Therefore, in the absence of an apparent need to be efficient or legitimate relative power over recipients, a message source who fails to attend to the face wants of recipients will be evaluated negatively, or derogated.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0093650211420136">1</xref></sup> This negative evaluation is the result of recipients’ defensive reaction to the source’s disregard for their face.</p>
<list id="list2-0093650211420136" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 2</italic>: Higher levels of perceived face threat will prompt greater source derogation (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0093650211420136">Figure 1</xref>).</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Consequently, source derogation impacts the extent to which message recipients derogate the message. When a source is derogated, their competence and intelligence are called into question; therefore, claims made by the source are likely to be derogated as well. Perceptions of the source can impact or even bias how the persuasive message is evaluated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0093650211420136">Bohner, Ruder, &amp; Erb, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0093650211420136">Sparks &amp; Areni, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0093650211420136">2008</xref>). For instance, in a study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0093650211420136">Bohner et al. (2002)</xref>, message recipients reported more negative cognitive responses when a low-quality persuasive message was attributed to an expert source, instead of a nonexpert source. Further, evidence for the claim that the type of language employed by the source impacts not only perceptions of the source but also perceptions of the message can be found in research investigating the influence of powerful language on the persuasiveness of sales presentations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0093650211420136">Sparks &amp; Areni, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0093650211420136">2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0093650211420136">Sparks and Areni (2008)</xref> found that the effect of language power on attitude was mediated by speaker-related thoughts, regardless of message recipients’ ability to process message details. In summarizing their findings, the authors point out, “language power still guides persuasion by distracting people from processing message content and then by biasing their assessment of relevant arguments and evidence to be consistent with their perception of the speaker’s style” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0093650211420136">Sparks &amp; Areni, 2008</xref>, p. 56). The findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0093650211420136">Sparks and Areni (2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0093650211420136">2008</xref>) suggest that message recipients consider speaker attributes as relevant arguments, which impact perceptions of the message.</p>
<p>Subsequently, these source-biased perceptions of the message impact attitude toward the stance advocated in the message. More specifically, when the claims made in the persuasive message are derogated, less positive attitudes toward the stance advocated in the message should occur. Ultimately, increased resistance to persuasion will occur as a consequence of source and message derogation brought about by the source’s use of face-threatening language. Therefore, we hypothesize the following (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0093650211420136">Figure 1</xref>):</p>
<list id="list3-0093650211420136" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 3</italic>: Increases in source derogation will lead to increases in message derogation.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 4</italic>: Increased message derogation will lead to less favorable attitudes toward the stance advocated in the message.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0093650211420136">
<title>The Hypothesized Model</title>
<p>People resist persuasive messages that employ forceful language because it threatens their face wants. For the current study, we will vary forceful language. Based on our application of politeness theory to resistance to persuasion, we have posited a model of resistance to persuasion (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0093650211420136">Figure 1</xref>). Further, our model is constrained to persuasive attempts in which there is no information available to recipients that would lead them to infer (a) the source has efficiency concerns, (b) the potential imposition of the advocated behavior is minor, (c) the source is higher in relative power, or (d) the source is low in social distance. Although at first glance, these constraints appear very limiting, many empirical tests of resistance to persuasion that employ reactance theory meet all four constraints (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0093650211420136">Miller et al., 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>The hypothesized model was tested by documenting responses to a health communication pamphlet advocating for regular flossing of one’s teeth. Participants received one of two versions of the pamphlet, more forceful language, and less forceful language. The pamphlets were modified versions of the pamphlets used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0093650211420136">Dillard and Shen (2005)</xref>. The goal of this study was to discern if resistance to the flossing pamphlet can be explained by politeness theory. We predict that people who receive a pamphlet with forceful language, compared to those who receive a pamphlet without forceful language, will experience greater face threat. Subsequently, as face threat increases, derogation of the source will increase. Further, increases in derogations of the pamphlet source will be associated with increased derogation of the pamphlet itself. Finally, derogation of pamphlet content will impact postmessage attitudes such that increases in message derogation will lead to more negative attitudes toward the advocated behavior.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0093650211420136" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section7-0093650211420136">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>Sixty-two students enrolled in communication courses at a West Coast University served as participants.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0093650211420136">2</xref></sup> One participant was judged as an outlier on the attitude variable and was subsequently excluded from analysis, resulting in a sample size of 61. The sample consisted of 35 females and 26 males, of whom 1 was a freshman, 9 were sophomores, 21 juniors, 26 seniors, and 4 were fifth-year seniors. The mean age was 20.87 (<italic>SD</italic> = 2.99).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0093650211420136">
<title>Design and Procedures</title>
<p>The study was an experimental comparison group design with some participants receiving a persuasive message that includes language that threatens the psychological freedom of recipients (<italic>n</italic> = 31) and some participants receiving a persuasive message with language that is low in psychological threat (<italic>n</italic> = 30). Participants were randomly assigned to conditions (i.e., more forceful language or less forceful language. In order to achieve random assignment, a condition order sheet was created before data collection, using a random number generator, and the researchers who administered the study materials used the condition order sheet to determine which message a participant would receive. The persuasive messages were a shortened version of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0093650211420136">Dillard and Shen’s (2005)</xref> pamphlets advocating people floss their teeth regularly. After reading the pamphlet, participants completed a questionnaire that included measures of face threat, message and source derogations, and attitude toward regular flossing.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0093650211420136">
<title>Messages</title>
<p>Persuasive messages were presented in the form of a pamphlet supporting the behavior of frequent flossing of one’s teeth. There were two versions of the pamphlet, one with more forceful language and one with less forceful language. Forceful language includes commands and instructions in the presentation of the message arguments and advocated stance. For the forceful language pamphlet, flossing is presented as something people must do. Additionally, the forceful language pamphlet includes demeaning language such as “it’s just plain stupid not to floss every day of your life.” The pamphlet without forceful language, however, presents flossing as a suggestion and has no demeaning language. The pamphlets were modified versions of the pamphlets used in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0093650211420136">Dillard and Shen (2005)</xref>. More specifically, information and argumentation concerning the impact of failing to floss on the likelihood of contracting pneumonia was omitted from both messages in order to reduce the length of the pamphlet. The last page of both pamphlets recommended that the reader floss regularly, see <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-0093650211420136">Appendix A</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0093650211420136">
<title>Measures</title>
<p>Confirmatory factor analyses were performed to assess the validity of all the measures. Confirmatory factor analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0093650211420136">Hunter &amp; Gerbing, 1982</xref>) consist of internal consistency and parallelism tests. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0093650211420136">Hunter and Hamilton’s (1992)</xref> CFA software was used to test the measurement model. The measurement model treated overall face threat, source derogation, message derogation, and attitude as different factors. Further, because (a) positive and negative face were highly correlated and (b) we have hypothesized that they correlate in similar ways with the other variables, overall face threat was tested for second order unidimensionality by treating each type of face threat as an alternate indicator of overall face threat. All items met internal consistency and parallelism standards and were therefore retained.</p>
<sec id="section11-0093650211420136">
<title>Face threat</title>
<p>The extent to which participants perceived the message as face threatening was measured by 17 Likert-type items, seven items measuring positive face and 10 measuring negative face. Four of the negative face items were pulled from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0093650211420136">Dillard and Shen’s (2005)</xref> threat to psychological freedom induction check. Each item had five response options ranging from strongly disagree to strongly agree. All of the face threat indicators are presented in <xref ref-type="app" rid="app2-0093650211420136">Appendix B</xref>. Higher scores indicate higher perceptions of face threat. The positive face threat items were averaged to form an index of positive face threat and the negative face threat items were averaged to form an index of negative face threat. The positive and negative face indexes were highly correlated, <italic>r</italic>(61) = .77, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. Both the negative and positive face threat indexes were converted to <italic>z</italic>-scores and subsequently summed to form an overall index of face threat. The scale, composed of the two <italic>z</italic>-scores indicators, had a reliability of α = .87.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0093650211420136">
<title>Source derogation</title>
<p>Perceptions of the message source were measured by seven semantic differential items anchored by bipolar adjectives: stupid/smart, unknowledgeable/knowledgeable, uninformed/informed, unintelligent/intelligent, unqualified/qualified, unreliable/reliable, and inexpert/expert. The category ratings were scored from 1 to 7. Higher scores indicate more negative perceptions of the message source. The items were averaged to form an index with a mean of 2.25 (<italic>SD</italic> = .90, α = .94).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0093650211420136">
<title>Message derogation</title>
<p>Perceptions of the message were measured by seven semantic differential items anchored by bipolar adjectives: unreasonable/reasonable, irrational/rational, illogical/logical, not plausible/plausible, unsound/sound, senseless/sensible, and unjustified/justified. The category ratings were scored from 1 to 7. Higher scores indicate more negative perceptions of the message. The items were averaged to form an index of message derogation (<italic>M</italic> = 2.06, <italic>SD</italic> = .85, α = .86).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0093650211420136">
<title>Attitude</title>
<p>Attitude toward regular flossing was measured by seven semantic differential items anchored by bipolar adjectives: bad/good, foolish/wise, unfavorable/favorable, negative/positive, undesirable/desirable, detrimental/beneficial, and unnecessary/necessary. The category ratings were scored from 1 to 7. Higher scores indicate more positive attitudes toward regular flossing. The seven items were averaged to form an index of attitude (<italic>M</italic> = 6.42, <italic>SD</italic> = .59, α = .86).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0093650211420136" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section16-0093650211420136">
<title>Main Effects</title>
<p>Amount of forceful language in the persuasive message produced several main effects. Forceful language significantly impacted the degree of face threat, <italic>t</italic>(59) = 4.61, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, <italic>r</italic> = .51, such that participants who received the persuasive message with more forceful language experienced greater face threat (<italic>M</italic> = .98, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.78) than participants who received the message with less forceful language (<italic>M</italic> = −.94, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.44). Additionally, forceful language produced a main effect for source derogation, <italic>t</italic>(59) = 2.87, <italic>p</italic> = .006, <italic>r</italic> = .35, and a main effect for message derogation, <italic>t</italic>(59) = 3.39, <italic>p</italic> = .001, <italic>r</italic> = .40. Specifically, participants who received the more forceful language persuasive message reported greater source derogation (<italic>M</italic> = 2.58, <italic>SD</italic> = .88) than participants who received the persuasive message with less forceful language (<italic>M</italic> = 2.03, <italic>SD</italic> = .93). In addition, participants who received the more forceful language message reported more message derogation (<italic>M</italic> = 2.40, <italic>SD</italic> = .92) than participants who received the persuasive message with less forceful language (<italic>M</italic> = 1.82, <italic>SD</italic> = .82). There was no statistically significant difference in post message attitudes based on the degree of forceful language in the message, <italic>t</italic>(59) = 1.09, <italic>ns.</italic> The mean post message attitude for participants who received the more forceful language persuasive message was 6.38 (<italic>SD</italic> = .96) and 6.34 (<italic>SD</italic> = .51) for the less forceful language persuasive message. Although the forceful language induction did not demonstrate a significant effect on postmessage attitudes toward flossing, because we are testing the total effect of forceful language on attitude, it is reasonable to continue to test our hypothesized model. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0093650211420136">Hayes (2009)</xref> points out that “a total effect is the sum of many different paths of influence, direct and indirect” (p. 414), therefore a longer causal chain with multiple mediators may demonstrate a nonsignificant total effect.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0093650211420136">
<title>Test of the Hypothesized Model</title>
<p>The hypothesized model was tested with path analysis. Path analysis tests whether the predicted model fits the pattern of the data as evidenced by the residuals between predicted and observed correlations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0093650211420136">Hunter &amp; Gerbing, 1982</xref>). Path analysis uses the same ordinary least squares estimates found in typical regression analyses. Residuals that are greater than what would be expected from sampling error indicate potential problems with individual links in the model (i.e., local error). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0093650211420136">Hunter and Hamilton’s (1995)</xref> PATH was used to estimate and test the indirect paths of the model. Further, the overall test of goodness of fit of the model can be evaluated with a chi-square statistic; a statistically significant chi-square statistic would indicate poor model fit. Two additional indicators of overall model fit were used as well, Root Mean Squared Error of Approximation (RMSEA) and Comparative Fit Index (CFI). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0093650211420136">Hu and Bentler (1999)</xref> advise that good overall fit is indicated by RMSEA values of .06 or less and CFI values greater than .95.</p>
<p>Before testing the model, our examination of scatterplots indicated that the variables were normally distributed. The data were consistent with the hypothesized causal model presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0093650211420136">Figure 2</xref>. The model parameters were estimated using the correlations presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0093650211420136">Table 1</xref>. All the path coefficients are substantial and in the predicted direction, therefore the data were consistent with all of the individual hypotheses. Consistent with Hypothesis 1, forceful language affected perceived face threat, β = .56, <italic>SE</italic> = .10, indicating that messages with forceful language produced greater perceived face threat than messages without forceful language. Consequently, as predicted by Hypothesis 2, perceived face threat impacted source derogation, β = .39, <italic>SE</italic> = .12, such that increases in perceived face threat led to increased source derogation. In turn, source derogation impacted message derogation such that increases in source derogation produced a corresponding increase in message derogation (Hypothesis 3: β = .68, <italic>SE</italic> = .10). Finally, message derogation impacted attitude such that increases in message derogation led to more negative attitudes (Hypothesis 4: β = −.77, <italic>SE</italic> = .11). Additionally, a test of the model as a whole indicated that it fit well with the data. Residuals were all explainable by sampling error and the overall test of the model’s residuals was not statistically significant, χ<italic><sup>2</sup></italic> (6) = 5.63, <italic>p</italic> = .466; RMSEA = .00; CFI = 1.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0093650211420136" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Obtained path model of politeness theory based process of resistance to persuasion. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0093650211420136-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-0093650211420136" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Correlations Associated With the Path Analysis for Experiment 1 (<italic>N</italic> = 61).</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0093650211420136" xlink:href="10.1177_0093650211420136-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">1</th>
<th align="center">2</th>
<th align="center">3</th>
<th align="center">4</th>
<th align="center">5</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1. Forceful Language</td>
<td/>
<td>.56</td>
<td>.36</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>−.16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2. Face threat</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td/>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>−.39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3. Source derogation</td>
<td>.35</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td/>
<td>.64</td>
<td>−.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4. Message derogation</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td/>
<td>−.72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5. Attitude</td>
<td>−.14</td>
<td>−.31</td>
<td>−.29</td>
<td>−.58</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0093650211420136">
<p>Note. Correlations corrected for attenuation due to measurement error are in the upper triangle.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0093650211420136">
<title>Test of an Alternative Model</title>
<p>Our hypothesized model reflects our argument that forceful language produces an overall face threat, which in turn prompts a defensive response in message recipients. Further, we assert, based on claims derived from politeness theory, that source derogation is the most proximal outcome of overall face threat. Although degree of forceful language encoded in a message impacts recipients’ perception of the source, forceful language also impacts perceptions of the message as well. We tested an alternative model (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0093650211420136">Figure 3</xref>) that posits that message derogation is the most proximal outcome of face threat and that message derogation, in turn, impacts source derogation, which ultimately impacts attitude.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0093650211420136" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Alternative path model.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0093650211420136-fig3.tif"/></fig>
<p>The alternative causal model does not fit the data as well as our hypothesized model. Although all the path coefficients are substantial and in the predicted direction, inspection of the residual error between the predicted and obtained indirect path between message derogation and attitude was too large to be attributable to sampling error alone, residual = −.5, <italic>p</italic> = .03. Even though the overall fit indices indicate adequate fit χ<sup>2</sup> (6) = 7.97, <italic>p</italic> = .24; RMSEA = .07; CFI = 1, based on the significant residual for the indirect path for message derogation and attitude, we conclude the hypothesized model fits the data better than the alternative model.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0093650211420136" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The results of the first experiment provide tentative empirical support for the usefulness of a politeness theory based explanation of the process of resistance to persuasion. It was argued that language features that threaten autonomy also threaten message recipients’ desire to be viewed as competent decision makers, which produces an overall perception of face threat. The results of the study indicate that forceful language produces positive and negative face threat, not just a threat to autonomy. Face threat, in turn, demonstrated a direct positive relationship with source derogation. Subsequently, source derogation impacted message derogation such that increases in source derogation led to increases in message derogation. Ultimately, message derogation was negatively related with postmessage attitude. Specifically, greater derogation of the message led to more negative attitudes toward the issue advocated in the message.</p>
<p>One potential issue with the findings of the first experiment is that forceful language confounds demeaning and controlling language. Due to this confound, we cannot discern whether the observed resistance process was a function of controlling language, demeaning language, or some interaction between the two language types. In order to address this potential confound, for the second experiment, we focused on the impact of controlling language only. Further, although we were able to demonstrate that the degree to which message recipients view the language used by the message source as face threatening ultimately impacts the persuasiveness of the message, there is nothing in the model that allows for an empirical test why these language features are face threatening.</p>
<p>It may be that face threatening language in a persuasive message prompts resistance to persuasion because controlling language conveys meta-communicative content. In order to provide further support for the usefulness of a politeness theory-based approach to the process of resistance to persuasion, it is necessary to explicate (a) the nature of the meta-communicative aspect of controlling language and (b) why message recipients experience face threat and demonstrate resistance due to the meta-communicative value of this particular language feature.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0093650211420136">
<title>Experiment 2</title>
<p>A second experiment was conducted to replicate and extend the results of Experiment 1. More specifically, the purpose of this second experiment was to (a) observe if findings of the first experiment can be generalized to another context (i.e., topic and cover story for message presentation) and (b) test the explanation that resistance to a compelling persuasive message is a function of the recipients’ rejection of the source’s claim to relative power, which is implied by the degree of face threatening language in the message.</p>
<p>Several modifications to the procedure used in Experiment 1 were made. In Experiment 2, participants read an Op-Ed (Opinion Editorial) piece advocating people eat organic foods to avoid exposure to pesticides. This difference in stimulus materials constitutes not only a change in the message topic but also a change in the cover story provided to participants. Health-oriented pamphlets, like the one used in Experiment 1, are more likely to be viewed as a vehicle for presenting facts and recommendations rather than inflexible opinions and commands. However, it is plausible for Op-Ed pieces to contain obstinate opinions on some topic. By using an Op-Ed piece, we were able to include more controlling language than with a pamphlet, because an abundance of commands in a pamphlet would most likely sacrifice the realism of the stimulus materials.</p>
<sec id="section21-0093650211420136">
<title>Controlling Language Use as a Means to Claim Relative Power</title>
<p>To better elucidate a politeness theory-based conception of the process of resistance to persuasion, it would be useful to discern why messages employing face-threatening language impact perceptions of the source and message. Language features, such as controlling language, have meta-communicative value. All communication has a content and meta-communicative aspect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0093650211420136">Watzlawick, Beavin, &amp; Jackson, 1967</xref>). The content aspect of a message corresponds to what is being conveyed. The meta-communicative aspect, however, pertains to how it is conveyed. Even when content is held somewhat constant, a change in how that content is conveyed can produce drastic changes in the meta-communicative aspect of a message.</p>
<p>Controlling language conveys a status differential between the source and receiver of a message. Studies establishing the relationship between language use and social interaction have demonstrated that when people read vignettes of two person conversations, they judge sources who use direct requests as higher status than sources who employ indirect requests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0093650211420136">Holtgraves, 1986</xref>, Study 2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0093650211420136">Holtgraves &amp; Yang, 1990</xref>, Study 3). Stated differently, highly face-threatening language (i.e., direct requests) is associated with higher status on the part of the source than less face-threatening language (i.e., indirect requests). Because these studies employ third-party judgments of two person conversations, the findings do not speak to how recipients of a message would interpret a source’s use of face threatening language when there is no information regarding the relative power between sender and hearer. Due to the assumed cooperative nature of conversation, unless presented with contextual features to the contrary, third-party judges will view a vignette in which a sender uses direct language in addressing a receiver as a situation in which the sender possesses greater power relative to the receiver.</p>
<p>When in the role of message recipient, however, people can choose to accept or reject the source’s apparent claim that they have greater power, relative to recipients. Although there is empirical evidence supporting the notion that language conveys information regarding the status of the speaker status relative to the hearer, there is a paucity of studies that investigate how a speaker is evaluated when the hearers reject the relative power inferred by the language of the message. Because people typically attempt to minimize potential face threats to message recipients, recipients may attribute a source’s blatant use of face threatening language to (a) the source’s need to be efficient, (b) the source’s belief that potential threat to recipients is minor, (c) the source’s perception that there is little social distance between self and recipients, or (d) the source’s perception that the recipients are lower in relative power (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0093650211420136">Brown &amp; Levinson, 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">1987</xref>). If there is nothing in the context that suggests the source has reason to abandon face concerns in favor of efficiency, the advocated behavior is more than a minor imposition on the recipients’ wants, or that the social distance between source and recipients is small, then recipients will view the source’s use of controlling language as an attempt to claim relative power over message recipients. Thus,</p>
<list id="list4-0093650211420136" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1</italic>: Recipients of the message with more controlling language will perceive the language as greater in implied relative power than recipients who read the message with less controlling language (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0093650211420136">Figure 4</xref>).</p></list-item>
</list>
<fig id="fig4-0093650211420136" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Path model of politeness theory based process of resistance to persuasion.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0093650211420136-fig4.tif"/></fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0093650211420136">
<title>Relative Power</title>
<p>Recipients can opt to reject or accept the source’s claim of relative power. Relative power is an asymmetric relationship between a source and recipients such that the source has material control and/or metaphysical control over the actions of the recipients. Material control and metaphysical control are conceptually similar to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0093650211420136">French and Raven’s (1959)</xref> notions of coercive and legitimate power. According to French and Raven, the process of social influence varies depending on the type of social power exerted by the source. In the case of coercive power, a source is influential because receivers believe lack of compliance will be met with punishment. Because our application of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0093650211420136">Brown and Levinson (1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">1987</xref>) is concerned with resistance to persuasion, instead of compliance, our discussion of relative power will focus on the metaphysical aspect of their conceptualization (i.e., legitimate power).</p>
<p>When the source has legitimate power, recipients comply because they believe the source has a right to influence them and the recipients feel obligated to accept the sender’s influence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0093650211420136">French &amp; Raven, 1959</xref>). The implication of French and Raven’s conceptualization is that a successful attempt at exercising legitimate power requires all involved parties, the source and recipients, to believe the source’s claim of right to influence is valid. A similar view is held by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">Brown and Levinson (1987)</xref> who assert that no person can claim relative power over another without their consent. Stated differently, an asymmetric power relationship cannot exist without the acquiescence of the person who is in the purportedly subordinate position. To the degree that a source has relative power over receivers, the source can oblige recipients face even when such obligations threaten recipients’ face or plans for future behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">Brown &amp; Levinson, 1987</xref>).</p>
<p>Although relative power is often conflated with role sets that are defined by an inherent asymmetry in power (e.g., boss-employee, parent-child, doctor-patient), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0093650211420136">Brown and Levinson (1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">1987</xref>) assert that relative power cannot be simply thought of as roles. Ultimately, the relative power between two people is not only a function of roles but also the context in which the social influence attempt takes place. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0093650211420136">French and Raven (1959)</xref> delineate one contextual feature by pointing out that for each role, legitimate power is typically confined to a specific range of behaviors or topics. For instance, doctors have legitimate power over their patients for behaviors related to maintaining health or curing ailments; lawyers have legitimate power over their clients for matters related to laws and litigation; and priests have legitimate power over their congregation for issues concerning religion and morality. Issues of morality and religion, however, are outside of the range of influence associated with the role of doctor. Therefore, if a doctor attempts to influence a patient on an issue related to religion and morality, the patient will be less likely to view the doctor as possessing legitimate power. Further, when a source attempts to use legitimate power outside of the range of behaviors or topics, not only is the influence attempt less successful but also recipients experience more negative feelings toward the source. So the patient of the doctor providing advice on religion and morality will not only reject the doctor’s advice but will have increased negative feelings for the doctor as well. Ultimately, when a source makes a claim of relative power over the source, regardless of whether this claim is made explicitly through message content or meta-communicative features of the message, the recipients must choose to accept the claim for the attempt at power to be successful.</p>
<p>If the behavior advocated by the persuasive message is not minor or there is no apparent justification for efficiency concerns on the part of the source, message recipients will view the use of controlling language in the persuasive message as a bid for power, on the part of the source. In the absence of any information that verifies that the source has legitimate power on the topic of the persuasive message or is socially close to recipients, recipients will resist the message arguments. Recipients resist the message because, although the message is compelling, accepting the stance of the message implies accepting the power bid made by the source. Resistance to the message is a way for recipients to reject the unsubstantiated claim of relative power implied by the language used by the source. Ultimately, the reason controlling language is face threatening is because of the unsubstantiated claim of relative power implied by the language selected by the source. Therefore, we predict as follows:</p>
<list id="list5-0093650211420136" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 2</italic>: Increases in perceived implied relative power will lead to increases in perceived face threat (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0093650211420136">Figure 4</xref>).</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0093650211420136">
<title>The Hypothesized Model</title>
<p>In order to test the claim that controlling language in a persuasive message is resisted because recipients perceive that the source’s language reflects an unsubstantiated relative power bid, the model tested in Experiment 1 was modified to include receivers’ perception of relative power implied by the source’s language (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0093650211420136">Figure 4</xref>). In addition to including implied relative power, behavioral intention was added to the model. There is ample research demonstrating that attitudes have a positive relationship with behavioral intentions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0093650211420136">Godin &amp; Kok, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0093650211420136">Sheeran &amp; Taylor, 1999</xref>). Further, behavioral intention is an important construct in the domain of persuasion because it is a strong predictor of volitional behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0093650211420136">Kim &amp; Hunter, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0093650211420136">Sheppard, Hartwick, &amp; Warshaw, 1988</xref>). Consequently, we predict the following:</p>
<list id="list6-0093650211420136" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 3</italic>: More positive attitudes toward the message stance will lead to increased intention to perform the behavior advocated in the message (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0093650211420136">Figure 4</xref>).</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Experiment 2 served as an extension and replication of the politeness theory derived model of resistance tested in the first experiment. Participants’ responses to an Op-Ed piece advocating that people eat organic foods to avoid exposure to pesticides were employed to test the model. We expect that controlling language will impact implied relative power. More specifically, the Op-Ed piece with more controlling language will demonstrate higher implied relative power than the Op-Ed piece with less controlling language. Increases in implied relative power will be associated with increased perceived face threat. Increased perceived face threat, in turn, will produce increases in derogation of the source of the Op-Ed piece. Consequently, source derogation will impact message derogation such that as derogation of the source increases, so does derogation of the message. Further, increases in message derogation will prompt more negative attitudes toward the stance advocated in the Op-Ed piece. Ultimately, attitudes toward eating organic to avoid pesticides will be positively related to behavioral intentions to eat organic foods.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0093650211420136" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section25-0093650211420136">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>Study participants were 76 students enrolled in communication courses at a West Coast University. Eighty percent of the sample was female and the mean age was 21.25 (<italic>SD</italic> = 2.24). Twelve were sophomores, 22 juniors, 38 seniors, and 4 were fifth-year seniors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-0093650211420136">
<title>Design and Procedures</title>
<p>The study was an experimental comparison group design. All participants, regardless of condition, received an opinion editorial piece (Op-Ed) advocating that people eat organic foods in order to reduce their exposure to pesticides. The Op-Ed piece served as the persuasive message. Some of the participants read an Op-Ed piece that employed highly controlling language (<italic>n</italic> = 37) and the remaining participants read an Op-Ed piece that used less controlling language (<italic>n</italic> = 39). Both versions of the persuasive message are presented in <xref ref-type="app" rid="app3-0093650211420136">Appendix C</xref>. Once participants finished reading the Op-Ed piece, they received a questionnaire that included measures of face threat, relative power implied by source’s language, message and source derogation, attitude toward eating organic to avoid pesticides, and intention to eat organic.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-0093650211420136">
<title>Messages</title>
<p>All persuasive messages were presented in the form of an Op-Ed piece titled, “Organic food for thought: More than an ‘Eco-Friendly’ trend.” Before reading the Op-Ed piece, all participants read an introductory statement, printed on a separate page, that indicated that the Op-Ed piece had appeared either in a national newspaper or on a website such as Politico, Yahoo!News, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Salon.com">Salon.com</ext-link>, or HuffingtonPost. The introductory statement was provided to participants to increase the likelihood that all participants would view the persuasive message they received as an Op-Ed piece. The Op-Ed piece was formatted so that it appeared to have been downloaded and printed from a website. Specifically, the title of the Op-Ed and the date and time the Op-Ed piece was apparently downloaded from the Internet appeared in eight-point font as a header. Also, the URL of the website from which the Op-Ed was supposedly downloaded appeared in eight-point font as a footer. Any content that identified the apparent author (i.e., the byline) or website (i.e., the host name of the URL) on which the Op-Ed piece appeared was crossed out with a black marker.</p>
<p>The version of the Op-Ed piece that contained less controlling language (i.e., suggestions instead of commands) was pilot tested (<italic>N</italic> = 52) for persuasiveness. In the pilot, participants who received the Op-Ed piece reported more positive attitudes toward eating organic to reduce pesticides (<italic>M</italic> = 5.53, <italic>SD</italic> = .92) compared to participants that did not receive the Op-Ed piece (<italic>M</italic> = 4.95, <italic>SD</italic> = .80), <italic>t</italic>(50) = 2.41, <italic>p</italic> = .02, <italic>r</italic> = .32.</p>
<sec id="section28-0093650211420136">
<title>Controlling language</title>
<p>Although both persuasive messages advocated eating organic food, the message with more controlling language commanded and ordered readers to perform the advocated behaviors. However, the message with less controlling language suggested readers perform the advocated behavior. Specifically, the highly controlling language message asserted that eating organic was something readers “have to do” or “must do.” Conversely, the less controlling message presented eating organic as something readers “may want to do” or “should try.” The length of the messages, not including title, byline, and header and footer, was 592 words for the more controlling language message and 602 for the less controlling language message.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-0093650211420136">
<title>Measures</title>
<p>Confirmatory factor analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0093650211420136">Hunter &amp; Gerbing, 1982</xref>) were performed to assess the validity of all the measures. We tested a measurement model that handled implied relative power, overall face threat, source derogation, message derogation, attitude, and intent as different factors. Consistent with the measurement model we employed for Experiment 1, overall face threat was tested for second order unidimensionality by treating each type of face as an alternate indicator of overall face. Items that failed to meet internal consistency and parallelism tests were discarded. Details regarding deletion of specific items are detailed for each measure.</p>
<sec id="section30-0093650211420136">
<title>Implied relative power</title>
<p>Perceptions of the degree of relative power implied by the language of the source was measured by five Likert-type items (see <xref ref-type="app" rid="app2-0093650211420136">Appendix B</xref>), each with five response options ranging from strongly disagree to strongly agree. Higher scores correspond to the perception that the language used by the source reflected the source’s belief of greater power relative to message recipients. The items were averaged to form an index of implied relative power with a mean of 3.23 (<italic>SD</italic> = .90, α = .86).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section31-0093650211420136">
<title>Face threat</title>
<p>The extent to which participants perceived the message as face threatening was measured by 20 Likert-type items, 10 measuring positive face and 10 measuring negative face. The positive and negative face indexes were positively correlated, <italic>r</italic>(76) = .74, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. The overall index of face threat, which was created by averaging all 20 items,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0093650211420136">3</xref></sup> had a reliability of .92 (<italic>M</italic> = 3.07, <italic>SD</italic> = .61).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section32-0093650211420136">
<title>Source and message derogation</title>
<p>Perceptions of the source and the message were measured with the same items from Experiment 1. Six of the seven source derogation items were retained and were subsequently averaged to form an index with a mean of 3.49 (<italic>SD</italic> = .92, α = .84). The seven-message derogation items were averaged to form index with a mean of 3.28 (<italic>SD</italic> = 1.06, α = .87).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section33-0093650211420136">
<title>Attitude</title>
<p>Attitude toward eating organic food to avoid pesticides was measured by seven semantic differential items anchored by bipolar adjectives: bad/good, foolish/wise, unfavorable/favorable, negative/positive, undesirable/desirable, dangerous/safe, and unnecessary/necessary. The category ratings were scored from 1 to 7. Higher scores indicate more positive attitudes. Six of the seven items were retained and averaged to form an index of attitude with a reliability of .87 (<italic>M</italic> = 5.21, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.03).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section34-0093650211420136">
<title>Intent</title>
<p>Intent to eat organic to avoid pesticides was measured by four Likert-type items, each with five response options ranging from strongly disagree to strongly agree. The items are listed in <xref ref-type="app" rid="app2-0093650211420136">Appendix B</xref>. Higher scores correspond to greater intent. All four items were averaged to form an index of behavioral intent with a reliability of .91 (<italic>M</italic> = 2.58, <italic>SD</italic> = .82).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section35-0093650211420136" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section36-0093650211420136">
<title>Main Effects</title>
<p>The amount of controlling language in the persuasive message produced several main effects. More specifically, controlling language affected implied relative power such that participants who received the message with more controlling language perceived higher implied relative power in the language selected by the message source (<italic>M</italic> = 3.59, <italic>SD</italic> = .75) compared to those who read the message with less controlling language (<italic>M</italic> = 2.89, <italic>SD</italic> = .91), <italic>t</italic>(74) = 3.65, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, <italic>r</italic> = .39. Also, participants who received the message with more controlling language reported a greater threat to face (<italic>M</italic> = 3.36, <italic>SD</italic> = .51) than participants who received the message with less controlling language (<italic>M</italic> = 2.80, <italic>SD</italic> = .58), <italic>t</italic>(74) = 4.46, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, <italic>r</italic> = .46. Further, degree of controlling language impacted message derogation such that derogation was greater for the message with more controlling language (<italic>M</italic> = 3.53, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.06) than for the message with less controlling language (<italic>M</italic> = 3.04, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.02), <italic>t</italic>(74) = 2.04, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05, <italic>r</italic> = .30. The degree of controlling language in the message, however, did not produce statistically significant differences in message derogation, <italic>t</italic>(74) = 1.40, <italic>ns.</italic> Participants who received the more controlling language message reported a mean message derogation of 3.64 (<italic>SD</italic> = .85) and those who received a less controlling message reported a mean message derogation of 3.35 (<italic>SD</italic> = .97). Also, degree of controlling language did not generate statistically significant differences in attitude, <italic>t</italic>(74) = 1.52, <italic>ns</italic>, or intention, <italic>t</italic>(74) = 1.38, <italic>ns.</italic> More controlling language message condition participants reported a mean attitude of 5.03 (<italic>SD</italic> = .93) and mean intention of 2.46 (<italic>SD</italic> = .83) and those who received a less controlling message reported a mean attitude of 5.38 (<italic>SD</italic> = 1.11) and mean intention of 2.71 (<italic>SD</italic> = .83). As with Experiment l, even though the controlling language induction did not demonstrate a significant effect on intentions to eat organic foods, it is reasonable to continue to test our hypothesized model. Because significant indirect effects are possible in the absence of a significant total effect, a nonsignificant total effect should not preclude a test of indirect effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0093650211420136">Hayes, 2009</xref>, p. 414).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section37-0093650211420136">
<title>Test of the Hypothesized Model</title>
<p>Our examination of scatterplots indicated that the variables were normally distributed. The data were consistent with the hypothesized causal model presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0093650211420136">Figure 5</xref>. The correlations used to estimate the model parameters appear in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0093650211420136">Table 2</xref>. All the path coefficients are substantial and in the predicted direction, therefore, the data were consistent with all of the individual hypotheses. As predicted in Hypothesis 1, controlling language affected implied power, β = .42, <italic>SE</italic> = .11, indicating messages with more controlling language were viewed as implying that the source had greater relative power than recipients than the message with less controlling language. Consequently, implied relative power impacted face threat such that increases in implied relative power led to increased face threat (Hypothesis 2: β = .72, <italic>SE</italic> = .08). In turn, face threat impacted source derogation, β = .60, <italic>SE</italic> = .09, such that increases in face threat produced a corresponding increase in source derogation. Further, increases in source derogation led to increases in message derogation, β = .88, <italic>SE</italic> = .06. Next, message derogation impacted attitude, β = −.71, <italic>SE</italic> = .08, such that increases in message derogation led to more negative attitudes. Finally, consistent with Hypothesis 3, attitude was positively related to behavioral intentions, β = .58, <italic>SE</italic> = .09. The model as a whole fit well with the data. Residuals were all explainable by sampling error and the overall test of the model’s residuals was not statistically significant, χ<italic><sup>2</sup></italic> (15) = 8.93, <italic>p</italic> = .881; <italic>RMSEA</italic> = .00; CFI = 1.</p>
<fig id="fig5-0093650211420136" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Obtained path model of politeness theory based process of resistance to persuasion. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0093650211420136-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table2-0093650211420136" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Correlations Associated With the Path Analysis for Experiment 2 (<italic>N</italic> = 76).</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0093650211420136" xlink:href="10.1177_0093650211420136-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">1</th>
<th align="center">2</th>
<th align="center">3</th>
<th align="center">4</th>
<th align="center">5</th>
<th align="center">6</th>
<th align="center">7</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1.Controlling language</td>
<td/>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.17</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td>−.18</td>
<td>−.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2. Implied relative power</td>
<td>.39</td>
<td/>
<td>.72</td>
<td>.31</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3. Face threat</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.64</td>
<td/>
<td>.60</td>
<td>.72</td>
<td>−.42</td>
<td>−.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4. Source derogation</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>.26</td>
<td>.53</td>
<td/>
<td>.88</td>
<td>−.42</td>
<td>−.32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5. Message derogation</td>
<td>.23</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>.64</td>
<td>.75</td>
<td/>
<td>−.71</td>
<td>−.42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6. Attitude</td>
<td>−.17</td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>−.38</td>
<td>−.36</td>
<td>−.62</td>
<td/>
<td>.58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7. Intention</td>
<td>−.16</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>−.23</td>
<td>−.28</td>
<td>−.37</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0093650211420136">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. Correlations corrected for attenuation due to measurement error are in the upper triangle.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section38-0093650211420136">
<title>Test of an Alternative Model</title>
<p>An alternative model (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0093650211420136">Figure 6</xref>) that posits face threat is the most proximal outcome of controlling language was tested. Our hypothesized model tests the claim that implied relative power mediates the relationship between degree of controlling language and face threat. If the alternative model demonstrates a better fit than our hypothesized model, then implied relative power is an outcome of face threat rather than an antecedent.</p>
<fig id="fig6-0093650211420136" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Alternative path model.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0093650211420136-fig6.tif"/></fig>
<p>The alternative causal model does not fit the data as well as our hypothesized model. All the path coefficients are substantial and in the predicted direction, however, inspection of the residual errors between the predicted and obtained indirect paths between face threat and source, (residual = .39, <italic>p</italic> = .03) and between face threat and message derogation (residual = .53, <italic>p</italic> = .002) were too large to be attributable to sampling error alone. Further, the chi-square statistic indicating overall fit approached significant levels, χ<sup>2</sup> (15) = 23.73, <italic>p</italic> = .07, and the RMSEA for the alternate model exceeded the criterion suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0093650211420136">Hu and Bentler (1999</xref>; RMSEA = .09; CFI = 1).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section39-0093650211420136" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The results provide further evidence for a politeness theory derived process of resistance to persuasion. In order to address some of the shortcomings of Experiment 1, controlling language alone was varied to replicate and extend our original hypothesized model. More specifically, we extended the model tested in our first experiment by including the perception of relative power implied by the language of the source as a mediator of language feature type and face threat. Also, behavioral intent was added to the model. Further, we replicated the findings of the first study and tested the model in a different context.</p>
<p>It was observed that participants in the more controlling language condition, compared to participants in the less controlling language condition, perceived that the source was implying their relative power over the recipients is higher. As perception of the relative power implied by the language increased, the threat to face increased as well. Increases in face threat, in turn, led to greater derogation of the message source. Further, source derogation was positively associated with message derogation. Then, message derogations impacted attitude toward the topic featured in the message such that increases in derogations led to more negative attitudes toward the advocated stance. Ultimately, attitude was positively related to behavioral intent.</p>
<p>The data provide support for our claim that face threatening language in a persuasive message prompts the process of resistance because features of the message convey an unsubstantiated claim of high relative power over recipients. It is important to note, however, that a more stringent test of this claim would vary the presence and absence of information verifying the source’s claim of relative power. We expect that the presence of information verifying relative power would moderate the relationship between implied relative power of the language and perceptions of face threat. Additionally, because we limited the induction to differences in controlling language, we do not know if forceful language or demeaning language alone would influence perceptions of implied relative power in the same way as controlling language.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section40-0093650211420136" sec-type="discussion">
<title>General Discussion</title>
<p>Taken together, the results of both experiments provide some support for a politeness theory-based explanation of the resistance process. We were able to establish that some of the message features that have been shown to threaten only the need for autonomy produce an overall threat to face, positive and negative. Also, we provided initial evidence supporting our claim that one reason messages threaten face is because they convey a relational claim on the part of the source, one of relative power over message recipients.</p>
<p>According to our model, the degree to which a message was perceived as face threatening impacted how recipients viewed the source. More specifically, as perceived face threat increased, derogation of the source increased. Consequently, as source derogation increased, the message was evaluated more negatively. In Experiment 2 we employed a message that, with less controlling language, was indeed persuasive. Yet, the negative feelings toward the message, prompted by the inclusion of more controlling language, mitigated the persuasive impact of the message. We were able to observe that this process generalizes beyond a particular cover story (i.e., pamphlet, Op-Ed piece) and topic (i.e., dental hygiene, organic food).</p>
<p>The findings of both experiments are limited in several ways. First, written messages from strangers were employed in our test of the model. It is desirable to discern if these findings would generalize to face-to-face interactions and people with established relationships. Second, our findings are restricted to topics of a prosocial nature. Additional investigation is required to determine if the process outlined here generalizes to topics that concern the self-interest of the sender. Third, because both studies employed proattitudinal messages, it is desirable to investigate whether our findings generalize to counterattituindal messages. Finally, although we found that overall face threat mediates the relationship between an implied relative power claim and derogation of the source, there may be circumstances in which positive and negative face function differently in the resistance process. Future research can attempt to discern the conditions under which positive and negative face play distinct roles in the process of resistance.</p>
<sec id="section41-0093650211420136">
<title>Implications of the Current Findings</title>
<p>Overall, these two experiments provide evidence supporting the claim that a reactance-based approach to resistance to persuasion is incomplete because only one type of threat is identified. Our process model identifies threat to autonomy and threat to the desire for positive regard as a proximal consequent of messages with forceful or controlling language.</p>
<p>The findings of Experiment 2 suggest that messages that initiate the resistance process have meta-communicative value. More specifically they constitute a claim of relative power over the recipients. It is this relational content that mediates the relationship between message feature(s) and face threat. Message recipients will opt to reject this claim if there is no corroborating information legitimizing the source’s claim of relative power. Accepting the influence of the arguments in the message constitutes acceptance of the source’s claim of relative power. Recipients resist the arguments in the persuasive message, even if the arguments are compelling, because failing to resist implies accepting the source’s power claim. If, however, the recipients believe that the source has a valid claim of relative power, then the recipients should be less resistant to the persuasive message.</p>
<p>Politeness theory offers a useful message-based approach to minimizing and understanding resistance. Such an approach can focus on the meta-communicative value of various language features in the absence or presence of information verifying the relational claims made by the speaker (i.e., power, social distance). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">Brown and Levinson (1987)</xref> identify numerous strategies that can be used to redress face threat (e.g., claim common ground, show deference) and, thereby, reduce resistance. Depending on the relative power and social distance of the source from recipients, these politeness strategies may be more or less effective in minimizing resistance. In addition, approaching persuasion from the framework of politeness theory allows us to examine how various source and message factors might influence the sociological factors of power, social distance, and imposition, thereby increasing or decreasing the potential level of threat in a given message. For example, sources that are socially close to message recipients may be able to reduce perceived face threat by showing solidarity through positive politeness.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section42-0093650211420136">
<title>Comparing Politeness Theory and Reactance Theory</title>
<p>Although at a conceptual level reactance theory and politeness theory provide very different explanations of the resistance process, the current method for assessing reactance is not altogether incompatible with the process model we have derived from politeness theory. Reactance theory states that resistance is a function of reactance aroused by the message. Recently, scholars employing a reactance theory approach to understanding resistance to persuasion have begun to measure reactance with a composite index of anger and negative cognitions in reaction to the message (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0093650211420136">Dillard &amp; Shen, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0093650211420136">Quick &amp; Considine, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0093650211420136">Rains &amp; Turner, 2007</xref>). Reactance mediates the relationship between autonomy threat and attitude, such that greater reactance (i.e., anger and negative cognitions) is associated with less positive attitudes toward the stance advocated in the message. Although the measure of anger used in the composite index is general, it is likely that the anger is directed at the source of the message. Anger is aroused when people appraise the situation as one in which they are being treated unfairly. Because differences in anger are observed based on the presence of forceful language in the message (i.e., higher levels of anger in response to forceful language and lower levels of anger when the language is not forceful), it is likely that the anger is aimed at the source who is the one employing the forceful language. It may be that the anger is aroused due to the appraisal that the source of the message is using language that implies an unjustified claim of relative power. Assuming that anger is directed at the message source then it is plausible that the anger component of the reactance measure is a reflection of source derogation. Also, frequency of negative cognitive responses can be viewed as an alternate measure of message derogation. Given the conceptual similarity between the composite index of reactance and our measures of source and message derogation, both approaches are consistent with the general claim that persuasive messages with language that threatens the psychological needs of recipients prompt negative perceptions of the source and the message, which ultimately lead to more negative attitudes toward the stance advocated in the message.</p>
<p>In order to provide evidence that one theoretical approach is more useful than the other in explicating the process of resistance to persuasion, one must posit and test aspects of the process than can only be accounted for by one of the two theories. By documenting that the degree of relative power implied by the language of the persuasive message is a mediator of the relationship between resistance inducing message features (e.g., controlling language) and perceived face threat, we believe that we have presented data that cannot be accounted for by reactance theory. More specifically, reactance theory does not account for the meta-communicative value of message features that induce the process of resistance to persuasion. However, reactance theory makes predictions that a politeness theory approach does not; according to reactance theory, importance of the threatened freedom impacts the degree of resistance demonstrated by the recipient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0093650211420136">Brehm, 1966</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0093650211420136">Wicklund &amp; Brehm, 1970</xref>). It may be that by integrating empirical findings derived from both theoretical approaches, one can further understand of the process of resistance to persuasion. In the end, politeness theory can add to the resistance literature because (a) it acknowledges a wider range of threat than reactance, (b) includes source and context factors not acknowledged by reactance theory, and (c) posits strategies for minimizing resistance not addressed by reactance (i.e., positive politeness).</p>
<p>In addition to politeness theory and reactance theory, expectancy violations theory (EVT) can provide a theoretical account of why forceful and controlling language in messages prompts resistance to persuasion.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0093650211420136">4</xref></sup> According to EVT, people have expectations regarding the degree of forceful or controlling language in persuasive messages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0093650211420136">Burgoon, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0093650211420136">Burgoon &amp; Miller, 1985</xref>). These expectations are based on norms for language use and vary based on the situation. When expectations are violated in a negatively valenced manner (e.g., in the absence of an apparent need to be efficient, a peer uses controlling language), then people will resist the persuasive message. Positive violations of expectations, however, facilitate persuasive outcomes. An EVT based explanation of our findings would assert that participants resisted the influence of the face threatening messages because the language employed to encode the persuasive arguments violates normative expectations for language use in that particular context (i.e., health pamphlet and Op-Ed). Whether or not use of forceful language in health pamphlets or controlling language in Op-Eds negatively violate expectations, however, is an empirical question that has yet to be addressed. Future research should attempt to determine if use of controlling or forceful language in health oriented pamphlets or Op-Eds (a) does in fact negatively violate normative expectations and (b) whether the degree of negative expectancy violation can account for variation in resistance behaviors better than perceived face threat.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section43-0093650211420136">
<title>General Contribution of the Current Findings</title>
<p>This study’s findings are relevant to domains beyond that of persuasion. First, the current findings not only add to the resistance literature but also add to the more general domain of politeness theory which has been applied across several social interaction contexts such as advice giving and conflict resolution. Second, this study captures the negotiation aspect of face and facework implied by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0093650211420136">Brown and Levinson (1987)</xref> and in this regard departs from dominant approaches to the study of politeness. For instance, some studies approach the study of politeness from a sender-oriented perspective (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0093650211420136">Ambady, Koo, Lee, &amp; Rosenthal, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0093650211420136">Holtgraves &amp; Yang, 1992</xref>) where participants are presented with a context, in which power and social distance are defined, and asked to imagine how they would respond. Other studies approach politeness from a recipient-oriented perspective in which power and social distance are defined (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0093650211420136">Goldsmith &amp; MacGeorge, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0093650211420136">Holtgraves &amp; Yang, 1990</xref>). Still others are interactive in nature, most closely capturing the negotiation aspect of face (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0093650211420136">Cansler &amp; Styles, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0093650211420136">Holtgraves, 1997</xref>). Although <italic>not</italic> interactional in nature, the present study nevertheless captures the negotiation aspect of facework because power and social distance are not defined for participants. The findings show that source bids of relative power, inferred by the meta-communicative aspects of the message, can be rejected by participants. These findings seem to suggest that in some situations, language does not derive its power from its intrinsic features but rather from the speaker.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-0093650211420136">
<title>Appendix A</title>
<sec id="section44-0093650211420136">
<title>Less Forceful Language</title>
<p>Regular flossing can greatly reduce the changes of gum disease. And most people would agree that flossing is worthy of serious consideration. There is pretty compelling evidence showing a link between gum disease and the failure to floss. The majority of dentists view that evidence as strong and clear. And, the fact that gum disease can lead to other severe problems such as heart disease, stroke, and diabetes means that you might want to think about making flossing a regular habit.</p>
<p>So, if you floss already, keep up the good work. And if you haven’t been flossing, now might be a good time to start. In fact, you may want to try it today.</p>
<p>Flossing: It’s easy. Why not give it a try? Set a goal for yourself to floss everyday during the next week (starting today)!</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section45-0093650211420136">
<title>More Forceful Language</title>
<p>Regular flossing can greatly reduce the changes of gum disease. As any sensible person can see, there is really no choice when it comes to flossing: You simply have to do it. In fact, the scientific evidence showing a link between gum disease and failure to floss is so overwhelming that only a fool would possibly argue with it. And the fact that gum disease can become the basis for other severe problems such as stroke makes it just stupid to not floss every single day of your life.</p>
<p>So, if you floss already, don’t stop even for a day. And, if you haven’t been flossing, right now is the time to start. Today. Do it because you have to. Floss every single day.</p>
<p>Flossing: It’s easy. Do it because you have to! Set a goal for yourself to floss everyday during the next week (starting today)!</p>
</sec>
</app>
<app id="app2-0093650211420136">
<title>Appendix B</title>
<sec id="section46-0093650211420136">
<title>Experiment 1 Negative Face Items</title>
<list id="list7-0093650211420136" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece tried to make a decision for me.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece tried to manipulate me.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece tried to pressurize me.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece threatened my freedom to choose.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece tried to impose something on me.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece talked to me as if I had a choice.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece used forceful language.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece was demanding.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>I feel like the author of the Op-Ed piece was not bossy.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece was domineering.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Experiment 1 Positive Face Threat Items</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece was insulting.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece was respectful.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece was insensitive.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece talked to me as if I didn’t know how to do something.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>I feel like the author of the Op-Ed piece disapproves of me.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>I feel like the author of the Op-Ed piece was concerned about my feelings.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>I feel like the author of the Op-Ed piece thinks I am competent.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section47-0093650211420136">
<title>Experiment 2 Negative Face Threat Items</title>
<list id="list8-0093650211420136" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece tried to make a decision for me.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece tried to manipulate me.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece tried to pressurize me.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece threatened my freedom to choose.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed was not respectful of my right to make my own decisions</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece was demanding.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece was not bossy.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece was domineering.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece tried to impose something on me.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed leaves me free to do what I want to do.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section48-0093650211420136">
<title>Experiment 2 Positive Face Threat Items</title>
<list id="list9-0093650211420136" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece was respectful.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece was insensitive.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece implied that I wasn’t a very capable person.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece disapproves of me.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece was concerned about my feelings.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece thinks I am competent.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece was insulting.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed understands me.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed identifies with me.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed made me feel disliked.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section49-0093650211420136">
<title>Implied Relative Power Items</title>
<list id="list10-0093650211420136" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-ed piece thinks he or she is of higher status than his or her readers.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece thinks he or she is more powerful than his or her readers.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece thinks he or she has the right to tell people what to do.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece thinks that people are required to do what he or she says.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The author of the Op-Ed piece thinks he/she has authority to tell his or her readers what to do.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section50-0093650211420136">
<title>Intent Items</title>
<list id="list11-0093650211420136" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>I plan to take steps to reduce my exposure to pesticides by eating only organic foods.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>I intend to take steps to reduce my exposure to pesticides by eating only organic foods.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>I will attempt to take steps to reduce my exposure to pesticides by eating only organic foods.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>I will aim to take steps to reduce my exposure to pesticides by eating only organic foods.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</app>
<app id="app3-0093650211420136">
<title>Appendix C</title>
<sec id="section51-0093650211420136">
<title>Less Controlling Language Message</title>
<p>Whenever possible you should try to eat organic. Organic foods are produced without the use of chemicals, herbicides, fungicides, petroleum, sewage or sludge-based fertilizers or chemical pesticides. Organic food is neither bioengineered, genetically modified, nor is it irradiated. Organically raised chickens and cows are fed only organic feed, graze on organically maintained pastures, and are not given antibiotics, hormones or animal by-products. Organic foods contain less pesticides, hormones, and antibiotics than conventionally raised foods. Also, organic foods taste better than conventionally raised foods. Further, organic foods are richer in vitamins and minerals than conventionally raised foods.</p>
<p>Until WWII, organic practices were the normal way of raising food. However, changes in farming practices, including the use of pesticides and other chemicals, have made organic methods the exception instead of the rule. Constant consumption of food laced with pesticides, herbicides, fungicides and other chemicals has a negative effect on fertility, childhood development, health, and longevity. The fact is that pesticides are poisons. Further, pesticides are endocrine disrupters that mimic or interfere with our hormones. Not to mention that extensive exposure to pesticides can cause cancer. Washing fruits and vegetables in an attempt to get rid of pesticides doesn’t always work. Because pesticides are absorbed in the plant through the roots, the toxins are actually inside the plant.</p>
<p>Some plants are more contaminated with pesticides than other plants. Among fruit peaches, strawberries, apples, bananas, and grapes tend to have the highest levels of pesticide contamination. Given the contamination level present in these fruits, you may want to consider buying organic varieties of these fruits instead of conventionally raised fruit. Potatoes, green and red peppers, lettuce, and corn are some of the vegetables that demonstrate high levels of pesticide contamination. Whenever you have a choice between organic and conventionally raised versions of these vegetables, organic is the much safer and healthier choice. Another reason you should buy organic corn is that you don’t have to worry about whether the corn has been genetically modified. If you purchase conventionally raised corn, you have no way of knowing whether the corn has been genetically modified. Additionally, you should eat organically raised nuts. Because of their high fat content, nuts hold onto pesticides more than other crops.</p>
<p>Eating organic is healthy and safe. You should try to eat only organic foods. Eating organically raised foods reduces your exposure to toxins and chemicals. Remember, organic foods are not just safer than conventionally raised food but are more nutritious and tasty.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section52-0093650211420136">
<title>More Controlling Language Message</title>
<p>You must eat organic. Organic foods are produced without the use of chemicals, herbicides, fungicides, petroleum, sewage or sludge-based fertilizers or chemical pesticides. Organic food is not bioengineered, genetically modified, nor is it irradiated. Organically raised chickens and cows are fed only organic feed, graze on organically maintained pastures, and are not given antibiotics, hormones or animal by-products. Organic foods contain less pesticides, hormones, and antibiotics than conventionally raised foods. Also, organic foods taste better than conventionally raised foods. Further, organic foods are richer in vitamins and minerals than conventionally raised foods.</p>
<p>Until WWII, organic practices were the normal way of raising food. However, changes in farming practices, including the use of pesticides and other chemicals, have made organic methods the exception instead of the rule. Constant consumption of food laced with pesticides, herbicides, fungicides and other chemicals has a negative effect on fertility, childhood development, health, and longevity. The fact is that pesticides are poisons. Further, pesticides are endocrine disrupters that mimic or interfere with our hormones. Not to mention that extensive exposure to pesticides can cause cancer. Washing fruits and vegetables in an attempt to get rid of pesticides doesn’t always work. Because pesticides are absorbed in the plant through the roots, the toxins are actually inside the plant.</p>
<p>Some plants are more contaminated with pesticides than other plants. Among fruit peaches, strawberries, apples, bananas, and grapes tend to have the highest levels of pesticide contamination. Given the contamination level present in these fruits, you must only buy organic varieties of these fruits instead of conventionally raised fruit. Potatoes, green and red peppers, lettuce, and corn are some of the vegetables that demonstrate high levels of pesticide contamination. You must choose organic over conventionally raised versions of these vegetables because organic is the much safer and healthier choice. Another reason you must buy organic corn is that you don’t have to worry about whether the corn has been genetically modified. If you purchase conventionally raised corn, you have no way of knowing whether the corn has been genetically modified. Additionally, you have to eat only organically raised nuts. Because of their high fat content, nuts hold onto pesticides more than other crops.</p>
<p>Eating organic is healthy and safe. You must eat only organic foods. Eating organically raised foods reduces your exposure to toxins and chemicals. Remember, organic foods are not just safer than conventionally raised food but are more nutritious and tasty.</p>
</sec>
</app>
</app-group>
<ack>
<p>The authors thank Robert Bell for his feedback on an earlier version of this article. A version of this article was presented at the annual convention of the National Communication Association in San Francisco, CA 2010.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0093650211420136">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Goffman (1967) employs the term <italic>heartless</italic> in reference to people who do not feel negative emotions in response to the face loss of another. Goffman’s use of this term echoes the notion that people who demonstrate disdain for the basic wants of others are negatively evaluated.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0093650211420136">
<label>2.</label>
<p>The data for both Experiments 1 and 2 were collected from a university that had the following ethnic composition: 39% Asian, 35% White, 15% Hispanic, 3% African American, 1% American Indian/Alaska Native, and 7% other (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0093650211420136">UC Davis Budget and Institutional Analysis, 2010</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0093650211420136">
<label>3.</label>
<p>In Experiment 1, scores from the positive and negative face threat scales were converted to <italic>z</italic>-scores to create a face threat index because there were more negative face threat items than positive face threat items. Given that the number of positive and negative face threat items was the same for Experiment 2, there was no need to convert the two scales to <italic>z</italic>-scores in order to create a face threat index.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0093650211420136">
<label>4.</label>
<p>We would like to thank the anonymous reviewer who pointed out the applicability of EVT to our study.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Mikayla Jenkins</bold> (PhD, Michigan State University, 2006) is an assistant professor in the Department of Communication at the University of California, Davis.</p>
<p><bold>Marko Dragojevic</bold> (BA, University of California, Davis, 2008) is a graduate student in the Department of Communication at the University of California, Davis.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ambady</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>More than words: Linguistic and nonlinguistic politeness in two cultures</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>996</fpage>-<lpage>1011</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bohner</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruder</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erb</surname><given-names>H. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>When expertise backfires: Contrast and assimilation effects in persuasion</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Social Psychology</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>495</fpage>-<lpage>519</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brehm</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1966</year>). <source>A theory of psychological reactance</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brehm</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brehm</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <source>Psychological reactance: A theory of freedom and control</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levinson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Universals in language usage: Politeness phenomena</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Goody</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Questions and politeness</source> (pp. <fpage>56</fpage>-<lpage>310</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levinson</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <source>Politeness: Some universals in language usage</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burgoon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Social influence</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robinson</surname></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of language and social psychology</source> (pp. <fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burgoon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alvaro</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grandpre</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Voulodakis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Revisiting the theory of psychological reactance: Communicating threats to attitudinal freedom</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dillard</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pfau</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The persuasion handbook: Developments in theory and practice</source> (pp. <fpage>213</fpage>-<lpage>232</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burgoon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>An expectancy interpretation of language and persuasion</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>St. Clair</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Recent advances in language, communication and social psychology</source> (pp. <fpage>199</fpage>-<lpage>229</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cansler</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stiles</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>Relative status and interpersonal presumptuousness</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>459</fpage>-<lpage>471</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cupach</surname><given-names>W. R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Facing corrections in the workplace: The influence of perceived face threat on the consequences of managerial reproaches</article-title>. <source>Applied Communication Research</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>215</fpage>-<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tracy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spisak</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>The discourse of requests: Assessments of politeness approach</article-title>. <source>Human Communication Research</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>437</fpage>-<lpage>468</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cupach</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Metts</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>Facework</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dillard</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>On the nature of reactance and its role in persuasive health communication</article-title>. <source>Communication Monographs</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>144</fpage>-<lpage>168</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dillard</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tusing</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kinney</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Politeness judgments in personal relationships</article-title>. <source>Journal of Language and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>297</fpage>-<lpage>325</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>French</surname><given-names>J. R. P.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1959</year>). <article-title>The basis of social power</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Carwright</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Studies in social power</source> (pp. <fpage>150</fpage>-<lpage>167</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor, MI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Research Center for Group Dynamics, Institute for Social Research, University of Michigan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Godin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kok</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The theory of planned behavior: A review of its applications to health-related behaviors</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Health Promotion</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Politeness theory: How we use language to save face</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Braithwaite</surname><given-names>D. O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Engaging theories in interpersonal communication: Multiple Perspectives</source> (pp. <fpage>255</fpage>-<lpage>268</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacGeorge</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The impact of politeness and relationship on perceived quality of advice about a problem</article-title>. <source>Human Communication Research</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>234</fpage>-<lpage>263</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Beyond Baron and Kenny: Statistical mediation analysis in the new millennium</article-title>. <source>Communication Monographs</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>408</fpage>-<lpage>420</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holtgraves</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Language structure in social interaction: Perceptions of direct and indirect speech acts and interactants who use them</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>305</fpage>-<lpage>314</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holtgraves</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Yes, but . . . positive politeness in conversation arguments</article-title>. <source>Journal of Language and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>222</fpage>-<lpage>239</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holtgraves</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Politeness as universal: Cross-cultural perceptions of request strategies and inferences based on their use</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>719</fpage>-<lpage>729</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holtgraves</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Interpersonal underpinnings of request strategies: General principles and differences due to culture and gender</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>246</fpage>-<lpage>256</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L.T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bentler</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Cutoff criteria for fit indexes in covariance structure analysis: Conventional criteria versus new alternatives</article-title>. <source>Structural Equation Modeling</source>, <volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gerbing</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Unidimensional measurement, second order factor analysis, and causal models</article-title>. <source>Research in Organizational Behavior</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>-<lpage>320</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>CFA</article-title>.<source>BAS [A program in BASICA to do confirmatory factor analysis]</source>. <publisher-loc>East Lansing, MI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Michigan State University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>PATH [A least squares path analysis program in BASICA]</article-title>. <publisher-loc>East Lansing, MI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Michigan State University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brehm</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>). <article-title>Persuasiveness of one- and two-sided communications as a function of awareness there are two sides</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M., S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Relationships among attitudes, behavioral intentions, and behavior; A meta-analysis of past research, part 2</article-title>. <source>Communication Research</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>331</fpage>-<lpage>364</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Facework solidarity, approbation, and tact</article-title>. <source>Human Communication Research</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>415</fpage>-<lpage>450</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>L. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deatrick</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Potts</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Psychological reactance and promotional health messages: The effects of controlling language, lexical concreteness, and the restoration of freedom</article-title>. <source>Human Communication Research</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>240</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Penman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Facework and politeness: Multiple goals in courtroom discourse</article-title>. <source>Journal of Language and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>121</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Quick</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Considine</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Examining the use of forceful language when designing exercise persuasive messages for adults: A test of conceptualizing reactance arousal as a two-step process</article-title>. <source>Health Communication</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>483</fpage>-<lpage>491</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rains</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Psychological reactance and persuasive health communication: A test and extension of the intertwined model</article-title>. <source>Human Communication Research</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>-<lpage>269</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sheeran</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Predicting intentions to use condoms: A meta-analysis and comparison of the theories of reasoned action and planned behavior</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1624</fpage>-<lpage>1775</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hartwick</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warshaw</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>The theory of reasoned action: A meta-analysis of past research with recommendations for modifications and future research</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>325</fpage>-<lpage>343</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Areni</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The effects of sales presentation quality an initial perceptions on persuasion: A multiple role perspective</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business Research</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>517</fpage>-<lpage>528</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Areni</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Style versus substance: Multiple roles of language power in persuasion</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Social Psychology</source>, <volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trees</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kerssen-Griep</surname></name>
<name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Earning influence by communicating respect: Facework’s contribution to effective instructional communication</article-title>. <source>Communication Education</source>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>397</fpage>-<lpage>416</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>UC Davis Budget and Institutional Analysis</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>Student headcount by ethnicity</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://facts.ucdavis.edu/student_headcount_ethnicity.lasso">http://facts.ucdavis.edu/student_headcount_ethnicity.lasso</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Watzlawick</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beavin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>). <source>Pragmatics of human communication</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>W. W. Norton</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wicklund</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brehm</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>). <article-title>Effects of threats to attitudinal freedom as a function of agreement with the communicator</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>18</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0093650211420136">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aleman</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leatham</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Identity implications of influence goals: A revised analysis of face-threatening acts and application to seeking compliance with same-sex friends</article-title>. <source>Human Communication Research</source>, <volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>64</fpage>-<lpage>96</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>