<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NCP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spncp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nutr Clin Pract</journal-id>
<journal-title>Nutrition in Clinical Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0884-5336</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1941-2452</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0884533611435991</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0884533611435991</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Clinical Research</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Maternal Mid–Upper Arm Circumference Is Associated With Birth Weight Among HIV-Infected Malawians</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Ramlal</surname><given-names>Roshan T.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MPH, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0884533611435991">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Tembo</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name>
<degrees>MPH</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0884533611435991">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Soko</surname><given-names>Alice</given-names></name>
<degrees>RN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0884533611435991">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Chigwenembe</surname><given-names>Maggie</given-names></name>
<degrees>RN</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0884533611435991">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ellington</surname><given-names>Sascha</given-names></name>
<degrees>MPH</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0884533611435991">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kayira</surname><given-names>Dumbani</given-names></name>
<degrees>MBBS</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0884533611435991">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>Caroline C.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MPH, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0884533611435991">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Chasela</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name>
<degrees>MSc, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0884533611435991">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>Denise</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, MPH</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0884533611435991">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>van der Horst</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0884533611435991">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>Margaret E.</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0884533611435991">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Adair</surname><given-names>Linda S.</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0884533611435991">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<collab>the BAN Study Team</collab>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0884533611435991"><label>1</label>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, North Carolina, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0884533611435991"><label>2</label>UNC Project Lilongwe, Lilongwe, Malawi</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0884533611435991"><label>3</label>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0884533611435991">Roshan T. Ramlal, <email>roshan.m.thomas@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<issue-title>Cardiovascular and Critical Illness</issue-title>
<fpage>416</fpage>
<lpage>421</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">The American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The authors examined the relationship of maternal anthropometry to fetal growth and birth weight among 1005 human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)–infected women in Lilongwe, Malawi, who consented to enrollment in the Breastfeeding, Antiretrovirals, and Nutrition Study (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.thebanstudy.org">www.thebanstudy.org</ext-link>). Anthropometric assessments of mid–upper arm circumference (MUAC), arm muscle area (AMA), and arm fat area (AFA) were collected at the baseline visit between 12 and 30 weeks’ gestation and in up to 4 follow-up prenatal visits. In longitudinal analysis, fundal height increased monotonically at an estimated rate of 0.92 cm/wk and was positively and negatively associated with AMA and AFA, respectively. These latter relationships varied over weeks of follow-up. Baseline MUAC, AMA, and AFA were positively associated with birth weight (MUAC: 31.84 g/cm<sup>2</sup>, 95% confidence interval [CI], 22.18-41.49 [<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01]; AMA: 6.88 g/cm<sup>2</sup>, 95% CI, 2.51-11.26 [<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01]; AFA: 6.97 g/cm<sup>2</sup>, 95% CI, 3.53-10.41 [<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01]). In addition, MUAC and AMA were both associated with decreased odds for low birth weight (LBW; &lt;2500 g) (MUAC: odds ratio [OR] = 0.85, 95% CI, 0.77-0.94 [<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01]; AMA: OR = 0.95, 95% CI, 0.91-0.99 [<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05]). These findings support the use of MUAC as an efficient, cost-effective screening tool for LBW in HIV-infected women, as in HIV-uninfected women.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>nutrition assessment</kwd>
<kwd>HIV</kwd>
<kwd>proteins</kwd>
<kwd>infant, low birth weight</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In resource-limited settings, low birth weight (LBW) is common. Research comparing data from resource-limited countries with that from resource-rich countries shows that most differences in LBW rates may be attributed to an increased prevalence of intrauterine growth restriction (IUGR), rather than preterm birth, with relative risks of 6.6 and 2.0, respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0884533611435991">1</xref></sup> It is well established that the short-term consequences of IUGR include increased risk of fetal, neonatal, and infant death and impaired postnatal growth, immune function, and intellectual development.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0884533611435991">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0884533611435991"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0884533611435991">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>Maternal nutrition status, as estimated by anthropometrics, is an important contributor to fetal growth and infant birth weight.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0884533611435991">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0884533611435991"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0884533611435991">7</xref></sup> In pregnant women, weight alone may not be the best indicator of maternal muscle and fat stores because it is a measure of both the mother and the fetus. Therefore, simple and inexpensive anthropometric measurements, such as mid–upper arm circumference (MUAC) and skinfold thickness measurements, are used in large-scale epidemiological studies to derive estimates of lean muscle mass and adiposity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0884533611435991">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0884533611435991"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0884533611435991">10</xref></sup> In resource-limited settings, intrauterine growth assessments rely on serial fundal height measurements during antenatal care, and determination of intrauterine growth restriction is based on low birth weight for estimated gestational age.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0884533611435991">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>The relationship between low MUAC and LBW has been studied extensively in human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)–uninfected populations; therefore, it is commonly used as a screening tool in developing countries.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0884533611435991">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0884533611435991"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0884533611435991">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0884533611435991">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0884533611435991">13</xref></sup> However, there are limited data on the utility of maternal anthropometrics as predictors for fetal growth and birth weight among cohorts of pregnant HIV-infected women.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0884533611435991">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0884533611435991"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0884533611435991">10</xref></sup> HIV-infected individuals may lose fat mass quicker than HIV-uninfected individuals due to an increased metabolic rate to combat infection and malabsorption of nutrients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0884533611435991">14</xref></sup> In addition, women in sub-Saharan Africa are vulnerable to factors such as high parity and short birth intervals, prevalent infectious disease, and seasonal variations in food insecurity. These combined factors place an added burden on pregnant women and therefore may contribute to poor birth outcomes, such as LBW.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0884533611435991">2</xref></sup> We hypothesized that low maternal nutrition stores among HIV-positive women, as measured by low arm muscle area (AMA) and low arm fat area (AFA), would relate to slower intrauterine growth and increased risk of LBW.</p>
<sec id="section1-0884533611435991" sec-type="methods">
<title>Patients and Methods</title>
<p>The current study includes 1005 HIV-infected women who delivered live singleton births between June 2004 and December 2006 and consented to enrollment in the Breastfeeding, Antiretrovirals, and Nutrition (BAN) Study, a postnatal clinical trial (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.thebanstudy.org">www.thebanstudy.org</ext-link>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0884533611435991">15</xref></sup> These study participants were recruited from 4 sites with outreach to all pregnant women in Lilongwe, Malawi, who met prenatal screening criteria: ≥14 years of age, no prior antiretroviral medication use, ≤30 weeks’ gestation, and no serious complications of pregnancy, CD4 count ≥200 cells/µL, hemoglobin ≥7 g/dL, and normal serum liver function tests (≤2.5 times the upper limit of normal). At the second antenatal visit approximately 1 week later (hereafter referred to as the baseline visit), 1130 eligible women completed a baseline interview, underwent a physical examination, and provided blood specimens again. Of these, 125 women were excluded from the analysis sample owing to fetal loss, still birth, twins, and late presentation to the clinic following home deliveries or delivery at other clinics (after 48 hours after delivery). Of 1005 women who had live singleton births, no fundal height was available for 92 women. Of 913 women who had at least 1 fundal height measurement, 20 women had no baseline measurement of fundal height.</p>
<p>MUAC, triceps skinfold thickness, and height were measured by trained BAN nutrition staff. Height was measured once either prenatally or postnatally with a standard height board. At each visit, MUAC was measured at the midpoint between the olecranon and acromion process, to the nearest 0.1 cm, using a nonstretchable insertion tape while the arm hung freely at the side. Triceps skinfold thickness was measured at each visit using Lange calipers. The mean of 3 separate determinations was used with MUAC to derive arm fat and muscle areas. AMA, an indicator of total muscle mass, was derived from MUAC and triceps skinfold measures as follows: AMA = [MUAC – (triceps skinfold × π)]<sup>2</sup>/4 π. AFA, an indicator of total fat mass, was derived from MUAC and AMA: AFA = (MUAC<sup>2</sup>/4 π – AMA).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0884533611435991">16</xref></sup></p>
<p>Gestational age at baseline and subsequent prenatal visits were derived from the date of last menstrual period (LMP) or, if LMP was unknown, first available fundal height. Depending on the estimated gestational age at baseline, women were asked to return for follow-up prenatal care at approximately 28, 32, and 36 weeks’ gestation, and fundal height was used to estimate intrauterine growth. In the BAN Study, fundal height was ascertained by measuring the distance between the upper edge of the pubic symphysis and the top of the uterine fundus using a tape measure. Beginning in the second trimester, fundal height ±1–3 cm should estimate gestational age in weeks (ie, a pregnant woman’s uterus at 26 weeks should measure 23–29 cm).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0884533611435991">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0884533611435991"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0884533611435991">19</xref></sup> Birth weight was measured using a Tanita Digital Baby Scale (Tanita, Arlington Heights, IL) to the nearest 0.1 kg immediately after delivery in the hospital or within 48 hours of delivery, upon arrival to the hospital, for home deliveries. LBW was defined according to the World Health Organization (WHO) definition of less than 2500 g.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0884533611435991">20</xref></sup></p>
<p>Basic sociodemographic information was collected during the baseline interview: age, parity, marital status, household characteristics, and the educational level and occupation status of the mother. A wealth index was derived from household characteristics to assess socioeconomic status (SES): house construction (type of walls, floors, and roof), number of rooms and residents, electricity, refrigeration, sanitation, and cooking fuel source.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0884533611435991">21</xref></sup> CD4 count was measured cross-sectionally during the first screening visit. None of the women took antenatal antiretrovirals during this or prior pregnancies, in accordance with the national guidelines of Malawi’s Ministry of Health on initiation of antiretroviral treatment, because these women had high CD4 count levels. All participants received iron and folate supplements, malaria prophylaxis and treatment, and mosquito nets. As of December 2005, all pregnant women with CD4 counts &lt;500 cells/µL were administered cotrimoxazole after the first trimester.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0884533611435991">13</xref></sup> At onset of labor, all participants received the HIVNET 012 regimen and a 7-day postnatal “tail” of zidovudine and lamivudine to prevent perinatal HIV transmission. The BAN Study protocol was approved by the Malawi National Health Sciences Research Committee and the institutional review boards at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> identifier NCT00164762).</p>
<sec id="section2-0884533611435991">
<title>Statistical Data Analysis</title>
<p>We used STATA version 9.0 for this analysis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0884533611435991">22</xref></sup> First, we evaluated the potential for selection bias by comparing women with anthropometric measurements collected at baseline who were included in our analysis (n = 1005) with those who were excluded from the analysis sample owing to fetal loss, still birth, home deliveries, or late presentation after delivery (n = 125). Two-sample <italic>t</italic> tests and χ<sup>2</sup> tests were used to compare means of continuous variables and proportions of categorical variables, respectively, between the samples, and inverse probability weighting was used to evaluate selection bias in our statistical models.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0884533611435991">23</xref></sup> The likelihood of being in the analysis sample (with complete data) was estimated from a logistic regression model, including baseline socioeconomic and demographic variables, and the inverse predicted probabilities were included as sample weights in regression models for birth outcomes.</p>
<p>Fundal height at each antenatal visit was modeled using longitudinal random effects regression. Time-varying anthropometric indicators measured concurrently with fundal height (eg, AMA and AFA) were included in the model, along with time-independent baseline maternal characteristics (age, parity, CD4 count, wealth index) and infant gender and in utero infection. Because food availability, malnutrition, and infectious disease morbidity vary substantially by season due to cycles of rainfall and agricultural production,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0884533611435991">24</xref></sup> the number of days spent in the famine season (August to March) in the month prior to anthropometric assessment was included as a time-varying cofactor. In addition, because of reported annual variations in the maize production, year at baseline was also included in the models.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0884533611435991">25</xref></sup> The time between the baseline visit and each subsequent visit was included in the model for fundal height. To anchor the timing of measurements relative to total gestational duration, the time between the last antenatal visit and delivery was included in the model. Interaction terms between the main predictors (MUAC, AMA, AFA) and each of the covariates were considered, estimated, and retained in the models if their <italic>P</italic> value was &lt;.15.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0884533611435991">26</xref></sup></p>
<p>Linear regression models were used to estimate the relationship between maternal anthropometry and birth weight, and logistic regression models were used to estimate odds ratios for LBW associated with each risk factor after adjustment for covariates. Model specification was guided by studies on nutrition outcomes among pregnant HIV-infected and HIV noninfected women. Two multivariable models were constructed for each outcome. One included AMA and AFA together as the main exposures; a second model included MUAC as the main exposure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0884533611435991">27</xref></sup> Internal sample-based <italic>z</italic> scores were calculated for these anthropometric measures so that the effect sizes of AMA and AFA, as well as MUAC, could be compared. We tested for linear trends between the independent variables and study outcomes, and if nonlinear, categorical variables were constructed and included in the models.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0884533611435991" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The median CD4 count was 439 cells/µL (interquartile range [IQR], 319–592), and about a third of women fell into each of 3 CD4 categories: 200–350 cells/µL (31%), 350–500 cells/µL (31%), and &gt;500 cells/µL (38%) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0884533611435991">Table 1</xref>). Almost two-thirds (62%) of the women were exposed to the famine season in the month prior to their baseline visit. The mean MUAC was 26.5 cm, with a mean arm muscle area of 36.8 cm<sup>2</sup> and mean arm fat area of 19.7 cm<sup>2</sup> at baseline. The average birth weight was 2998 g, and the prevalence of low birth weight was 8.7% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0884533611435991">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0884533611435991" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Characteristics of HIV-Infected Pregnant Women and Their Infants in Malawi (n = 1005)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0884533611435991" xlink:href="10.1177_0884533611435991-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Characteristic</th>
<th align="center">Value</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Maternal characteristics at baseline</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="2"> Age, y, %</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  &lt;20</td>
<td>6.76</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  20–24</td>
<td>35.88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  25–29</td>
<td>34.39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  ≥30</td>
<td>22.96</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Education level, %</td>
<td>75.83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  None</td>
<td>12.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Primary level</td>
<td>52.74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Secondary level</td>
<td>34.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2"> Marital status, %</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Married or cohabitating</td>
<td>92.82</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Single, divorced, or widowed</td>
<td>7.18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2"> Employment, %</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  No</td>
<td>80.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Yes</td>
<td>19.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2"> Exposure to famine season in month prior to baseline visit, %</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Total</td>
<td>42.83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Partial</td>
<td>19.56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  None</td>
<td>37.61</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2"> Parity, %</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  0</td>
<td>18.21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  1–2</td>
<td>58.70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  ≥3</td>
<td>23.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Height, cm, mean ± SD</td>
<td>155.9 ± 5.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mid–upper arm circumference, cm, mean ± SD</td>
<td>26.5 ± 2.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Arm muscle area, cm<sup>2</sup>, mean ± SD</td>
<td>36.8 ± 6.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Arm fat area, cm<sup>2</sup>, mean ± SD</td>
<td>19.7 ± 7.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Fundal height, cm<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0884533611435991">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>24.9 ± 4.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> CD4 count, ×10<sup>6</sup> cells/L<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0884533611435991">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>439 (319–592)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Infant characteristics at birth</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Birth weight, g, mean ± SD</td>
<td>2998 ± 440</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Low birth weight, %</td>
<td>8.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Infant gender, % male</td>
<td>50.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Infant HIV status, % positive</td>
<td>3.8</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0884533611435991">
<label>a</label>
<p>Sample size reduced to 893; 92 women had no fundal height, and 20 women had fundal height missing at baseline.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0884533611435991">
<label>b</label>
<p>CD4 count displayed as median and interquartile range.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Women included in our analysis (n = 1005) were significantly younger (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01), commenced prenatal care earlier (<italic>P</italic> = .03), and were more likely to be primiparous (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .01) than women excluded (n = 125); they did not differ significantly on CD4 count, maternal anthropometrics, or fundal height. Weighted and unweighted models were not appreciably different, suggesting that selection bias was not a problem. Thus, we present unweighted results.</p>
<p>Fundal height increased monotonically at a rate of about 0.92 cm/wk (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0884533611435991">Table 2</xref>). In the longitudinal analysis, AMA was associated with a subtle yet significant increase in fundal height over the course of the latter part of pregnancy; in contrast, AFA was associated with a subtle yet significant decrease in fundal height. MUAC was not significantly related as a predictor. The effects of AMA and AFA were significantly modified by weeks of follow-up. The βs of equivalent magnitude but opposite direction for AMA and AFA, as well as their interaction terms with gestational week, are consistent with the lack of an overall effect of MUAC on fundal height. An important predictor of decreased fundal height was infant HIV status. However, there was no association between fundal height and maternal CD4 count. Furthermore, there was no evidence famine season or year of enrollment affected fundal height. Although the association between infant gender and fundal height was statistically significant, clinically the difference in association between males and females and fundal height was very subtle. Age, parity, and wealth index also had weak associations with fundal height.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0884533611435991" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Longitudinal Regression Analysis of Fundal Height as Main Outcome and Maternal Arm Measurements as Main Predictors in 913 HIV-Infected Malawian Women</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0884533611435991" xlink:href="10.1177_0884533611435991-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Fundal Height, cm</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Main Predictor<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0884533611435991">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center">
<italic>P</italic> Value</th>
<th align="center">95% Confidence Interval</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Arm muscle area (AMA), cm<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>0.01 to 0.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Arm fat area (AFA), cm<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>−0.03</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>−0.05 to –0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Weeks<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0884533611435991">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>0.83 to 1.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AMA × wk</td>
<td>−0.003</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>−0.006 to –0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AFA × wk</td>
<td>0.003</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>0.001 to 0.006</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Weeks between last visit and delivery</td>
<td>−0.32</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>−0.39 to –0.18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Covariates<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0884533611435991">c</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"> Age, y</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  &lt;20</td>
<td>0.52</td>
<td>.27</td>
<td>−0.41 to 1.45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  20–24</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  25–29</td>
<td>0.78</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>0.22 to 1.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  30+</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>−0.01 to 1.51</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Parity</td>
<td>0.31</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>0.08 to 0.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Wealth index</td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>0.07 to 0.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Famine<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0884533611435991">d</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.19</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>−0.46 to 0.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"> Year of enrollment</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  2004</td>
<td>−0.59</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>−1.27 to 0.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  2005</td>
<td>−0.15</td>
<td>.55</td>
<td>−0.63 to 0.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  2006</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"> CD4 count, cells/µL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  200–350</td>
<td>−0.36</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>−0.95 to 0.24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  350–499</td>
<td>−0.33</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>−0.88 to 0.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  ≥500</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Infant gender (female is referent)</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>0.04 to 0.93</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Infant infected in utero (uninfected is referent)</td>
<td>−1.69</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>−2.91 to –0.48</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0884533611435991">
<label>a</label>
<p>Sample size reduced to 913 because 92 had no fundal height available.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0884533611435991">
<label>b</label>
<p>Number of weeks since baseline visit; baseline visit = 0 weeks.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0884533611435991">
<label>c</label>
<p>Maternal height was included in model and was not statistically significant.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0884533611435991">
<label>d</label>
<p>Famine defined as number of days in famine season during preceding month.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Baseline maternal MUAC, AMA, and AFA were strong predictors of infant birth weight, with the greatest effect observed for MUAC based on internal sample <italic>z</italic> scores, which were calculated. For each 1-cm increase in MUAC, there was a 31.8-g increase in birth weight (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0884533611435991">Table 3</xref>, model 2). In contrast, each 1-cm<sup>2</sup> increase in AMA and AFA was associated with a 6.88-g and 6.97-g increase in birth weight, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0884533611435991">Table 3</xref>, model 1). In models with LBW as the outcome, higher baseline maternal MUAC was a strong predictor for decreased odds of LBW (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0884533611435991">Table 3</xref>, model 2). The odds of having an LBW infant also decreased with increasing AMA; a similar pattern was observed for the relationship between AFA and LBW, although this was not statistically significant (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0884533611435991">Table 3</xref>, model 1).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0884533611435991" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Multiple Variable Regression Models With Birth Weight and Low Birth Weight (LBW) as Main Outcomes and Baseline Maternal Arm Measurements as Main Predictors in 1005 HIV-Infected Malawian Women</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0884533611435991" xlink:href="10.1177_0884533611435991-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Birth Weight,<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0884533611435991">a</xref></sup> g</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">LBW<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0884533611435991">b</xref></sup> (&lt;2500 g)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Main Predictor</th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center">P Value</th>
<th align="center">95% Confidence Interval</th>
<th align="center">Odds Ratio</th>
<th align="center">P Value</th>
<th align="center">95% Confidence Interval</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Model 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Arm muscle area, cm<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>6.88</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>2.51–11.26</td>
<td>0.95</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>0.91–0.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Arm fat area, cm<sup>2</sup></td>
<td>6.97</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>3.53–10.41</td>
<td>0.97</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>0.94–1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Model 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mid–upper arm circumference, cm</td>
<td>31.84</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>22.18–41.49</td>
<td>0.85</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>0.77–0.94</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn7-0884533611435991">
<label>a</label>
<p>Estimated with multiple linear regression; covariates include maternal height, age, parity, education, place of delivery (hospital, home), CD4 cell count, infant sex, infant human immunodeficiency virus status at birth.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn8-0884533611435991">
<label>b</label>
<p>Estimated with multivariate logistic regression models with covariates described in note a.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0884533611435991" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Birth weight is an important predictor of infant survival and future development. In our study of HIV-infected pregnant women with high CD4 counts, mean baseline MUAC, fetal growth, and birth weight were similar to other sub-Saharan populations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0884533611435991">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0884533611435991">29</xref></sup> In addition, maternal MUAC was a strong predictor of birth weight and LBW in this HIV-infected population, as has been reported for HIV-uninfected women.</p>
<p>With repeated measures, we observed similar patterns of increasing fundal height with increasing muscle mass and decreasing fundal height with increasing fat mass during late pregnancy, as seen in comparable HIV-uninfected populations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0884533611435991">30</xref></sup> However, the small increase in fundal height associated with AMA coincided with an equally small decrease associated with AFA, thus explaining why MUAC did not show any relationship to fetal growth.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0884533611435991">31</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0884533611435991"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0884533611435991">33</xref></sup> Currently, no comparative literature has examined maternal factors and their associations with fundal height. The use of fundal height to estimate gestational age has been criticized in resource-limited contexts where IUGR is prevalent because fundal height can misclassify a growth-restricted infant as having an earlier week of gestation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0884533611435991">34</xref></sup> Rather than using fundal height as an indicator of gestation week, we modeled repeated measurements of fundal height as an outcome and examined how it related longitudinally to maternal anthropometry and other maternal characteristics. Serial measurements of fundal height are being increasingly used in resource-limited settings for the prediction of birth weight and diagnosis of IUGR.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0884533611435991">35</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0884533611435991"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0884533611435991">37</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although AMA and AFA minimally affected fetal growth, and MUAC did not affect fetal growth at all, AMA, AFA, and MUAC were directly related to birth weight. MUAC was the strongest predictor for birth weight, both as a continuous measurement and dichotomized to indicate LBW. This finding is consistent with reports from European and African women. In pregnant European women, pregravid lean body mass was found to be a significant predictor of birth weight.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0884533611435991">38</xref></sup> Among a cohort of 110 Kenyan women, increased odds for LBW were reported for mothers with smaller MUAC during the second and third trimesters.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0884533611435991">6</xref></sup> Among 1002 HIV-infected women in Tanzania, mothers with the highest quartile of MUAC distribution had higher infant birth weights relative to mothers in the lowest quartile of MUAC.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0884533611435991">8</xref></sup> In contrast, the latter study found no association between MUAC and LBW.</p>
<p>Although AMA was associated with birth weight as a continuous measure and as the dichotomous measure for LBW (vs not LBW), AFA was significantly associated only with birth weight as a continuous variable. The positive association between AFA and birth weight may appear contradictory to the inverse association between AFA and fundal height; however, the association between AFA and fundal height was evaluated in a longitudinal model that includes serial measures during pregnancy over which AFA tends to decline while fundal height increases. In contrast, the association between AFA and birth weight was evaluated in a cross-sectional model using a baseline AFA measurement, which reflects fat storage earlier in pregnancy. The cross-sectional association between AFA and birth weight is consistent with a study in Zimbabwe among 1669 HIV-infected women that found low AFA (&lt;20 cm<sup>2</sup>) measured once during late pregnancy was associated with lower birth weight.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0884533611435991">10</xref></sup> However, unlike our study, the authors found no relationship between AMA and LBW.</p>
<p>A major strength of our study is serial anthropometric measurements during pregnancy on a large cohort of HIV-infected women. However, with no HIV-uninfected comparison group in the BAN Study, we could not do a relative comparison with HIV-uninfected pregnant women. Hence, the focus of this analysis was the effects of nutrition status among HIV-infected pregnant women who received prenatal care on intrauterine growth and birth weight. Our sample comes from those who consented, tested positive for HIV/AIDS, and met the primary eligibility criteria. We do not have follow-up data on women with low CD4 counts or hemoglobin levels below 7 because they were considered ineligible for the BAN Study and referred to care. This is a plausible reason we were not able to derive a cutoff value for MUAC and LBW. However, in an analysis done on 300 women who did not participate, the descriptive characteristics were similar to our sample (unpublished data). Higher CD4 counts and low LBW prevalence in our sample may explain why we were unable to detect an association between maternal CD4 count or infant HIV status and LBW, as reported by other studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0884533611435991">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0884533611435991">40</xref></sup> In addition, regular antenatal care and prevention or monitoring and treatment for opportunistic infections may have attenuated any possible effects of HIV status on birth outcomes in this population.</p>
<p>Our study supports the use of MUAC as an efficient, cost-effective screening tool for LBW among HIV-infected women, as currently used among HIV-uninfected women,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0884533611435991">7</xref></sup> without concern for potential risk factors, such as seasonality, infectious disease, and poor SES conditions, often associated with adverse birth outcomes. Although we were unable to define a cutoff point that predicted LBW, according to previous reports, HIV-infected women who were wasting or had a MUAC of &lt;22 cm were found to have an increased risk of adverse pregnancy outcomes and death in African populations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0884533611435991">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0884533611435991">42</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>Financial disclosure: This analysis was funded by the National Institutes of Health R03 grant R03HD057637.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0884533611435991">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Villar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Belizán</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The timing factor in the pathophysiology of the intrauterine growth retardation syndrome</article-title>. <source>Obstet Gynecol Surv</source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>499</fpage>-<lpage>506</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0884533611435991">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>de Onis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blossner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Villar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Levels and patterns of intrauterine growth retardation in developing countries</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<supplement>suppl 1</supplement>): <fpage>S5</fpage>-<lpage>S15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0884533611435991">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ashworth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of intrauterine growth retardation on mortality and morbidity in infants and young children</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<supplement>suppl 1</supplement>):<fpage>S34</fpage>-<lpage>S41</lpage>; <comment>discussion S41-S42</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0884533611435991">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>In utero programming of cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>555</fpage>-<lpage>574</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0884533611435991">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>World Health Organization (WHO)</collab>. <article-title>Maternal anthropometry for prediction of pregnancy outcomes: memorandum from a USAID/WHO/PAHO/MotherCare meeting</article-title>. <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>523</fpage>-<lpage>532</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0884533611435991">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>World Health Organization (WHO)</collab>. <article-title>Maternal anthropometry and pregnancy outcomes. A WHO Collaborative Study</article-title>. <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<supplement>suppl</supplement>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0884533611435991">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization (WHO)</collab>. <source>Physical Status: The Use and Interpretation of Anthropometry</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>; <year>1995</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0884533611435991">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Villamor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baylin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Msamanga</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fawzi</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Weight loss during pregnancy is associated with adverse pregnancy outcomes among HIV-1 infected women</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1424</fpage>-<lpage>1431</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0884533611435991">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Friis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gomo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nyazema</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ndhlovu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaestel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krarup</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Michaelsen</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>HIV-1 viral load and elevated serum alpha(1)-antichymotrypsin are independent predictors of body composition in pregnant Zimbabwean women</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3747</fpage>-<lpage>3753</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0884533611435991">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Friis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gomo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nyazema</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ndhlovu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaestel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krarup</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Michaelsen</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Maternal body composition, HIV infection and other predictors of gestation length and birth size in Zimbabwe</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>833</fpage>-<lpage>840</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0884533611435991">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Belizán</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Villar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nardin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malamud</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Vicurna</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Diagnosis of intrauterine growth retardation by a simple clinical method: measurement of uterine height</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>1978</year>;<volume>131</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>643</fpage>-<lpage>646</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0884533611435991">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kevany</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Onis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A WHO Collaborative Study of Maternal Anthropometry and Pregnancy Outcomes</article-title>. <source>Int J Gynaecol Obstet</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>233</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0884533611435991">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ngare</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of low birthweight at the community level</article-title>. <source>East Afr Med J</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>296</fpage>-<lpage>299</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0884533611435991">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kotler</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Human immunodeficiency virus-related wasting: malabsorption syndromes</article-title>. <source>Semin Oncol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>25</volume>(2)(<supplement>suppl 6</supplement>):<fpage>70</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0884533611435991">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van der Horst</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chasela</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Modifications of a large HIV prevention clinical trial to fit changing realities: a case study of the Breastfeeding, Antiretroviral, and Nutrition (BAN) protocol in Lilongwe, Malawi</article-title>. <source>Contemp Clin Trials</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>24</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0884533611435991">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frisancho</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>New norms of upper limb fat and muscle areas for assessment of nutritional status</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2540</fpage>-<lpage>2545</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0884533611435991">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>Institute of Medicine (IOM)</collab>. <source>Nutrition During Pregnancy—Part I: Weight Gain</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>; <year>1990</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0884533611435991">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Traisathit</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Le Coeur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mary</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kanjanasing</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lamlerkittikul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lallemant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Gestational age determination and prevention of HIV perinatal transmission</article-title>. <source>Int J Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>176</fpage>-<lpage>180</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0884533611435991">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swingler</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Symphysis-fundus measurements in screening for small-for-dates infants: a community based study in Gloucestershire</article-title>. <source>J R Coll Gen Pract</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>319</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0884533611435991">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>World Health Organization (WHO) and United Nations Children’s Fund (UNICEF)</collab>. <source>Low Birthweight: Country, Regional and Global Estimates</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UNICEF</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0884533611435991">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kolenikov</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Angeles</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>The Use of Discrete Data in PCA: Theory, Simulations, and Applications to Socioeconomic Indices</source>. <publisher-loc>Chapel Hill</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and Carolina Population Center</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0884533611435991">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<source>STATA Statistical Software</source> [<comment>computer program</comment>]. <publisher-loc>Release 9. College Station, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>StataCorp LP</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0884533611435991">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gottschalk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moffitt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An analysis of sample attrition in panel data: the Michigan Panel Study of Income Dynamics</article-title>. <source>J Hum Resources</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>251</fpage>-<lpage>299</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0884533611435991">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hartikainen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maleta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kulmala</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ashorn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Seasonality of gestational weight gain and fetal growth in rural Malawi</article-title>. <source>East Afr Med J</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>82</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>294</fpage>-<lpage>299</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0884533611435991">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>World Food Programme (WFP)</collab>. <source>Malawi—2005/2006 Biennial Report</source>. <publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WFP</publisher-name>; <fpage>2005</fpage>-<lpage>2006</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0884533611435991">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harrell</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Regression Modeling Strategies: With Application to Linear Models, Logistic Regression and Survival Analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Science +Business Media</publisher-name>; <year>2001</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0884533611435991">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Willett</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Nutritional Epidemiology</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <volume>1998</volume>:<fpage>244</fpage>-<lpage>268</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0884533611435991">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Metaferia</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kafulafula</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malunga</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Birth weights and gestational ages of Malawian newborns at Queen Elizabeth Central Hospital—Blantyre Malawi—a retrospective analysis</article-title>. <source>Malawi Med J</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>88</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0884533611435991">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Enquoselassie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Minyilshewa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Changes in birthweight of hospital-delivered neonates in Addis Ababa</article-title>. <source>Ethiop J Health Dev</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>169</fpage>-<lpage>176</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0884533611435991">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hediger</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scholl</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schall</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Healey</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Changes in maternal upper arm fat stores are predictors of variation in infant birth weight</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>124</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>24</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0884533611435991">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ash</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Truswell</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Irwig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Maternal weight gain, smoking and other factors in pregnancy as predictors of infant birth-weight in Sydney women</article-title>. <source>Aust N Z J Obstet Gynaecol</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3, pt 1</issue>):<fpage>212</fpage>-<lpage>219</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0884533611435991">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pipe</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Halliday</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edmonds</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coltart</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Changes in fat, fat-free mass and body water in human normal pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Br J Obstet Gynaecol</source>. <year>1979</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>929</fpage>-<lpage>940</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0884533611435991">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Taggart</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holiday</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Billewics</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hytten</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomason</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Changes in skinfolds during pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source>. <year>1967</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>439</fpage>-<lpage>451</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0884533611435991">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MFS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNay</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>JEE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>First-trimester growth and the risk of low birth weight</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>339</volume>(<issue>25</issue>):<fpage>1817</fpage>-<lpage>1822</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0884533611435991">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The symphysis-fundus height graph and fetal growth retardation: gimmick or useful clinical tool?</article-title> <source>J Trop Pediatr</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>4</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0884533611435991">
<label>36.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bergstrom</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liljestrand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Parturient fundal height and its relation to fetal weight</article-title>. <source>J Trop Pediatr</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0884533611435991">
<label>37.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bergstrom</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Use of fundal height as a proxy for length of gestation in rural Africa</article-title>. <source>J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>169</fpage>-<lpage>172</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0884533611435991">
<label>38.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Langhoff-Roos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wibell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gebre-Medhin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindmark</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Placental hormones and maternal glucose metabolism: a study of fetal growth in normal pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Br J Obstet Gynaecol</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>320</fpage>-<lpage>326</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0884533611435991">
<label>39.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Msamanga</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Determinants of low birth weight among HIV-infected pregnant women in Tanzania</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>814</fpage>-<lpage>826</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0884533611435991">
<label>40.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mock</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhadrakom</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>., <article-title>Maternal viral load and timing of mother-to-child HIV transmission, Bangkok, Thailand. Bangkok Collaborative Perinatal HIV Transmission Study Group</article-title>. <source>AIDS</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>407</fpage>-<lpage>414</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0884533611435991">
<label>41.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lindan</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Serufilira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of mortality among HIV-infected women in Kigali, Rwanda</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>116</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>320</fpage>-<lpage>328</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0884533611435991">
<label>42.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Villamor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Msamanga</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>HIV status and sociodemographic correlates of maternal body size and wasting during pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Nutr</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>415</fpage>-<lpage>424</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>