<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CHD</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spchd</journal-id>
<journal-title>Childhood</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0907-5682</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7013</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0907568212458441</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0907568212458441</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Changing household dynamics: Children’s American generational resources in street vending markets</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Estrada</surname><given-names>Emir</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0907568212458441">University of Southern California, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0907568212458441">Emir Estrada, Department of Sociology, University of Southern California, Kaprielian 352, Los Angeles, CA 90089-2539, USA. Email: <email>emir.estrada@usc.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>20</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>51</fpage>
<lpage>65</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article prompts a re-visioning of segmented assimilation theory by examining the household dynamics and consequences that occur when Latino immigrant children and youth become active contributors to family street vending businesses. Based on participant observation and 20 in-depth interviews with Latino children who work with their immigrant parents as street vendors in Los Angeles, the article demonstrates how adolescent street vendors contribute to household decisions. It is argued that children in street vending families share power in the household because of: (1) their contributions to their family’s income; (2) their involvement in business negotiations and decision-making processes; and (3) their ‘American generational resources,’ which include English language skills, citizenship, and technological and popular culture knowledge, all valued by their parents and useful for the family street vending business.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Family–work relation</kwd>
<kwd>informal economy</kwd>
<kwd>Latino immigrant youth</kwd>
<kwd>street vending</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Sonia is a street vendor who sells fruit at a local park in Los Angeles from 10:00 a.m. to 5:00 p.m. on the weekend. After her long day of street vending at the park, Sonia goes to <italic>La Cumbrita</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0907568212458441">1</xref></sup> a small side street, and sells pirated DVDs from 7:00 p.m. to 11:00 p.m. Sonia is not your typical street vendor. At only 13 years old, she has been street vending with her parents since age 5. The sight of children working with their parents as street vendors is not an anomaly in Los Angeles. At <italic>La Cumbrita</italic>, it is common to see children preparing food, assisting their parents with cash transactions, and promoting their food to customers through a rhythmic chant of ‘<italic>tamales, papitas, platanos fritos</italic>,’ just like their parents taught them. Yet, despite the ubiquity of these young street vendors, we know very little about their work and family life experiences. This is in part because street vending and more specifically child street vending is seldom associated with developed countries like the US. Based on interview data and 9 months of participant observation, this article explores the role of children in household decision-making by addressing the following questions: (1) What role do children play in the decision to work? (2) How do they experience street vending? and (3) How does this process correspond with parent–child relations in the household?</p>
<sec id="section1-0907568212458441">
<title>Theoretical framework</title>
<p>Sociological scholarship on immigrant children and the children of immigrants has been guided by segmented assimilation theory showing how the children of post-1965 immigrants from Asia, the Caribbean, and Latin America are incorporating into the US (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0907568212458441">Portes and Rumbaut, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0907568212458441">Portes and Zhou, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0907568212458441">Zhou et al., 2008</xref>). Within this model, the children known as the 1.5 and second generation,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0907568212458441">2</xref></sup> are theorized as objects of socialization and acculturation, and language learners. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0907568212458441">Portes and Rumbaut (2001)</xref> children and their parents may achieve <italic>consonant acculturation</italic>, which may lead to upward mobility, when both children and parents gradually learn American culture and language because parents retain their authority over their children and can communicate with them in both their native language and in English. By contrast, they suggest that <italic>dissonant acculturation</italic>, associated with downward mobility, occurs when children learn American culture and language skills at a faster rate than their parents because parental authority is more likely to be undercut.</p>
<p>Segmented assimilation theory is a top-down acculturation model consistent with normative American beliefs of how children should be socialized. Children are normally thought to be dependent, socialized recipients of ‘cultural capital’ from their parents and not the other way around (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0907568212458441">Lareau, 2003</xref>). In the immigration literature, as Throne (1987) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0907568212458441">Orellana (2009)</xref> have indicated, children are often framed as ‘luggage,’ or as something that parents bring with them and not as full social actors. Children continue to be relegated to the separate sphere of family and school and are largely excluded from paid work.</p>
<p>The children in this study have a combination of resources I call <italic>American generational resources</italic> that their parents do not, including English language skills, citizenship, and knowledge of popular culture and technology. These resources help the family business and provide them with leverage and negotiation power in the household and in their family business. However, these resources do not undercut parental authority and lead to <italic>dissonant acculturation</italic> as segmented assimilation theory predicts. Analyzing the experience of adolescent street vendors in L.A. allows us to empirically learn more about this immigrant occupation<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0907568212458441">3</xref></sup> and, more broadly, it expands our knowledge of the immigration process that has largely excluded the experience of children as contributors to family processes and not only as objects of socialization.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0907568212458441">
<title>Literature review</title>
<p>Immigration literature illuminates some of the familial behavior transitions that occur as a result of immigration. Scholars have drawn attention to the changes that occur among spousal relations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0907568212458441">Fernandez-Kelly and Garcia, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0907568212458441">Hondagneu-Sotelo, 1994</xref>). When men are unable to be sole economic supporters, women must seek employment outside the home. As a result, men’s authority in the house is often diminished and inversely, these earnings give women agency and power within the household (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0907568212458441">Fernandez-Kelly and Garcia, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0907568212458441">Hondagneu-Sotelo, 1994</xref>). Migration has consequences that affect all family members, not only spouses. Segmented assimilation theory focuses on transitions as acculturation processes. The present study helps us to better understand these household dynamics and transitions. Like the women in previous household studies the youth in this study are also economic contributors and their work supplements the low earnings of their parents in the US.</p>
<p>Most research on children and work is mostly situated in ‘third world’ countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0907568212458441">Camacho, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0907568212458441">Jaquemin, 2004</xref>). Anthropologist <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0907568212458441">Gonzalez de la Rocha (1994)</xref> calls this household economic strategy the <italic>resources of poverty</italic>. She argues that power in the household is centralized in the patriarchal father, and women and children remain disenfranchised despite their labor contributions. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0907568212458441">Bunster and Chaney (1989</xref>: 174), in their study of street vendors in Peru, also found that fathers are the official decision-maker where their ‘<italic>machista</italic> authority is never questioned.’</p>
<p>In the US, low-income and working-class families also employ a family pooled income strategy where children also work. In studies of Mexican and Central American immigrant children in Los Angeles, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0907568212458441">Orellana (2009)</xref> documented children engaged in translating for parents and taking care of younger siblings. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0907568212458441">Park (2005)</xref> studied the children of Korean and Chinese immigrants who worked with their parents in family businesses such as restaurants and liquor stores. They also help the family with social adaptation by serving as translators and mediators between schoolteachers, doctors, and lawyers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0907568212458441">Katz, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0907568212458441">Orellana, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0907568212458441">Valenzuela, 1999</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0907568212458441">Vikki Katz (2010)</xref>, shows that the Latino children in Los Angles she researched are also <italic>media brokers</italic> for their immigrant parents. These families depend on their children to use old media (telephones and US mail) and new media (internet and cellular technologies) to integrate in the new society. These authors highlight the children’s contributions to their families, but they also recognize that mainstream society views their family contributions as anachronistic. It is now normative to think that children and teens require parental protection and economic support, and if children do work it is for their own pocket money or savings – not to help support the family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0907568212458441">Ong and Terriquez, 2008</xref>). This is in part due to the changing conceptions of what it means to be a child and how this has shaped the social value and appropriateness of children’s labor.</p>
<p>Yet, a quick look at history shows that the labor contribution of children in the family is not a new phenomenon. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0907568212458441">Viviana Zelizer (1985)</xref>, in her seminal book <italic>Pricing the Priceless Child</italic>, noted the transformation of the nineteenth-century ‘useful child,’ to the ‘useless’ yet ‘emotionally priceless’ twentieth-century child. The time when a child was valued for his or her economic contributions to the family is a practice of the nineteenth century that is now not only heavily criticized but also outlawed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0907568212458441">Zelizer, 2005</xref>). Unlike the children in previous studies, adolescent street vendors in L.A. are exposed to the public eye and local authorities that enforce child labor laws since the work they perform with their parents takes place in the public sphere – the street.</p>
<p>The children in this study earn income alongside their parents and are language and media brokers as well. These resources in addition to their citizenship are important in changing household dynamics because they allow children to contribute to the family’s social and economic adaptation in a unique way. In this study, children see their own citizenship, not as an individual right and privilege, but as a resource that can be used to help the family as a protection mechanism against the police. This is facilitated by the US context in which street vending takes place and the children’s distinctive resources that are also context based. For example, in Mexican and Peruvian household studies, children, like their mothers, are portrayed as victims of the patriarchal father, where the father has power over the resources and the decision-making process in the household (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0907568212458441">Bunster and Chaney,1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0907568212458441">Gonzalez de la Rocha, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0907568212458441">Torres, 2002</xref>). While citizenship, language skills, and popular culture knowledge may be irrelevant resources in a ‘third world’ context, they are valuable resources for street vending youth and their families in the US.</p>
<p>In Los Angeles, Latino immigrant children and adolescents working alongside their parents in informal sector occupations are both ubiquitous and seemingly invisible. Many immigrants from Mexico and Central America are relegated to working in the informal sector of the economy because they are educationally disadvantaged and lack the skills needed to find employment in the formal sector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0907568212458441">Cross and Morales, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0907568212458441">Hondagneu-Sotelo, 2001</xref>). In Los Angeles County there were an estimated 303,800 informal workers in 2004. According to the Census Bureau, 61% of the informal labor force in Los Angeles County is composed of undocumented immigrants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0907568212458441">Haydamack and Flaming, 2005</xref>). Scholars estimate that there are over 10,000 street vendors in Los Angeles, most of whom are Mexican and Central American (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0907568212458441">Muñoz, 2008</xref>). Yet, where are the children in this body of literature? This research fills this gap in the literature and in turn expands our knowledge of Latino immigrant families in the US by looking at family household dynamics from a child-centered perspective.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0907568212458441" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methodology</title>
<p>I conducted field observations for nine months at a site I call <italic>La Cumbrita.</italic> By day, <italic>La Cumbrita</italic> is an isolated strip surrounded by two parking lots just off a main avenue in Los Angeles. As soon as the sun sets, this street transforms into an informal lively open market. The families sell from 7:00 p.m. to 11:00 p.m. on Friday, Saturday, and Sunday. I was a participant observer at least one day a week. At first, I blended in with the customers and stood along the sidewalk eating food from paper plates or comfortably sat on folding chairs arranged in front of a small television provided by one of the street vendors. More than once I also enjoyed <italic>la novella Al Diablo Con Los Guapos</italic> (soap opera) or <italic>Sábado Gigante</italic> (Spanish language show). Later, I helped by running errands to the store. I also cut fruit and assisted customers while the children took bathroom breaks or socialized with their cousins and friends. More than once I helped the families hide their wares and food when police would threaten to take them away. As recommended by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0907568212458441">Emerson et al. (1995)</xref>, I kept a small notepad and pen and jotted notes when I was alone. I also recorded my observations during my drive home and later transcribed them. I spent time with families at other vending destinations during the day including parks, plazas, and at their homes and social events.</p>
<p>The 20 children and three parents I interviewed were recruited while they worked. I told them about my study while I purchased and ate their food. This practice was very successful. One mother told me she only agreed to participate in this study after I purchased a bag of fruit from her because cops or health inspectors do not buy food. Some families were afraid of me when I approached them. They thought I was an undercover police officer or a health inspector. Some street vendors were also leery of me because they believed a sociologist was a social worker and as such I could be looking to report instances of child exploitation.</p>
<p>My ability to speak Spanish without an accent helped me explain my research to the parents (all monolingual Spanish speakers) and ease their fears. Trust and rapport were enhanced when they learned about my own experience working with my parents in Mexico at our small grocery store, and in the US when my father worked as a parking attendant and my mother worked as a domestic and sewing operator. I also brought my 2-year-old daughter and mother to various site visits. Scholars have found that bringing family members, children specifically, helps establish rapport faster (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0907568212458441">Kaplan, 1997</xref>).</p>
<p>I used a semi-structured interview guide and I asked questions about the family business, the working arrangements with parents and siblings, household work, school, and future aspirations. All interviews were recorded and transcribed verbatim and lasted approximately 1–2 hours.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0907568212458441">
<title>Who are the children?</title>
<p>The youth in this study juggled school, family, and street vending responsibilities. Alicia, for example, street vends with her mother on the weekend and at the age of 16 she is already in charge of managing her mother’s finances. After street vending, Alicia puts money aside to buy more merchandise, pay the household bills, and for the last few months she has been allocating money for her high school graduation expenses. In addition to her school and street vending responsibilities, Alicia also helps take care of her sister (age 12) and two little stepbrothers (ages 5 and 4) by helping them with their homework, giving them baths, and babysitting them during the week nights when her mother and stepfather are street vending.</p>
<p>Like Alicia, my other respondents between the ages of 10 and 18<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0907568212458441">4</xref></sup> also juggled multiple responsibilities at home and school. Ten of my respondents were older than 16 years old. The rest were younger than 14 and only one was 10 years old. At the time of the interview, 18 of my respondents were in school and three were in private tuition based Catholic schools. I use the term children, adolescents, and youth interchangeably to refer to my respondents. While, in the US, the legal age of adulthood is 18, I recognize that childhood is a social construction and what is deemed appropriate activity for children varies across time and space (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0907568212458441">Ariès, 1962</xref>), and is situated within relations of race, nation, migration, and gender (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0907568212458441">Thorne et al., 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>The sample was not equally distributed by gender (4 males and 16 females). My time in the field revealed that more girls were engaged in this type of activity.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0907568212458441">5</xref></sup> Thirteen of my respondents were born in the US and the rest had immigrated with their parents at a very young age. Most respondents were of Mexican descent and three were from Central America. All the children in this study street vend with their parents on weekends and seven also do it after school. Only five got paid for their work ($5 to $30 per day).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0907568212458441">6</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0907568212458441">
<title>Children’s entrance into street vending</title>
<p>Street vending mothers often bring their toddlers with them as a babysitting strategy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0907568212458441">Muñoz, 2008</xref>). However, linger around <italic>La Cumbrita</italic> and you will notice that children are also vendors. Children do play and socialize when business is slow, but for the most part, they are busy charging customers, taking food orders, heating up tortillas, running errands to the store, and translating for parents. Most of the work they do is invisible to customers since it takes place at home where they cut, bag, sort, and cook the food they sell. For example, Noelia (age 14) is in charge of making seven types of sauces, Lolita (17) bags peanuts and the <italic>churros</italic> she makes at home, and Salvador (age 12) cooks the goat meat in their back yard while his mother and sister make the sauces and dice onions in the kitchen. What role then do children play in the decision to street vend? Do they unquestioningly follow orders from their patriarchal father, or is their input valued in the family? In the following paragraphs, the youth explain how they decided to street vend with their families.</p>
<sec id="section6-0907568212458441">
<title>Optional work</title>
<p>Repeatedly, the youth highlighted how the decision to street vend was their own. As a researcher, I was constantly aware of my position and wondered if their responses were post-facto rationalizations – something they felt compelled to tell me. This is ultimately left for the reader to judge. However, the degree of their agency was made more compelling when I learned that many of my respondents had siblings who opted not to street vend. Out of the 20 children interviewed, 17 had siblings living at home who did not work with the family. The three remaining were Edgar (age 13) and Eric (age 18), who had no siblings and Carmen (age 18), whose siblings also street vended. Some boys in the family, however, were able to ‘slack off’ street vending responsibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0907568212458441">Estrada and Hondagneu-Sotelo, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0907568212458441">Estrada and Hondagneu-Sotelo, forthcoming 2013</xref>).</p>
<p>According to some parents, street vending is an optional activity for children. Jose described his children’s work as ‘going to the park’:<disp-quote>
<p>It’s work without being work. It’s helping the family, but in a different way because it’s optional. . . . Well, we always ask them [the children] if they want to come and if they say yes, then we come. It’s like when we go to the park. If you say, do you want to go to the park, and they say let’s go, then we go. (Author’s translation)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Jose’s children were interviewed separately and both echoed his views about street vending. When I asked his daughter Chayo (age 14) if she had to street vend with her father she said, ‘No, I don’t have to come.’ Both Chayo and her brother Juan (age 10) did not feel obligated to help their father; but both knew that failing to help him also meant missing out on the family business earnings of $20 each. Said Juan, ‘I like helping my family and all because I want them to do me a birthday party. . . . That’s why I’m trying to earn money to do it myself.’</p>
<p>For some children, the decision to help was, indeed, like deciding to go to the park. Linda and Susana, two sisters who sold <italic>pupusas</italic> with their parents, agreed to help in a very nonchalant manner. Linda explained, ‘One day [my mother] just told us if we wanted to come and sell. We were like “Sure we don’t have anything else good to do.” ’ According to Susana, she and her sister used to ‘take turns’ going with their mother when they sold <italic>pupusas</italic> door to door before they sold at <italic>La Cumbrita</italic>.</p>
<p>For others, deciding to street vend was anything but a walk at the park. Norma (age 18) and her brother Salvador (age 12) were faced with an important decision to make when their father lost his job soon after their arrival in the US from Mexico, where they had lived with their mother. This family experienced ambivalence. On the one hand, they rejoiced being together again after a long period of separation. On the other hand, they were faced with the harsh economic reality of unemployment. With his family now in the US, Norma’s father had to find a way to make money fast but was unable to find a job in the formal sector due to his undocumented status. When Norma’s father had the idea to sell <italic>tacos de barbacoa</italic> (goat meat), he first asked his children if they would agree to help. Norma explained:<disp-quote>
<p>My father asked us if we would agree to sell <italic>tacos de barbacoa</italic> on the street and he also asked if we could help him because they were not going to be able to do this on their own, and we said yes.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This is a typical conversation between parents and children when negotiating a family-based business where children, such as Norma and Samuel, also weigh in on the decision to street vend.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section7-0907568212458441">
<title>Decision-making power</title>
<p>Adolescents were intricately involved in the family’s decision-making process. Most of the youth knew how the business functioned, how much money it generated, and they constantly had innovative ideas to increase the family’s revenue. This is atypical for most children according to western modernity. Children are believed to be oblivious to adult worries such as work and finances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0907568212458441">Orellana, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0907568212458441">Valenzuela, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0907568212458441">Zelizer, 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0907568212458441">2005</xref>).</p>
<p>These relations between parents and children became very clear during one of my evening field visits when I witnessed a conversation between Susana (age 14), her parents, and Gregorio, a local Latino gang leader. This conversation took place at 1:00 a.m. Only the dim lights from the two light bulbs tied on a stick above the taco stand illuminated the liquor store driveway that now served as an outdoor eatery.</p>
<p>Susana’s father was already talking to Gregorio when we arrived. Immediately, Susana and her mother joined in on the conversation while I stood next to them as if I was their shadow without participating in the discussion. Gregorio was dressed in black with an oversized jacket and wore a black cap covering his dazed eyes as if he was drugged.</p>
<p>The conversation centered on street vending issues such as fights among street vendors, competition over space, and the self-initiated efforts from the street vendors to get vending permits from the city. Gregorio advocated for peace at <italic>La Cumbrita</italic> exclaiming, ‘We have to stop this north versus south side issue,’ referring to the fights between vendors from the different sides of the street. Susana’s mother interjected and said she would not go to the meeting organized by vendors to discuss issues concerning street vending. Gregorio immediately shifted his attention to Susana’s mother and in a condescending tone told her in broken Spanish, ‘I understand you don’t want to go, but I think it would be a good idea. Please don’t get offended, but I’m going talk to your husband now’ (author’s translation). Gregorio turned towards the father once more and said, ‘As the man of the house, I think you should put a stop to this,’ referring to the fights, and he suggested they leave <italic>La Cumbrita</italic> to sell their tacos and <italic>pupusas</italic> at this new spot.</p>
<p>This time Susana interjected, ‘I don’t think we should leave. Then, they will think we just gave up and that they were able to push us out. We can’t move!’ she stated firmly. Gregorio then turned towards her, looked her straight in the eyes and told her in English and in a low tone of voice. ‘<italic>Mija</italic>, what you need to do is this. You know when you want to go to a party and you convince your parents to let you go? You put a lot of effort into convincing your parents to let you go, right? Well <italic>mija</italic>, I need you to put the same amount of effort and help me convince your father to just leave <italic>La Cumbrita.</italic>’</p>
<p>Children are involved in the decisions over where the family street vends. Even though Susana’s father was overshadowed by his wife’s and daughter’s strong character and firm opinions, Gregorio incorrectly assumed that the father alone held the power in the family to make decisions regarding the family and their business. Repeatedly, Gregorio refocused his attention and energy on the husband and talked to him like the ‘man of the house,’ as if he were the sole decision-maker. When the mother stated that she would not go to the meeting, Gregorio ignored her comment and told her he was going to talk to her husband instead. Yet, when Susana interjected, Gregorio recognized Susana’s potential to persuade her father. Gregorio did not push her aside like he did the mother, but instead asked for her assistance in convincing her father to move out of <italic>La Cumbrita</italic>. When I spoke to Susana the following week, she said, ‘I told my parents not to move, I like it here better,’ referring to <italic>La Cumbrita</italic>.</p>
<p>Some children were very influential in important family decisions. For example, Veronica (age 18) convinced her father to street vend full-time and quit his back-breaking job as a driver. During our interview, Veronica told me she was tired of seeing her parents suffer at their jobs. Her dad constantly suffered from back pain and her mother ‘always used to come like all stressed’ from her job at the factory. Since Veronica’s father knew how to make <italic>tejuino</italic> (a corn based drink), she encouraged her parents to leave their jobs, after her calculations revealed that they would make more money selling <italic>tejuino</italic>. Veronica got scared after her parents followed up on her proposal because the money they made from selling <italic>tejuino</italic> became their only source of income:<disp-quote>
<p>I’ll be scared cuz what [if] we didn’t make that much money and I had already told my dad that it’s better [that] we work here because we make more money. But no, I [have] seen the difference and yeah [my father] was even happy. He was like . . . ‘it was good that you told me . . . that it’s better right here [selling <italic>tejuino</italic>] than over there [previous job].</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The youth in this study were business savvy and they constantly had ideas of how to increase revenues. Unlike studies of households where children were disenfranchised and obligated to obey their father when he would ‘order them to get out of the house and sell merchandise he would bring home’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0907568212458441">Bunster and Chaney, 1989</xref>: 174), the adolescents in this study were an important part of the decision-making process.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0907568212458441">
<title>Children’s American generational resources</title>
<p>Adolescent street vendors in this study have leverage in the family business and decision-making power in the household because they have <italic>American generational resources</italic> including citizenship, English language skills, and knowledge of popular culture and technology. These resources are valued by the parents and useful for the family business. The following section shows how these <italic>American generational resources</italic> empower children in everyday street vending and family life interaction.</p>
<sec id="section9-0907568212458441">
<title>Citizenship: ‘Dude, I was born here!’</title>
<p>US citizenship for these children and their families is a valuable resource. The parents in this study, as other studies have found, were undocumented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0907568212458441">Dohan, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0907568212458441">Hamilton and Chinchilla, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0907568212458441">Muñoz, 2008</xref>). Only one parent was a legal resident. Yet, over half of the children in this sample (13 out of 20) were born and raised in the US and thus challenge our assumptions about this occupation.</p>
<p>Children often cited their parents’ lack of citizenship in their decision to street vend. ‘My mom can’t work [elsewhere] because she doesn’t have papers,’ said Esmeralda (age 13). Similarly, Norma’s father, a sewing operator, got fired after his employers did a mass document verification search at the factory and now they turned to street vending. Andrea (age 18) said with resignation: ‘Before I wasn’t planning to help them [street vend] . . . but now, like, I have to because they can’t get hired or else they’re going to get sent to Mexico.’ The underlying fear for these young street vendors was the fear of being separated from their parents via deportation.</p>
<p>Undocumented status made parents vulnerable to local authorities, but the children’s US citizenship provided them and their families with a unique resource. Even having legal permanent residency afforded little security for parents. For example, Katia’s mother is a legal US resident with legal authorization to work in the US. Katia’s mother worked in the formal sector of the economy as a janitor for many years, but for the last 16 years had been selling fruit with her daughter because she makes more money and has a more flexible schedule. Even though street vending is a better work arrangement for her, street vending is illegal in Los Angeles and thus, her permit to work in the US does not protect her from police harassment when she is street vending. Katia, narrated how she has helped her mother hide from the police on several occasions because she fears that her mother will lose her residency if she gets too many citations for street vending:<disp-quote>
<p><italic>Mi mamá agarraba</italic> [my mom would get] tickets and tickets. <italic>Mi mamá</italic> [My mom] has papers, so you know, [it] is bad for her record. It’s bad for her record because she could lose her papers, I guess.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>According to Katia, her mother was only a resident and thus enjoyed a temporary status that could easily be taken away. Katia, on the other hand, was a US citizen by birth and her citizenship was a privilege she did not risk losing because of her street vending work. Similarly, 16-year-old Sonia said this:<disp-quote>
<p>I can’t get in trouble as much as she can. . . . Like the worst thing they [the police] can probably do is give me a ticket cuz I’m still a minor. And well with her [my mother] they may take her to jail and who knows like, she may have her papers . . . but that can change.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Sonia and Katia’s concerns are not far from reality. The Illegal Immigrant Reform and Immigrant Responsibility Act (IIRIRA ) of 1996 imposed provisions that could mean deportation for current US residents ‘deemed likely to become a public charge’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0907568212458441">Afrasiabi, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0907568212458441">Chang and Boos, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The children’s citizenship was not only an immediate resource for the family. Esmeralda (age 12) saw her own citizenship as an opportunity to invest in her education with the purpose of helping her parents in the future. Esmeralda, who sells fruit with her mother, plans to go to school to become a lawyer in order to help ‘fix . . . [her] mom’s problems .’ Esmeralda explained that with a law degree she would help people, like her mother, who did not have papers, ‘so she [her mom] could have a good work . . . cuz she doesn’t really like that job [street vending].’</p>
<p>US citizenship also granted these children the opportunity to get a driver’s license. Street vending requires these families to drive and transport heavy wares. Most parents drive without a license and risk getting fines or getting their cars confiscated. When I met Noemi (age 16) she told me she was saving money to get her driver’s license in order to be able to drive their van without constantly fearing the police.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0907568212458441">
<title>English language skills</title>
<p>The ability to speak English is known to give children an upper hand in day-to-day interactions in US society (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0907568212458441">Portes and Rumbaut, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0907568212458441">Portes and Zhou, 1993</xref>). However, for young street vendors, the ability to speak English is a resource for the entire family because knowing English mitigates the illegality of their work. It also helps them expose their business to non-Latino/Spanish-speaking clientele.</p>
<p>Lack of English language skills makes street vendors more vulnerable to police harassment and discrimination. Being able to communicate with the police eases the aggression against street vendors. Sofia explains that she feels comfortable letting her daughters (ages 16 and 17) street vend alone because they speak English:<disp-quote>
<p>The police approach the people that don’t speak [English]. And [the police] gets mad. But when [my daughters] respond back to them [in English] ‘ok then I’ll move’ . . . then [the cops] say ‘well you know you can’t street vend here because someone called us and they don’t want you to be here.’ But [the cops] do discriminate when you don’t speak the language. (Author’s translation)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Sofia, like others in this study, recognize that speaking English is an important asset for the business, and this is a skill that mostly children possess. According to Sofia, the police approach the street vendors assuming that they do not understand or speak English. When they come with these preconceptions, they are loud and rude to street vendors who do not comply with the police officer’s orders or who cannot defend themselves verbally. Children, on the other hand, comply with the orders both by putting away their street vending goods and by telling the police they understand.</p>
<p>Speaking English also serves to increase clientele. Contrary to the common belief that street vendors are only patronized by Latino Spanish speakers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0907568212458441">Dohan, 2003</xref>), the street vendors’ clientele were becoming increasingly diverse. For example, Susana (age 14), told me that ‘Koreans, Latinos, and White people’ purchased <italic>pupusas</italic> from her family. When asked about her experience with these customers, she replied: ‘It’s the same because I speak English; and then I ask them what I want so I treat them the same. I speak both languages.’ For Susana, being bilingual made her comfortable when interacting with non-Spanish speakers. Susana’s mother, on the other hand, was a little uncomfortable with non-Spanish speakers. Below is an excerpt from my field notes when Susana translates for an Asian couple eager to taste <italic>pupusas</italic> for the first time:<disp-quote>
<p>An Asian couple approached the <italic>pupusa</italic> stand and asked the cook, Hilda, what she was selling. Without saying a word, Hilda turns to her daughter Susana and immediately Susana explains to the couple, in English, that <italic>pupusas are</italic> like Mexican <italic>gorditas</italic> but traditionally from El Salvador and Honduras. ‘We put cheese or <italic>chicharrón</italic> inside and then put cabbage and sauce over it once they are cooked.’</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Meanwhile, Hilda remained silent, continuing to make the <italic>pupusas</italic>; with a clap-like-motion she molded the <italic>pupusa</italic> to an almost perfect flat circle and carefully softened the rough edges with her index finger.</p>
<p>For many Latino families, it is common for children to serve as translators and mediators between their parents and schoolteachers, doctors, or even lawyers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0907568212458441">Orellana, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0907568212458441">Valenzuela, 1999</xref>). Among street vending families, speaking English and translating for the parents also has positive consequences for the family’s income. Customers were often surprised to learn that street vendors spoke English. When I went street vending with Martha (age 17), two young men approached us on the street. They spoke to one another in English and switched to Spanish when they addressed us. Martha rolled her eyes annoyed by the customer’s assumption that she did not speak English. During my interview with Martha she explained:<disp-quote>
<p>They [customers] are like ‘I can’t believe you are helping your dad. And you know English!’ I mean even most of the people . . . are like ‘oh my God I can’t believe you know English’ and I am like ‘dude I was born here, what is wrong with you?’</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Martha’s ability to speak English challenged the customers’ stereotypes of street vendors as undocumented monolingual Spanish speakers. But most importantly, speaking English allowed her to establish rapport with diverse customers, build a steady clientele, and ultimately generate more revenues for the family.</p>
<p>Similarly, Lolita also sold corn on the cob to non-Hispanic and non-Spanish speakers. Lolita, her father, and uncle each separately pushed their carts around a large park with a lake. Lolita had Indian customers who only purchased corn on the cob from her. She boasted:<disp-quote>
<p>There are these Indian people and they always come to me. My uncle would pass or my dad would pass and they would not go with them they would go with me. And a lot of people do that. They are like, ‘yeah we were looking for you.’ And I could be like on the opposite side and they will go all the way over there just to look for me.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Even though her relatives sold the same food she did, Lolita believes customers liked her better because she spoke English. Unlike her father and uncle, she was able to establish a customer and vendor relation by simply having informal conversations with clients in English.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0907568212458441">
<title>Access to technology and knowledge of popular culture</title>
<p>It is common for children to serve as <italic>media brokers</italic> for their immigrant parents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0907568212458441">Katz, 2010</xref>). My respondents were into technology (computers, video games, cell phones) and US popular culture like music, movies, and clothing. Parents and children alike used cell phones to communicate while street vending. However, children also used their smart phones to promote the family business by creating and updating their social pages including Facebook and Twitter with information about their business. One Facebook message from Jazmin read ‘We don’t Sell Today Due To The Weather :/ <italic>Hoy No Vendemos Pero Los Esperamos Mañana</italic>!!’ This task was solely the child’s responsibility. When I asked parents if they knew how to update the pages they usually replied, ‘I don’t even know how to turn on a computer.’</p>
<p>Children were also aware of internet blogs mentioning <italic>La Cumbrita</italic> and their <italic>puesto</italic> (street vending stand). Some internet blogs were from L.A. <italic>foodies</italic>. Others were from recognized newspaper reporters. <italic>La Cumbrita</italic> was ‘a must’ according to some of these bloggers who recommended this place for its authentic ethnic food. Children sometimes used these blogs to lure in customers. On one occasion, one of my respondents and his family catered for an event attended by the Los Angeles Mayor. The young street vendor showed me a cell phone picture of them with Mayor Villaraigosa. While this picture was taken, he told the mayor ‘the police tells us that you sent them,’ referring to their current struggle with the police. He also directed him to the website where people praised their food.</p>
<p>Sonia (age 13) sold DVDs and CDs with her parents and her knowledge of popular culture benefited the family business. On our way to a Halloween party, I saw how Sonia selected the movies they sold from their distributor. I was sitting in the back of their 2007 Yukon truck when their distributor dealt directly with 13-year-old Sonia and not with her father or mother. Sonia made sure they got the correct number of movies and requested more of the popular movies. ‘I need three more <italic>High School Musical</italic>,’ she told their distributor. She passed the movies to me and asked, ‘have you seen this one?’ and then randomly stated, ‘This one is good. We sell this one a lot.’</p>
<p>While street vendors do not depend on social pages for their business, we do see that children are applying their knowledge of popular media and culture to outreach to a larger audience. In fact, this is already a popular strategy among sophisticated food truck businesses in Los Angeles and New York (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0907568212458441">Zukin, 2010</xref>). It is in this realm that children of street vendors are the experts and the parents take on a more auxiliary role.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section12-0907568212458441">
<title>Concluding remarks</title>
<p>Immigrant children are important members in the family, however they remain obscure in the scholarly literature dominated by the male migratory model. By looking at the youth’s participation in this occupation, we come to understand street vending in a more complex manner. This study also illuminates the immigration experience in ways that a focus on adults only, or children only as objects of socialization cannot do. As this study shows, children are not the ‘baggage’ that adult immigrants simply bring along. In the case of street vendors, we see that they are also contributors to family processes.</p>
<p>This article sheds light on the labor contributions of Latino adolescent street vendors in Los Angeles and shows from their standpoint how they experience street vending – a racialized immigrant occupation. Their stories demonstrate that not all Latino vendors are undocumented and Spanish monolinguals. The youth in this study can communicate in English with peers and customers, they have better knowledge of American popular culture and technology, and most are US citizens. The aforementioned are what I call <italic>American generational resources.</italic> These are unique resources these young street vendors possess that their immigrant parents do not. Yet, rather than seeing this as a disadvantage or a <italic>dissonant form of acculturation</italic>, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0907568212458441">Portes and Rumbaut (2001)</xref> would argue, the children in this study benefit from these resources and in turn benefit their street vending family business. These children are in many ways apprentices to their parents, who carry the cultural knowledge of cooking traditional ethnic foods. However, the children’s <italic>American generational resources</italic> allows the youth to support that work and make it possible for their parents to sell to more people. The adolescents in this study are not marginalized, exploited family members, but rather co-economic providers with parents. This type of family–work relation allows us to see that parent-child relations do not always fall into a top-down hierarchical model. Here we are able to see that parents also learn and benefit from their children’s skills and knowledge.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<notes><fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0907568212458441">
<label>1.</label>
<p>All names are pseudonyms.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0907568212458441">
<label>2.</label>
<p>The second generation are US born children of immigrant parents. The 1.5 generation are children born outside the US, who immigrated before the age of 13.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0907568212458441">
<label>3.</label>
<p>The focus has been on first generation immigrants.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0907568212458441">
<label>4.</label>
<p>One respondent was 21. She was interviewed because she had been street vending with her mother since age 5.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0907568212458441">
<label>5.</label>
<p>For a more in-depth gender analysis of this study, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0907568212458441">Estrada and Hondagneu-Sotelo (forthcoming 2013)</xref>.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0907568212458441">
<label>6.</label>
<p>For a more in-depth analysis, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0907568212458441">Estrada and Hondagneu-Sotelo (forthcoming 2013)</xref>.</p></fn>
</fn-group></notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Afrasiabi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Show Trials: How Property Gets More Legal Protection Than People in Our Failed Immigration System</article-title>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Envelope Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ariès</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1962</year>) <source>Centuries of Childhood: A Social History of Family Life</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Vintage Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bunster</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chaney</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>Sellers and Servants Working Women in Lima, Peru</source>. <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bergin and Garvey</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>AZV</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Family, child labour and migration: Child domestic workers in metro Manila</article-title>. <source>Childhood</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Chang &amp; Boos</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The Illegal Immigration Reform and Immigrant Responsibility Act of 1996</article-title>. Chang &amp; Boos Attorneys-at-Law. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.americanlaw.com/1996law.html">www.americanlaw.com/1996law.html</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 25 September 2009</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Introduction: Locating street markets in the modern/postmodern world</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Street Entrepreneurs: People, Place and Politics in Local and Global Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dohan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Price of Poverty: Money, Work, and Culture in the Mexican American Barrio</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley and Los Angeles</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fretz</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Writing Ethnographic Fieldnotes</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Estrada</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hondagneu-Sotelo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Intersectional dignities: Latino immigrant street vendor youth in Los Angeles</article-title>. <source>Journal of Contemporary Ethnography</source> <volume>40</volume>(<issue>1</issue>) <fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>131</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Estrada</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hondagneu-Sotelo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Forthcoming <month>July</month> <day>13</day>, <year>2013</year>) <article-title>Latina Adolescent Street Vendors in Los Angeles: Gendered Streetwise?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Flores-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romina Guevarra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toro-Morn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Immigrant Women Workers in the Neoliberal Age</source>. <publisher-loc>Urbana, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Illinois Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fernandez-Kelly</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Power surrendered, power restored: The politics of work and family among Hispanic garment workers in California and Florida</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Tilly</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gurin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Women, Politics and Change</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Russell Sage Foundation</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gonzalez de la Rocha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>The Resources of Poverty: Women and Survival in a Mexican City</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chinchilla</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Seeking Community in Global City: Guatemalan &amp; Salvadorans in Los Angeles</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haydamack</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Flaming</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Hopeful workers, marginal jobs: LA’s off-the-books labor force</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Economic Roundtable</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Underwritten by the City of Los Angeles’ LA Economy Project</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hondagneu-Sotelo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Gendered Transitions: Mexican Experiences of Immigration</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley and Los Angeles</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hondagneu-Sotelo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Domestica: Immigrant Workers Cleaning and Caring in the Shadows of Affluence</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley and Los Angeles</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jacquemin</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Children’s domestic work in Abidjan, Cote d’Ivoire: The petites bonnes have the floor</article-title>. <source>Childhood</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Black teenage mothers and their mothers: The impact of adolescent childbearing on daughters’ relationships with mothers</article-title>. <source>Social Problems</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Media connecting family and community</article-title>. <source>Journal of Children and Media</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lareau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Unequal Childhoods: Class, Race, and Family Life</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley and Los Angeles</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="thesis">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muñoz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Tamales…Elotes…Champurrado’: The production of Latino vending landscapes in Los Angeles</source>. PhD Dissertation, <publisher-name>Department of Geography</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>University of Southern California</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Terriquez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Can multiple pathways offset inequalities in the urban spatial structure?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Oakes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Beyond Tracking: Multiple Pathways to College, Career, and Civic Participation</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard Education Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Orellana</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Translating Childhoods: Immigrant Youth, Language, and Culture</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rutgers University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Consuming Citizenship: Children of Asian Immigrant Entrepreneurs</source>. <publisher-loc>Stanford: CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Portes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rumbaut</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Legacies: The Story of the Second Generation</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley and Los Angeles</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Portes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The new second generation: Segmented assimilation and its variants</article-title>. <source>Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science</source> <volume>530</volume> (<issue>November</issue>): <fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thorne</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orellana</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>WSE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Raising children, and growing up across national borders: Comparative perspectives on age, gender and migration</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hondagneu-Sotelo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Gender and U.S. Immigration: Contemporary Trends</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Making Ends Meet: Income-generating Strategies among Mexican Immigrants</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>LFB Scholarly Publishing LLC</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Gender roles and settlement activities among children and their immigrant families</article-title>. <source>American Behavioral Scientist</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>720</fpage>–<lpage>742</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zelizer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <source>Pricing the Priceless Child: The Changing Social Value of Children</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zelizer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Kids and commerce</article-title>. <source>Childhood</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>396</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zelizer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The priceless child revisited</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Qvortrup</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Studies in Modern Childhood: Society, Agency and Culture</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>184</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Agius Vallejo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Success attained, deterred, and denied: Divergent pathways to social mobility in Los Angeles’s new second generation</article-title>. <source>Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science</source> <volume>620</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0907568212458441">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zukin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Naked City: The Death and Life of Authentic Urban Places</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>