<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ISP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spisp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Soc Psychiatry</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Journal of Social Psychiatry</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0020-7640</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-2854</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0020764012463520</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0020764012463520</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book review: Trichotillomania, skin picking and other body-focused repetitive behaviours</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bhugra</surname><given-names>Dinesh</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0020764012463520">King’s College London</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>59</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>190</fpage>
<lpage>191</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keuthen</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.), <source>Trichotillomania, skin picking and other body-focused repetitive behaviours</source>, <publisher-name>APPI</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <year>2012</year>. ISBN <isbn>978 1 58562 398 3</isbn> (pbk); pp. <page-count count="xv"/> + <page-count count="252"/>. <price>$59.00</price>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Chronic hair pulling (trichotillomania), skin picking and other body-focused repetitive behaviours are relatively rare but intriguing and often difficult to manage for a number of reasons. As the editors say in their introduction, the main aim of this book is to educate clinicians about these conditions and to encourage research. To this end, they and their contributors have succeeded remarkably well. The multi-authored volume has 13 chapters, divided into three sections. The first section deals with clinical characteristics, the second provides an overview of diagnosis and evaluation, and the last section deals with treatment strategies. Trichotillomania is said to be more common than previously believed, and the prevalence is reportedly around 4%, but this range can be attributed to inconsistencies in diagnosis and variability in diagnostic patterns. There also appear to be cultural and ethnic differences in rates, although epidemiological data across cultures are limited. Trichotillomania is said to start in the early teens, with equal gender distribution and fairly similar psychopathology. Different hair-pulling sites have been described, with potentially reinforcing consequences. Pathological skin picking is said to occur in nearly 5% of the general population, although epidemiological data are extremely limited. The age of onset is described as trimodal (under 10, 15–21 and then 30–45). It occurs much more frequently in females and can lead to significant tissue damage. Motor stereotypes include thumb sucking, nail biting, rhythmic stereotypic movements and head banging. There may be associated co-morbidities, and psychological and dermatological assessments are needed. Assessments need to be multi-modal, involving clinicians, patients, families and teachers, among others. Managing these conditions will include rapport building, education, cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT), family work, response prevention and pharmacotherapy, among other strategies. There is plenty of material in this slim volume for clinicians and researchers alike.</p>
</body>
</article>