<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PRQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spprq</journal-id>
<journal-title>Political Research Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1065-9129</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-274X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1065912911398048</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1065912911398048</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Making Voting Easier</article-title>
<subtitle>Convenience Voting in the 2008 Presidential Election</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>R. Michael</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1065912911398048">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>Ines</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1065912911398048">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>J. Andrew</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1065912911398048">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1065912911398048"><label>1</label>California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1065912911398048">Ines Levin, California Institute of Technology, MC 228-77, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA 91125, USA. Email: <email>ilevin@hss.caltech.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>65</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>248</fpage>
<lpage>262</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 University of Utah</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="other">University of Utah</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The authors analyze the choice of voting mode in the 2008 presidential election using a large-sample survey with national coverage that allows a new perspective of convenience voting. Most importantly, they make clear distinctions among the major forms of convenience voting and demonstrate that not all “convenience voters” share the same attributes. In addition, the authors find little support for the hypothesis that convenience voting methods have partisan implications, despite the differences among mail, early, and election-day voters. Results like these have important implications for future moves toward convenience voting and the design of new outreach campaigns.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>convenience voting</kwd>
<kwd>early voting</kwd>
<kwd>2008 presidential election</kwd>
<kwd>multilevel modeling</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A basic observation motivates our research: in a democracy, election rules matter. How elections are administered can change the costs of elections, voter satisfaction with the process, the strategies campaigns pursue, the election’s integrity, and who wins the election. In recent decades, at the federal, state, and local levels officials and legislators have taken steps to make participating in elections more convenient. One approach is broadly called “convenience voting,” including both in-person early voting and voting by mail. Our goal is to examine who takes advantage of these alternatives to better understand the consequences of convenience.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1065912911398048">Berinsky (2005</xref>, 482) argues that this question is closed. “All told,” he writes, “using a variety of methods and data sources to assess the effect of different voting reforms, a series of scholars have come to a single conclusion.” He observes that studies indicate convenience voters are “more politically engaged” and are likely to be wealthier and better educated. In other words, convenience voters are likely voters.</p>
<p>We believe that this debate is far from settled. It is not the case that scholars have come to a “single” conclusion; rather than providing a single clear picture, the literature presents a murky view. There is some interesting and well-considered research on this topic, but other studies are less convincing. In addition, convenience voting is a broad topic, and much research focuses on a single election, single state, or small number of survey respondents. This is understandable, and not necessarily a criticism, but the limited scope of the existing literature demands more study before the question is considered closed.</p>
<p>There is also simply the matter of time. For example, one of the early and oft-cited articles is <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1065912911398048">Patterson and Caldeira’s (1985)</xref> study. In 1982, 6.5 percent of California voters utilized the recently introduced no-excuse absentee voting law; many of them cast ballots for Republican George Deukmejian and landed him in the governor’s office. Decades later in the 2008 June primary, 59 percent of California voters submitted ballots by mail; in the 2008 November general election, 42 percent of California voted by mail. It is not appropriate to draw conclusions about the voting behavior of nearly half of California’s voters in 2008 based on research regarding the behavior of a small fraction of California’s electorate in 1982. Nor is it appropriate to apply conclusions from the study of by-mail voting in California in 1982 to in-person early voters in Texas in 2010. Thus, we believe that the effects of convenience voting reforms in recent years deserve study.</p>
<p>We intend to clarify our understanding of convenience voting. We make clear the distinction between in-person early voting and by-mail voting, a place of confusion in the application of previous research. We use a large-sample national survey from 2008 to study the choice of voting mode—Election Day, early, and by mail—in the 2008 election. To estimate a well-specified model of individual voter choices regarding how to cast their ballots, we use a Bayesian hierarchical multinomial logit model. This allows us to better understand the choices made by voters, which will give a greater understanding of the effects of allowing more convenience voting.</p>
<sec id="section1-1065912911398048">
<title>Previous Research</title>
<p>The question “who uses which voting alternative” should be fairly straightforward if the data are readily available. Unfortunately, the data are not. The diversity of approaches used in the literature reflects a variety of methods political scientists have used to study this question. We are not immune to some of the difficulties previous authors encountered; for example, we conducted this survey only in 2008. To offset the weakness of using a single election, our approach has some advantages relative to previous studies: our national coverage, large sample size, sophisticated methodology, and analytic distinction between “early in-person” and “by-mail” voting.</p>
<p>Early studies used county-level election and census data to infer which demographic variables were associated with high levels of absentee voting.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1065912911398048">1</xref></sup> The advantage of this approach is the availability of election data over a long period of time: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1065912911398048">Patterson and Caldeira (1985)</xref> put together three California elections and a single Iowa election, while <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1065912911398048">Dubin and Kalsow (1996)</xref> compiled data from thirty-three California elections. The main methodological disadvantage of these studies is the unresolved ecological inference problem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1065912911398048">King 1997</xref>). While the conclusions of the Patterson and Caldeira article are widely cited in the literature—“partisan candidates are likely to harvest absentee votes in the very localities where their party is otherwise strong”—this conclusion is drawn from separate ordinary least squares regressions run on data from these four, decades-old, elections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1065912911398048">Patterson and Caldeira 1985</xref>, 766). Nevertheless, this sort of approach formed the original foundation for our research; their conclusions suggest that likely voters are also likely convenience voters, and we started from that hypothesis.</p>
<p>Another branch of the literature that informed our expectations and choices of independent variables focuses on Oregon’s transition to a vote-only-by-mail (VOBM) system. Oregon switched in the late 1990s to conducting all of its elections entirely through the mail. Political scientists have studied whether this switch changed turnout or changed the composition of the electorate, demographically or politically. It is difficult to say whether conclusions drawn from the Oregon experience might apply in other states or on the national level. For example, if the VOBM system resulted in a higher proportion of elderly voters participating, this could be because elderly voters found the VOBM system easier or because younger voters found the <italic>absence</italic> of a traditional polling place to be an obstacle. Nevertheless, this literature can provide important clues for how to approach the national convenience voting picture.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, in our reading of the literature, these studies do not reach a consensus on either turnout or composition questions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1065912911398048">Magleby 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1065912911398048">Southwell and Burchett 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1065912911398048">2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1065912911398048">Karp and Banducci 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1065912911398048">Berinsky, Burns, and Traugott 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1065912911398048">Hanmer and Traugott 2004</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1065912911398048">Berinsky, Burns, and Traugott (2001</xref>, 194) find that VOBM “increases turnout by a small amount,” but only because of “selective retention of voters”—those “already predisposed to vote.” The disagreement among the studies appears to be on the magnitude and significance of education, income, political party, and so on. We do not attempt to resolve these differences; in fact, in our analysis, we do not use survey respondents from Oregon.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1065912911398048">2</xref></sup> Instead, we focus on the ability to generalize to the national level the hypothesis that voters “predisposed to vote” are convenience voters.</p>
<p>Other studies have used survey data. Survey data avoid the ecological inference problem of inferring individual behavior from aggregate data and allow the researchers to elicit more information about the voters’ motivation for their choice. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1065912911398048">Barreto et al. (2006</xref>, 224) conducted a study of California by-mail voters in the 2003 recall election; they concluded that “absentee voters do not differ significantly from the overall state electorate in terms of their vote preferences, despite being older and better educated.” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1065912911398048">Karp and Banducci (2001</xref>, 191) tried to put together a national study using the National Election Studies survey data; they found that “persons who vote early are likely to be educated, active in politics, and partisan” but not likely to be from one party or the other. Although theirs was a national study, they had only 446 voters in forty-two states pooled over five successive elections; our survey contains many more voters.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1065912911398048">Stein (1998)</xref> conducted a survey of Texas early and Election Day voters in 1994 and concluded that early voters differed from Election Day voters primarily by their attitudes toward politics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1065912911398048">Stein 1998</xref>, 67). This confirmed a previous study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1065912911398048">Stein and Garcia-Monet 1997</xref>) of the 1992 Texas general election. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1065912911398048">Gronke et al. (2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1065912911398048">Gronke and Krantz Toffey 2008</xref>) made much the same observation about convenience voters in general: strength of partisanship may inform voting mode decisions. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1065912911398048">Gronke and Toffey (2008)</xref> did not find the same, but <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1065912911398048">Neeley and Richardson (2001)</xref> did in their analysis of a single Tennessee county.</p>
<p>One other article deserves mention here because it explicitly addresses the important issue that vote mode choice interacts with party strategy. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1065912911398048">Oliver’s (1996</xref>, 507) study of the 1992 general election used the Current Population Survey and a survey of his own directed at party organizations. He found that turnout increased in liberalized absentee voting states only when combined with state party mobilization and that Republicans were far more active in recruiting absentee voters than Democrats. This relates to the motivation for the Patterson and Caldeira article; they observed that Republican George Deukmejian’s gubernatorial campaign in 1982 sent out prefilled absentee forms while Democrat Tom Bradley’s campaign did not (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1065912911398048">Patterson and Caldeira 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1065912911398048">Quinn 1983</xref>). This implies that older studies might not generalize to the contemporary situation; if Democrats have in recent elections adopted Republican tactics from the 1980s, then new research is required in this field to keep abreast of changes in political tactics.</p>
<p>Taking all of this into consideration, we advance the study of convenience voting in several ways. First, we separate and explicitly evaluate the differences between “early” and “by-mail” voting. This enables us to test our first hypothesis, which is really an assumption frequently made in other studies, that individual characteristics will have the same effect on early voting as they do on by-mail voting. This hypothesis would not hold, for example, if elderly or disabled people were more likely to vote “by mail” rather than in person “early,” a reasonable belief. Testing this hypothesis allows us to clarify the assumptions in the field of convenience voting.</p>
<p>Since it appears that political parties are changing their convenience voting strategies and that the convenience voting population continues to grow, it is also worthwhile to test two hypotheses commonly studied in the literature. Our second hypothesis, inspired by the conventional political wisdom, is that Republican and conservative voters are less likely to vote on Election Day. This is inspired by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1065912911398048">Oliver’s (1996)</xref> revelations on the greater Republican efforts to mobilize absentee voters and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1065912911398048">Quinn’s (1983)</xref> description of the Deukmejian campaign.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1065912911398048">Stein (1998)</xref> observed that individuals who already know how they want to vote do not need to wait until Election Day to vote. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1065912911398048">Gronke et al. (2005)</xref> attempted to test this in Florida in the 2004 election with mixed results. This is still a compelling argument, though. If a voter <italic>always</italic> votes for the straight Democratic ticket, for example, the voter may not need the information presented in the last few days of a campaign. So our third hypothesis is that strength of partisanship increases the probability that a voter will choose one of the convenience voting options, relative to precinct voting on Election Day.</p>
<p>Finally, previous studies have found that election administration and voting technology have implications for political representation, in particular regarding race and ethnicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1065912911398048">Alvarez et al. 2008</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1065912911398048">Alvarez, Hall, Llewellyn 2008</xref>. Alvarez 2004. Sinclair and Alvarez 2008; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1065912911398048">Bullock, Hood, and Clark 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1065912911398048">Tomz and Van Houweling 2003</xref>). Therefore, it is possible that voters belonging to different racial or ethnic groups have different preferences for voting modes. This is particularly an issue in 2008, the first election with an African American presidential candidate as the Democratic nominee. In the days preceding November 4, 2008, researchers examined early voting figures by race and argued that black voters were making wider use of early voting relative to the 2004 election (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1065912911398048">McDonald 2008</xref>). Accordingly, our fourth hypothesis is that nonwhite voters were more likely to vote early.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1065912911398048" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method and Research Design</title>
<p>We use data from a unique study of voter attitudes about election administration and voting behavior, the 2008 Survey of the Performance of American Elections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1065912911398048">Alvarez et al. 2009</xref>). This first-of-its-kind survey was developed to provide a comprehensive national assessment of voter experiences with the electoral process in the 2008 presidential election; the general election survey (which we use in our analysis), while implemented the week after the election, had been extensively pilot tested in prior gubernatorial elections in the fall of 2007 (Mississippi, Kentucky, and Louisiana) as well as in the 2008 Super Tuesday presidential primary.</p>
<p>The survey interviews we use in this study were conducted online, with two hundred interviews from registered voters in every state (yielding a total sample of ten thousand responses from registered voters nationally). YouGov/Polimetrix conducted these interviews, using matched random samples of registered voters in each of the fifty American states. Weights were developed so that on a number of demographic characteristics the samples matched the national demographic profile of registered voters. With these weights used, the external validity of the online survey results was quite strong: the state-by-state Obama vote estimated by the online survey was strongly correlated with the actual state vote (.94). A telephone survey was also undertaken, with a sample of two hundred registered voters in ten states, and these interviews were conducted using computer-assisted random-digit dialing techniques. The telephone survey was conducted to provide an assessment of the online sample and survey response, and comparative analysis of the two methods produced a conclusion that overall both methods produced results that are consistent.</p>
<p>Our analysis of convenience voting in the 2008 presidential elections uses responses from a question that was asked to those who said that they voted in the election: did they vote in person on Election Day at a polling place, in person before Election Day, or by mail. In our work, we refer to these different means of casting a ballot as <italic>in-person Election Day voting, in-person early voting</italic>, and <italic>voting by mail</italic>. Relative to what may happen with self-reported turnout we do not expect respondents to misreport their voting mode because of willingness to conform to socially desirable behavior because no voting mode is perceived as socially unacceptable. Still, we are aware that answers to these questions are subject to misreporting caused by imperfect recall, confusion caused by question wording, and also systematic choice of voting mode by those who misreport their turnout. For instance, individuals who answer that they voted, when they actually abstained, might be more prone to say they voted by mail instead of in person early or on Election Day. If individuals who misreport differ systematically in their characteristics relative to the rest of the sample, models based on self-reported behavior can lead to biased and inconsistent inferences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1065912911398048">Katz and Katz 2010</xref>). Unfortunately, since no validation study was conducted to verify self-reports of voting mode, we cannot correct for potential misreporting.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1065912911398048">3</xref></sup> That said, we are reassured by the fact that authors who have studied the consequences of turnout misreporting in recent years have found few differences in parameters across models based on self-reported and validated behavior and almost no change in the substantial implications of their analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1065912911398048">Achen and Blais 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1065912911398048">Karp and Brockington 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1065912911398048">Katz and Katz 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>The research design of our study is straightforward. We begin by examining data from the various states regarding how permissive their policies in the 2008 presidential election were for each mode of voting, concentrating on how easy it was for voters to cast an in-person early voting ballot or to vote by mail (as those are the modes of voting that vary greatly in their convenience across the states). We then look to our survey data to ascertain across the states what fraction of the electorate might have used each mode of voting in each state. Then, we look at how the choice of voting mode varies by important covariates, and finally we use a Bayesian hierarchical model to estimate parameters of a model where the choice of voting mode is the dependent variable. As we discuss below, this method is appropriate for addressing both the discrete nature of the voting mode choice as well as the fact that we have a data set constructed from individual state samples. The latter point is important to keep in mind, as there is likely much systematic heterogeneity in choices about how to vote across the states, and controlling for this heterogeneity is essential to obtain meaningful estimates for our covariates of interest.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1065912911398048">
<title>An Initial Look at Convenience Voting in 2008</title>
<p>We begin our study by examining the permissiveness of state laws regarding voting by mail and in-person early voting in 2008. We use data on methods of voting across the states that were originally collected by the Early Voting Information Center at Reed College, presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1065912911398048">Table 1</xref>.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1065912911398048">4</xref></sup> There we see that in 2008 there was substantial variation across the nation in which types of convenience voting methods were allowed.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1065912911398048" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Procedural Permissiveness by State</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1065912911398048" xlink:href="10.1177_1065912911398048-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">By mail</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Early voting</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Allows permanent</th>
<th align="center">No excuse</th>
<th align="center">Requires excuse</th>
<th align="center">No excuse</th>
<th align="center">Requires excuse</th>
<th align="center">Not allowed</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Alabama</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Alaska</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Arizona</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Arkansas</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>California</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Colorado</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Connecticut</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Delaware</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Florida</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Georgia</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hawaii</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Idaho</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Illinois</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indiana</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Iowa</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kansas</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kentucky</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Louisiana</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Maine</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Maryland</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Massachusetts</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Michigan</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Minnesota</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mississippi</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Missouri</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Montana</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nebraska</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nevada</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New Hampshire</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New Jersey</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New Mexico</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New York</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>North Carolina</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>North Dakota</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ohio</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Oklahoma</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Oregon</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pennsylvania</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rhode Island</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>South Carolina</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>South Dakota</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tennessee</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Texas</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Utah</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Vermont</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Washington</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>West Virginia</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wisconsin</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wyoming</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td>1</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Beginning with voting by mail, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1065912911398048">Table 1</xref> documents that there were four states (California, Colorado, Montana, and Washington) that allowed voters to register as permanent by-mail voters—these voters receive all of their election materials by mail. Twenty-eight of the states allowed for no-excuse provision of ballots by mail (including Oregon, where all voters receive their ballots by mail). And twenty-two of the states required some form of a voter excuse or reason for requesting a ballot by mail. Note that there are not any clear geographic or population size patterns regarding which states adopt which rules.</p>
<p>When we turn to the second set of columns in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1065912911398048">Table 1</xref>, where we provide information on the permissiveness of the states with regards to early voting, we see that four states did not allow early voting in 2008: Maryland, Oregon (which instead provides all voters with election materials by mail), Rhode Island, and Washington (which also has widespread use of by-mail voting). Thirty-two of the states allowed no-excuse in-person early voting, while fourteen of the states allowed for in-person early voting if the voter provided some excuse or rationale for voting before Election Day.</p>
<p>Correspondingly we provide in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1065912911398048">Table 2</xref> data from our survey that document the percentage and number from each state sample of respondents who reported using each mode of voting. The data in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1065912911398048">Table 2</xref> show that across the nation, voting in person on Election Day was the most prevalent method of participation in the 2008 presidential election, as 64 percent of voters in our samples said that they voted on Election Day. This of course implies that 36 percent voted before the election, with equal percentages saying they voted before the election in person (18 percent) and by mail (18 percent).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1065912911398048" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Voting Mode by State</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1065912911398048" xlink:href="10.1177_1065912911398048-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Election Day</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Early voting</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">By mail</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">%</th>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="center">%</th>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="center">%</th>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Alabama</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>355</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Alaska</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>126</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Arizona</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>153</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>205</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Arkansas</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>California</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>195</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>170</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Colorado</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>115</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Connecticut</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>178</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Delaware</td>
<td>96</td>
<td>183</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Florida</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>156</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>151</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>78</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Georgia</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>173</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>178</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hawaii</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>93</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Idaho</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>124</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Illinois</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>273</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indiana</td>
<td>74</td>
<td>143</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Iowa</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>117</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kansas</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>110</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kentucky</td>
<td>93</td>
<td>172</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Louisiana</td>
<td>77</td>
<td>140</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Maine</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>125</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Maryland</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>177</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Massachusetts</td>
<td>91</td>
<td>176</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Michigan</td>
<td>73</td>
<td>133</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Minnesota</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>174</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mississippi</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>363</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Missouri</td>
<td>87</td>
<td>160</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Montana</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nebraska</td>
<td>69</td>
<td>129</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nevada</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>116</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New Hampshire</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>175</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New Jersey</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>165</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New Mexico</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>101</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>47</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New York</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>341</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>North Carolina</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>North Dakota</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>98</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ohio</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>118</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Oklahoma</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>148</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Oregon</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>97</td>
<td>184</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pennsylvania</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>178</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rhode Island</td>
<td>93</td>
<td>175</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>South Carolina</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>132</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>South Dakota</td>
<td>76</td>
<td>140</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tennessee</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>114</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Texas</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>119</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>221</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Utah</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>102</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Vermont</td>
<td>73</td>
<td>137</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td>84</td>
<td>160</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Washington</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>86</td>
<td>330</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>West Virginia</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>119</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wisconsin</td>
<td>77</td>
<td>147</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wyoming</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>134</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>7,222</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>1,986</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>2,034</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1065912911398048">
<p><italic>n</italic> is the number of observations. All figures were computed using sampling weights.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>These data indicate that there are some states where voting in person on Election Day was the primary method of voting in 2008: in sixteen states at least 80 percent of voters said that they voted in person on Election Day. However, in four states more than 50 percent of voters said that they voted by mail: Oregon (97 percent), Washington (86 percent), Colorado (61 percent), and Arizona (54 percent). In another ten states more than 20 percent of ballots were cast by mail. And finally, another five states had voters report that more than 50 percent voted in person before the election: Tennessee (63 percent), Texas (62 percent), Nevada (62 percent), North Carolina (53 percent), and New Mexico (52 percent). Another twelve states had more than 20 percent of voters report voting in person before the election.</p>
<p>The bivariate tables provide a useful introduction to the data before moving on to the multivariate analysis (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1065912911398048">Table 3</xref>). Some of the results are foreshadowed by differences in the bivariate tables: for example, given the previous literature, it is surprising that Hispanic and African American voters were more likely to choose in-person early voting than were White or Asian respondents, although not out of line with our last hypothesis. Note the ten-percentage-point difference between White and Hispanic respondents in particular. Furthermore, Hispanic voters are the least likely to vote in person on Election Day.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1065912911398048" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Bivariate Tables</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1065912911398048" xlink:href="10.1177_1065912911398048-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center">Election Day (%)</th>
<th align="center">Early voting (%)</th>
<th align="center">By mail (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Survey mode</td>
<td>Phone</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Web</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Race</td>
<td>White</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Black</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Hispanic</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Asian</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gender</td>
<td>Male</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Female</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age group</td>
<td>18–34 years old</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>35–54 years old</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Older than 55</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Disability</td>
<td>Not disabled</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Disabled</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Time in residency</td>
<td>At most 1 year</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>More than 1 year</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Home owner</td>
<td>Home owner</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Not home owner</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Education</td>
<td>No high school</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>High school graduate</td>
<td>69</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Some college</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>2-year college</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>4-year college</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Postgrad</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ideology</td>
<td>Very liberal</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Liberal</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Moderate</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Conservative</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Very conservative</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Three-point party ID</td>
<td>Democrat</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Republican</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Independent</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Seven-point party ID</td>
<td>Strong Democrat</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Not very strong Democrat</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Lean Democrat</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Independent</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Lean Republican</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Not very strong Republican</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Strong Republican</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>First-time voter</td>
<td>Not first time</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>First time</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1065912911398048">
<p>Proportion of respondents choosing each voting mode. All figures were computed using sample weights.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The data on mode choice, by the other demographic characteristics, are consistent with previous research. Disabled people are more likely to vote by mail rather than in person early, although they are still more likely to choose to vote in a traditional polling place than to take advantage of the “convenience” alternatives. There are virtually no differences by gender, as we expected, and also little evidence regarding an association with home ownership or length of residency. Furthermore, also exactly as expected, increasing levels of education correspond with decreasing probability of voting in person on Election Day; however, the differentiation between education levels and their mode preferences will have to wait until the multivariate analysis as little difference is immediately evident from this analysis.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1065912911398048">Table 3</xref> also provides an introductory analysis of the relationship between voting mode and political attitudes. As we move along the ideological scale from “very liberal” to “very conservative” respondents are more likely to vote in person on Election Day, and we observe the opposite for both early and by-mail voting. Turning to partisanship, the proportion of those who vote in person on Election Day is larger for Independents and Republicans while Democrats are substantively more likely to vote early. However, the proportion of by-mail voters does not vary by party identification. Finally, while strong Democrats tend to vote early at greater rates compared to other Democrats, strong Republicans tend to vote early at lesser rates relative to other Republicans.</p>
<p>In the remainder of this article we examine these patterns across states and voters and study which factors might determine how voters in the 2008 presidential election decided to cast their ballots. We are most interested in testing hypotheses regarding individual-level voter attributes, and we use a Bayesian estimation method that we describe in the next section. This method lets us obtain estimates about the different potential individual-level determinants of the choice of voting method while controlling for state-level differences in the extent to which different modes of voting were available to the voters in the state.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1065912911398048">
<title>Multivariate Method</title>
<p>The goal of our multivariate analysis is to study how sociodemographic attributes and political attitudes affect choice of voting mode. In contrast to much of the previous literature, we do not assume that convenience voting modes are perfect substitutes but instead allow individual characteristics to have different effects on preferences for by-mail and early voting. Since the large-scale national survey is composed of state-by-state samples, not only are we interested in estimating how individual characteristics affect average preferences at the national level, but also we wish to allow for systematic and random taste variation across states. Thus, we use a hierarchical multinomial logit specification where all coefficients (not only intercepts) are allowed to vary randomly across states and parameter means are modeled as a function of state electoral law. Thus, not only does our analysis improve on previous studies in terms of sample size and generalizability but also our multilevel specification allows us to consider effect heterogeneity. Furthermore, since we explain voter behavior as a function of a diverse set of individual-level characteristics, our analysis is not subject to the aggregation bias that potentially compromises the results of previous ecological studies.</p>
<p>The specification of a flexible random effects model where all parameters are allowed to change across states comes at a cost because it prevents us from extending the model in alternative directions. One limitation is that it assumes the relative odds of choosing any of two alternatives does not depend on the characteristics of other alternatives, or on whether other alternatives enter or leave the choice set—that is, it imposes the assumption of independence of irrelevant alternatives. If our main interest were not allowing for random taste variation but analyzing substitution patterns, a more appropriate approach would be to use an alternative specification allowing for correlated disturbances across voting modes such as multinomial probit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1065912911398048">Alvarez and Nagler 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1065912911398048">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1065912911398048">Hausman and Wise 1978</xref>), error components mixed logit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1065912911398048">Brownstone and Train 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1065912911398048">Glasgow 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1065912911398048">Train 2003</xref>, 139), or generalized extreme value models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1065912911398048">Train 2003</xref>, 80; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1065912911398048">Wen and Koppelman 2001</xref>). Since the goal of our article is to study taste variation allowing for heterogeneity of effects across states, we use a flexible random effects specification, and we leave the study of substitution patterns for future research.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1065912911398048">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>To model random taste variation across states, we estimate a Bayesian hierarchical multinomial logit model where the utility (<italic>U</italic><italic><sub>ij</sub></italic>) voters perceive from each mode of voting is decomposed into a systematic component (<italic>X</italic><italic><sub>i</sub></italic>′B<italic><sub>ij</sub></italic>) and a random component following an extreme value distribution (ε<italic><sub>ij</sub></italic>). As is usual in random utility models, we assume voters behave consistently with utility maximization and choose the alternative providing the largest utility.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1065912911398048">6</xref></sup> The classical regression approach assumes coefficients do not vary across individuals or units—that is, it is usually assumed that B<italic><sub>ij</sub></italic> = B<italic><sub>j</sub></italic>, where <italic>i</italic> indicates individuals and <italic>j</italic> indicates alternatives. However, this assumption is not appropriate for modeling choice of voting mode because covariate effects may vary by individual depending on the procedural permissiveness of their state of residence. For instance, absentee or early voting may be easier and relatively more appealing in states with no-excuse absentee and/or early voting. Similarly, Election Day voting may attract more voters in states where polling places close late in the evening. Therefore, we specify a model with varying coefficients across states, allowing us to capture heterogeneity caused by differences in electoral law or other idiosyncratic factors. Specifically, we model state-level coefficients using a multivariate regression approach, letting B<italic><sub>ij</sub></italic> = <italic>Z</italic><italic><sub>i</sub></italic>′Δ<italic><sub>j</sub></italic> + <italic>V</italic><italic><sub>ij</sub></italic>, where <italic>Z</italic><italic><sub>i</sub></italic>′ is a vector of state characteristics, Δ<italic><sub>j</sub></italic> is a vector of alternative-specific coefficients, and <italic>V</italic><italic><sub>ij</sub></italic> is a disturbance term following a flexible mixture of normal distributions.</p>
<p>The first level of our model examines the individual choice of voting mode—Election Day voting, voting in person before the election, or voting by mail. We use voting by mail as our baseline or comparison category in our choice model, so the initial results that we present in the next section must be interpreted in that light. As covariates in the individual-level model, we use include race, gender, educational attainment, and age. We also have covariates for whether the voter is disabled or a home owner and how long the voter has lived in his or her current residence. Finally, we have covariates that measure the voter’s strength of partisanship, his or her partisan affiliation, and his or her ideological identification. The second level of our model examines how first-level parameters vary as a function of the electoral law in effect within the different states. As covariates in the state-level model we include indicators of registration closing dates (coded as distance from Election Day), no-excuse or permanent absentee voting, no-excuse early voting, and an indicator of polling place closing time.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1065912911398048">7</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1065912911398048" sec-type="results">
<title>Multivariate Results</title>
<p>In our multivariate analysis we focus on the forty-six states that allow all three voting modes—in-person on Election Day, in-person early, and by-mail voting. Our model was estimated three times with different starting values, resulting in three Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) chains of parameters estimates. Each chain ran for one hundred thousand iterations, and we kept one of every fifty draws. We evaluated convergence by computing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1065912911398048">Gelman and Rubin’s (1992)</xref> univariate potential scale reduction factors (PSRFs) and found that PSRFs fell below 1.2 by the last iteration for all coefficients. This indicates that model parameters converged to their stable posterior distribution.</p>
<p>Among respondents included in our multivariate analysis, 65.7 percent voted in person on Election Day, 19.6 percent voted early, and 14.7 percent voted by mail, and similar proportions are found if we use model estimates to compute median voting mode probabilities, suggesting our model predicts overall behavior well. Furthermore, if we use estimated individual probabilities to predict choice of voting mode for each respondent, then our model correctly classifies 74 percent of the respondents.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1065912911398048">8</xref></sup> We used the second part of each MCMC chain to summarize the posterior distribution of coefficients and quantities of interest. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1065912911398048">Figure 1</xref> gives average values and 90 percent posterior intervals for the coefficients of an average state.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1065912911398048">9</xref></sup> Also, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1065912911398048">Table 4</xref> gives 90 percent posterior intervals for the change in the probability of choosing each voting mode, at the national level.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1065912911398048">10</xref></sup> We present first difference results in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1065912911398048">Table 4</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1065912911398048" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Coefficients for average state</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1065912911398048-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="table4-1065912911398048" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Marginal Effects</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1065912911398048" xlink:href="10.1177_1065912911398048-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Election Day</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Early voting</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">By mail</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="center">Change with respect to hypothetical voter</th>
<th align="center">5 percent</th>
<th align="center"><bold>50 percent</bold></th>
<th align="center">95 percent</th>
<th align="center">5 percent</th>
<th align="center"><bold>50 percent</bold></th>
<th align="center">95 percent</th>
<th align="center">5 percent</th>
<th align="center"><bold>50 percent</bold></th>
<th align="center">95 percent</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Probability of support</td>
<td/>
<td>69.1</td>
<td><bold>71.2</bold></td>
<td>73.4</td>
<td>15.5</td>
<td><bold>17.3</bold></td>
<td>19.2</td>
<td>9.9</td>
<td><bold>11.4</bold></td>
<td>13.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Years in residency</td>
<td>At most 1 to more than 1</td>
<td>−6.1</td>
<td><bold>−3.7</bold></td>
<td>−1.6</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td><bold>2.9</bold></td>
<td>5.2</td>
<td>−0.9</td>
<td><bold>0.7</bold></td>
<td>2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Home owner</td>
<td>Yes to no</td>
<td>−3.9</td>
<td><bold>−1.8</bold></td>
<td>0.3</td>
<td>−1.7</td>
<td><bold>0.1</bold></td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>0.0</td>
<td><bold>1.7</bold></td>
<td>3.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Disabled</td>
<td>No to yes</td>
<td>−5.6</td>
<td><bold>−3.2</bold></td>
<td>−1.0</td>
<td>−3.2</td>
<td><bold>−1.4</bold></td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td>2.7</td>
<td><bold>4.5</bold></td>
<td>6.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Schooling</td>
<td>College to postgrad</td>
<td>−10.7</td>
<td><bold>−8.2</bold></td>
<td>−5.5</td>
<td>4.5</td>
<td><bold>6.9</bold></td>
<td>9.2</td>
<td>−0.5</td>
<td><bold>1.2</bold></td>
<td>3.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Party ID</td>
<td>Independent to Democrat</td>
<td>−6.0</td>
<td><bold>−3.3</bold></td>
<td>−0.4</td>
<td>0.0</td>
<td><bold>2.5</bold></td>
<td>5.2</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td><bold>0.7</bold></td>
<td>2.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Independent to Republican</td>
<td>−0.8</td>
<td><bold>1.7</bold></td>
<td>4.3</td>
<td>−4.7</td>
<td><bold>−2.7</bold></td>
<td>−0.5</td>
<td>−1.0</td>
<td><bold>0.9</bold></td>
<td>3.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Strength of partisanship</td>
<td>Not strong to strong</td>
<td>−5.1</td>
<td><bold>−2.8</bold></td>
<td>−0.7</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td><bold>2.5</bold></td>
<td>4.5</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td><bold>0.3</bold></td>
<td>2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ideology</td>
<td>Moderate to liberal</td>
<td>−7.1</td>
<td><bold>−4.9</bold></td>
<td>−2.7</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td><bold>3.6</bold></td>
<td>5.6</td>
<td>−0.4</td>
<td><bold>1.3</bold></td>
<td>3.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Moderate to conservative</td>
<td>−1.1</td>
<td><bold>1.0</bold></td>
<td>3.1</td>
<td>−3.1</td>
<td><bold>−1.4</bold></td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>−1.2</td>
<td><bold>0.4</bold></td>
<td>1.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Race</td>
<td>White to nonwhite</td>
<td>−4.3</td>
<td><bold>−1.8</bold></td>
<td>0.7</td>
<td>−0.1</td>
<td><bold>2.0</bold></td>
<td>4.2</td>
<td>−2.1</td>
<td><bold>−0.2</bold></td>
<td>1.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gender</td>
<td>Female to male</td>
<td>−3.5</td>
<td><bold>−1.8</bold></td>
<td>−0.3</td>
<td>0.7</td>
<td><bold>2.1</bold></td>
<td>3.5</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td><bold>−0.2</bold></td>
<td>1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>53 (median) to 62 (3rd quartile)</td>
<td>−5.0</td>
<td><bold>−4.2</bold></td>
<td>−3.4</td>
<td>0.5</td>
<td><bold>1.2</bold></td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>2.3</td>
<td><bold>2.9</bold></td>
<td>3.6</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1065912911398048">
<p>Median and 90 percent posterior intervals for baseline choice probabilities and effects of marginal changes in model covariates. For each iteration national effects were computed as a weighted average of state-level effects.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The factors explaining the choice of Election Day precinct voting in our analysis are consistent with our expectations. In particular, increasing the level of education from “college” to “postgrad” and living in the same residence for more than a year significantly decrease the probability that a voter chooses to vote in a precinct on Election Day. Also, as Stein’s analysis implies, and line with our third hypothesis, changing a voter’s partisanship from “not strong” to “strong” decreases the probability that such a person would vote on Election Day. In addition, male voters, the elderly, and the disabled are less likely to make this mode choice. The most surprising results are the negative and significant three-percentage-point change from switching Independent to Democrat and the negative and significant five-percentage-point change from switching moderate to liberal. So we find the reverse of conventional wisdom: a voter identifying as more liberal or as a Democrat is actually less likely to choose voting in person on Election Day than a conservative or Republican.</p>
<p>The determinants of in-person early voting are quite different from those affecting Election Day precinct voting or by-mail voting. Specifically, the probability of early voting is greater among liberal, well-educated, older, male, strong partisan voters. This fits much of the theory on convenience voters, in the sense that older people, strong partisans, and the well-educated are typically “likely voters.” These voters are willing to pay the cost of learning to use a new type of voting system and will take time before the election to go and vote. The result for ideology or partisanship opposes the expectation from the early literature and the conventional wisdom of no effect or a Republican advantage. Switching partisanship from Independent to Democrat or ideology from moderate to liberal increases the probability of voting early by three and four percentage points, respectively. Conversely, switching partisanship from Independent to Republican reduces the probability of voting early by three percentage points.</p>
<p>The supposed Republican advantage with by-mail voting is not evident in our results. In fact, switching ideology from moderate to liberal slightly increases the probability of voting by mail by one percentage point, although this effect is not significant at conventional confidence levels. We find the expected signs and significance on age and disability. These results clearly support the hypothesis that it is much easier for disabled or elderly people to vote at home by mail than to get to a polling place to vote in person. On the other hand, the other variables the literature would have us expect to find—education, race, and party identification–all turn out to be insignificant. We do not find a significant result for strength of partisanship.</p>
<p>As a consequence, we reject the hypothesis that demographics and political attitudes have the same effect on by-mail voting as on early voting, reject the hypothesis that Republicans are more likely to make use of convenience voting opportunities, and fail to reject the hypothesis that strength of partisanship has a positive effect on early voting. We observe the strongest difference between Election Day and early voting, although by-mail is a popular choice for the disabled or elderly. We find some support for Stein’s results—attitudinal differences separate Election Day and early voters—for early voting, although it is not generalizable to by-mail voting. The most surprising result is the reversal of the conventional wisdom and the discovery that at the national level Republicans or conservatives are more likely to choose Election Day voting than early voting, although it is quite possible that this result may vary by state.</p>
<p>To study how results vary across states, we replicated <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1065912911398048">Table 4</xref> for California, Florida, Illinois, New Mexico, and Minnesota.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1065912911398048">11</xref></sup> Not surprisingly, the baseline probability of voting in person on Election Day is highest in Minnesota (99 percent), which requires an excuse for both early and by-mail voting. There, the probability of voting by mail increases significantly with schooling and male gender. Most interesting, contrary to the national pattern, the probability of voting by mail in Minnesota increases slightly when partisanship is changed from Independent to Republican and when ideology is changed from moderate to conservative, although the former effect is not significant at conventional confidence levels. Conversely, the probability of voting early increases significantly when partisanship changes from Independent to Democrat and when ideology changes from moderate to liberal.</p>
<p>Also as expected, the baseline probabilities of voting in person on Election Day or early are large in Illinois (57 percent and 42 percent, respectively), which requires an excuse for voting absentee but does not require an excuse for voting early. In this case, no covariate had a statistically significant estimate for explaining changes in by-mail voting. In addition, attitudinal effects in Illinois differ from the average pattern, as well from the Minnesota case. Specifically, switching partisanship from Independent to Democrat or ideology from moderate to liberal has no significant effect on early voting. Nevertheless, switching partisanship from Independent to Republican has a negative and significant effect on early voting. Thus, the direction of the partisan effect is similar to the one we observe at the national level. In particular, we observe no evidence of a Republican advantage in the use of no-excuse early voting</p>
<p>In Florida and New Mexico, which do not require an excuse for either absentee or early voting, baseline probabilities of voting by mail are larger than in Minnesota and Illinois (22 percent and 23 percent, respectively), and probabilities of voting early are also large (42 percent and 52 percent, respectively). In these states, partisanship is not significant for explaining either early or by-mail voting. The only attitudinal changes with considerable effects on convenience voting are switching ideology from moderate to liberal (increases the probability of voting early by eighteen percentage points in Florida) and switching ideology from moderate to conservative (decreases the probability of voting early by nineteen percentage points in New Mexico), although these effects are not significant at conventional confidence levels. Thus, the impact of ideology is similar in sign to the one observed at the national level.</p>
<p>In contrast to other states, California allows no-excuse early and by-mail voting as well as permanent absentee voting. In this state, the baseline probability of voting by mail (47 percent) is substantively higher than the states considered before. In addition, the baseline probability of voting early is very low (2 percent). In California, covariates have no significant effect on early voting. Switching partisanship from Independent to Republican slightly decreases the probability of voting early, but this effect is not significant at the 90 percent level. Moving to by-mail voting, in contrast to the national pattern, switching ideology from moderate to conservative has a large and significant effect on choice probabilities. Also, home owners, those who are disabled, and white voters exhibit higher likelihood of voting by mail, although some of these effects are not significantly different from zero.</p>
<p>Finally, we test the hypothesis that nonwhite voters were more likely to vote early. At the national level, we found that nonwhites are more likely to vote early (by two percentage points). In addition, our multilevel specification allowed us to measure how the effect of belonging to a nonwhite racial group varied across states. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1065912911398048">Figure 2</xref> shows the change in the baseline probabilities of choosing different voting modes, when race is switched from white to nonwhite, for each state. In California a nonwhite hypothetical voter has a greater probability of voting on Election Day, the same probability of voting early, and a lower probability of voting by mail, compared to a white hypothetical voter. On the contrary, in South Carolina, nonwhite race reduces the probability of Election Day voting and increases the probability of early and by-mail voting. In Nebraska, Tennessee, and West Virginia, nonwhite race also reduces the probability of Election Day voting and increases the probability of early voting but has no significant effect on by-mail voting. Finally, in North Carolina, a nonwhite hypothetical voter is less likely to vote in person on Election Day, more likely to vote early, but less likely to vote by mail. For the remaining states we found that nonwhite race has no effect on voting mode at conventional levels of significance (&gt; 90 percent). Therefore, even though national results show overall support for the hypothesis that nonwhite race has a positive effect on early voting, we also found heterogeneity in these effects across states.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1065912911398048" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Effects of nonwhite race</p>
<p>Dots indicate mean effects, and segments indicate 90 percent posterior intervals.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1065912911398048-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1065912911398048" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>In just the past decade, convenience voting methods have gone from being a novelty in the United States to being virtually ubiquitous. Oregon conducts elections exclusively by mail, and in neighboring Washington the overwhelming bulk of ballots in recent elections arrive by mail. In many other states, voters have taken the opportunity provided by election officials to cast ballots before elections by mail, and increasingly to cast ballots before election in person. Voters are “voting for convenience” when given the opportunity, a trend that election officials throughout the nation appear to encourage and facilitate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1065912911398048">Alvarez and Hall 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>With the dramatic growth in convenience voting has come academic focus on the choice of voting method. As we discussed in detail earlier, additional research about convenience voting is necessary. Many of the previous studies have been restricted in geographic focus; for example, much of the literature on voting by mail has been limited to studies of Oregon’s recent experiences. It is not clear whether the results from those studies can be generalized to other states. Other studies have used very limited types of data or have made very restrictive methodological assumptions about voting behavior, also limiting the ability of scholars and policy makers to draw clear inferences from that body of research.</p>
<p>Our study takes a variety of new methodological steps, in an attempt to move beyond the problems that we see plaguing the previous research literature. We use a large-scale national survey—the survey is constructed of state-by-state samples, thus ensuring that we have widespread coverage of the different voting methods used across the United States. The fact that we use individual-level survey data also means that we are not restricted to ecological analysis, and our survey provides a rich array of social and political covariates. Finally, we use a Bayesian hierarchical choice model, which allows for flexible estimation of our well-specified individual- and state-level model of voting mode choice.</p>
<p>With our analysis, we provide a number of insights into some of the important debates about convenience voting. First and most importantly, we find little support for the hypothesis that convenience voting methods have partisan implications, holding a variety of covariates constant. The conventional wisdom has long been that convenience voting favors the Republican Party; here we find no support for that bit of conventional wisdom. Nevertheless, we do find other voter attributes that lead to the choice of some form of convenience voting; for example, elderly voters and those with disabilities are more likely, ceteris paribus, to vote by mail. Results like these have important implications for future moves toward convenience voting and for how policy makers might develop new outreach campaigns to make additional eligible voters aware of their choices about how to cast their ballots.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>We thank the Pew Charitable Trusts Make Voting Work Project for providing funding to conduct the survey we use for our research in this article. We also thank Charles Stewart III for his work overseeing the 2008 Survey of the Performance of American Elections, and Stephen Ansolabehere, Adam Berinsky, Thad Hall, and Gabriel Lenz for their assistance with that survey project.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interests with respect to the authorship and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The authors received the following financial support for the research and/or authorship of this article:</p>
<p>The Pew Charitable Trusts Make Voting Work Project provided funding to conduct the survey used for the research in this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1065912911398048">
<label>1.</label>
<p>A note on terminology: We use “by-mail” voting for the process by which a voter submits a ballot through the mail, although this used to be called (broadly) “absentee” voting. This is different from the “vote-only-by-mail” system, a system used in most of Washington, a few areas in California, and the entirety of Oregon. In a vote-only-by-mail locality, polling place voting is generally unavailable.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1065912911398048">
<label>2.</label>
<p>As well as those from Maryland, Rhode Island, and Washington, states that did not allow any form of in-person early voting in the 2008 general election (not even with an excuse).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1065912911398048">
<label>3.</label>
<p>Validation data might not be enough to solve misreporting issues because validation studies are also subject to misclassification caused by misspelling and other errors in voter registration lists, or failure to locate or get access to registration information for certain respondents.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1065912911398048">
<label>4.</label>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.earlyvoting.net">http://www.earlyvoting.net</ext-link>. These regulations are not those for eligible voters who are overseas or who fall under the provisions of the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act (UOCAVA) and its revisions in the Help America Vote Act. UOCAVA voters, typically members of the Armed Forces and their dependents as well as American citizens who reside overseas, have the ability to request and obtain election materials by mail or electronically that are distinct from the rights of non-UOCAVA voters. See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1065912911398048">Alvarez, Hall, and Roberts (2007)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1065912911398048">
<label>5.</label>
<p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1065912911398048">Train (2003</xref>, 40), even if the researcher believes the independence of irrelevant alternatives assumption does not hold, a model imposing this assumption is not problematic as long as the interest of the study is learning about taste variation and not estimating substitution patterns.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1065912911398048">
<label>6.</label>
<p>More formally, we assume they prefer alternative <italic>j</italic> over alternative <italic>k</italic> if <italic>U</italic><italic><sub>ij</sub></italic> &gt; <italic>U</italic><italic><sub>ik</sub></italic>, which holds whenever ε<italic><sub>ij</sub></italic> − ε<italic><sub>ik</sub></italic> &gt; <italic>X</italic><italic><sub>i</sub></italic>′B<italic><sub>ik</sub></italic> − <italic>X</italic><italic><sub>i</sub></italic>′B<italic><sub>ij</sub></italic>. Since error terms follow an extreme value distribution, the difference ε<italic><sub>ij</sub></italic> – ε<italic><sub>ik</sub></italic> follows a logistic distribution, and the probability of choosing alternative <italic>j</italic> can be written as</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1065912911398048">
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-1065912911398048">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>|</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>′</mml:mo>
</mml:msup>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:munder>
<mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" mathsize="140%">
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>∀</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:munder>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>′</mml:mo>
</mml:msup>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-1065912911398048" xlink:href="10.1177_1065912911398048-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula>
</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1065912911398048">
<label>7.</label>
<p>It is possible that the decision to vote in person early or by mail, instead of on Election Day, is affected by the perceived competitiveness of the race. We replicated the analysis including an indicator of closeness of the presidential race (state-level presidential vote margins from the 2008 election) as a covariate in the second-level model. We found no significant effect of this variable on first-level intercepts or slopes, meaning that it does not contribute to explaining heterogeneity of choice of voting mode across states. Results of this replication are available from the authors upon request.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1065912911398048">
<label>8.</label>
<p>Our model predicts individual behavior better than a model that assumes all voting modes are chosen with equal probability (33 percent correct classification), an only-constant model predicting all voters vote in precinct on Election Day (66 percent correct classification), and an alternative Bayesian hierarchical model with only a random constant by state (70 percent correct classification rate).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1065912911398048">
<label>9.</label>
<p>The supplementary file contains similar information in tabular format (see Table A1 at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://prq.sagepub.com/supplemental/">http://prq.sagepub.com/supplemental/</ext-link>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1065912911398048">
<label>10.</label>
<p>Entries in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1065912911398048">Table 4</xref> were computed based on a hypothetical voter: a moderate and Independent fifty-two-year-old white female who is a home owner but has resided in the same residence for less than a year, who has at least some college education, who is not disabled, and who is not a first-time voter. This hypothetical voter has a 71 percent probability of voting in person on Election Day, a 17 percent probability of voting early, and an 11 percent probability of voting by mail.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1065912911398048">
<label>11.</label>
<p>Available in the supplementary file.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Achen</surname><given-names>Christopher H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blais</surname><given-names>André</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. “<article-title>Intention to Vote and Validated Vote: A Research Note</article-title>.” <conf-name>Paper presented at the 68th annual national conference of the Midwest Political Science Association</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Chicago</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>R. Michael</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ansolabehere</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berinsky</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lenz</surname><given-names>Gabriel</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>Thad</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. “<article-title>2008 Survey of the Performance of American Elections: Final Report</article-title>.” <comment>Manuscript, Caltech/MIT Voting Technology Project</comment>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dspace.mit.edu/bitstream/handle/1721.1/49847/Final%20report20090218.pdf?sequence=6">http://dspace.mit.edu/bitstream/handle/1721.1/49847/Final%20report20090218.pdf?sequence=6</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>R. Michael</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>Thad E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2007</year>. “<article-title>Controlling Democracy: The Principal-Agent Problems in Election Administration</article-title>.” <source>Policy Studies Journal</source> <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>491</fpage>-<lpage>510</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>R. Michael</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>Thad</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Llewellyn</surname><given-names>Morgan H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2008</year>. “<article-title>Are Americans Confident Their Ballots Are Counted?</article-title>” <source>Journal of Politics</source> <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>754</fpage>-<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>R. Michael</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>Thad E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>Brian F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2007</year>. “<article-title>Military Voting and the Law: Procedural and Technological Solutions to the Ballot Transit Problem</article-title>.” <source>Fordham Urban Law Journal</source> <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>935</fpage>-<lpage>96</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>R. Michael</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagler</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1995</year>. “<article-title>Economics, Issues and the Perot Candidacy: Voter Choice in the 1992 Presidential Election</article-title>.” <source>American Journal of Political Science</source> <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>714</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>R. Michael</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagler</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1997</year>. “<article-title>Economics, Entitlements and Social Issues: Voter Choice in the 1996 Presidential Election</article-title>.” <source>American Journal of Political Science</source> <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>1349</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>Matt</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Streb</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>Mara</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guerra</surname><given-names>Fernando</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. “<article-title>Do Absentee Voters Differ from Polling Place Voters? New Evidence from California</article-title>.” <source>Public Opinion Quarterly</source> <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>224</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berinsky</surname><given-names>Adam J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2005</year>. “<article-title>The Perverse Consequences of Electoral Reform in the United States</article-title>.” <source>American Politics Research</source> <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>471</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berinsky</surname><given-names>Adam J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>Nancy</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Traugott</surname><given-names>Michael W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2001</year>. “<article-title>Who Votes by Mail? A Dynamic Model of the Individual Level Consequences of Voting-by-Mail Systems</article-title>.” <source>Public Opinion Quarterly</source> <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>178</fpage>-<lpage>97</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brownstone</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Train</surname><given-names>Kenneth</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1999</year>. “<article-title>Forecasting New Product Penetration with Flexible Substitution Patterns</article-title>.” <source>Journal of Econometrics</source> <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bullock</surname><given-names>Charles S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hood</surname><given-names>M. V.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. “<article-title>Punch Cards, Jim Crow, and Al Gore: Explaining Voter Trust in the Electoral System in Georgia, 2000</article-title>.” <source>State Politics and Policy Quarterly</source> <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>283</fpage>-<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dubin</surname><given-names>Jeffery A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalsow</surname><given-names>Gretchen A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1996</year>. “<article-title>Comparing Absentee and Precinct Voters: A View over Time</article-title>.” <source>Political Behavior</source> <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>369</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>Donald B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1992</year>. “<article-title>Inference for Iterative Simulation Using Multiple Sequences</article-title>.” <source>Statistical Science</source> <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glasgow</surname><given-names>Garrett</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2001</year>. “<article-title>Mixed Logit Models for Multiparty Elections</article-title>.” <source>Political Analysis</source> <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gronke</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. “<article-title>Early Voting Reforms and American Elections</article-title>.” <conf-name>Paper presented at the annual meeting of the American Political Science Association</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Chicago IL</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gronke</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bishin</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Galanes-Rosenbaum</surname><given-names>Eva</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. “<article-title>Early Voting in Florida, 2004</article-title>.” <conf-name>Paper prepared for the annual conference of the American Political Science Association</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Washington, DC</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gronke</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toffey</surname><given-names>Daniel Krantz</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. “<article-title>The Psychological and Institutional Determinants of Early Voting</article-title>.” <source>Journal of Social Issues</source> <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>503</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hanmer</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Traugott</surname><given-names>Michael W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2004</year>. “<article-title>The Impact of Voting by Mail on Voter Behavior</article-title>.” <source>American Politics Research</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>375</fpage>-<lpage>405</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hausman</surname><given-names>Jerry A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>David A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1978</year>. “<article-title>A Conditional Probit Model for Qualitative Choice: Discrete Decisions Recognizing Interdependence and Heterogeneous Preferences</article-title>.” <source>Econometrica</source> <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>Jeffery A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banducci</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2000</year>. “<article-title>Going Postal: How All-Mail Elections Influence Turnout</article-title>.” <source>Political Behavior</source> <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>223</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>Jeffery A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banducci</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2001</year>. “<article-title>Absentee Voting, Mobilization, and Participation</article-title>.” <source>American Politics Research</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>Jeffery A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brockington</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. “<article-title>Social Desirability and Response Validity: A Comparative Analysis of Overreporting Voter Turnout in Five Countries</article-title>.” <source>Journal of Politics</source> <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>825</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>Jonathan N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>Gabriel</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. “<article-title>Correcting for Survey Misreports Using Auxiliary Information</article-title>.” <source>American Journal of Political Science</source> <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>815</fpage>-<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>Gary</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1997</year>. <source>A Solution to the Ecological Inference Problem: Reconstructing Individual Behavior from Aggregate Data</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Magleby</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1987</year>. “<article-title>Participation in Mail Ballot Elections</article-title>.” <source>Western Political Quarterly</source> <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. “<article-title>Election 2008: Early Voting and Exit Polling</article-title>.” <source>Washington Post</source>, <month>November</month> <day>3</day>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/discussion/2008/10/31/DI2008103103039.html">http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/discussion/2008/10/31/DI2008103103039.html</ext-link></comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neeley</surname><given-names>Grant W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>Lilliard E.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
</person-group> <year>2001</year>. “<article-title>Who is Early Voting? An Individual Level Examination</article-title>.” <source>Social Science Journal</source> <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>381</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>J. Eric</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1996</year>. “<article-title>The Effects of Eligibility Restrictions and Party Activity on Absentee Voting and Overall Turnout</article-title>.” <source>American Journal of Political Science</source> <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>498</fpage>-<lpage>513</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>Samuel</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caldeira</surname><given-names>Gregory</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1985</year>. “<article-title>Mailing in the Vote: Correlates and Consequences of Absentee Voting</article-title>.” <source>American Journal of Political Science</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>766</fpage>-<lpage>88</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>Tony</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1983</year>. “<article-title>How Governor Deukmejian Won in the Mailbox, Not the Ballot Box</article-title>.” <source>California Journal</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>148</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>Betsy</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>R. Michael</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. “<article-title>Who Overvotes, Who Undervotes, Using Punchcards? Evidence from Los Angeles County</article-title>.” <source>Political Research Quarterly</source> <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Southwell</surname><given-names>Priscilla</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burchett</surname><given-names>Justin</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1997</year>. “<article-title>Survey of Vote-by-Mail Senate Election in the State of Oregon</article-title>.” <source>PS: Political Science &amp; Politics</source> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Southwell</surname><given-names>Priscilla</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burchett</surname><given-names>Justin</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2000</year>. “<article-title>Does Changing the Rules Change the Players? The Effect of All-Mail Elections on the Composition of the Electorate</article-title>.” <source>Social Science Quarterly</source> <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>837</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1998</year>. “<article-title>Early Voting</article-title>.” <source>Public Opinion Quarterly</source> <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>69</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garcia-Monet</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1997</year>. “<article-title>Voting Early but Not Often</article-title>.” <source>Social Science Quarterly</source> <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>657</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tomz</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Houweling</surname><given-names>Robert P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2003</year>. “<article-title>How Does Voting Equipment Affect the Racial Gap in Voided Ballots?</article-title>” <source>American Journal of Political Science</source> <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Train</surname><given-names>Kenneth</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <source>Discrete Choice Methods with Simulation</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1065912911398048">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Chieh-Hua</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koppelman</surname><given-names>Frank S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2001</year>. “<article-title>The Generalized Nested Logit Model</article-title>.” <source>Transportation Research Part B: Methodological</source> <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>627</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>