<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EHQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spehq</journal-id>
<journal-title>European History Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0265-6914</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7110</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0265691411428783b</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0265691411428783b</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Alexander Badenoch and Andreas Fickers, eds, <italic>Materializing Europe: Transnational Infrastructures and the Project of Europe</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Daddow</surname><given-names>Oliver</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0265691411428783b">Loughborough University</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>118</fpage>
<lpage>119</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0265691411428783b"><title>Alexander Badenoch and Andreas Fickers, eds, <italic>Materializing Europe: Transnational Infrastructures and the Project of Europe</italic>, Palgrave Macmillan: Basingstoke, 2010; xi + 333 pp., 45 tables and figures; 9780230232891, £65.00 (hbk)</title>
<p>The historiography of European integration remains heavily weighted towards consideration of the drive to unity provided by the formal institutions of what today is the European Union (EU) and what was formerly the European Economic Community (EEC). Supposed ‘hindrances’ to the project have been studied both at the level of national resistances and, in recent years, in the context of the transnational phenomenon of Euroscepticism, evident within the national politics of even the oldest ‘European’ countries, and, indeed, also at the European level. The contributions in this book offer up a different appreciation of the idea of ‘Europe’ by studying how the creation and development of transnational infrastructures have contributed to the unity project, sometimes as motors of integration and sometimes as brakes upon it. As the editors explain in the introduction, there is a paradox in the historiography which makes much of Europe as a modernizing force in regional and global politics, but overlooks the study of the very practical projects for modernization that flourished through the twentieth century. Studying transnational infrastructures in Europe creates space to reflect on the competing ideas of Europe that have existed outside the formal institutions, as well as on the politics of uniting European nations as a practical project that transcends national borders. In this book, the self-congratulatory official history of integration is replaced by one in which ruptures, border crossings, national competition and practical, often highly technical issues throw many a spanner in the works of the engine of unity. The smoothness of the journey implied by the political rhetoric, the book argues, has not always been matched by concrete developments on the ground, calling into doubt any imminent realization of the European vision of the ‘founding fathers’.</p>
<p>The opening part of the book covers ideas of Europe as expressed in plans for integrating, amongst other things, Europe and the colonies of its leading nation states, its visual representation in network maps, and energy and transport infrastructures in the early post-Second World War era of integration. Throughout the book, the main fare is supplemented by short ‘biographies’ of objects, people and symbols that have circulated in elite and technological circles and which cast light on competing visions of Europe left out of official histories. Academics Ernst Haas and David Mitrany, together with the Oliven Plan, are given the limelight here. The second part of the book studies the ‘movements’ that have been fashioned with a view to bringing European nations closer together: rail, road and electricity, food transport infrastructure, the development of the cashless mass payments system and the transnational telecommunications infrastructure. It is noteworthy that many of these organizations developed under the rubric of the League of Nations and later the United Nations, demonstrating how the regional politics of European integration was tightly bound up with developments in wider global politics, especially important being the upheaval of ‘hot’ wars and the East–West Cold War after 1945. This part is supported by biographies of Louis Armand, the search for Europe’s ‘capital’ city and Georges Valensi. The third and final part of the book covers early and troubled attempts to create all-European broadcast infrastructures, waterway connections and civil aviation structures between the world wars. The ‘biographical’ segments in the third part cover the history of the radio station scale, and atomic energy as symbolic of the prospects and limits of European projects. As in the rest of the book, this part indicates how Europe is ‘a constantly de- and reconstructed, linked and de-linked, boosted and jammed broadcast space’ (246), with many and often competing constructions imposed upon it.</p>
<p>As someone not well versed in the history of technology I found this book a useful adjunct to the politically and economically inclined studies that dominate the contemporary literature. It might have benefited from a conclusion that drew out the significance of the main empirical and theoretical findings to emerge from the chapters. That said, its main point is well made. European integration is often set up by supporters and detractors alike as an unstoppable juggernaut bent on the unification of a (disputed) geographic conception of ‘Europe’ which might in time supersede nation states as the source of the public’s political loyalty and civic pride. This book demonstrates the ongoing frailty of this popular journey metaphor. Supporters of integration overplay its unifying effects and underplay the difficulties of transcending supposedly porous national borders, especially with regard to the rise of ‘identity politics’ in the past two decades or so. Opponents of integration likewise overplay the power and influence of the central institutions in Brussels, especially the Commission, and spread mythical stories about the dissolution of the nation state in a culturally monotonous ‘Europe’. What this book suggests is that nuance needs to be the order of the day. Europe as a project is, and has always been, in a constant state of flux. Its end state remains far from clear.</p>
<p><bold>Oliver Daddow</bold>, <italic>Loughborough University</italic></p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>