<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SRI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsri</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Surg Innov</journal-id>
<journal-title>Surgical Innovation</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-3506</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-3514</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1553350612451353</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1553350612451353</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Technology</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Albumin-Coated Bioactive Suture for Cell Transplantation</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Horváthy</surname><given-names>Dénes Balázs</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1553350612451353">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1553350612451353">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Vácz</surname><given-names>Gabriella</given-names></name>
<degrees>MSc</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1553350612451353">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Cselenyák</surname><given-names>Attila</given-names></name>
<degrees>MSc</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1553350612451353">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Weszl</surname><given-names>Miklós</given-names></name>
<degrees>MSc</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1553350612451353">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>Levente</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1553350612451353">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lacza</surname><given-names>Zsombor</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1553350612451353">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1553350612451353">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1553350612451353"><label>1</label>Institute of Human Physiology and Clinical Experimental Research, Semmelweis University, Budapest, Hungary</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1553350612451353"><label>2</label>Department of Orthopedics, Semmelweis University, Budapest, Hungary</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1553350612451353">Dénes Balázs Horváthy, Institute of Human Physiology and Clinical Experimental Research, Semmelweis University, Tűzoltó utca 37-47, Budapest, Hungary. Email: <email>denes.horvathy@tissueengineering.hu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>20</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>249</fpage>
<lpage>255</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Cell therapy holds the promise for a novel modality in the surgical toolkit; however, delivery of cells into damaged soft tissues constitutes a challenge. The authors hypothesized that growing stem cells on the surface of absorbable sutures in vitro and then implanting them via stitching would be a suitable delivery route for cell therapy. Fibronectin, poly-L-lysine, and albumin coatings were used to increase attachment of human and rat bone-marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells (BMSC) to polyfilament absorbable sutures in vitro. Fluorescence microscopy was performed to localize the cells on the suture. After 48 hours of incubation, the albumin-coated sutures had the highest cell number, and after 168 hours cell number reached confluency. In the in vivo experiments, a 10-mm incision was made on the triceps surae muscle of male Wistar rats and rat BMSC coated sutures were placed into the muscle. Two days after the implantation, cells were seen on the surface of the sutures as well as in the surrounding muscle tissue. Long-term results at 5 weeks showed that transplanted cells survived and the sutures were partly absorbed. In conclusion, coating absorbable sutures with proteins, especially serum albumin, improves attachment and proliferation of cells, and only 48 hours in culture is enough to cover the sutures sufficiently. Using these stitches in vivo resulted in short-term and long-term survival of cells. As a result, albumin-coated suture can be a vehicle for stem cell therapy in soft tissues such as muscle, tendon, or peripheral nerves.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>bioactive suture</kwd>
<kwd>cell therapy</kwd>
<kwd>albumin</kwd>
<kwd>regenerative medicine</kwd>
<kwd>stem cells</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1553350612451353" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Cell therapies are already in the spectrum of possible treatment strategies in human diseases. Cell transplantation could be a promising option to increase healing potential in soft tissues, such as skeletal muscle, tendon, or peripheral nerves. In these tissues, the proliferation activity and cell turnover is rather low; therefore, delivering an enhanced number of pluripotent cells is a reasonable supporting mechanism. In addition, several experiments are focusing on stem cell transplantation techniques in tissues with higher cellular turnover such as skin. In our preliminary experiments, we transplanted bone-marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells (BMSC) after skeletal muscle injury in rats, but we were unable to deliver the cell suspension precisely and keep it at the trauma site (Horváthy et al, unpublished observations). We hypothesized that cell-coated sutures will create an easy to use method for cell transplantation, while delivered cells will remain at the injury site, ready to support regeneration. The first problem to be tackled is to reach sufficient adherence and coverage of cells on the sutures in vitro, then to test biocompatibility in an animal model in vivo.</p>
<p>The idea that resorbable sutures may be used for cell delivery is rather simple and straightforward; however, only a few scientific studies aimed to create bioactive sutures by covering them with stem cells have been conducted to date. Mazzocca and coworkers hypothesized that protein-coated sutures might attract endogenous multipotent cells in vivo, which could help tendon to bone healing after a rotator cuff injury.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1553350612451353">1</xref></sup> They coated nonabsorbable sutures with type I collagen and investigated adhesion, proliferation, and protein synthesis of human osteoblasts and tenocytes. They found that collagen coating improves the above-mentioned functions in vitro. Yao and coworkers tested different adhesion proteins to support tendon healing with cell therapies and concluded a that poly-L-lysine and fibronectin coating incorporates significant amount of mouse embryonic stem cells after 8 days of incubation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1553350612451353">2</xref></sup> However, 8 days in culture significantly changes the characteristics of freshly isolated MSCs; therefore, in further clinical use it would be better to decrease this time to 1 to 2 days in order to achieve minimal manipulation of cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1553350612451353">3</xref></sup> They also tested the bioactive suture on explanted tendon in vitro and found that adherent cells endure the mechanical stress created by suturing and remain metabolically active 96 hours after the transplantation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1553350612451353">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>In terms of in vivo biocompatibility of cell-coated sutures, there is only one published report. Pascual and colleagues tested cell-coated sutures without protein coating in a rat colon anastomosis model. They concluded that adipose-derived stem cells seeded on sutures have no effect on colon anastomosis healing.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1553350612451353">5</xref></sup> Gut epithelium, however, has strong regenerative potential with high cellular turnover, so it is possible that there is no room for improvement in this model for any therapy. Nonetheless, these early experiments highlighted the idea that using sutures for cell delivery methods is viable as long as suitable in vitro constructs are designed. The aim of the present study was 2-fold: (<italic>a</italic>) to design a coating and seeding protocol that achieves sufficient stem cell coverage within 1 to 2 days in culture and (<italic>b</italic>) to test the short-term and long-term survival of the implanted cells in muscle tissue.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1553350612451353" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="section3-1553350612451353">
<title>Animals</title>
<p>Male Wistar rats weighing 250 to 300 g were used. Animals were maintained on lab chow and tap water ad libitum with a 12-hour day–night cycle in the conventional animal facility of the Institute of Human Physiology and Clinical Experimental Research, Budapest. The investigation was approved by the local animal research committee according to the guidelines for animal experimentation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1553350612451353">
<title>Stem Cell Harvest and Culture</title>
<p>Wistar rats were terminated with urethane (5 mg/mL). Both tibia and femur were cleaned of tissue and placed in 70% ethanol. Under hood, both ends of the bones were cut and the medulla was flushed out slowly with 10 mL medium (DMEM supplemented with 1 g/L glutamine, 1 g/L glucose, 10% fetal bovine serum, 100 U/mL penicillin, and 100 µg/mL streptomycin) into 15-mL tubes. Bone marrow was centrifuged at 1200 rpm for 8 minutes at room temperature and was placed in 100-mm Petri dishes. After harvesting, BMSCs were maintained at 5% CO<sub>2</sub> level and 37°C. Two days later, the culture was washed in Dulbecco’s phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and fresh medium was given every 48 hours.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1553350612451353">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1553350612451353"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1553350612451353"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1553350612451353">9</xref></sup> After informed consent, human stem cells (HBMSC) were harvested during total hip replacement procedures. Human BMSCs were cultured similar to the previous cell type. The identity of cells was confirmed by the presence of lineage-specific cell surface markers with flow cytometry (BD FacsCalibur, Becton Dickinson, Franklin Lakes, NJ). The majority of cells that were used for the study exhibited mesenchymal lineage-specific cell surface markers (CD73, CD90, CD105, CD166) and lacked hematopoietic markers (CD34, CD45; data not shown).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1553350612451353">
<title>Seeding Cells on Sutures</title>
<p>5-0 Polyfilament absorbable sutures (Vicryl, Ethicon, Somerville, NJ, #W9442) were used for the in vitro experiments. Albumin (Biotest Hungary Kft, Törökbálint, Hungary, #10547a96), fibronectin (Sigma, St Louis, MO, #F0895), and poly-L-lysine proteins (Sigma, #P4832) were applied onto sutures by freeze-drying. Mesenchymal stem cells were labeled with 1 µg/mL Hoechst 33342 (excitation 350 nm, emission 461 nm) for 30 minutes at 37°C. Two-centimeter-long freeze-dried sutures and native, uncoated sutures were put in a 24-well plate with low cell attachment surface (Costar, #3473), and 100 000 labeled cells in 1 mL culture medium were seeded onto each suture. After 48 hours, fresh medium was given to the suture-cell culture. After 24, 48, and 168 hours of incubation, fluorescent confocal microscopy (Zeiss LSM 510 META, Carl Zeiss, Jena, Germany) was performed to localize cells attached to the suture. Seven random regions were selected from the sutures, and nucleus–volume fraction was calculated with the Image J (National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD) analysis program as previously described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1553350612451353">10</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1553350612451353">
<title>In vivo Experiments</title>
<p>To visualize rat BMSC lipophilic membrane, dye Vybrant DiD (excitation 644 nm, emission 665 nm, Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR, #V22889) was applied. A total of 1 700 000 labeled rat BMSCs were seeded onto 17-cm albumin-coated sutures in vitro and were incubated for 1 week as previously described.</p>
<p>Halothane anesthesia was maintained during the operation of male Wistar rats. After the skin incision, the triceps surae muscle was prepared by atraumatic methods. A 10-mm incision was made on the muscle with a scalpel, and the albumin-coated sutures with rat BMSC were applied immediately. The longitudinal incision on the muscle was united with running technique. Following the transplantation process, the wound was closed and animals regained consciousness in their cages. Three animals were terminated at 48 hours. Approximately 1 × 0.5 × 0.2 mm muscle tissue with the bioactive suture in place was removed and native samples underwent fluorescent microscopy. After 5 weeks, another 3 animals were sacrificed, and muscle samples underwent immunohistochemistry.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1553350612451353">
<title>Immunohistochemistry</title>
<p>The samples were embedded in paraffin followed by formalin fixation. After deparaffinaziation, the sections were washed 3 times with PBS. DNAse I (Sigma Aldrich, #DN-25) was used to DNAse digestion. After the antigen retrieval with Retrivagen A (BD Pharmingen, San Jose, CA, #550524) and washing with PBS, the sections were blocked in normal goat serum (Vector, Burlington, CA, #S-1000) for 1 hour. The primer mouse anti-BrDU antibody (BD Pharmingen, #555627) was solubilized in blocking serum and taken on the sections in a dilution of 1:200 overnight at 4°C. After washing with PBS, Alexa Fluor 488 goat antimouse was used to visualize the labeling (30 minutes, room temperature; Molecular Probes, #A11001). Hoechst 33342 (Molecular Probes, #H3570) was applied to the nuclei staining (10 minutes, room temperature). Before covering with Gel Mount (BioMeda, Foster City, CA, #M01) the sections were washed with distilled water.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1553350612451353">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>Results are reported as mean ± SEM. Statistical significances were determined by 1-way, 2-way ANOVA and Bonferroni post hoc tests, using Graphpad Prism statistical software. Probability values of <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01, and <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001 were considered significant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1553350612451353" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>After 24 hours of incubation in vitro, cells were found on the surface of each suture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1553350612451353">Figure 1</xref>). No significant differences were observed between the different coatings. After 48 hours of incubation, the number of attached cells increased on every suture. In addition, at 48 hours of incubation, albumin-coated sutures adhered the highest number of stem cells. There was significant difference between albumin coating and native, uncoated sutures by human BMSCs in the nucleus volume fraction analysis (native 2253 ± 1066 µm<sup>3</sup> vs albumin 53 204 ± 12 949 µm<sup>3</sup> volume fraction, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01). Fibronectin and poly-L-lysine, however, were unable to attach significantly more cells compared with the native sutures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1553350612451353">Figure 2</xref>). Rat BMSCs showed similar adhesion results to the previous cell type; a significantly higher adherent cell number was observed on the albumin-coated sutures after 48 hours (native vs albumin: 13 215 ± 4479 µm<sup>3</sup> vs 59 182 ± 19 722 µm<sup>3</sup> volume fraction, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1553350612451353">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1553350612451353" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Rat BMSCs on albumin-coated suture. Albumin-coated polyfilament suture after 24 hours. The green color represents the Hoechst-labeled rat BMSCs. The 3D structure Z-stack image confirms the attachment of the cells.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1553350612451353-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-1553350612451353" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Nucleus volume fraction of human and rat BMSCs on native, albumin, fibronectin, and poly-L-lysine coated sutures after 24 and 48 hours. Significant difference can be seen in cell the attachment on albumin coated surface after 48 hours. (A) the result with human BMSCs; (B) rat BMSC attachment.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1553350612451353-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Incubation time was extended to 168 hours in order to monitor cell activity on the albumin-coated sutures. At 48 hours of incubation, as described previously, the used medium was removed along with the unattached cells and fresh medium was given. By the end of the 168 hours of incubation, the albumin-coated sutures were completely covered with mesenchymal stem cells. The longer incubation time allowed increased cell adhesion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1553350612451353">Figure 3</xref>). Significant differences were found between 24 and 168 hours (24 vs 168 hours: 27 531 ± 8822 µm<sup>3</sup> vs 153 974 ± 34 738) and between 48 and 168 hours (48 vs 168 hours: 59 182 ± 19 722 µm<sup>3</sup> vs 153 974 ± 34 738; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1553350612451353">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig3-1553350612451353" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Rat BMSCs on albumin-coated suture after 24, 48, and 168 hours. Rat BMSCs successfully attached to the albumin-coated suture already after 24 hours. Green color represents the nuclei of attached cells. The nucleus volume fraction of adhered cells increased as the incubation time increased (A, B, C). (D) The significant difference between the 24 hours and 48 hours incubation compared with 168 hours incubation. (E) 3D reconstruction after 168 hours incubation.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1553350612451353-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In the in vivo experiments, 48 hours after the operation Vibrant DiD labeled cells (red) were found on the surface of the sutures as well as in the muscle tissue next to the sutures, so the mechanical stress did not damage the cells. The cells started to detach from the albumin-coated surface and start to migrate into the injured tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1553350612451353">Figure 4A</xref>). After 5 weeks in vivo incubation, BrDU-labeled cells were still present in the muscle tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1553350612451353">Figure 4B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig4-1553350612451353" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>(A) A freshly harvested sample at 48 hours after suturing. Rat BMSCs labeled with Vibrant DiD (red) can be seen on the suture and in the muscle tissues in close proximity to the suture. Transplanted cells already started to leave the coated surface and migrate into the injured tissue. (B) A representative histology of a transplanted cell at 5 weeks after implantation (white arrow). Green color shows the nuclear Hoescht staining, red represents BrDU positivity. Colocalization results in yellow color.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1553350612451353-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1553350612451353" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In the present study, we have shown that using serum albumin coating on regular absorbable sutures provides a milieu for seeded stem cells to reach a sufficient number in just 48 hours. Implantation of these cells through stitching the material into skeletal muscle was successful; in 2 days the cells were found on the suture and in the surrounding tissue, while at 5 weeks the cells migrated into deeper layers, and absorption of the suture was underway.</p>
<p>Stitching is still the standard method for the repair of soft tissues because it is a simple application, has good mechanical properties, and there is a wide range of available suture material. However, microscopic studies have shown that sutures placed through tendon tissues leads to a well-demarcated “acellular zone” around the suture, which may persist up to 14 days until it is repopulated with healthy cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1553350612451353">11</xref></sup> Therefore, augmenting mechanical repairs with cell therapy protocols can facilitate the repopulation of the acellular zone and induce repair.</p>
<p>Paracrin factors and direct cell contact have been shown to support and save damaged tissues through cell therapy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1553350612451353">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1553350612451353">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1553350612451353"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1553350612451353"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1553350612451353">15</xref></sup> For example, after skeletal muscle injury, satellite cells become active and through the production of myogen precursos initiate tissue regeneration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1553350612451353">16</xref></sup> Even though this is an effective cell population, experimental evidence shows that after muscle injury, and even in physiological conditions, BMSCs are contributing to skeletal muscle remodeling.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1553350612451353">17</xref></sup></p>
<p>In addition, recent findings suggest that the transplantation of skin-derived precursor cells in chronic peripheral nerve injuries results in Schwann cell recruitment and increased proliferation rate. With this technique improved axonal regeneration can be achieved.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1553350612451353">18</xref></sup> Moreover, data show that other cell types such as bone marrow or adipose tissue–derived cells are also able to differentiate into Schwann cell-like lineage; therefore, they are also eligible candidates in nerve remodeling.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1553350612451353">19</xref></sup> Bone-marrow-derived stem cells were shown to support epithelial repair following skin injury because they have the capacity to transdifferentiate into multiple skin cell types.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1553350612451353">20</xref></sup></p>
<p>Even though there are multiple soft tissue targets for cell therapy, the delivery route is still a bottleneck. Simple injections may be effective in generalized damage, such as in end-stage limb ischemia; however, getting cell suspensions into a posttraumatic tissue such as a torn tendon or lacerated muscle is less than optimal.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1553350612451353">21</xref></sup> Experience gained from cardiac implantations shows that the ideal delivery route is far more important than previously thought, since even minor hypoxic or mechanical damage during the transplantation process can diminish the healing potential of cells. Therefore, we first optimized the in vitro process along the lines of previous studies.</p>
<p>In the present study, only polyfilament sutures were used to increase the adhesion surface. We observed that cells prefer to attach to the space between the woven filaments, which may also be a sufficient protection from mechanical stress while suturing. We also hypothesized that coating the surgical sutures with proteins can improve cellular attachment. Coating of suture material with bioactive substrates is a way to further encourage cellular adhesion and proliferation in situ.</p>
<p>To improve not just the seeding efficiency but also the proliferation of the cells, Dines et al used sutures coated with growth differentiation factor-5 in tendon repair without cell implantation and showed a significantly higher tensile load and stiffness at 3 weeks.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1553350612451353">22</xref></sup> In a similar study, Rohrich et al reported on covalently bound epidermal growth factor on Mersilene suture that showed increased cell proliferation along the suture in a rat flexor tendon suture model,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1553350612451353">23</xref></sup> and Hamada et al developed a monofilament nylon suture that continuously elutes basic fibroblast growth factor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1553350612451353">24</xref></sup> They observed that tendons repaired with these BFGF-coated sutures increased biomechanical strength after repair for about 20 days. In an earlier study, Mazzocca et al reported on a type I collagen coated suture, which led to a significant increase in adhesion and proliferation of human osteoblasts in vitro.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1553350612451353">1</xref></sup> Another similar approach was to coat silk suture with the oligopeptid arginine-glycine-aspartic acid to stimulate tenocyte differentiation and proliferation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1553350612451353">25</xref></sup> In this study, Kardestuncer and colleagues found a mild increase in tenocyte adhesion compared with tissue culture plastic. However, the relevance of this comparison is less important for an in vivo situation.</p>
<p>In our experiment, we tested albumin along with the above-mentioned proteins and investigated human and rat BMSC adhesion. We observed that after 24 and 48 hours, cell number is growing on every suture without further seeding, which is a sign of proliferation. In our experiments, we tested cell adhesion in shorter periods of time, because in cell therapies it will be extremely important to keep incubation time as low as possible to fulfill the “minimal manipulation” criteria for regulatory purposes. To fulfill these requirements, we can envision a product such as a coated suture in a closed cell culture bag. Adding freshly isolated bone marrow to the bag and keeping it under cell culture conditions for several days may be enough to reach an implantable cell-coated suture. It would be best to reduce the time in culture to the minimum in order to decrease cell transformation and also to fit better into hospital workflows.</p>
<p>We found that after 48 hours of incubation, albumin coating attached the highest number of cells. To further increase cell number, we incubated albumin-coated sutures for 168 hours. It is important to note that the cell culture medium along with the nonadherent cells were removed and fresh medium was given after 48 hours. At 168 hours of incubation, larger adherent cell numbers were observed, meaning that cells adherent to the sutures at 48 hours were alive and proliferated. Yao and coworkers found a similar pattern of proliferation as in our study, where metabolic activity increased to a peak at day 5 and decreased afterwards.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1553350612451353">4</xref></sup> This decrease in growth likely represents saturation of the suture surface area and competition of the cells for both space and media. Further incubation until 168 hours allowed longer time for proliferation; however, an earlier time point at 48 hours may be used in further human studies. We also found that human and rat cells behave the same and have the same attachment tendency, indicating that translating animal experimental findings to human protocols would be a justified approach. Albumin coating therefore provides a convenient milieu for BMSCs, which may have a significant role in protection from the environmental and mechanical stress created by the transplantation process.</p>
<p>From a clinical point of view, in this work we present a new technique of cell transplantation that can be used in the everyday surgical practice without complicating the surgical procedure itself. Absorbable sutures can be coated with adhesion proteins and cells may be transplanted via the suture material without the use of scaffolds. Several potential products can be designed based on this technology. It is possible to create a precoated suture material with albumin or fibronectin, which is seeded with autologous stem cells at the point of care. Stem cells can be isolated even from peripheral blood,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1553350612451353">26</xref></sup> therefore it can be a minimally invasive procedure for both harvesting and applying cell therapy. A product like this would face minimal regulatory issues since the cells are autologous and freshly isolated, and if a closed system is used, no GMP is required. In case more specific cells are needed, a service can be set up in a similar manner like autologous chondrocyte implant services.</p>
<p>In conclusion, our experiments showed that albumin coating is a suitable environment for BMSCs on the surface of regular suture materials. The cells only adhered to the albumin surface transitionally and become unattached after suturing, so they are able to migrate into the injured tissue readily to support the regenerative process. Therefore, stem-cell-coated sutures may be a suitable new delivery method for cell therapy that is easy to introduce into current surgical practices.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<label>Authors’ Note</label>
<p>Dénes Balázs Horváthy and Gabriella Vácz contributed equally to this study.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This study was supported by TÉT-SIN, TÁMOP 4.2.2-08/1/KMR-2008-0004, TÁMOP 4.2.1/B 09/1/KMR-2010-0001, and OTKA 83803, Bolyai.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1553350612451353">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mazzocca</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arciero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Tendon and bone responses to a collagen-coated suture material</article-title>. <source>J Shoulder Elbow Surg</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>S222</fpage>-<lpage>S230</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1553350612451353">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Korotkova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riboh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Bioactive sutures for tendon repair: assessment of a method of delivering pluripotential embryonic cells</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1558</fpage>-<lpage>1564</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1553350612451353">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Majd</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wipff</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hinz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic expansion culture for mesenchymal stem cells</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>698</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1553350612451353">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Korotkova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Viability and proliferation of pluripotential cells delivered to tendon repair sites using bioactive sutures—an in vitro study</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>252</fpage>-<lpage>258</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1553350612451353">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Miguel</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gómez-Pinedo</surname><given-names>UA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Miguel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arranz</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>García-Olmo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Adipose-derived mesenchymal stem cells in biosutures do not improve healing of experimental colonic anastomoses</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>1180</fpage>-<lpage>1184</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1553350612451353">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gala</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burdzińska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Idziak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Makula</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pączek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of bone-marrow-derived rat mesenchymal stem cells depending on donor age</article-title>. <source>Cell Biol Int</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>1055</fpage>-<lpage>1062</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1553350612451353">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kinnaird</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stabile</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Marrow-derived stromal cells express genes encoding a broad spectrum of arteriogenic cytokines and promote in vitro and in vivo arteriogenesis through paracrine mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Circ Res</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>678</fpage>-<lpage>685</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1553350612451353">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Javazon</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colter</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prockop</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rat marrow stromal cells are more sensitive to plating density and expand more rapidly from single-cell-derived colonies than human marrow stromal cells</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>225</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1553350612451353">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muneta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koga</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sekiya</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of rat mesenchymal stem cells derived from bone marrow, synovium, periosteum, adipose tissue, and muscle</article-title>. <source>Cell Tissue Res</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>327</volume>:<fpage>449</fpage>-<lpage>462</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1553350612451353">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Solé</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Esteve</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A new method based on image analysis for determining cyanobacterial biomass by CLSM in stratified benthic sediments</article-title>. <source>Ultramicroscopy</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>107</volume>:<fpage>669</fpage>-<lpage>673</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1553350612451353">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>JKF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cerovac</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGrouther</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The cellular effect of a single interrupted suture on tendon</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Br</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>358</fpage>-<lpage>367</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1553350612451353">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Majka</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Regeneration of ischemic cardiac muscle and vascular endothelium by adult stem cells</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>1395</fpage>-<lpage>1402</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1553350612451353">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cselenyak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pankotai</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horváth</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lacza</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mesenchymal stem cells rescue cardiomyoblasts from cell death in an in vitro ischemia model via direct cell-to-cell connections</article-title>. <source>BMC Cell Biol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1553350612451353">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sadat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Germert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The cardioprotective effect of mesenchymal stem cells is mediated by IGF-I and VEGF</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>363</volume>:<fpage>674</fpage>-<lpage>679</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1553350612451353">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skelding</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simper</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caplice</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Bone marrow-derived cardiomyocytes are present in adult human heart: a study of gender- mismatched bone marrow transplantation patients</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>1247</fpage>-<lpage>1249</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1553350612451353">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Horváthy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nardai</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Major</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Muscle regeneration is undisturbed by repeated polytraumatic injury</article-title>. <source>Eur J Trauma Emerg Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>-<lpage>167</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1553350612451353">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Palermo</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Labarge</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doyonnas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pomerantz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blau</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Bone marrow contribution to skeletal muscle: a physiological response to stress</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>279</volume>:<fpage>336</fpage>-<lpage>344</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1553350612451353">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Addas</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Midha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Skin-derived precursor cells enhance peripheral nerve regeneration following chronic denervation</article-title>. <source>Exp Neurol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>223</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>228</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1553350612451353">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Midha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Practical considerations concerning the use of stem cells for peripheral nerve repair</article-title>. <source>Neurosurg Focus</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>E2</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1553350612451353">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Inokuma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mesenchymal stem cells are recruited into wounded skin and contribute to wound repair by transdifferentiation into multiple skin cell type</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>180</volume>:<fpage>2581</fpage>-<lpage>2587</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1553350612451353">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tateishi-Yuyama</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murohara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Therapeutic angiogenesis for patients with limb ischaemia by autologous transplantation of bone-marrow cells: a pilot study and a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>360</volume>:<fpage>427</fpage>-<lpage>435</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1553350612451353">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dines</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Razzano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of growth differentiation factor-5-coated sutures on tendon repair in a rat model</article-title>. <source>J Shoulder Elbow Surg</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>S215</fpage>-<lpage>S221</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1553350612451353">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rohrich</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trott</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beran</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Orenstein</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mersilene suture as a vehicle for delivery of growth factors in tendon repair</article-title>. <source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>1713</fpage>-<lpage>1717</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1553350612451353">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hibino</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kosaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yasui</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of monofilament nylon coated with basic fibroblast growth factor on endogenous intrasynovial flexor tendon healing</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>530</fpage>-<lpage>540</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1553350612451353">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kardestuncer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karageorgiou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gronowicz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>RGD-tethered silk substrate stimulates the differentiation of human tendon cells</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>448</volume>:<fpage>234</fpage>-<lpage>239</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1553350612451353">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marfe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rotta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Martino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A new clinical approach: use of blood-derived stem cells (BDSCs) for superficial digital flexor tendon injuries in horses</article-title>. <source>Life Sci</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>825</fpage>-<lpage>830</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>