<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ISS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spiss</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Sociology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0268-5809</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7242</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0268580912452370e</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0268580912452370e</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reviews: Migration, ethnic lives and communalism</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Saskia Bonjour, Andrea Rea and Dirk Jacobs (eds), <italic>The Others in Europe</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>Jonas</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0268580912452370">University of Virginia, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>646</fpage>
<lpage>649</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bonjour</surname><given-names>Saskia</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rea</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>Dirk</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds), <source>The Others in Europe</source>, <publisher-name>Editions de l’Université de Bruxelles</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Bruxelles</publisher-loc>, <year>2011</year>; <page-count count="203"/> pp.: ISBN <isbn>9782800415062</isbn>, <price>US$28.40</price></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">International Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Europe</kwd>
<kwd>identity</kwd>
<kwd>immigration</kwd>
<kwd>labor</kwd>
<kwd>migration policy</kwd>
<kwd>otherness</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Ongoing social, political, and economic uncertainty in Europe bring to the fore long-standing concerns about who ‘belongs’ in Europe raising questions about the responsibilities of the European Union and individual states are to those who do belong, and to those who are deemed not to belong. European states have built up deep and enduring cultural identities that appear less certain following the establishment of the EU, and, the impact of decades of immigration from both within and, more especially, outside Europe has exacerbated those concerns in recent years. While the development of EU citizenship has improved certain aspects of social, political, and economic functionality and development, this added layer of identity further complicates the relationship between sovereign states and the EU, especially when considering non-European immigrants.</p>
<p>It is within this context that Bonjour, Rea, and Jacobs have produced <italic>The Others in Europe</italic> – essays presented at a conference held by the Migration, Asylum, and Multiculturalism (MAM) research center at the Université de Libre de Bruxelles. This edited volume offers a transdisciplinary perspective on the various relationships between migration and ‘Otherness’ in Europe. The editors group the collection into two sets of chapters – the first offering insights from the disciplines of legal, political, and sociological studies and the second set provides social psychological and anthropological analysis.</p>
<p>Bonjour and her colleagues open the book with an overview of several of the major themes of both the collected essays and the MAM project more generally. These include migration shifts and the resulting effects on the processes of identity creation and maintenance for Europeans and non-Europeans; security and risk management for receiving states; and to identity mobilization within a context of national, supra-national, and non-national possibilities. Occupying a central role throughout the introduction and much of the collection is a concern for particular national and universal EU immigration and citizenship laws and policies. This is a valuable inclusion given the unique European experiences with immigration and transnational unification, as legal structures and processes frame virtually all of the dynamics between European states and their ‘Others.’ Although not a central theme among the papers, Bonjour, Rea, and Jacobs rightly remind us that the concept of ‘otherness’ frequently carries with it religious implications – specifically that of Islam – that add a global, political dimension to identity that complicates questions of equality and integration even further.</p>
<p>The first three chapters take up questions concerning the legal integration of ‘third country nationals’ (TCN) within the European Union. Kees Groenendijk in Chapter 2 (‘Categorizing human beings in EU migration law’) outlines the development of European categories of migrant peoples from 1957 to 2010 and analyses the influence of EU policies on member state policies regarding migrants. Specifically, he finds the development of the TCN to be a potentially constructive category, but concludes that the use of large databases by the EU and member states to catalogue both immigration and crime data may be combined in such ways to disproportionately target TCNs, thus creating more risk than do other particular legal labels. In Chapter 3 (‘Mandatory integration provisions in EC and EU Member States law’), Yves Pascouau discusses the interaction between EU and member states’ mandatory integration policies and the potential ramifications of that interaction as more states implement their own integration policies. Focusing on family reunification policies targeting TCNs implemented by the EU and enacted by member states, Pascouau argues that member states can use integration policies as a means to limit TCNs’ entrance into Europe, rather than aid integration. Continuing the focus on EU laws concerning the integration of TCNs in Chapter 4 (‘Some foreigners more equal than others under EU law’), Cholé Hublet’s in-depth analysis of Article 18 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union (TFEU) suggests that non-Europeans will continue to face nationality-based discrimination, despite the law’s intent to prevent it. She argues that the 2009 <italic>Vatsouras</italic> ruling by the European Court of Justice confirms that Article 18 only protects Europeans from nationality-based discrimination, not TCNs. While other legal avenues may be sought to protect TCNs, current interpretations of Article 18 underscore the ability of EU law to hinder the integration of non-European ‘Others.’</p>
<p>Taking up the Foucauldian perspective on ‘governmentality.’ Bigo, Jeandeboz, Ragazzi, and Bonditti ask ‘what is the relationship between mobility, security, and government?’ in Chapter 5 (‘Borders and security: The different logistics of surveillance in Europe’). Bigo et al. suggest that the implementation of greater technological measures throughout the EU reflects a refocusing on monitoring ‘unwanted, marginalized, and abnormalized’ migration (p. 83), and so argue that transnational security efforts should no longer be understood in terms of a tradeoff between freedom and security. Drawing on the example of the Frontex agency and echoing arguments from Chapter 2, the authors suggest the data gathering made available through technological enhancements – a ‘proactivity/profiling/prevention’ model (p. 88) – may subject particular groups and individuals – presumably the European ‘Other’ – to increased surveillance and social injustice.</p>
<p>In Chapter 6 (‘Reasonable accommodation of religious diversity in Europe and Belgium: Law and practice’), Bribosia, Rea, Ringelheim, and Rorive address the lack of reasonable accommodation laws regarding religious identity and practice in the EU, and Belgium specifically, in the context of labor relations. While a comparative case like the Canadian system has developed high levels of reasonable accommodation that account for both worker and employer rights, Bribosia et al. conclude that such broad, legal accommodation is not likely in Belgium in the foreseeable future. Rather, recent examples of ad hoc religious accommodations for workers made by employers might serve as demonstrations of a potentially acceptable, intermediate step toward eventual national-level policy.</p>
<p>Didier Fassin offers insight into several sociopolitical processes that help produce otherness in Europe in the seventh chapter (‘The social construction of Otherness’). Where otherness was once a product of national or geographic difference, it is now defined by race, ethnicity, and religion, regardless of national origin. This is particularly salient in France, for instance, where the national statistics purposely exclude collecting data on racial or ethnic indicators – a result of policies meant to create blind equality. However, given the predominant, implicit, self-identity of Europeans as white, Christian, and democratic, French (or other European) citizenship does not guarantee equal social, political, or economic treatment for those who do not match that traditional European identity.</p>
<p>The next two chapters examine minority self-identity from the field of social psychology. Maykel Verkuten’s chapter (‘Ethnic discrimination and minority identity: A social psychological perspective’) shifts the discussion of otherness from the unilateral impacts of ascription to an understanding of otherness as a dynamic process between and among groups. Applying social psychological theory and survey data, Verkuten confirms that discrimination increases when immigrants are perceived to hold values deemed contrary to majority values or display strong ethic identities. Surprisingly, he finds that when ethnic minorities in the Netherlands acquire more education – a long-supported means for social integration – the more attuned they become to social inequalities and the more negative their attitudes toward the majority population, creating an ‘integration paradox’ that is at the heart of Verkuten’s study. In Chapter 9 (‘Why do minorities rarely report experiences with discrimination?’), Alarcon-Henriquez and Azzi present an exploratory study of the underreporting of discrimination, identified in a 2009 report by the EU Agency for Fundamental Rights. Their interviews demonstrate three, discrete explanatory phenomena for underreporting: (1) respondents did not perceive discriminatory action toward them; (2) respondents viewed discriminatory practices as part of the social landscape for minorities; (3) respondents knew little about the various anti-discrimination resources available to them.</p>
<p>The final two chapters explore the role of civil society as a means by which minorities negotiating their otherness in the EU. Gregoire and Petit’s chapter (‘Communitarian rhetorics within a changing context: Belgian Pan-African associations in a comparative perspective’) argues that previous understandings of Pan-African movements, especially those in the United States, do not offer sufficient analytical power for the Belgian context. The development of these immigrant civil associations in Belgium represents grassroots efforts toward overcoming social, political, and economic barriers that accompany the otherness of race and immigration status. Finally, Bruno Riccio concludes the collection with an examination of second generation minorities’ development of civil associations in Italy (Second generation associations and the Italian social construction of ‘Otherness’). Though born in Italy, members of these organizations are working to both overcome multiple forms of discrimination, as well as demonstrate their rights and aspirations for opportunity – something seemingly not afforded by citizenship alone.</p>
<p>Given the current state of European economics, the relationship between immigration policy and labor demographics, and the political climate produced by these intersecting phenomena, this work offers valuable insight into many of the ways in which otherness continues to play a significant role in the European trajectory. Although lacking (by design) a clearly articulated, cohesive argument to bind all the contributions, the diversity of the articles reflects the complexity of identity politics in Europe. This work will be of value for those looking for comparative cases within the EU context and will provide an important reminder of the tangled nature of European immigration, race, labor, and legal concerns.</p>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<p><bold>Jonas Hart</bold> is a doctoral candidate of sociology at the University of Virginia. His research focuses on state policy and Muslim communities in North America and Europe <italic>Address</italic>: Department of Sociology, University of Virginia, 2015 Ivy Road, Dynamics Building, 3rd Floor, PO Box 400766, Charlottesville, VA 22904-4766, USA. Email: <email>jonas.hart@virginia.edu</email></p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>