<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OTO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spoto</journal-id>
<journal-title>Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0194-5998</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1097-6817</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599812445165</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0194599812445165</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Pediatric Otolaryngology: Principles and Practice Pathways</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Baldassari</surname><given-names>Cristina M.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<aff id="aff1-0194599812445165">Eastern Virginia Medical School, Norfolk, Virginia, USA</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>146</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>1044</fpage>
<lpage>1044</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wetmore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muntz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGill</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>Pediatric Otolaryngology: Principles and Practice Pathways</source>. <edition>2nd edition</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Thieme Medical Publishers</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year>. ISBN-10: <isbn>9781604064131</isbn>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Academy of Otolaryngology—Head and Neck Surgery Foundation 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Official journal of the American Academy of Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery Foundation</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The second edition of <italic>Pediatric Otolaryngology: Principles and Practice Pathways</italic> by R. Wetmore, H. Muntz, and T. McGill was recently published in March 2012. This single-volume text features a comprehensive review of pediatric otolaryngology in a concise and evidence-based format. The book highlights the medical and surgical management of disease processes and pathologies encountered in pediatric otolaryngology. The authors’ aim was to provide clinicians with practical, evidence-based practice pathways to treat a wide range of pediatric otolaryngology disorders. The target readership is residents, fellows, pediatric and general otolaryngologists, pediatricians, and pediatric subspecialists. The text was designed to serve as an “authoritative reference for day-to-day pediatric otolaryngology clinical practice.”</p>
<p>The text is 976 pages in length and features contributions from many of the leading experts in the subspecialty of pediatric otolaryngology. The book is divided into 6 sections, including “General Considerations”; “The Ear”; “The Nose, Paranasal Sinuses, and Orbit”; “The Oral Cavity, Pharynx, and Esophagus”; “The Larynx, Trachea, and Upper Airway”; and “The Neck.” This second edition contains updated sections on cochlear implantation, genetic breakthroughs that affect congenital hearing loss, and controversies in pediatric adenotonsillectomy.</p>
<p>One of the main strengths of this book is the inclusion of pertinent figures and tables. There are more than 725 illustrations in the text. For quick reference, the authors have also included tables titled “At a Glance.” These tables provide readers with take-home points on disorders commonly encountered in pediatric otolaryngology. For example, in the chapter titled “Diseases of the Cochlea and Labyrinth,” 2 “At a Glance” tables highlight the most common causes of autosomal dominant childhood hearing loss and the differential diagnosis for progressive childhood sensorineural hearing loss. The authors also include “Special Consideration” boxes that provide the reader with further information regarding controversial topics or new developments on a given subject. Finally, each chapter contains several unique “Practice Pathways.” The pathways, which are depicted in the form of flowcharts, are designed to aid physicians in identifying and managing clinical problems in pediatric otolaryngology. Examples of these evidence-based algorithms found in the pediatric cochlear implantation chapter include practice pathways for determining cochlear implant candidacy and imaging in the evaluation for cochlear implantation.</p>
<p><italic>Pediatric Otolaryngology: Principles and Practice Pathways</italic> will be a great addition to the libraries of both pediatric and general otolaryngologists as it highlights evidence-based, practical management strategies for common and complex pediatric otolaryngology disorders.</p>
</body>
</article>