<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JFN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjfn</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Fam Nurs</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Family Nursing</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1074-8407</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-549X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1074840713483496</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1074840713483496</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Family Nursing Network</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>History Lesson</article-title>
<subtitle>How a Little Girl and Her Family Moved Mountains to Change Care and Policy to Help Children With Special Health Care Needs Go Home</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sullivan-Bolyai</surname><given-names>Susan L.</given-names></name>
<degrees>DNSc, CNS, RN</degrees>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Feetham</surname><given-names>Suzanne</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD, RN, FAAN</degrees>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>278</fpage>
<lpage>280</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>We were both saddened to hear of Katie Beckett’s passing away at 34 years of age in May 2012 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1074840713483496">Hevesi, 2012</xref>). In the early 80s, Katie and her family were pioneers in transitional care for children with medical technology needs in the United States. During her early life she lived in an Iowa hospital due to complications related to viral encephalitis that left her ventilator dependent. During this time there had been major medical and technological advances to sustain the lives of children with special health care needs with growing numbers of children being supported by technology, yet living in hospital settings rather than being discharged home. For many of these families when discharged they were not prepared for the complexity of their child’s care. For those of you who have worked with this special patient and family population, Katie Beckett’s name may be well-known and associated with pioneering transitional home care innovation, and freedom for children with high technology needs, to allow them to thrive at home with their families rather than remain in institutional care.</p>
<p>In the 1980’s, it was the perfect storm of several important events and innovative ideas that changed where these children would live (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1074840713483496">Goldberg, Faure, &amp; O’Callaghan, 2005</xref>). It was the efforts of Katie’s parents (Julie and Mark) and their vision for their daughter that would over time change the lives of more than half a million children across the United States, transitioning them from hospital to home. They advocated through their Iowa congressman to explore financial options to help them bring Katie home. At the same time, Dr. C. Everett Koop, U.S. Surgeon General also believed in the home care model for medically fragile children, thus in 1982 he brought together experts from diverse fields including Dr. S. Feetham, to discuss transitioning children home with ventilator support. The Beckett family was able to start a grassroots effort to help children and families live as normally as possible in the least restrictive environment. The hospital versus home trajectory was also altered by Vice President George H.W. Bush bringing the Becketts’ plight to the attention of President Ronald Reagan who made an “exception to policy” that allowed Medicaid monies to pay for Katie’s home care costs. Then in 1982 a bipartisan-driven Medicaid bill that President Reagan signed allowed states to use both federal and state funds to help pay for home care for children and adults who had complex health care needs (referred to in the State of Illinois as the Katie Beckett Waiver, P.L. 97-248 under Tax Equity and Fiscal Responsibility Act-TEFRA—permitting states to ignore family income for certain chronic conditions and use Medicaid benefits; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1074840713483496">Musumeci, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Prior to the Medicaid waivers, many of the children requiring high technology support lived for years in hospitals that were financially costly and developmentally restrictive. The children were cared for by interdisciplinary teams consisting of nurses, physicians, nutritionists, physical, occupational, and speech therapists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1074840713483496">Goldberg, et al., 2005</xref>). Yes, the interdisciplinary team concept that is now the rage in adult health care is not a new one to those of us working with families of children with special health care needs. The policy and grassroots storm led us all on an exciting adventure across the United States of finding ways for the best strategies for teaching and preparing families to manage their children’s care at home that included close follow-up and support.</p>
<p>The first time I (first author, Susan Sullivan-Bolyai) met Dr. Feetham was in 1984 at a State of Illinois task force through the Division of Specialized Care for Children (DSCC). We were meeting to discuss how we could ensure continuity of care (with the Medicaid waiver) for families with children that required high technology support. Dr. Feetham consulted with our interdisciplinary team to help us develop a family framework that would help guide us in this important task. There were several pediatric-family facilities at the time across the country charged with this special mission. At LaRabida Children’s Hospital in Chicago (where I worked as the continuity of care coordinator) we collaborated with state and home care agencies to ensure that these children and their families went home safely with continuous coordinated and cost effective care. It was a beautiful comprehensive model that embraced the family with resources and support.</p>
<p>Fast forward and now there are many kinds of financial and coordination issues resulting in fragmentation of care that leaves families to navigate the system on their own and threatens the coordinated home care model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1074840713483496">Goldberg, et al., 2005</xref>). In the current context it is important that we remember the vanguard efforts of Katie’s family that enabled her to grow up and lead a normal life, completing her college education, and working as a contributing citizen of Iowa. Isn’t that what all parents want for their children? As nurses through our programs of research and scholarship we need to develop and describe innovative family interventions. We need to capitalize on opportunities as members of interdisciplinary teams across health care systems to assure continuity of care that includes timely education, coordination of services, follow-up, advocacy, and support. All children with special health care needs deserve the opportunity like Katie to live life to its fullest potential. All families need the skills to navigate the health, education, and social systems to meet the needs of their child and family. We thank Katie and her family for what they taught us and for demonstrating how one family can change policy. Outcome data from research of families positions nurses for advocacy and informing policy both as a collective and as individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1074840713483496">Feetham, 2011</xref>).</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>Susan L. Sullivan-Bolyai, DNSc, CNS, RN<break/>
<italic>Graduate School of Nursing, University of Massachusetts</italic><break/>
<italic>Medical School, Worcester, MA</italic><break/>
Suzanne Feetham, PhD, RN, FAAN<break/>
<italic>University of Wisconsin–Milwaukee, Milwaukee, WI</italic><break/>
<italic>Children’s National Medical Center, Washington, DC</italic></sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1074840713483496">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feetham</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The role of science policy in programs of research and scholarship</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hinshaw</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grady</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Shaping health policy through nursing research</source> (pp. <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1074840713483496">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>A. I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>E. A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Callaghan</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>High-technology home care: Critical issues and ethical choices</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Monagle</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomasma</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Health care ethics: Critical issues for the 21st century</source> (pp. <fpage>146</fpage>-<lpage>163</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jones &amp; Bartlett</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1074840713483496">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hevesi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>, <month>May</month> <day>22</day>). <article-title>Katie Beckett, who inspired health reform, dies at 34</article-title>, <source>New York Times</source>, p. <fpage>A21</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1074840713483496">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Musumeci</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Modernizing Medicaid eligibility criteria for children with significant disabilities: Moving from a disabling to an enabling paradigm</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Law and Medicine</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>81</fpage>-<lpage>127</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>