<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JRN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjrn</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Research in Nursing</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1744-9871</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1744-988X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1744987110379784</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1744987110379784</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Review: Attitudes of Jordanian nursing students to nursing research</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>MacGuire</surname><given-names>Jillian</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1744987110379784"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1744987110379784">Emeritus Professor, University of Cardiff, UK</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1744987110379784">Jillian MacGuire, Selwyn Garden House, Lime Kiln Quay Road, Woodbridge, Suffolk, IP12 1BB, UK Email: <email xlink:type="simple">jill@macguire.org.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>17</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>374</fpage>
<lpage>375</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2010 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>There have been many studies of nurses' interest in research but most of them have been from North America or Europe. This is the first such study to be carried out in an Arabic country.</p>
<p>The development work on the scale used was of high quality. The items included were derived from earlier research by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1744987110379784">Funk et al. (1991)</xref>. They were carefully piloted to ensure that they were intelligible and then translated into Arabic. The translation was vetted by the language department of the university and the items were piloted for a second time.</p>
<p>A Lickert-type scale of 18 items was developed and students were asked to identify their attitudes to nursing research on one of four points ranging from strongly disagree (1) to strongly agree (4). This was a forced choice scale eliminating the possibility of a neutral middle position. A second questionnaire covered demographic data and there was a face sheet outlining the purpose of the research.</p>
<p>Senior nursing students were targeted. In total 900 questionnaires were distributed and completed documents were returned by 68%. This is not a high response rate given that the students were in the nursing faculty, were obliged to have completed a course in nursing research as a condition of inclusion and could be easily contacted.</p>
<p>The analysis of the data was sophisticated. There is some question about whether this was warranted because of nature of sample. Analysis of variance produced four dimensions of the scale items. The Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic>-test was used to explore the differences between the attitudes of male and female students to research.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most useful aspect of this research is that the scale can be used in all Arabic-speaking countries. Its use would enable universities to see if they are getting the message across. Testing at the start of the course and re-testing at the end of the module is the next logical development, All students should be required to participate, This would not only give their views but a measure of the success of the course in bringing about positive attitudes to nursing research.</p>
<p>Although the sample was large and the response just over two-thirds, it was a self-selected group and the results cannot be generalised to all students following similar courses in Jordan nor even to the senior student body at the University of Amman. This piece of research has to be regarded as a pilot if only because of the way the sample was obtained. However, the scale developed is robust and could be used in other faculties, as could the types of analyses carried out. It is a significant step forward in the assessment of senior students' attitudes towards research in nursing and has considerable potential for the future monitoring of courses in nursing research.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>Reference</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1744987110379784"><citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Champagne</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiese</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tornquist</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Barriers to using research findings in practice: the clinician's perspective</article-title>. <source>Appl Nurs Res</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<bio xlink:type="simple">
<p><bold>Jillian MacGuire</bold> (BA, PhD, RGN) graduated at London University (LSE) and went on to do research work on nursing training in Oxford registering for a PhD at LSE at the same time. After a period of part-time teaching, she was appointed Director of Nursing Research at the (then) General Nursing Council. She was seconded as a researcher to the Briggs Committee in the early 1970s and also taught the MA students at the Royal College of Nursing. She has written one book and many research papers. In her early 40s she trained as a nurse, worked in a hospital for elderly people and was made RCN Professor of Nursing Research at Cardiff in 1992.</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>