<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EHQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spehq</journal-id>
<journal-title>European History Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0265-6914</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7110</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0265691411428783av</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0265691411428783av</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Gareth Stockey, <italic>Gibraltar: ‘A Dagger in the Spine of Spain?’</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>Jennifer Ballantine</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0265691411428783av">Gibraltar</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>199</fpage>
<lpage>201</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0265691411428783av"><title>Gareth Stockey, <italic>Gibraltar: ‘A Dagger in the Spine of Spain?’</italic>, Sussex Academic Press: Brighton, 2009; 256 pp.; 9781845193010, £55.00 (hbk)</title>
<p>Gareth Stockey looks at trans-border relations between Gibraltar and Spain during the first half of the twentieth century, with particular focus on the years spanning the fall of the Second Republic, the Spanish Civil War and Second World War, and the lead up to the 1954 visit to Gibraltar by Elizabeth II. These years are dealt with in great detail, with Stockey analysing the complexity of interactions between both countries and across different sectors and interest groups on either side of the frontier. The Gibraltar/Spain border is therefore of central consideration, and, indeed, Stockey’s point of departure is the construction, by the British military authorities, of the fence on the neutral ground in 1908, an event which, he suggests, ‘marked for the first time in over a century, the existence of a physical “border” between Gibraltar and the Campo’. A fence had in any case always existed at the Spanish edge of the neutral ground but Stockey places some emphasis on this development given that the relocation of the British fence was only possible through the absorption, by the British authorities, of their section of the neutral ground into ‘mainland’ Gibraltar. The shifting of the boundary not only brought Gibraltar physically closer to Spain, it also redefined her territorial limits. Still, the question of proximity is a central consideration here as Stockey sets out to ‘challenge the importance of a formal frontier as a dividing force between two communities’, going as far as to suggest that these communities were so close by the first half of the twentieth century that it might not be inaccurate to suggest that they functioned as one rather than two separate entities. Such a thesis raises all sorts of questions, especially when considered in light of the powerful geopolitical discourse that followed the closure of the frontier in 1969. The closure not only kept communities apart, but also gave rise to insecurity and the belief, on the part of Gibraltarians, that proximity to Spain, culturally or otherwise, challenged their Britishness, an important factor when it came to keeping the Spanish territorial claim at bay. These complex feelings and some of the historiography that followed tended to transplant the sentiments of 1969 onto the historical past as a means to explain Franco’s decision to close the frontier.</p>
<p>Then again, these are precisely the readings that Stockey sets out to address; ones which he terms as ‘present-day attitudes’ (although these are increasingly less current), and which have served to define constructs of a Gibraltarian identity and perceptions of her relationship with Spain. The focus on the frontier has been such that the barriers (political, class, economic, institutional or linguistic ones) that existed within Gibraltar and between the Garrison and the civilian population were rarely discussed.</p>
<p>Stockey extends his challenge of a formal frontier to include discussion on those other barriers within, making this a very detailed study of Gibraltar society of the day. The emphasis Stockey gives to the complex levels of interactions is considerable and significant. He goes to great lengths to demonstrate that far from a divider, the border with Spain facilitated an economy and the transfer of cultural norms. We are also dealing with trans-border relationships based on dependencies; that of El Campo on the Gibraltar economy and just as important, that of Gibraltar on El Campo for a workforce. This very fact ensured, as Stockey argues, that every diplomatic effort was made during some very challenging times (see for example the Second World War and the threat posed by Spain’s alliance with the Axis), to maintain fluidity across the frontier.</p>
<p>We see therefore, that despite diplomatic tensions and the more local ones stemming from, on the whole, the contraband trade, the frontier between Gibraltar and Spain operated with fluidity and ease. A fence or frontier constructed by officials may well have caused friction, but on the ground it did little to alter the relationship between Gibraltar and El Campo. Whether or not such interface led to these communities, or at least certain sectors from each, being more similar than dissimilar, or whether or not they functioned as one larger community rather two separate ones remains a compelling question. Stockey seems to suggest that it was during this first half of the twentieth century that Gibraltarians became progressively more ‘socially, culturally, linguistically and increasingly politically’, closer to El Campo. It would also be useful to look back to at least the nineteenth century to determine if this trend forms part of a natural progression, one which peaked in the twentieth century, or if we are dealing with a pattern of interactions informed by ruptures over a period of time. It is also interesting to note that it was precisely Gibraltar’s status as a separate (from Spain) economic and sovereign jurisdiction that fuelled, if not sustained, the impressive level and range of interactions across both spaces.</p>
<p><bold>Jennifer Ballantine Perera</bold>, <italic>Gibraltar</italic></p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>