<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TTJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spttj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Theology Today</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0040-5736</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2044-2556</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0040573613485526</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0040573613485526</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Review Essay</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Mystic and Rebel—The Pathbreaking Journey of Dorothee Soelle</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>DioGuardi</surname><given-names>Shirley Cloyes</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0040573613485526"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0040573613485526">Ossining, New York, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0040573613485526">Email: <email>cloyes@bestweb.net</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>70</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>196</fpage>
<lpage>199</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Princeton Theological Seminary/Theology Today</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic>Dorothee Soelle—Mystic and Rebel: The Biography</italic></p>
<p>Renate Wind</p>
<p>Minneapolis: Fortress, 2012, 203 pp. Hardcover. $25.00</p>
<p>While Dorothee Soelle’s theological writings and political engagement would prevent her from ever receiving a university teaching appointment in Germany, where she was born in 1929, they would catapult her onto the international stage and lead to an invitation to join the faculty at New York’s Union Theological Seminary. When she arrived at Union, where she would teach four months a year from 1975 to 1987, her words were already having a huge impact on a new generation of students who, in Renate Wind’s words, “had turned their backs on the traditional church, its appearance and language, and now discovered themselves and their world in her text” (63). I was among them. Although I entered Union in the fall of 1976, I would not meet Dorothee until 1981, after I had completed two years of a Master of Divinity degree, taught for two years on the faculty of a university in Indonesia, and returned to Union for my third and final year of study. In 1982, I would become the editor of Soelle’s first book written in English for an American audience: <italic>To Work and To Love: A Theology of Creation</italic> (Fortress, 1984).</p>
<p><italic>Dorothee Soelle—Mystic and Rebel</italic> is the first biography to be written about one of the most prolific, inspiring, and controversial theologians to emerge in the postwar era. It is well served by Wind’s interviews with two of Soelle’s closest and most innovative colleagues at Union, Tom Driver and Beverly Harrison, as it is also by her decision to focus on the “two most important witnesses to her life” (xii): Soelle’s husband, Fulbert Steffensky, and her best friend, Luise Schottroff. Steffensky and Schottroff, both fellow theologians, contributed greatly to the biography by giving Wind many previously unpublished photographs, documents, and stories. The book is further enhanced by Wind’s discussions with daughter Mirjam Steffensky.</p>
<p>The title of Wind’s biography is well chosen, because central to the power of Soelle’s contribution is that she defied conventional categories as she wrote, lectured, taught, and protested her way across continents from the 1960s until her death in 2003. She was a scholar, a lover of art and music, a poet and a mystic, a pacifist and a defender of revolutionary struggles. She was a Protestant ecumenicist, who found her roots in Judaism. She was a wife, mother of four, and a feminist. Her experience growing up during the Nazi Holocaust in a highly educated and affluent family would lead her to become a voice for the people of the “Third World” struggling for self-determination in the second half of the twentieth century.</p>
<p>Ten years after Soelle’s death, pastors, theologians, students, church members, and activists familiar with her work (25 of her books are available in English translation) no doubt will herald Wind’s biography as long overdue, thoroughly researched, and superbly written. The publication in English of <italic>Dorothee Soelle: Mystic and Rebel</italic> is occurring at a historical juncture, when Soelle’s appeal to church and theology to speak not to “timeless and generalized truths,” but to “the thirst for justice and righteousness,” once again demands our attention in a world ensnared by her abiding concerns: an ever-increasing gap between rich and poor, environmental degradation, the unrestrained growth of the military industrial complex, and war.</p>
<p>I also believe that readers who have been influenced by Soelle’s life and work will find Wind to be an ideal interlocutor. In her preface, Wind explains that she did not strive for “completeness,” given the “many other important theological and spiritual appraisals of Soelle that would fill volumes by themselves” (xiii). Instead, Wind, Professor of Biblical Theology and Church History at the Evangelische Hoschschule Nürnberg, chose to write from her perspective as an activist in the peace and solidarity movements since 1965. When she finally met Soelle in person in 1995, Wind had already spent many years recognizing in Dorothee a “shared dream of a world in which life, love, and work are given their due place, a world … of justice and peace for human beings and for nature” (xiii). Even so, Wind succeeds in merging an accessible analysis of several of Soelle’s principal writings, including books not yet published in English, with the multifaceted components of her personal journey.</p>
<p>Wind is well suited to this task. In 1991, she published the acclaimed <italic>Dietrich Bonhoeffer: A Spoke in the Wheel</italic> (Eerdmans). Bonhoeffer helped found the Confessing Church in 1934 in opposition to German Christian acquiescence to Nazism, spent a brief time at Union Theological Seminary in New York in June 1939, returned to Germany to openly protest the Nazi persecution of Jews, and participated in a failed plot on Hitler’s life that would lead to his incarceration and subsequent execution at the Flossenbürg concentration camp at the age of 39 in 1945.</p>
<p>The evolution of Soelle’s life and work (she was 16 when Bonhoeffer was executed) can be understood only against the backdrop of the Holocaust. Wind devotes appropriate attention to the link between Bonhoeffer’s legacy and Soelle’s struggle with orthodox Christianity and a German Protestant church that had overwhelmingly succumbed to Hitler. Later Soelle would assert that her “attempt to do theology is marked by the awareness that I live after Auschwitz,”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0040573613485526">1</xref></sup> and she would take up Bonhoeffer’s challenge “to see the great events of world history from below, from the perspective of those who suffer” (11).</p>
<p>While Soelle’s parents privately opposed Hitler and his racial ideology, they did not join the resistance. They were not forced to leave Germany, and her father, a renowned professor of labor law, gave nominal public support to the Nazi party in order to safeguard the lives of his wife and children. Soelle’s parents hid a Jewish woman in their attic, at the same time that they concealed the Jewish identity of Dorothee’s paternal grandmother, even from their children. Drawing on Soelle’s early diaries and her 1999 <italic>Against the Wind: Memoir of a Radical Christian</italic>, Wind skillfully charts Dorothee’s rite of passage as a privileged adolescent sheltered from the Nazi terror and enthralled with German Romantic poetry, music, and art, to her feeling of victimization when her family is forced to evacuate their home and scavenge for food during the Allied bombing, and finally to her coming to terms as a young adult with the accommodation of her father and the complicity of his generation in the Holocaust.</p>
<p>Soelle entered university in 1949 and eventually decided to complete a doctorate in theology “to get at the truth that had been kept from me long enough” (31; from <italic>Against the Wind</italic>, 13). This was the basis on which she became a Christian and from which she would begin to challenge the church and orthodox theology. An overarching theme of her critique over four decades would be the church’s failure to make the connection between the West’s militarism, materialism, and the oppression of the poor abroad and apathy and alienation at home. In her 1981 book <italic>Choosing Life</italic> (Fortress), she would assert that “the material misery of the Third World and the psychological misery of the West belong together, economically, politically, and ecologically—culturally and psychologically as well. To establish this connection and to make it evident is a theological task for our time” (65).</p>
<p>Wind demonstrates how Soelle’s theological inquiry was deeply entwined with her personal journey. When in the 1960s, her marriage to her first husband collapsed, Soelle joined a discussion forum of Protestants and Roman Catholics seeking to “put into practice the statement that faith and politics are inseparable” (<italic>Against the Wind</italic>, 37). Fulbert Stefensky, her future husband, was among the organizers of what became known as “Political Evensong,” drawing about a thousand people to its meetings in the 1960s and the 1970s. It was in this context that Soelle began her study of the Vietnam War, Western imperialism, liberation movements, and life in the developing world. “The Vietnam War,” she wrote, “helped me to see my own history from a new perspective: Auschwitz did not end with the war; it continued—that was the lesson to be learned” (<italic>Against the Wind</italic>, 43). Henceforth she would embark on a lifelong involvement in anti-war and solidarity movements around the world.</p>
<p>Dorothee thrived at Union Theological Seminary, and as her theological writings and poetry began to appear in English translation, she traveled widely and became involved with Latin American liberation movements, the North American Sanctuary movement for refugees fleeing war and poverty, the anti-apartheid movement in South Africa, the international effort to halt the arms race, and more. Wind explores the impact of these movements on Soelle’s political and theological thinking and shows how they were inextricably bound up with her spiritual development. The latter is something that Dorothee would fully address in the last book that she published: <italic>The Silent Cry: Mysticism and Resistance</italic> (Fortress, 2001). “It is the mystical element,” she wrote, “that will not let go of me. What I want to live, understand, and share with others is <italic>love for God</italic>” (1–2).</p>
<p>Wind rightly observes that Soelle “never managed more than occasional excursions into the world of the poor” (121). But I am not sure that this ultimately matters. What matters is that, out of her deep empathy for humanity, Dorothee was able to open Western theological thought and experience to the realities of millions around the world who gave their lives to end violence and injustice. Hopefully Wind’s powerful biography will reopen the discussion of Dorothee Soelle in the arena of theological reflection and debate in the twenty-first century and also inspire members of the contemporary church to embrace her passion for activism and commitment to change.</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1-0040573613485526"><label>1</label><p>Dorothee Soelle, <italic>Against the Wind: Memoir of a Radical Christian</italic> (Minneapolis: Augsburg Fortress, 1999), 30.</p></fn></fn-group>
<bio><title>Author biography</title>
<p><bold>Shirley Cloyes DioGuardi</bold>, the former publisher of Lawrence Hill Books, is a writer, human rights activist, and foreign policy analyst specializing in the Albanian dimension of the Balkan conflict and the history of Southeast Europe. She resides with her husband, former Congressman Joe DioGuardi, in Ossining, New York.</p></bio>
</back>
</article>