<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JOA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjoa</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Advanced Academics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1932-202X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1932202X12439705</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1932202X12439705</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title><italic>Author’s</italic> Response to Commentaries on “Differentiating Low Performance of the Gifted Leaner</article-title>
<subtitle>Achieving, Underachieving, and Selective Consuming Students</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Figg</surname><given-names>Stephanie</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1932202X12439705">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1932202X12439705"><label>1</label>University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1932202X12439705">Stephanie Figg, 2 Bourke Street, Pymble, Sydney 2073, Australia Email: <email>stephanie.figg@optusnet.com.au</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>23</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>180</fpage>
<lpage>184</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Commentary on my study has focused on two issues: the merits of distinguishing selective consumers from other students and the quality of the study’s methodology.</p>
<p>I am delighted that my article is stimulating discussion regarding the merits of classifying underachieving students. Critical discussion will lead to fresh thinking on the topic, and underachievement certainly needs fresh thinking.</p>
<sec id="section1-1932202X12439705">
<title>The Merits of Distinguishing Selective Consumers From Other Students</title>
<p>It appears that Dr. Peters sees merit in exploring the selective consuming student, whereas Dr. Flint and Ms. Ritchotte appear less convinced. Dr. Flint and Ms. Ritchotte take the position that underachievement is multifaceted and that therefore students underachieve for a variety of reasons. They question the utility of trying to identify selective consumers as a special breed of underachieving students. Perhaps, they argue, selective consumers are just like other underachievers and underachieve for their own reasons. Dr. Flint and Ms. Ritchotte argue that to move forward “we should be spending our time and energy focusing on extending the extensive work of earlier researchers rather than creating new microconcepts that may or may not lead to novel solutions.” However, the reality is that we have been spending decades extending the extensive work of earlier researchers and yet we have not moved forward—underachievement continues at epidemic proportions. I believe we have to explore new concepts so that we may develop novel solutions. As Einstein pointed out, to raise new questions- to regard old problems from a new angle- requires creative imagination and marks real advance in science. Despite decades of research into underachievement and debate, we are still wrestling to find effective solutions to the problem. I see no merit in sustaining our efforts by doing “more of the same.” We need creative alternatives.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1932202X12439705">Jim Delisle’s (2002)</xref> idea of identifying selective consuming students is a creative alternative. It is creative because it applies trait theory to underachievement. From trait theory, we learn that traits are determining tendencies or predispositions people have to respond consistently over time and across situations. In other words, our behavior derives from a particular pattern of personal traits. Our colleagues in the field of psychology have had great successes with trait theory, especially with its application to personality and cognition. Psychologists have successfully isolated clusters of personality and cognitive traits that reliably correlate together, and have developed instruments to measure those traits. The application of trait theory is pervasive in, for example, the corporate environment. It is common practice for organizations to measure for types of personalities (e.g., introverts; subjective) and types of thinkers (e.g., reflective; risk adverse) and use such information to effectively develop their employees and manage employee disengagement. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1932202X12439705">Delisle’s (2002)</xref> theory encourages educators to apply trait theory to teaching and the management of underachievement.</p>
<p>My study sought to clarify whether selective consumers can be identified and classified by isolating certain traits. If they can, then including selective consumers in the broad and general category of “underachievers” may not produce the best results. Dr. Peters, I believe, understood my goal that if we can find specific traits by which to classify selective consuming students, then we can plan appropriate intervention. This approach is not unique. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1932202X12439705">Betsy McCoach and Del Siegle (2003)</xref> themselves sought to develop an instrument that would classify adolescents and explained that “isolating factors that contribute to the academic underachievement of adolescents is the first step toward reversing adolescent underachievement” (p. 426). That statement underpins my study’s approach of attempting to isolate a Type I thinking preference as a trait that correlates with underachievement.</p>
<p>Rather than isolate for traits and provide selected strategies to selected students, Dr. Flint and Ms. Ritchotte argue that a more effective way to manage underachievement would be to examine the underlying faults with our educational system and then to apply good teaching principles to <italic>all</italic> students, so they can enjoy the best possible outcome from their schooling. I recognize and acknowledge the importance of a good educational system but believe that a good educational system is only a necessary first step on which much more needs to be built. A good educational system should be the beginning point, not the end in itself, as I believe Dr. Flint and Ms. Ritchotte suggest. For example, within any one household do we suggest that a good parenting system applied to <italic>all</italic> children is sufficient in itself to ensure that each child can reach its potential? Or rather, do children become “their truest selves” only because we spend time identifying their unique needs and then provide support and development for those needs? Individualism is the most compelling and fundamental issue confronting any educator. I believe Dr. Flint and Ms. Ritchotte miss this fundamental point when considering best practice management of underachievement. We would be wise to remember Gordon Allport’s advice (cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1932202X12439705">Hjelle &amp; Ziegler, 1976</xref>) that every educator, in one way or another, must deal with the enigma of individual differences if education theory is to remain a viable commodity in the market place of psychological science. Hence my question is, “What do selective consumers need beyond a good educational system?”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1932202X12439705" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>I agree with both commentaries that my research design has many limitations. But where does one begin when entering new territory? I chose to begin by finding common ground. Both <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1932202X12439705">Delisle’s (2002)</xref> theory and the qualitative research findings on selective consumers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1932202X12439705">Hèbert &amp; Schreiber, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1932202X12439705">Kanevsky &amp; Keighley, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1932202X12439705">Speirs Neumeister &amp; Hèbert, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1932202X12439705">Thompson &amp; McDonald, 2007</xref>) identified what I concluded to be learning style preference as a common trait among selective consumers. I was well aware of the skepticism regarding the concept of learning style and the substantial debate on this topic. But at the same time, I was also aware of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1932202X12439705">Entwistle and Ramsden’s (1982)</xref> 5-year analysis of students’ learning methods and their comment that</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>The preponderance of research on “learning styles” to date can be taken to justify the assumption of stability of a large number of learner traits. These findings provide the foundations of a number of typologies classifying learners by various constellations of traits posited as stable over time. This evidence commends us to think in terms of types of students; each type characterized by abiding preferences for proceeding in a certain way in address to learning tasks. (p. 11)</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>I understand Dr. Peter’s comment that using Type I preference as the distinguishing factor might be a narrow perception of talent, but in trait theory, a preference is not an island. We function with a network of overlapping traits but have a predisposition to respond consistently over time with a certain preference. For example, we can all engage in impulsive and logical thinking, but will have a predisposition to respond consistently with one of these preferences. By determining that selective consumers have Type I preferences, we merely determine that they prefer to think in a Type I way, not that they only think that way. Therefore using the Type 1 preference to identify selective consumers is not a “narrow perception of talent.” And certainly, to take up Dr. Peters’ point of argument, this is where disconnect becomes relevant, even essential. I agree with Dr. Peters that if a student has a Type I preference but receives a Type II instructor, a disconnect ensues. However, I cannot agree with Dr. Peters that “perhaps the focus should be more on whether there is such a disconnect, as opposed to the particular kinds of thinking styles themselves.” I would argue that disconnect happens only after we understand what the need is—only if we know a student prefers Type I thinking and our teaching strategies do not provide for such thinking do we create a disconnect.</p>
<p>Was choosing the Thinking Styles Inventory the right instrument to isolate learning style traits of selective consumers? I agree this needs further exploration.</p>
<p>Again, I agree that my research has many limitations. Both commentaries expressed concern with the grade ranking I used. I personally am not convinced that selective consumers should be evaluated against domain-specific behavior. In my opinion, underachievement is a sign of disengagement. If underachievement is a sign of disengagement, then achieving students, by their achievement results, demonstrate engagement with the <italic>overall</italic> educational experience. Selective consumers, however, engage with only part of the education system (domain specific). I believe we should aim to engage selective consumers with the overall school experience. I do not think we should be happy to allow selective consuming students to engage only when it suits them. I agree with Dr. Peters that it should be our goal to “encourage students to actively evaluate what they are being taught, even if it leads some of them to determine what we are teaching is not as valuable as we would like.” Why do achieving students engage with the overall system? What traits do selective consumers have that result in them only partially engaging with the overall system? If we can identify why they are more “fussy” about how they learn, we can isolate what it is that they need and offer them a teaching style that might lead them to begin to value the overall content being delivered.</p>
<p>Both articles criticized the size of the sample used in my study. I agree that the sample size was very small and was neither diverse nor geographically representative enough to be generalizable. But I had to start somewhere and began with a convenient sample. I have subsequently repeated the study with a bigger sample and a randomly chosen sample. However, the repeat study did not include female gifted learners and neither did it include a more geographically representative sample. Addressing such shortcomings is the necessary next step before the findings can be generalized. However, the necessary first goal is to isolate and identify the traits that distinguish selective consumers from their achieving and underachieving peers.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1932202X12439705">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Delisle</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Underachiever or selective consumer?</article-title> In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Delisle</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Galbraith</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>When gifted kids don’t have all the answers: How to meet their social and emotional needs</source> (pp. <fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>190</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Spirit</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1932202X12439705">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Entwistle</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramsden</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <source>Understanding student learning</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nichols</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1932202X12439705">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hèbert</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>An examination of selective achievement in gifted males</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Education of the Gifted</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>570</fpage>-<lpage>605</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1932202X12439705">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hjelle</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <source>Personality theories: Basic assumptions, research and applications</source>. <publisher-loc>Tokyo, Japan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill Kogakusha</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1932202X12439705">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kanevsky</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keighley</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>To produce or not to produce? Understanding boredom and the honor in underachievement</article-title>. <source>Roeper Review</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1932202X12439705">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McCoach</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siegle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The school attitude assessment survey-revised: A new instrument to identify academically able students who underachieve</article-title>. <source>Educational and Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>414</fpage>-<lpage>429</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1932202X12439705">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Speirs Neumeister</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hèbert</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Underachievement versus selective achievement: Delving deeper and discovering the difference</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Education of the Gifted</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>238</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1932202X12439705">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Examining the influence of teacher-constructed and student-constructed assignments on the achievement patterns of gifted and advanced sixth-grade students</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Education of the Gifted</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>198</fpage>-<lpage>226</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>