<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spajh</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Hosp Palliat Care</journal-id>
<journal-title>American Journal of Hospice and Palliative Medicine®</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1049-9091</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-2715</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049909112436711</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1049909112436711</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Close Relatives Find Meaning to Cope With Cancer Diagnosis and Treatment of Family Members</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Feyh</surname>
<given-names>Janelle M.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909112436711">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1049909112436711"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Levine</surname>
<given-names>Ellen G.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909112436711">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Clay</surname>
<given-names>Karine</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049909112436711">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1049909112436711">
<label>1</label>Walden University, Minneapolis, MN, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1049909112436711">Janelle M. Feyh, PhD, 3004 NE Kansa Trail Topeka, KS 66617, USA Email: <email>feyhfamily@cox.net</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>29</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<fpage>647</fpage>
<lpage>654</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Pediatric palliative care has recently become a priority in the health care field and is implemented at the time of diagnosis rather than days or weeks before the child’s death. Social constructivism theory in which humans generate meaning from their experiences was utilized as a general framework to determine the impact of pediatric palliative care on close relatives. The purpose of this grounded theory study was to generate a substantive theory that explains how close relatives such as grandparents, aunts, and uncles of a child with cancer experience palliative care. The participants of the study included close relatives of children in palliative care. Semistructured interviews and journaling were used to collect data. Initial, focused, and axial coding procedures were used to manage the data and a content analysis of the textual data was performed. Findings from the data suggested a process of <italic>finding meaning </italic>which helps close relatives to let go of what they cannot control while holding on to what they can control. Social change implications of this study may include improving health care programming for close relatives utilizing supportive–expressive measures. This programming may promote mental health of the close relatives who will learn to deal with their adjustment difficulties and improve their coping skills.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>oncology</kwd>
<kwd>pediatric</kwd>
<kwd>palliative care</kwd>
<kwd>close relatives</kwd>
<kwd>qualitative</kwd>
<kwd>psychosocial</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1049909112436711">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Pediatric palliative care became a priority in the health care field when the Initiative for Pediatric Palliative Care was established in 1998 as an education research forum for pediatric palliative care.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1049909112436711">1</xref>
</sup> The focus of research in this area has generally included the experience of parents, the child, the siblings, and the health care system. However, no research has been conducted to identify the experience of the close relatives. The Initiative for Pediatric Palliative Care,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1049909112436711">1</xref>
</sup> American Academy of Pediatrics,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049909112436711">2</xref>
</sup> Institute of Medicine,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1049909112436711">3</xref>
</sup> and the World Health Organization<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1049909112436711">4</xref>
</sup> stressed importance of pediatric palliative care involving the child and the family, including close relatives. Although these organizations have agreed that this is a priority for high-quality pediatric palliative care, no research with relatives in pediatric palliative care currently exists. A qualitative grounded theory methodology was used to understand how close relatives experience pediatric palliative care and how their experience can be used to fill a gap in the health care arena with regard to palliative care programming. Implications from the findings of this study will be described and a rationale for how the conceptual framework that resulted in this study can be used in other areas will be presented. The intent of this study was to substantiate a theory that explained how close relatives experience pediatric palliative care and in what ways their experience can be valued in the health care system.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1049909112436711">
<title>Research Questions</title>
<p>The primary research questions for this study were the following:
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>To what extent is a close relative’s experience of pediatric palliative care impacted through interactions with other family members and health care professionals?</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>To what extent is a close relative’s experience of pediatric palliative care impacted by factors of hope, uncertainty, adaptation, stress, and coping?</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1049909112436711">
<title>Growth in Pediatric Palliative Care</title>
<p>This study attempted to add to the growing literature in the pediatric palliative care field. Pediatric palliative care programs aim to focus on life, although dying is regarded as part of the natural process. Pediatric palliative care does not attempt to postpone or hasten death; rather it focuses on the psychological and spiritual aspects of care, offers a support system to help patients live as actively as possible, and offers a support system to help the families cope during the patient’s illness and during their bereavement.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1049909112436711">5</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Utilizing a grounded theory approach this study attempted to fill a gap that exists in the current literature regarding the perspectives of grandparents, aunts, and uncles of a child with cancer that is involved in the pediatric palliative care process. Effective palliative care requires a broad multidisciplinary approach that includes the family and utilizes community resources if needed; and can be provided in several environments including the patients home, community health centers, or in tertiary care facilities. This overwhelming growth in palliative care services for children has led to increased research into how best to implement pediatric palliative care programs that will meet the needs of the child and his or her family; understand the perspectives of children, siblings, parents, and the health care professionals; to utilize theories to explain how families cope with this traumatic experience; and what health care professionals can do to improve communication, programming, and services to address the needs of these families.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1049909112436711">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1049909112436711"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1049909112436711">8</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1049909112436711">
<title>Parents’ Perspectives</title>
<p>Parents who have a child with a life-threatening illness, such as cancer, are experiencing a tragedy. From the moment of diagnosis, through the many treatment modalities, until remission or death, a parent is consumed with his or her child’s illness, treatment, and finding a cure. The interaction between the child’s health care staff, the child, and the family is vital to the parents’ beliefs, that care for their child is acceptable and responsive.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049909112436711">9</xref></sup> Open, honest communication with the health care staff appears to be one attribute in which parents measure positive experiences of palliative care.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049909112436711">10</xref></sup> Additional measures of positive experiences of palliative care involve managing the child’s pain and symptoms, supportive health care staff, and an understanding for the parents’ need to never lose hope. For parents the perspective of cancer-directed care and symptom-directed care are interchangeable. Parents tend to want to search beyond the limits imposed upon them by the oncologist, to engage in cancer-directed and cancer-symptom care simultaneously, and to be primarily responsible for the decisions that affect their child’s treatment and quality of life.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1049909112436711">11</xref></sup> Contradictory to this study regarding a parents’ need to be heavily involved in decision making is a grounded theory study conducted by Carnevale<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1049909112436711">12</xref></sup> in France, where the parents’ wanted the responsibility of the life-support decisions regarding their children to lie in the hands of the physicians. However, similar to other studies previously reviewed better parent communication training was a primary factor in the care of critically ill children for families in France.</p>
<p>A more recent study conducted in Australia by Monterosso<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1049909112436711">13</xref></sup> found that parents required honest and open communication throughout their child’s disease trajectory and in to palliative and supportive care. Furthermore, the 69 parents interviewed wanted the opportunity to care for their child at home with family, close relatives, and friends providing support. Parents that participated in this study were eager to share their stories regarding their child’s illness and death and were hopeful that their experiences would lead to improvements in the care of children with cancer and their families.</p>
<p>The stress of caring for a child with a fatal disease is incomprehensible. Parents are faced with challenges in ensuring that their child’s pain is managed, their psychological and spiritual needs are being met, and their quality of life is maintained until death. These burdens add to the parents’ emotional suffering. Additionally, while the child’s physical needs are often met the psychological symptoms of children and parents are often overlooked.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1049909112436711">14</xref></sup> Preparing parents for the loss of their child is an insurmountable task. Understanding the major factors that affect parents as they prepare for the death of their child is vital to addressing their needs. Kreichbergs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1049909112436711">15</xref></sup> found that the inability to alleviate the physical pain of a child near death and a difficult moment of death affected parents years after the child’s death. These findings suggest that children with cancer involved in palliative and end-of-life care may be suffering more than is recognized and that the parent’s inability to alleviate the pain and difficulties at death creates long-term emotional turmoil.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1049909112436711" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section6-1049909112436711">
<title>Context of the Study</title>
<p>The study took place partially through a hospice organization in a major metropolitan area in Missouri, and through a snowball sample in the Midwest. After recruiting participants and obtaining consent, participants were interviewed and asked to respond to 2 journal entries. The participants were asked to be creative or expressive in any manner in their journals. The Institutional review board (IRB) approval was obtained before collecting the data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1049909112436711">
<title>Selection of Participants</title>
<p>Eligibility criteria for this study was participants over the age of 18, who were a grandparent, aunt, or uncle to a child who has cancer and is receiving pediatric palliative care services or has received pediatric palliative care services. A purposive sample, a nonprobability means of sampling, in which the participants were chosen based on the eligibility criteria were utilized for this study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1049909112436711">16</xref></sup> (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1049909112436711">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1049909112436711" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Profiles of Participants</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1049909112436711" xlink:href="10.1177_1049909112436711-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>Age</th>
<th>Gender</th>
<th>Child’s diagnosis</th>
<th>Status</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Participant 1</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>Grandmother</td>
<td>Leukemia</td>
<td>Deceased</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Participant 2</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>Aunt</td>
<td>Empendemoblastoma</td>
<td>Deceased</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Participant 3</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>Grandmother</td>
<td>Rhadomysarcoma</td>
<td>Living</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Participant 4</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>Uncle</td>
<td>Acute myleiod leukemia</td>
<td>Deceased</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Participant 5</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>Grandfather</td>
<td>Rhadomyosarcoma</td>
<td>Living</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Participant 6</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>Grandmother</td>
<td>Rhadomyosarcoma</td>
<td>Living</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Participant 7</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>Aunt</td>
<td>Acute myleiod leukemia</td>
<td>Deceased</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Participant 8 </td>
<td>66</td>
<td>Grandmother</td>
<td>Leukemia</td>
<td>Living</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Participant 9</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>Aunt</td>
<td>Leukemia</td>
<td>Living</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1049909112436711">
<title>Ethical Considerations</title>
<p>All potential close relatives chosen to participate were provided with the purpose of the study, the role of the researcher, and the expectations of the participants. Participants were informed that all information would be kept private and confidential. A written consent form outlining this information was obtained. A copy was given to participants. Confidentiality was assured by conducting interviews in secluded locations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1049909112436711">
<title>Data Collection Techniques</title>
<p>Interviews are the primary method for collection of data in grounded theory research.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1049909112436711">16</xref></sup> Semistructured interviews were conducted in quiet places that the participants chose including some secluded offices and coffee shops. The IRB suggested secluded public places versus private homes to ensure that they were not overly influenced by pictures or other sentiments found in their familiar surroundings. The semistructured format allows for the combination of open-ended questions and the ability to seek clarification and generate hypotheses throughout the interview process.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1049909112436711">17</xref></sup> Additionally, journal responses to 2 interview questions were collected. This approach allowed data to be collected by multiple methods. All interviews were conducted using a digital audio-recorder, so that all files could be uploaded for analysis.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1049909112436711">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The interviews were used to identify the perspectives of the close relatives in relation to their experience of the pediatric palliative care process. The journal entries were used to add to the depth of their experience and provide additional data of their perspectives. Data analysis begins with what Charmaz<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049909112436711">18</xref></sup> describes as initial coding. This process begins with transcribed digital recordings and interview notes completed during the interview process. Journal entries were also used to identify initial codes. Memo writing that occurred after the interviews were used to record the researcher’s initial impressions of the interview and to record salient themes emerging at that time. To increase reliability of themes that were present a second coder was used. The researcher used NVivo 9 software <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1049909112436711">19</xref></sup> as well as her own process to completely review, sort, and analyze the data for accuracy of findings. The initial data units were then reconstructed in to larger units through focused coding. Initial codes were reviewed with less useful codes being discarded and smaller categories combined into larger categories. Commonalities in larger categories were then subdivided and reduced through axial coding.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1049909112436711">
<title>Focused Coding</title>
<p>The second step in the analysis process was to synthesize and explain larger segments of data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049909112436711">18</xref></sup> Through this process less useful codes were eliminated and smaller categories were combined with larger categories or subdivided if responses were assigned the same code. At that point, repeated ideas surfaced which were then organized into larger themes that connected different codes and helped to identify the core category. The focused coding process constructed categories that could be readily analyzed in the subsequent axial coding phase. Descriptions of the focused coding results provide an elaboration of the constructs and emerging themes that facilitated the development of the grounded theory.</p>
<p>The participants relayed a variety of emotions that they experienced throughout this process. These emotions were relevant with responses to the question, “What thoughts and feelings did you have regarding your grandchild, niece, or nephew during this pediatric palliative care process?” And this question, “What was the most difficult part?” It was evident from their long silences and flowing tears that responding to this question evoked various emotions that appeared to be just under the surface (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1049909112436711">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1049909112436711">3</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1049909112436711" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Quotes of Participants for Helplessness</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1049909112436711" xlink:href="10.1177_1049909112436711-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Participant</th>
<th>Quote</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>Just devastated. I just felt very sorry, very sad for my son and his wife. We had not experienced anything like this in our family. It broke my heart for them and for his siblings.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>Just that it was very hard to see her go through all of this knowing there was nothing we could do for her. But be there for her. (Long pause). Um, she was a fighter. It was hard to know what to say to them. You wanted to ask what did you find out. My stomach would be in turmoil, not knowing what am I going to say, or tell them if they call me and tell me that they found more or that it was back. Just waiting, that was hard. Hard to know especially towards the end.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Just well when she was diagnosed just shock of all overwhelming just trying to process what she will go through, just trying to be there for support. I think mainly just I felt like my position was to be supportive as much as I could be for both of them (child and grandchild). I think seeing her suffer (crying) through treatment. It was like having my heart ripped out of my chest. I felt so helpless. It was almost like grieving for a lost loved one. It was really hard for my daughter to deal with it since she had to stay strong and positive for my granddaughter. That was just the hardest part seeing her so … I wish I could take a day of it for her. Helpless.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table3-1049909112436711" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Theme of Hope</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1049909112436711" xlink:href="10.1177_1049909112436711-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Participant</th>
<th>Quote</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>Uh. my main thought is that it will be completely gone and he will have a normal life. [Long pause.] well … you know just pray everyday that he's gonna make it through this and you know that his dad and mom will have the strength and patience and the love uh … so that they can know make it through this and um … they will be closer together and have a good life.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>It was a curse and a blessing. He doesn’t know any better. It is hard to watch little ones go through this. But children can persevere. Hard to watch what they go through and all the pain. He would have to get a pic line put in and he would always say Oh, no "no owies," When he was a little dizzy after what they put in his pic line, he would say I’m a good boy. Right? You watched and crumble watching his mom having to do that with her child.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Most of the participants were amazed and so utterly impressed with the strength of their grandchildren, nieces, and nephews as well as the parents of the child. They were taken back by the parents’ ability to handle themselves so well and to be a source of strength for their child. This source of strength seemed to help the close relatives cope with what was occurring in their lives (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1049909112436711">Table 4</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1049909112436711" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Theme of Recognizing Child’s and Parent’s Strength</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1049909112436711" xlink:href="10.1177_1049909112436711-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Participant </th>
<th>Quote</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>She was such a trooper and fighter through all of this. It’s amazing to me how strong little kids are going through something so horrible. When my sister and her brother-in-law were told that their little girl had CANCER! I can’t imagine how their hearts felt, cause it broke my heart tons and I was just her Aunt.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>My daughter was the other number one person. She was a rock and no matter what was going on with her child. She seemed so strong and I remember stayiung there with them. She would call me and ask if I could come Anna wants to watch a movie with grandma. I would go and watch a movie with her and that would be Emily's time that would be when she could let it all out and just cry. I just kept thinking I am so proud of her the strength and courage she showed and I think my granddaughter could see that in her mom and that she didn't give up. It could have been so easy for my daughter to fall apart but she didn't. She was a huge person in all of that.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>He was so courageous for someone so young. As long as he had his parents around he had no fear. He had NO FEAR! He looked upon each day with unending joy and relentless courage.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>How we have a limited time not knowing when that day will come and watching my nephew not even given a chance to live and go through this and how strong he was at his young age and knowing that he was really support for us, watching how positive he was I just can't imagine as an adult going through this same process handling it as well as he did. In watching my nephew handle this experience with optimism and vigor made me further realize what a strong and amazing boy we had in our presence.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>[Crying] well I'm not sure that I would have been able to do that. And it's just I am in awe to watch my son be able to do all this stuff, I thought oh my God this is my baby (he's the youngest of 5) and how much he has grown and uh. he has a whole different side to him. I watched her grow and she's like one of my kids. And uh …. I think she is a great mom and uh.[Crying]</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>For these participants giving support became their way to give encouragement and respite to their families. Through giving support, they were able to feel as if they were doing something to help eliminate some of the pain and suffering felt by their family members. Giving support also provided a sense of value to their experience (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1049909112436711">Table 5</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-1049909112436711" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Giving Support to Child and Parents</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1049909112436711" xlink:href="10.1177_1049909112436711-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Participant</th>
<th>Quote</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>My husband and I went down there a lot. Spent the week when they first went down there. We always joked around, she called me Aunt Monkey. We were so fortunate that we got to spend that time with her. We could make it down there we were going to be down there. No matter what. It was too important to not be down there.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Just tyring to be there for support. Um, actually that first week I stayed up there with her and her mom. I'm sorry I'm going to cry [cry and tears]. I think mainly just I felt like my position was to be supportive as much as I could be for both of them [child and grandchild]. And that there was any part of it that I could be helpful or supportive I tried to be. Just seeing how hard it was with all those things together to get her where she was.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>It was kind of a remote relationship. We were there all the time, but yet she didn't really respond to us because she was sick a lot. She didn't feel good, she knew we were there, she knew we were there for her. At the same time she kind of wanted us at arm's distance from it. She didn't want us to be right on top of her helping her with stuff.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>Just physically being there, whatever support you could be and help out. We'd go out and visit and they could step out of the room. We became his playmates and they would go off in a different room. at first I was like that is kind of rude. When I started thinking about it it was the only time they had to breathe and to take a break. You would go home and you feel so physically worn out and you say how could I be physically worn out when I am not even dealing with this everyday. You kind of pinch yourself into reality and then do what you can.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>All of the close relatives had an appreciation for the health care staff and a reliance on them to take care of their grandchild, nephew, or niece. Most of them had a very positive experience with the health care system and built relationships with these individuals. Additionally, these close relatives had to trust these people who were charged with taking care of their loved ones and ensuring that they did everything possible to find a cure (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-1049909112436711">Table 6</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table6-1049909112436711" position="float">
<label>Table 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Reliance on Doctors and Health Care Staff</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-1049909112436711" xlink:href="10.1177_1049909112436711-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Participant</th>
<th>Quote</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>Trying to keep us together. It was a very nice place for him and the people there are just wonderful. Not a cross person there. Hospice house is a very special place. I was glad there was a hospice house.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>Seeing the doctors the nurses and everything. Being there in such a bad situation they made it seem like not a bad situation. How did they do that? It has to be hard on them?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>The family is encouraged to spend as much time as the care facility allows with the loved one and at times to help with the care when the nurses are busy. The medical personnel sees to your loved ones every need and sees that the doctors’ orders are followed. The staff is very helpful in answering any questions you might have or will get the answers for you. They are supportive of the families and encourage spending as much time as allowed with the loved on.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>Well, once we got to know the oncologist, I thought that was really important because you kind of to build a trust with the doctor and she was really on top of everything that she did she was well versed and rounded in what her treatment plan was going to be.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>When they first started, the hospital gave them tons of information about the trial they were in. I think resource wise was great. Not only did they talk about it, they laid out everything. This is what to expect if this and this happens, you pick up the phone. They had a nurse 24/7. Um….the one thing if you had a perfect world. What a great thing it would be if everyone 's schedules would allow the families to sit down with a whole med team and talk about this is what is going on this week. Some sort of once a week or once a month to sit down with your team and say this is what is going on, we called you this many times, can you help us alleviate this or this. Maybe that would be beneficial. Probably would never work. But maybe with Facebook it would work.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>These close relatives were highly reliant on their faith and their belief in God to get them through this process. They put that which they could not control in His hands and relied on their faith to somehow pull them through. Reliance on God meant that they could surrender control to a higher power. Their responses to, “What helped you cope?” gave credence to their trust in God, and their reliance on their faith to deal with the darkest of days (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table7-1049909112436711">Table 7</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table7-1049909112436711" position="float">
<label>Table 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Reliance on God</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table7-1049909112436711" xlink:href="10.1177_1049909112436711-table7.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Participant</th>
<th>Quote</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>Only God knows why and our church. I knew he was going to be gone into the arms of Jesus. But that comforted us. Because babies are special to God I think. Only God knows why</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Our church family um, our pastor and honestly God. I mean I feel like all of our hope is in Him. I was just going to take it as it comes. Just hope in God and just knowing He sees the big picture. We don't necessarily know what is going to happen tomorrow but He already has the plan in store for us and He will get us through it a day at a time. God took us through this.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>We all had hope and knew he was a strong-willed little guy. There for a time, he did improve and I thought for certain he’d beaten it. I mean this was my nephew! Surely God wouldn’t take this sweet, innocent, loving little boy from us right? After all, of there are those in the world out to harm others who live to be 90, how would He let my nephew die, right? Right?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>I just pray everyday that he's gonna make it through this and you know that his dad and mom will have the strength and patience and the love uh…so that they can you know make it through this and um… they will be closer together and have a good life. With all the prayers, God’s help and our children this has helped to be there whenever they needed to play, take care of whatever we have to do to share in this little angel’s life.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>Well during the pain I have a very strong personal faith and the times I would cringe at some of the things I would see him going through and I was praying for him. I believe it is in someone else's hand. I don't know anybody that honestly could see someone suffer especially a child and not think to yourself God why can't it be me. Seek the guidance and peace that I personally know only comes away from God…in the times when words, my presence, my help, my “whatever” was not enough… my prayers were, it is when I would lay my nephew and his illness at God’s feet—that I truly found peace—it was when I could lift my brother and his wife to God in prayers that I found peace----There are many times –when I don’t question at all…God sending angels to lift his weary little body –to a place of rest so that he could make it through another day.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1049909112436711">
<title>Axial Coding</title>
<p>After utilizing the coding procedures of identifying initial codes and themes and then subdividing these themes into larger categories through focused coding, a theory began to emerge. At this point, axial coding procedures identified and connected the relationships between the themes. Based on the findings of this study through the coding procedures utilized by the researcher, there is an overriding theory of <italic>finding meaning.</italic> For these close relatives <italic>finding meaning</italic> was one way to hold on to that which they had no control. In the beginning of the process, close relatives find themselves struggling to find answers. They question how and why this could happen to a child? They are filled with feelings of helplessness, shock, sadness, and devastation. They question how could this happen to our loved one? How could this happen to a child? They entertain their uncertainties and their fears. They look for answers in the doctors, the nurses, the laboratory techs, whoever can help them. They struggle between dealing with the pain and suffering and never losing hope. They struggle to understand why their grandchild would be so willing to climb up on the radiation table and take her treatment. They struggle when they remember their niece’s face when she lost her hair and had to wear a wig. But as the process continues they begin to recognize that there is meaning in this situation. They create meaning because that is one way they can control the situation.</p>
<p>Participant 9 stated:<disp-quote>
<p>In watching my nephew handle this experience with optimism and vigor made me further realize what a strong and amazing boy we had in our presence. I can only imagine what he and his family must have felt during this time. He taught me everything in his short time on Earth and to love unconditionally and let go of the “little things” that seem to get a hold of us and stay with us.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1049909112436711">
<title>Interpretation of Findings</title>
<sec id="section14-1049909112436711">
<title>Finding Meaning</title>
<p>In addressing the research questions as the experience of the close relatives and how their needs are being met through the health care system, it was apparent that these close relatives see their experience as a journey that is out of their control, one that they must surrender too. Their journey is filled with psychological, physical, emotional, and spiritual symptoms that often are overlooked. This is similar to the findings of Theunissen et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1049909112436711">14</xref>
</sup> who found that children and parents often exhibit many psychological and physical symptoms that are readily missed. This is apparently no different for close relatives. It was important for this researcher to gain a better understanding of the close relatives through a qualitative analysis. Meert et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1049909112436711">20</xref>
</sup> uncovered similar findings when they examined parents’ needs while in the pediatric palliative care process.</p>
<p>Results of this study show that close relatives are highly impacted by their experience and that they struggle with many of the same experiences as parents, children, and siblings.</p>
<p>Beckett<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1049909112436711">21</xref>
</sup> suggested that when 1 member of the family is impacted by a stressor, all family members are impacted; and the results of this study suggest that this includes close relatives. Patterson et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1049909112436711">22</xref>
</sup> also found that the diagnosis of the child impacts the entire family system. Close relatives are part of this system, and they also experience feelings of uncertainty, attempts to understand and find meaning, and being supportive to their family members.</p>
<p>Close relatives in this study expressed struggling with both positive and negative emotions throughout their experience. However, because they felt unable to control their journey, part of being in control meant attempting to find meaning in their process. Through close relatives’ questions of “why” would their relatives have to go through this painful process; they experienced various emotions. These questions continued to elicit feelings of helplessness, devastation, uncertainty, and general overall questions about how to cope. Through the struggle with these feelings close relatives began to identify the positives of their experience, which led them to find meaning. Santacroce<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049909112436711">23</xref>
</sup> found that feelings of anxiety and posttraumatic symptoms were experienced by parents. Close relatives in this study also experienced these feelings but to a lesser degree than the parents. A similar finding of the close relatives in this study was the anxiety and uncertainty that increased as the treatment came to an end. This finding was also similar to those of Stam<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1049909112436711">24</xref>
</sup> who found that parents’ anxiety was the greatest at the end of treatment. In addition to struggling with the negative feelings, these close relatives expressed positive feelings as well. The strongest positive feeling expressed by these close relatives was that of hope. These close relatives believed that part of their job as caregivers was to keep hope and have faith. Reder and Serwint<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1049909112436711">25</xref>
</sup> had similar findings in their study of parents of children with cancer in which the parents felt obligated to be the bearers of hope even when all else failed. These close relatives are impacted just as heavily as the parents with regard to hope, uncertainty, adaptation, stress, and coping. Their interaction with their family members during this process has an enormous impact on their functioning. However, these parents and these children rely on these close relatives for support, so it is difficult for these close relatives to focus on their own needs when their loved ones rely on them for so much support. Who is there to support the caregiver?</p>
<p>Close relatives also recognized the strength of their loved ones and their ability to cope with the circumstances. This strength resonated with the close relatives and led them to find meaning amid their traumatic experience. Close relatives also found meaning through their role as caregivers. The fulfillment of this role aided in their ability to make sense of their experience and to further define the meaning of how and why this could happen to their loved ones. Furthermore, close relatives found meaning through their experience by focusing on things they had control over and letting go of the things out of their control. Through focusing on the things they could control, caregiving, never losing hope, and embracing each and every moment, meaning and importance of their journey was clear. They must find meaning in order to survive the experience.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1049909112436711">
<title>Recommendations for Action</title>
<p>There are many individuals and organizations that can benefit from the results of this study. Families who are involved in the pediatric palliative care process, health care agencies, hospice and palliative care agencies, and close relatives who have loved ones that are experiencing palliative care could all benefit from the findings of this study. Furthermore, close relatives and families that are dealing with a chronic family illness may also benefit from these findings. The results of this study led to the following recommendations in pediatric palliative care: implementation of programming within the pediatric palliative care and health care system to address close relatives’ needs and provide relative information regarding supportive measures; individual one-to-one or group forums must be made available for close relatives to access during and beyond their palliative care process; encouraging close relatives to utilize programming through creative strategies may be needed to ensure participation; implementation of support groups for other close relatives who live far away through the Internet; educating close relatives on how to cope and what to expect from their family members during this time; pediatric palliative care programming must provide ways for these close relatives to be heard, to get their stories out. Finding ways to tell their story and to remember their loved ones must be part of any pediatric palliative care programming; due to the richness of data obtained from the journaling process of this study, it is likely that this emotional disclosure should be part of pediatric palliative care programming for both close relatives and parents. Art programs for both parents and close relatives that allow for expressive and supportive avenues may be warranted.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1049909112436711">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>Interpretation of the findings of this study is bound by limitations of this study. First, the sample size is small and limited data collection. Limitations affecting the generalizability and validity of the study included the participants’ retrospective self-reports of their experiences, which may have increased bias. Participants may have censored actions, thoughts, and feelings in order to present themselves in a more positive light. The participants who volunteered to be in this study were caucasians; which means no other races/ethnic groups were represented. Furthermore, only 2 men participated, which also limits the results of this study in terms of gender. The study was also bound by recruitment of participants through a purposive and snowball sample. These types of sampling limit the generalizability of the results due to purposive and snowball samples consisting of participants that meet certain criteria. Therefore, the results cannot be generalized to other populations that fall outside of the criteria.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1049909112436711">
<title>Research Recommendations for Future Studies</title>
<p>In this study, the researcher explored specific themes that emerged with close relatives and their experience of pediatric palliative care. As this study only included 9 close relative participants, it would be important for additional studies with more participants and/or quantitative studies to provide additional data regarding the theory of surrendering to the journey and close relatives’ perspectives. The outcome of this study could have a great impact on the way we view the close relatives in pediatric palliative care. Longitudinal studies that evaluate close relatives over a period of years may be a useful tool in understanding how they adapt over time and how/if their perspectives change. Many ideas and themes emerged from this study that could be further examined (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table8-1049909112436711">Table 8</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table8-1049909112436711" position="float">
<label>Table 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>Recommendations for Future Research</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table8-1049909112436711" xlink:href="10.1177_1049909112436711-table8.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Questions</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>What are the differences between male close relatives perspectives compared to female perspectives with regards to palliative care?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Are grandparents more heavily impacted by the experience than aunts or uncles?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>How does the implementation of support groups for close relatives affect their ability to cope and handle their care giving duties?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Does the incorporation of journaling in pediatric palliative care programming provide an effective means for communicating thoughts, fears, and plans?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Do other ethnic groups have the same experiences of pediatric palliative care?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Does age of the grandparents, aunts, and/or uncles have an impact on perceptions of pediatric palliative care?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Is the impact on close relatives different for those who live farther away from their loved ones?</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1049909112436711">
<title>Summary</title>
<p>Pediatric palliative care efforts are on the rise. Increases in programming to address family needs have been substantiated. Means for effective coping and valuing of family members is an undertaking that must be addressed. Although pediatric palliative care measures are being implemented at the time of diagnosis whether a cure is found or palliative measures are needed, the focus has been on the child and the immediate family members. However, as can be seen from the results of this study, close relatives are highly impacted by their own experience and need to be included in any and all programming that addresses the family’s needs. Pain, suffering, uncertainty, hope, caregiving, and reliance on God and others are all factors that affect the perspectives of close relatives. Health care programming cannot proclaim to be meeting the needs of families in the palliative care process if it does not contain specific programming for close relatives. The findings from this study have shown that close relatives are being impacted by their experience of pediatric palliative care. They have shared their stories, their emotions, and their journey. Therefore, it is our duty to listen and respond.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-1049909112436711">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1049909112436711">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1049909112436711">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Initiative for Pediatric Palliative Care</collab>. <source>About IPPC</source>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ippcweb.org/about.asp">http://ippcweb.org/about.asp</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed January 5, 2010</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1049909112436711">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="author">American Academy of Pediatrics</collab>. <article-title>Palliative care for children</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1049909112436711">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Institute of Medicine</collab>. <source>When Children die: Improving Palliative and end-of-life care for Children and their Families</source>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iom.edu/Reports/2002/When-Children-Die-Improving-Palliative-and-end-of-life-care-for-children-and-their-families.aspx">http://www.iom.edu/Reports/2002/When-Children-Die-Improving-Palliative-and-end-of-life-care-for-children-and-their-families.aspx</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed December 20, 2009</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1049909112436711">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">World Health Organization</collab>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>WHO Definition of palliative care</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/cancer/publication/definition/en/">http://www.who.int/cancer/publication/definition/en/</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed March 1, 2010</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1049909112436711">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cannaerta</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dierck de Casterle</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grypdonck</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Palliative care, care for lifea study of the specificity of residential palliative care</article-title>. <source>Qual Health Res</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>816</fpage>–<lpage>835</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1049909112436711">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Davies</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sehring</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Partridge</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Barriers to pediatric palliative care for children: perceptions of pediatric healthcare providers</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>282</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1542/peds.2006-3153</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1049909112436711">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Feudtner</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Santucci</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feinstein</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Snyder</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rourke</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hopeful thinking and level of comfort regarding providing pediatric palliative care: a survey of hospital nurses</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>119</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>e186</fpage>–<lpage>e192</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1542/peds.2006-1048</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1049909112436711">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hewitt-Taylor</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Caring for children with complex needs: Staff education and training</article-title>. <source>J Child Health Care</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1177/1367493505050506</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1049909112436711">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mack</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hilden</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Watterson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Parent and physician perspectives on quality of care at the end of life in children with cancer</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>36</issue>):<fpage>9155</fpage>–<lpage>9161</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1200/JCO.2005.04.010</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1049909112436711">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Solomon</surname>
<given-names>MZ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Browning</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pediatric palliative care: Relationships matter and does pain control</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>36</issue>):<fpage>9055</fpage>–<lpage>9057</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1200/JCO.2005.04.4677</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1049909112436711">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bluebond-Langner</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Belasco</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goldman</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Belasco</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Understanding parents’ approaches to care and treatment of children with cancer when standard therapy has failed</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>2414</fpage>–<lpage>2419</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1200/JCO.2006.08.7759</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1049909112436711">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carnevale</surname>
<given-names>FA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Canoui</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hubert</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The moral experience of parents regarding life-support decisions for their critically-ill children: A preliminarystudy in France</article-title>. <source>J Child Health Care</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1177/1367493506060209</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1049909112436711">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Monterosso</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kristjanson</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Supportive and palliative care needs of families of children who die from cancer: An Australian study</article-title>. <source>Palliat Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1177/0269216307084608</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1049909112436711">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Theunissen</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hoogerbrugge</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van Achterberg</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Prins</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vernooij-Dassen</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van den Ende</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Symptoms in the palliative phase of children with cancer</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Blood Cancer</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1002/pbc.21042</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1049909112436711">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kreichbergs</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Valdimarsdottir</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Onelov</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bjork</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Steineck</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Henter</surname>
<given-names>JI</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Care related distress: a nationwide study of parents who lost their child to cancer</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>36</issue>):<fpage>9162</fpage>–<lpage>9171</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1049909112436711">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Creswell</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Qualitative Research and Quality Design: Choosing Among Five Traditions</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1049909112436711">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schensul</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>LeCompte</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Ethnographer’s ToolKit</source>. <publisher-loc>Walnut Creek, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Altamira Press</publisher-name>; <year>1999</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1049909112436711">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Charmaz</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Constructing Grounded Theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1049909112436711">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">QSR International NVivo 9 (Qualitative analysis software)</collab>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.qsrinternational.com">http://www.qsrinternational.com</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed January 10, 2010</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1049909112436711">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Meert</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Briller</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schim</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thruston</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kabel</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>Examining the needs of bereaved parents in the pediatric intensive care unit: a qualitative study</article-title>. <source>Death Stud</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>712</fpage>–<lpage>740</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1080/07481180903070434</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1049909112436711">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beckett</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Family Theory as a Framework for Assessment</source> Flagstaff, AZ:. <publisher-name>Northern Arizona University</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1049909112436711">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Patterson</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holm</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gurney</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The impact of childhood cancer on the family: A qualitative analysis of strains, resources, and coping behaviors</article-title>. <source>Psycho-Oncology</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1002/pon.761</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1049909112436711">
<label>23</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Santacroce</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Uncertainty, anxiety, and symptoms of post-traumatic stress in parents of children recently diagnosed with cancer</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Oncol Nurs</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1177/104345420201900305</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1049909112436711">
<label>24</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stam</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grootenhuis</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brons</surname>
<given-names>PP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Caron</surname>
<given-names>HN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Last</surname>
<given-names>BF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Health-related quality of life in children and emotional reactions of parents following completion of cancer treatment</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Blood Cancer</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>312</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1049909112436711">
<label>25</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Reder</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Serwint</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Until the last breath: exploring the concept of hope for parents and healthcare professionals during a child’s serious illness</article-title>. <source>Archives Pediatr Adolesc Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>163</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>653</fpage>–<lpage>657</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>