<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PCH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppch</journal-id>
<journal-title>World Journal for Pediatric and Congenital Heart Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">2150-1351</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2150-0136</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2150135112437796</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2150135112437796</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Expert Techniques</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Modified Technique for the Implantation of Berlin Heart Excor Ventricular Assist Device in Children</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Botha</surname>
<given-names>Phil</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD, MRCS</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150135112437796">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hasan</surname>
<given-names>Asif</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>FRCS (CTh)</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150135112437796">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Perri</surname>
<given-names>Gianluigi</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150135112437796">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Filippelli</surname>
<given-names>Sergio</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150135112437796">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Griselli</surname>
<given-names>Massimo</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, MS, FRCS (CTh)</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150135112437796">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-2150135112437796"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-2150135112437796"><label>1</label>Department of Paediatric Cardiothoracic Surgery, Freeman Hospital, Newcastle Upon Tyne Hospitals NHS Trust, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-2150135112437796">Massimo Griselli, Department of Paediatric Cardiothoracic Surgery, Freeman Hospital, Freeman Road, High Heaton, Newcastle upon Tyne NE7 7DN, UK Email: <email>massimo.griselli@nuth.nhs.uk</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>373</fpage>
<lpage>377</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>5</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>26</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">World Society for Pediatric and Congential Heart Surgery</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The Berlin Heart Excor (BHE) assist device has become our standard mechanical support device for long-term support in children with heart failure. We report two useful surgical modifications for the implantation of the BHE in the pediatric population, improving ease of implantation as well as subsequent surgical procedures at the time of explantation or transplantation. The first modification entails the use of a polytetrafluoroethylene graft for cannulation via the innominate artery for arterial perfusion during cardiopulmonary bypass. This graft is preserved and reused for institution of bypass at the time of transplantation or explantation of the device after recovery. The second modification consists of an extension of the BHE arterial cannula using a length of knitted polyester graft. This allows for improved positioning of the arterial cannula in the ascending aorta or main pulmonary artery, facilitates vascular anastomosis, and improves hemostasis.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>circulatory assist devices</kwd>
<kwd>congenital heart surgery</kwd>
<kwd>CPB components and configurations</kwd>
<kwd>transplantation heart</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-2150135112437796">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The Berlin Heart Excor (BHE) assist device (Berlin Heart AG, Berlin, Germany) has become the most widely used ventricular assist device (VAD) for the treatment of heart failure in the pediatric population.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-2150135112437796">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-2150135112437796">2</xref>
</sup> Since its introduction to the European market in 2005, it has been implanted in nearly 900 patients around the world. The device has been used successfully to support pediatric patients with dilated cardiomyopathy as well as in an increasing number of patients with congenital heart disease. The available cannula and ventricle configurations allow for the support of wide range of patients with diverse anatomical and pathological considerations. Case reports and series have documented successful support up to 591 days attesting to the reliability and versatility of the device.</p>
<p>We performed our first implantation of the BHE in a child in 2005. With growing experience, our implantation technique has evolved to address some of the difficulties experienced in particular in the pediatric population. We would like to present two surgical modifications introduced in our unit, which we have found particularly useful to facilitate not only implantation in small children but also subsequent explantation and/or transplantation. We review the impact that these developments have had on surgical outcomes in our pediatric heart failure population.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-2150135112437796">
<title>Description of Surgical Techniques</title>
<p>Our institutional review board approved the development of a mechanical circulatory support program as well as any required modifications in implantation technique. The first modification involves the use of a polytetrafluoroethylene (PTFE) tube graft (Goretex, Gore &amp; Associates, Flagstaff, Arizona) to provide arterial inflow via the innominate artery for perfusion during cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB). The graft is anastomosed to the innominate artery using a continuous 7/0 or 8/0 monofilament polypropylene suture after application of a side-biting clamp. The hemostasis of the anastomosis is secured, the graft is flushed with heparinized saline, and the patient is heparinized for CPB. An adequate length of graft (typically 4-5 cm) is used to allow the arterial cannula to be inserted into it outside of the chest. At this stage, the appropriate arterial cannula tip is inserted in the distal end of shunt and fixed with two silk ties (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2150135112437796">Figure 1</xref>). The cannula is then connected to the CPB circuit after careful de-airing. After completion of the VAD implantation procedure, the arterial cannula is removed from the graft, which is then closed with a titanium vascular clip at the insertion point, with two further clips placed on its length. The graft is then placed in the suprasternal space just above the innominate vein and the chest closed per normal routine. At reoperation, the graft is usually easily dissected out from the suprasternal space and allows for easy access for arterial cannulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2150135112437796">Figure 2</xref>). A side-biting clamp is again applied widely across the innominate artery and the occluding titanium clips removed. The graft is thoroughly irrigated with heparinized saline via a rigid cannula to expel any clot. A brief release of the side-biting clamp confirms patency and the absence of thrombus. Before the arterial cannula is fixed to the graft, any remaining air is carefully expelled.</p>
<fig id="fig1-2150135112437796" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Polytetrafluoroethylene graft on the innominate artery connected to arterial limb of cardiopulmonary bypass circuit.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2150135112437796-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-2150135112437796" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Polytetrafluoroethylene graft reopened at the time of heart transplant.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2150135112437796-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The second modification consists of extension of the BHE arterial cannula using a length of knitted polyester graft (Vascutek Gelseal, Terumo, Tokyo, Japan). A graft with a diameter of 2 to 3 mm wider than the arterial cannula is used. When using a 6-mm BHE arterial cannula, we attach an 8-mm graft with five interrupted 5/0 polypropylene sutures through the sewing cuff. The metal flange of the 6-mm cannula allows a silk ligature to be passed around the graft to tie the conduit to the metal flange. For the 9-mm cannula, which does not have a flange, we use a 14-mm Vascutek graft that is joined to the cannula with a continuous 4/0 polypropylene suture reinforced as needed by a number of interrupted sutures. The graft is trimmed to a length of approximately 1.5 cm as needed and joined to the aorta (or pulmonary artery for right VAD [RVAD]). This anastomosis is easily performed after the application of a side-biting clamp using continuous 4/0 or 5/0 polypropylene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-2150135112437796">Figures 3</xref>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-2150135112437796"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2150135112437796">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2150135112437796"/>). We apply tissue fibrin sealant to the anastomosis routinely before removing the side-biting clamp and leave the pleurae intact bilaterally where possible to avoid the need for postoperative pleural drainage.</p>
<fig id="fig3-2150135112437796" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Knitted polyester graft sutured to the distal end of Berlin Heart Excor arterial cannula.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2150135112437796-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-2150135112437796" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Modified Berlin Heart Excor cannula ready for implantation.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2150135112437796-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig5-2150135112437796" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Modified Berlin Heart Excor cannula implanted on the ascending aorta with a side-biting clamp.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2150135112437796-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig6-2150135112437796" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Polytetrafluoroethylene graft reconnected to the arterial limb of cardiopulmonary bypass at the time of heart transplant.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2150135112437796-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-2150135112437796">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Since the introduction of the BHE device to our practice in 2005, we have implanted 84 devices in 53 pediatric patients, totaling 2742 days of circulatory support. Support was biventricular VAD (BiVAD) in 32, left VAD (LVAD) in 27 two-ventricle patients, and Univentricular Assist Device in 4 single ventricle patients. We have used a PTFE graft to cannulate the innominate artery in 15 patients with a median age of 8 months (range 0.1-105.0) and mean weight of 9 kg (range 3-20). The graft diameter was 3 mm in one, 3.5 mm in six, and 4 mm in eight patients. We have not observed any difference in the rate of cerebral thromboembolic events during VAD support (25% vs 20%; <italic>P</italic> = 0.5). Similarly, we have carefully monitored clinically for neurological complications at the time of graft reuse. The graft has been successfully reused for arterial cannulation in 14 patients (once in ten patients, twice in three patients, and three times in one patient). Reuse of the graft occurred after a median of 25 days (range 4-78 days) from implantation. We have not observed any neurological event directly attributable to this technique. Five patients in whom a graft was used for cannulation had neurological events. One had a presupport right internal capsule infarct and two had left middle cerebral artery embolic events while on VAD support. One patient had hemorrhage into an existing presupport infarct in the left cerebral circulation. One more patient had recurrent bilateral cerebral thromboembolic events while on VAD support (three documented episodes) and a further right thalamic infarct peritransplant. Surgical bleeding complications have reduced over time, with no patients using the modified BHE outflow cannula requiring reexploration for bleeding versus 50% in the remainder of our cohort (<italic>P</italic> = .003, Fisher exact test). Mediastinal drain losses at 24 hours (13 ± 14 vs 28 ± 17 mL/kg, <italic>P</italic> = .002, median ± interquartile range [IQR], Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test) were significantly lower and there was a trend toward a lower requirement for postoperative packed red cell transfusion (0 ± 10 vs 9 ± 21 mL/kg; <italic>P</italic> = .1, median ± IQR, Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test). We have not observed any negative impact of altering the BHE outflow cannula in the described manner on VAD driving pressures nor the rate of cerebral thromboembolic events (10% vs 24% in modified vs standard cannulation, respectively; Fisher exact test, <italic>P </italic>= .26).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-2150135112437796">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The availability of smaller volume pumps and cannulae has made longer term mechanical support possible in children but several challenges remain. The smaller relative size of the chest and great vessels can make cannula placement particularly challenging. Several modified techniques of device implantation have been reported in literature.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-2150135112437796">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-2150135112437796">4</xref>
</sup> We have found the technique described by Nguyen<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-2150135112437796">3</xref>
</sup> particularly useful as the extension of the BHE outflow cannula in this manner allows it to lie in a more natural position in small children with ventricular hypertrophy/dilatation. The modification allows the aortic anastomosis to be undertaken without resorting to aortic cross-clamping, therefore avoiding ischemic injury to the right ventricle and possibly reducing the requirement of RVAD. In addition, we have found the anastomosis easier to perform to the polyester graft than the sewing cuff of the original cannula. We believe that the polyester extension provides some flexibility to the connection between the arterial cannula and the great arteries. We have found hemostasis to be more easily achieved with this extended cannula possibly because of the improved flexibility, but increased experience and a reduction in the proportion of patients receiving BiVAD in the more recent cohort may have been additional factors influencing rates of bleeding and reexploration. We have found the graft to also allow improved control at the time of transplantation or explantation of the assist device (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2150135112437796">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
<p>The use of a PTFE graft to facilitate perfusion via the innominate artery during CPB is well described in the repair of interrupted aortic arch and the Norwood procedure and for repeat sternotomy.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-2150135112437796">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-2150135112437796">6</xref>
</sup> We have found it to be a useful modification in the implantation of the BHE for two main reasons. First, it allows for a much greater length of ascending aorta to be available for the BHE outflow cannula anastomosis, particularly in small infants where the BHE cannula is relatively big compared with the length of the ascending aorta. The second and the most important advantage has been at the time of transplantation or explantation. Following implantation of VAD, we have observed a marked inflammatory response in the mediastinum resulting in tough adhesions, even after a short period of time from implantation. Therefore, the dissection of adhesions to the heart and cannulae can be quite troublesome in these conditions, and the availability of rapid arterial access for CPB constitutes a significant advantage in terms of safety. The area exposed above the innominate vein, particularly after thymectomy in children, is quite wide and able to easily accommodate the graft. We have not observed any cases of innominate or subclavian vein obstruction as a result of leaving the graft in situ. One patient required superior vena cava stenting for obstruction after heart transplantation but well below the level of the innominate vein. Even in the presence of tough adhesions, this area is easy to dissect and the graft is easily found. In one child, the implantation of graft was, however, not possible because of a dissection of the right carotid artery at the time of previous cardiac surgery. We have not observed any clinically relevant neurological cerebroembolic sequelae from using this cannulation/recannulation technique. However, we have not performed routine radiological imaging, and the possibility of an increased rate of microembolization as a result of this technique, therefore, cannot be completely excluded.</p>
<p>In conclusion, we present our experience with what we believe to be two very useful modifications of the implantation technique for the BHE assist device. These modifications have allowed for a sustained improvement in outcomes despite an increasing complexity of pediatric cardiac cases supported to transplantation or recovery using this device.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-2150135112437796">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-2150135112437796">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-2150135112437796">
<p>Presented at the Third Scientific Meeting of the World Society for Pediatric and Congenital Heart Surgery, Istanbul, Turkey; June 23–26 2011.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<glossary content-type="abbr">
<title>Abbreviations and Acronyms</title>
<def-list>
<def-item>
<term id="term1-2150135112437796">BHE</term>
<def>
<p>Berlin Heart Excor</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term2-2150135112437796">BiVAD</term>
<def>
<p>biventricular VAD</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term3-2150135112437796">CPB</term>
<def>
<p>cardiopulmonary bypass</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term4-2150135112437796">IQR</term>
<def>
<p>interquartile range</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term5-2150135112437796">LVAD</term>
<def>
<p>left VAD</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term6-2150135112437796">PTFE</term>
<def>
<p>polytetrafluoroethylene</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term7-2150135112437796">RVAD</term>
<def>
<p>right VAD</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term id="term8-2150135112437796">VAD</term>
<def>
<p>ventricular assist device</p>
</def>
</def-item>
</def-list>
</glossary>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-2150135112437796">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Morales</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Almond</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jaquiss</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Bridging children of all sizes to cardiac transplantation: the initial multicenter North American experience with the Berlin Heart EXCOR ventricular assist device</article-title>. <source>J Heart Lung Transplant</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-2150135112437796">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hetzer</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Potapov</surname>
<given-names>EV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alexi-Meskishvili</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Single-center experience with treatment of cardiogenic shock in children by pediatric ventricular assist devices</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>141</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>616</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>, <fpage>623 e1</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-2150135112437796">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nguyen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A technique for implanting outflow cannulas for Berlin Heart EXCOR ventricular assist device in small pediatric patients</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>. <volume>142</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>223</fpage>-<lpage>224</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-2150135112437796">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tjan</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hoffmeier</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Scheld</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Klotz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Ventricular assist device implantation in neonates: adjustment of the BerlinHeart EXCOR arterial cannula with bovine pericardium</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>. <volume>139</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>783</fpage>-<lpage>784</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-2150135112437796">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Masuda</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ishino</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kato</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group> <article-title>Isolated cerebral and myocardial perfusion during aortic arch repair in neonates [in Japanese]</article-title>. <source>J Cardiol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>163</fpage>-<lpage>168</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-2150135112437796">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Knott-Craig</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goldberg</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kirklin</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Surgical strategy to prevent cardiac injury during reoperation in infants</article-title>. <source>J Cardiothorac Surg</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>