<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppic</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part C: Journal of Mechanical Engineering Science</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0954-4062</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-2983</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0954406212439515</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0954406212439515</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Special Issue Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Experimental studies on damping by parametric excitation using electromagnets</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0954406212439515"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0954406212439515">Institute of Structural Dynamics, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0954406212439515">F Dohnal, Institute of Structural Dynamics, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Petersenstr. 30, 64287 Darmstadt, Germany. Email: <email>dohnal@sdy.tu-darmstadt.de</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>226</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<issue-title>Includes a special section on Parametric Excitation: Applications in science and engineering</issue-title>
<fpage>2015</fpage>
<lpage>2027</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Transient vibrations in mechanical systems are a common problem in engineering. Several theoretical studies have shown analytically and numerically that a vibrating system can be stabilised or its vibrations can be reduced when excited close to a specific parametric combination resonance frequency. At this operation, the transient vibrations are effectively <italic>damped</italic> by parametric excitation. The basic step in exploiting this method is its experimental implementation in mechanical systems. In this review, recent experiments are discussed for a simple chain mass system, a continuous cantilever and a flexible rotor system. The parametric excitation is realised by electromagnetic variable-stiffness actuators driven by a periodic open-loop control. It is demonstrated experimentally that a parametrically excited structure can exhibit enhanced damping properties. A certain level of the excitation amplitude has to be exceeded to achieve the damping effect in which the existing damping in the system is artificially amplified. Upon exceeding this value, the additional artificial damping provided to the system is significant and most effective for vibration suppression of the lower vibration modes.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Vibration suppression</kwd>
<kwd>parametric excitation</kwd>
<kwd>self-excitation</kwd>
<kwd>parametric anti-resonance</kwd>
<kwd>cantilever</kwd>
<kwd>flexible rotor</kwd>
<kwd>active magnetic bearings</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0954406212439515" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Systems of differential equations with time-periodic coefficients, also termed parametrically excited systems, have been the focus of scientific research in mechanical engineering since more than six decades. Parametrically excited vibrations occur if one or more parameters of the differential equations are not constant but are described explicitly by a function of time; periodic and independent of the system motion. Classical examples are the pendulum with periodically varying length or periodically moving pivot point or a rotating shaft with non-symmetric cross-section, leading to the famous Mathieu, Hill or Meissner equation. Parametrically excited systems and structures have been studied extensively in the past because of the interesting phenomena that occur in such systems. A parametrically excited system may exhibit a destabilising parametric resonance if at least one system parameter is varied close to a parametric excitation frequency, see e.g.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954406212439515">1</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0954406212439515">2</xref></sup>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0954406212439515"><label>(1)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
Herein ω<sub><italic>k</italic></sub> and ω<sub><italic>l</italic></sub> denote the <italic>k</italic>th and <italic>l</italic>th natural frequency of the underlying undamped system with constant coefficients. The denominator <italic>n</italic> represents the order of the parametric resonance. This frequency is called a principal parametric resonance for <italic>k</italic> = <italic>l</italic>, and a parametric combination resonance for <italic>k</italic> ≠ <italic>l</italic>. Mostly, only first-order resonances <italic>n</italic> = 1 are significant.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954406212439515">1</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954406212439515">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>Almost all investigations on the dynamics of a single or coupled differential equations having time-periodic coefficients are focusing on the resonant behaviour of parametric excitation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954406212439515">1</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0954406212439515">9</xref></sup> The main focus there was to investigate the destabilising effect of parametric excitation, i.e. the instability boundary curves in the domain of system parameters. The non-resonant cases were not considered since they do not compromise the operation of a machine or do not amplify the system vibration in sensor applications. The benefit of introducing a non-resonant parametric excitation in an unstable coupled system was first highlighted in the pioneering works by Tondl.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0954406212439515">10</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0954406212439515">11</xref></sup> He showed that an unstable self-excited system can be stabilised by introducing a time-harmonic stiffness coefficient, a parametric excitation, at a specific parametric combination resonance frequency. Since this occurs at the frequency of a parametric resonance, the mechanism was named parametric <italic>anti</italic>-resonance.</p>
<p>Tondl's works initiated theoretical studies of several <italic>self-excited two-mass systems</italic> with time-harmonic stiffness using numerical simulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0954406212439515">12</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0954406212439515">14</xref></sup> and perturbation and bifurcation theory.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0954406212439515">15</xref></sup><sup>–</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0954406212439515">17</xref></sup> The method was enhanced to systems with time-harmonic damping<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0954406212439515">18</xref></sup> or inertia coefficients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0954406212439515">19</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0954406212439515">20</xref></sup> Almost all these investigations considered the variation of a single system parameter. Comprehensive analytical and numerical investigations for time-harmonic variations of a single as well as multiple physical parameters, a simultaneous single-frequency variation of stiffness, damping and inertia coefficients, were carried out in the reference.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0954406212439515">14</xref></sup> Especially, the interaction between parametric stiffness and damping variation is of great importance for implementations of parametric excitation, because, in general, it is rather difficult to control a single physical property without changing other properties in a specific system. The benefit of a simultaneous variation of a stiffness and a damping coefficient was highlighted in references.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0954406212439515">21</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0954406212439515">22</xref></sup> The shape of a general periodic stiffness variation was optimised in the study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0954406212439515">23</xref></sup> in order to maximise the stabilising region and, consequently, enhance the robustness.</p>
<p>For a long time, it had been believed that parametric anti-resonance can occur only in combination with self-excitation, see the review article.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0954406212439515">24</xref></sup> However, the stabilising mechanism of a parametric anti-resonance was identified as the coupling of eigenvalues of the underlying system with constant coefficients, see the studies of Dohnal.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0954406212439515">14</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0954406212439515">25</xref></sup> This qualitative interpretation drastically enlarged the applicability of the method, since a properly chosen parametric anti-resonance not only stabilises an already unstable system (stabilisation by parametric excitation) but also enhances the already existing damping; independent of self-excitation being present or not – the method of <italic>damping by parametric excitation</italic>. Furthermore, introducing a parametric anti-resonance in a system with multiple degrees of freedom offers the unique possibility, at least in first-order approximation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0954406212439515">14</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0954406212439515">25</xref></sup> to couple only two of the many vibration modes of the original system.</p>
<p>In recent years, several attempts were undertaken to verify the existence of parametric anti-resonances experimentally. Starting with discrete two-mass systems of an artificial nature, the method of damping by parametric excitation was confirmed for continuous and more complex systems. A chronological order of experimental verifications of parametric anti-resonances is listed here:
<list id="list1-0954406212439515" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>System 1, 1998.</italic> Analogue computer calculation by Tondl<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0954406212439515">11</xref></sup> of a non-linear self-excited two-mass system exhibiting parametric anti-resonance.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>System 2, 2006.</italic> Artificial two-mass system: air track with two gliding rigid bodies connected by helical springs. One body is self-excited electromagnetically while the second body is attached to a string with time-periodic tension.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0954406212439515">26</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0954406212439515">27</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>System 3, 2006.</italic> Artificial two-mass system: two rigid bodies connected by helical springs, hanging on long inextensible wires. One body is connected to a long-stroke (up to 40 mm) electromagnetic actuator driven by a variable current. The electromagnetic device was designed by Dohnal.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0954406212439515">27</xref></sup> Successful tests were reported in Schmidt et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0954406212439515">28</xref></sup> that was later reproduced in reference.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0954406212439515">29</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>System 4, 2008.</italic> Flexible cantilever under transversal force realised by a semi-active electromagnetic mount.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0954406212439515">30</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>System 5, 2009.</italic> Flexible cantilever under mainly axial force realised by a tension-controlled string using a piezoelectric actuator.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0954406212439515">31</xref></sup> This device was built for testing an active control concept<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0954406212439515">32</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0954406212439515">33</xref></sup> and was reused to resemble the system in Dohnal et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0954406212439515">34</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>System 6, 2010.</italic> Flexible rotor with multiple disks in two active magnetic bearings (AMBs).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0954406212439515">35</xref></sup></p></list-item>
</list>In the following, the basic idea of the method will be outlined on a minimum model for which a parametric anti-resonance can be realised by a harmonic stiffness variation. Conditions for regions of damping by parametric excitation will be stated in order to gain some physical insight and to extract a measure for how efficient a specific implementation of a parametric anti-resonance actually is. This enables an objective classification of the experiments undertaken so far. Finally, the three different Systems 3, 4 and 6 employing electromagnetic stiffness actuators will be discussed in some detail, including first experimental verifications of the method of damping by parametric excitation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0954406212439515"><title>Performance measure for a simple parametric stiffness excitation</title>
<p>The mechanism of damping by parametric excitation is based on the effect of coupling vibration modes by parametric excitation, which is quite different to the stabilisation of the inverse pendulum. In contradiction to the inverse pendulum, the minimum model possesses two degrees of freedom. For the case of a harmonic stiffness variation, the mass and damping matrices are constant while the stiffness matrix is varied harmonically with a frequency ν. A system with <italic>n</italic> degrees of freedom linearised at an operation point can be described by a set of coupled linear differential equations with time-periodic coefficients of the form
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0954406212439515"><label>(2)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
with the time <italic>t</italic>, the parametric excitation frequency ν, the position vector <bold>x</bold>, a scalar ε and a non-singular matrix <bold>M</bold><sub>0</sub>. The matrices <bold>M</bold>, <bold>C</bold> and <bold>K</bold> correspond to the mass/inertia, damping and stiffness coefficients. The index 0 denotes constant matrices and the indices <italic>s</italic> and <italic>a</italic> the symmetric and skew-symmetric part of the stiffness excitation matrix. Note that, due to the fact that <bold>K</bold><sub><italic>s</italic></sub>, <bold>K</bold><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> are matrices, more than one stiffness parameter of the system can be varied. The only restrictions which apply are that these variations have the same frequency ν and the same phase. Restricting the following study to systems with distinct eigenvalues, the equations of motion can be transformed to the normal form
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0954406212439515"><label>(3)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
where
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0954406212439515"><label>(4)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
The transformation matrix <bold>T</bold> diagonalises the constant system matrices. The ω<sub><italic>i</italic></sub> are the undamped natural frequencies for the underlying constant system. For a mechanical system with two degrees of freedom, this yields
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0954406212439515"><label>(5)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
Note that the damping matrix <bold>Θ</bold> is rescaled by ε for the following analytical formulae.</p>
<p>Linear differential equations with time-periodic coefficients cannot be solved analytically exact, so the solution is approximated by performing a perturbation technique, as used in literature in the various fields of physics. Famous representatives of these techniques are: harmonic balance (or two-timing), Poincaré-Lindstedt method, averaging method, method of multiple scales or successive approximation to mention the most popular ones. A general survey of these methods can be found in references.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0954406212439515">36</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0954406212439515">8</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0954406212439515">37</xref></sup> The methods above assume that the factor ε is small. A method for arbitrary size of ε based on the original Lyapunov transformation can be found in reference<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0954406212439515">38</xref></sup> leading to analytically solvable but cumbersome expressions that are hard to interpret.</p>
<p>The results shown here were derived by the averaging method, see Verhulst.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0954406212439515">39</xref></sup> Further details on the calculation steps can be found in references.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0954406212439515">15</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0954406212439515">25</xref></sup> The approximations of the slow dynamics of the system were derived for a first-order perturbation and are valid on the time scale 1/ε. Only parametric resonances of first order (<italic>n</italic> = 1) were investigated since the instability tongues of resonances of higher order are much narrower, see e.g. references.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954406212439515">3</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954406212439515">5</xref></sup> An approximation up to second order can be found in reference<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0954406212439515">17</xref></sup> which needs to be used for a certain class of systems.</p>
<p>In the analytical analysis, the scalar ε needs to be assumed small and a detuning of the parametric excitation frequency ν of first order near a frequency ν<sub>0</sub> defined in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0954406212439515">1</xref>) is introduced in the form of
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-0954406212439515"><label>(6)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<sec id="sec3-0954406212439515"><title>General case</title>
<p>If the excitation frequency ν<sub>0</sub> is not close to a frequency defined in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0954406212439515">1</xref>) then, in first-order approximation, the parametric excitation has no effect. The system motion is stable if the necessary and sufficient conditions
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-0954406212439515"><label>(7)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
are satisfied: all diagonal damping terms are positive. This result is the classical result that can be found in every common textbook on dynamical systems. A damped, non-gyroscopic system is stable if all modal damping coefficients are positive, and therefore kinetic energy is dissipated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0954406212439515"><title>Principal parametric resonance</title>
<p>If the parametric excitation frequency is tuned close to a principal parametric frequency of first order, ν ≈ ν<sub>0</sub> = 2ω<sub><italic>k</italic></sub>, then the strict stability conditions in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula7-0954406212439515">7</xref>) are relaxed and the following well-known stability conditions of the trivial solution, see e.g. reference,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0954406212439515">39</xref></sup> are obtained
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8-0954406212439515"><label>(8)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq8.tif"/></disp-formula>
where δ<sub><italic>ik</italic></sub> is the Kronecker delta-function. The critical values σ<sub><italic>c</italic></sub> represent the boundary between stable and unstable frequency regimes. Again, all modal damping parameters need to be positive for stable system operation. No parametric resonance occurs, if the more restrictive condition Θ<sub><italic>kk</italic></sub> &gt; |<italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>kk</italic></sub>|/2/ω<sub><italic>k</italic></sub> for the modal damping coefficient Θ<sub><italic>kk</italic></sub> is satisfied. This stability condition for systems with multiple degrees of freedom coincides with conditions stated in the classical literature, e.g. reference,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0954406212439515">5</xref></sup> during analysis of systems with a single degree of freedom – the famous Mathieu, Hill or Meissner equation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0954406212439515"><title>Parametric combination anti-resonance</title>
<p>Now, the parametric excitation frequency is tuned close to a parametric combination frequency of first order, ν<sub>0</sub> = |ω<sub><italic>k</italic></sub>∓ω<sub><italic>l</italic></sub>|, wherein the following upper signs correspond to a parametric combination frequency of difference type and the lower signs to summation type. This case gives, after some lengthy calculations, the following stability conditions of the trivial solution of the slow flow in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-0954406212439515">3</xref>)
<disp-formula id="disp-formula9-0954406212439515"><label>(9)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq9.tif"/></disp-formula>
A comparison of the stability conditions derived from different perturbation methods of first order was carried out in reference,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0954406212439515">40</xref></sup> which was reproduced later in reference,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0954406212439515">13</xref></sup> and shows that, to first order, all methods give the same approximation above. The critical expression σ<sub><italic>c</italic></sub> in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula9-0954406212439515">9</xref>) was derived for a system with two degrees of freedoms by Yamamoto and Saito<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0954406212439515">2</xref></sup> and Cartmell<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0954406212439515">7</xref></sup> applying harmonic balance, and for systems with an arbitrary number of degrees of freedom by Seyranian and Mailybaev<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954406212439515">3</xref></sup> evaluating perturbed Floquet multipliers based on the study of Yakubovich and Starzhinskii.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0954406212439515">1</xref></sup> However, since these contributions assumed positive definite damping matrices, the conditions for the diagonal damping elements in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula9-0954406212439515">9</xref>) were not derived which is a reason why the parametric anti-resonance could not be discovered. The full stability conditions as stated in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula9-0954406212439515">9</xref>) were derived for a system with arbitrary degrees of freedom first by Tondl<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0954406212439515">11</xref></sup> and later in the study of Seyranian and Mailybaev<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0954406212439515">3</xref></sup> by evaluating Floquet multipliers and in references<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0954406212439515">14</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0954406212439515">25</xref></sup> applying the averaging method based on the studies of Fatimah and Verhulst<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0954406212439515">15</xref></sup> and Abadi.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0954406212439515">16</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0954406212439515"><title>Performance measure</title>
<p>For an experimental design, it is crucial that the sign of the parametric excitation term <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>kl</italic></sub>Q<sub><italic>lk</italic></sub> defines the location of the parametric anti-resonance frequency and decides whether the anti-resonance is located at the parametric excitation frequency of the difference type, ν<sub>0</sub> = |ω<sub>1</sub> − ω<sub>2</sub>|, or the summation type at ν<sub>0</sub> = ω<sub><italic>k</italic></sub> + ω<sub><italic>l</italic></sub>, see reference<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0954406212439515">41</xref></sup> for more details. In the experiments undertaken so far, only systems with a parametric anti-resonance at the difference type were considered.</p>
<p>It has to be highlighted that the conditions stated in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula9-0954406212439515">9</xref>) define the system and operation parameters at which the system is at its stability border and the effective system damping is 0. Consequently, these relations state the conditions for <italic>destabilisation/stabilisation by parametric excitation</italic> of an originally stable/unstable system. Following the same approach as outlined here leads to analytical conditions for a desired level of effective damping – <italic>damping by parametric excitation</italic>. Unfortunately, the resulting expressions are cumbersome. However, numerical investigations undertaken so far showed that the width of the frequency interval εσ<sub><italic>c</italic></sub> is directly proportional to the effective damping in the system. This qualitative interpretation allows the definition of a dimensionless performance measure from the stability condition in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula9-0954406212439515">9</xref>) in combination with equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula6-0954406212439515">6</xref>)
<disp-formula id="disp-formula10-0954406212439515"><label>(10)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq10.tif"/></disp-formula>
This measure sets the maximum realisable strength of the parametric excitation ε in relation to the system's natural frequencies ω<sub><italic>i</italic></sub>, modal damping coefficients Θ<sub><italic>ii</italic></sub> and the strength of the coupling coefficients <italic>Q</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub>. The higher the performance measure becomes, the stronger the mechanism of damping by parametric excitation. This qualitative measure enables a straightforward procedure for how to implement effectively the mechanism of damping by parametric excitation in mechanical systems independent of the fact whether the parametric anti-resonance is applied to stabilise an originally unstable system or to enhance the effective damping of an already stable system.</p>
<p>The performance measure of experiments on parametric anti-resonance undertaken so far is listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0954406212439515">Table 1</xref>. This comparison helps to identify potentials and limitations in the application field of damping by parametric excitation and identifies clearly which of the presently existing system configurations needs to be redesigned. The system configuration 5 is very close to the optimally tuned system configuration 1 which means that there is only a small chance to tune it better. The remaining system configuration could perform better and a redesigned should be taken into consideration. Some experimental results are reviewed in the next section.
<table-wrap id="table1-0954406212439515" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Comparison of experiments on parametric anti-resonance using the performance measure defined in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula10-0954406212439515">10</xref>).</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0954406212439515" xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead>
<tr><th>System configuration</th>
<th>α<sub><italic>kl</italic></sub></th></tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>System 1, 1998: Tondl<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0954406212439515">11</xref></sup></td>
<td>40.0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>System 2, 2006: Dohnal et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0954406212439515">26</xref></sup></td>
<td>1.6</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>System 3, 2006: Dohnal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0954406212439515">27</xref></sup> and Schmidt et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0954406212439515">28</xref></sup></td>
<td>2.0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>System 4, 2008: Dohnal and Mace<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0954406212439515">30</xref></sup></td>
<td>35.0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>System 5, 2009: Ecker and Pumhösseel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0954406212439515">31</xref></sup></td>
<td>5.3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>System 6, 2010: Dohnal and Markert<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0954406212439515">35</xref></sup></td>
<td>6.7</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0954406212439515"><title>Experimental implementations</title>
<p>There are numerous theoretical studies on the parametric anti-resonance. Not everything is understood but a good amount of knowledge has been gathered. The next main step towards engineering applicability is experimental studies to (im)prove theoretical results. The present review examines experiments on this open-loop strategy to increase the effective damping of a vibrating system. The main motivation is to prove that the method of damping by parametric excitation is applicable for damping the low-frequency modes of simple chain systems as well as of a complex flexible structure.</p>
<p>This section reviews successful experimental implementations of a parametric anti-resonance employing electromagnetic actuators: Systems 3, 4 and 6 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0954406212439515">Table 1</xref>. All these systems are described in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0954406212439515">2</xref>) and possess symmetric system and excitation matrices, and therefore exhibit a parametric anti-resonance only at a parametric combination resonance of the difference type in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0954406212439515">1</xref>). The method of damping by parametric excitation is based on coupling the vibration modes of the underlying system with constant coefficients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0954406212439515">25</xref></sup> Therefore, any experimental verification of the method needs at least two degrees of freedom. Starting with an artificial two-mass system, a flexible cantilever and a flexible rotor system were built and tested successfully. Experimental verification of the damping effect is provided by measurements taken of the transient vibrations. Direct numerical simulation is performed to calculate ranges for control and system parameters where damping by parametric excitation is effective. Main experimental results are shown to demonstrate the applicability of the method.</p>
<p>A parametric anti-resonance was introduced in the system in a simple open-loop manner, since the stiffness parameter in focus needs to be varied at a well-defined, fixed frequency and fixed amplitude. Consequently, the method can be operated in parallel to existing and well-established controllers already in use.</p>
<sec id="sec8-0954406212439515"><title>Device 1: Artificial uniaxial actuator – System 3</title>
<p>This is the first design in a series of electromagnetic actuators that were capable of realising a parametric anti-resonance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0954406212439515">27</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0954406212439515">28</xref></sup> The main task was to design an actuator for long stroke (∓40 mm) with an adjustable stiffness characteristic. Due to the large gap between permanent magnet and electromagnets, only a small magnetic force was realised. This first design is sufficient for an experimental verification of a parametric anti-resonance but not very effective for further studies, see performance measure in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0954406212439515">Table 1</xref>. Different configurations were chosen in the subsequent development Systems 4 and 5.</p>
<p>The configuration of System 3 is sketched in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0954406212439515">Figure 1</xref>: two rigid bodies <italic>m</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>m</italic><sub>2</sub> connected by a helical springs <italic>k</italic><sub>01</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>12</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>02</sub> to each other and to the ground. After experiencing problems with a reproducible damping in System 2, the use of an air track with two gliding rigid bodies was avoided. In System 3, the bodies are hanging on long inextensible wires for guidance (not shown) with virtually zero damping. The second body <italic>m</italic><sub>2</sub> is realised by a long-stroke electromagnetic actuator consisting of an electromagnet C which is fixed to a moving fibre tube. The damping <italic>c</italic><sub>02</sub> is easily adjustable by an eddy current damper, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954406212439515">Figure 2</xref>. The counterpart of the electromagnet is formed by two permanent magnets PM. Due to the large distance between the magnets (100 mm), very strong NdFeB permanent magnets (remanent magnetic flux density of 1.36 T) are used. They are connected by a cylindrical steel housing that focuses the magnetic field radially. It has to be highlighted that no core material is chosen since this would lead to a magnetic field concentration within the core instead of the large air gap. The electromagnet C is moving between two fixed permanent magnets. The polarity of the magnetic fields generated by the permanent magnet and the electromagnet is chosen such that only repelling forces are generated. The strength of the resulting forces depends on the distance between the magnets and the strength of the magnetic field. The magnetic field strength can be altered by the current provided to the electromagnet resulting in a change of the magnetic force and, subsequently, a change of an equivalent mechanical stiffness characteristic. These stiffness elements are indicated as spring elements on both sides of the electromagnet C with a stiffness coefficient of <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>)/2.
<fig id="fig1-0954406212439515" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Configuration of System 3: a two-mass system.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig2-0954406212439515" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Uniaxial electromagnetic actuator developed for System 3.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The setup is designed numerically using the finite element program Comsol Multiphysics. Starting from chosen ring-shaped permanent magnets (the main limitation in the design), calculations of the magnetic field are performed for different shapes and sizes of the steel housing. The resulting force is calculated by integration of the Maxwell stress tensor. Due to the the strong magnetisation of the permanent magnets, the ferromagnetic housing holds most of the magnetic field. Consequently, the interaction of the steel housing and the magnetic field generated by the moving coil is negligible, even for very long stroke and high velocities of the coil, and the force remains linearly dependent on the coil current.</p>
<p>A comparison of the calculated and the measured stiffness coefficient shows excellent agreement, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0954406212439515">Figure 2</xref>. The stiffness characteristic depends linearly on the coil current <italic>i</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and quadratically on the deflection <italic>x</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) of the moving coil
<disp-formula id="disp-formula11-0954406212439515"><label>(11)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq11.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>Introducing a time-periodic parametric excitation is realised by varying the driving current periodically. Since the parametric excitation amplitude and the frequency can be determined in advance, a signal feedback and a closed-loop control is not needed. Consequently, the moving coil is driven by a time-harmonic current of the form
<disp-formula id="disp-formula12-0954406212439515"><label>(12)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq12.tif"/></disp-formula>
in order to resemble a system of the form in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula5-0954406212439515">5</xref>). Because the stiffness characteristic does also depend on the deflection of the moving coil, the resulting parametric excitation consists of linear and non-linear parts. However, for the parametric anti-resonance, this is no problem because the linear part, that determines the occurrence of a parametric anti-resonance, is dominant.</p>
<p>During experiments, both masses were deflected in the same direction and then released to vibrate freely until the system came to rest. The parametric excitation was switched on when both masses are released. Sample measurements for the magnetic actuator driven with a constant as well as a harmonic current are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0954406212439515">Figure 3</xref>. Introducing a parametric anti-resonance increases the system damping by a factor of 1.4. This increase is small but sufficient to confirm the parametric anti-resonance and the mechanism of damping by parametric excitation.
<fig id="fig3-0954406212439515" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>System 3: transient vibrations of mass <italic>m</italic><sub>1</sub> after an initial deflection.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-fig3.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0954406212439515"><title>Device 2: Electromagnetic mounting – System 4</title>
<p>After successful experimental verifications of a parametric anti-resonance for artificial two-mass systems (Systems 1, 2 and 3 resemble more an equation than a real physical system), the next main step towards engineering applications was testing the method on a flexible structure: a cantilever with semi-active mounting.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0954406212439515">30</xref></sup> Up to now, this is by far the most effective implementation with a very high performance measure in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0954406212439515">Table 1</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212439515">Figure 4</xref> shows the experimental realisation of the system, an aluminium cantilever (390 × 10 × 1 mm<sup>3</sup>) with an additional electromagnetic mount. The cantilever performs lateral vibrations in the horizontal plane.
<fig id="fig4-0954406212439515" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Configuration of System 5: cantilever with additional electromagnetic mount.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-fig4.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The parametric anti-resonance at a chosen position is implemented by an electromagnetic actuator that consists of two pairs of permanent magnets and electromagnets. Different to System 3, the electromagnetic actuator consists of a permanent magnet moving between two fixed electromagnets, and no ferromagnetic housing is used. The distance between the electromagnets can be adjusted in order to achieve an almost linear force characteristic within the deflection range of the beam. The permanent magnets are attached to the beam while the electromagnets were fixed. The magnetisation was chosen such that repulsive forces, i.e. forces that simulate a spring, were generated between the permanent magnets and electromagnets driving the beam back to its equilibrium position. These forces depend on the beam deflection and the magnetic field. The magnetic field strength can be changed in an arbitrary manner by the current provided to the electromagnets. A parametric anti-resonance is realised, again, by driving the electromagnets by a pre-defined periodic current in an open-loop manner. Both coils are fed by a single amplifier such that exactly the same current flows through both coils. An electrically operated latch was used to hold the tip of the cantilever at a reproducable initial position and released to initiate a transient vibration. Discretising the cantilever by <italic>n</italic> finite beam elements, allowed to approximate the displacement field by Rayleigh–Ritz shape functions which results in equations of motion of the form in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0954406212439515">2</xref>).</p>
<p>A theoretical analysis of the system showed that a parametric anti-resonance was found in the vicinity of ν = ω<sub>2</sub> − ω<sub>1</sub>. Further, a certain level of the parametric excitation amplitude ε has to be exceeded to achieve the parametric anti-resonance at which the existing damping in the system is increased. For the present system, the threshold was computed to ε &gt; 0.28. Upon exceeding this value, the system damping is increased artificially. The mechanism of damping by parametric excitation is most effective for suppression of vibrations of the lower modes of the cantilever. This configuration allows a maximum amplitude of ε = 0.8.</p>
<p>A series of experiments were performed by varying the parametric excitation frequency ν. Starting from an initial displacement of 20 mm at the tip position, the transient displacement of a point close to the tip was measured by a laser displacement transducer, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0954406212439515">Figure 4</xref>. Two samples of this series are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212439515">Figure 5</xref>. The dashed line represents the transient motion of the beam when the additional mount is inactive. The solid line corresponds to the transient motion for active parametric anti-resonance.
<fig id="fig5-0954406212439515" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Comparison of transient vibrations for the nominal system and at activated parametric anti-resonance.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-fig5.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The effective damping (exponential decay) of the measured signals is identified by fitting an exponential function to its envelopes. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0954406212439515">Figure 6</xref> shows the identified effective damping as a function of the parametric excitation frequency ν at ε = 0.8. This result is compared to the theoretical prediction by direct numerical integration of equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0954406212439515">2</xref>). For the cantilever with inactive mount, the exponential decay is 1.8 due to the passive damping in the system. In the frequency range considered, a parametric resonance is observed close to the frequency 2ω<sub>1</sub> = 89.3 s<sup>−1</sup> and a parametric anti-resonance close to |ω<sub>2</sub> − ω<sub>1</sub>| = 73.5 s<sup>−1</sup>. The theoretical results agree excellently with the experimental results. The minimum value of the identified decay is found at 73 Hz, which reflects the fact that the frequencies defined in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0954406212439515">1</xref>) are only approximate locations of the parametric resonances and anti-resonances of the system.
<fig id="fig6-0954406212439515" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Effective damping at a parametric excitation amplitude of ε = 0.8.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-fig6.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>An additional parametric resonance is predicted at the frequency ω<sub>1</sub> + ω<sub>2</sub> = 162.8 s<sup>−1</sup>. However, in the experiment, only a small decrease in the identified damping was seen. This is due to the fact that a parametric resonance is not established immediately after releasing the beam from its initial displacement. In general, the vibration amplitudes first decrease at a slow rate before the parametric resonance kicks in and the amplitudes start to increase rapidly. Depending whether the time of this turning point lies within the measured time interval, different damping coefficients will be identified. For a better agreement between theory and experiment in a frequency band around ω<sub>1</sub> + ω<sub>2</sub>, a significantly longer time interval should be chosen.</p>
<p>The effect of the parametric anti-resonance, damping by parametric excitation, can be observed clearly in the frequency interval between 50 and 83 Hz. In this range, the damping of the system is artificially increased, hence, amplified. At the optimum frequency of 73 Hz, the decay reaches its minimum value of 8.05. Compared to the system with a constant stiffness, ν = 0, this corresponds to an amplification of damping by a factor of 4.5. The transient at this frequency was plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0954406212439515">Figure 5</xref> showing that the equilibrium position of the beam is reached just after three vibration cycles.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0954406212439515"><title>Device 3: AMB – System 6</title>
<p>In this section, the implementation of a parametric anti-resonance for a flexible rotor shaft with multiple rigid disks attached to its shaft under the action of unbalance and electromagnetic forces is discussed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0954406212439515">35</xref></sup> The experimental realisation of the system is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0954406212439515">Figure 7</xref>: A slender, flexible rotor shaft rotating at a constant rotational speed and supported by two AMBs. The shaft is assumed to be torsionally rigid and isotropic. Five rigid disks are attached to the shaft, three disks (D1, D2, D3) and two bearing studs (AMB1, AMB2). The disks are unbalanced. The total length of the shaft is 680 mm.
<fig id="fig7-0954406212439515" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Configuration of System 6: flexible rotor with multiple disks supported by two active magnetic bearings.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-fig7.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The electromagnetic forces generated in the AMBs depend on the rotor deflection and the magnetic field. The magnetic field can be changed in a wide range by the current provided to the electromagnets. The actual position of the rotor shaft is measured by inductive sensors (two for each radial direction). These signals are processed by the real-time controller hardware dSpace, which implements decentralised proportional–integral–derivative PID controllers to regulate the currents provided by power amplifiers to each of the electromagnets and, hence, to levitate the rotor.</p>
<p>AMBs consist of pairs of electromagnets that are arranged, in general, in two perpendicular axes enabling to control the rotor position within a plane. Since electromagnets can apply only attracting but no repelling forces, two electromagnets are needed for each direction. The electromagnetic force generated by the AMB depends on its geometry parameters (cross-section of the pole shoes, size of the air gap) and its electromagnetic properties (number of turns, permeability) and is a strongly non-linear function of these parameters. In practice, however, the resulting force can be linearised close to a certain operation point as
<disp-formula id="disp-formula13-0954406212439515"><label>(13)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq13.tif"/></disp-formula>
assuming a high bias current for pre-magnetisation, a small control current <italic>i</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> and rotor deflection <italic>r</italic>. Herein, <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the current–force constant and −<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub> the negative bearing stiffness. Cross-coupling parameters are neglected.</p>
<p>The most widely used control concept for an AMB is a PID controller. The proportional (<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>P</italic></sub>) and the derivative actions (<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>D</italic></sub>) constitute the stiffness and damping characteristics of the bearing while the integral action (<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>I</italic></sub>) assures that the radial rotor deflection <italic>r</italic> keeps track with a predefined setpoint
<disp-formula id="disp-formula14-0954406212439515"><label>(14)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq14.tif"/></disp-formula>
Inserting into equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula13-0954406212439515">13</xref>) leads to
<disp-formula id="disp-formula15-0954406212439515"><label>(15)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq15.tif"/></disp-formula>
with the active stiffness and active damping coefficients <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub>. Adjusting the control parameters <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>P</italic></sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>D</italic></sub> determines the dynamic properties of the AMB. Both AMBs are isotropic. Within the present investigation, the influence of gyroscopic effects on the first four natural frequencies is below 4%.</p>
<p>In parallel to this PID control, an <italic>open-loop control</italic> of the proportional action is implemented, which realises a periodic change in the active bearing stiffness according to equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula15-0954406212439515">15</xref>). This parametric stiffness excitation is realised in both AMBs simultaneously according to
<disp-formula id="disp-formula16-0954406212439515"><label>(16)</label><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-eq16.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>Numerical calculations are performed in order to find a proper parametric anti-resonance for this complex system. The flexible, continuous shaft is discretised using finite beam elements and the rotor system is excited by unbalance forces originating from the five rigid disks. The discretised equations of motion are of the form in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0954406212439515">2</xref>) with an additional right hand side for the unbalance force vector. These equations are solved by direct numerical integration for different values of the control frequency ν of the time-periodicity introduced in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula16-0954406212439515">16</xref>). The control amplitude ε is kept constant at 0.30. The rotor is driven at a constant speed well below its first critical speed. Transient vibrations of the rotor are introduced by an initial deflection of the rotor. All time histories in the frequency range of interest are summarised in the contour plot in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212439515">Figure 8</xref>. Light areas depict low values and dark areas high values of the radial deflection |<italic>r</italic><sub><italic>D</italic>2</sub>| of disk <italic>D</italic>2. Additionally, frequency lines of the frequencies ν<sub>0</sub> defined in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0954406212439515">1</xref>) are plotted for the orders <italic>n</italic> = 1 up to <italic>n</italic> = 5 on the right hand side of the figure. Their line thickness is inversely scaled by the order <italic>n</italic>. All possible parametric frequencies ν<sub>0</sub> are divided into three groups corresponding to the three blocks on the right hand side of the figure: the two groups 2ω<sub><italic>i</italic></sub>/<italic>n</italic> and (ω<sub><italic>k</italic></sub> + ω<sub><italic>l</italic></sub>)/<italic>n</italic> that correspond to destabilising parametric resonancies, and the group |ω<sub><italic>k</italic></sub> − ω<sub><italic>l</italic></sub>|/<italic>n</italic> which corresponds to a parametric anti-resonance. These frequency lines help in encoding the complex distribution of the time series. At each of these frequencies, a dense frequency interval exists within which the system vibrations are either excited or damped. If these frequency intervals overlap, it depends which effect dominates.
<fig id="fig8-0954406212439515" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Numerically calculated radial deflection <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>D</italic>2</sub> of disk <italic>D</italic>2 at ε = 0.30.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-fig8.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The transient behaviour of the nominal rotor corresponds to ν = 0. Switching on the periodic open-loop control of the AMBs following the control law in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula16-0954406212439515">16</xref>) changes the transient behaviour. Destabilising effects, parametric resonances, are observed for control parameter ν being close to the frequencies 49, 172 and 221 s<sup>−1</sup>. The corresponding parametric resonance frequencies can be identified by comparing with the frequency lines on the right hand side, e.g. the shaded area at 221 s<sup>−1</sup> corresponds to the frequency 2ω<sub>1</sub> = 221.2 s<sup>−1</sup>. Indentations in the distribution towards lower time values in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0954406212439515">Figure 8</xref> give hints of an increase in effective damping, a parametric anti-resonance. The main parametric anti-resonance is close to ν = |ω<sub>2</sub> − ω<sub>3</sub>| = 113.4 s<sup>−1</sup>. This is the optimum control frequency to be chosen for the proposed open-loop control in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula16-0954406212439515">16</xref>) and for this specific rotor system.</p>
<p>The experimental rotor is driven at the sample rotor speed of 600 r/min (below its first critical speed) and open-loop control is operated at the theoretically predicted parametric anti-resonance, at ν = |ω<sub>2</sub> − ω<sub>3</sub>| = 113.4 s<sup>−1</sup>. At the time of 8 s an impulse is applied to the rotor system realised by adding an impulse-like current to the controller current. Time histories for different values of the control amplitude ε are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0954406212439515">Figure 9</xref>. For the nominal system without open-loop control (ε = 0), the system response decays with an effective logarithmic decrement of 0.8. Activating the parametric anti-resonance enhances the system damping artificially which results in increased logarithmic decrements. A value of 1.6 is achieved at a control amplitude of ε = 0.15 and a value of 3.7 at ε = 0.30. Higher control amplitudes are not possible with the present setup of the rotor test rig.
<fig id="fig9-0954406212439515" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Measured time histories at the optimal controller parameter ν = |ω<sub>2</sub> − ω<sub>3</sub>|.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0954406212439515-fig9.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Without the proposed open-loop control (ε = 0), the system damping can be increased simply by increasing the active damping <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula15-0954406212439515">15</xref>) introduced by the PID controllers, too. However, this increase is limited by the level of noise in the control loop and its amplification by the derivative action <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>D</italic></sub>. Starting from optimum PID controllers in the nominal system, <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>D</italic></sub> can be amplified maximally by a factor of 1.7. Introducing the proposed open-loop control at the control parameters ε = 0.3 and ν = |ω<sub>2</sub> − ω<sub>3</sub>|, allows an increase in effective system damping well above this factor. The maximum amplification factor for the effective damping that was achieved experimentally is 4.6 which lies well above the limit realisable by conventional active damping.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0954406212439515" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In this review, recent experiments on damping by parametric excitation are discussed employing electromagnetic actuators. Three systems are outlined: an artificial chain system, a flexible cantilever and a flexible rotor system. It is demonstrated that introducing a parametric excitation in a vibrating system not only destabilises the system but also enhances damping properties when excited close to a non-resonant parametric combination resonance – a parametric anti-resonance or damping by parametric excitation. The damping effect achieved by this method is significant for the lowest modes, e.g. the first mode of a structure. A characteristic advantage of the method presented is the fact that parametric excitation works as an open-loop system with no feedback control necessary. This is very advantageous for practical applications, since it will save cost, weight and energy for additional sensors and controllers. Furthermore, the control method can be applied in parallel with existent methods, since it affects mainly the free vibrations of a system by coupling two vibration modes of the underlying constant system. Consequently, instead of adding new damping into the system, the existing system damping is enhanced artificially.</p>
<p>A performance measure is defined that enables to benchmark specific implementations of parametric anti-resonance and that can be used to select efficient experimental designs. So far, only simple, single-frequency parametric anti-resonances were realised. Additional experimental studies are needed to further explore the potential of the method and, finally, enter engineering applications.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec12-0954406212439515"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0954406212439515"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yakubovich</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Starzhinskii</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Linear differential equations with periodic coefficients</source>, <volume>Vols. 1 and 2</volume>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>, <year>1975</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0954406212439515"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On the vibrations of summed and differential types under parametric excitation</article-title>. <source>Mem Fac En Nagoya Univ Japan</source> <year>1970</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0954406212439515"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Seyranian A and Mailybaev A. <italic>Multiparameter stability theory with mechanical applications</italic> (series on stability, vibration and control of systems) vol 13. Singapore: World Scientific, 2003</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0954406212439515"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On the parametric excitation of a dynamic system having multiple degrees of freedom</article-title>. <source>J Appl Mech Trans ASME</source> <year>1963</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>372</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0954406212439515"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolotin</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Dynamic stability of elastic systems</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Holden-Day</publisher-name>, <year>1964</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0954406212439515"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwatsubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Simple and combination resonances of columns under periodic axial loads</article-title>. <source>J Sound Vib</source> <year>1974</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0954406212439515"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cartmell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Introduction to linear, parametric and nonlinear vibrations</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>, <year>1990</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0954406212439515"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayfeh</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mook</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Nonlinear oscillations</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons</publisher-name>, <year>1995</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0954406212439515"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>M-K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Parametric instability of a cantilevered column under periodic loads in the direction of the tangency coefficient</article-title>. <source>J Sound Vib</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>183</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0954406212439515"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On the interaction between self-excited and parametric vibrations</article-title>. <source>In Monographs and Memoranda 25</source>. <publisher-loc>Prague</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Research Institute for Machine Design</publisher-name>, <year>1978</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0954406212439515"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>To the problem of quenching self-excited vibrations</article-title>. <source>Acta Tech CSAV</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0954406212439515"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cancelling of self-excited vibrations by means of parametric excitation</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the 1999 ASME DETC</source>. <publisher-loc>Las Vegas</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nevada, USA</publisher-name>, <year>12–15 September 1999, DETC99/VIB-8071, pp. 1–10</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0954406212439515"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Suppression of self-excited vibrations in mechanical systems by parametric stiffness excitation</article-title><source>Fortschrittsberichte Simulation, Vol. 11</source><comment>ARGESIM/ASIM Verlag, 2005</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0954406212439515"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Damping of mechanical vibrations by parametric excitation</article-title>. <source>PhD Thesis</source>. <publisher-name>Vienna University of Technology, Austria</publisher-name>, <year>2005</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0954406212439515"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fatimah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhulst</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Suppressing flow-induced vibrations by parametric excitation. Nonlinear Dyn</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0954406212439515"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abadi</surname></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nonlinear dynamics of self-excitation in autoparametric systems</article-title>. <source>PhD Thesis</source>. <publisher-name>Utrecht University, Netherlands</publisher-name>, <year>2003</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0954406212439515"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhulst</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Averaging in vibration suppression by parametric stiffness excitation</article-title>. <source>Nonlinear Dyn</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0954406212439515"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Combination resonances and anti-resonances in systems parametrically excited by harmonic variation of linear damping coefficients</article-title>. <source>Acta Tech CSAV</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0954406212439515"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Systems with periodically variable masses</article-title>. <source>Acta Tech CSAV</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0954406212439515"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Suppressing flutter vibrations by parametric inertia excitation</article-title>. <source>J Appl Mech</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>76</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <comment>paper no. 031006</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0954406212439515"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Suppression of self-excited vibrations by synchronous stiffness and damping variation</article-title>. <source>J Sound Vib</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>306</volume>: <fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0954406212439515"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Damping of a flexible rotor by time-periodic stiffness and damping variatio</article-title>. <source>In: Proceedings of the 9th VIRM, Exeter, UK, 8–10 September 2008, pp. 1–12</source>, <year>2008</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0954406212439515"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Optimal dynamic stabilisation of a linear system by periodic stiffness excitation</article-title>. <source>J Sound Vib</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>320</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>–<lpage>792</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0954406212439515"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tondl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>To the problem of self-excited vibration suppression</article-title>. <source>Eng Mech</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0954406212439515"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Damping by parametric stiffness excitation: parametric resonance and anti-resonance</article-title>. <source>J Vib Control</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>688</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0954406212439515"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Paradeiser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Experimental study on cancelling self-excited vibrations by parametric excitation</article-title>. <source>In: Proceedings of IMECE ASME</source> <year>2006</year>. <comment>Chicago, USA, 5–10 November 2010, paper no. 14552, pp. 1–10</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0954406212439515"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Experimental realisation of self-excitation and parametric excitation</source>. <publisher-name>Technical report PES-No. 2, Vienna University of Technology, Austria</publisher-name>, <year>2006</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0954406212439515"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Paradeiser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Design of an electromagnetic actuator for parametric stiffness excitation</article-title>. <source>COMPEL</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>800</fpage>–<lpage>813</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0954406212439515"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prototype design and experimental verification of an electromagnetic actuator for parametric stiffnesss excitation</article-title><source>In: <italic>Proceedings of IEEE CCECE</italic></source><comment>Calgary, Canada, 2–5 May 2010, pp. 1–5</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0954406212439515"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Amplification of damping of a cantilever beam by parametric excitation</article-title>. <source>In: Proceedings of the 9th MOVIC</source> <year>15–18 September 2008, paper no. 1248, pp. 1–10</year>. <publisher-name>Munich</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0954406212439515"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pumhössel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental results on parametric excitation damping of an axially loaded cantilever beam</article-title><source>In: Proceedings of the 2009 ASME IDETC</source><comment>San Diego, USA, 30 August–2 September 2009, DETC, 86555, pp. 1–9</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0954406212439515"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovyrshin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Active parametric vibration control of a smart beam</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of 8th international conference on VIRM</source>. <publisher-loc>Swansea</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Wales</publisher-name>, <year>7–9 September 2004, IMECHE, C623/017</year>, pp. <fpage>703</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0954406212439515"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pumhössel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Active damping of vibrations of a lightweight beam structure – experimental results</article-title><source>In: Proceedings of the 9th MOVIC</source><comment>Munich, Springer Verlag, 15–18 September 2008, paper no. 1150, pp. 253–262</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0954406212439515"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Amplification of damping of an elastic beam by parametric excitation</article-title>. <source>Arch Appl Mech</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>947</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0954406212439515"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Markert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Enhancement of external damping of a flexible rotor in active magnetic bearings by time-periodic stiffness variation</article-title>. <source>J Sys Des Dyn</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>856</fpage>–<lpage>865</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0954406212439515"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mickens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>An introduction to nonlinear oscillations</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge Press</publisher-name>, <year>1981</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0954406212439515"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Vibrations and stability: advanced theory, analysis and tools</source>, <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg, New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Verlag</publisher-name>, <year>2003</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0954406212439515"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Butcher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Symbolic computation of fundamental solution matrices for linear time-periodic systems</article-title>. <source>J Sound Vib</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>206</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0954406212439515"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verhulst</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nonlinear differential equations and dynamical systems (texts in applied mathematics) vol. 50</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg, New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>, <year>2000</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0954406212439515"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Application of the averaging method on parametrically excited 2dof-systems</source>. <publisher-name>Technical report PES-No. 1, Vienna University of Technology, Austria</publisher-name>, <year>2003</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0954406212439515"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>General parametric stiffness excitation: parametric anti-resonance frequency and symmetry</article-title>. <source>Acta Mech</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>196</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>