<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JDR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjdr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Dent Res</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Dental Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0345</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1544-0591</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022034512453324</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0022034512453324</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reviews</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Critical Reviews in Oral Biology &amp; Medicine</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>TMJ Disc Removal</article-title>
<subtitle>Comparison between Pre-clinical Studies and Clinical Findings</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hagandora</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Almarza</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0022034512453324">*</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0022034512453324">Department of Oral Biology, Department of Bioengineering, School of Dental Medicine, Center for Craniofacial Regeneration, McGowan Institute of Regenerative Medicine, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA 15260, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0022034512453324"><label>*</label><email>aja19@pitt.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>91</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<fpage>745</fpage>
<lpage>752</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>18</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>7</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>7</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 International &amp; American Associations for Dental Research</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">International &amp; American Associations for Dental Research</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The debate continues surrounding the use of disc removal (discectomy) as the primary surgical treatment for patients suffering from severe temporomandibular joint disorders. Furthermore, the effectiveness of pre-clinical animal models for predicting the response of the joint to discectomy in humans remains uncertain. This review compares the results of animal models with the most recent clinical findings while also focusing on investigations that use imaging as an assessment tool. After a review of the literature from well-established animal studies to clinical findings, it was found that the results of animal models for discectomy corresponded to the clinical findings seen in patients. Overall, there is adaptive remodeling or degeneration of the TMJ following discectomy. Additionally, there is some reduction in pain but with various amounts of dysfunction remaining following disc removal. Noteworthy, in the most recent clinical studies, imaging was not used as an outcome to assess the success of discectomy at preventing further joint degeneration.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>temporomandibular disorders</kwd>
<kwd>cartilage</kwd>
<kwd>gender differences</kwd>
<kwd>joint disease</kwd>
<kwd>oral and maxillofacial surgery</kwd>
<kwd>tissue engineering</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0022034512453324" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<sec id="section2-0022034512453324">
<title>TMJ Pathology and Treatments</title>
<p>The clinical necessity for investigation stems from the fact that temporomandibular joint disorders (TMDs) may affect over 10 million Americans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0022034512453324">NIH, 2010</xref>), with up to 70% of people with TMJ disorders suffering from displacement of the TMJ disc, or ‘internal derangement’ of the TMJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022034512453324">Farrar and McCarty, 1979</xref>). Internal derangement can be described as an abnormal positional relationship of the disc relative to the mandibular condyle and the articular eminence, in which the disc is generally anteriorly displaced, possibly resulting in pain, joint clicking, locking of the joint, and degeneration of the surrounding tissues.</p>
<p>Patients with severe TMDs, or joint pain and dysfunction that do not respond to non-surgical treatments, resort to surgical interventions, including disc repositioning, disc removal, and replacement of the condylar, fossa, or both components with a prosthetic device. When the TMJ disc is too damaged to be repositioned, and there is no apparent condylar degeneration, surgeons will choose to perform a discectomy (disc removal).</p>
<p>The effectiveness of discectomy in alleviating the symptoms of TMDs remains controversial. The crux of the debate is whether or not discectomy is a safe long-term treatment option for patients suffering from TMDs, or if surgical removal of the disc creates an environment more susceptible to joint degeneration. The implementation of animal models has been a critical step in the examination of this process, but the comparability of joint remodeling observed in animals following discectomy with that seen in humans merits further investigation. While comprehensive reviews exist regarding the use of animal models for TMJ degeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0022034512453324">Almarza <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>) as well as general clinical outcomes of discectomy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0022034512453324">Dimitroulis, 2011b</xref>), this review will examine established animal models for discectomy and critically assess the validity of these models in light of recent longer term clinical results in patients. In the first part of this review, animal models will be discussed in sequence of mid-sized (rabbit, guinea pig) and large (sheep, primate) models, focusing on the results of both (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0022034512453324">Table 1</xref>). The second part of this review will focus on clinical findings in patients receiving discectomy alone or with biologic graft materials in the past 10 years. We will then focus on a broader range of investigations that used imaging as an assessment tool following discectomy. The implications of all sets of findings will then be evaluated. The methodology utilized in our literature search is outlined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0022034512453324">Fig. 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0022034512453324" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Pre-clinical Animal Models for Discectomy, Describing the Animal Model Size, Graft Material Used, Age/Weight, Total Number of Animals Used, Last Time-point Assessed, and Whether a Bilateral/Unilateral Surgery Was Performed</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0022034512453324" xlink:href="10.1177_0022034512453324-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Size</th>
<th align="center">Graft</th>
<th align="center">Animal</th>
<th align="center">Age/Weight</th>
<th align="center">n=</th>
<th align="center">Last Time-point</th>
<th align="center">Bilateral/Unilateral</th>
<th align="center">Authors</th>
<th align="center">Year</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Medium</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>Rabbit</td>
<td>3-3.5 kg</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>3 mos</td>
<td>Unilateral</td>
<td>Sato <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>2002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Medium</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>Rabbit</td>
<td>3-3.5 kg</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>3 mos</td>
<td>Unilateral</td>
<td>Sato <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>2002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Medium</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>Rabbit</td>
<td/>
<td>15</td>
<td>20 wks</td>
<td>Unilateral</td>
<td>Dimitroulis <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>2006</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Medium</td>
<td>Auricular Cartilage</td>
<td>Rabbit</td>
<td>14 wks (3-4 kg)</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>24 wks</td>
<td>Unilateral</td>
<td>Takatsuka <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>1996</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Medium</td>
<td>Collagen/Dermal Graft</td>
<td>Rabbit</td>
<td>Adult</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>36 wks</td>
<td>Bilateral</td>
<td>Feinberg <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>1995</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Medium</td>
<td>Lyophilized Auricular Cartilage</td>
<td>Guinea Pig</td>
<td>Adult</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>24 wks</td>
<td>Unilateral</td>
<td>Ioannides <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>1988</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Medium</td>
<td>Sternal and Auricular Cartilage</td>
<td>Guinea Pig</td>
<td>Adult</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>3, 6, 12, 24 wks</td>
<td>Unilateral</td>
<td>Ioannides <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>1988</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Large</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>Monkey</td>
<td>Adult</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>12 mos</td>
<td>Unilateral</td>
<td>Yaillen <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>1979</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Large</td>
<td>None</td>
<td>Monkey</td>
<td>At least 48 mos (1,970-3,100 g)</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>6 mos</td>
<td>Unilateral</td>
<td>Bjornland <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>1999</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Large</td>
<td>Auricular Cartilage</td>
<td>Monkey</td>
<td>Adult</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>24 wks</td>
<td>Bilateral</td>
<td>Tucker <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>1990</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Large</td>
<td>Fascia Lata graft</td>
<td>Monkey</td>
<td>Adult</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>18 mos</td>
<td>Unilateral</td>
<td>Tong <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>2000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Large</td>
<td>Auricular cartilage and pedicled temporalis myofascial</td>
<td>Monkey</td>
<td>Adult</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>18 mos</td>
<td>Unilateral</td>
<td>Tong <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>2000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Large</td>
<td>Temporalis Muscle</td>
<td>Sheep</td>
<td>Adult (2 yrs)</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>24 wks</td>
<td>Bilateral</td>
<td>Thyne <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>1992</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig1-0022034512453324" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Schematic of manuscript inclusion and exclusion criteria. All searches were performed in PubMed.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0022034512453324-fig1.tif"/></fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0022034512453324">
<title>Mid-size Animal Models</title>
<p>Mid-size animal models, such as the rabbit and guinea pig, have been used to further explore the effects of discectomy on the remaining joint tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0022034512453324">Sato <italic>et al</italic>., 2002a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0022034512453324">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0022034512453324">Dimitroulis and Slavin, 2006</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0022034512453324">Table 1</xref>). The results of the mid-size animal discectomy studies showed that disc removal alone can result in thickening of the fibrous layer of the condyle and articular eminence, changes in collagen fiber density, and flattening of the condyle on the unoperated joint (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0022034512453324">Sato <italic>et al</italic>., 2002a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0022034512453324">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0022034512453324">Dimitroulis and Slavin, 2006</xref>). The general response is remodeling of the articulating surfaces, such as thickening of the condylar cartilage, to compensate for the loss of the disc. While these studies show, qualitatively, the changes that take place following discectomy, they lack evidence of change of function of the tissue, which could be verified by mechanical testing.</p>
<p>Mid-size animal models have also been used to examine the effect of discectomy with graft replacement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0022034512453324">Ioannides and Maltha, 1988a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0022034512453324">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022034512453324">Feinberg and McDonnell, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0022034512453324">Takatsuka <italic>et al</italic>., 1996</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0022034512453324">Table 1</xref>). In a rabbit model, it has been shown that although auricular cartilage grafts developed perforations or fragmentations, animals that did not receive a graft showed more intense degenerative changes with flattening of the condyle and the eminence compared with the rabbits that did receive the graft (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0022034512453324">Takatsuka <italic>et al</italic>., 1996</xref>). The rabbit model has also been used to investigate the effectiveness of dermis and collagen graft replacements, and, although the grafts were resorbed by 8 wks, the authors concluded that both grafts seemed to prevent early degenerative changes in the joint (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022034512453324">Feinberg and McDonnell, 1995</xref>). The effect of auricular cartilage grafting was also investigated in a guinea pig model, and it was found that, at 24 wks post-surgery, most of the implant had been resorbed and replaced by young fibrous connective tissue completely separated from the surface of the condyle and fossa, with newly formed cartilage observed at the rostral part of the new fibrous structure. The articulating surfaces exhibited either slight or no major changes in histological structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0022034512453324">Ioannides and Maltha, 1988a</xref>). The use of fresh autogenous sternal grafting was also examined in adult female albino guineas pigs, with the authors concluding that autogenous sternal cartilage should not be recommended as a replacement material, because it is difficult to cut into shape and has a tendency to warp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0022034512453324">Ioannides and Maltha, 1988b</xref>).</p>
<p>The mid-size animal models discussed provide important information regarding the joint tissue response to discectomy with graft replacement. While certain graft materials appear to protect against degeneration when compared with discectomy alone, it is unclear if fibrous tissue formation around implants could lead to fibrous ankylosis or other functional problems at later time-points. Additionally, the remodeling that takes place in response to discectomy could be an indicator of adaptation and not degeneration. If so, the necessity of using graft materials that could lead to unwanted side effects should be validated. The clear limitations of the use of the rabbit and guinea pig models are the distinct differences in anatomy and masticatory frequency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0022034512453324">Gerstner and Gerstein, 2008</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0022034512453324">Fig. 2</xref>). However, the use of a mid-size model is a critical springboard for studies with larger, more relevant animal models to investigate the effect of discectomy alone and with graft replacement.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0022034512453324" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Anatomy of rabbit (<bold>A</bold>), goat (<bold>C</bold>), pig (<bold>E</bold>), and human (<bold>G</bold>) skulls. Mandibular condyles of rabbit (<bold>B</bold>), goat (<bold>D</bold>), pig (<bold>F</bold>), and human (<bold>H</bold>) skulls. Arrows indicate the head of the mandibular condyle.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0022034512453324-fig2.tif"/></fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0022034512453324">
<title>Large Animal Models</title>
<p>Larger animal models have also been used to study the effect of discectomy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0022034512453324">Yaillen <italic>et al</italic>., 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0022034512453324">Bjornland and Haanaes, 1999</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0022034512453324">Table 1</xref>). Yaillen <italic>et al</italic>. studied the effect of discectomy in 5 mature <italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic> monkeys and found that, at 12 mos, the operated joints exhibited severe degenerative changes signified by bone resorption, broadening and flattening of the condylar head, and ankylosis between the condyle and temporal bone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0022034512453324">Yaillen <italic>et al</italic>., 1979</xref>). The effect of discectomy on primate joints was further evaluated by Bjornland and Haanaes, who observed, at 6 mos post-surgery, a variety of joint changes, including fibrous ankylosis, condylar flattening, absence of cartilage on the condyle or fossa, absence of cartilage lining of the condyle and fossa, formation of fibrous tissue, newly formed bone, and increased cartilage thickness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0022034512453324">Bjornland and Haanaes, 1999</xref>). The findings in this primate model correspond with those of the mid-size animal models in which discectomy resulted in substantial destruction of the articulating cartilage surfaces.</p>
<p>The discussed discectomy studies provide valuable insight into the process of joint degradation following disc removal in a relevant animal model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0022034512453324">Yaillen <italic>et al</italic>., 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0022034512453324">Bjornland and Haanaes, 1999</xref>). The non-human primate studies demonstrated that disc removal does result in joint tissue remodeling, which does not seem to cause a significant change in joint function. The sex of the experimental animals in these studies is not specified or discussed. Clarifying differences, if any, in joint response to discectomy with regard to sex is a vital step in understanding the gender polarity of the disease and propensity for females treated with disc removal to develop osteoarthritis.</p>
<p>Primate models have been utilized to determine the effects of biologic grafts on the TMJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0022034512453324">Tucker <italic>et al</italic>., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0022034512453324">Thyne <italic>et al</italic>., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0022034512453324">Tong and Tideman, 2000a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0022034512453324">b</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0022034512453324">Table 1</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0022034512453324">Tucker <italic>et al</italic>. (1990)</xref> investigated the effect of discectomy and autogenous auricular cartilage implantation in 4 adult <italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic> monkeys. Both sides of the joint underwent discectomy and condylar shaving, but only one side received the cartilage graft. At 24 wks, the control side exhibited layers of dense fibrous connective tissue disrupted in areas, along with projections of bone into the joint space. In the graft group, the condylar surface appeared smooth, with a covering of fibrous connective tissue, and the grafts were closely adapted to the fossa, showing viable chondrocytes. The study showed that auricular grafts might be a viable option for patients with degradation of both the articulating cartilage and the TMJ disc.</p>
<p>In a study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0022034512453324">Tong and Tideman (2000a)</xref>, the effect of discectomy with and without replacement with a <italic>fascia lata</italic> graft was observed in 8 adult <italic>Macaca mulatta</italic> monkeys. The graft did not survive after implantation. At 18 mos, the graft did not protect against morphological changes of the condyle and glenoid fossa, thickening of the articular surface tissue, osteoarthritic changes, or fibrous ankylosis. A follow-up study compared auricular cartilage graft with a pedicled temporalis myofascial graft in 8 rhesus monkeys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0022034512453324">Tong and Tideman, 2000b</xref>). At 6 mos post-surgery, the cartilage graft or remnants could not be identified. Auricular cartilage did not survive after grafting and did not induce reformation of the articular disc (except in the 6-month-old group). The pedicled temporalis muscle graft formed a band of fibrovascular tissue which appeared to remain intact under normal functional loads. The authors concluded that a myofascial graft has the greatest potential to restore a “disc-like” structure while also protecting against osteoarthritic changes in the joint. The sheep model has been used to observe the effect of graft replacement following discectomy. Thyne <italic>et al</italic>. also investigated the use of the temporalis muscle flap as a replacement for the TMJ disc in sheep (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0022034512453324">Thyne <italic>et al</italic>., 1992</xref>). At 24 wks, the joints were empty, and the condyle and fossa were in close contact. The authors concluded that the temporalis muscle is not a good replacement material and that replacement of the TMJ disc following discectomy is not necessary to prevent ankylosis.</p>
<p>The large-animal discectomy studies utilizing graft replacement suggested that biologic grafts may provide some protection against the progression of osteoarthritis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0022034512453324">Tucker <italic>et al</italic>., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0022034512453324">Thyne <italic>et al</italic>., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0022034512453324">Tong and Tideman, 2000a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0022034512453324">b</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0022034512453324">Table 1</xref>). However, the regeneration potential of many of these grafts is limited, suggesting that they might just serve to delay the remodeling that would occur in discectomy alone. Based on current animal studies, there is little evidence to support the advantage of graft material to replace the TMJ disc when compared with discectomy alone. It should also be noted that the described large-animal models are relatively dated (1979-2006), and the porcine model has recently been regarded as the best model for the human TMJ and should be considered in future large-animal studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0022034512453324">Herring, 2003</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0022034512453324">Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0022034512453324">
<title>Clinical Findings</title>
<sec id="section6-0022034512453324">
<title>Recent Investigations (past 10 years)</title>
<sec id="section7-0022034512453324">
<title>Discectomy Alone</title>
<p>While notable findings have been published prior to 2002, such as comparisons between the effectiveness of discectomy and other surgical techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0022034512453324">Holmlund <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>), we will focus on the most up-to-date manuscripts for this portion of the review. Several longer term follow-up studies have been performed to determine the impact of discectomy on joint pain and function since 2002 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0022034512453324">Table 2</xref>). Prior to removal of the disc without graft replacement, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), arthrography, and arthrotomography have been used to confirm disc displacement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0022034512453324">Bjornland and Larheim, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0022034512453324">Nyberg et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0022034512453324">Miloro and Henriksen, 2010</xref>). It has been shown that discectomy alone does result in an increase in chewing ability as well as a decrease in joint pain after 1- to 10-year follow-up (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0022034512453324">Bjornland and Larheim, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0022034512453324">Nyberg <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0022034512453324">Miloro and Henriksen, 2010</xref>). A significant increase in maximal mouth-opening ability following surgery has also been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0022034512453324">Bjornland and Larheim, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0022034512453324">Miloro and Henriksen, 2010</xref>). The most notable negative finding following surgery has been crepitus, or joint noise (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0022034512453324">Bjornland and Larheim, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0022034512453324">Nyberg <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0022034512453324">Miloro and Henriksen, 2010</xref>). Studies have also been performed comparing discectomy with other common surgical interventions. Hall <italic>et al</italic>. did a prospective comparison of 4 TMJ operations – arthroscopy, condylotomy, discectomy, and disc repositioning – revealing that pain relief was significant at 1 mo post-surgery and statistically indistinguishable among procedures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0022034512453324">Hall <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>). The visual analogue scale chewing score as well as vertical range of motion (opening between the incisors) were improved at 1 yr and indistinguishable by operation. The results of this study call into question the superiority of discectomy as a treatment method for painful TMD over less-invasive procedures.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0022034512453324" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Clinical Studies for Discectomy, Describing the Graft Material Used, Sex, Age, Study Size, Longest Time-point Assessed, and Whether a Bilateral/Unilateral Surgery Was Performed</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0022034512453324" xlink:href="10.1177_0022034512453324-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Graft</th>
<th align="center">Sex</th>
<th align="center">Mean Age (yrs)</th>
<th align="center">n=</th>
<th align="center">Longest Follow-up Time</th>
<th align="center">Indication for Surgery</th>
<th align="center">Bilateral/Unilateral</th>
<th align="center">Post-operative Treatment</th>
<th align="center">First Author</th>
<th align="center">Year</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>None</td>
<td>m = 3</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>5 yrs</td>
<td>Disc displacement, unsuccessful non-surgical treatment for at least 6 mos</td>
<td>Unilateral</td>
<td>Physiotherapy</td>
<td>Nyberg <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>2004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>f = 12</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>None</td>
<td>m = 2</td>
<td>36.3</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>60 mos</td>
<td>Pain, dysfunction, disc displacement, lack of improvement with non-surgical therapies</td>
<td>Both</td>
<td>Soft food diet for 4-6 wks, self-administered opening motion exercises at 1 wk after surgery,change/</td>
<td>Miloro <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>2010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>f = 28</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Self-directed physical therapy</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>None</td>
<td>m = 5</td>
<td>37.2</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>10 yrs</td>
<td>Reduced mandibular motion, pain and dysfunction not alleviated by non-surgical treatments, disc displacement with or without reduction</td>
<td>Both</td>
<td>Soft food diet 14 days post-operatively</td>
<td>Bjornland <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>2003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>f = 24</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>Physical therapy</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>None</td>
<td>92-100% female</td>
<td>30.8-41.7</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>1 yr</td>
<td>Internal derangement and intolerable pain after standard medical treatment</td>
<td>Both</td>
<td>ROM exercises, splints, physical therapy, and/or home exercises depending on surgery</td>
<td>Hall <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>2005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dermis</td>
<td>m = 4</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>79 mos</td>
<td>Severe internal derangement, pain and dysfunction not responding to at least 6 mos of non-surgical treatment</td>
<td>Both</td>
<td>Physiotherapy beginning 10 days after surgery</td>
<td>Dimitroulis</td>
<td>2005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>f = 25</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dermis-fat</td>
<td>m = 1</td>
<td>51.5</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>7 yrs</td>
<td>Severe internal derangement not responding to at least 6 mos of preliminary treatment measures</td>
<td>Both</td>
<td>Physical therapy beginning 7 days after surgery</td>
<td>Dimitroulis</td>
<td>2011</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>f = 27</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dermis-fat</td>
<td>Post-surgical</td>
<td>Post-surgical</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>6 yrs</td>
<td>Intolerable joint pain and dysfunction not responding to at least 6 mos of non-surgical treatment</td>
<td>Unilateral</td>
<td/>
<td>Dimitroulis <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>2010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>m = 1</td>
<td>45.4</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>f = 31</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Pre-surgical</td>
<td>Pre-surgical</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>m = 3</td>
<td>41.6</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>f = 26</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Auricular Cartilage</td>
<td>m = 1</td>
<td>41.1 Discectomy</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>1 yr</td>
<td>Intra-articular pathology and unsuccessful non-surgical treatment for at least 6 mos</td>
<td>Both</td>
<td>Pharmacotherapy and physical therapy</td>
<td>Krug <italic>et al</italic>.</td>
<td>2004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>f = 32</td>
<td>27.6 Discoplasty</td>
<td>Discectomy</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>11 Discoplasty</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>The discussed studies indicate an overall positive longer term response to discectomy in a majority of patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0022034512453324">Bjornland and Larheim, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0022034512453324">Nyberg <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0022034512453324">Hall <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0022034512453324">Miloro and Henriksen, 2010</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0022034512453324">Table 2</xref>). However, a limitation of the clinical studies is the use of a small number of patients with various clinical backgrounds. While the literature generally describes the indication for surgery as internal derangement with pain and/or dysfunction unresponsive to non-surgical treatments, specific details regarding the origin of the disorder are often unavailable. While exclusion criteria were used in these studies to help homogenize the patient population, there are inherent discrepancies in patient age and history which will affect the results. The use of a small number of surgeons calls into question whether the findings were the result of the skill of the surgeon or the effectiveness of the procedure itself.</p>
<p>Variations in post-surgical treatment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0022034512453324">Table 2</xref>) can also have a substantial impact on the overall success of discectomy. In the discussed clinical studies, some form of physical therapy and/or soft food diet was always utilized following the discectomy procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0022034512453324">Bjornland and Larheim, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0022034512453324">Nyberg <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0022034512453324">Hall <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0022034512453324">Miloro and Henriksen, 2010</xref>). It is important to take into account the possibility that physical therapy as well as the implementation of a soft food diet immediately following surgery could affect the remodeling process, limiting the comparability of clinical results with those from animal studies, where such post-surgical therapies are rarely used.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0022034512453324">
<title>Discectomy and Graft</title>
<p>While many surgeons perform discectomy alone, several clinicians opt for the placement of autogenous grafts between the condyle and skull. Dimitroulis <italic>et al</italic>. examined the effect of discectomy with autogenous dermis used as an immediate interpositional graft in patients with advanced internal derangement of the TMJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0022034512453324">Dimitroulis, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0022034512453324">2011a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0022034512453324">Dimitroulis <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). According to the visual analogue scale, there was a 66% improvement in pain and a 42% improvement in mandibular function following surgery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0022034512453324">Dimitroulis, 2005</xref>). Orthopantomograms were used to examine the morphology of the condylar head, revealing that the graft did not prevent remodeling of the joint, and that the only advantage of the graft is the elimination of crepitus when compared with discectomy alone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0022034512453324">Dimitroulis, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0022034512453324">2011b</xref>). However, it was shown that discectomy with dermis graft replacement does result in a statistically significant improvement in pain, diet and chewing, mood, anxiety, and general health in the post-surgical group when compared with the presurgical group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0022034512453324">Dimitroulis <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Discectomy with auricular cartilage graft replacement has also resulted in a significant reduction in pain and a significant increase in maximum interincisal distance at 1 yr post-surgery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0022034512453324">Krug <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>These studies show that the use of autogenous graft material may help to reduce the onset of crepitus resulting from discectomy alone, while also delaying degeneration. However, there is still little evidence to support the long-term benefit of these interpositional materials when compared with those of discectomy alone. This should be further examined to validate the use of these grafts and justify the additional donor site morbidity. Furthermore, imaging modalities should be utilized more frequently and consistently to observe joint remodeling in response to discectomy with and without graft replacement, and not solely for diagnosis.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0022034512453324">
<title>Imaging to Assess Surgical Outcomes</title>
<sec id="section10-0022034512453324">
<title>Discectomy Alone</title>
<p>Unfortunately, none of the recent studies describing discectomy alone used imaging for assessing the joint response following surgery. For a more effective comparison of the results from animal studies with clinical findings, this section will focus on discectomy studies published since the year 1985 where imaging was used as an assessment tool to investigate structural changes that occur in the TMJ after discectomy. These imaging techniques include radiography, arthrography, tomography, and MRI. MRI has gained popularity as a diagnostic tool for TMD patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0022034512453324">Schellhas <italic>et al</italic>., 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0022034512453324">1989a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0022034512453324">Schellhas, 1989</xref>). Studies have shown that MRI is useful at predicting certain pathologies in the joint, such as degeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0022034512453324">Schellhas <italic>et al</italic>., 1992</xref>), bone remodeling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0022034512453324">Yabuta <italic>et al</italic>., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0022034512453324">Dimitroulis, 2005</xref>), internal derangement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0022034512453324">Takaku <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>), synovial chondromatosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022034512453324">Chen <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>), exostosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0022034512453324">Takaku <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>), hard tissue changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0022034512453324">Flygare <italic>et al</italic>., 1997</xref>), disc perforation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0022034512453324">Yabuta <italic>et al</italic>., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0022034512453324">Takaku <italic>et al</italic>., 1995</xref>), osteochondritis dissecans or avascular necrosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0022034512453324">Schellhas <italic>et al</italic>., 1989b</xref>), and risk factors for surgery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0022034512453324">Kirk, 1998</xref>). However, the use of MRI still requires careful interpretation when used as a diagnostic tool, since tissues can easily be misrepresented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0022034512453324">Petersson <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>). Case studies also demonstrate the usefulness of imaging techniques for more atypical diagnoses such as identifying metallic foreign bodies in the joint (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0022034512453324">Persson <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>), ossified discs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0022034512453324">Shibuya <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>), or synovial chondromatosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0022034512453324">Shibuya <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>There is conflicting evidence regarding the effect of discectomy on degenerative changes in the TMJ. While it has been reported that discectomy alone results in no radiographic changes in the joint (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0022034512453324">Mazzonetto and Spagnoli, 2001</xref>), there are many studies describing radiographic evidence of joint remodeling following discectomy. These results are consistent with the changes in morphology observed in the discussed animal studies. This remodeling often presents itself as flattening of the condyle and/or fossa, sclerosis, and the presence of osteophytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022034512453324">Eriksson and Westesson, 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0022034512453324">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0022034512453324">Takaku and Toyoda, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0022034512453324">Widmark <italic>et al</italic>., 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0022034512453324">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0022034512453324">Widmark, 1997</xref>). It has also been shown that new tissue formation occurs between the condyle and fossa following discectomy, possibly acting as a “pseudodisc” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0022034512453324">Takaku <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>). There are conflicting results regarding the correlation between radiographic changes in the joint structure and pain following surgery. While there is generally a reduction in pain following the surgical removal of the disc, patients with pain after discectomy exhibited signs of fibrous adhesions on MRI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0022034512453324">Westesson <italic>et al</italic>., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0022034512453324">Hansson <italic>et al</italic>., 1992</xref>). Similarly, while it has been reported that discectomy alone results in adaptive remodeling of the joint that does not interfere with overall surgical success in terms of pain and function, a positive correlation between patients’ overall pain and radiographic scores has also been observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0022034512453324">Widmark <italic>et al</italic>., 1997</xref>). Changes such as narrowing of the joint space and osteophyte formation are accompanied by increased aggrecan/cartilage oligomeric matrix protein, indicating that this remodeling process may lead to osteoarthritis of the joint (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0022034512453324">Flygare <italic>et al</italic>., 1997</xref>). Furthermore, conflicting results also exist as to whether unilateral discectomy results in morphological changes in the opposing joint. Widmark <italic>et al</italic>. found moderate to severe osteoarthrotic changes mostly confined to the operated side of the joint (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0022034512453324">Widmark <italic>et al</italic>., 1996</xref>). However, Takaku and Toyoda found that bony changes were present in non-operated joints at an average follow-up of 20 yrs post-surgery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0022034512453324">Takaku and Toyoda, 1994</xref>). The overall impact of discectomy on the development of pain and osteoarthritis remains controversial.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0022034512453324">
<title>Discectomy and Graft</title>
<p>While a majority of the discectomy studies that used imaging as an assessment focused on discectomy without graft replacement, synthetic graft replacements, such as silicone sheets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0022034512453324">Schliephake <italic>et al</italic>., 1999</xref>), have been used and resulted in little improvement in joint function following surgery. Polytetrafluoroethylene disc replacements resulted in severe radiographic changes in the joint as well as foreign body giant cell reaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0022034512453324">Florine <italic>et al</italic>., 1988</xref>). The use of Proplast Teflon interpositional implants also resulted in symptomatic joints with condylar resorption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0022034512453324">Spagnoli and Kent, 1992</xref>) as well as implant migration and fragmentation accompanied by severe condylar, glenoid fossa, and eminence remodeling changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0022034512453324">Heffez <italic>et al</italic>., 1987</xref>). Similarly, Dacron-reinforced silicone caused bone destruction and foreign body response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0022034512453324">Westesson <italic>et al</italic>., 1987</xref>).</p>
<p>Fewer studies with imaging as an assessment tool are available to describe morphological changes in the joint following discectomy with autograft replacement. Dermis grafting has been shown to result in a reduction of pain, increase in function, decrease in crepitus, and increase in quality of life following surgery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0022034512453324">Dimitroulis, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0022034512453324">Dimitroulis <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). However, dermal grafts could not be detected by MRI at 6 to 23 mos post-surgery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0022034512453324">Lieberman <italic>et al</italic>., 1990</xref>). Because of the wide use of autografts for TMJ disc replacement, more studies with imaging as an assessment tool are needed to validate the use of these materials and their ability to prevent osteoarthritis in the joint.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0022034512453324">
<title>Inferences from Pre-clinical Animal Models to Human Findings</title>
<p>The discussed discectomy and discectomy with graft replacement studies provide insight into the predictive power of animal models for projecting changes in human joints. Many of the studies with imaging to assess the TMJ after discectomy are consistent with the findings observed in animal models, with both exhibiting adaptive remodeling of the articulating surfaces of the joint, mainly destruction or resorption of the cartilage, with changes in joint function.</p>
<p>The recent clinical studies showed that the mean age in years of patients receiving discectomy was in the 30s and early 40s, with the majority being female. Although the authors of the longer term clinical studies reported generally positive outcomes from discectomy with and without graft replacement, it is important to note that many of the patients still suffered from different degrees of pain and joint dysfunction, and no imaging was performed to assess the healing of the TMJ. The lack of imaging makes it hard to compare the recent results with those from the animal models.</p>
<p>The discussed discectomy models in rabbits, sheep, and monkeys have focused on gross morphological/histological assessments, and were not designed to characterize the fundamental altered joint movement (kinematics) driving degeneration, or the functional consequences. While clinical results provide relevant information regarding pain and end-of-range motion, more radiographic evidence is needed for a closer examination of changes in joint structure and the path of joint movement that occur, especially with the use of grafting material. Imaging modalities should be utilized more consistently in both animal and human studies to help quantify changes in joint kinematics.</p>
<p>The discectomy and use of graft replacement results seen in animals tend to mirror those seen in humans. There is a general consensus that the use of graft material does retard the onset of degenerative changes in the joint. However, the currently used graft materials in both animals and humans have a short lifespan, and there is little evidence to support the long-term benefit of these interpositional materials. The limited success of autogenous graft material, as well as the additional site morbidity required by their use, reaffirms the need for tissue-engineered devices to regenerate the lost disc, restore mobility, reduce pain, and eliminate the onset of crepitus. In conclusion, animal models provide valuable insight into the joint changes that occur as a result of discectomy, and should be considered as an essential step in the validation of tissue-engineered disc replacements for the treatment of patients requiring a discectomy.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>We gratefully acknowledge the University of Pittsburgh School of Dental Medicine as well as funding from the National Science Foundation under Grant No. 0812348.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The authors declare no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the authorship and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Almarza</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hagandora</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Animal models of temporomandibular joint disorders: implications for tissue engineering approaches</article-title>. <source>Ann Biomed Eng</source> <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>2479</fpage>-<lpage>2490</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bjornland</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haanaes</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Discectomy of the temporomandibular joint: an experimental study in monkeys</article-title>. <source>J Craniomaxillofac Surg</source> <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>-<lpage>116</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bjornland</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larheim</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Discectomy of the temporomandibular joint: 3-year follow-up as a predictor of the 10-year outcome</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Synovial chondromatosis in the inferior compartment of the temporomandibular joint: different stages with different treatments</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>E32</fpage>-<lpage>E38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dimitroulis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The use of dermis grafts after discectomy for internal derangement of the temporomandibular joint</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>-<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dimitroulis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011a</year>). <article-title>Condylar morphology after temporomandibular joint discectomy with interpositional abdominal dermis-fat graft</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>439</fpage>-<lpage>446</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dimitroulis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011b</year>). <article-title>A critical review of interpositional grafts following temporomandibular joint discectomy with an overview of the dermis-fat graft</article-title>. <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>-<lpage>568</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dimitroulis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slavin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The effects of unilateral discectomy and condylectomy on the contralateral intact rabbit craniomandibular joint</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>1261</fpage>-<lpage>1266</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dimitroulis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCullough</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Quality-of-life survey comparing patients before and after discectomy of the temporomandibular joint</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westesson</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Diskectomy in the treatment of anterior disk displacement of the temporomandibular joint. A clinical and radiologic one-year follow-up study</article-title>. <source>J Prosthet Dent</source> <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>106</fpage>-<lpage>116</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westesson</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Discectomy as an effective treatment for painful temporomandibular joint internal derangement: a 5-year clinical and radiographic follow-up</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>750</fpage>-<lpage>758</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Farrar</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCarty</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>The TMJ dilemma</article-title>. <source>J Ala Dent Assoc</source> <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feinberg</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McDonnell</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The use of a collagen sheet as a disc replacement in the rabbit temporomandibular joint</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>535</fpage>-<lpage>542</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Florine</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gatto</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Waite</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Tomographic evaluation of temporomandibular joints following discoplasty or placement of polytetrafluoroethylene implants</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flygare</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saxne</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ericson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petersson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Cartilage matrix macromolecules in lavage fluid of temporomandibular joints before and 6 months after diskectomy</article-title>. <source>Eur J Oral Sci</source> <volume>105</volume>:<fpage>369</fpage>-<lpage>372</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gerstner</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Chewing rate allometry among mammals</article-title>. <source>J Mammalogy</source> <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>1020</fpage>-<lpage>1030</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Indresano</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Prospective multicenter comparison of 4 temporomandibular joint operations</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>1174</fpage>-<lpage>1179</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hansson</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westesson</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Magnetic-resonance evaluation after temporomandibular-joint diskectomy</article-title>. <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol</source> <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>801</fpage>-<lpage>810</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heffez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mafee</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>CT evaluation of TMJ disc replacement with a Proplast-Teflon laminate</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>657</fpage>-<lpage>665</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Herring</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>TMJ anatomy and animal models</article-title>. <source>J Musculoskelet Neuronal Interact</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>391</fpage>-<lpage>394</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holmlund</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Axelsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gynther</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>A comparison of discectomy and arthroscopic lysis and lavage for the treatment of chronic closed lock of the temporomandibular joint: a randomized outcome study</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>972</fpage>-<lpage>977</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ioannides</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maltha</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988a</year>). <article-title>Lyophilized auricular cartilage as a replacement for the interarticular disc of the craniomandibular joint. An experimental study in guinea pigs</article-title>. <source>J Craniomaxillofac Surg</source> <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>-<lpage>300</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ioannides</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maltha</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988b</year>). <article-title>Replacement of the interarticular disc of the craniomandibular joint with fresh autogenous sternal or auricular cartilage. An experimental study in guinea pigs</article-title>. <source>J Craniomaxillofac Surg</source> <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>343</fpage>-<lpage>349</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Risk factors and initial surgical failures of TMJ arthrotomy and arthroplasty: a four to nine year evaluation of 303 surgical procedures</article-title>. <source>Cranio</source> <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>154</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krug</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jirousek</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Suchmova</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cermakova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Influence of discoplasty and discectomy of the temporomandibular joint on elimination of pain and restricted mouth opening</article-title>. <source>Acta Medica (Hradec Kralove)</source> <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bradrick</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Indresano</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bellon</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Dermal grafts of the temporomandibular joint: postoperative appearance on MR images</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source> <volume>176</volume>:<fpage>199</fpage>-<lpage>203</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mazzonetto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spagnoli</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Long-term evaluation of arthroscopic discectomy of the temporomandibular joint using the holmium YAG laser</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>1018</fpage>-<lpage>1023</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Miloro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henriksen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Discectomy as the primary surgical option for internal derangement of the temporomandibular joint</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>782</fpage>-<lpage>789</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>NIH</collab> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>TMJ disorders</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Bethesda, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NIH Publication No</publisher-name>. <fpage>10</fpage>-<lpage>3487</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nyberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Temporomandibular joint discectomy for treatment of unilateral internal derangements—a 5 year follow-up evaluation</article-title>. <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gjerdet</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tornes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Metal fragment in the temporomandibular joint: a case report</article-title>. <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>653</fpage>-<lpage>655</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Petersson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westesson</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>MR images mimic disc after discectomy</article-title>. <source>Dentomaxillofac Radiol</source> <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>239</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Motegi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002a</year>). <article-title>Changes of the elastic fibre network of the rabbit temporomandibular joint following discectomy</article-title>. <source>J Oral Rehabil</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>847</fpage>-<lpage>852</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Motegi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002b</year>). <article-title>Changes of the collagen fibre arrangement of the rabbit temporomandibular joint following discectomy</article-title>. <source>J Craniomaxillofac Surg</source> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>178</fpage>-<lpage>183</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schellhas</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Internal derangement of the temporomandibular joint: radiologic staging with clinical, surgical, and pathologic correlation</article-title>. <source>Magn Reson Imaging</source> <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>495</fpage>-<lpage>515</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schellhas</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilkes</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Omlie</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keck</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>The diagnosis of temporomandibular joint disease: two-compartment arthrography and MR</article-title>. <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source> <volume>151</volume>:<fpage>341</fpage>-<lpage>350</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schellhas</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilkes</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989a</year>). <article-title>Facial pain, headache, and temporomandibular joint inflammation</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>232</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schellhas</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilkes</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fritts</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Omlie</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lagrotteria</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989b</year>). <article-title>MR of osteochondritis dissecans and avascular necrosis of the mandibular condyle</article-title>. <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source> <volume>152</volume>:<fpage>551</fpage>-<lpage>560</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schellhas</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Piper</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Omlie</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Facial skeleton remodeling due to temporomandibular-joint degeneration – an imaging study of 100 patients (reprinted from AJNR 11:41-555, 1990)</article-title>. <source>Cranio</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>248</fpage>-<lpage>259</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schliephake</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmelzeisen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maschek</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haese</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Long-term results of the use of silicone sheets after diskectomy in the temporomandibular joint: clinical, radiographic and histopathologic findings</article-title>. <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>-<lpage>329</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shibuya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amagasa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Synovial chondromatosis of the left temporomandibular joint superficially resembling chondrosarcoma: a case report</article-title>. <source>Cranio</source> <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>286</fpage>-<lpage>288</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shibuya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Synovial osteochondromatosis accompanying an ossified articular disk in the temporomandibular joint: a case report</article-title>. <source>J Oral Pathol Med</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>441</fpage>-<lpage>442</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spagnoli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Multicenter evaluation of temporomandibular-joint Proplast-Teflon disk implant</article-title>. <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol</source> <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>411</fpage>-<lpage>421</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Takaku</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toyoda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Long-term evaluation of discectomy of the temporomandibular joint</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>722</fpage>-<lpage>726</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Takaku</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toyoda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heishiki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Correlation of magnetic resonance imaging and surgical findings in patients with temporomandibular joint disorders</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1283</fpage>-<lpage>1288</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Takaku</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toyoda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>A comparison between magnetic resonance imaging and pathologic findings in patients with disc displacement</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>-<lpage>176</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Takaku</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Long-term magnetic resonance imaging after temporomandibular joint discectomy without replacement</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>739</fpage>-<lpage>745</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Takatsuka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Narinobou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Histologic evaluation of auricular cartilage grafts after discectomy in the rabbit craniomandibular joint</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>1216</fpage>-<lpage>1225</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thyne</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luyk</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Temporalis muscle as a disc replacement in the temporomandibular joint of sheep</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>979</fpage>-<lpage>987</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tideman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000a</year>). <article-title>A comparative study on meniscectomy and autogenous graft replacement of the rhesus monkey temporomandibular joint articular disc—Part I</article-title>. <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>140</fpage>-<lpage>145</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tideman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000b</year>). <article-title>A comparative study on meniscectomy and autogenous graft replacement of the rhesus monkey temporomandibular joint articular disc—Part II</article-title>. <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>146</fpage>-<lpage>154</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kennady</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacoway</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Autogenous auricular cartilage implantation following discectomy in the primate temporomandibular joint</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>38</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Westesson</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Destructive lesions of the mandibular condyle following diskectomy with temporary silicone implant</article-title>. <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol</source> <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>-<lpage>150</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Westesson</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tallents</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Magnetic-resonance-imaging of temporomandibular-joint after surgical-treatment of internal derangement</article-title>. <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol</source> <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>407</fpage>-<lpage>411</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Widmark</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>On surgical intervention in the temporomandibular joint</article-title>. <source>Swed Dent J Suppl</source> <volume>123</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>87</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Widmark</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grondahl</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kahnberg</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haraldson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Radiographic morphology in the temporomandibular joint after diskectomy</article-title>. <source>Cranio</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Widmark</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dahlstrom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kahnberg</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindvall</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Diskectomy in temporomandibular joints with internal derangement – A follow-up study</article-title>. <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source> <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>314</fpage>-<lpage>320</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yabuta</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sakuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Diagnostic arthroscopy of temporomandibular joint on outpatient. Review of 47 examinations, 40 cases</article-title>. <source>J Osaka Univ Dent Sch</source> <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0022034512453324">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yaillen</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luschei</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Temporomandibular joint meniscectomy—effects on joint structure and masticatory function in <italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic></article-title>. <source>J Maxillofac Surg</source> <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>-<lpage>264</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>