<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjsr</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Service Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1094-6705</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7379</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1094670511428166</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1094670511428166</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Spectator Rage as the Dark Side of Engaging Sport Fans</article-title>
<subtitle>Implications for Services Marketers</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grove</surname>
<given-names>Stephen J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1094670511428166">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Pickett</surname>
<given-names>Gregory M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1094670511428166">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1094670511428166"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>Scott A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1094670511428166">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dorsch</surname>
<given-names>Michael J.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1094670511428166">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1094670511428166">
<label>1</label>Department of Marketing, Clemson University, Clemson, SC, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1094670511428166">
<label>2</label>Department of Marketing, Stetson University, DeLand, FL, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1094670511428166">Gregory M. Pickett, College of Business and Behavioral Science, Clemson University, 165 Sirrine Hall Clemson, SC 29634, USA. Email: <email>pgregor@clemson.edu</email>
</corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1094670511428166">
<p>
<bold>Stephen J. Grove</bold> is a professor of Marketing at Clemson University (Clemson, SC, USA). His published articles have appeared in the <italic>Journal of Retailing, Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science, Journal of Services Research, The Service Industries Journal, Journal of Services Marketing,</italic>
<italic>Managing Service Quality, Journal of Public Policy and Marketing, Journal of Advertising, Journal of Advertising Research, Journal of Macromarketing, Journal of Business Research,</italic> and others. He is the coauthor of the text, <italic>Interactive Services Marketing</italic> (Cengage Publishing) and the book, <italic>Services Marketing Self- Portraits: Introspections, Reflections and Glimpses from the Experts</italic> (American Marketing Association).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1094670511428166">
<p>
<bold>Scott A. Jones</bold> is an assistant professor of Marketing in the School of Business Administration at Stetson University (DeLand, FL, USA). Dr. Jones has published more than 25 intellectual contributions including manuscripts in the <italic>Journal of Public Policy and Marketing</italic>, the <italic>Journal of Internet Commerce,</italic> and the <italic>Sport Marketing Quarterly</italic>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1094670511428166">
<p>
<bold>Gregory M. Pickett</bold> is an associate dean, College of Business and Behavioral Science at Clemson University (Clemson, SC, USA). His research has been widely published in numerous marketing/business journals, including <italic>Journal of Business Research</italic>, <italic>Journal of Services</italic>
<italic>Research</italic>, <italic>Journal of Services Marketing</italic>, <italic>Services Industry Journal, Journal of Marketing Education, Journal of Advertising</italic>, <italic>European Journal of</italic>
<italic>Marketing</italic>, <italic>Journal of Personal Selling and Sales Management, Sport Marketing Quarterly</italic> and <italic>Journal of Public</italic>
<italic>Policy and Marketing</italic>, among others. His most recent research interests are focused on Sport Marketing issues, specifically, spectator rage, the downside of sponsoring teams and/or individual players that engender strong feelings among fans and the perceived pricing fairness of sport concessions.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1094670511428166">
<p>
<bold>Michael J. Dorsch</bold> is a professor of Marketing at Clemson University (Clemson, SC, USA). His primary research interests pertain to services marketing, customer loyalty, and research methodology. His research is published in journals such as the <italic>Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science</italic>, the <italic>Journal of Business Research</italic>, the <italic>Journal of Advertising</italic>, the <italic>Journal of Services Marketing</italic>, the <italic>Journal of Personal Selling and Sales Management</italic>, the <italic>Journal of Macromarketing</italic>, the <italic>European Journal of Marketing</italic>, the <italic>Services Industry Journal</italic>, the <italic>Journal of Travel Researc</italic>h, among others. His honors include Best Journal Article Awards, Outstanding Journal Reviewer Awards, and recognition for quality teaching.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>20</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Customer rage is a complex phenomenon that is beginning to receive attention from researchers and practitioners. To date, research into the phenomenon has focused exclusively on its occurrence within a failed service context; however, rage may also occur in nonfailure situations as a negative by-product of an organization’s efforts to engage the customer at an emotional level. As a service entity, the live sporting event is characterized by a number of features which make it particularly susceptible to acts of rage. This article examines rage within the context of spectator sport by utilizing a framework that is capable of organizing and focusing attention upon those factors that shape a fan’s consumption experience and render spectator sport, and services in general, susceptible to rage. Services marketers may be unable to eliminate all incidents of spectator rage, especially those that arise when a customer becomes excessively and emotionally absorbed with the service encounter. Nevertheless, fans’ propensity to rage may be reduced by understanding the factors that contribute to it and by carefully designing servicescapes and vigilantly managing customer interactions to generate exhilarating, yet nonaggressive, customer experiences.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>spectator sport</kwd>
<kwd>spectator rage</kwd>
<kwd>fan rage</kwd>
<kwd>sport marketing</kwd>
<kwd>service marketing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Incidents of customer rage have become more prevalent in recent years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1094670511428166">Grainer 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-1094670511428166">McColl-Kennedy et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr102-1094670511428166">Shellenbarger 2010</xref>), yet relatively little is known about the phenomenon or how to diffuse it. Extant research documents its existence and focus attention on rage incidents related to service failures (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1094670511428166">Grove, Fisk, and John 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1094670511428166">Kalamas, Laroche, and Makdessian 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-1094670511428166">McColl-Kennedy et al. 2009</xref>). However, rage may also occur in situations when service delivery does not fail, for example, when a restaurant employee refuses to serve lunch during breakfast hours (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr102-1094670511428166">Schellenbarger 2010</xref>). Such occurrences are perhaps even more perplexing than rage incidents linked to service delivery breakdowns. The limited understanding of customer rage, including is antecedents and consequences, make most companies ill-equipped to manage this potentially dangerous phenomenon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1094670511428166">Grove, Fisk, and John 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-1094670511428166">McColl-Kennedy et al. 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>We propose that customer rage emerges as an undesirable by-product of customer engagement in the service. Through customer engagement, patrons cocreate customer value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1094670511428166">Lusch and Vargo 2006</xref>) that customizes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr114-1094670511428166">van Doorn et al. 2010</xref>) and personalizes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-1094670511428166">Prahalad and Ramaswamy 2000</xref>) the customer-to-brand experience. Consequently, even if the service performance is flawless, customer rage can still arise from an unfavorable experience resulting from customer- or context-related factors. Whereas research examines rage as a consequence of service failure, less is known about its occurrence within service contexts designed to engage customers at an emotional level.</p>
<p>Spectator sport is multisensory phenomenon that evokes a range of emotional responses, including rage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1094670511428166">Hirschman and Holbrook 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1094670511428166">King, Kahle, and Close 2011</xref>). As such, rage at sporting events has been examined in various disciplines; however, it has received relatively little attention by marketers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1094670511428166">Hunt, Bristol, and Bashaw 1999</xref>). This is unfortunate since fan rage has potentially significant implications for sport marketers, both financially and socially. To gain an understanding of both customer and spectator rage, we examine rage as a negative by-product of an emotionally engaged customer. Specifically, our study addresses the following research questions: What factors contribute to the occurrence of spectator rage, even when the service itself (i.e., the sporting event) is performed flawlessly and what are the implications associated with these factors for enhancing the understanding customer rage within services, in general? By examining the incidences of customer rage within the context of spectator sport, we contribute to the rage literature by introducing a framework that illuminates the complexity of the phenomenon by depicting factors and dynamics that characterize spectator rage specifically and customer range in general. We also shed light on the diversity of controllable and uncontrollable factors that may prompt rage across service industries, whether it is triggered by service failure or other dynamics.</p>
<p>In the following sections, we establish that customer rage may arise as a negative by-product within the emotionally engaging service context of spectator sport and propose a model of spectator rage based on an existing customer rage framework. Research propositions associated with the framework are provided, as are theoretical and managerial implications for spectator sport and services, in general.</p>
<sec id="section1-1094670511428166">
<title>Spectator Sport as a Service Business</title>
<p>A customer’s role in the cocreation of value is unmistakable in spectator sport (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1094670511428166">Greyser 2011</xref>) where the live sporting event is the primary product of the sport industry, with various other products (i.e., licensing agreements, broadcast rights, and sponsor relationships) contingent on it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr90-1094670511428166">Mullin, Hardy, and Sutton 2000</xref>). While the size of the spectator sport industry is difficult to accurately estimate, one source states that spectator spending (e.g., ticket sales, concessions, and travel) in the United States is approximately $26 billion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr112-1094670511428166">
<italic>Street and Smith’s Sport Business Journal</italic> 2002</xref>). In 2009, about 75 million people attended a regular season Major League Baseball game and 17 million spectators attended a regular season National Football League (NFL) contest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1094670511428166">ESPN.go.com 2010</xref>). Clearly, any circumstance such as the occurrence of customer rage that undermines the attractiveness of sporting contests may have deleterious consequences for various stakeholders.</p>
<p>Spectator sport is a service industry in which a set of intangible actions are directed at consumer’ minds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1094670511428166">Lovelock 1983</xref>). Even though spectator sport does not readily lend itself to customization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1094670511428166">Lovelock 1983</xref>), fans are increasingly interested in personalizing their experiences just as customers are with any good or service (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-1094670511428166">Prahalad and Ramaswamy 2000</xref>). Companies that successfully engage and emotionally satisfy customers tend to be rewarded with superlative outcomes in terms of top-line and bottom-line performance and relationship growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1094670511428166">Fleming, Coffman, and Harter 2005</xref>). The importance and predominance of customer engagement in spectator sport has led to claims that fans represent the heart and soul of sport and sport properties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1094670511428166">Greyser 2011</xref>); that sport fans differ from other types of customers in the magnitude of emotion and depth of affiliation that characterizes their sporting experiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1094670511428166">King, Kahle, and Close 2011</xref>); and, that the interactive aspect of fan experiences is a key driver of service quality with respect to spectator sport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1094670511428166">Ko et al. 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Like services, in general, spectator sporting events are comprised of four key components that combine to create a service encounter: a setting (the sport venue), employees (the athletes and the venue staff), the service performance (the athletic contest and all of the facets of its staging within the venue), and customers (the spectators). Each of these has the potential to impact spectators’ experience and perception of excellence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1094670511428166">Fisk, Grove, and John 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1094670511428166">Langeard et al. 1981</xref>). In this study, we use the terms spectator or fan interchangeably to identify an individual who is physically present at a live sporting event (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr122-1094670511428166">Wenner and Gantz 1998</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1094670511428166">
<title>Customer Rage and Spectator Rage: An Overview Customer Rage</title>
<p>Customer rage is a strong negative and antisocial emotion, an intense anger that manifests itself in numerous ways, including verbal, physical, nonverbal, and displaced aggression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1094670511428166">Deffenbacher et al. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-1094670511428166">McColl-Kennedy et al. 2009</xref>). Some argue that rage is distinguished from other forms of anger because it is a stronger or more pronounced emotion (Kalamas, Laroche, and Makdessian 2007). Consistent with this conceptualization, we use the term rage to broadly represent a behavioral response that is intensely negative, antisocial, and displays hostility, ferocity, hate, and the like. Hence, customer rage consists of an affective state and a behavioral response. The former involves the fore mentioned negative, antisocial emotions, while the latter typically represents the overt expression of those emotions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-1094670511428166">McColl-Kennedy et al. 2009</xref>) as a means of coping and relieving stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1094670511428166">Lazarus and Folkman 1984</xref>). Feelings of hostility, while deleterious in their own right, are not rage until those feelings lead to actions. Rage may occur in three types of situations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-1094670511428166">Shaver et al 1987</xref>): when something interferes with a person’s execution of plans or attainment of personal goals; when one believes that he or she is being harmed, physically or psychologically, by another; or, when one feels that behavioral interference being experienced is illegitimate and contrary to what ought to be.</p>
<sec id="section3-1094670511428166">
<title>Customer Rage and Services</title>
<p>Customer rage is commonly found in the service sector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1094670511428166">Grove, Fisk, and John 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-1094670511428166">McColl-Kennedy and Smith 2006</xref>) and any of the four components of a service encounter—the workers, the service process, the setting, or the assembly of customers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1094670511428166">Fisk, Grove, and John 2008</xref>)—may prompt it. The creation and delivery of services in real time, combined with both a potentially large number of service inputs that are difficult to control and the limited ability to personalize the service, increases the likelihood and magnitude of an unfavorable customer service experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1094670511428166">Fisk, Grove, and John 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1094670511428166">Lovelock and Wirtz 2011</xref>) that may ultimately result in rage (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1094670511428166">Bougie, Pieters, and Zeelenberg 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr106-1094670511428166">Smith and Bolton 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>Rage is one of many forms of dysfunctional customer behavior that can occur during service delivery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1094670511428166">Fisk et al. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1094670511428166">Fullerton and Punj 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1094670511428166">Harris and Reynolds 2004</xref>). When it does arise, a service patron may become an unwelcomed “jaycustomer” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1094670511428166">Lovelock 1994</xref>), a customer who acts in a thoughtless or abusive manner, creating problems for employees, other customers and the firm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1094670511428166">Harris and Reynolds 2004</xref>). The actions of a raging customer (e.g., yelling, vandalizing, physical assault, etc.) are often disruptive and can undermine the service experience of all other parties involved. Clearly, service organizations would benefit by practices and policies that reduce the likelihood and/or impact of customer rage.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1094670511428166">
<title>Spectator Rage</title>
<p>Consistent with rage’s conceptualization in other contexts, spectator rage refers to violent and uncontrolled acts of aggression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1094670511428166">Coakley 1998</xref>). Moreover, the phenomenon of spectator rage is complex with roots and expression that are difficult to address due to its multifaceted nature. To help comprehend the phenomenon, we employ the broad 4-Ts framework (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1094670511428166">Grove, Fisk, and John 2004</xref>) to organize pertinent issues and provide insights. The framework represents a useful and logical tool, but in no way catalogues all of the specifics pertaining to the phenomenon due to the vast array of particulars pertaining to each of the key issues. Instead, the 4-Ts are offered as a structure to establish the efficacy of the framework to better understand spectator rage. In the following pages, we utilize the framework to investigate key issues related to fan rage and to offer research propositions resulting from our examination. Ultimately, insights gleaned from this activity are offered in terms of their implications for understanding customer rage in general.</p>
<sec id="section5-1094670511428166">
<title>The “4-Ts” Framework for Understanding Spectator Rage</title>
<p>The “4-Ts of Customer Rage” framework (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1094670511428166">Grove, Fisk, and John 2004</xref>) captures the complexity of customer rage and bring attention to services-related issues associated with it. The framework posits that customer rage may be understood by examining the interrelationships among four factors which relate broadly to dysfunctional behavior, in general (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1094670511428166">Fullerton and Punj 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1094670511428166">Keeffe and Russell-Bennett 2006</xref>): the <italic>targets</italic> of consumer rage behavior; the <italic>temperament</italic> of customers that may predispose one to rage; the <italic>triggers</italic> that spark rage behavior; and, the <italic>treatments</italic> for addressing and rage’s occurrence. In this study, we adapt and apply the 4 -Ts framework to discern the unique aspects of rage associated with spectator sport and to develop insights pertaining to customer rage at large. While each of the Ts is addressed separately, it is important to recognize that the four factors may be intricately interrelated (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511428166">Figure 1</xref>
).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1094670511428166" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Framework for understanding spectator rage.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig1-1094670511428166" xlink:href="10.1177_1094670511428166-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<sec id="section6-1094670511428166">
<title>Targets</title>
<p>Live sporting events are characterized by rich and complex interactions among customers (i.e., spectators) and service providers, usually within a well-defined service setting (e.g., stadium). Correspondingly, just as with customer rage in general, a fan who rages may direct his or her anger toward its source within the service context, displace it by transferring it to another object, or attempt to suppress it (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-1094670511428166">McColl-Kennedy et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-1094670511428166">Shaver et al. 1987</xref>). With respect to the latter option, once anger is elicited, cognitive biases and physiological tendencies arise automatically unless one can suppress the emotion through self-control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-1094670511428166">Shaver et al. 1987</xref>). For example, enraged fans may seek to stem their anger by denying their feeling (e.g., telling themselves to get over it or to calm down) or restraining their tendencies to act on it. Unfortunately, an emotion often becomes public before one can successfully control it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-1094670511428166">Shaver et al. 1987</xref>). Hence, it is likely that an enraged fan will express his or her angst by directing or displacing it toward service participants (fans and employees/contestants), aspects of the service setting (stadium) or even the service performance (the athletic contest) itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1094670511428166">Fullerton and Punj 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1094670511428166">Harris and Reynolds 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1094670511428166">Lovelock 1994</xref>), rendering them the targets of fan rage.</p>
<p>As with many services (e.g., hotels and hospitals), the live sporting event typically offers its attendees multiple opportunities to interact with various venue employees that are responsible for creating the spectator experience. Whether they are concessionaires, ticket-takers, security personnel or other personnel, these frontline or boundary-spanning service workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1094670511428166">Bowen and Schneider 1985</xref>) are sometimes easy targets for raging fans. Clearly, that’s the case when such employees provoke fans by their actions (directed rage), yet they may also become targets due to causes for which they are not responsible (displaced rage). The upshot of this is that in the milieu of spectator sport, as in many service contexts, employees are sometimes in harm’s way for spectator rage.</p>
<p>Live sporting events also involve interaction—albeit relatively indirect—between spectators and those participating in a contest itself such as players, coaches, and officials. Indeed, the interaction between spectators and game participants (e.g., cheering, distracting an opponent with noise, shouting at an umpire or official, etc.) is a fundamental component of the spectator sport experience and often there is no separation between the athlete, the entertainment, and the fan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr104-1094670511428166">Shank 2002</xref>, p. 234). Unfortunately, some spectators who are displeased with the on-field performance, event outcome, or officiating may cross the line of civility and sling vulgarities at or, worse yet, physically accost the sport participants. For example, spectators attending the National Association for Stock Car Auto Racing hurled debris (i.e., beer cans) on to the track and in the direction of the winning driver as a show of disfavor toward him (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr100-1094670511428166">Ryan 2007</xref>). Sporting events also offer opportunity for substantial interaction among spectators. Fans at sporting events are often seated very close to one another—a circumstance that sometimes makes one a party to another’s unwelcome verbal and physical behavior. Innocent bystanders’ spectator experience can easily be ruined by others and prompt varied responses, including rage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1094670511428166">Grove and Fisk 1997</xref>; Harris and Reynolds 2003). Even those not directly interacting with a raging fan but simply in his or her proximity may have their spectator experience disrupted or negatively impacted through a contagion effect (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-1094670511428166">Martin and Pranter 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-1094670511428166">McColl-Kennedy and Smith 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>Furthermore, sporting events are typically attended by supporters of the opposing teams or athletes involved in the competition. Obviously, the ideal outcome of a contest may vary substantially based on which team or individual a spectator supports, and interactions among spectators may reflect this conflict of objectives. One or more fans may respond with verbal insults, ugly gestures, and violence toward their counterparts if they become upset with the nature of the contest or its result. When a larger collectivity of fans is involved, these actions on occasion can continue beyond the confines of the stadium or arena and spill out into the community where the public in general may be affected.</p>
<p>In services in general or spectator sport specifically, sometimes the target of an enraged customer’s actions is not another person or persons, but rather the physical setting for the event (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1094670511428166">Fullerton and Punj 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1094670511428166">Harris and Reynolds 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-1094670511428166">McColl-Kennedy and Smith 2006</xref>). Whatever the cause of their anger, spectators have been known to strike out at their surroundings. Ripping seats apart, pounding partitions, marring walls, and damaging the landscape are common expressions of spectator fury. Occasionally, the fury is not rooted in anger but develops as a celebratory expression including traditions such as tearing down of football goal posts, storming the field of play and the like. Regardless, such acts reflect a vandalism response associated with <italic>jaycustomer</italic> behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1094670511428166">Lovelock 1994</xref>) plague service organizations.</p>
<p>Finally, in some instances fans’ ire, particularly when it is a collective expression, can be directed at the athletic contest itself. Athletic contests, like service performances in general, are essentially processes that evolve within a set structure to reach a particular end, that is, declare a winner. When the actual performance deviates too far from the one desired by the fans, their disenchantment with the service performance may turn to intense anger or wrath that spawns sabotage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1094670511428166">Harris and Ogbonna 2008</xref>) of the sporting event itself. Violent displays in the stands, unruly actions toward contestants, vandalism and sundry other displays of collective rage can bring a halt to an athletic contest before its conclusion in the name of safety and sanity. The postponement of Italian soccer matches under such circumstances has occurred (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr109-1094670511428166">Sports Network 2007</xref>). When viewed in whole, it is apparent that <italic>any</italic> component of the service encounter (i.e., employees, customers, service setting, and process) associated with spectator sport (i.e., athletes/staff, fans, stadium, and contest) may become targets of spectator rage. Propositions 1 and 2 address the customer rage targets component depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511428166">Figure 1</xref>.<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 1</italic>: Fans are more likely to engage in rage behavior when they are less skilled at suppressing a felt anger with some aspect of the sporting event.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 2:</italic> Fans are more likely to displace rage when they are (a) unable to identify or (b) unable to interact with, or (c) unwilling to direct their rage toward its source.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1094670511428166">
<title>Temperament</title>
<p>A spectator’s (customer’s) temperament (i.e., personality and/or current state of mind) influences the likelihood that he or she may become enraged at a live sporting event. Spectator sport, like many services, involves an activity that is performed before a large number of customers simultaneously and it should be recognized that some in attendance may be prone to rage. In fact, some fans seem predisposed to rage and appear ready to “go off” with little provocation. For example, a person’s predisposition to rage may be influenced a number of <italic>physiological conditions,</italic> including low levels of serum cholesterol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr108-1094670511428166">Spitz and Hillbrand 1994</xref>) or serotonin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1094670511428166">Brown, Goodwin, and Bunney 1982</xref>), high levels of testosterone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-1094670511428166">
<italic>MyMindField.com</italic> 2007</xref>), and even genetic disposition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1094670511428166">
<italic>APAOnline</italic> 2007</xref>). A susceptibility to rage may also rest with one’s <italic>psychological profile</italic>. For instance, people with passive-aggressive personalities are prone to antagonistic verbal displays and may seek retribution for the slightest of perceived transgressions by other fans or stadium personnel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr111-1094670511428166">Stone 1993</xref>). Similarly, spectators with Type A personalities (i.e., highly competitive, intense achievement orientation) often allow their free-floating hostility to be triggered over minor incidents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1094670511428166">Friedman 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1094670511428166">Holmes and Will 1985</xref>). Even those with borderline personalities marked by feelings of low self-worth, obsessive behavior, and need for assurance can become aggressive and push others to act similarly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1094670511428166">Mahari 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>A sport spectator’s propensity to rage may be attributable to powerful psychological factors as well. Consider the psychological phenomenon of identification, the process of maintaining a positive, self-defining relationship with others that one deems attractive (Kelman 1958, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1094670511428166">1961</xref>). When sport fans consider their favorite team or athlete as an extension of their self (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1094670511428166">End et al. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1094670511428166">Kahle et al. 2001</xref>), their identification becomes a potentially intense psychological orientation, whereby individuals define themselves in terms of their attachment and derive strength and a sense of identity from the affiliation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1094670511428166">Harris and Ogbonna 2008</xref>). When a strong link is formed between a spectator’s favorite sport teams/athletes and his or her self-concept (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1094670511428166">End et al. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1094670511428166">Hunt, Bristol, and Bashaw 1999</xref>), threats (e.g., losing, opponent’s fans, etc.) to the source of their self-concept (i.e., team/athlete) are taken personally. As a result, some fans become enraged in an effort to enhance their identity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1094670511428166">Branscombe and Wann 1994</xref>) or as a defense strategy to restore self-esteem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1094670511428166">Branscombe and Wann 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr117-1094670511428166">Wann et al. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr116-1094670511428166">Wann, McLean, and Pullen 2003</xref>). While few services appear to provide a strong impetus for customer identification and self-concept enhancement as spectator sport, some examples do exist. Consider the strong brand community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-1094670511428166">Muniz and O’Guinn 2001</xref>) among the passionately loyal supporters of Nordstrom’s department stores and Southwest Airlines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1094670511428166">Hart and Johnson 1999</xref>). While passionately loyal customers/fans are typically desired, services marketers should also recognize that avid patrons may also be more prone to rage when “their” retailers/teams underperform. Consider the anger and resentment expressed by loyal Netflix customers when the company announced rate changes to boost its revenue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr123-1094670511428166">Wortham and Stelter 2011</xref>). The influence of a fan’s physiological condition, psychological profile, and social identification on is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511428166">Figure 1</xref> as customer temperament’s direct effect on rage.<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 3:</italic> Fans’ propensity to rage becomes stronger when their (a) medical conditions energize their emotional state, (b) personality types are characterized by a desire to control their environment (e.g., Type A personalities), and/or (c) identification with the underperforming team is more intense.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<italic>Sociological factors</italic> may also influence a spectators’ inclination to rage. For instance, sport spectators often accept and identify with prescribed roles on how to behave at the sporting event (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr98-1094670511428166">Pratt and Cardador 2006</xref>) that may encourage aggressive behavior. One role typically assigned by the home team to its spectators is to foster a hostile environment for an opponent. For example, collegiate athletic stadiums are frequently branded with labels such as “Death Valley,” “The Pit,” and “The Swamp” and may serve as a reminder to home team fans that they are responsible for creating an intense, unwelcoming environment for opposing teams. In fact, a National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) official observed that “what becomes acceptable is to do your best to create an intimidating (home-field) atmosphere. And that has taken a toll on sportsmanship” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr120-1094670511428166">Weiberg 2002</xref>, p. 1). While the adversarial nature of fanatical sport spectators may appear somewhat unique, it is not totally unheard of in other service contexts. Expectations of confrontational roles often emerge or exist in retail encounters such as automobile purchase negotiations, themed restaurants like Dicks Last Resort, and services that involve tough-love personal interventions of various types.</p>
<p>The creation of a hostile home-field environment for an opponent may be intensified by a prevailing tradition of hostility that exists between the rival teams. For instance, antagonism between Croatians and Serbs is easily provoked due to their long history of mutual hatred. Similarly, fans of Scottish soccer rivals, Celtics and Glasgow Rangers, are often primed for action. The felt disdain for rival teams may exacerbate behaviors consistent with the rage-like fan role that include the creation of noise and the heckling or taunting of opponents and their supporters. In its extreme, there are spectators such as the “hooligans” who plague European soccer who have internalized the hostile fan role as part of a subculture identity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1094670511428166">Hughson 1998</xref>). The sense of solidarity, excitement, and autonomy found in one’s affiliation with other like-minded fanatics facilitates an expression of boundless violence (i.e., hooliganism) directed at opponents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr107-1094670511428166">Spaaij 2008</xref>) and may provoke retaliatory responses from the hooligans’ targets. In a sense, then, aggression and its potential manifestation as spectator rage may be learned via socialization as appropriate behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1094670511428166">Bandura 1973</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1094670511428166">1986</xref>).</p>
<p>The social context associated with sport spectatorship is another sociological factor that may influence a spectator’s propensity to rage. More specifically, a spectator’s temperament for rage may result from a pronounced transformation that occurs when norms prescribing appropriate social behavior are suspended during sporting events in favor of a more egocentric view (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1094670511428166">Bredemeier, Shields, and Horn 1985</xref>). Hence, the social context of spectator sport may make it easy for some fans to replace the prescriptions of normally acceptable behavior in favor of a different set of norms that they believe define a “true fan.” For example, some spectators may believe that a “true fan” is expected to display passionate loyalty to the home team and hatred toward the opposition that, when overly intense or aggressive, may become rage. Similarly, group dynamics that commonly exist at sporting events may also contribute to the suspension of appropriate social behavior. All else being equal, social consequences for individuals’ actions are oftentimes less severe in large groups than when a person acts alone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1094670511428166">Guerin 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1094670511428166">1998</xref>; Spaaij 2008). Accordingly, spectators may learn that the crowd at a sporting event provides a degree of anonymity which protects them from repercussions for hostile behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr116-1094670511428166">Wann, McLean, and Pullen 2003</xref>). Likewise, the collective excitement of the crowd at an event may intensify emotional responses among spectators making them more susceptible to rage behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1094670511428166">Coakley 2008</xref>). Similar group dynamics may certainly occur at other service venues such as rock concerts and amusement parks, yet are not as common, nor likely to spawn behaviors as extreme.</p>
<p>The upshot of this discussion is that the social surroundings characterizing spectator sport and the marketing tactics directed at sport spectators within a group context may exacerbate the likelihood of rage by fostering a temperament for its expression. The influence of social (group)-related factors on rage is portrayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511428166">Figure 1</xref> by customer temperament’s direct effect on the phenomenon.<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 4:</italic> Fans are increasingly prone to rage when they (a) take an active role in nurturing a “home-field” advantage through the creation of a hostile environment for the opposing team and/or (b) perceive that anonymity protects them from repercussions associated with hostile behavior.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1094670511428166">
<title>Triggers</title>
<p>Spectator and customer rage may be triggered by one or more factors that shape a fan’s/customer’s consumption experience (cf. de Rivera 1981; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-1094670511428166">Shaver et al. 1987</xref>).When a spectator is exposed simultaneously to several energizing forces, their combination is likely to generate an even higher level of stimulation that leads to increasingly aggressive and potentially antisocial behaviors, including rage. Moreover, the strength of rage inducing triggers may be moderated by fan temperament, that is, the influence of the triggers may be stronger when one’s personality and/or current state of mind predisposes them to rage behavior. For instance, when a fan’s medical condition, personality type, or identification with a sport team/athlete heightens his or her emotional state it may also magnify the intensity of rage-inducing triggers. These observations are represented by Triggers’ direct effect (Proposition 5) and Temperament’s moderating influence on rage (Proposition 6) depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511428166">Figure 1</xref>.<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 5:</italic> The interactive effect associated with a combining of energizing triggers is likely to increase a fan’s propensity to rage.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 6:</italic> A fan’s temperament may sensitize him or her to the energizing triggers and is likely to increase the propensity to rage.</p>
</list-item>
</list>The triggers of spectator and customer rage may be related to the nature of the consumption activity itself and/or situational factors present during a sporting event. The situational factors include five sets of influences posed by Belk (1975): The physical surroundings, social surroundings, task definition, temporal aspects, and antecedent states associated with one’s consumptive experience. These factors are likely to have a greater influence on the experiences of some spectators than others (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1094670511428166">Bandura 1973</xref>). Examples of sport characteristics and situational forces that trigger spectator rage are discussed below as well as presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1094670511428166">Table 1</xref>
.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1094670511428166" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Types Spectator Rage Triggers</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1094670511428166" xlink:href="10.1177_1094670511428166-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Factor</th>
<th>Trigger Examples</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Nature of the consumption activity</td>
<td>Uncertainty of the sporting event’s outcome</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Amount and type of aggressive behavior comprising the sport performance</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Physical surroundings</td>
<td>Close proximity to the field</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Temperature extremes at venue</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Noise level in stadium</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Social surroundings</td>
<td>Crowding at the venue</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Absence of authority at stadium</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Verbal/physical behaviors of other fans</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Task definition/spectatorship motives</td>
<td>Contest is a heated rivalry</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Wager made on the contest</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Strong identification with the team/athlete</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Temporal perspective</td>
<td>Long waits for refreshments, restrooms, admission</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Hunger (length of time since last meal)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Late start (more time tailgating)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Antecedent states</td>
<td>Bad mood from traffic congestion while traveling to the event</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Aggressive behavior by opposing fans at last contest</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Over imbibing of alcohol prior to the event</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section9-1094670511428166">
<title>The nature of the consumption activity</title>
<p>The amount of suspense and/or aggressive behavior that characterizes a sporting event can evoke strong emotional responses from spectators. For instance, the suspense associated with the uncertainty of the outcome of a live sporting event can generate intense excitement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1094670511428166">Madrigal 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr124-1094670511428166">Zillman 1996</xref>) and may turn to rage when a spectator witnesses the defeat of his or her favorite team, especially when the loss is to a hated rival (Zillman and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr125-1094670511428166">Paulus 1993</xref>). Emotions may also be piqued by the degree of on field violence witnessed during a contest that may increase the likelihood that spectators will engage in aggressive behavior if they become frustrated or angry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1094670511428166">Berkowitz 1993a</xref>). The nature of the consumption event’s influence on rage is portrayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511428166">Figure 1</xref> by Triggers’ direct effect on rage.</p>
<p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 7</italic>: Fans are prone to rage when (a) uncertainty of the contest’s outcome is distressing leading to frustration when it is unfavorable and/or (b) a contest is perceived as markedly aggressive and violent.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1094670511428166">
<title>Physical surroundings</title>
<p>Conditions pertaining to the servicescape at the sport venue may contribute to a fan’s propensity to rage. Physical factors such as weather, the venue’s layout elevated sounds/noise level, cramped seating, and the like (cf, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1094670511428166">Belk 1975</xref>) may cause irritability that can ignite into rage. For instance, research has demonstrated that uncomfortably hot temperatures may lead to aggressive behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1094670511428166">Anderson 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1094670511428166">Bushman, Wang, and Anderson 2005</xref>) and excessive heat was recognized as one factor contributing to an intense brawl between Croatian and Serbian fans at an Australian Open Tennis Tournament (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr113-1094670511428166">Sydney Morning Herald 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>One of the more scrutinized potential triggers of fan rage is the proximity of spectators to the athletic contest. Largely, a function of stadium design, the closer spectators are to the contest, the easier it is for them to become emotionally charged and to focus the release of their emotions toward the athletes. Consider an incident involving a fracas that erupted during a professional basketball contest between the Indiana Pacers and Detroit Pistons. The proximity of the fans to the action created a pronounced sense of game involvement and the opportunity for direct, physical interaction between spectators and players. Clearly, as with any servicescape, the spatial layout and functionality of the sport venue has the potential to influence fans’ actions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1094670511428166">Bitner 1992</xref>).</p>
<p>Noise has also been linked to increased aggressive tendencies and physiological arousal (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1094670511428166">Geen and McCown 1984</xref>), yet it is often encouraged at sport venues to enhance the spectator experience and to serve as an intimidation factor for opponents of the home team. Promotional tactics such as dispensing noise-making devices to fans to create clatter or broadcasting video or audio messages that implore spectators to “make some noise” are frequent at many sporting events. It is also common for arenas to play loud music during intermissions and, increasingly, while a game is in progress. Furthermore, the lyrics of some of the broadcasted songs at arenas have been criticized for promoting and glamorizing hostility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1094670511428166">Elmore 2004</xref>). Ironically, while these phenomena are meant to emotionally engage fans and enhance fans’ enjoyment of the sporting event, they may undermine it as well. While spectator sport is somewhat unique with respect to how it embraces noise, it is apparent that noise is a situational factor that can affect the likelihood of customer rage across diverse service contexts. The impact of an event’s physical surroundings on rage is depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511428166">Figure 1</xref> by Triggers’ direct effect on rage.<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 8:</italic> Fans are prone to rage when the physical surroundings of the venue (e.g., noise levels, close proximity to the field of play, uncomfortable temperatures, etc.) energize and/or irritate them.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1094670511428166">
<title>Social surroundings</title>
<p>The number and social profile of those present at a sporting event, along with fans’ responsibilities and interpersonal interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1094670511428166">Belk 1975</xref>), may affect the likelihood of rage. For example, crowded stadiums may trigger reactions of hostility. It is important to recognize that a distinction can be made between the phenomenon of crowding, an unpleasant feeling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1094670511428166">Hui and Bateson 1991</xref>), and the related concept of density, the “spatial parameters” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr110-1094670511428166">Stokolos 1972</xref>) that characterize a servicescape. Sporting events are frequently marked by a high density of fans which may foster perceptions of crowding. Research suggests that discomfort, dissatisfaction, and negative feelings increase as the number of people in a service setting grows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1094670511428166">Eroglu and Machleit 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1094670511428166">Jackson and Latane 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1094670511428166">Machleit, Eroglu, and Mantel 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Density and the perception of crowding are a function of both the desire to maximize the number of seats available within a sport venue and to fill those seats with paying fans. While capacity crowds increases the potential for revenue generation and fan excitement at a sports venue, large crowds can also have adverse effects on fans’ experience that may result in incidents of rage. For example, increasing crowd density increases the likelihood of spectators bumping into another or accidentally spilling food or a beverage on others, which may prompt an aggressive response from the victim. Likewise, large crowds frequently create long queues at entry and exit gates, in concession areas and restrooms. Such queues may increase anxiety or stress and provide the opportunity for physical or verbal transgressions that can boost the probability of hostile behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1094670511428166">Grove and Fisk 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1094670511428166">Kumar, Kalwani, and Dada 1997</xref>).</p>
<p>Large crowds may also nurture the potential for fan rage by providing individuals with relative anonymity and deindividuation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr126-1094670511428166">Zimbardo 1970</xref>). Within spectator sport, this condition may lead some fans to lose their inhibitions about acting aggressively and feel unaccountable for their actions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1094670511428166">Hirt and Clarkson 2011</xref>). The tendency for aggressive behavior may be exacerbated when there is an absence of visible authority figures at the venue. Security guards, law enforcement personnel, stadium staff, and the like operate as formal agents of social control<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1094670511428166">1</xref>
</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-1094670511428166">Pfohl 1994</xref>) and their visible presence may be sufficient to reduce the probability of fan hostility. While the presence of authority figures is unlikely to curtail all expressions of rage, it may prompt one to reflect on the consequences of rage before he or she acts. Significant others (e.g., spouse, date and child) may perform a similar control function by informally inhibiting the likelihood of fan hostility due to the scorn, embarrassment, or rejection that might ensue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1094670511428166">Goode 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1094670511428166">Grove, Fisk, and John 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Another social factor related to spectatorship that may lead to rage involves fan violations of unwritten rules regarding appropriate fan behavior. Typically, fans tend to abide by a common set of assumptions regarding the appropriate moments during a sporting event when conversation may take place, such as between plays (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr88-1094670511428166">Melnick 1993</xref>). Similar assumptions apply to moving to and from one’s seat. For instance, during a professional tennis match, fans normally are not allowed to relocate to their seats between or during points. In addition, fans are expected to allow other spectators a clear line of sight while the action is in progress and to move quickly out of the line of sight of other spectators when relocating to or from their seats. If these rules are not honored an offended fan’s viewing experience is interrupted and he or she may become irritated, resulting in anger and rage. To be sure, negative aspects of crowding may have a similar effect across other services as well, yet, when crowding is coupled with other situational variables (e.g., noise) present at sport venues, its impact is greatly enhanced. The influence of an event’s social surroundings on rage is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511428166">Figure 1</xref> by Triggers’ direct effect on rage.<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 9</italic>: Fans are prone to rage when (a) there is discomfort due to crowding; (b) a perceived absence of authority; and/or (c) inappropriate spectatorship behaviors by others.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1094670511428166">
<title>Task definition/spectator motives</title>
<p>Frustration-Aggression Theory, a broad explanation for aggressive behavior in general, posits that people may exhibit violent tendencies when they are blocked from achieving certain goals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1094670511428166">Berkowitz 1993b</xref>). Correspondingly, spectator rage may arise when fans perceive that they are unduly blocked from fulfilling their spectator roles, referred to as task definitions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1094670511428166">Belk 1975</xref>), or from realizing their spectator motives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-1094670511428166">Shaver et al. 1987</xref>). Fans engage in spectatorship for a variety of reasons such as a desire to be entertained; to be aroused and excited; or, to escape from the stresses of everyday life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1094670511428166">Hirt and Clarkson 2011</xref>). Fans may also engage in spectatorship to rid themselves of negative/detrimental emotions and tensions; to display positive emotions; to provide a forum for self-expression through identification with a team or athlete; to display pride in the city/place that is home to their favorite teams/athletes and, to promote social bonding with other fans who share a common interest and enthusiasm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1094670511428166">Grove, Dorsch, and Hopkins 2012</xref>).</p>
<p>The likelihood of aggressive behavior increases when excessively engaged fans are unable to realize their spectatorships goals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr117-1094670511428166">Wann et al. 2001</xref>). For instance, fans may believe that the athletic performance is not as entertaining as they had hoped or falls below typical standards. Fans may also show their displeasure when a contest fails to display the amount of aggressiveness they desired. For example, hockey fans sometimes show their displeasure with the entertainment value of a lackluster contest by chanting “More fights, less hockey.” In other situations, highly identified fans may become enraged when they witness a loss by their favorite team. More specifically, whereas fans with a weak team attachment may engage in CORFing—a process of cutting off reflected failure—in an attempt to protect their self-esteem following their team’s loss, highly identified fans tend to avoid CORFing since it is akin to devaluating the self (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr118-1094670511428166">Wann and Branscombe 1990</xref>). As a sport team/athlete becomes an important part of a fan’s self-concept, it is more difficult for the fan to distance himself or herself from the team’s outcomes/ performances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1094670511428166">Hirt and Clarkson 2011</xref>), and it is more likely that the fan will express anger and rage when the contest outcome is negative.</p>
<p>Spectatorship motives of excessively engaged fans may induce rage. For instance, consider the highly publicized incidents involving European football fans who trek to away games and support their team by aggressively challenging their counterparts. Taunts, chants, and other negative behaviors that are perceived by some spectators as a part of an ardent fan’s role can also incite hostility from the opposition. In addition, similar to consumers of other types of hedonic consumption, sport spectators, tend to create and act upon a subjective reality that may not be congruent with objective reality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1094670511428166">Hirschman and Holbrook 1982</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-1094670511428166">Shaver et al. (1987)</xref> found that individuals exhibit cognitive biases and distortions when describing personal experiences that tend to extol the appropriateness of their own positions. Hence, when fans become absorbed with escaping their daily lives, they may create a subjective reality that enables them to flee the rules/norms that normally govern them and redefine aggressive and antisocial behaviors as appropriate. Escaping reality in such a manner may explain why some fans of winning teams physically and/or verbally abuse fans of the losing opposition.</p>
<p>The significance fans place on a contest may also increase their likelihood of rage. When fans are intensely focused on the outcome of a contest, the strong psychological tie between spectators and their favored team may pique tensions and anxieties when the desired outcome is in jeopardy. Sport rivalries involving local teams (e.g., New York Yankees and Boston Red Sox) or national sides (e.g., India and Pakistan cricket teams) may be particularly vulnerable to such behavior. When organizers and the media aggressively promote heated competitive rivalries and key events (e.g., championship games and geographic rivalries), some fans may place a heightened importance on the contest’s outcome. In these instances, the “win or die” or “there’s no tomorrow” meaning that emerges may stokes fans’ passion and propensity to rage.</p>
<p>From a task definition perspective, the sporting event may be important to some spectators for other nonsport reasons. Consider the case of gambling. Placing a bet on an athletic contest obviously increases its significance to the bettor. Hence, it not surprising that studies indicate gamblers may be more likely to engage in acts of rage—particularly if one should lose his or her wager (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr95-1094670511428166">Parke and Griffiths 2004</xref>). Despite the link between hostile behavior and gambling, many sport organizations have relaxed policies which in the past restricted the formation of relationships with gambling entities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-1094670511428166">McKelvey 2004</xref>). The upshot of this is that the importance one assigns to a service encounter—whether it is an anticipated vacation, the repair of one’s cherished automobile, or the outcome of an athletic contest against a hated foe—may increase the possibility of rage. The influence of customers’ Task Definitions on rage is portrayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511428166">Figure 1</xref> by Triggers’ direct effect on rage.<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 10</italic>: Fans are prone to rage when they (a) find it difficult to realize their spectatorship motives and/or (b) are dominated by a desire to accomplish them.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1094670511428166">
<title>Temporal perspective</title>
<p>Sometimes the time-based issues surrounding a consumptive activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1094670511428166">Belk 1975</xref>) may induce customer frustration/anxiety that can lead to rage. When examined from a temporal perspective, crowding and lengthy queues may create exasperatingly long waits for fans that keep them from realizing various objectives (e.g., watching the live sporting event), ultimately causing irritability and anxiety—two states that may ignite rage. This is particularly so when fans feel as if little progress is being made toward their goal of entering or leaving the stadium, acquiring refreshments, or gaining access to the restroom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1094670511428166">Haynes 1990</xref>). Likewise, fan perceptions of being hurried or rushed may also create an ill temper. Hence, similar to customers in general, fans who feel they are being herded in or out of a venue at a pace not to their liking may react in an abusive fashion.</p>
<p>As a situational variable, time may contribute to the likelihood of spectator rage in other ways as well. For instance, the amount of time that has (or has not) transpired between infractions by the opposing team, how long it has been since one team has been victorious against a foe, or the time pressure a fan may feel as a result of a contest lasting too long may create a heightened emotional state that renders one rage ready. In short, how time is experienced by spectators (and service customers as a whole) may contribute to one’s ire. The Temporal aspects’ impact on rage is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511428166">Figure 1</xref> by Triggers’’ direct effect on rage.<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 11:</italic> Fans are prone to rage when they perceive an inappropriate amount of time has elapsed associated with some aspect of the spectator experience.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1094670511428166">
<title>Antecedent states</title>
<p>Antecedent states, such as momentary moods or temporary conditions that customers or spectators experience prior to engaging in consumption, establishes a context which may influence customers’ consumption experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1094670511428166">Belk 1975</xref>) and their likelihood to rage. Moods may influence or be influenced by one’s consumption experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1094670511428166">Gardner 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1094670511428166">Knowles, Grove, and Pickett 1993</xref>) and spectators whose moods prior to a sporting event reflect feelings of being anxious, frustrated, highly energized, or aggressive are prime candidates to rage. For example, spectators may become frustrated by unexpected traffic delays in arriving at the stadium; failure to bring an item that enhances the spectatorship experience (e.g., binoculars, seating cushion); or, receiving unpleasant news unrelated to the sporting event. Other conditions that can affect fan mood and influence rage may be traced to a sport venue’s marketing practices or policies such as those that ban certain personal possessions (e.g., umbrellas, beverage coolers, etc.) from the venue.</p>
<p>As an antecedent state, a temporary mental state resulting from alcohol consumption is perhaps the most common trigger of spectator rage. When used as a means to escape or to ostensibly enhance one’s experience, alcohol consumption may exacerbate the impact of other triggers present at a sporting event. Alcohol is intricately linked to spectator sport in general. It is frequently a key aspect of pregame rituals such as “tailgating” as well as postgame celebrations or commensurations. Further, alcohol is commonly sold inside the venue, allowing fans to continue imbibing during an event. According to one estimate, nearly 10% of the males leaving a major league baseball game are legally drunk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-1094670511428166">O’Brien and Hersch 1998</xref>). A number of studies show that alcohol increases the likelihood of aggressive behavior (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1094670511428166">Bushman and Cooper 1990</xref>), particularly for those with antisocial personality disorder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr89-1094670511428166">Moeller and Dougherty 2001</xref>). There is even some evidence that the mere image of alcohol can evoke aggressive tendencies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1094670511428166">Bartholow and Heinz 2006</xref>), raising questions about advertising of alcohol outside of or within sporting venues.</p>
<p>While other triggers of customer rage exist, the preceding discussion and examples provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1094670511428166">Table 1</xref> point to broad categories of factors that may prompt spectators to lash out at other fans, workers, sport participants, the sport setting, or even the athletic performance itself. Moreover, these factors often operate in combination (e.g., crowded circumstances, loud noises, and excessive alcohol consumption) to create a service environment that is more conducive for acts of aggression and rage. The impact of antecedent states on rage is depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511428166">Figure 1</xref> by Triggers’ direct effect on the phenomenon.<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 12:</italic> Fans are prone toward rage when they experience unexpected and temporary factors that have an adverse influence on their moods.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1094670511428166">
<title>Treatments</title>
<p>Sport marketers may employ various tactics to reduce fans’ proneness to rage and address those incidences when rage occurs. In many ways, these treatments reflect efforts to manage customer compatibility in service contexts in general (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-1094670511428166">Martin and Pranter 1989</xref>) and suggest initiatives that could be applied to services at large. For example, adopting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1094670511428166">Lovelock and Wirtz’s (2011)</xref> three-stage model of service consumption, one way to approach treatment options is to consider actions that an organization might take <italic>before, during,</italic> and <italic>after</italic> an event. Clearly, the result of any pregame planning will be evident during a contest, yet we categorize activities based on when the substantive work required to address rage incidents is likely to occur. Regardless, the foci of the treatments are the Triggers, Temperament, and Targets, separately or in combination (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511428166">Figure 1</xref>) and involve endeavors that are typically directed at one or more the four components of the service encounter—customers, employees, service setting, or service process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1094670511428166">Fisk, Grove, and John 2008</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section16-1094670511428166">
<title>Pregame treatments</title>
<p>Role definition: Perhaps, the best opportunity to address temperament characteristics that influence spectator rage is prior to the service encounter. This endeavor may involve customer socialization similar to the approaches used to educate patrons of any service. In the context of sport, these tactics include the efforts of leagues or other governing bodies that prescribe spectator roles that reflect good sportsmanship. Recently, the NFL defined the boundaries of appropriate and inappropriate fan behavior through publication of its “Fan Code of Conduct” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-1094670511428166">McCarthy 2008</xref>). This guide addresses a broad cross section of unacceptable fan action including intoxication, disruptive behavior, foul language, obscene gestures, game interference, and verbal harassment of opposing team fans. Similarly, a Florida youth baseball organization was recognized as a model for educating parents and spectators regarding appropriate fan behavior. The organization annually packs more than 1,500 parents into a stadium to watch a video concerning how to be a good sports parent, to provide a handbook describing sportsmanship, and to sign a sportsmanship pledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1094670511428166">Cary, Dotinga, and Comarow 2004</xref>). In a related effort, the NCAA has held sportsmanship summits where coaches and athletic administrators discuss ideas for curbing violence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1094670511428166">Brown 2003</xref>). Some of the recommendations include encouraging staff from opposing teams to participate in pregame planning activities and to meet with key student groups before/during the season to review consequences of rage behavior. These and similar campaigns introduce alternatives to the hostile role assumed by many spectators by educating the fans and imparting appropriate behavior.</p>
<p>Repositioning the sport brand: It may be possible to position a sport brand to encourage civil behavior. A sport enterprise that emphasizes responsible competition and a positive experience should motivate spectators to exhibit those properties as well. Moreover, hostility toward opposing fans or other targets as a means of restoring self-esteem when poor performances occur should diminish as an acceptable defense mechanism. For example, Clemson University’s athletic department initiated a campaign in recent years to emphasize the message “our actions honor our university, traditions, teams, performance, people and each other” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-1094670511428166">Match 2007</xref>). The message is communicated through a variety of media before entering the sport venues, as well as once fans are seated via signage and in-game announcements. Hence, building and reinforcing a sport organization’s brand image that stresses positive attributes of sportsmanship and is void of elements that undermine it may curb the likelihood of spectator rage.</p>
<p>Information provision:. Beyond the broad efforts to promote civil behavior, pregame planning should focus on informing patrons of specific behaviors that are considered inappropriate and subject to disciplinary sanctions. Teams often list actionable offenses on the backside of game tickets and in promotional materials sent to ticket purchasers. In addition, reminders about appropriate fan behaviors are announced prior to the beginning of a competitive event via signage and other forms of messaging. Sponsors might also help reduce the potential for poor fan behavior by closely scrutinizing the nature of items distributed to fans as part of their sponsorship activities. Giveaway such as key chains with team logos or miniature baseball bats can become projectiles or weapons for unruly fans.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1094670511428166">
<title>Game-day treatments</title>
<p>Spectator screening: Pregame planning for fan rage may involve implementing policies and practices that minimize fan access to the targets of rage and eliminate or reduce the influence of potential rage triggers. While such tactics may require considerable circumspection prior to an event, they are essentially initiated at the outset of the service encounter or sport contest. For example, spectators attending an event are commonly confronted with security personnel as they enter the facility. Beyond ticket validation, the opportunity exists to screen spectators prior to granting entrance for banned items (e.g., alcohol, noise makers, projectiles, weapons/ fireworks, and lasers) that could trigger or be used in episodes of rage. The NFL, for instance, maintains a policy requiring teams to establish a screening process that subjects fans to the possibility of a random search. While the policy has received legal scrutiny as a violation of one’s protection from unreasonable search (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr93-1094670511428166">Nagel 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr115-1094670511428166">Varian 2005</xref>), U.S. courts rejected the contention clearing the way for other organizations to follow the precedence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr119-1094670511428166">Washington Post 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Event security: Inside the servicescape, most sporting events are staffed by security and law enforcement whose presence is intended to deter acts of aggression and enforce stadium policies regarding breaches of acceptable behavior. After all, one role that the service marketer must play to prompt customer adherence to rules is that of the police officer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1094670511428166">Lovelock 1981</xref>). Spectators engaging in objectionable acts are typically removed from a venue and if their rage behavior is criminal in nature they may face charges from local or state authorities. In fact, the NFL’s recently endorsed a fan policy in which poor behavior from a season ticketholder’s guest can result in the loss of season ticket rights for the ticket owner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-1094670511428166">McCarthy 2008</xref>). More recently, some sport organizations have adopted technologies to assist them in the identification of fans engaging in hostile behavior. Monitoring systems (e.g., closed-circuit cameras), including those that may require considerable pregame planning, are often used to ensure effective coverage of potential trouble locations. Such systems have aided various professional teams attempting to identify disruptive spectators and are now mandatory for all Greek and Italian professional soccer stadiums (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1094670511428166">Kitsantonis 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr101-1094670511428166">Sanminiatelli 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Another technology-driven means to address incidence of unruly spectators involves the use of dedicated mobile telephone numbers that allow fans to report disruptive behavior of others in real time and relative anonymity to appropriate security officials. Such efforts can enhance the efficiency of a security force by allowing them to better target their actions. Empowering fans through technology can also minimize their feelings of helplessness and isolation while helping organizations to respond to inappropriate spectator behavior.</p>
<p>Alcohol restrictions: Other game-day strategies might attempt to minimize the influence of alcohol as a potential trigger for hostility. For example, the NCAA prohibits the sale of alcoholic beverages in on-campus athletic facilities. Further, some universities place restrictions on “pass-outs” (a term referring to the practice of allowing spectators to exit and reenter the stadium), which are often used by some fans as an opportunity to consume more alcohol. Other institutions are taking a more hard line approach to curbing the negative effect of alcohol consumption by restricting or banning alcoholic beverages in the parking lots outside of stadiums. Given the strong link between alcohol consumption and spectator sports, such policies are often met with considerable resistance, yet are also likely to reduce the incidence of spectator rage.</p>
<p>Strict restrictions are also placed on the sale of alcohol during athletic events. For instance, beer sale inside stadiums is often terminated at a designated time well before a game’s scheduled conclusion. In fact, during a 2005 contest, the New York Jets and the New Jersey Sports and Exposition Authority (facility owners) agreed to ban the sale of alcohol inside the stadium for an entire game to reduce the likelihood of hostilities during the event carrying over from a previous meeting of the opposing teams. Relatedly, to minimize the potential of fan rage outside of their stadium, the Chicago Bears have removed tailgaters from the parking lots at Soldier Field at kick-off if they fail to produce a ticket to the scheduled game (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1094670511428166">Bonk 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Seating assignments: By thoughtfully considering the spatial functionality and layout of the servicescape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1094670511428166">Bitner 1992</xref>), a variety of seating options may be developed that allow logical fan segmentation (i.e., students, opposing fans, etc.) to quell the likelihood of rage. Through ticket distribution, spectators with the potential to be targets or initiators of rage may be assigned seating with additional security and/or monitoring. A feature common in many European soccer stadiums is special fencing around sections designated for fans of the visiting team. In addition, many sports venues offer family sections inside the stadium which are “free from alcohol sales, exposure to alcohol, and foul, suggestive or vulgar language” (Seattle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr103-1094670511428166">Seahawks 2007</xref>). By creating advance seat selection processes, seating options that mitigate frustrations at an event that contribute to aggressive feelings and displays of inappropriate behavior are possible.</p>
<p>Queuing methods: Service providers have long recognized the importance of managing wait times to improve customers’ service experience (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1094670511428166">Hui and Tse 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-1094670511428166">McGuire and Kimes 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr99-1094670511428166">Rafaeli, Barron, and Haber 2002</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1094670511428166">Haynes (1990)</xref> offers a number of waiting guidelines that are applicable in a sport setting. For instance, concession or restroom waits might seem shorter if sport venues provide fans closed-circuit viewing or audio broadcasting of the action they are missing to counter the perception that “empty minutes are long minutes.” Additionally, offering creative concession options such as single-item purchase lines, special queues for popular items, or employing technology that enables in-seat purchases may prove efficient and equitable. When waiting is unavoidable, efforts could be made to make customer/fan wait time as comfortable as possible. For instance, during extremely hot outdoor events positioning a fan/air conditioner or a misting system to cool those in line might lessen spectators’ angst.</p>
<p>Random acts of kindness: Like customers in general, most fans arguably want a congenial environment where they feel safe and where their basic needs are supported by the hosting organization. In that regard, simple acts of kindness such as making water or a personal cooling system (e.g., a hand-held fan) freely available to spectators on hot days might create feelings of goodwill that alleviates sour moods, reduces anxiety, and ultimately creates a more enjoyable atmosphere. Similarly, a venue could employ goodwill ambassadors who would patrol the stands to assist patrons with small gestures of kindness, which might change the temperament of some fans and reduce the potential for rage behavior.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1094670511428166">
<title>Postgame treatments</title>
<p>Fines and sanctions: Increasingly, sport organizations address incidents of spectator rage by imposing significant financial penalties for failure to enforce security policies. For example, in 2005, the international governing body for soccer (Federation Internationale de Football Association) fined three national clubs “for lack of proper security arrangements for that match” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1094670511428166">CNN.com 2005</xref>). Similarly, the Italian Soccer Federation passed several “zero tolerance” rules intended to curb fan violence at soccer matches, including cancelling a game at any time should violence erupt inside or outside of the stadium or if offensive signs, banners, or symbols are seen inside the venue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1094670511428166">Associated Press 2005</xref>). While these actions are punitive in nature, they vividly underscore the link between fan misbehavior and measures that have been developed to address it.</p>
<p>Video review: Information regarding significant incidents of spectator rage should be collected, catalogued, and reviewed following every sporting event. A system can be developed wherein officials who witness rage are required to file a written report detailing the incident from their perspective. Such feedback can be aggregated and examined for trends and patterns. Accounts of rage episodes can be submitted by hand-written reports or via technology (e.g., video cameras). For example, during the mid-1990s, the NFL’s New England Patriots used the footage from cameras mounted inside its stadium to identify spectators engaging in inappropriate behavior. During the camera surveillance system’s first year in use, a total of 70 season ticket holders were refused requests to renew their tickets due to violations of the team policies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr121-1094670511428166">Weisman 1995</xref>).</p>
<p>Service recovery: Management can review “critical rage incidents” to determine if the spectator/spectators were principally at fault or if the organization/service employee/employees played an instrumental role in triggering hostile action. If the right type of information is collected, the sport organization may be afforded an opportunity to engage in service recovery for innocent parties and bystanders who were significantly impacted by the rage event. In addition, employee training and incentive programs might be developed that emphasize effective management of service failure and customer rage incidents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1094670511428166">Grove, Fisk, and John 2004</xref>). Finally, using the postgame information, sport venues can embrace an organizational learning perspective that welcomes process review and improvement through regular and systematic examination of collected accounts. Proposition 13 is portrayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1094670511428166">Figure 1</xref> by Treatment’s negative direct effect on rage.<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p>
<italic>Proposition 13:</italic> Fans are less prone to rage when (a) they are aware that their behavior is being monitored and accountable for their actions and/or (b) the venue effectively manages fan experiences before, during, and after an event to disarm aggressive behavior.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-1094670511428166">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>As services marketers continue to explore ways to emotionally engage customers, the possibility exists that those efforts may result in unexpected and unfavorable customer reactions. Customer rage is a complex and potentially disruptive response that emotionally charged patrons may exhibit as a reaction to extreme irritation and/or frustration created by a variety of interactive elements present in many service encounters. Through an application of the 4-Ts of Customer Rage framework, sport marketers might better understand the circumstances that intensify one’s propensity to rage and potential treatments to address its occurrence. As related here, many of the variables leading to combustible situations within a sport context can be anticipated and managed before, during and after rage’s occurrence. In fact, many sport organizations are currently mobilizing to deal more effectively with rage’s detrimental circumstances. We hope that by bringing attention to and applying the 4-Ts of customer rage, sport practitioners are provided a valuable tool in their quest to create a more positive fan experience.</p>
<p>One of the hallmarks of the service sector is duality of the uniqueness of the industries that comprise it and the commonality among them. Service firms that study organizations confronting similar problems in other service industries can learn from them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1094670511428166">Lovelock 1994</xref>). Hence, by investigating spectator rage, services marketers in general may glean insights regarding rage behavior that apply to their industry. Our framework suggests that when services emotionally engage their customers, rage can occur even when the service is performed properly and without failure. This can happen when customers personalize the service encounter and experience obstructions in accomplishing their consumptive goals due to factors unrelated to actual service performance (Prahalad and Ramaswamy 2006). Even when organizations customize their service delivery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1094670511428166">Lovelock 1983</xref>), the possibility exists that some customers may still exhibit different and contradictory responses (cf, Hirschman and Holbrook 1982). Moreover, when services emotionally engage their customers, the potential for customer rage increases; this is especially true when patrons become highly stimulated and experience frustrations/interruptions that affect their goal-oriented behavior (cf, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1094670511428166">de Rivera 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-1094670511428166">Shaver et al. 1987</xref>).</p>
<p>Evidence presented here suggests that rage also results from individual traits inherent among some customers, situational variables found in many service encounters, and conditions that may be created as part of an organizations’ marketing effort. Understanding that these factors may interact to produce rage events should help organizations plan and manage inappropriate behavior. For example, airlines today aggressively screen passengers and have established elaborate procedures to identify the most threatening customers. Unfortunately, other practices such as ignoring seat assignments which fliers “reserved” when purchasing their ticket or charging passengers a fee for basic accommodations such as a beverage or a pillow and blanket may foster disdain that percolates into fury. “Acts of kindness” in these service delivery decisions can set a tone of civility and hospitality to enhance positive mood states rather than prompting negative responses.</p>
<p>Our framework acknowledges that sport marketers may be unable to completely eliminate fan rage; instead, we offer suggestions for reducing its likelihood that are also applicable to services in general. For example, during the service design process, marketers might identify those moments of truth that are expected to generate emotional highs and/or lows for customers. The creation of certain strong emotions (e.g., pleasure and excitement) may be part of the service experience design, while others (e.g., aggressiveness, anxiety, and anger) are likely to be unintended. Recognizing that both emotional responses are possible, service design should include discussions/blueprinting that identify experiential factors that evoke strong emotional reactions, whether intended or unintended, favorable or unfavorable (cf, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1094670511428166">Haeckel, Carbone, and Berry 2003</xref>). When a moment-of-truth that increases one’s proneness to rage is ascertained, the service can be redesigned to incorporate experience-related elements that are meant to diffuse/reduce anger-related tendencies (e.g., warning/cautioning customers about becoming overly emotional prior to and upon completion of their service experience, visible signage or other communications that reminds customers to engage in pro-social behaviors, observable security, etc.). Additionally, customers can be monitored during the service performance to identify problems and conduct “experience intervention” to keep emotionally charged customers from becoming enraged. Experience interventions may require a patron to be removed from the stimulating environment in order to calm him or her down (essentially, putting the customer in an “emotional time-out”). In other situations, the customer may be detained and required to provide retribution for injuring others or damaging property while in the highly charged emotional state.</p>
<p>Service organizations such as large retailers, amusement venues, and others might learn from sport marketers how to better manage anticipated overcrowding situations that sometimes occur in conjunction with special shopping days and events. Just as sport venues utilize a season ticket process and point systems to allocate scarce seating capacity, other services might anticipate capacity shortages and better manage the process of queuing customer demand through allocation of desired scarce goods or services well in advance of a heavy shopping day. Such a system would be valuable to assuage potential rage events that might occur on “Black Friday” when shoppers are in pursuit of the newest digital device that is in short supply. Crowded entertainment settings, such as theme parks and concerts, could certainly benefit from nearly all of the treatments suggested within the sport context. From security planning and execution to seating arrangements to information provision and screening systems, directives that reflect how sport venues address these considerations could be studied and applied to reduce the potential for rage events in other service contexts. For example, sports venue practices regarding scheduling and placing security personnel/surveillance, physically segregating customers within the servicescape who may not get along well with each other, and denying entrance or re-entrance into the service establishment could be adopted to quell rage in other service contexts.</p>
<p>It is important to recognize that two distinct considerations exist for the effective management of rage, whether the efforts involve spectator sport or other service types: (a) the degree to which marketers are able to address the features that render a service encounter susceptible to rage and (b) the extent to which potential treatments for rage conflict with marketing objectives. Some of the factors that enhance the opportunity for rage may be addressed while others may not. In general, circumstances that pass for the <italic>triggers</italic> of rage offer a greater potential for control and treatment. To a large degree, trigger conditions are traceable to a distinct cause-and-effect relationship that might be minimized by organizational action. As noted, organizations could create a less volatile servicescape by communicating appropriate and inappropriate behavior to customers, using systems and technology to reduce long queues, branding the service experience to embrace civil behavior and discourse, attending to controllable situational factors that have the potential to diminish customer frustration (such as lowering the music volume or minimizing crowding), and curtailing alcohol sales (where applicable).</p>
<p>Slightly less treatable are those service aspects linked to the <italic>target</italic> category of rage factors. Targets of rage are often requisite parts of the service encounter that cannot be removed without altering the essence of the experience itself. Customers, front-stage employees, and other support personnel that may become targets of rage are integral elements of many service experiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1094670511428166">Booms and Bitner 1981</xref>). In sport, the potential targets of rage include the fans, players, officials, and coaches. While efforts by services marketers to manage customer compatibility can reduce the likelihood of rage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1094670511428166">Grove and Fisk 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-1094670511428166">Martin and Pranter 1989</xref>), it is difficult to completely eliminate its rapid and spontaneous expression. Nevertheless, services marketing efforts that center on designing/managing the servicescape to preempt incidents of fan rage and limit customer access to targets might be pursued. For instance, the ambient conditions (e.g., noise level and air temperature), signs, symbols and artifacts (e.g., video communications and audio announcements), and space/function (e.g., seating arrangements, capacity expansions, and queuing processes) are elements that can be addressed in spectator sport and other service contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1094670511428166">Bitner 1992</xref>). Arguably, the same facility features that many organizations incorporate to create a high degree of interaction and intimacy with their customers may also increase the potential or opportunity for rage and require careful scrutiny.</p>
<p>The least addressable set of factors contributing to rage reside in the <italic>temperament</italic> category. Knowing that some people may be predisposed to rage incidents is certainly unsettling. Ultimately, the enduring personality characteristics and less obvious physical and social conditions that comprise a customer’s temperament can only be managed when employees are trained to monitor and recognize the inappropriate behavior that temperament manifests. Thus, preemptive actions necessary to screen for potential disruptive customers are very difficult and offer the least opportunity for treatment options.</p>
<p>Ironically, there may be no service industry other than spectator sport where an organization’s interest in reducing or eliminating acts of aggressive behavior conflict more directly with the organizational objectives assigned to marketers. Sport marketers are charged with providing spectators with an engaging and exciting entertainment experience, yet many of the practices used to create an emotionally arousing and profitable experience (e.g., availability of alcohol, a loud and electrifying atmosphere, the criticality of a contest, etc.) may also trigger fan rage. For example, the availability and promotion of alcoholic is largely based on the fact that sales of it represent a substantial revenue stream for many sport organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr117-1094670511428166">Wann et al. 2001</xref>) and devices such as “thunder sticks” (inflatable noise-making plastic balloons), given to spectators at an event are typically emblazoned with sponsor logos. Further, promoting contests as rivalries, “big games” and “do-or-die” situations may stir emotions among patrons that simultaneously piques fan interest and the likelihood of aggressive behavior; such contests may enhance revenue through premium ticket pricing, media rights, and sponsorship fees, yet carry a cost in terms of spectator rage. In short, efforts to emotionally energize fans can go awry when they generate a response that nudges them beyond rage’s “boiling point” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1094670511428166">Grove, Fisk, and John 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>While the focus of this article examines the deleterious effects of fan and customer rage, it bears noting that there may also be an upside to the phenomenon. As paradoxical as it may seem, dysfunctional customer behavior such as the incidence of spectator rage may foster manifest and/or latent positive outcomes as well (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1094670511428166">Fisk et al. 2010</xref>). For example, rage’s occurrence creates an obvious need for personnel to monitor and address incidents of hostility that can manifest itself as employment opportunities or the development of innovative surveillance systems and technology. At the very least, rage’s repeated incidence signals the need for change in handling spectator participation at the sport venue. Furthermore, latent benefits ensuing from fan rage may exist that include an affirmation of the ideal spectator role through a contrast effect with the role embodied by the misbehaving fan, or a growth in the study of and education about rage phenomena that contributes to behavioral knowledge in general. Clearly, other positive outcomes might be identified when carefully considering the occurrence of spectator rage.</p>
<p>It is also possible that some of the rage treatments found in sport and other service enterprises favorably impact customer satisfaction and revenue. For example, customers are sometimes willing to pay a premium for access to family only seating sections in sport venues or to become a favored customer with special membership access to organizational services and information. Similarly, improved queuing methods and various amenities (e.g., fans, heaters, spacious aisles, and restrooms) at a service site may improve customers’ experience and the likelihood of future patronage. In addition, efforts to improve security may deter vandalism against facility features, thereby reducing maintenance costs while enhancing the servicescape overall.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-1094670511428166">
<title>Future Research Directions</title>
<p>The research propositions posed in the article identify various factors linked to the likelihood of dissatisfying service encounters that may explode into rage filled episodes and provide direction for empirical research into the phenomenon of customer rage. Additional rage-related research should explore some very basic issues that are pertinent to service practitioners. Beyond the societal costs associated with raging customers, other costs exist. For instance, research is needed to monetize the financial costs associated with rage incidents in terms of the outlay needed to manage rage and the lower revenue potential that may result from its occurrence. In general, studies that assess the size and scope of the impact of rage on a firm’s bottom line are desirable.</p>
<p>Also needed is research that examines the strength of the potential triggers of rage incidents, whether it is fan rage or rage associated with some other type of service. At what point might single rage intensifiers reach a threshold prompting customer action detrimental to the service enterprise? In what combination are triggers most potent and is it worth the expense to reduce or lock down some triggers and not others? Efforts that examine the potency of various rage triggers and the extent to which they reside in different sports and/or service industries might help pinpoint those most susceptible to rage. In this respect, service blueprints that identify rage fail points might be developed as tools to aid practitioners by clarifying where money should be allocated to curtail rage,s incidence, for example, increasing the presence of security personnel, developing proactive messaging to promote appropriate customer behavior, or servicescape redesign to alleviate long queues or frustrating waits.</p>
<p>Other investigations should examine how rage impacts employee and customer satisfaction and the service’s brand’ image, as well as study the effect specific recovery programs have on dealing with the aftermath of rage incidents. For instance, while enraged customers are likely to perceive the encounter in a less positive light, how does a rage incident impact the perceptions of other customers who witnessed the episode? Are there sustained consequences affecting future patronage patterns or negative word of mouth? Such information is desirable as a critical first step in designing recovery systems that minimize long-term damage to the sport or service enterprise.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-1094670511428166">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Spectator rage is a complex phenomenon that shares some common underpinnings with customer rage in general and possesses some aspects that are unique to spectator sport. The occurrence of rage in any specific service type is likely to be comprised of shared and unique features that pose a myriad of challenges for those concerned with the deleterious consequences of aggressive patron behavior. However, for service encounters that create an emotional connection with the customer, it may be impractical (if not impossible) for organizations to completely eliminate hostile behavior from the customer experience; this is certainly true with respect to spectator sport. In those situations, organizations are faced with difficult decisions regarding what <italic>can</italic> be done to control the potential for rage and what <italic>should</italic> be done to control it while still preserving the essence of the interactive service experience. In the preceding pages, the 4-Ts of Customer Rage framework was employed to systematically categorize and examine these issues with respect to spectator sport to enhance our knowledge of both fan rage and customer rage at large. While specific solutions for managing the incidence of rage are likely to be driven by the resources and needs of each organization individually, we believe that organizations can benefit from a comprehensive plan of attack that we hope our treatment may facilitate.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1094670511428166">
<label>1.</label>
<p>While not a subject of this discussion, it bears noting that security personnel at sport venues may also be a Target of rage. For example, a number of recent incidents at Italian soccer matches have been attributed to conflict between Italian youth and police. In such instances, the sporting event provides a vehicle for the expression of rage toward social concerns, political issues, or the like.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>Craig A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>), <article-title>“Heat and Violence,”</article-title> <source>Current Directions in Psychological Science</source>, <volume>10</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="author">APAOnline</collab> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Control Anger–Before It Controls You,”</article-title> <source>American Psychological Association</source>, <comment>(accessed February 2, 2009), [available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.apa.org/topics/controlanger.html">http://www.apa.org/topics/controlanger.html</ext-link>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Associated Press</collab> (<year>2005</year>), <article-title>“Italy Cracks Down on Soccer Violence,”</article-title> <comment>(accessed April 14, 2009), [available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="nbcsports.msnbc.com">nbcsports.msnbc.com</ext-link>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bandura</surname>
<given-names>Albert</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>), <source>Social Foundations of Thought and Action</source>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bandura</surname>
<given-names>Albert</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>), <source>Social Learning Theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bartholow</surname>
<given-names>Bruce D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Heinz</surname>
<given-names>Adrienne</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <article-title>“Alcohol Aggression without Consumption,”</article-title> <source>Psychological Science</source>, <volume>17</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Belk</surname>
<given-names>Russell. W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>), <article-title>“Situational Variables and Consumer Behavior,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source>, <volume>2</volume> (<month>December</month>), <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Berkowitz</surname>
<given-names>Leonard</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993a</year>), <source>Aggression</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Berkowitz</surname>
<given-names>Leonard</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993b</year>), <source>Aggression: Its Causes, Consequences and Control</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bitner</surname>
<given-names>Mary Jo</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>), <article-title>“Servicescapes: The Impact of Physical Surroundings on Customers and Employees,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing</source>, <volume>56</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bonk</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Bears Put Brakes on Tailgaters’ Partying,”</article-title> <source>Los Angeles Times</source>, <month>August</month> <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>D2</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Booms</surname>
<given-names>Bernard H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bitner</surname>
<given-names>Mary Jo</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>), <article-title>“Marketing Strategies and Organizational Structures for Service Firms,”</article-title> in <source>Marketing of Services</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Donnelly</surname>
<given-names>J. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>George</surname>
<given-names>W. R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Marketing Association</publisher-name>, <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bougie</surname>
<given-names>Roger</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pieters</surname>
<given-names>Rik</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zeelenberg</surname>
<given-names>Marcel</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>), <article-title>“Angry Customers Don’t Come Back, They Get Even: The Experience and Behavioral Implications of Anger and Dissatisfaction in Services,”</article-title> <source>Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science</source>, <volume>31</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>393</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bowen</surname>
<given-names>David E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>Benjamin</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>), <article-title>“Boundary- Spanning Role Employees and the Service Encounter: Some Guidelines for Management and Research,”</article-title> in <source>The Service Encounter</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Czepiel</surname>
<given-names>J. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Solomon</surname>
<given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Surprenant</surname>
<given-names>C. F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds. <publisher-loc>Lexington, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lexington Books</publisher-name>, <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Branscombe</surname>
<given-names>Nyla. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wann</surname>
<given-names>Daniel L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>), <article-title>“Collective Self-Esteem Consequences of Outgroup Derogation When a Valued Social Identity is on Trial,”</article-title> <source>European Journal of Social Psychology</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>641</fpage>–<lpage>657</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bredemeier</surname>
<given-names>Brenda Jo</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shields</surname>
<given-names>David L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Horn</surname>
<given-names>Jack C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>), <article-title>“Values and Violence in Sports Today”</article-title> <source>Psychology Today</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>Gary T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. (<year>2003</year>), <article-title>“Leaders Seek Behavior Shift after Sportsmanship Summit,”</article-title> <source>The NCAA News</source>, <comment>March 3</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>Guian L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goodwin</surname>
<given-names>Frederick K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bunney</surname>
<given-names>Wilson E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>), <article-title>“Human Aggression and Suicide: Their Relationship to Neuropsychiatric Diagnoses and Serotonin Metabolism,”</article-title> In <source>Serotonin in Biological Psychiatry</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>Beng T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schoolar</surname>
<given-names>Joseph. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Usdin</surname>
<given-names>Earl</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Raven Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bushman</surname>
<given-names>Brad J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Morgan C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>Craig C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>), <article-title>“Is the Curve Relating Temperature to Aggression Linear or Curvilinear? Assaults and Temperature in Minneapolis Reexamined,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>89</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bushman</surname>
<given-names>Brad J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>Harris M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>), <article-title>“Effects of Alcohol on Human Aggression: An Integrative Research Review,”</article-title> <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>107</volume>, <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cary</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dotinga</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Comarow</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>), <article-title>“Rescuing Children’s Games from Crazed Coaches and Parents,”</article-title> <source>U.S. News and World Report</source>, <volume>136</volume> (<issue>20</issue>), <fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">CNN.com</collab> (<year>2005</year>), <article-title>“FIFA fine Swiss after Fans Protest,”</article-title> <comment>(accessed September 26)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Coakley</surname>
<given-names>Jay. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <source>Sport and Society: Issues and Controversies</source>, <edition>10th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Coakley</surname>
<given-names>Jay. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>), <source>Sport in Society: Issues and Controversies</source>, <edition>6th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>St. Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Times Mirror/Mosby</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Deffenbacher</surname>
<given-names>Jerry J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lynch</surname>
<given-names>Rebekah S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Oetting</surname>
<given-names>Eugene R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Swaim</surname>
<given-names>Randall C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>), <article-title>“The Driving Anger Expression Inventory: A Measure of How People Express Their Anger on the Road,”</article-title> <source>Behavior Research and Therapy</source>, <volume>40</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>737</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>de Rivera</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>“The Structure of Anger,”</article-title> In <source>Conceptual Encounter: A Method for the Exploration of Human Experience</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>de Rivera</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> ed. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University Press of America</publisher-name>, <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Elmore</surname>
<given-names>Charles</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>), <article-title>“An Image Problem,”</article-title> <source>The Palm Beach Post</source>, <issue>November</issue>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1B</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>End</surname>
<given-names>Christian M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dietz-Ulher</surname>
<given-names>Beth</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harrick</surname>
<given-names>Elizabeth A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jacquemotte</surname>
<given-names>Lindy</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>), <article-title>“Identifying with Winners”: A Re-examination of Sport Fans’</article-title> <source>Tendency to BIRG, <italic>Journal of Applied Social Psychology</italic>
</source>, <volume>32</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>1017</fpage>–<lpage>1030</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eroglu</surname>
<given-names>Sevgin A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Machleit</surname>
<given-names>Karen</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>), <article-title>“An Empirical Study of Retail Crowding,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Retailing</source>, <volume>66</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">ESPN.go.com</collab> (<year>2010</year>), <article-title>“MLB Attendance Report - 2010,”</article-title> <comment>(accessed March 17, 2011), [available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://espn.go.com/mlb/attendance/_/year/2010">http://espn.go.com/mlb/attendance/_/year/2010</ext-link>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fisk</surname>
<given-names>Ray</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grove</surname>
<given-names>Stephen J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>Lloyd C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Keeffe</surname>
<given-names>Dominique A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Daunt</surname>
<given-names>Kate L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Russell-Bennett</surname>
<given-names>Rebekah</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wirtz</surname>
<given-names>Jochen</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>), <article-title>“Customers Behaving Badly: A State of the Art Review, Research Agenda and Implications for Practitioners,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Services Marketing</source>, <volume>24</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fisk</surname>
<given-names>Raymond P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grove</surname>
<given-names>Stephen J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>John</surname>
<given-names>Joby</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <source>Interactive Services Marketing</source>, <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Houghton Mifflin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fleming</surname>
<given-names>John H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Coffman</surname>
<given-names>Curt</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harter</surname>
<given-names>James K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>), <article-title>“Manage Your Human Sigma,”</article-title> <source>Harvard Business Review</source>, <volume>83</volume>
<issue>(July/August)</issue>, <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Friedman</surname>
<given-names>Meyer</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>), <source>Type A Behavior: Its Diagnosis and Treatment</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Plenum Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fullerton</surname>
<given-names>Ronald. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Punj</surname>
<given-names>Girish N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>), <article-title>“Repercussions of Promoting an Ideology of Consumption: Consumer Misbehavior,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Business Research</source>, <volume>57</volume> (<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>1249</fpage>–<lpage>1259</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fullerton</surname>
<given-names>Ronald. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Punj</surname>
<given-names>Girish N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>), <article-title>“Choosing to Misbehave: A Structural Model of Aberrant Consumer Behavior,”</article-title> <source>Advances in Consumer Research</source>, Vol. <volume>20</volume>, <publisher-loc>L. McAlister and M. L. Rothschild, eds. Provo, UT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Association for Consumer Research</publisher-name>, <fpage>570</fpage>–<lpage>574</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gardner</surname>
<given-names>Meryl. P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>), <article-title>“Mood States and Consumer Behavior: A Critical Review,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source>, <volume>12</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Geen</surname>
<given-names>Russell G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McCown</surname>
<given-names>Eugene J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>), <article-title>“Effects of Noise and Attack on Aggression and Physiological Arousal,”</article-title> <source>Motivation and Emotion</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goode</surname>
<given-names>Erich</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <source>Deviant Behavior</source>, <edition>8th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice-Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grainer</surname>
<given-names>Marc</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>), <article-title>“First Results of the 2004 National Customer Rage Study: A Case of Customer Rage Unassuaged,”</article-title> <comment>(accessed April 1, 2009), [available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.customercaremc.com">www.customercaremc.com</ext-link>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Greyser</surname>
<given-names>Stephen A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>), <article-title>“Consumers: Alpha and Omega of Marketing,”</article-title> in <source>Consumer Behavior Knowledge for Effective Sports and Event Marketing</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Kahle</surname>
<given-names>Lynn R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Close</surname>
<given-names>Angeline G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge, xiii-xviii</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grove</surname>
<given-names>Stephen J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dorsch</surname>
<given-names>Michael J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hopkins</surname>
<given-names>Christopher D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>), <article-title>“Assessing the Longitudinal Robustness of Spectators’ Perceptions of the Functions of Sport: Implications for Sport Marketers,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing Theory and Practice</source>, <volume>20</volume> (<issue>winter</issue>), <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grove</surname>
<given-names>Stephen J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fisk</surname>
<given-names>Raymond P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Joby John</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>), <article-title>“Surviving in the Age of Rage,”</article-title> <source>Marketing Management</source>, <volume>13</volume> <comment>(March/April)</comment>, <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grove</surname>
<given-names>Stephen J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fisk</surname>
<given-names>Raymond P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>), <article-title>“The Impact of Other Customers on Service Encounters: A Critical Incident Examination of ‘Getting Along’,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Retailing</source>, <volume>73</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Guerin</surname>
<given-names>Bernard</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>), <article-title>“Religious Behaviors as Strategies for Organizing Groups of People: A Social Contingency Analysis,”</article-title> <source>Behavior Analyst</source>, <volume>21</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Guerin</surname>
<given-names>Bernard</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>), <source>Analyzing Social Behavior: Behavior Analysis and the Social Sciences</source>. <publisher-loc>Reno, NV</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Context Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Haeckel</surname>
<given-names>Stephen H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Carbone</surname>
<given-names>Lewis P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>Leonard L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>), <article-title>“How to Lead the Customer Experience,”</article-title> <source>Marketing Management</source>, <volume>12</volume> <comment>(January/February)</comment>, <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>Lloyd C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ogbonna</surname>
<given-names>Emmanuel</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“The Dynamics Underlying Service Firm-Customer Relationships: Insights from a Study of English Premier Soccer Fans,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Services Research</source>, <volume>10</volume> (<issue>4</issue>) <fpage>302</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>Lloyd C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>Kate L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>), <article-title>“Jaycustomer Behavior: An Exploration of Types and Motives in the Hospitality Industry,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Services Marketing</source>, <volume>18</volume>
<issue>(4/5)</issue>, <fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>Lloyd C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>Kate L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>), <article-title>“The Consequences of Dysfunctional Customer Behavior,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Service Research</source>, <volume>6</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hart</surname>
<given-names>Christopher W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>Michael D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>), <article-title>“Growing the Trust Relationship,”</article-title> <source>Marketing Management</source>, <volume>8</volume> (<issue>Spring</issue>), <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Haynes</surname>
<given-names>Paula J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>), <article-title>“Hating to Wait: Managing the Final Service Encounter,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Services Marketing</source>, <volume>4</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hirschman</surname>
<given-names>Elizabeth C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holbrook</surname>
<given-names>Morris B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>), <article-title>“Hedonic Consumption: Emerging Concepts, Methods, and Propositions,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing</source>, <volume>46</volume> (<issue>Summer</issue>), <fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hirt</surname>
<given-names>Edward R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Clarkson</surname>
<given-names>Joshua J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>), <article-title>“The Pscyhology of Fandom: Understanding the Etiology, Motives, and Implications of Fanship,”</article-title> in <source>Consumer Behavior Knowledge for Effective Sports and Event Marketing</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Kahle</surname>
<given-names>Lynn R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Close</surname>
<given-names>Angeline G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Holmes</surname>
<given-names>Davis A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Will</surname>
<given-names>Michael J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>), <article-title>“Expression of Interpersonal Aggression by Angered and Nonangered Persons with Type A and Type B Behavior Patterns,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>48</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>723</fpage>–<lpage>727</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hui</surname>
<given-names>Michael. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tse</surname>
<given-names>David K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>), <article-title>“What to Tell Customers in Waits of Different Lengths: An Integrative Model of Service Evaluation,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing</source>, <volume>80</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hui</surname>
<given-names>Michael. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bateson</surname>
<given-names>John E. G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>), <article-title>“Perceived Control and the Effects of Crowding and Consumer Choice on the Service Experience,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source>, <volume>18</volume> ,<comment>(September)</comment>, <fpage>174</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hughson</surname>
<given-names>John</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>), <article-title>“Among the Thugs,”</article-title> <source>International Review of the Sociology of Sport</source>, <volume>33</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hunt</surname>
<given-names>Kenneth H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bristol</surname>
<given-names>Terry</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bashaw</surname>
<given-names>Ralph Edward</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>), <article-title>“A Conceptual Approach to Classifying Sports Fans,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Services Marketing</source>, <volume>13</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>Jeffrey M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Latane</surname>
<given-names>Bibb</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>), <article-title>“All Alone in Front of All Those People: Stage Fright as a Function of Number and Type of Co-Performers and Audience,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>40</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kahle</surname>
<given-names>Lynn</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Duncan</surname>
<given-names>Marc</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dalakas</surname>
<given-names>Vassilis</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aiken</surname>
<given-names>Damon</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>), <article-title>“The Social Values of Fans for Men’s and Women’s University Basketball,”</article-title> <source>Sport Marketing Quarterly</source>, <volume>10</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kalamas</surname>
<given-names>Maria</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Laroche</surname>
<given-names>Michel</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Makdessian</surname>
<given-names>Lucy</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Reaching the Boiling Point: Consumers’ Negative Reactions to Firm-Attributed Service Failures,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Business Research</source>, <volume>61</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>813</fpage>–<lpage>824</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Keeffe</surname>
<given-names>Dominique</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Russell-Bennett</surname>
<given-names>Rebekah</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <article-title>“An Investigation of Functional and Dysfunctional Consumer Behaviour during Frontline Service Encounters,”</article-title> <source>Australian and New Zealand Marketing Academy (ANZMAC) Proceedings</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Ali</surname>
<given-names>Yunus</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dessel</surname>
<given-names>Maria van</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds. <publisher-loc>Brisbane, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ANZMAC</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kelman</surname>
<given-names>Herbert C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1961</year>), <article-title>“Processes of Opinion Change,”</article-title> <source>Public Opinion Quarterly</source>, <volume>25</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Keeffe</surname>
<given-names>Dominique</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1958</year>), <article-title>“Compliance, Identification and Internalization: Three Processes of Attitude Change,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Conflict Resolution</source>, <volume>2</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kitsantonis</surname>
<given-names>Niki</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Soccer: Greece Wrestles with Fan Violence,”</article-title> <source>The New York Times</source>, <comment>(accessed April 19), [available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/sports/19iht-GREEKS.1.5350626.html">http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/sports/19iht-GREEKS.1.5350626.html</ext-link>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>King</surname>
<given-names>Jesse</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kahle</surname>
<given-names>Lynn R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Close</surname>
<given-names>Angeline G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>), <article-title>“Introduction: The Study of Sports and Events Consumer Behavior,”</article-title> in <source>Consumer Behavior Knowledge for Effective Sports and Event Marketing</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Kahle</surname>
<given-names>Lynn R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Close</surname>
<given-names>Angeline G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Knowles</surname>
<given-names>Patricia A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grove</surname>
<given-names>Stephen J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pickett</surname>
<given-names>Gregory M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>), <article-title>“Mood and the Service Customer,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Services Marketing</source>, <volume>7</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ko</surname>
<given-names>Yong Jae</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>James</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cattani</surname>
<given-names>Kevin</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pastore</surname>
<given-names>Donna</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>), <article-title>“Assessment of Event Quality in Major Spectator Sports,”</article-title> <source>Managing Service Quality</source>, <volume>20</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>304</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>Piyush</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kalwani</surname>
<given-names>Manohar</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dada</surname>
<given-names>Maqbool</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>), <article-title>“The Impact of Waiting Time Guarantees on Customers’ Waiting Experiences,”</article-title> <source>Marketing Science</source>, <volume>16</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>314</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Langeard</surname>
<given-names>Eric</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bateson</surname>
<given-names>John E. G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lovelock</surname>
<given-names>Christopher H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eiglier</surname>
<given-names>Pierre</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>), <source>Services Marketing: New Insights from Consumers and Managers</source>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Marketing Science Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lazarus</surname>
<given-names>Richard S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Folkman</surname>
<given-names>Susan</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>), <source>Stress, Appraisal and Coping</source>, <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lovelock</surname>
<given-names>Christopher H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wirtz</surname>
<given-names>Jochen</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>), <source>Services Marketing: People Technology and Strategy</source>. <edition>7th ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Upper Saddle River, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lovelock</surname>
<given-names>Christopher H.</given-names>
</name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>), <source>Product Plus</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lovelock</surname>
<given-names>Christopher H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>), <article-title>“Classifying Services to Gain Strategic Marketing Insight,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Marketing</source>, <volume>47</volume> (<issue>Summer</issue>), <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lovelock</surname>
<given-names>Christopher H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>), <article-title>“Why Marketing Management Needs to be Different for Services,”</article-title> in <source>Marketing of Services</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Donnelly</surname>
<given-names>J. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>George</surname>
<given-names>W. R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Marketing Association</publisher-name>, <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lusch</surname>
<given-names>Robert F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vargo</surname>
<given-names>Stephen L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <article-title>‘‘Service-Dominant Logic: Reactions, Reflections and Refinements,’’</article-title> <source>Marketing Theory</source>, <volume>6</volume> <comment>(September)</comment>, <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Machleit</surname>
<given-names>Karen A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eroglu</surname>
<given-names>Sevgin A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mantel</surname>
<given-names>Susan P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>), <article-title>“Retail Crowding and Shopping Satisfaction: What Modifies This Relationship?”</article-title> <source>Journal of Consumer Psychology</source>, <volume>9</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Madrigal</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>), <article-title>“A Review of Team Identification and Its Influence on Consumers’ Responses Toward Corporate Sponsors,”</article-title> in <source>Sport Marketing and the Psychology of Marketing Communication</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Kahle</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Riley</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>, <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mahari</surname>
<given-names>Ace-Jensen</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <source>BPD and Rage</source>. <publisher-name>Phoenix Rising Publications</publisher-name>, <comment>(accessed February 20, 2009), [available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.phoenixrisingbooks.com">www.phoenixrisingbooks.com</ext-link>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>Charles L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pranter</surname>
<given-names>Charles A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>), <article-title>“Compatibility Management: Customer-to-Customer Relationships in Service Environments,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Services Marketing</source>, <volume>3</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Match</surname>
<given-names>Timothy A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>Associate Athletic Director of Marketing and Promotion at Clemson University, Personal Interview</article-title>, <comment>October 15, 2007</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McCarthy</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Enforcing New Fan Code Shapes Up as Challenge,”</article-title> <source>USA Today</source>, <comment>August 6, Sec. C, 10</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr84-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McColl-Kennedy</surname>
<given-names>Janet. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Patterson</surname>
<given-names>Paul</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>Amy K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brady</surname>
<given-names>Michael K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>), <article-title>“Customer Rage Episodes: Emotions, Expressions and Behaviors,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Retailing</source>, <volume>85</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>222</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr85-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McColl-Kennedy</surname>
<given-names>Janet. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>Amy K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <article-title>“Customer Emotions in Service Failure and Recovery Encounters,”</article-title> in <source>Research on Emotions in Organizations</source>, <volume>Vol. 2</volume>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Zerbe</surname>
<given-names>Wilfred J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ashkanasky</surname>
<given-names>Neal M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hartel</surname>
<given-names>Charmine E. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam, The Netherlands</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>JA1 (Elsevier)</publisher-name>, <fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr86-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McGuire</surname>
<given-names>Kelly A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kimes</surname>
<given-names>Sheryl E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <article-title>“The Perceived Fairness of Waitlist Management Techniques for Restaurants,”</article-title> <source>Cornell Hotel and Restaurant Administration Quarterly</source>, <volume>47</volume> (<issue>May</issue>), <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr87-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McKelvey</surname>
<given-names>Stephen M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>), <article-title>“The Growth in Marketing Alliances between US Professional Sport and Legalised Gambling Entities: Are We Putting Sport Consumers at Risk?”</article-title> <source>Sport Management Review</source>, <volume>7</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr88-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Melnick</surname>
<given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>), <article-title>“Searching for Sociability in the Stands: A Theory of Sports Spectating,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Sport Management</source>, <volume>7</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr89-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gerard</surname>
<given-names>Moeller F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dougherty</surname>
<given-names>Donald M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>), <article-title>“Antisocial Personality Disorder, Alcohol and Aggression,”</article-title> <source>Alcohol Research and Health</source>, <volume>25</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr90-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mullin</surname>
<given-names>Bernard</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hardy</surname>
<given-names>Stephen</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sutton</surname>
<given-names>William</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>), <source>Sport Marketing</source>, <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Windsor, ON</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Human Kinetics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr91-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Muniz</surname>
<given-names>Albert M.</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
<name>
<surname>O’Guinn</surname>
<given-names>Thomas C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>), <article-title>“Brand Community,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source>, <volume>27</volume> <comment>(March)</comment>, <fpage>412</fpage>–<lpage>432</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr92-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">MyMindField.Com</collab> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Anger Management,”</article-title> <comment>(accessed February 20, 2009), [available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://topcondition.com/images/mymindfield/anger_management.html">http://topcondition.com/images/mymindfield/anger_management.html</ext-link>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr93-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nagel</surname>
<given-names>Kim</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>), <article-title>“NFL Pat-Down Policy at Issue in Cincy,”</article-title> <source>Cox News Service</source>, <comment>October 19</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr94-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>O’Brien</surname>
<given-names>Richard</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hersch</surname>
<given-names>Hank</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>), <article-title>“Go Figure,”</article-title> <source>Sports Illustrated</source>, <volume>88</volume> (<issue>22</issue>), <fpage>22</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr95-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Parke</surname>
<given-names>Adrian</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Griffiths</surname>
<given-names>Mark</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>), <article-title>“Aggressive Behaviour in Slot Machine Gamblers: A Preliminary Observational Study.”</article-title> <source>Psychological Reports</source>, <volume>95</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr96-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pfohl</surname>
<given-names>Stephen J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>), <source>Images of Deviance and Social Control</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr97-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Prahalad</surname>
<given-names>C. K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
<given-names>Venkatram</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>), <article-title>“Co-opting Customer Competence,”</article-title> <source>Harvard Business Review</source>, <volume>78</volume> (<comment>January</comment>), <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr98-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pratt</surname>
<given-names>Michael G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Teresa Cardador</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>), <article-title>“Identification Management and Its Bases: Bridging Management and Marketing Perspectives through a Focus on Affiliation Dimensions,”</article-title> <source>Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science</source>, <volume>34</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>174</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr99-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rafaeli</surname>
<given-names>Anat</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barron</surname>
<given-names>Greg</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Haber</surname>
<given-names>Keren</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>), <article-title>“The Effects of Queue Structure on Attitudes,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Services Research</source>, <volume>5</volume> (<comment>November</comment>), <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr100-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ryan</surname>
<given-names>Nate</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Gordon Ventures into Earnhardt Turf,”</article-title> <source>USA Today</source>, <comment>April , 27</comment>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr101-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sanminiatelli</surname>
<given-names>Maria</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Fans could be barred from Italian Soccer Stadiums if Security not Improved,”</article-title> <source>Associated Press Financial Wire</source>, <comment>February 5</comment>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr102-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shellenbarger</surname>
<given-names>Sue</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>), <article-title>“How to Keep Your Cool in Angry Times,”</article-title> <source>WSJ.com</source>
<comment>(accessed September 22)</comment> [<comment>available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704129204575505943489630732.html">http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704129204575505943489630732.html</ext-link>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr103-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Seahawks</surname>
<given-names>Seattle</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <comment>(accessed June 1, 2009), [available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.seattleseahawks.com">www.seattleseahawks.com</ext-link>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr104-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shank</surname>
<given-names>Matthew D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Sports Marketing: A Strategic Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Upper Saddle River, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr105-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shaver</surname>
<given-names>Phillip</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>Judith</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kirson</surname>
<given-names>Donald</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>O’Connor</surname>
<given-names>Cary</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>), <article-title>“Emotion Knowledge: Further Exploration of a Prototype Approach,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>52</volume> (<issue>June</issue>), <fpage>1061</fpage>–<lpage>1086</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr106-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>Amy K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bolton</surname>
<given-names>Ruth N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>), <article-title>“The Effect of Customer Emotional Responses to Service Failures on Their Recovery Effort Evaluations and Satisfaction Judgments,”</article-title> <source>Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science</source>, <volume>30</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr107-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Spaaij</surname>
<given-names>Ramon</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>), <article-title>“Men Like Us, Boys Like Them: Violence, Masculinity, and Collective Identity in Football Hooliganism,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Sport and Social Issues</source>, <volume>32</volume> <comment>(November)</comment>, <fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>392</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr108-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Spitz</surname>
<given-names>Rueben T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hillbrand</surname>
<given-names>Marc</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>), <article-title>“Serum Cholesterol Levels and Aggressive Tendencies,”</article-title> <source>Psychological Reports</source>, <volume>74</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>622</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr109-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Sports Network</collab> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Series A Play Suspended after Fan Violence on Friday,”</article-title> <comment>February 3</comment>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr110-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stokolos</surname>
<given-names>Daniel</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1972</year>), <article-title>“On the Distinction between Density and Crowding: Some Implications for Future Research,”</article-title> <source>Psychological Review</source>, <volume>79</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr111-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stone</surname>
<given-names>Michael H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>), <source>Abnormalities of Personality: Within and Beyond the Realm of Treatment</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>W.W. Norton</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr112-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Street and Smith’s Sport Business Journal</collab> (<year>2002</year>), <article-title>“About Us—The Sports Industry,”</article-title> <comment>March 11</comment>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr113-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sydney Morning</surname>
<given-names>Herald</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Heat Dampens Fears of More Tennis Violence,”</article-title> <comment>January 16</comment>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr114-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>van Doorn</surname>
<given-names>Jenny</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Katherine</surname>
<given-names>N. Lemon</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mittal</surname>
<given-names>Vikas</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nass</surname>
<given-names>Stephan</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pick</surname>
<given-names>Doreén</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pirner</surname>
<given-names>Peter</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Verhoef</surname>
<given-names>Peter C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>), <article-title>“Customer Engagement Behavior: Theoretical Foundations and Research Directions,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Service Research</source>, <volume>13</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>266</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr115-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Varian</surname>
<given-names>Bill</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>), <article-title>“Fan Challenges Legality of Stadium Patdowns,”</article-title> <source>St. Petersburg Times</source>, <comment>October 14</comment>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr116-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wann</surname>
<given-names>Daniel L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hayes</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McLean</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pullen</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>), <article-title>“Sport Team Identification and Willingness to Consider Anonymous Acts of Hostile Aggression,”</article-title> <source>Aggressive Behavior</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>406</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr117-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wann</surname>
<given-names>Daniel L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Melnick</surname>
<given-names>Merrill J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Russell</surname>
<given-names>Gordon W.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pease</surname>
<given-names>Dale G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>), <source>Sport Fans: The Psychology and Social Impact of Spectators</source>, <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr118-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wann</surname>
<given-names>Daniel L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Branscombe</surname>
<given-names>Nyla R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>), <article-title>“Die-Hard and Fair-Weather Fans: Effects of Identification on BIRGing and CORFing Tendencies,”</article-title> <source>Journal of Sport and Social Issues</source>, <volume>14</volume> (<comment>September</comment>), <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr119-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Washington Post</collab> (<year>2007</year>), <article-title>“Court Allows Pat-Downs To Resume at Bucs Games,”</article-title> <comment>June 28</comment>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr120-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weiberg</surname>
<given-names>Steve</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>), <article-title>“Rowdy Fans Concern College Officials,”</article-title> <source>USA Today</source>, <comment>November 15</comment>, <fpage>1</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr121-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Weisman</surname>
<given-names>Larry</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>), <article-title>“Patriot Fans Must Play by the Rules, Too,”</article-title> <source>USA Today</source>, <comment>August 30</comment>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr122-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wenner</surname>
<given-names>Lawrence A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gantz</surname>
<given-names>Walter</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>), <article-title>“Watching Sports on Television: Audience Experience, Fanship, Gender and Marriage,”</article-title> in <source>MediaSport</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Wenner</surname>
<given-names>L. A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> ed. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr123-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wortham</surname>
<given-names>Jenna</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stelter</surname>
<given-names>Brian</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>), <article-title>“Latest Move Gets Netflix More Wrath,”</article-title> <comment>(accessed October 3, 2011)</comment>, [<comment>available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.NewYorkTimes.com">www.NewYorkTimes.com</ext-link>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr124-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zillman</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>), <article-title>“The Psychology of Suspense in Dramatic Exposition,”</article-title> in <source>Suspense: Conceptualizations, Theoretical Analyses, and Empirical Explorations</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Vorderer</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wulff</surname>
<given-names>H. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Friedrichsen</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>, <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>231</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr125-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zillman</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Paulus</surname>
<given-names>P. B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>), <article-title>“Spectators: Reactions to Sport Events and Effect on Athletic Performance,”</article-title> in <source>Handbook of Research on Sports Psychology</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Singer</surname>
<given-names>R. N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Murphey</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tennant</surname>
<given-names>L. K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>, <fpage>600</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr126-1094670511428166">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zimbardo</surname>
<given-names>P.G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>), <article-title>“The Human Choice: Individuation, Reason, and Order Versus Deindividuation, Impulse, and Chaos,”</article-title> in <source>Nebraska Symposium on Motivation</source>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Arnold</surname>
<given-names>W. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Levine</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> eds. <publisher-loc>Lincoln, NB</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Nebraska Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>