<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">USJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spusj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Urban Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0042-0980</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1360-063X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0042098011410336</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0042098011410336</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Transport Impacts of Clustered Development in Beijing: Compact Development versus Overconcentration</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Jiawen</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Qing</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Jinzhen</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Canfei</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0042098011410336">Jiawen Yang is in the School of City and Regional Planning, Georgia Institute of Technology, 204 Architecture Building East, 245 4th Street NW, Atlanta, Georgia, GA 30332, USA. E-mail: <email>jy78@mail.gatech.edu</email>.</corresp>
<corresp id="corresp2-0042098011410336">Qing Shen is in the Department of Urban Design and Planning, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA. E-mail: <email>qs@u.washington.edu</email>.</corresp>
<corresp id="corresp3-0042098011410336">Jinzhen Shen is in the Beijing Municipal Commission of Urban Planning, Xingzheng No. 23, Daxing District, Beijing, 102600, China. E-mail: <email>shjzh@bjghw.gov.cn</email>.</corresp>
<corresp id="corresp4-0042098011410336">Canfei He is in the Department of Urban and Economic Geography, Peking University, College of Urban and Environmental Sciences, No.5 Yiheyuan Road, Haidian District, Beijing, 100871, China. E-mail: <email>hecanfei@urban.pku.edu.cn</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>49</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>1315</fpage>
<lpage>1331</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2011 Urban Studies Journal Limited</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Urban Studies Journal Limited</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This research aims to inform the compact city discussion with a case study of Beijing, where urban planning has emphasised clustered suburban development in the past half-century. It uses three decades of census data to describe Beijing’s spatial development trajectory and a household survey to assess its transport impacts. The research reveals an overconcentration of urban activities as a result of the featureless expansion of the central built-up area and the absorption of the suburban clusters; and, a lengthened commuting time stemming from the observed spatial development pattern. Beijing’s experience adds to the existing literature by informing the search for good city forms in urban areas of high density. It is essential to differentiate compact development from overconcentration when combating sprawling development. Developing and maintaining suburban nodal characteristics around public transit can reduce travel in high-density urban areas.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0042098011410336" sec-type="intro">
<title>1. Introduction</title>
<p>One aspect of urban planning characterises spatial development in urban China: the emphasis of moderate to high-density suburban cluster development. This strategy has been employed not only during the period of the planned economy, but also in today’s market economy. However, there has been no systematic study of the transport impacts of the persistent planning efforts for clustered development in Chinese cities. Revealing these transport impacts, therefore, can help to explain urban transport in China’s metropolitan cities where worsening congestion calls for long-term demand management strategies. In addition, the Chinese lesson is more than just another case study. It may well inform the debate on compact city development and policy-making in other places.</p>
<p>For example, spatial containment strategies in American metropolitan areas have been viewed as a potential solution to undesirable social and environmental impacts of sprawling suburban development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0042098011410336">Nelson <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0042098011410336">Wheeler, 2008</xref>), particularly when compact city development is coupled with a suitable planning process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0042098011410336">Neuman, 2005</xref>). The US stories focus on the debate whether and how the addition of a spatial containment strategy in a low-density context can reduce automobile-based travel and improve air quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0042098011410336">National Research Council, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0042098011410336">Cervero and Duncan, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0042098011410336">Stone <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0042098011410336">Gordon and Richardson, 1997</xref>). Empirical studies tend to confirm the transport and health benefits of several land use strategies, including densification, infill development, mixed land use and job–housing balance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0042098011410336">TRB, 2005</xref>). By comparison, the Chinese story could enrich this discussion from another perspective: how a weakened implementation of clustered development in a high-density urban area could affect individual travel and urban transport.</p>
<p>The practice of clustered development in China has been well documented in China’s planning textbooks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0042098011410336">Li, 2005</xref>). In the planned economy, the satellite communities developed during the socialist construction were generally separated from the central built-up areas with greenbelts, which could include agricultural land, forest, parks and lakes. Suburban towns were seldom planned as dormitory communities, but as a group of work unit compounds that included both workplace and residence. Employees could work and live within short distances, and society saved transport costs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0042098011410336">Yang, 2006a</xref>).</p>
<p>The idea of clustered development did not disappear during the transition towards a market economy, but it has been much more weakly implemented. First, the geographical level at which the balance of workplace and residence is evaluated has changed. With the economic foundation evolving towards a market mechanism, employers have been released from the responsibility to house their employees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0042098011410336">Wu, 1996</xref>). There is no need to balance housing and job opportunities around each workplace. Typical suburban settlements are only expected to provide a mixture of job and housing opportunities through land use plans. There is no guarantee that the numbers of job and housing opportunities are comparable.</p>
<p>Secondly, market forces have made it difficult for clustered development to materialise. Evidence exists that incremental urban growth in the suburban areas does not follow city master plans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0042098011410336">Schneider <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>). In Beijing, China’s capital city, the idea of clustered development is embedded in the spatial development strategy called ‘decentralised concentration’, which is detailed in the next section. The public media have attributed Beijing’s congestion to the failure of implementing its spatial development strategies, claiming that the disappearance of suburban clusters and the featureless expansion of the central built-up area have led to severe congestion problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0042098011410336">Zhao and Tian, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>The extent to which Beijing’s spatial development strategy and its implementation success or failure have impacted urban transport has never been systematically studied. This article aims to fill this gap with empirical research, which is then used to inform the dialogue on planning for compact cities in a high-density context. The following sections first examine the spatial development planning and development outcomes in Beijing and then model the commuting impacts of the planning efforts for clustered development. The article ends with a discussion of policy and planning implications for compact city development.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0042098011410336">
<title>2. Spatial Development in Beijing</title>
<p>Beijing lies on the north-eastern edge of the North China Plain. The spatial organisation of the city is characterised by the continuous addition of ring roads. Today’s Beijing has six rings. The first ring circles the Forbidden City, which was the palace of the emperors for three dynasties. Because of development restrictions, this area has a low residential density and relatively few employees. The first ring does not carry heavy traffic and has been kept as local streets. All other ring roads were added either to mitigate existing traffic congestion or to open suburban land for development. Construction of the second ring began in the 1950s and it was completely changed into an urban expressway in 1992. The third ring road was completed in 1994. After that, the fourth and fifth ring roads were added in 2001 and 2003 respectively. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0042098011410336">Figure 1</xref> presents the layout of the five ring roads. The sixth ring was not completed until late 2009 and is not included in the figure.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0042098011410336" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Beijing: five ring roads the and 48 surveyed neighbourhoods in the study area.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0042098011410336-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Today’s Beijing has about 18 million residents and over 10 million residents in the core built-up area, which is served by the five ring roads and other connecting roads. The second ring roughly delineates the boundary of ‘old Beijing’ developed before the Communist party took power in 1949. Development in the 1980s mainly occurred around or within the third ring and seldom went beyond the fourth ring. In the 1990s and thereafter, the fourth and fifth rings have enabled conversion of rural or semi-rural areas into urban landscape, stimulated by a strong demand for housing and office space.</p>
<p>Beijing’s spatial development planning was strongly affected by the multi-nuclei garden city idea and the new town programmes in Britain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0042098011410336">Madge, 1962</xref>). A decentralised concentration strategy has been employed by Beijing’s municipal government when directing spatial development. The basic spatial framework was specified in Beijing’s 1957 master plan, which included the first four ring roads as well as many new suburban communities along the ring roads.</p>
<p>As population growth crowds the existing central built-up area, the municipal government has chosen to build suburban constellations, which are expected to accommodate new growth as well as the outward relocation of existing urban activities. For example, the city’s 1983 master plan specified 10 satellite suburban settlements around today’s fourth or fifth ring roads. In the master plan of 1993, the number of satellite communities increased to 14. Several suburban communities along today’s sixth ring were also included. In the 2005 master plan, the 14 satellite communities were reconfigured to become ‘eleven new cities’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0042098011410336">Zhang, 2009</xref>). The major motivation for this spatial development strategy has been to mitigate overcrowding in the central built-up area and, at the same time, to encourage the re-use of infrastructure and previously developed land and to increase overall access to workplaces and green space.</p>
<p>These communities are linked to the central built-up area with radial roads. They were originally separated from each other and from the central built-up area with greenbelts. These suburban communities were anticipated to accommodate 90 per cent of the total population increase from 1989 to 2010 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0042098011410336">Beijing Transport Commission, 2003</xref>). They are expected to be desirable residential locations for those who work there. Universities and big enterprises have been used as anchor institutes for the suburban development. For example, the town centre of Haidian, which includes Zhongguancui, Peking University and Tsinghua University, was planned to be a suburban community in the plan from the 1950s, but today it has become one of the leading business centres in Beijing.</p>
<p>The implementation of the spatial framework, however, has been subject to increasing criticism. One frequently mentioned ‘implementation failure’ is the disappearance of the greenbelts, which previously separated the suburban clusters from each other and from the central built-up area. The three-dimensional population density maps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0042098011410336">Figure 2</xref>) illustrate this spatial expansion and absorption process in Beijing. The data come from the population censuses of 1982, 1990 and 2000. Population density is calculated for each sub-district (<italic>JieDaoBanShiChu</italic> in Chinese or ‘Street Office’ in literal English translation), which is the smallest administrative unit for census data tabulation. The height of the vertical bar is proportional to population density and all three maps have the same vertical scale. The ring roads are also shown and can be used as a spatial reference for a comparison of the three maps.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0042098011410336" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Three-dimensional visualisation of population density in Beijing, 1982, 1990 and 2000.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0042098011410336-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The first noticeable trend is the outward expansion of the central built-up area. The relatively high-density suburban clusters around the third ring in 1982 became absorbed in 1990. The suburban communities around the fourth ring became absorbed in 2000. This absorption does not increase the density of the pre-existing central built-up area and suburban clusters, but fills the space between with increased population density. As a result, population density in the expanding central built-up area is rather flat. This contrasts with what we observe in typical Western cities, where population density tends to decrease steeply from a small central area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0042098011410336">O’Sullivan, 2003</xref>). Note that this expansion process does not push up the population density within the second ring, even though the density beyond the second ring has increased. Since the overall density gradient appears to be quite flat and density variation decreases with time, the Chinese have nicknamed this pattern of growth <italic>TanDaBing</italic>, which vividly describes the expansion process as an enlarging thick pie.</p>
<p>While Beijing has no doubt experienced significant suburban development beyond the old city core (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0042098011410336">Feng and Zhou, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0042098011410336">Wang and Zhou, 1999</xref>), from the perspective of density variation, the encroachment of greenbelts and the absorption of the satellite constellations make the development outcome more like a high-density monocentric metropolitan city than a multi-nuclei one. Why can Beijing not maintain clustered suburban development despite the persistent planning ideology? Is the decentralised concentration strategy doomed to fail in China’s market economy? Or is it a result of some other poorly co-ordinated choices in Beijing’s spatial development? It is beyond the scope of this article to provide a complete answer. However, it is worth noting that the continuous expansion of Beijing’s central built-up area and the absorption of the suburban clusters are not a purely market-based process, but one conditioned by government strategies of spatial planning and infrastructure investment.</p>
<p>First, those selected suburban clusters are typically too close to the central built-up area to remain as high-density clusters in the market economy. They are only several kilometres away from the pre-existing central built-up area, except for those along the sixth ring. This distance could keep trips contained within the cluster if urban transport is mainly supported by non-motorised modes, as occurred in the planned economy. However, as household income increases and motorised transport becomes more affordable, residents in these communities can easily travel to the central built-up area for work, shopping and entertainment opportunities. Firms also want to stay as close as possible to the central built-up areas to have better access to clients. As a result, the central built-up area has expanded faster than expected. Greenbelts have been gradually encroached and satellite communities are absorbed by the expanding central built-up area.</p>
<p>Some statistics can help to illustrate this situation. During the five-year period from 1997 to 2002, urban land increased by 50 square km annually, about 10 square km of which was the infill development in the central built-up area. During this period, the total constructed floor area was 80 million square metres, 80 per cent of which was in the central built-up area. From 1992 to 2001, the central built-area increased its population share from 58 per cent to 60 per cent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0042098011410336">Beijing Transport Commission, 2003</xref>), instead of experiencing a population decrease.</p>
<p>Secondly, absorption of the suburban clusters is perhaps predetermined because of the associated planning goal. Under Beijing’s spatial development strategy, decentralised suburban development is encouraged because concentration of urban activity in the central built-up area leads to overcrowding. Compared with the central built-up area, suburban clusters are neither better nor equivalent places, but an alternative. Beijing’s municipal government, the metropolitan city government that makes land development plans for the whole urban region, has prioritised infrastructure investment in the central part. The highest quality infrastructure and social services have been supplied there. By contrast, suburban communities have been relatively neglected when receiving municipal investment. In today’s Beijing, the best hospitals, the best public transport services and the best schools are all in the central built-up area. Relatively high-income households have elected to live in a central location rather than in suburban locations. The retail and service industries follow consumer power and concentrate in the central built-up area, too.</p>
<p>Thirdly, the revenue-maximising behaviour of the municipal government in project permitting is in conflict with the idea of contained clustered development. Beijing’s ring roads are only several kilometres apart. With ring roads and radial roads adding accessibility to undeveloped land planned for greenbelts, developers compete for those land parcels that are adjacent to the central built-up area and served by roads. This choice of the private sector is backed by government interest in land-lease revenue. These infill parcels are more likely to be leased with a high land price than those in the suburban communities. The revenue-seeking governments are more likely to prioritise these infill parcels than others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0042098011410336">Yang <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). This fiscally motivated project-permitting fosters a development pattern of flat density rather than contained clusters. How this spatial development leads to some interesting transport outcomes is discussed in the next section.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0042098011410336">
<title>3. Transport Impacts of Beijing’s Spatial Development</title>
<p>The expansion of the central built-up area and the absorption of the suburban communities have been accompanied by increased trip length as travellers look for employment and entertainment opportunities throughout the ever-enlarging urban region. Large volumes of traffic, reaching the capacity limit of existing transport facilities, have increased road congestion. It was reported that bus speed was about 10 km per hour during peak periods. The disappearance of the greenbelts and the overconcentration of urban activities are claimed to be partially responsible for the increases in travel and congestion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0042098011410336">Zhao and Tian, 2004</xref>). If this observation is true, we should see a systematic variation in travel demand by location. Residents in urban districts where clustered development is well implemented should have relatively low travel demand, particularly for commuting. We will examine this hypothesis with a household survey conducted in 2006.</p>
<p>The survey data were collected by John Logan and his research team at Brown University. The survey was conducted to aid our understanding of the dynamics of housing markets, household location and travel behaviour. Coded survey results record detailed information on vehicle ownership, commuting duration and modes, and residence location. The survey covers 48 urban neighbourhoods, with 25 households surveyed in each neighbourhood. The survey data are then used to develop a group of neighbourhood-level indicators, such as average commuting time, mode split (percentages of commutes by various transport modes) and automobile ownership. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0042098011410336">Figure 1</xref> shows the location of the surveyed neighbourhoods. These neighbourhoods are scattered in the central city, the inner suburbs and the outskirts beyond the fifth ring. The survey includes 1499 workers with self-reported commuting time and modes. The average reported one-way commuting time is 36.5 minutes. The mode split is 51 per cent by non-motorised modes (including walking and cycling), 37 per cent by transit (including 34 per cent bus and 3 per cent urban rail) and 12 per cent by driving or taxi.</p>
<p>In a spatial analysis of Beijing’s urban transport based on the same dataset, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042098011410336">Yang (2010)</xref> has found that commuting time and commuting mode split do not vary significantly according to three distance-based location measures: the distance from the surveyed neighbourhood to the geometric centre (Tianmen Square), the distance from the surveyed neighbourhood to the closest job centre and the distance to the nearest subway or urban rail stations. Instead, he found that commuting time and mode split vary according to the age of the neighbourhood: the newer the neighbourhood, the higher the percentage of non-motorised modes (including walking and cycling) and the shorter the commuting time.</p>
<p>The fact that residents of new neighbourhoods have a shorter commuting time in Beijing suggests that Beijing is obviously different from other places that do not have a planning history of clustered suburban development. For example, in American metropolitan areas, residents in relatively new neighbourhoods tend to have longer commutes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0042098011410336">Sultana and Weber, 2007</xref>). This difference suggests a possible linkage between travel demand and the history of urban development and planning in Beijing. The relatively short commuting time in Beijing’s relatively new neighbourhoods might be related to the relatively strong presence of planning efforts for clustered development there.</p>
<p>There is no scientific approach to quantifying the degree of clustered development or measuring the planning effort for clustered development. However, we do know that different areas have kept various aspects of this planning legacy. We divide the whole study area into three zones: the central core area within the second ring; a suburban zone that covers the suburban clusters specified in the 1983 municipal master plan and their immediate proximity; and, a hybrid area between the suburban zone and the central core area. Since the central core area within the second ring was mainly constructed before communist China, it was initially developed without any explicit consideration of clustered development. It was part of the core built-up area before the idea of clustered development was articulated for the first time in 1957. Therefore, it tends to show the least evident legacy of clustered development. In this area, of course, many self-contained work unit compounds were built during the planned economy. However, in the transition towards a market economy, this central area has been subject to significant redevelopment and many of these compounds have been dissolved and lost their self-containment.</p>
<p>By contrast, the suburban zone around the fifth ring road should retain more of a legacy of cluster development because its suburban location makes it less absorbed or affected by the expansion of the central built-up area. Many pre-existing neighbourhoods still keep self-contained travel and activity patterns, despite significant transitions in the past two decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0042098011410336">Zhang, Cai and Chen, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0042098011410336">Zhang, Cai and Zhou, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0042098011410336">Wang and Cai, 2009</xref>). Workers in this zone are expected to have shorter commute times than those in the central area. The hybrid area between the central and suburban zones features a mixture of the two.</p>
<p>The survey data contain commuting time reported by workers. The descriptive statistics in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0042098011410336">Table 1</xref> show a variation of commuting time among the three residence location categories. Those who live in the central core area have an average commuting time of 40.6 minutes, longer than those in the hybrid area (37.6 minutes) and those in the suburban communities (32.4 minutes). While self-reported commuting time is subject to issues of data accuracy, we have no reason to believe that this problem is more serious for one group than the others. The statistics tend to confirm a linkage between commuting time and the legacy of cluster development</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0042098011410336" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Average commuting time and mode split by age of neighbourhood</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0042098011410336" xlink:href="10.1177_0042098011410336-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Zones/mode</th>
<th align="left">Number of cases</th>
<th align="left">Mode split percentages</th>
<th align="left">Commuting time (minutes)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><italic>Suburban area</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Driving or Taxi</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>13.6</td>
<td>28.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Non-motorised</td>
<td>298</td>
<td>56.1</td>
<td>19.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Transit</td>
<td>161</td>
<td>30.3</td>
<td>58.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>531</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>32.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><italic>Hybrid area</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Driving or Taxi</td>
<td>97</td>
<td>16.2</td>
<td>34.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Non-motorised</td>
<td>283</td>
<td>47.2</td>
<td>27.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Transit</td>
<td>219</td>
<td>36.6</td>
<td>52.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>599</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>37.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><italic>Central core</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Driving or Taxi</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>11.4</td>
<td>35.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Non-motorised</td>
<td>183</td>
<td>49.6</td>
<td>26.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Transit</td>
<td>144</td>
<td>39.0</td>
<td>60.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>369</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>40.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><italic>All</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Driving or Taxi</td>
<td>211</td>
<td>14.1</td>
<td>33.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Non-motorised</td>
<td>764</td>
<td>51.0</td>
<td>23.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Transit</td>
<td>524</td>
<td>35.0</td>
<td>56.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>1499</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>36.5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Since commuting time varies significantly by mode, it is quite possible that suburban residents have shorter commute times because they drive cars while the central-city residents have longer commuting time because they take buses or commute by foot. In Beijing, this relationship between commuting mode and residence location is not so straightforward. While it is true that those in the central core use transit more and drive less, they actually use non-motorised modes less than those in the suburban area.</p>
<p>Since many other factors could also cause the variation in commuting, a regression model is developed to test the significance of the observed zonal differences by controlling other relevant factors. The three zones are represented with two dummy variables in the regression model. The dummy variable <italic>hybrid_area</italic> is used to represent workers who live in the area of hybrid development. The dummy variable <italic>suburban_area</italic> is used to represent communities in the new suburbs. The central core area is the benchmark. Signs and significance levels of the coefficients for those two variables help us to identify the impacts on commutes of efforts to plan for clustered suburban development.</p>
<p>The regression model includes several categories of moderator variables. First, it has two neighbourhood environment variables: population density and job density in the sub-district where the worker lives. These two variables help to control the effect of the local job markets and local built environment. Secondly, five dummy variables of commuting modes are included to control the mobility variation associated with different modes. Since mode selection and residence location selection could be correlated and long-distance commuters are more likely to select high-mobility options, including the mode variables will yield relatively conservative estimates of the commuting time impacts of clustered development and reduce the risk of overstating the zonal differences.</p>
<p>Thirdly, three household variables are included to control the effect of household income and household composition. Fourthly, three variables of commuters’ characteristics are included to control the effect of age, gender and level of education. Fifthly, given China’s segmented housing markets, five housing dummies are included to present those living in a rental unit or those who own their housing units through different housing markets. Since housing ownership (or housing market segmentation) in Chinese cities is related to the characteristics of the employers, including those housing variables will also help to avoid biased estimators resulting from missing information on commuters’ employers. Descriptive statistics of these variables are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0042098011410336">Table 2</xref>. The results of the regression are in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0042098011410336">Table 3</xref>. The model contains 1453 valid cases.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0042098011410336" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Descriptive statistics of the variables</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0042098011410336" xlink:href="10.1177_0042098011410336-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">Minimum</th>
<th align="left">Maximum</th>
<th align="left">Mean</th>
<th align="left">S.D.</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Commuting time</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>180</td>
<td>36.5</td>
<td>27.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Suburb_area</italic></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.35</td>
<td>0.48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Hybrid_area</italic></td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>0.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Job density (persons/sq km)</td>
<td>444</td>
<td>80 938</td>
<td>17 791</td>
<td>15 412</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Population density (persons/sq km)</td>
<td>1 681</td>
<td>32 577</td>
<td>16 343</td>
<td>9 569</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Walk (dummy)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>0.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bike (dummy)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.40</td>
<td>0.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fixed-route bus (dummy)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.30</td>
<td>0.45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Employer bus (dummy)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.04</td>
<td>0.21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Urban rail (dummy)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>0.16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Male (dummy)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.57</td>
<td>0.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>College education (dummy)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.43</td>
<td>0.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dual-worker household (dummy)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.63</td>
<td>0.48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Multiworker household (dummy)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.11</td>
<td>0.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Household income</td>
<td>1 200</td>
<td>300 000</td>
<td>40 601</td>
<td>25 254</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Commercial housing (dummy)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.21</td>
<td>0.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Relocation housing (dummy)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.05</td>
<td>0.21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Municipal housing (dummy)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.05</td>
<td>0.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Work-unit subsidised housing (dummy)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0.35</td>
<td>0.47</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rented housing (dummy)</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>0.27</td>
<td>0.44</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table3-0042098011410336" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Commuting time regression model</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0042098011410336" xlink:href="10.1177_0042098011410336-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="2">Model</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Unstandardised coefficients</th>
<th align="left">Standardised coefficients</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="2">T</th>
<th align="left" rowspan="2">Significance</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">B</th>
<th align="left">Std. Error</th>
<th align="left">Beta</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>(Constant)</td>
<td>37.477</td>
<td>4.715</td>
<td/>
<td>7.948</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Suburb_area</italic></td>
<td>−6.099</td>
<td>2.164</td>
<td>−0.107</td>
<td>−2.818</td>
<td>0.005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Hybrid_area</italic></td>
<td>−3.509</td>
<td>1.675</td>
<td>−0.063</td>
<td>−2.095</td>
<td>0.036</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Job density</td>
<td>0.000</td>
<td>0.000</td>
<td>−0.042</td>
<td>−1.419</td>
<td>0.390</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Population density</td>
<td>0.000</td>
<td>0.000</td>
<td>0.026</td>
<td>0.876</td>
<td>0.156</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Walk (dummy)</td>
<td>−16.449</td>
<td>2.248</td>
<td>−0.191</td>
<td>−7.317</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bike (dummy)</td>
<td>−4.747</td>
<td>1.741</td>
<td>−0.085</td>
<td>−2.727</td>
<td>0.007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fixed-route bus (dummy)</td>
<td>26.349</td>
<td>1.812</td>
<td>0.442</td>
<td>14.545</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Employer bus (dummy)</td>
<td>24.114</td>
<td>3.002</td>
<td>0.190</td>
<td>8.032</td>
<td>0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Urban rail (dummy)</td>
<td>10.094</td>
<td>3.688</td>
<td>0.060</td>
<td>2.737</td>
<td>0.006</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Male (dummy)</td>
<td>2.974</td>
<td>1.215</td>
<td>0.054</td>
<td>2.449</td>
<td>0.014</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>0.001</td>
<td>0.065</td>
<td>0.000</td>
<td>0.016</td>
<td>0.987</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>College education (dummy)</td>
<td>1.405</td>
<td>1.312</td>
<td>0.025</td>
<td>1.071</td>
<td>0.284</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dual-worker household (dummy)</td>
<td>−3.577</td>
<td>1.413</td>
<td>−0.063</td>
<td>−2.532</td>
<td>0.011</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Multiworker household (dummy)</td>
<td>−1.136</td>
<td>2.139</td>
<td>−0.013</td>
<td>−0.531</td>
<td>0.595</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Household income</td>
<td>0.000</td>
<td>0.000</td>
<td>−0.020</td>
<td>−0.844</td>
<td>0.399</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Commercial housing (dummy)</td>
<td>−4.053</td>
<td>2.826</td>
<td>−0.060</td>
<td>−1.434</td>
<td>0.152</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Relocation housing (dummy)</td>
<td>−3.898</td>
<td>3.518</td>
<td>−0.031</td>
<td>−1.108</td>
<td>0.268</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Municipal housing (dummy)</td>
<td>−2.451</td>
<td>3.481</td>
<td>−0.020</td>
<td>−0.704</td>
<td>0.481</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Work-unit subsidised housing (dummy)</td>
<td>−1.090</td>
<td>2.532</td>
<td>−0.019</td>
<td>−0.430</td>
<td>0.667</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rented housing (dummy)</td>
<td>−2.137</td>
<td>2.616</td>
<td>−0.035</td>
<td>−0.817</td>
<td>0.414</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0042098011410336">
<p><italic>Notes</italic>: <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.357; <italic>N</italic> = 1453.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Coefficients for the two zonal dummy variables show significant commuting duration variation among those in different zones. Those living in the hybrid area commute 3.5 minutes less than those in the core area and those in the suburban satellite communities have even shorter commutes—about 6 minutes less than those in the central area. This result indicates that the practice of clustered development has some benefits in urban transport. A relatively strong presence of clustered development in suburban zones helps to keep commuting duration shorter. This connection between commuting and suburban centres has been confirmed by other studies on Asian and European cities with similar density contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0042098011410336">Alpkokina <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0042098011410336">Veneri, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0042098011410336">Alpkokina <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). The results, however, contrasted with a study on the San Francisco Bay Area by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0042098011410336">Cervero and Wu (1998)</xref>. They have postulated that the multicentre structure failed to reduce the average commuting distance. This difference could be attributed to the differences in their suburban centres: suburban clusters in North America are typically much less dense than their Asian counterparts and they are unlikely to lead to similar transport outcomes.</p>
<p>The coefficients in the regression model also imply that the transport benefits of clustered development tend to disappear once suburban clusters become absorbed by the central built-up area. Those who live in the hybrid area, which was originally built as self-contained suburban clusters during the planned economy, now have longer commuting durations than those in the suburban zone. In addition, those living in the hybrid area have a relatively high percentage of commuting by driving and a relatively low percentage by non-motorised transport. The cross-sectional analysis, therefore, reveals a connection between the planning effort for clustered development and transport outcomes.</p>
<p>The model specification described earlier was selected after we tested several alternatives. First, we tested a model without the five housing variables, which do not have significant individual coefficients in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0042098011410336">Table 3</xref>. The regression model without the five housing variables has an <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> value of 0.354. By comparing these two models, we calculated an F-statistic of 2.40. The threshold F-value is 2.21, which enables us to reject the null hypothesis that this group is not significant as a whole. We thus keep them in the final regression model. Secondly, we also tested a model with five interaction variables, which are the products of the income variable and the five mode variables. None of these five interaction variables has a significant T-score. This model has an <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> value of 0.358. The calculated F-statistic is 0.80, which is much lower than the threshold F-value of 2.21. The five interaction variables, therefore, are not significant as a group. They are eliminated from the final model specification. Thirdly, we tested a model with one additional job accessibility variable, which is a powerful explanatory factor of commute duration in American metropolitan areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0042098011410336">Shen, 2000</xref>). Because data required for calculating more sophisticated accessibility measures are not readily available, we used the ratio of jobs to employed residents within 5 km of each worker’s residence, which was calculated using the dynamic buffering technique described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0042098011410336">Peng (1997)</xref>. This additional variable does not add any additional explanatory power, however, and therefore was also eliminated from the final model.</p>
<p>Note that our research neither confirms nor rejects other relevant commuting studies on Beijing, but adds new knowledge. For example, several existing studies have explored the commuting impacts of the evolving workplace–residence relationship. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0042098011410336">Wang and Chai (2009)</xref> found that commuting time varies according to housing type. Those living in work-unit housing have shorter commuting times than those in market housing. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0042098011410336">Yang (2006a)</xref> has explored the relocation patterns of households and found that they strongly affect commuting. As market forces increasingly separate residences from workplaces, commuting time and the usage of motorised modes increase significantly. Distinct from existing studies, the empirical analysis here demonstrates that regional-scale spatial development, particularly clustered development, can also significantly impact individual commuting.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0042098011410336">
<title>4. Beijing as a Case of Compact City Development</title>
<p>The search for a good city form arose as a response to overcrowding in industrial cities and has been recently renewed to resist urban sprawl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0042098011410336">Talen and Ellis, 2002</xref>). The compact city movement has highlighted the urban form–transport behaviour relationship, assuming that there is a strong link between urban form and transport outcome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0042098011410336">Jenks <italic>et al</italic>., 1996</xref>). In this vein, researchers have argued that compact urban development is one way of reducing travel and stimulating physical activities, thereby reducing emissions and greenhouse gases and promoting public health (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0042098011410336">Hillman, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0042098011410336">Stone <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0042098011410336">Frumkin <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Beijing’s concentration of urban activities in a high-density built-up area probably qualifies it as a compact city from a pure density perspective. Beijing’s transport, however, is not an example of good urban transport in its aggregate outcome. Today’s Beijing is badly congested and polluted. Motor vehicle ownership is rising; by the end of 2009, the number of registered motor vehicles had reached 4 million. With a population of 18 million, the motor vehicle ownership rate reaches almost one for every four residents. Accommodating such a big motor vehicle population in an overconcentrated urban area causes undesirable congestion, despite Beijing’s tremendous effort to build urban expressways.</p>
<p>The congestion stemming from overconcentration can be observed in the regression model. Higher density is generally associated with shorter commute distances, since higher density tends to bring more opportunities nearby. This distance reduction effect, however, does not lead to a reduction in commuting time in the regression model. The coefficients for the two density variables are not statistically significant. The regression results probably suggest that congestion stemming from overconcentration cancels out the distance-saving benefits of high density. While multicollinearity among the dependent variables could hide the true effects of density, a separate correlation analysis confirms the congestion effect: neighbourhoods with relatively high densities do not necessarily have lower percentages of commuting by driving. Commuting time is longer for residents in high population density neighbourhoods.</p>
<p>This problem does not imply that compact city development fails to create transport benefits, as compactness is not equal to overconcentration. Breheny (1996) once categorised compact city development into two groups: mononuclear centralisation and decentralised concentration. The latter is advocated in the recent literature, which emphasises neither extreme centralisation nor decentralisation solutions, but favours moderate-density developments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0042098011410336">Buchanan <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0042098011410336">Burton, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0042098011410336">Holden and Norland, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0042098011410336">Scoffham and Vale, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0042098011410336">Thomas and Cousins, 1996</xref>).</p>
<p>From this perspective, the idea of the compact city is in line with the moderate centrism and multi-nuclei theorists such as Ebenezer Howard, whose ‘garden city’ idea has been widely taught in China’s planning schools and consequently guided spatial development planning in Beijing and other Chinese cities. Beijing’s experience feeds the existing literature. The empirical analysis indeed indicates that efforts to plan for clustered development under the spatial framework of decentralised concentration have a significant transport legacy. Areas where this planning practice has been more influential tend to have shorter commuting times, even after controlling for other socioeconomic variables. Putting this transport legacy in the dynamic context of Beijing’s spatial development history, Beijing’s story confirms that overconcentration stemming from featureless expansion of the central built-up area leads to an increase in commuting time and a loss of urban quality.</p>
<p>Addressing overconcentration and maintaining suburban nodal characteristics in the growth process can therefore help to improve urban transport. First, the suburban clusters have to be sufficiently distant from the central built-up area. The current urban settlements in ex-urban counties can possibly play this role. They are located about 30–60 minutes driving distance from the core built-up area, which makes these areas desirable for residents to live and work in a single suburban cluster. The population in each of these settlements is already over 100 000 residents, big enough to provide high-quality urban services with reasonable economies of scale. Learning from past experience, more municipal investment should be put into these communities to build better parks, schools and hospitals. These infrastructure improvements and public services are necessary in order to attract households and private investment into the suburban clusters.</p>
<p>Secondly, the empirical analysis suggests that a careful selection of transport technology can help. Those commuting by rail have much shorter commutes, by about 15 minutes, than those who commute by bus, as indicated in the regression model. As for land development, both housing and office development have been increasingly concentrated around rail stations during the past decade. On the housing side, developers are locating new residential properties in suburban rail stations, resulting in significant peripheral growth. Residential properties near rail stations are popular and competitive in the housing market. Empirical studies of Shanghai, Shenzhen and Beijing’s housing prices indicate that proximity to urban rail stations has a significant impact on housing prices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0042098011410336">Wang and Huang, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0042098011410336">Zheng and Liu, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0042098011410336">Xu, 2007</xref>). Analysis of Beijing’s mode split based on the same dataset reveals that proximity to rail stations increases the percentages of commuting by public transit and non-motorised modes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042098011410336">Yang, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Analysing job growth based on Beijing’s 2001 employer census, we find clustered development around rail stations. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0042098011410336">Table 4</xref> presents proximity to urban rail stations with three buffer zones: 0–0.5 km, 0.5–1 km and 1–2 km. The statistics indicate that pre-1991 development is rail-oriented. If the density in the outer zone is 1, it increases in the middle zone to 2.3 and further doubles in the inner zone to 4.5. This rail orientation could work in two directions. On the one hand, rail alignment was designed to improve services to high-density sites. On the other hand, new growth is more likely to occur near rail stations. This preference for rail proximity can be more clearly identified in post-1992 growth data. If employee density is 1.0 in the outer zone, the comparable density increases to 2.5 in the middle zone and further increases to 5.1 in the inner zone. The density gradient has become steeper over time, which indicates that job growth is becoming even more rail-oriented, despite the fact that the urban rail system was already designed to serve high-density job sites and that no additional planning effort has been made to attract further higher-density development around those stations.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0042098011410336" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Employment growth in relation to urban rail stations</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0042098011410336" xlink:href="10.1177_0042098011410336-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">First year of operation/buffer zone</th>
<th align="left">Employees (thousand)</th>
<th align="left">Employee density (thousands/sq km)</th>
<th align="left">Normalised density</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><italic>1950–91</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0.5 km buffer</td>
<td>283</td>
<td>361</td>
<td>4.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0.5–1 km buffer</td>
<td>444</td>
<td>188</td>
<td>2.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1–2 km buffer</td>
<td>572</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><italic>1992-2001</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0.5 km buffer</td>
<td>712</td>
<td>907</td>
<td>5.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0.5–1 km buffer</td>
<td>1037</td>
<td>440</td>
<td>2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1–2 km buffer</td>
<td>1251</td>
<td>177</td>
<td>1.0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0042098011410336">
<p><italic>Notes</italic>: The indicators are computed based on China’s 2001 work-unit census. Since this census shows the beginning year of operation for each employer, we divide all employers into two groups—those starting operation by 1991 and those after 1992—in order to develop some preliminary insight into the trend over time. (In 1992, Deng Xiaoping’s strong speech significantly advanced the reform and open-up policies.) We then calculate the number of employees and job density in each buffer zone.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Clustered development around rail stations, as revealed, suggests the potential of urban rail services to attract new development or redevelopment into a relatively contained area. Meanwhile, it provides regional mobility comparable with automobile-based travel. Beijing’s planners have realised this and have increased the pace of urban rail investment. Specifically, in December 2008, the Beijing Municipal Commission of Urban Planning advanced the completion dates of the Yizhuang and Daxing lines—two suburban light rail projects—from 2012 to 2010.</p>
<p>The emphasis on urban rail does not exclude investment in better bus systems. As suggested in the regression model, the coefficients for the mode variables are all significant and the two bus variables appear to be the best predictors of commuting time. Those who commute by bus on average spend about 25 more minutes for a one-way trip and 50 minutes more for a round trip. The statistics in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0042098011410336">Table 2</xref> indicate that 11 per cent of commuters travel by foot, 40 per cent by bike, 30 per cent by fixed-route bus, 4 per cent by employer-provided bus and 3 per cent by urban rail. Given the large percentage of individuals commuting by bus, strategies to improve bus speed, such as bus rapid transit systems, can serve as an effective strategy to shorten commuting times and relieve congestion, even though the impacts of bus systems on urban land development are typically not as strong as urban rail.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0042098011410336" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>5. Conclusions</title>
<p>As has been observed in many other fast-growing cities, Beijing’s transport system is badly congested. How to supply much-needed mobility and accessibility for the ever-increasing urban population through urban land and transport development is a significant challenge. While development into suburban areas is unavoidable, the format of suburban development matters. In an analysis of the transport impacts of relatively low-density decentralised development in American metropolitan areas, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0042098011410336">Yang (2006b)</xref> states that sprawling low-density suburban development tends to lead to faster increases in travel demand than does clustered development.</p>
<p>Beijing’s experience suggests what could happen at the other end of the spectrum of urban forms. Extremely concentrated development in a high-density urban area does not appear desirable either, particularly when policies restricting motor vehicle ownership and usage are not effective enough. As a result of the absorption of previous suburban clusters, overconcentration of urban activities in Beijing’s central built-up area has led to increased commuting times, road congestion and air pollution. A multi-nuclei form appears to be desirable for Beijing to achieve its vision of compact city development.</p>
<p>While perceptions of ‘high’ density could vary by culture, balancing concentration and decentralisation and maintaining strong suburban clusters are planning challenges for compact city development in varied density contexts. Beijing’s experience demonstrates both lessons and hopes in high-density urban regions. First, efforts to plan for clustered development in suburban areas have transport benefits. Areas with a relatively strong presence of clustered development planning tend to have relatively short commutes. This benefit, however, cannot be sustained because of the overconcentration of urban activities and the loss of nodal characteristics stemming from the continuous expansion of the central built-up area. Secondly, the failure to implement Beijing’s multi-nuclei vision of spatial development has its root in transport investment strategies, site selection for satellite communities and municipal investment strategies. An emphasis on urban rail investment, if coupled with appropriate municipal investment in suburban clusters, could have significant impacts on future spatial development and transport in Beijing.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="section6-0042098011410336">
<title>Funding Statement</title>
<p>This research is supported by the Lincoln Institute of Land Policy.</p>
</sec>
<ack>
<p>The authors wish to thank Professor John Logan for providing the survey data and PhD student Ge Song for providing valuable research assistance.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alpkokina</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Dynamics of clustered employment growth and its impacts on commuting patterns in rapidly developing cities</article-title>, <source>Transportation Research Part A</source>, <volume>42</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), pp. <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>444</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alpkokina</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshitsugu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gercek</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Polycentric employment growth and impacts on urban commuting patterns: case study of Istanbul</article-title>, <source>Journal of the Eastern Asia Society for Transportation Studies</source>, <volume>6</volume>, pp. <fpage>3835</fpage>–<lpage>3850</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Beijing Transport Commission</collab> (<year>2003</year>) <source>The outline of Beijing’s transportation strategy</source> (<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.chinautc.com/information/newsshow.asp?newsid=871">http://www.chinautc.com/information/newsshow.asp?newsid=871</ext-link></comment>; <access-date>accessed 17 May 2008</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Breheny</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1966</year>) <article-title>Centrists, decentrists and compromisers: views on the future of urban form</article-title>, in: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jenks</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds) <source>The Compact City: A Sustainable Urban Form?</source>, pp. <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>E &amp; FN Spon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kingham</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The effect of urban growth on commuting patterns in Christchurch, New Zealand</article-title>, <source>Journal of Transport Geography</source>, <volume>14</volume>, pp. <fpage>342</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Measuring urban compactness in UK towns and cities</article-title>, <source>Environment and Planning B</source>, <volume>29</volume>, pp. <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>250</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cervero</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Which reduces vehicle travel more: jobs–housing balance or retail–housing mixing</article-title>, <source>Journal of American Planning Association</source>, <volume>72</volume>, pp. <fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>490</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cervero</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Sub-centring and commuting: evidence from the San Fransisco Bay area, 1980–90</article-title>, <source>Urban Studies</source>, <volume>35</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), pp. <fpage>1059</fpage>–<lpage>1076</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The influence of urban form on travel: an interpretive review</article-title>, <source>Journal of Planning Literature</source>, <volume>15</volume>, pp. <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Intraurban migration and correlative spatial behaviour in Beijing in the process of suburbanisation: based on 1000 questionnaires</article-title>, <source>Geographic Research</source>, <volume>23</volume>, pp. <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage> [<comment>in Chinese</comment>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frumkin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Urban Sprawl and Public Health: Designing, Planning and Building for Healthy Communities</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Island Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Are compact cities a desirable planning goal?</article-title>, <source>Journal of the American Planning Association</source>, <volume>63</volume>, pp. <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hillman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>In favour of the compact city</article-title>, in: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jenks</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds) <source>The Compact City: A Sustainable Urban Form?</source>, pp. <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>E &amp; FN Spon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norland</surname><given-names>I. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Three challenges for the compact city as a sustainable urban form: household consumption of energy and transport in eight residential areas in the Greater Oslo region</article-title>, <source>Urban Studies</source>, <volume>42</volume>, pp. <fpage>2145</fpage>–<lpage>2166</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jenks</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds) (<year>1996</year>) <source>The Compact City: A Sustainable Urban Form?</source> <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>E &amp; FN Spon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Principles of City Planning</source>. <comment>China Architecture Press</comment> [<comment>in Chinese</comment>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Madge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1962</year>) <article-title>The new towns program in Britain</article-title>, <source>Journal of the American Planning Association</source>, <volume>28</volume>, pp. <fpage>208</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Research Council (US) and Committee for the Study on the Relationships among Development Patterns, Vehicle Miles Traveled, and Energy Consumption</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Driving and the Built Environment: The Effects of Compact Development on Motorized Travel, Energy Use, and CO<sub>2</sub> Emissions</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dawkins</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>The Social Impacts of Urban Containment</source>. <publisher-loc>Aldershot</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The compact city fallacy</article-title>, <source>Journal of Planning Education and Research</source>, <volume>25</volume>, pp. <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Sullivan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Urban Economics</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill/Irwin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Z. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Jobs–housing balance and urban commuting</article-title>, <source>Urban Studies</source>, <volume>34</volume>, pp. <fpage>1215</fpage>–<lpage>1235</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2003</year>) <source>Spatial and temporal patterns of urban dynamics in Chengdu, 1975–2002</source>. <comment>Discussion paper</comment>, <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <publisher-name>Shorenstein Asia-Pacific Research Center</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scoffham</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>How compact is sustainable—how sustainable is compact?</article-title>, in: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jenks</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds) <source>The Compact City: A Sustainable Urban Form?</source>, pp. <fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>E &amp; FN Spon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Spatial and social dimensions of commuting</article-title>, <source>Journal of the American Planning Association</source>, <volume>66</volume>, pp. <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mednick</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spak</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Is compact growth good for air quality</article-title>?, <source>Journal of the American Planning Association</source>, <volume>73</volume>, pp. <fpage>404</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Journey-to-work patterns in the age of sprawl: evidence from two midsize southern metropolitan areas</article-title>, <source>The Professional Geographer</source>, <volume>59</volume>, pp. <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Talen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Beyond relativism: reclaiming the search for good city form</article-title>, <source>Journal of Planning Education and Research</source>, <volume>22</volume>, pp. <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cousins</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The compact city: a successful, desirable and achievable urban form?</article-title>, in: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jenks</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds) <source>The Compact City: A Sustainable Urban Form?</source>, pp. <fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>E &amp; FN Spon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>TRB (Transportation Research Board)</collab> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Does built environment influence physical activity? Examining the evidence</article-title>. <comment>Special Report No. 282</comment>, <publisher-loc>TRB, Washington, DC</publisher-loc> (<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://onlinepubs.trb.org/onlinepubs/sr/sr282.pdf">http://onlinepubs.trb.org/onlinepubs/sr/sr282.pdf</ext-link></comment>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Veneri</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Urban polycentricity and the social costs of commuting</source>. <comment>Research paper</comment>, <publisher-name>Department of Economics, Università Politecnica delle Marche</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Italy</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The jobs–housing relationship and commuting in Beijing, China: the legacy of danwei</article-title>, <source>Journal of Transport Geography</source>, <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), pp. <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Hedonic models for housing price and its application in urban studies</article-title>, <source>Urban Planning</source>, <volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), pp. <fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage> [<comment>in Chinese</comment>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y. X.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Modelling urban population densities in Beijing 1982–90: suburbanisation and its causes</article-title>, <source>Urban Studies</source>, <volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), pp. <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The evolution of built landscapes in metropolitan regions</article-title>, <source>Journal of Planning Education and Research</source>, <volume>27</volume>, pp. <fpage>400</fpage>–<lpage>416</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Changes in the structure of public housing provision in urban China</article-title>, <source>Urban Studies</source>, <volume>33</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), pp. <fpage>1601</fpage>–<lpage>1628</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="thesis">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>The impacts of new urban rail projects on housing prices</source>. <comment>MA thesis</comment>, <publisher-name>China Southwestern Jiaotong University</publisher-name> [<comment>in Chinese</comment>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006a</year>) <article-title>Transportation implications of land development in a transitional economy: evidence from housing relocation in Beijing, China</article-title>, <source>Transportation Research Record</source>, <volume>1954</volume>, pp. <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006b</year>) <article-title>Commuting impacts of spatial decentralization: a comparison of Boston and Atlanta</article-title>, <source>Journal of Regional Analysis and Policy</source>, <volume>5</volume>, pp. <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The spatial and social characteristics of urban transportation in Beijing</article-title>, <source>Transportation Research Record</source>, <volume>2193</volume>, pp. <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Land and transportation development in China: an economic analysis of government behavior</article-title>, <source>Journal of the Transportation Research Board</source>, <year>2038</year>, pp. <fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gakenheimer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The physical and social dimension of job–housing balance in urban China</article-title>, in: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds) <source>Smart Growth in China, ch. 11</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lincoln Institute of Land Policy Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The evolution from danwei community to citizen community: case study of Tongrentang in Beijing</article-title>, <source>Urban Planning International</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), pp. <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage> [<comment>in Chinese</comment>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Chinese edition of transit-oriented development</article-title>, <source>Transportation Research Record</source>, <volume>2038</volume>, pp. <fpage>120</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Six master plans in Beijing’s sixth years</article-title>, <source>Beijing Evening News</source>, <day>17</day> <month>August</month> [<comment>in Chinese</comment>] (<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cn.chinagate.cn/economics/2009-08/17/content_18350023.htm">http://cn.chinagate.cn/economics/2009-08/17/content_18350023.htm</ext-link></comment>; <access-date>accessed 20 December 2009</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The spatiality and spatial changes of danwei compound in Chinese cities: case study of Beijing No. 2 textile</article-title>, <source>Urban Planning International</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), pp. <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage> [<comment>in Chinese</comment>].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Beijing’s traffic will get worse before it gets better</article-title>, <source>Caijing English Newsletter</source>, <day>20</day> <month>January</month>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0042098011410336">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The impacts on housing prices of Shenzhen’s subway development</article-title>, <source>Journal of Urban Rail Studies</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), pp. <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage> [<comment>in Chinese</comment>].</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>