<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CNU</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcnu</journal-id>
<journal-title>European Journal of Cardiovascular Nursing</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1474-5151</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1873-1953</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1474515112438163</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1474515112438163</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Gender differences in respiratory disturbance, sleep and daytime sleepiness in hypertensive patients with different degrees of obesity</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Broström</surname><given-names>Anders</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1474515112438163">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1474515112438163">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sunnergren</surname><given-names>Ola</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1474515112438163">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1474515112438163">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Nilsen</surname><given-names>Per</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-1474515112438163">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Fridlund</surname><given-names>Bengt</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1474515112438163">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ulander</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1474515112438163">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1474515112438163">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Svanborg</surname><given-names>Eva</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1474515112438163">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1474515112438163">4</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1474515112438163"><label>1</label>Department of Nursing Science, School of Health Sciences, Jönköping University, Jönköping, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1474515112438163"><label>2</label>Department of Clinical Neurophysiology, Linköping University Hospital, Linköping Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1474515112438163"><label>3</label>Ear, Nose and Throat Clinic, County Hospital Ryhov, Jönköping, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff4-1474515112438163"><label>4</label>Department of Clinical and Experimental Medicine, Division of Clinical Neurophysiology, Faculty of Health Sciences Linköping University, Linköping, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff5-1474515112438163"><label>5</label>Division of Social Medicine and Public Health Science, Faculty of Health Sciences, Department of Health and Society, Linköping University, Linköping, Sweden</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1474515112438163">Anders Broström, Department of Neurophysiology, University Hospital, S-581 85 Linköping, Sweden. Email: <email>anders.brostrom@hhj.hj.se</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>140</fpage>
<lpage>149</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>2</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>17</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The European Society of Cardiology 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">European Society of Cardiology</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-1474515112438163">
<title>Background:</title>
<p>Hypertension (HT) and obesity have both been linked to obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA). Difficulties have been described in identifying patients with OSA in primary care, causing low referral rates to sleep clinics. Increased knowledge about gender-specific characteristics and symptoms may help to identify patients.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1474515112438163">
<title>Aim:</title>
<p>The aim was to describe gender differences regarding undiagnosed OSA, self-rated sleep, insomnia and daytime sleepiness in middle-aged primary care patients with HT and different degrees of obesity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1474515112438163">
<title>Methods:</title>
<p>A cross-sectional design was used and 394 patients (52.5% women), mean age 57.8 years (SD 6.7 years), with HT (BP &gt;140/90 mmHg) were included. Clinical examinations, respiratory recordings and self-rated scales regarding OSA symptoms, sleep, insomnia and daytime sleepiness were used. Body mass index (BMI) was classified according to the criteria from the National Institutes of Health.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1474515112438163">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>Pre-obesity and obesity classes I and II were seen among 53%, 26% and 8% of the men and 37%, 19% and 14% of the women, respectively. Occurrence of mild, moderate and severe OSA increased significantly across the BMI classes for both genders (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01). Ninety percent of the men and 80% of the women in obesity class II had OSA. Insomnia was prevalent in obese patients. Other clinical variables did not differ between BMI classes or genders.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1474515112438163">
<title>Conclusion:</title>
<p>The occurrence of overweight/obesity and OSA was high among both genders. A high BMI might be a convenient clinical marker for healthcare personnel to identify hypertensive patients with possible OSA in need of further evaluation and treatment.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Hypertension</kwd>
<kwd>obstructive sleep apnoea</kwd>
<kwd>obesity</kwd>
<kwd>insomnia</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section6-1474515112438163">
<title>Background</title>
<p>Hypertension (HT) and obesity are two conditions associated with severe health implications. HT has been estimated to cause 62% of cerebrovascular disease, 49% of ischaemic heart disease (IHD) and 7.1 million deaths each year.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1474515112438163">1</xref></sup> Obesity has recently replaced smoking as ‘the number one killer’ worldwide.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1474515112438163">2</xref></sup> In recent cardiovascular and sleep medicine guidelines, both conditions have been linked to obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1474515112438163">3</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1474515112438163"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1474515112438163">5</xref></sup> OSA is a sleep-related breathing disorder characterized by repetitive apnoeas and hypopnoeas during sleep despite maintained or increased respiratory efforts.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1474515112438163">4</xref></sup> OSA is often but not always characterized by severe snoring, witnessed apnoeas, frequent awakenings from sleep, poor sleep quality, excessive daytime sleepiness, as well as decreased quality of life.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1474515112438163">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1474515112438163"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1474515112438163">7</xref></sup> If daytime symptoms are present, the disease is termed OSA syndrome (OSAS).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1474515112438163">5</xref></sup> To establish the diagnosis and severity, the number of apnoeas and hypopnoeas per hours of sleep are scored into an index – the apnoea–hypopnoea index (AHI). An AHI ≥5, ≥15 and &gt;30 reflect mild, moderate or severe OSA, respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1474515112438163">5</xref></sup> The prevalence of mild OSA has been estimated to be 28% in middle-aged North Americans of both genders. In the same population, the prevalence of OSAS is 4% in men and 2% in women.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1474515112438163">8</xref></sup></p>
<p>The National Institutes of Health (NIH) divide body mass index (BMI) into five classes; BMI &lt;18.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (underweight), 18.5–24.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (normal weight), 25–29.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (pre-obesity), 30–34.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (obesity class I) and &gt;35 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (obesity class II).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1474515112438163">9</xref></sup> Obesity has previously been more common in the USA,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1474515112438163">10</xref></sup> but recent data indicate that it is an increasing problem in many European populations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1474515112438163">11</xref></sup> Obesity is a predictor for OSA in sleep-clinic populations, especially in male patients with severe OSA.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1474515112438163">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1474515112438163">13</xref></sup> Anatomical and functional effects on the upper airway, decreased leptin sensitivity and a large amount of central obesity probably interact in the development of OSA.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1474515112438163">14</xref></sup> Obesity is also a well-known risk factor for cardiovascular disease (CVD). A prospective 10-year follow-up of 21,570 hospitalized patients with myocardial infarction and/or heart failure showed that obesity class II was an independent predictor of cardiovascular death.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1474515112438163">15</xref></sup> However, the data revealed a U-shaped curve for the mortality risk with the lowest mortality in normal weight, pre-obesity and obesity class I and the highest death risk in those underweight or in obesity class II.</p>
<p>The presence of OSA in an obese patient may further increase the burden on the cardiovascular system.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1474515112438163">13</xref></sup> Increased levels of catecholamines, causing inflammation, arterial stiffness and atherosclerosis can be seen as a result of the sympathetic activation caused by hypoxia and hypercapnia, as well as arousal due to apnoeas/hypopnoeas. Furthermore, the negative intra-thoracic pressure induced by the inspiratory efforts against the obstructed airway leads to increased afterload, left ventricular hypertrophy and reduced cardiac output.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1474515112438163">16</xref></sup> OSA has been associated with increased risk for cardiovascular morbidity and mortality in both genders.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1474515112438163">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1474515112438163">18</xref></sup> However, it has proved difficult to identify patients with OSA in primary care, causing low referral rates to sleep clinics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1474515112438163">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1474515112438163">20</xref></sup> Increased knowledge among primary care healthcare personnel working with cardiovascular patients about the occurrence of undiagnosed OSA, its gender-specific characteristics and symptoms may help to identify those in need of OSA evaluation. Studies investigating gender differences in sleep-clinic populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1474515112438163">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1474515112438163"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1474515112438163"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1474515112438163"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1474515112438163">25</xref></sup> have found a marked male dominance both regarding prevalence (3:1 or even 8:1) and frequency of reported symptoms (snoring, witnessed apnoeas and excessive daytime sleepiness). No studies have been conducted to examine this issue with regard to primary care patients with HT, undiagnosed OSA and different degrees of obesity. The aim was therefore to describe gender differences regarding undiagnosed OSA, self-rated sleep, insomnia and daytime sleepiness in middle-aged primary care patients with HT and different degrees of obesity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1474515112438163" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section8-1474515112438163">
<title>Design and population</title>
<p>A cross-sectional design was used. All 918 eligible patients 18–65 years of age with diagnosed hypertension (140/90 mmHg) at four primary care centres in the south-east of Sweden were invited to participate in the study. Exclusion criteria were terminal disease, ongoing treatment for OSA, severe psychiatric disease, dementia, alcohol/drug abuse or difficulty reading and understanding the Swedish language. The study protocol was approved by the ethics committee (Dnr M29-07) at the Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Linköping, Sweden, and all participants provided informed consent. The study was conducted in accordance with the Helsinki declaration <bold>and data were collected between 2008 and 2010.</bold></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1474515112438163">
<title>Clinical variables</title>
<p><bold>One</bold> nurse collected <bold>data from all patients</bold> regarding weight, height, body composition (waist, hip, and neck circumference), blood pressure, subjective sleep (sleep duration, estimated sleep need), medication and comorbidities during a clinical examination. Blood pressure was measured in the supine position. <bold>An</bold> Ear, Nose and Throat specialist also examined <bold>all</bold> the patients and collected data regarding sleep and symptoms of OSA. Diagnosis of diabetes mellitus was based on history, current treatment (oral therapy or insulin) or repeated fasting blood glucose values ≥7 mmol/l. IHD was defined as a history of angina pectoris and/or myocardial infarction and/or coronary angioplasty and/or coronary bypass surgery. Respiratory disease was defined as a history of asthma or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, or current treatment with β<sup>2</sup> agonists and/or inhaled corticosteroids.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1474515112438163">
<title>Recordings of obstructive sleep apnoea</title>
<p>Full-night respiratory recordings with monitoring of nasal airflow, pulse oximetry, respiratory movements and body position were performed in the patients’ homes using polygraphic equipment (Embletta, ResMed AB, Trollhättan, Sweden).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1474515112438163">26</xref></sup> Apnoeas and hypopnoeas were manually scored. An apnoea was scored if the nasal ressure signal amplitude dropped ≥90% for &gt;10 seconds and 90% of the event met amplitude reduction criteria. A hypopnoea was scored if the nasal pressure signal amplitude dropped ≥30%, oxygen-saturation dropped ≥4%, for &gt;10 seconds and 90% of the events met amplitude reduction criteria. The total number of apnoeas and hypopnoeas was divided by estimated sleep time giving the AHI. An oxygen desaturation index (ODI) was calculated in the same manner based on desaturations of &gt;4%. Mild, moderate and severe OSA were defined as AHI 5–14.9, 15–29.9 or &gt;30, respectively. Since sleep stages were not recorded, sleep time was estimated from a combination of breathing pattern, posture and movements as well as self-estimated sleep onset and morning awakening. All recordings were scored by the same researcher (OS) blinded to the other data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1474515112438163">
<title>Self-rating scales</title>
<p>The Berlin Sleep Apnea Questionnaire (BSAQ), comprising 11 items, was used to measure occurrence of OSA symptoms/characteristics (habitual snoring, witnessed apnoeas, daytime fatigue, weight increase, obesity and hypertension).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1474515112438163">27</xref></sup> The instrument has shown good validity and reliability and has been used in several studies in primary care settings. The minimal insomnia symptoms scale (MISS), comprising three items, was used to measure difficulties initiating sleep, difficulties maintaining sleep and difficulties with non-restorative sleep.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1474515112438163">28</xref></sup> The patients graded their difficulties on a scale ranging from no problems (0) to very great problems (4). The well-validated Epworth sleepiness scale (ESS) was used to measure excessive daytime sleepiness.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1474515112438163">29</xref></sup> The eight items (different daily situations in which the subjects are asked to rate the likeliness of dozing or falling asleep) are rated on a scale of 0–3, where high scores indicate a greater propensity to falling asleep. The total score range is 0–24 points, with a cut-off of &gt;10 indicating excessive daytime sleepiness.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1474515112438163">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Categorical data were described with percentages and numbers, whereas continuous data were described with means and standard deviations. Normally distributed variables were analyed with <italic>t</italic>-test, ANOVA or Pearson correlations. Chi-square test or Spearman rank correlations were used on non-normally distributed or dichotomous variables. The significance level was set to <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05. All statistical analyses were performed with the PASW statistics 18 (IBM Inc, USA).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1474515112438163" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section14-1474515112438163">
<title>Study population</title>
<p>Of the 918 patients, 12% (50 men/59 women) fell for exclusion criteria (terminal disease: 4 men/4 women; ongoing treatment for OSA: 12 men/ 5 women; severe psychiatric disease: 5 men/ 6 women; dementia: 4 men/4 women; alcohol/drug abuse: 42 men/ 10 women; difficulty understanding/reading Swedish: 8 men/5 women). A total of 170 men and 159 women declined to participate, but they did not differ regarding demographic variables compared to the included patients. Of the 480 patients who participated in the clinical examination, 411 agreed to undergo a respiratory recording. Out of these, 17 recordings were lost because of technical problems or poor data quality. Thus, a total of 394 patients were included in the study. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1474515112438163">Table 1</xref> shows demographic and clinical data of the study population. The mean age of the population was 57.8 years (SD 6.7 years) and 47.5% were male. IHD and hypercholesterolaemia were the most common comorbidities among both men and women. Men had significantly greater waist and neck circumferences than women (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001). Medication with angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors (ACEI) and angiotensin-receptor blockers (ARB) was more common among men (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001) and diuretics more common among women (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01). A family history of CVD was highly prevalent among both men and women. A total of 78% of the patients had a BMI &gt;25 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. Pre-obesity, obesity class I and II was seen among 44%, 23% and 11% of the patients, respectively. Mild, moderate and severe OSA was seen among 29%, 16% and 14% of the patients, respectively. OSA (AHI &gt;5) was found in 66% of the men compared to 54% of the women (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1474515112438163" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Characteristics of the population (n = 394) according to gender</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1474515112438163" xlink:href="10.1177_1474515112438163-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"><bold>Variables</bold></th>
<th align="left"><bold>Total</bold> (n=394)</th>
<th align="left"><bold>Men</bold> (n=187, 47.5 %)</th>
<th align="left"><bold>Women</bold> (n=207, 52.5 %)</th>
<th align="left"><bold>Men vs Women</bold></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><bold>Age</bold>, m (sd)</td>
<td>57.8 (6.7)</td>
<td>57.5 (7.6)</td>
<td>58.1 (5.9)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Education</bold>, n (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 years</td>
<td>62 (16)</td>
<td>36 (20)</td>
<td>26 (13)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9 years</td>
<td>87 (23)</td>
<td>31 (17)</td>
<td>56 (28)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 years</td>
<td>133 (35)</td>
<td>77 (42)</td>
<td>56 (28)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>&gt; 15 years</td>
<td>103 (27)</td>
<td>40 (22)</td>
<td>63 (31)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1474515112438163">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Marital status</bold>, n (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Married</td>
<td>257 (65)</td>
<td>124 (67)</td>
<td>133 (65)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Unmarried</td>
<td>82 (21)</td>
<td>45 (24)</td>
<td>37 (18)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Divorced</td>
<td>38 (10)</td>
<td>15 (8)</td>
<td>23 (11)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Widow/widower</td>
<td>14 (4)</td>
<td>1 (0.5)</td>
<td>13 (6)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Body composition</bold>, m (sd)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Body mass index</td>
<td>28.8 (4.9)</td>
<td>29.1 (4.0)</td>
<td>28.6 (5.6)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Waist circumference</td>
<td>101.0 (13.21)</td>
<td>105.6 (10.5)</td>
<td>97.0 (14.0)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1474515112438163">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Waist-hip-ratio</td>
<td>1.0 (0.1)</td>
<td>1.0 (0.1)</td>
<td>0.9 (0.7)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Neck circumference</td>
<td>39.2 (5.6)</td>
<td>42.3 (6.2)</td>
<td>36.4 (2.8)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1474515112438163">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Blood pressure</bold>, m (sd)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Systolic blood pressure</td>
<td>140.5 (17.3)</td>
<td>141.1 (17.7)</td>
<td>140.0 (17.0)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diastolic blood pressure</td>
<td>87.2 (10.5)</td>
<td>88.1 (11.0)</td>
<td>86.4 (10.1)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Comorbidities</bold>, n (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IHD</td>
<td>288 (73)</td>
<td>135 (73)</td>
<td>153 (74)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hypercholesterolemia</td>
<td>115 (30)</td>
<td>56 (31)</td>
<td>59 (29)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TIA/Stroke</td>
<td>8 (2)</td>
<td>4 (2)</td>
<td>4 (2)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diabetes</td>
<td>68 (18)</td>
<td>37 (20)</td>
<td>31 (15)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Respiratory disease</td>
<td>24 (6)</td>
<td>14 (8)</td>
<td>10 (5)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Risk factors for CVD</bold>, n (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Smoking</td>
<td>52 (14)</td>
<td>21 (12)</td>
<td>31 (16)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ex-smoker</td>
<td>102 (28)</td>
<td>57 (33)</td>
<td>45 (23)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Family history of CVD</td>
<td>225 (58)</td>
<td>91 (50)</td>
<td>134 (66)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Medication</bold>, n (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ACEI/ARB</td>
<td>227 (58)</td>
<td>127 (70)</td>
<td>100 (48)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1474515112438163">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CA-blockers</td>
<td>80 (20)</td>
<td>42 (23)</td>
<td>38 (18)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>B-blockers</td>
<td>185 (47)</td>
<td>87 (47)</td>
<td>98 (47)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diuretics</td>
<td>130 (33)</td>
<td>49 (26)</td>
<td>81 (39)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1474515112438163">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hypnotics</td>
<td>18 (5)</td>
<td>4 (2)</td>
<td>14 (7)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Obstructive sleep apnea</bold>, n (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No OSA</td>
<td>159 (40)</td>
<td>61 (33)</td>
<td>98 (47)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1474515112438163">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mild OSA</td>
<td>115 (29)</td>
<td>57 (30)</td>
<td>58 (28)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Moderate OSA</td>
<td>64 (17)</td>
<td>30 (16)</td>
<td>34 (17)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Severe OSA</td>
<td>56 (14)</td>
<td>39 (21)</td>
<td>17 (8)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1474515112438163">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Self-rated sleep</bold>, m (sd)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sleep duration, hours</td>
<td>6.7 (1.1)</td>
<td>6.8 (1.0)</td>
<td>6.7 (1.1)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Estimated sleep need, hours</td>
<td>7.7 (0,9)</td>
<td>7.7 (0.9)</td>
<td>7.8 (0.8)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sleep sufficiency index, %</td>
<td>0.9 (0.1)</td>
<td>0.9 (0.1)</td>
<td>0.9 (0.1)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Insomnia symptoms</bold>, n (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Difficulties initiating sleep</td>
<td>126 (33)</td>
<td>53 (13)</td>
<td>73 (18)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Difficulties maintaining sleep</td>
<td>199 (50)</td>
<td>81 (21)</td>
<td>118 (30)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Difficulties with non-restorative sleep</td>
<td>188 (48)</td>
<td>85 (22)</td>
<td>103 (26)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Daytime sleepiness</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total ESS score, m (sd)</td>
<td>8.0 (4.3)</td>
<td>8.0 (4.1)</td>
<td>7.9 (4.5)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ESS &gt;10, n (%)</td>
<td>129 (33)</td>
<td>61 (15)</td>
<td>68 (17)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1474515112438163">
<label>*</label>
<p>&lt;0.05, ** &lt;0.01, *** &lt;0.001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1474515112438163">
<title>Study population characteristics according to body composition and gender</title>
<p>Eighty-six percent of the men were overweight (BMI &gt;25 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) compared to 70% of the women (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001). Obesity class II was more common among women compared to men, 14% vs 8% (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001). Mean age was significantly lower for men in obesity class II compared to all other classes (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001). Waist and neck circumference increased significantly across the BMI classes for both genders (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001), and neck circumference was significantly greater in men compared to women in all classes (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001). Systolic and diastolic blood pressure did not differ across the BMI classes or between genders. Neither did occurrence of IHD, hypercholesterolaemia or respiratory disease. Diabetes was found among 36% of those in obesity class II, compared to 4%, 16% and 25% of those with normal weight, pre-obesity and obesity class I (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001), respectively. No gender differences were found in any of the classes. ACEI/ARB use was more common among men with pre-obesity and obesity class I compared to women (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01). Diuretics were more commonly taken by women with obesity class I compared to men in the same class (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1474515112438163">
<title>OSA according to body composition and gender</title>
<p>Occurrence of mild, moderate, and severe OSA increased significantly across the BMI classes for both genders (p&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1474515112438163">Table 2</xref>). Ninety percent of the men and 80% of the women in obesity class II had OSA. Mild, moderate and severe OSA was seen in 25%, 12%, and 8% of the men with normal weight compared to 40%, 13% and 40% of men in obesity class II (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05). In women with normal weight, the occurrence of mild, moderate and severe OSA was 26%, 6% and 5% compared to 30%, 30% and 20% in those in obesity class II. Severe OSA was significantly more common in men (39%) compared to women (12%) in obesity class I (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01). Mean AHI was significantly higher in pre-obesity and obesity class I men compared to women (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) in the same classes. ODI was significantly higher in men in obesity class I (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05). Mean and nadir oxygen saturation (SaO2) was significantly lower (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) for men with pre-obesity, and nadir SaO2 among men with normal weight (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01) compared to women in the same classes. The mean number of desaturations was significantly higher among pre-obese men (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05), men in obesity class I (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01) and class II (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001) compared to women in the same classes. Saturation time &lt;90% was significantly more common in men in obesity class I compared to women (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1474515112438163" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Characteristics of the population (n = 394) according to body mass index (BMI) and gender</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1474515112438163" xlink:href="10.1177_1474515112438163-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"><bold>Variables</bold></th>
<th align="left" colspan="8">BMI classes<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Under weight/Normal weight</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Pre obesity</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Obesity class I</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Obesity class II</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="2">BMI &lt;24.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (n=86, 22%)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">BMI 25-29.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (n=174, 44%)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">BMI 30-34.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (n=89, 23%)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">BMI &gt;35 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (n=45, 11%)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Men (n=24, 13%)</th>
<th align="left">Women (n=62, 30%)</th>
<th align="left">Men (n=97, 53%)</th>
<th align="left">Women (n=77, 37%)</th>
<th align="left">Men (n=49, 26%)</th>
<th align="left">Women (n=40, 19%)</th>
<th align="left">Men (n=15, 8%)</th>
<th align="left">Women (n=30, 14%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><bold>Age</bold>, m (sd)</td>
<td>60.5 (4.1)</td>
<td>58.7 (5.9)</td>
<td>58.3 (6.0)</td>
<td>59.7 (5.0)</td>
<td>57.2 (6.7)</td>
<td>55.9 (5.3)</td>
<td>54.14 (5.6)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1474515112438163">***</xref></td>
<td>56.1 (6.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Body composition</bold>, m (sd)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Waist circumference</td>
<td>94.2 (6.4)</td>
<td>84.4 (6.9)</td>
<td>101.5 (5.9)</td>
<td>93.6 (8.0)</td>
<td>112.7 (6.1)</td>
<td>106.12 (7.4)</td>
<td>126.3 (8.8)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1474515112438163">***</xref></td>
<td>119.5 (8.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Waist-hip-ratio</td>
<td>1.0 (0.2)</td>
<td>0.88 (0.1)</td>
<td>1.0 (0.2)</td>
<td>0.89 (0.7)</td>
<td>1.05 (0.1)</td>
<td>0.93 (0.1)</td>
<td>1.1 (0.1)</td>
<td>0.93 (0.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Neck circumference</td>
<td>39.7 (1.9)</td>
<td>34.3 (2.2)</td>
<td>40.7 (2.0)</td>
<td>36.0 (2.3)</td>
<td>43.4 (2.1)</td>
<td>37.9 (1.94)</td>
<td>53.1 (18.0)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1474515112438163">***</xref></td>
<td>39.9 (2.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Blood pressure</bold>, m (sd)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Systolic blood pressure</td>
<td>145.4 (19.7)</td>
<td>138.4 (16.3)</td>
<td>137.7 (16.8)</td>
<td>142.0 (16.4)</td>
<td>145.1 (17.9)</td>
<td>139.9 (19.3)</td>
<td>144.6 (17.3)</td>
<td>136.6 (15.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diastolic blood pressure</td>
<td>87.2 (11.0)</td>
<td>87.3 (9.0)</td>
<td>86.3 (9.5)</td>
<td>84.5 (9.1)</td>
<td>91.3 (12.5)</td>
<td>87.8 (9.8)</td>
<td>90.4 (14.1)</td>
<td>86.8 (13.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Comorbidities</bold>, n (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IHD</td>
<td>20 (83)</td>
<td>43 (69)</td>
<td>68 (70)</td>
<td>53 (69)</td>
<td>35 (71)</td>
<td>33 (82)</td>
<td>9 (60)</td>
<td>22 (73)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hypercholesterolemia</td>
<td>4 (17)</td>
<td>18 (29)</td>
<td>30 (31)</td>
<td>24 (31)</td>
<td>17 (35)</td>
<td>13 (32)</td>
<td>4 (27)</td>
<td>10 (33)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TIA/Stroke</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2 (2)</td>
<td>1 (1)</td>
<td>1 (2)</td>
<td>1 (2)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diabetes</td>
<td>1 (4)</td>
<td>2 (3)</td>
<td>15 (15)</td>
<td>12 (16)</td>
<td>15 (31)</td>
<td>7 (17)</td>
<td>6 (40)</td>
<td>9 (30)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Respiratory disease</td>
<td>2 (8)</td>
<td>2 (3)</td>
<td>8 (8)</td>
<td>4 (5)</td>
<td>2 (4)</td>
<td>0 (0)</td>
<td>2 (13)</td>
<td>4 (13)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Risk factors for CVD</bold>, n (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Smoking</td>
<td>2 (8)</td>
<td>7 (11)</td>
<td>9 (9)</td>
<td>7 (9)</td>
<td>9 (18)</td>
<td>7 (17)</td>
<td>1 (7)</td>
<td>10 (33)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1474515112438163">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ex-smoker</td>
<td>7 (29)</td>
<td>10 (16)</td>
<td>28 (29)</td>
<td>20 (26)</td>
<td>14 (28)</td>
<td>11 (27)</td>
<td>7 (47)</td>
<td>4 (13)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Family history of CVD</td>
<td>8 (33)</td>
<td>37 (60)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
<td>53 (55)</td>
<td>54 (70)</td>
<td>20 (41)</td>
<td>24 (60)</td>
<td>9 (60)</td>
<td>18 (60)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Medication</bold>, n (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ACEI/ARB</td>
<td>13 (54)</td>
<td>25 (40)</td>
<td>66 (68)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1474515112438163">**</xref></td>
<td>37 (48)</td>
<td>35 (71)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
<td>20 (50)</td>
<td>10 (67)</td>
<td>16 (53)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CA-blockers</td>
<td>8 (33)</td>
<td>10 (16)</td>
<td>21 (22)</td>
<td>17 (22)</td>
<td>12 (24)</td>
<td>4 (10)</td>
<td>1 (7)</td>
<td>7 (23)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>B-blockers</td>
<td>14 (58)</td>
<td>30 (48)</td>
<td>44 (45)</td>
<td>39 (51)</td>
<td>21 (43)</td>
<td>13 (32)</td>
<td>6 (40)</td>
<td>15 (50)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diuretics</td>
<td>6 (25)</td>
<td>21 (34)</td>
<td>23 (24)</td>
<td>29 (38)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
<td>13 (26)</td>
<td>18 (45)</td>
<td>6 (40)</td>
<td>12 (40)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hypnotics</td>
<td>0 (0)</td>
<td>4 (6)</td>
<td>3 (3)</td>
<td>4 (5)</td>
<td>1 (2)</td>
<td>5 (12)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
<td>0 (0)</td>
<td>1 (3)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1474515112438163">
<label>*</label>
<p>&lt;0.05, ** &lt;0.01, *** &lt;0.001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1474515112438163">
<title>Self-rated symptoms according to body composition and gender</title>
<p>Habitual snoring was reported by 37%, 43% and 40% of the men in pre-obesity, obesity class I and class II, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1474515112438163">Table 3</xref>). Women in the same classes reported 48%, 42% and 37%, but no gender differences were identified. In obesity class II, 60% of the men and 27% of the women reported witnessed apnoeas (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05). Almost 50% of both genders in obesity class I and II suffered from difficulties maintaining sleep and/or non-restorative sleep. Women with normal weight reported more problems with initiating sleep (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01) than men with normal weight, while women with pre-obesity reported more difficulties maintaining sleep (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) and morning headaches (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) than pre-obese men. Excessive daytime sleepiness (ESS &gt;10) occurred in around 30% of the patients in all classes and no gender differences were found</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1474515112438163" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA), self-rated symptoms, sleep complaints and daytime sleepiness according to body mass index (BMI) and gender</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1474515112438163" xlink:href="10.1177_1474515112438163-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"><bold>Variables</bold></th>
<th align="left" colspan="8">BMI classes<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Under weight/Normal weight</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Pre obesity</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Obesity class I</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Obesity class II</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left" colspan="2">BMI &lt;24.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (n=86, 22%)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">BMI 25-29.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (n=174, 44%)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">BMI 30-34.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (n=88, 23%)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">BMI &gt;35 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (n=45, 11%)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Men (n=24, 13%)</th>
<th align="left">Women (n=62, 30%)</th>
<th align="left">Men (n=97, 53%)</th>
<th align="left">Women (n=77, 37%)</th>
<th align="left">Men (n=49, 26%)</th>
<th align="left">Women (n=40, 19%)</th>
<th align="left">Men (n=15, 8%)</th>
<th align="left">Women (n=30, 14%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>OSA</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Yes, n (%)</td>
<td>11 (46)</td>
<td>23 (37)</td>
<td>60 (62)</td>
<td>39 (51)</td>
<td>39 (80)</td>
<td>26 (65)</td>
<td>14 (93)</td>
<td>24 (80)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No OSA, n (%)</td>
<td>13 (54)</td>
<td>39 (63)</td>
<td>37 (38)</td>
<td>38 (49)</td>
<td>10 (20)</td>
<td>14 (35)</td>
<td>1 (7)</td>
<td>6 (20)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mild OSA, n (%)</td>
<td>6 (25)</td>
<td>16 (26)</td>
<td>30 (31)</td>
<td>21 (27)</td>
<td>13 (26)</td>
<td>12 (30)</td>
<td>6 (40)</td>
<td>9 (30)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Moderate OSA, n (%)</td>
<td>3 (12)</td>
<td>4 (6)</td>
<td>18 (18)</td>
<td>13 (17)</td>
<td>7 (14)</td>
<td>8 (20)</td>
<td>2 (13)</td>
<td>9 (30)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Severe OSA, n (%)</td>
<td>2 (8)</td>
<td>3 (5)</td>
<td>12 (12)</td>
<td>5 (6)</td>
<td>19 (39)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1474515112438163">**</xref></td>
<td>5 (12)</td>
<td>6 (40)</td>
<td>6 (20)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Apnea hypopnea index, m (sd)</td>
<td>10.1 (11.1)</td>
<td>6.0 (8.3)</td>
<td>12.8 (13.51)</td>
<td>9.1 (10.5)</td>
<td>24.6 (21.3)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
<td>15.9 (20.0)</td>
<td>30.7 (27.6)</td>
<td>22.4 (28.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Oxygen desaturation index, m (sd)</td>
<td>7.7 (9.0)</td>
<td>5.2 (7.9)</td>
<td>11.3 (12.52)</td>
<td>8.4 (9.8)</td>
<td>23.4 (20.4)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
<td>14.9 (18.1)</td>
<td>29.4 (26.3)</td>
<td>21.7 (29.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SaO2 – M, m (sd)</td>
<td>94.5 (1.6)</td>
<td>94.7 (5.2)</td>
<td>93.9 (1.7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
<td>94.7 (1.5)</td>
<td>93.3 (2.0)</td>
<td>91.6 (14.3)</td>
<td>92.5 (2.1)</td>
<td>93.6 (2.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SaO2 – N, m (sd)</td>
<td>78.9 (24.4)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
<td>87.4 (5.6)</td>
<td>84.6 (6.0)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
<td>86.4 (5.0)</td>
<td>82.0 (7.5)</td>
<td>80.9 (14.4)</td>
<td>78.7 (7.5)</td>
<td>78.9 (16.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total desaturations, m (sd)</td>
<td>46.0 (54.5)</td>
<td>32.1 (51.6)</td>
<td>71.8 (81.2)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
<td>54.8 (69.9)</td>
<td>146.8 (135.4)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1474515112438163">**</xref></td>
<td>90.9 (100.8)</td>
<td>203.4 (189.3)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1474515112438163">***</xref></td>
<td>124.4 (182.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Time (%) &lt;90%, m (sd)</td>
<td>1.7 (2.0)</td>
<td>0.8 (3.9)</td>
<td>2.8 (6.9)</td>
<td>2.0 (7.1)</td>
<td>9.3 (14.1)</td>
<td>3.6 (7.0)</td>
<td>15.6 (23.2)</td>
<td>6.6 (10.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Symptoms of OSA</bold>, n (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Snoring</td>
<td>8 (33)</td>
<td>20 (32)</td>
<td>36 (37)</td>
<td>37 (48)</td>
<td>21 (43)</td>
<td>17 (42)</td>
<td>6 (40)</td>
<td>11 (37)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Witnessed apneas</td>
<td>5 (21)</td>
<td>16 (26)</td>
<td>34 (35)</td>
<td>40 (52)</td>
<td>19 (39)</td>
<td>15 (37)</td>
<td>9 (60)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
<td>8 (27)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dry mouth</td>
<td>4 (17)</td>
<td>17 (27)</td>
<td>25 (26)</td>
<td>30 (39)</td>
<td>13 (26)</td>
<td>20 (50)</td>
<td>6 (40)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
<td>8 (27)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Morning headache</td>
<td>2 (8)</td>
<td>10 (16)</td>
<td>5 (5)</td>
<td>12 (16)</td>
<td>5 (10)</td>
<td>8 (20)</td>
<td>1 (7)</td>
<td>3 (10)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Self-rated sleep</bold>, m (sd)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sleep duration, hours</td>
<td>7.0 (0.7)</td>
<td>7.0 (1.2)</td>
<td>6.8 (1.0)</td>
<td>6.7 (1.0)</td>
<td>6.8 (1.1)</td>
<td>6.4 (1.1)</td>
<td>6.4 (1.0)</td>
<td>6.4 (1.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Estimated sleep need, hours</td>
<td>7.6 (0.6)</td>
<td>7.7 (0.6)</td>
<td>7.7 (0.8)</td>
<td>7.8 (0.9)</td>
<td>7.8 (1.1)</td>
<td>7.8 (0.8)</td>
<td>7.6 (0.7)</td>
<td>7.9 (0.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sleep sufficiency index, %</td>
<td>0.92 (0.1)</td>
<td>0.90 (0.1)</td>
<td>0.88 (0.1)</td>
<td>0.87 (0.1)</td>
<td>0.88 (0.1)</td>
<td>0.82 (0.1)</td>
<td>0.85 (0.1)</td>
<td>0.82 (0.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Insomnia symptoms</bold>, n (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Difficulties initiating sleep</td>
<td>1 (4)</td>
<td>21 (33)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1474515112438163">**</xref></td>
<td>18 (18)</td>
<td>22 (28)</td>
<td>14 (28)</td>
<td>17 (42)</td>
<td>6 (40)</td>
<td>13 (43)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Difficulties maintaining sleep</td>
<td>9 (37)</td>
<td>31 (50)</td>
<td>38 (39)</td>
<td>43 (56)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-1474515112438163">*</xref></td>
<td>24 (49)</td>
<td>23 (57)</td>
<td>10 (67)</td>
<td>21 (70)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Difficulties with non-restorative sleep</td>
<td>8 (33)</td>
<td>28 (45)</td>
<td>42 (43)</td>
<td>38 (49)</td>
<td>27 (55)</td>
<td>22 (55)</td>
<td>8 (53)</td>
<td>15 (50)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Daytime sleepiness</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total ESS score, m (sd)</td>
<td>7. 4 (4.7)</td>
<td>7.4 (4.7)</td>
<td>7.9 (4.1)</td>
<td>8.2 (4.7)</td>
<td>8.0 (3.8)</td>
<td>7.9 (4.3)</td>
<td>9.3 (4.3)</td>
<td>8.1 (4.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ESS &gt;10, n (%)</td>
<td>7 (29)</td>
<td>19 (31)</td>
<td>33 (34)</td>
<td>30 (39)</td>
<td>14 (28)</td>
<td>11 (27)</td>
<td>7 (47)</td>
<td>8 (27)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1474515112438163">
<label>*</label>
<p>&lt;0.05, ** &lt;0.01, *** &lt;0.001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1474515112438163" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>This study of primary care patients with HT confirms the associations between OSA and obesity. Being overweight was highly prevalent and the occurrence of mild, moderate and severe OSA increased significantly across the BMI classes for both genders. Ninety percent of the men and 80% of the women in obesity class II had OSA. Insomnia was also prevalent among both genders with high BMI.</p>
<p>We found a mean BMI of 29.1 ± 4.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup> for men and 28.6 ±5.6 kg/m<sup>2</sup> for women. Pre-obesity was seen in 53% of the men and 37% of the women. Obesity class I was identified in 26% of the men and 19% of the women, and 8% of the men and 14% of the women were in obesity class II. Another recent Swedish study,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1474515112438163">30</xref></sup> not focusing on OSA or HT, found lower figures with 50% of men and 30% of female aged 16-84 years being overweight or obese. Romero-Corral et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1474515112438163">31</xref></sup> examined 13,601 subjects from the USA and found a mean BMI of 26.6 ±4.6 kg/m<sup>2</sup> in men and 27.6 ±6.4 kg/m<sup>2</sup> in women. A BMI &gt;30 kg/m<sup>2</sup> was present in 21% of men and 31% of women. Obesity is closely linked to OSA, HT, diabetes and CVD. Anthropometric factors (excess body weight, large neck circumference) can alone, or together with anatomical factors (such as maxillo-mandibular retrognathia or enlarged tonsils) compromise the size of the upper airway and increase the risk for OSA and other comorbidities over time. Huang et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1474515112438163">32</xref></sup> used data from 60,197 Australian medical records and found that obesity and OSA showed a similar time course of onset (age 25–29 years), with a latent period of 5 years for HT and Type 2 diabetes (age 30–34 years) and 15 years (age 40–44 years) for IHD. Fifty-nine percent of our mostly middle-aged patients with HT had OSA. Eighty percent and 90% of the men in obesity class I and II, respectively, suffered from OSA. Furthermore, 60% and 80% of the women in the same obesity classes had OSA. We did not, however, follow our patients over time, but IHD was a highly prevalent comorbidity in all BMI classes.</p>
<p>Patients with OSA can be difficult to identify in clinical practice since many are unaware of their situation due to the fact that the apnoeas occur during sleep.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1474515112438163">5</xref></sup> We found that less than 40% of the men and women in obesity class I reported witnessed apnoeas despite an objective occurrence of OSA of 80%. In obesity class II men, the occurrence of reported witnessed apnoeas increased to 60%, but only 27% of the women (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) in this BMI class reported witnessed apnoeas. Difficulties maintaining sleep and non-restorative sleep were more prevalent among both genders in obesity class I and II, but not in line with the objective occurrence of OSA. Nevertheless, information from patients or their relatives about habitual snoring, disturbed sleep and especially witnessed apnoeas are of vital importance in identifying patients with OSA.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1474515112438163">33</xref></sup> The absence of reports of these signs does not exclude the presence of OSA. Furthermore, no gender differences were found regarding systolic and diastolic blood pressure, neither did IHD, hypercholesterolaemia or occurrence of excessive daytime sleepiness differ between BMI classes or genders. A high BMI might, therefore, be a convenient clinical marker for healthcare personnel at HT clinics in primary care for identifying patients with possible OSA in need of further objective evaluation and treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1474515112438163">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>There is evidence that treating obesity reduces the severity of OSA and, conversely, that treating OSA decreases obesity. OSA may itself predispose to further weight gain because of sleep disturbances, daytime sleepiness and negative effects on the metabolism.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1474515112438163">13</xref></sup> Peppard et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1474515112438163">34</xref></sup> found that a 10% weight gain predicted an approximate 32% increase in AHI and a 6-fold increase in the odds of developing moderate to severe OSA among persons initially free of OSA. Furthermore, a weight loss of 10% predicted a 26% decrease in AHI. A recent study by Johansson et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1474515112438163">35</xref></sup> using an intensive intervention based on a low calorie diet in obese patients (with a mean BMI &gt;35 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) with severe OSA (AHI &gt;30) showed promising results with decreased weight and reduced AHI. Reducing the BMI from obesity class II to class I may also hypothetically decrease the risk for CVD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1474515112438163">15</xref></sup> Long-term results of dietary interventions and cardiovascular death are few, but a recent study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1474515112438163">36</xref></sup> showed promising results regarding sustained reduction of weight and AHI. However, changing eating habits to reduce weight can be difficult for the individual to achieve. The degree to which a person is committed to the objective – for example, a change in eating habits – may also influence the sustainability of the behaviour in question. Smith et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1474515112438163">37</xref></sup> found that a minority of obese patients with OSA was prepared to change eating and exercise habits.</p>
<p>Motivation is a key predictor of behaviour change in many cognitive and social–cognitive theories concerning behaviour modification. Hence, knowledge of factors that impact on motivation to achieve behavioural changes is important in clinical situations, such as when healthcare personnel address an OSA patient’s dietary habits. The Self-determination Theory<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1474515112438163">38</xref></sup> posits that different types of motivation guide behaviours. An extrinsically motivated behaviour is performed in order to obtain a reward or to avoid negative consequences, such as a person avoiding unhealthy food simply by being told to by a healthcare personnel. Introjected regulation refers to behaviours that have been partially taken in by the person and are performed to avoid feeling guilt, such as someone eating wholesome food because of anxieties about CVD. Identified regulation occurs when a person engages in an activity in order to demonstrate ability or worth, such as eating healthy food to gain appreciation from one’s spouse. Integrated regulation means that the behaviour has become fully congruent with one’s sense of self, for instance eating a wholesome diet because ‘it’s the right thing to do’. Intrinsically motivated or self-determined behaviours are performed for their own sake, such as eating a wholesome diet for the sheer pleasure of doing so. A behaviour that is inherently satisfactory is more likely to be repeated and become habitual than a behaviour that offers little or no pleasure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1474515112438163">38</xref></sup> Research has identified factors that impact positively and negatively on OSA patients’ motivation for behaviour change. Excessive daytime sleepiness, fatigue and listlessness have been shown to impact negatively on motivation, whereas fear of CVD, negative social effects and support from spouses have been shown to influence motivation positively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1474515112438163">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1474515112438163">39</xref></sup> Nurses should be aware of these barriers and facilitators for behavioural change and strive to provide information about the potential gains of achieving weight reduction to foster a more intrinsically motivated behaviour.</p>
<p>Habits are learned sequences of acts that have been repeated until they become more or less automatic responses to situational or contextual cues. Forming good habits is facilitated by a stable context that allows a person to repeat the same behavioural choice in the same situation, gradually building up associations between situational or contextual cues and the response.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1474515112438163">40</xref></sup> Applying so-called implementation intentions by defining specific cues and associated action plans on ‘when’, ‘how’ and ‘where’ to perform a behaviour can bridge the gap between intention and behaviour. An implementation intention plan for an obese patient with HT/OSA and a sedentary life style can specify that the person will exercise every day after work (when) by swiftly walking (how) around the neighbourhood (where). Integrating physical activity as part of daily routines has been advocated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1474515112438163">41</xref></sup> and combining diet and physical activity are generally found to be effective weight reduction measures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1474515112438163">42</xref></sup></p>
<sec id="section19-1474515112438163">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>This study has some limitations that must be taken into account. The BMI measure does not account for the distribution between lean mass and adipose tissue.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1474515112438163">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1474515112438163">31</xref></sup> There is, therefore, a risk that BMI overestimates adiposity in patients with leaner body mass, whereas adiposity may be under-estimated among those with less lean body mass. Thus, the magnitude of obesity may have been underestimated due to the use of BMI as a measure of obesity. However, BMI is a well-known and widely applied measure and makes it possible to compare results with other datasets. Another limitation is the small number of subjects in obesity class I (<italic>n</italic>=89) and II (<italic>n</italic>=45), which made it difficult to perform gender-specific analyses. Still another limitation is the lack of objective sleep data although the AHI obtained by the Embletta recording device has been shown to have a fair correlation with AHI obtained by polysomnographic equipment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1474515112438163">26</xref></sup> Strengths of the study include the relatively large sample size (<italic>n</italic>=394) and the use of established, well-validated questionnaires.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1474515112438163">27</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1474515112438163"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1474515112438163">29</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-1474515112438163">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Being overweight and obesity was prevalent among both genders. Occurrence of OSA increased with BMI. Difficulties maintaining sleep was highly common in obese men and women. Habitual snoring and witnessed apnoeas were less prevalent even in the obese group. High BMI could be used by healthcare personnel in primary care as a convenient clinical marker to identify cardiovascular patients of both genders who are in need of further investigation and referral to a sleep clinic.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We wish to thank Jan Albers and Anna Ståhlkrantz from the Department of Internal Medicine, County Hospital Ryhov, Jönköping, Sweden, as well as Eva Berntzen and Maria Elfström from the Ear, Nose and Throat Clinic, County Hospital Ryhov, Jönköping, Sweden for their contributions to the study.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors wish to thank the Health Research Council in the South-East of Sweden for financial support, Grant FORSS-12568, Grant FORSS-12710, Grant FORSS-79491, Grant FORSS-88221 and The Swedish Heart Lung Foundation Grant 20090547.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>None declared.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1474515112438163">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>The World Health Report 2002</collab>. <source>Reducing risks, promoting healthy life</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>, <year>2002</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1474515112438163">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haslam</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>James</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Obesity</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>366</volume>: <fpage>1197</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1474515112438163">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>The Task Force for the Management of Arterial Hypertension of the European Society of Hypertension (ESH) and of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) 2007</collab>. <article-title>Guidelines for the management of arterial hypertension</article-title>. <source>J Hypertens</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1105</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1474515112438163">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chobanian</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bakris</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The Seventh Report of the Joint National Committee on Prevention, Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure: the JNC 7 report</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1206</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1474515112438163">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kristo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strollo</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical guideline for the evaluation, management and long-term care of obstructive sleep apnea in adults</article-title>. <source>J Clin Sleep Med</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1474515112438163">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moyer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sonnad</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garetz</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Quality of life in obstructive sleep apnea: a systematic review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Sleep Med</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>477</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1474515112438163">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect on quality of life of continuous positive airway pressure in patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Lung</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>186</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1474515112438163">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peppard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of obstructive sleep apnea: a population health perspective</article-title>. <source>Am J Resp Crit Care Med</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>165</volume>: <fpage>1217</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1474515112438163">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>National Institutes of Health, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</collab>. <article-title>Clinical guidelines on the identification, evaluation, and treatment of overweight and obesity in adults: the evidence report</article-title>. <source>Obes Res</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>6</volume> (<supplement>Suppl 2</supplement>): <fpage>S51</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1474515112438163">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <source>Obesity: preventing and managing the global epidemic</source>. Report of a WHO Consultation, 2000. World Health Organization Tech Rep Ser <year>2000</year>; <volume>894</volume>: <fpage>i</fpage>–<lpage>xii</lpage>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1474515112438163">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Andreyevaa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Michaudb</surname><given-names>P-C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Soest</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Obesity and health in Europeans aged 50 years and older</article-title>. <source>Publ Health</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>509</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1474515112438163">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Drager</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Genta</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pedrosa</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Characteristics and predictors of obstructive sleep apnea in patients with systemic hypertension</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>1135</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1474515112438163">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pack</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gislason</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and cardiovascular disease: a perspective and future directions</article-title>. <source>Progr Card Dis</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>434</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1474515112438163">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pillar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shehadeh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Abdominal fat and sleep apnea. The chicken or the egg?</article-title> <source>Diab Care</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>S303</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1474515112438163">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abdulla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Køber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abildstrøm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Impact of obesity as a mortality predictor in high-risk patients with myocardial infarction or chronic heart failure: a pooled analysis of five registries</article-title>. <source>Euro Heart J</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>594</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1474515112438163">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wolk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shamsuzzaman</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Obesity, sleep apnea, and hypertension</article-title>. <source>Hypertension</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1067</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1474515112438163">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carrizo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term cardiovascular outcomes in men with obstructive sleep apnoea-hypopnoea with or without treatment with continuous positive airway pressure: an observational study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>365</volume>: <fpage>1046</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1474515112438163">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lavie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mortality in sleep apnoea syndrome: a review of the evidence</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir Rev</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1474515112438163">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kapur</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strohl</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Redline</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Underdiagnosis of sleep apnea syndrome in U.S. communities</article-title>. <source>Sleep Breath</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1474515112438163">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Netzer</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hoegel</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loube</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of symptoms and risk of sleep apnea in primary care</article-title>. <source>Chest</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>1406</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1474515112438163">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Gender differences in obstructive sleep apnea and treatment implications</article-title>. <source>Sleep Med Rev</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1474515112438163">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Quintana-Gallego</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carmona-Bernal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Capote</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Gender differences in obstructive sleep apnea syndrome: a clinical study of 1166 patients</article-title>. <source>Respir Med</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>984</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1474515112438163">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>L-G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Gender differences in symptoms related to sleep apnea in a general population and in relation to referral to sleep clinic</article-title>. <source>Chest</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1474515112438163">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vagiakis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kapsimalis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lagogianni</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Gender differences on polysomnographic findings in Greek subjects with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source>Sleep Med</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>424</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1474515112438163">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The gender bias in sleep apnea diagnosis: are women missed because they have different symptoms?</article-title> <source>Arch Intern Med</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>156</volume>: <fpage>2445</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1474515112438163">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Collop</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boehlecke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical guidelines for the use of unattended portable monitors in the diagnosis of obstructive sleep apnea in adult patients. Portable Monitoring Task Force of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine</article-title>. <source>J Clin Sleep Med</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>737</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1474515112438163">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Netzer</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stoohs</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Netzer</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Using the Berlin Questionnaire to identify patients at risk for the sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>485</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1474515112438163">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Broman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smedje</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mallon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The Minimal Insomnia Symptom Scale (MISS): a brief measure of sleeping difficulties</article-title>. <source>Ups J Med Sci</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1474515112438163">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth Sleepiness Scale</article-title>. <source>Sleep</source> <year>1991</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1474515112438163">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Asplund</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Obesity in elderly people with nocturia: cause or consequence?</article-title> <source>Can J Urol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>3424</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1474515112438163">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Romero-Corral</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sierra-Johnson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Accuracy of body mass index in diagnosing obesity in the adult general population</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>959</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1474515112438163">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>QR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical patterns of obstructive sleep apnea and its comorbid conditions: a data mining approach</article-title>. <source>J Clin Sleep Med</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>543</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1474515112438163">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Broström</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>6-month CPAP-treatment in a young male patient with severe obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome – a case study from the couple’s perspective</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cardiovasc Nurs</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1474515112438163">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peppard</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Longitudinal study of moderate weight change and sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>284</volume>: <fpage>3015</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1474515112438163">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neovius</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lagerros</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of a very low energy diet on moderate and severe obstructive sleep apnoea in obese men: a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>339</volume>: <fpage>b4609</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1474515112438163">
<label>36.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hemmingsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harlid</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Longer term effects of very low energy diet on obstructive sleep apnoea in cohort derived from randomised controlled trial: prospective observational follow-up study</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>342</volume>: <fpage>d3017</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1474515112438163">
<label>37.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pascoe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Intention to exercise in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source>J Clin Sleep Med</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>689</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1474515112438163">
<label>38.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Intrinsic motivation and self-determination in human behavior</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Plenum Press</publisher-name>, <year>1985</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1474515112438163">
<label>39.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Broström</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nilsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Putative facilitators and barriers for adherence to CPAP treatment in patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome: a qualitative content analysis</article-title>. <source>Sleep Med</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1474515112438163">
<label>40.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Verplanken</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Beyond frequency: habit as mental construct</article-title>. <source>Br J Soc Psych</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>639</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1474515112438163">
<label>41.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aarts</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paulussen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schaalma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Physical exercise habit: on the conceptualization and formation of habitual health behaviours</article-title>. <source>Health Ed Res</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1474515112438163">
<label>42.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Froelicher</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Management of overweight and obesity in adults: behavioral intervention for long-term weight loss and maintenance</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cardiovasc Nurs</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>