<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppia</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part A: Journal of Power and Energy</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0957-6509</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-2967</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0957650912471291</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0957650912471291</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Special Issue Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Why is renewable heat in the UK underperforming? A socio-technical perspective</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>Noam</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0957650912471291"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0957650912471291">Environmental Change Institute, School of Geography and Environment, Oxford, UK</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0957650912471291">Noam Bergman, Environmental Change Institute, School of Geography and Environment, South Parks Road, Oxford OX1 3QY, UK. Email: <email>noam.bergman@ouce.ox.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>227</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<issue-title>Special issue on micro-generation and related energy technologies and practices for low carbon buildings</issue-title>
<fpage>124</fpage>
<lpage>131</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The potential role of microgeneration in energy supply, carbon emissions reduction, energy security and even fuel poverty has been a topic of much interest in the past few years. Industry and government focus has been on financial tools and other policies aimed at maximising uptake. However, some recent studies on solar hot water and heat pumps suggest that not all microgeneration installations are delivering the expected energy or emissions savings, and consumers are in turn not reaping the expected financial benefits. The reasons are a mixture of technical problems and poor installations, institutional issues, poor information supply to users, and improper use. Such issues could delay or jeopardise plans for rolling out microgenerators such as heat pumps. This article considers what policies would help maximise the above-listed benefits of microgeneration, including the implications for the Renewable Heat Incentive, and the importance of measuring actual energy savings in homes. Given the mixed nature of the issues, a broader systemic view is used to analyse the institutional, cultural and behavioural reasons for the discrepancies in energy savings.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Microgeneration</kwd>
<kwd>heat pumps</kwd>
<kwd>solar hot water</kwd>
<kwd>socio-technical system</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0957650912471291" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>The potential of microgeneration to contribute to the UK’s energy system through generation, emissions reduction, fuel poverty alleviation and diversity of supply has been a hot topic for the past decade or more. Despite different policies regulating microgeneration and supporting uptake over this time, it has so far failed to play a significant part in the domestic energy sector. There has been some controversy over the efficacy of microgenerators, with some (e.g. small rooftop wind turbines in urban settings) falling out of favour after evidence of poor performance. In this article, two renewable heat technologies are considered, which recent evidence suggests might be performing far less efficiently than commonly thought. Possible reasons and consequences of this underperformance are analysed. This is done using a systemic view, considering domestic renewable heat as part of the <italic>socio-technical system</italic> of household energy, which includes technology and the human dimension of users and the supply chain in their cultural and institutional context.</p>
<p>Previous policies supporting microgeneration include the Low Carbon Buildings Programme (LCBP), which ran from April 2006 and recently ended. The LCBP gave grants for installations, with pre-requirements including some energy efficiency measures, such as loft insulation. This was intended as a ‘whole house’ energy approach. The LCBP did not have enough uptake to make microgeneration more than a small niche in the (domestic) energy sector. The LCBP has been replaced by feed-in tariffs (FITs) for electricity-producing microgenerators, with the Renewable Heat Incentive (RHI) soon to replace grants for heat-producing systems. There is stopgap funding for renewable heat in the meantime. FITs and RHI are not based on grants but pay households for the energy they have micro-generated: FITs are metered; domestic RHI generation will probably be deemed (estimated), although metering was also discussed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957650912471291">1</xref></sup> It is hoped that FITs and RHI will increase uptake, following the success of FITs in other countries. At the time of writing UK energy policy is fluid: the launch of domestic RHI was postponed, first to the autumn of 2012,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957650912471291">2</xref></sup> and more recently been has postponed again; other policies such as the Green Deal are also being introduced in 2012 and 2013.</p>
<p>Two (microgeneration) renewable heating technologies are considered: solar hot water (SHW) and heat pumps (HPs). Recent studies surveying 55 and 88 SHW households,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957650912471291">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650912471291">4</xref></sup> respectively, found energy savings were often significantly lower than the industry or policy documents estimates. Another recent study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957650912471291">5</xref></sup> monitored 83 households with heat pumps and found disappointing coefficients of performance (COPs), with most of the installed systems not reaching the estimated 2.6 benchmark for ‘renewable energy’. Additional information comes from a recent study on actors in the heat pump supply chain.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0957650912471291">6</xref></sup> For both technologies, the reasons for poor performance were not merely technical, but varied and complex. We consider renewable energy policy and the RHI in particular, through analysis of these two technology niches.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0957650912471291"><title>Solar hot water</title>
<p>Solar hot water (SHW) is the most common of microgeneration installations, with an estimated 90,000 installations in the UK by 2007.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0957650912471291">7</xref></sup> It is also the most mature technology, with a market emerging in the 1970s, and the first code of practice introduced in 1980.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0957650912471291">8</xref></sup></p>
<sec id="sec3-0957650912471291"><title>Cost</title>
<p>A recent study of domestic microgeneration installations in the UK under the LCBP programme<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0957650912471291">9</xref></sup> found the large majority of SHW systems had an expected output of 500–3000 kWh/year, although energy capacity was poorly reported. The price range for these installations is very large, ranging approximately from £1000 to £8000, with an average around £4000. Moreover, there is hardly any correlation between the expected output of the system and the price of these installations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0957650912471291">Figure 1(a)</xref>). This is in sharp contrast with photovoltaics (PV) installations from the same programme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0957650912471291">Figure 1(b)</xref>), which show very high correlation between price and expected output.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0957650912471291">9</xref></sup>
<fig id="fig1-0957650912471291" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>(a) Price (without VAT) of solar thermal systems installed in the first two years of the LCBP as a function of energy output. (b) Price (without VAT) of solar photovoltaic systems installed in the first two years of the LCBP as a function of installed capacity.</p>
<p>Source: Reproduced with permission from Environmental Change Institute, 2009.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0957650912471291">9</xref></sup></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912471291-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>There are clear differences between the two solar technologies, which can explain some of this difference. For example, plumbing costs associated with SHW can vary considerably. However, this huge variation in prices for seemingly similar installations in the most widespread and mature microgeneration technology is most likely also the result of different profit margins between installers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0957650912471291">9</xref></sup> Another factor is consumers’ poor understanding of expected energy generation, combined with the difficulty in estimating the exact amount of energy SHW saves (unlike PV which is easily metered).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0957650912471291"><title>Energy savings</title>
<p>A recent study on domestic solar hot water<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957650912471291">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0957650912471291">10</xref></sup> estimated that savings were considerably lower than expected, with at least 60% of the systems surveyed achieving <italic>no more than 6% of their potential savings</italic>. Another recent study by the Energy Saving Trust (EST)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650912471291">4</xref></sup> measured SHW performance in 88 households geographically dispersed around the UK and the Republic of Ireland. The EST study found that most contributed less than 40% of the household’s hot water (The report states that the median output energy is equivalent to 39% of a household’s hot water use. This does not indicate the distribution of percentages of hot water supplied in individual households.), compared with 60% achievable for a well-installed, properly used system. While this is better than the estimates of the first study, it is still well below the often assumed 50%. The low savings had variety of causes, including poor use, insufficient information, inappropriate installations and technical faults.</p>
<p>The way households use SHW is crucial to maximising savings, but only 36% in one study received such advice from their installer.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650912471291">4</xref></sup> Most households were unaware that having their boilers on both in the morning and the evening greatly reduced their savings, with many using boilers in the mornings, losing up to 75% of potential savings.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957650912471291">3</xref></sup> Moreover, ‘conversations with manufacturers’ technical personnel suggest that they are not apparently aware of this factor (a technical representative of one installation company stated that ‘it does not matter what you do, solar will work for you anyway’) and the installers they train are not therefore in a position to inform householders.’ (p. 5).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957650912471291">3</xref></sup> Considering that most people accept the recommendation of the installer, often without detailed understanding of the technology,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0957650912471291">11</xref></sup> this household behaviour is not surprising, and may be reinforced by many households having shared time controls for boilers and heating, which by default turn on the hot water system with the heating.</p>
<p>Another factor affecting energy savings was the small size (one or two people) of the large majority of SHW households.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957650912471291">3</xref></sup> The prevalence of small households among solar hot water households reduces potential savings, and is probably partly due to the profile of households investing in microgeneration. However, it was also most likely affected by the upper limit of the LCBP grant, which only paid a small fraction of cost of larger installations, limiting savings (and appeal) for larger households. The RHI would allow greater monetary savings for larger installations, but would not, as currently proposed, assist with the higher upfront cost. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0957650912471291">Figure 2</xref> shows the estimated potential savings for small and large households with and without morning usage of the boiler.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957650912471291">3</xref></sup> The second study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650912471291">4</xref></sup> also suggested that larger households achieved greater benefits from solar hot water.
<fig id="fig2-0957650912471291" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>The percentage of hot water savings available for households from solar thermal boiler<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957650912471291">3</xref></sup> (reproduced with kind permission from Springer Science+Business Media B.V.). While the other SHW study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650912471291">4</xref></sup> found similar savings from flat plates and evacuated tube systems, it confirms larger savings in larger households.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912471291-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The EST study revealed that efficiency was reduced in some households through various technical faults, as well as through insufficient insulation of hot water cylinders and pipes (although the latter affects other hot water systems too).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650912471291">4</xref></sup> Finally, health and safety regulations regarding pasteurisation to avoid Legionella risk might be overkill, and reduce SHW savings.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957650912471291">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>Put together, these factors suggest that maximising energy savings from SHW is no simple task, and requires a systemic perspective to change. We turn next to heat pumps, to see a different but familiar picture.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0957650912471291"><title>Heat pumps</title>
<p>Heat pumps are among the newer microgeneration technologies, and are still a small market niche in the UK, especially in the domestic sector. Ground source heat pumps (GSHPs) are better established and were included in the LCBP from the start, while air source heat pumps (ASHPs) are a more recent market entry, and were added to the LCBP from June 2008.</p>
<p>The small market has seen significant growth in recent years, although exact numbers are unknown. GSHP estimated sales in 2008 were 4000–5000, nearly doubling the market size from 2007,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0957650912471291">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0957650912471291">13</xref></sup> although this is still a small market compared to Sweden, Germany or France. Air source heat pumps (ASHP) had a smaller share of the market in the past, but some estimates put their sales in 2008 close to GSHPs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0957650912471291">12</xref></sup></p>
<sec id="sec6-0957650912471291"><title>Efficiency</title>
<p>Heat pumps require electricity (or another auxiliary energy input) to function. They can reach a COP of 3 or higher, i.e. an output of 3 (or more) units of usable heat energy for every unit of electricity input. When considering renewable energy resources, ‘Only heat pumps with an output that significantly exceeds the primary energy needed to drive it should be taken into account.’ (para. 31).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0957650912471291">14</xref></sup> This is defined as an output of 15% or more above the primary energy input, using the EU electricity production average<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0957650912471291">14</xref></sup> (Annex VII). The heat pump output is calculated using the average seasonal performance factor (SPF), which is not straightforward to calculate (unlike the COP), and which will be strictly defined in 2013. The necessary SPF for the Renewable Energy Directive has been estimated as 2.6,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957650912471291">15</xref></sup> although using the UK’s current grid efficiency gives an estimate closer to 2.9. The SPF is expected to be slightly lower than the COP.</p>
<p>The EST has recently performed the first ‘real conditions in actual homes’ field study of domestic heat pumps in 83 sites across the UK,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957650912471291">5</xref></sup> including both GSHPs and ASHPs. They found highly variable performance rates, with the trial not going as well as expected.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957650912471291">15</xref></sup> Only 13% reached a COP of 3, with approximately 20% reaching 2.6; GSHPs performed slightly better than ASHPs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957650912471291">5</xref></sup> This would suggest that only 1/5th of domestic heat pump energy could be considered renewable, a serious disappointment if domestic heat pumps are to play a significant role in the UK meeting its renewable energy requirements.</p>
<p>The EST study does not detail specific reasons for the low COPs, but does refer to UK weather conditions, installation and commissioning practices and customer behaviour as affecting performance. It also states that many householders had difficulty understanding their heat pump instructions for use.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957650912471291">5</xref></sup> While the two technologies are very different, there is a certain similarity in the underperformance of HPs and SHW installations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0957650912471291"><title>Niche</title>
<p>The UK heat pump market is a small niche, which was recently described through interviews with supply chain actors, including installers, suppliers, manufacturers and others, as well as researchers and policy makers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0957650912471291">6</xref></sup> The supply chain is currently small, with over 300 accredited installers, compared with 60–70,000 domestic heating installers. Current domestic installations are mostly found in new build, off mains gas, and in rural areas (or other houses with adequate space). Household which installed heat pumps tended to be wealthier and older than the average population, and often had a desire to reduce their emissions. Housing associations seeking to reduce heating bills were another market segment. Currently, GSHPs dominate, but the interviews showed many believed ASHPs would overtake them.</p>
<p>Potential drivers for this niche were seen as the manufacturers themselves, who believed they could change the industry rapidly should they choose to do so, and government regulation, as was the case with condensing boilers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0957650912471291"><title>Barriers</title>
<p>When questioned, niche actors saw the main barrier to the heat pump market growing as upfront capital costs, especially for GSHPs, and the lack of grants.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0957650912471291">6</xref></sup> However, the interviews reveal various other barriers, highlighting how maximising uptake and energy savings is not just a matter of financial support for consumers.
<list id="list1-0957650912471291" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Technical difficulties, including a lack of suitable technology for the retrofit market and lack of suitable space for GSHPs.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Poor performance due to poor installation, especially under-sizing – and concerns over a ‘bad name’ from poor installations and poor information for consumers.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Regulatory and bureaucratic barriers, including a possible bottleneck in approval of HP products and equipment, and the lack of grants in the hiatus between the LCBP and the RHI.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Social and cultural barriers, including lack of awareness about HPs, the belief that they are an unproven technology, and preference of ‘wet’ heating systems (over air-to-air).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Cultural barriers in the profession, including cynicism about GSHPs among mechanical and electric consultants, and conservatism in the heating industry, could prevent HPs from being installed even if customers are interested.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Skill deficits, with only a small percentage of installers becoming accredited and a lack of competence to install HPs among traditional installers (heating engineers and plumbers), e.g. dealing with refrigerants.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Institutional barriers, such as the lack of involvement of installers in new-build, where architects’ plans may be incompatible with heat pumps.</p></list-item>
</list>A more technical view of the barriers to uptake<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957650912471291">16</xref></sup> suggests they include the low COPs mentioned, high capital cost and a view that heat pumps require more maintenance than standard boilers. In addition, maximising HP energy savings depends on two factors completely outside the HP sector. The first is the question of the retrofit market, as good use of HPs requires delivery of nontrivial energy efficiency measures. The second is the electricity grid: HP uptake could result in high simultaneous demands for electricity, even as there is pressure to decarbonise the grid for reducing emissions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957650912471291">16</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0957650912471291"><title>RHI</title>
<p>As part of the government’s commitment to increase renewable energy, the RHI was set to run from April 2011, across England, Wales and Scotland, aiming to bridge the financial gap between cost of renewable and conventional domestic heating systems.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957650912471291">17</xref></sup> The RHI will give ‘clean energy cash back’ for renewable heat, similarly to the feed-in tariffs (FITs) for small-scale renewable electricity, although the proposed rates of return are higher that FITs. This is designed to meet different barriers, e.g. installing renewable heat could be considered a greater risk as it would be the primary heating source in the home with no back up, whereas homes with renewable electricity are generally connected to the grid.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0957650912471291">18</xref></sup> At the time of writing, the domestic RHI scheme has been delayed and is currently intended to start in summer 2013.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0957650912471291">19</xref></sup></p>
<sec id="sec10-0957650912471291"><title>Deeming and metering</title>
<p>DECC’s consultation on the RHI<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957650912471291">17</xref></sup> proposed that for small and medium scale installations (which would include domestic installations), generated heat would be estimated – or <italic>deemed</italic> – rather than metered. The deemed heat output is to be calculated as a ‘reasonable heat requirement’ based on SAP (or a variant such as EPC), which would include energy efficiency measures such as loft and cavity wall insulation. The rationale is that this would encourage efficient energy consumption, whereas tariffs paid on a metered basis could encourage ‘generation of surplus heat’ in order to increase RHI income; if metering is used, care must be taken to avoid such perverse incentives. DECC has considered metering,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957650912471291">1</xref></sup> although deeming is stated in the latest updates.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0957650912471291">19</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0957650912471291"><title>Criticisms of RHI</title>
<p>The LCBP required some energy efficiency measures – such as insulation – before receiving a grant for installation of microgeneration. This was partly because one of the goals of the LCBP was a more holistic approach to energy use in buildings, linking efficiency (energy demand) and production. However, the LCBP arguably failed in its attempt to create a holistic energy approach among householders and installers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0957650912471291">9</xref></sup> The RHI as originally proposed followed a similar approach, with later suggestions that <italic>some</italic> homes could receive an RHI ‘premium payment’ which would require a well insulated home based on its energy performance certificate.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957650912471291">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>It is hypothesised that the deeming procedure – which is calculated as heat requirements after efficiency measures are taken – will encourage people to increase their energy efficiency. However, it is hard to see how this would work: when installing a heating system, insulation (beyond the minimum required for eligibility) could be seen as another expense, so would be likely to be put off, especially considering the lack of upfront grants under RHI. After installation, the RHI payback will lower energy bills significantly – thereby reducing the financial incentive to insulate. Poorly insulated homes would still have higher bills, but this is true regardless of RHI policy. On the other hand, one could argue that measures such as solid wall insulation should be deemed and paid for under the RHI, as an installation for saving domestic energy (Thanks to Simon Roberts of the Centre for Sustainable Energy, Bristol, for this insight.).</p>
<p>The RHI does not offer grants on purchase, unlike the LCBP. The long term of the repayment might, from a consumers’ perspective, be worth less than the capital costs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957650912471291">20</xref></sup> This could be a problem, given that upfront costs are a known barrier to microgeneration purchase;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957650912471291">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0957650912471291">21</xref></sup> it also leaves open the problem of how the fuel poor will benefit from the RHI.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957650912471291">20</xref></sup> More generally, the RHI does not tackle any other demand-side barriers.</p>
<p>Another criticism of the RHI is that it does not take into account wider energy policy goals.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957650912471291">20</xref></sup> For example, the integration with building energy demand policies, such as the Household Energy Management Strategy (HEMS) is not systematic. This strengthens the conclusion that there is no holistic approach in the RHI, with little incentive to increase understanding of energy use in the home. However, the energy policy landscape is changing; recent consultations link the RHI to the Green Deal, and this might have the potential to create more of a whole house approach to energy use.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0957650912471291" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>Taking a step back, it is worth considering the role of renewable heat in reducing emissions from the domestic sector, how those savings can be maximised, and the policy implications. This is a systemic view, considering domestic renewable heat as part of the <italic>socio-technical system</italic> of household energy, which includes technology and the human dimension of users and the supply chain in their cultural and institutional context.</p>
<sec id="sec13-0957650912471291"><title>Heat, electricity and performance</title>
<p>The renewable heating examples of solar hot water and heat pumps are very different in some ways – the first is mostly used as an auxiliary water heating system, the second as the primary heating source for homes. SHW is more widespread in the UK, with a more mature market, and is relatively cheap among microgeneration installations. Nonetheless, field based research has shown disappointing energy savings from both, and there are clear parallels between the two. In both cases, there is no one simple reason for the worse than expected performance, but rather there is a mix of technical, institutional and behavioural problems. In other words, the underperformance is systemic. The human dimension (including users, installers and manufacturers) plays an important part in both, including user behaviour and a lack of information provided by installers, as well as poor installations despite accreditation schemes and regulatory standards. The EST heat pump study points out that HPs are a new technology in the UK, while other European countries have more mature markets and more experienced installers – and also better performing domestic heat pumps.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957650912471291">5</xref></sup> This implies that performance is expected to improve as the market matures. However, the poor performance and worrying price range of the mature UK solar thermal market should serve as a warning – time and market growth do not guarantee better performance.</p>
<p>It is easy to see how heat pumps – especially GSHPs, which are buried in the ground unseen – could be treated as a black box like SHW (‘it works for you whatever you do’). It is worth considering whether the heat pump market can be modelled more on the PV market, where cost and (estimated) performance are well correlated. Unlike the poor reporting of predicted energy capacity for SHW, PV expected performance is well documented.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0957650912471291">9</xref></sup> Metered PV installations can show users at a glance how much electricity they are producing and how much money they are saving, which can easily be compared to expected output. As heat pumps are electric, their energy input can be easily metered (although heat output is more complex to measure), and possibly compared to the expected energy required to heat the home in question, e.g. by comparison to the EPC.</p>
<p>The PV / SHW comparison shows how heat and electricity are treated differently. All electrical appliances have power ratings on them, making quantification easy compared to (gas powered) heating, water heating and cooking appliances. This is mainly because ‘[a]ccurate metering of electricity is more common, easier and cheaper than heat metering’ (p. 38).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957650912471291">17</xref></sup> While this is partly a technical difference, there are institutional and cultural differences in expectations of quantification and metering; people are not used to thinking of heat in these terms. In other words, there may well be a connection between the poor reporting of SHW estimated energy capacity and its poor performance. This strengthens the case for metering of renewable heat wherever possible, supporting metering at domestic level in the RHI.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-0957650912471291"><title>Heat pump niche revisited</title>
<p>Another aspect of the systemic view is to consider the current market niches – i.e. who is likely to install renewable heat technologies – and what changes are necessary if the technology is to reach the mainstream. The heat pump niche is analysed as an example.</p>
<p>Current and potential installations of domestic heat pumps are thought to be concentrated in a few small niches<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0957650912471291">6</xref></sup>: rural off-mains houses with adequate space, and some new build; householders tend to be upper middle class, older than average and environmentally aware. This matches other studies’ perspective of who installs microgeneration as wealthier, older and better educated than the average UK household.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0957650912471291">22</xref></sup> These users can be classified as ‘early adopters’ of the new technology. They are more willing to invest money in new technology than the mainstream, and are more environmentally aware.</p>
<p>However, the purchase decision of the majority of consumers tends to be different. They are less likely to invest large sums of money in a technology they know little about, which makes upfront cost a significant issue. They are more likely to be influenced by social and psychological factors, including familiarity with technologies and habitual behaviour. The different use of heat pumps compared to conventional heating systems therefore represents a barrier, highlighting the importance of ease of use and access to information. These factors mean increasing uptake is not trivial, and certainly not guaranteed by the current policy proposals such as the RHI.</p>
<p>Maximising uptake is not the only challenge for this niche. The list of barriers collected from actors in the heat pump industry is an example of the systemic nature of the challenge facing renewable heat technology. The combination of regulatory, institutional, technical, cultural and economic barriers is formidable. We add to this the question of limitations on the numbers of heat pumps can be installed: large scale domestic installation has to be linked to significant retrofitting of existing housing and an enhanced electricity grid which is both larger in capacity <italic>and</italic> lower in carbon.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-0957650912471291"><title>Realistic savings</title>
<p>The low energy savings from solar hot water<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957650912471291">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650912471291">4</xref></sup> are in contrast to the assumed 50% efficiency in a NERA and AEA report, which supplies some of the evidence base for the RHI (p. 87).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0957650912471291">23</xref></sup> The latter is an ‘estimate based on generally available information’.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0957650912471291">23</xref></sup> Similarly for GSHPs, the mere 13% reaching a COP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957650912471291">5</xref></sup> of 3.0 is in contrast to assumed domestic COP values of 3.15–3.85 in the abovementioned report (p. 80).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0957650912471291">23</xref></sup></p>
<p>These more pessimistic numbers on SHW and GSHPs are not definitive results. However, they highlight the fact that actual energy savings from renewable heat installed in homes must be calculated using field studies conducted in real homes with a variety of installations. The two recent EST studies are therefore very welcome. In turn, policy tools must address the various shortcomings in performance – institutional, technological, regulatory and cultural.</p>
<p>The studies reviewed here show that maximising uptake of renewable heat technology is insufficient to maximise savings, and can be far from yielding the ‘potential’ technical savings. Maximising savings requires institutional, behavioural and cultural changes to the socio-technical system.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0957650912471291">24</xref></sup> A rush to maximise uptake of heat pumps without addressing these issues is therefore problematic both in terms of poor energy savings and in terms of long-term damage to the industry’s reputation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec16-0957650912471291"><title>Policy</title>
<p>Given the discussion so far, a holistic policy approach to renewable domestic heating should consider the following: (1) Well-performing installations require increased skills and cultural changes in the industry. (2) There are various barriers to uptake, not just cost. (3) There is a need to supply users with good information, linking renewable heat to household energy use. (4) The realistic size of the market needs to be assessed, considering links to upgrading the existing housing stock and the electricity grid.</p>
<p>The RHI seems to lack a holistic approach. Unlike the Household Energy Management Strategy (HEMS), the RHI does not address barriers and incentives to building energy improvement other than cost, and does not address the upfront cost issue.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0957650912471291">20</xref></sup> It is not well integrated with other policies such as HEMS, and is actually a move towards a separation of heat policy tools from house fabric and efficiency policy tools, stepping back from the LCBP approach. It is worth considering how the RHI can be adjusted or complemented by other policies to ensure not only increased uptake of renewable heat technologies, but also maximising their performance and making sure they are used by well-informed households. For example, metering promotes better-informed users and could increase energy literacy,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0957650912471291">24</xref></sup> although perverse incentives must be avoided with heat pumps, as discussed in section ‘Deeming and metering’.</p>
<p>The repeated delays in starting the domestic RHI will not increase confidence in the industry that the government is committed to these policies, and this could delay improvement in renewable heating performance. The importance of confidence is highlighted in a recent study of different European heat pump markets.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0957650912471291">25</xref></sup> Mature markets are found in countries with good perceptions of the technology among end users and installers alike (e.g. Sweden and Switzerland), and these countries have highly skilled installers and good performing installations. By contrast, in emerging markets such as the UK, installers’ training and installation quality are both variable and consumer and industry confidence in the technology is low.</p>
<p>The abovementioned study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0957650912471291">25</xref></sup> suggests the UK HP market might be in 2012 where Sweden and Switzerland were in the 1980s and 1990s. The experience of those mature markets suggests that a programme of HP market development must build on cooperation among all key stakeholders groups if it is to be successful; this includes government, strong industry associations, manufacturers and utilities. The conclusions from the European study match the idea of a systemic approach described here, which could be broadened for development of renewable heat in general.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec17-0957650912471291" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The main conclusion of this study is that the underperformance of domestic solar hot water and heat pumps is systemic in nature, and needs to be addressed accordingly, rather than by piecemeal policies. More specific conclusions are as follows.
<list id="list2-0957650912471291" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>There is no guarantee that the young HP market will improve as it matures. Steps must be taken to ensure better performance. It is worth considering how it can be modelled on the PV market rather than the SHW market, and what lessons can be learned from the approaches taken in European countries where mature, successful HP markets have evolved.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Building up the heat pump niche market requires a systemic approach, not just user cost incentives. Government interaction with a variety of industry stakeholders, sending clear, consistent signals, is a prerequisite. This interaction must include addressing skills and attitudes in the industry.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The technical and cultural differences between metering of gas/heat and electricity might contribute to the poor performance.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>RHI calculations must rely on measuring systems in use in real homes, not just on lab results and modelling predictions. There is a strong case to prefer metering domestic heat production over deeming where possible.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>A holistic policy approach, linking RHI to other household energy related policies (such as HEMS), would help ensure greater uptake and improve energy savings.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec18-0957650912471291"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0957650912471291"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>DECC. World's first renewable heat incentive launched to reduce emissions. Press Notice 11/023, 10 March 2011. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/news/PN2011_023/PN2011_023.aspx">http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/news/PN2011_023/PN2011_023.aspx</ext-link> (accessed 17 November 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0957650912471291"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>DECC. Renewable heat incentive (RHI) scheme: RHI Update - 26 October 2011. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/meeting_energy/renewable_ener/incentive/incentive.aspx">http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/meeting_energy/renewable_ener/incentive/incentive.aspx</ext-link> (accessed 17 November 2011)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0957650912471291"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Levermore</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Consumer impacts on dividends from solar water heating</article-title>. <source>Energy Efficiency</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0957650912471291"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>EST</collab>. <source>Here comes the sun: a field trial of solar water heating systems</source> , <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Energy Saving Trust</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0957650912471291"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>EST</collab>. <source>Getting warmer: a field trial of heat pumps</source> , <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Energy Saving Trust</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0957650912471291"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Spicer S. <italic>Heat pumps: prospects for the UK industry</italic>. MSc thesis, University of Oxford, 2010</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0957650912471291"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Element Energy</collab>. <source>The growth potential for microgeneration in England, Wales and Scotland</source> , <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Element Energy Inc</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0957650912471291"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brinkworth</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Solar DHW system performance correlation revisited</article-title>. <source>Sol Energy</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>71</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0957650912471291"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Bergman N and Jardine C. <italic>Power from the people: domestic microgeneration and the low carbon building programme</italic>. Environmental Change Institute, University of Oxford, 2009</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0957650912471291"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Hill F. <italic>Consumer impacts on dividends from solar water heating</italic>. MSc Thesis, University of East London, London, 2008</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0957650912471291"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caird</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Herring</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Improving the energy performance of UK households: results from surveys of consumer adoption and use of low- and zero-carbon technologies</article-title>. <source>Energy Efficiency</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0957650912471291"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>BSRIA</collab>. <source>Super successful heat pumps</source> , <publisher-loc>Berkshire, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>BSRIA Limited</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0957650912471291"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>EurObserv’ER. Ground source heat pumps. In: <italic>The state of renewable energies in Europe: 9th EurObserv’ER Report</italic>, 2009, pp. 46–61</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0957650912471291"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>EU. Directive 2009/28/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 April 2009 on the promotion of the use of energy from renewable sources. Official Journal of the European Union L140, 2009</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0957650912471291"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Vaughan A. UK ‘heat pumps' fail as green devices, finds study. The Guardian, 8 September 20101. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2010/sep/08/heat-pumps-green-heating">http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2010/sep/08/heat-pumps-green-heating</ext-link> (accessed 20 December 2010)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0957650912471291"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Hoggett R, Ward J and Mitchell C. <italic>Heat in homes: customer choice on fuel and technologies</italic>. Scotia Gas Networks, University of Exeter, Energy Policy Group, 2011</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0957650912471291"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>DECC. <italic>Renewable heat incentive: consultation on the proposed RHI ﬁnancial support scheme</italic>. Department of Energy and Climate Change, 2010</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0957650912471291"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>DECC. <italic>Renewable heat incentive - frequently asked questions</italic>. Department of Energy and Climate Change, 2010</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0957650912471291"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>DECC. Next steps on renewable heat. Press Notice 12/106, 20 September 2012. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/news/pn12_106/pn12_106.aspx">http://www.decc.gov.uk/en/content/cms/news/pn12_106/pn12_106.aspx</ext-link> (accessed 4 October 2012)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0957650912471291"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Eyre N, Boardman B, Bagdanavicius A, et al. <italic>UKERC response to the DECC consultation on the proposed RHI financial support scheme</italic>. UK Energy Research Centre, 2010</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0957650912471291"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>DJL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>UK microgeneration. Part I: policy and behavioural aspects</article-title>. <source>Energy</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>162</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0957650912471291"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Caird</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abelman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>YIMBY Generation – yes in my back yard! UK householders pioneering microgeneration heat</source> , <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Energy Saving Trust</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0957650912471291"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>NERA and AEA</collab>. <source>The UK supply curve for renewable heat</source> , <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Energy and Climate Change</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0957650912471291"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>What role for microgeneration in a shift to a low carbon domestic energy sector in the UK?</article-title> <source>Energy Efficiency</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0957650912471291"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Delta</collab>. <source>Confidence &amp; quality in heat pump markets</source> , <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Delta Energy &amp; Environment, Ltd</publisher-name>, <year>2012</year>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>