<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MSS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmss</journal-id>
<journal-title>Memory Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1750-6980</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1750-6999</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1750698011405183</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1750698011405183</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Governing memory: Justice, reconciliation and outreach at the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1750698011405183">1</xref></sup></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1750698011405183">London School of Economics, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1750698011405183">Peter Manning, Department of Sociology, London School of Economics, Houghton Street, London, WC2A 2AE, UK Email: <email>p.manning@lse.ac.uk</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-1750698011405183">
<p>Peter Manning is a doctoral student in the Department of Sociology at the London School of Economics and Political Science, UK. His research focuses on the relationship between the Khmer Rouge trials and the politics of memory in Cambodia.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>165</fpage>
<lpage>181</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article explores how devolved outreach work for the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia works to govern the past as it acts to reshape and reframe potentially ambivalent and conflicting memories of political violence. The article specifically examines an example of outreach targeting a former Khmer Rouge community that has been situated as a key party in Cambodia’s attempts to realize ‘justice’ and ‘reconciliation’. The article analyses the sites and crucibles of memory that outreach work for the court utilizes in licensing a particular reading of Cambodia’s experiences of war and genocide. First, the article shows how museum and memorial sites and technologies produce acquiescent, ambivalent and resistant effects among outreach subjects. Second, the article then considers the consolidation and contestation of memory at a public forum event, noting the ways in which outreach attempts to disarm and reconstitute memorial accounts that conflict with the officially sanctioned reading of Cambodia’s past political violence. Whilst acknowledging the unique characteristics of the case, I argue that it is illustrative of the various ways in which Cambodians might question the legitimacy of the Extraordinary Chambers.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Cambodia</kwd>
<kwd>ECCC</kwd>
<kwd>Khmer Rouge</kwd>
<kwd>memory</kwd>
<kwd>reconciliation</kwd>
<kwd>transitional justice</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Memory is central to the work of war crimes trials: reckoning with past wrongs, acknowledging past sufferings, and reconciling previously divided communities. Moreover, memory is crucial for these processes because they rely upon the widespread acceptance of a particular reading of past events. This article considers examples of how the ‘strategies’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1750698011405183">2</xref></sup> of ‘justice’ and ‘reconciliation’ that have emerged in the context of the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia (ECCC) prosecutions organize memory and are mediated with the public. The discussion focuses on devolved ECCC outreach work conducted by a Cambodian non-governmental organization (NGO), the Centre for Social Development (CSD), during the build up to and on the day of the Pailin public forum on ‘Justice and Reconciliation’, held 24 October 2008. The Pailin public forum is of particular interest as a case because the city is principally comprised of former Khmer Rouge (KR) members, and was the home to a number of senior KR leaders now indicted by the ECCC under charges of genocide, war crimes and crimes against humanity. On the one hand, because of this, the Pailin case must be understood as exceptional and particular in revealing conflicts between an institutionally sanctioned reading of the past and localized memorial accounts. On the other, the case remains important, despite this singularity, because it is illustrative of the reception of the prosecutions as a memorial project within a ‘perpetrator’ community that has been positioned by the ECCC as a key party to both justice and reconciliation: as the nationally distributed ECCC radio and poster outreach series have been quick to emphasize, ‘Ordinary Khmer Rouge have nothing to fear’,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1750698011405183">3</xref></sup> and lower level KR are increasingly articulated as ‘victims’ of the Democratic Kampuchea (DK) regime. Importantly, the case is instructive of how otherwise ambivalent or conflicting memory is acted upon to legitimate the ECCC. Moreover, we can take more general lessons from this outreach exercise because the approaches deployed, such as using museums and memorials as tools in public education are common across ECCC outreach initiatives.</p>
<p>The discussion will first examine how the strategies of justice and reconciliation organize memory by privileging some memorial accounts over others. These strategies are anchored and given form by the ECCC prosecutions because they are the principal ‘outcomes’ that are expected to follow from the court’s work, but also hinge on the particular reading of the past that the ECCC has formalized. Importantly, ECCC outreach initiatives are deployed to frame public understandings of justice and reconciliation. These outreach initiatives are often conducted by civil society groups (such as the CSD), and frequently utilize museum and memorial sites to license and evidence the reading of the past that justice and reconciliation are contingent upon. The middle section of the article draws upon data gathered from an outreach visit to the Tuol Sleng Museum of Genocide Crimes and the Choeung Ek ‘Killing Field’ memorial to consider how such sites are deployed as a means of constituting a shared understanding of Cambodia’s Khmer Rouge past. The discussion then analyses how understandings of justice and reconciliation are subsequently consolidated or contested at the Pailin public forum as an outreach exercise that works to ‘govern’ memory. I suggest that the case shows conflicts and discontinuities in memory that are revealing of the varied ways in which the meaning of the ECCC – and Cambodia’s past more broadly – are contested.</p>
<sec id="section1-1750698011405183">
<title>Justice, reconciliation and memory</title>
<p>The ECCC were established in 2006 to prosecute under international and Cambodian law ‘senior leaders’ and ‘those most responsible’ for crimes perpetrated during the DK ‘Khmer Rouge’ regime (1975–79). The court is one of a ‘new wave’ of mixed tribunals, comprised of both international and domestic staff, that seeks to provide a localized sense of accountability within a partly internationalized court body. In July 2010, the ECCC concluded its first case, finding ‘Duch’, the former head of the S21 interrogation facility, guilty of crimes against humanity and sentencing him to 35 years in prison (reduced to 19 years for time already served and infringements of Duch’s pre-trial rights). As of January 2011, the ECCC had indicted and brought charges of genocide, crimes against humanity, war crimes and torture against four other senior leaders of the KR regime.</p>
<p>The composition of transitional justice mechanisms and the accounts of the past they reconstruct tend to emerge in ways that favour existing hierarchies of power. The ECCC is no different in this regard. The restricted mandate for prosecutions – personally to ‘senior leaders’ and ‘those most responsible’, and temporally to the 1975–1979 period – was a crucial factor in obtaining consent from the Cambodian government and mobilizing international support for the trials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1750698011405183">Ciorciari, 2006</xref>: 20). In the first instance, by ascribing blame only to senior leaders, the trials do not jeopardize the domestic politics of reconciliation by stigmatizing large numbers of lower level KR, and such lower level KR are increasingly articulated as ‘victims’ of DK. Moreover, the temporal mandate precludes proper institutional scrutiny of the human rights abuses that occurred during the broader Cambodian conflict spanning, in different guises, the period from 1945 to 1999:<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1750698011405183">4</xref></sup> a period including purges against left-leaning dissidents under the Sihanouk regime in the 1960s, pogroms against ethnic Vietnamese during Lon Nol’s Khmer Republic (1970–75), the hundreds of thousands killed by the illegal carpet bombing of Cambodia by the USA in 1973, the widespread use of forced labour and detention without trial by the People’s Republic of Kampuchea (PRK) (1979–89), and the continuing Khmer Rouge perpetrated massacres of civilians that occurred after their removal from power in 1979.</p>
<p>The selective mandate of the ECCC mechanism shows the court to be an explicitly political means of reckoning with past violence because the process designates some periods as worthy of institutional remembering, but not others. Moreover, the ECCC’s restricted prosecutions show how neatly war crimes trials organize memory: they ask us to remember particular events through (necessarily) narrow factual/forensic lenses, rather than illuminating broader historical contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1750698011405183">Cohen, 2001</xref>: 228–31). These narrow legal discourses ascribe moral meaning in specific ways, reconstructing memory in neat oppositions between guilt and innocence. Tasked with the goals of providing ‘justice’ and ‘reconciliation’, the ECCC is as much about selective forgetting as it is about remembering.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1750698011405183">
<title>Centre for Social Development public forums and ECCC outreach</title>
<p>The ECCC has attracted criticism because of a perceived failure to provide comprehensive public education on its work. In 2009, the nationwide Berkley Human Rights Centre study ‘So We Will never Forget’ found that 85 percent of Cambodians had little or no knowledge of the ECCC, and improving ECCC outreach in order to maximize domestic legitimacy in the public mind was one of the key recommendations of the report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1750698011405183">Pham et al., 2009</xref>). NGOs have increasingly taken the lead in conducting public education on the work of the court, and the ECCC has now come to rely on civil society ‘partner’ groups to supply its outreach. As a result of this licence, and depending on the focus of the particular NGO, outreach work extends beyond the specific remit of public education on the ECCC mechanism, but is generally directed around four identifiable aims (although the balance and combination of these vary).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1750698011405183">5</xref></sup> First, as noted, outreach work has been concerned with disseminating information on the work of the court itself and updating provincial groups on judicial proceedings. Second, outreach focuses on encouraging and enabling participation in ECCC proceedings as witnesses, complainants or as ‘civil parties’ seeking reparation. Third, extending beyond information on the detail of the ECCC mechanism, some groups involved in ECCC outreach have conducted public education and seminars on the history and detail of the DK regime itself. Lastly, some civil society groups look to provide information on mental health issues and trauma, as well as providing psychotherapeutic support services where possible.</p>
<p>Each of these four features of ECCC outreach can be understood as co-constitutive and mutually validating in making the ECCC necessary as an intervention. For example, the Documentation Centre of Cambodia of Cambodia (DC-Cam) has held provincial film screenings that are intended to educate the population about the atrocities of the DK regime, eliciting public testimony from survivors, and, at the same time soliciting legal applications for participation in ECCC proceedings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1750698011405183">Ly, 2008</xref>: 24–7). The Transcultural Psychosocial Organization (TPO) works in partnership with both the ECCC and other civil society groups at outreach events to ‘raise awareness about trauma’, advocating testimonial techniques in order to document and recover memories of DK, whilst positioning the ECCC as one means of empowering victims in overcoming trauma.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1750698011405183">6</xref></sup> These approaches therefore conceptualize DK as a problematic site of memory (historically, legally and medically), specifically in relation to its purported remedy and amelioration through the ECCC process. In this sense, outreach hinges upon techniques for rendering ‘knowable’ a problem that simultaneously implies and validates its solution.</p>
<p>CSD conducted outreach on the ECCC, justice and reconciliation through a combination of public education on the court mechanism, enabling participation in the court process, and holding seminars and forums on the history of DK that ran alongside attempts to raise awareness of mental health issues and trauma stemming from conflict.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1750698011405183">7</xref></sup> Following the establishment of the ECCC in 2006, CSD public forums became an important component in the court’s outreach strategy. The provincially held forums were organized to include a preparatory visit to Phnom Penh to tour the Tuol Sleng Museum of Genocide Crimes, the Choeung Ek Killing Field genocide memorial, and the ECCC court buildings by a section of the forum participants. The visits were therefore structured in such a way as to (1) reveal the factual evidence of KR atrocities (the ‘truth’), (2) encounter a site that is of significant symbolic and iconic memorial importance dedicated to those atrocities (the ‘nation’), and (3) demonstrate the now authoritative moral response to those atrocities (justice and reconciliation through the ECCC).</p>
<p>The forums were intended to ‘facilitate dialogue on issues of justice and reconciliation’ but the creation of the ECCC in 2006 meant that the forums became less able to accommodate debate about whether justice is or is not <italic>necessary or desirable</italic>. The ECCC prosecutions and ensuing strategies of justice and reconciliation are now the dominant frames that lend themselves to the delimitation of what can and cannot be said about the KR period (and the protracted 1945–98 civil conflict altogether). Rather, following the establishment of the ECCC in 2006, the forums became predisposed to disseminate information about how justice will be administered and how reconciliation follows from this. In this vein, the forums were explicitly intended to spread information about the work of the ECCC, broadcasting proceedings on television and radio, and encouraging participants to act as information ‘multipliers’ in local communities.</p>
<p>The CSD public forums drew heavily on therapeutic assumptions about memory in an attempt to reconfigure the stigmatized notion of ‘national reconciliation’ (associated with amnesty and pardon policies that are purportedly in conflict with the ECCC’s prosecutions) to an understanding of reconciliation that includes a therapeutic transformative lens: that reconciliation begins with individual ‘healing’, understanding personal and community trauma and, by virtue of this, the generation of broader catharsis for Cambodia’s social ‘wounds’. This follows from the increasing influence of international psychological and therapeutic assumptions about the nature and role of memory that now govern transitional justice strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1750698011405183">Moon 2009</xref>). These therapeutic assumptions are applied by civil society groups within Cambodia’s attempts to reckon with its history of political violence, and the CSD public forums were specifically organized into two sessions: in the morning emphasis was placed on ‘justice and history’, and in the afternoon the discussion shifted to focus upon ‘reconciliation and healing’.</p>
<p>The CSD forums were endorsed by the ECCC, as evidenced by the attendance of at least two ECCC staff at each event. ECCC attendees have included staff from the co-prosecutor’s office, defence, judges and the Victims Unit, as well as the ECCC’s own media and outreach personnel. Whilst the forums were billed as a space within which the attending ECCC staff are able to listen to the ideas and perspectives of local communities to take back to the stakeholders of the ECCC, in reality the attendance of individuals occupying authoritative positions within the ‘justice’ process means that large periods of each forum often resemble more of a ‘question and answer’ session than a forum for open dialogue.</p>
<p>This is not to suggest that the forums exclude personal testimony and experience from discussion. It was evident that by retelling or stating experiences of the DK regime participants were legitimized as authoritative speakers on the topics of justice and reconciliation. Rather, the divided format of the public forums since 2006 between history and justice on the one hand, and reconciliation and healing on the other, delimits clear fields which both enable and constrain what is spoken about the KR period (and the protracted 1945–98 conflict more broadly) and how and when it is spoken. As I will illustrate in the coming sections, the ECCC reading of the past is contested at points. Whilst the public forums operate in such a way as to marginalize and reframe possible alternative readings and responses to the KR period, the forum is not entirely successful as a space that ‘governs’ memory in accordance with the memorial account sanctioned by the ECCC.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1750698011405183">
<title>Outreach through the Tuol Sleng Museum of Genocide Crimes</title>
<p>Tuol Sleng (along with the ‘killing field’ at Choeung Ek) is today the principal Cambodian museum site concerning the atrocities of the KR. The museum building is a former high school in Phnom Penh, though during DK the site was put to use as an incarceration centre, dubbed ‘S-21’. At that time it was the largest of a network of prisons operated by the KR security apparatus. Chandler’s approximation of the numbers interred at S-21 indicates that around 14,000 people were held at the centre, the majority of whom were killed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1750698011405183">1999</xref>: 36).</p>
<p>The site was discovered by the Vietnamese after the capture of Phnom Penh in January 1979 and the founding of the People’s Republic of Kampuchea (PRK). The PRK government quickly recognized the potential of the site in purchasing popular support and legitimacy on a domestic footing. The site was thus projected within Cambodia as proof of the atrocities of the KR and, in the context of an ongoing civil war, to legitimate the new PRK state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1750698011405183">Hughes 2003</xref>: 176–8). As Ledgerwood notes, the curation of Tuol Sleng revolved around a state master-narrative that told of a ‘glorious revolution’ in 1975 that was stolen and hijacked by a small number of ‘murderous criminals’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1750698011405183">1997</xref>: 91). This highly personalized attribution of guilt for the DK period also materialized in particular significance at the 1979 ‘People’s Revolutionary Tribunal’. The court was dismissed as a ‘showtrial’ by the West, but this particular construction of culpability around the ‘Ieng Sary–Pol Pot’ clique was an important step in the deployment of the reconciliatory politics throughout the 1980s and 1990s in Cambodia. With the blame for the DK period focused upon two individuals, the PRT remained highly ambivalent about lower level KR responsibility, playing to absolve the guilt of lower level KR under a de facto amnesty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1750698011405183">Gottesman, 2003</xref>: 60–2), and leaving enough room to entice defections of other senior KR leaders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1750698011405183">Fawthrop and Jarvis, 2004</xref>: 42). As Fawthrop and Jarvis have noted, the fact that the court provided a formal space for Cambodians to express their experiences of DK has largely been neglected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1750698011405183">2004</xref>: 49).</p>
<p>Today Tuol Sleng operates principally as a tourist attraction, with non-Cambodians comprising the majority of visitors to the site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1750698011405183">Hughes, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1750698011405183">Williams, 2004</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1750698011405183">8</xref></sup> However, the site and its documentation are considered to constitute important evidence in the legal prosecutions at the ECCC, and the recent trial of Duch even involved a ‘re-enactment’ of his role at the site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1750698011405183">BBC News, 2008</xref>). Moreover, as I will discuss below, civil society organizations such as CSD have utilized the site (and Choeung Ek) as a form of public proof about the regime. Much as in 1979, Tuol Sleng today plays a double role in promoting and licensing a ‘factual-forensic’ and ‘public/historical’ ‘<italic>truth</italic>’ about the DK period.</p>
<p>On 7 October 2008, a group of around 60 residents of the Pailin region<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1750698011405183">9</xref></sup> of Western Cambodia were brought to Phnom Penh to tour Tuol Sleng, Choeung Ek and the ECCC. The role of the CSD visit to Phnom Penh was principally pedagogic, intended to enhance participation at the ensuing public forum. As one CSD staff member remarked:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>it is about building their schema, their existing knowledge. … They may have experienced those four years [of DK] they have never been to these places. In their imagination Tuol Sleng is like this, or like this – they have no information. We want people to get active and involved on public forum day. We want to activate their memory … when they come to Tuol Sleng they start to remember whatever happened.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1750698011405183">10</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In the absence of comprehensive textual supporting information, it is the ‘untouched’ appearance of the artefacts on display that make Tuol Sleng persuasive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1750698011405183">Hughes, 2003</xref>: 176–8; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1750698011405183">Williams, 2004</xref>: 242). The museum includes photographs of corpses found in cells when the site was first discovered; torture implements and shackles remain in place as they were left in 1979; blood stains remain unwashed on some of the walls; and in building B displays include the iconic ‘mugshots’ taken upon entry of those interred at the centre. The little textual information that is available at Tuol Sleng communicates culpability for the atrocities committed at the site around the Pol-Pot–Ieng Sary clique.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1750698011405183">11</xref></sup> A board at the entrance to the museum complex notes the transformation of the site from high school to prison on the orders of the Pol Pot–Ieng Sary clique. Whilst guilt is articulated as a property of senior KR leaders that were intent on genocide and there is silence about the role of lower level KR (a construction of culpability that corresponds to the prosecutions at the ECCC today), suffering at Tuol Sleng is communicated as nationally generalized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1750698011405183">Ledgerwood, 1997</xref>), the entrance board noting that S-21 was the largest of a nationwide prison system.</p>
<p>Ledgerwood has suggested that ‘Cambodians generally accept the story of the museum as true to their experiences’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1750698011405183">1997</xref>: 82). The reactions and responses of the public forum attendees do not refute or corroborate Ledgerwood’s claim, but rather provide insight into the importance of the ‘knowledge’ that visitors bring to bear on a site, and how meaning emerges through a relationship between site, audience and (particularly) the context of visitation. One resident of Pailin, when viewing shackles for example, recalled in detail the types of punishment he had witnessed during DK. Upon entering a cell in ‘Block A’ of Tuol Sleng, one former KR soldier asked ‘who gave these orders?’ On the one hand this shows that the visitors were highly attuned to issues of culpability represented at the site, arguably, in part, as a result of the fact that the tour was organized directly as a means of understanding the current ECCC prosecutions. On the other hand, what was occurring during the visit was a struggle by the visitors to situate their own memories of KR rule within the ‘truth’ of DK propagated at Tuol Sleng.</p>
<p>The pedagogical aims of the visit reflect assumptions made by CSD staff that many attendees did not know or have information about Tuol Sleng prior to their visit. Moreover, their struggle (and at points disbelief) in rationalizing what was witnessed is evidence that members of communities such as Pailin largely experienced KR rule in a setting of agrarian cooperativism receiving more favourable treatment, rather than in incarceration and torture facilities in an urban setting. Importantly, though, it also reveals the dissonance that existed between the localized memories of the group and a projection of blame – as substantiated and exemplified by Tuol Sleng – <italic>prior</italic> to the CSD visit.</p>
<p>The visit to Tuol Sleng provoked very mixed responses among the visitors. A former student of the Tuol Sleng school prior to 1975, who was invited onto the tour exceptionally, had never returned to the site since the DK era, despite awareness of its existence. For him, returning to the site had simply been too painful a proposition. By the time the tour had reached the last block of the museum he began to publicly denounce the trial (despite his self-identification as a ‘victim that lost many relatives; when I am here, I am shaking with anger’). The rest of the Pailin attendees remained impassive as the former student proclaimed that the ECCC is a theatre, that he felt hopeless about ‘justice’, and that he would not file a complaint with the court.</p>
<p>The former student’s reaction to Tuol Sleng is instructive about the diversity of lenses through which Cambodians can question the legitimacy or are critical of the ECCC. His dismissal of the ECCC as an effective enterprise arose in the first instance from his feeling that the evidence presented at Tuol Sleng was, in itself, so <italic>overwhelming</italic> he could not understand the delay in prosecutions. In his eyes, the ECCC proceedings were suffering setbacks because of political influences: ‘I bet my life that this court will not have a fair trial. If it was a pure international tribunal, justice would be satisfied.’ This remark could be understood in part as an anxiety about the influence of the government on proceedings. This view is not just pervasive among international and domestic Cambodian civil society groups, but also among those ordinary Cambodians that question the legitimacy of the current Cambodian government. In this sense, he accepted and approved of Tuol Sleng as a site of historical and factual evidence but simultaneously dislocated the appropriateness of the ECCC institution as the authoritative moral response to those truths.</p>
<p>In a change of tack, the former student continued to note that ‘the revolution began in 1954, but the jurisdiction is only four years [1975–79]. Where there is smoke there is fire. The ECCC is not interested in the root causes.’ The interest in publicly disinterring aspects of the broader conflict outside of the 1975–79 period is indicative of a desire in some sections of Cambodian society to address a broader historical and contextual truth about the KR period. This appears to reflect a frustration with the temporally delimited factual and forensic truth licensed by the ECCC jurisdiction. The responses of many of the former KR during the visit to the Choeung Ek ‘Killing Field’, the ECCC, and at the public forum suggests that they shared this concern.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1750698011405183">
<title>Outreach through the Choeung Ek ‘Killing Field’ memorial</title>
<p>Choeung Ek ‘killing field’, roughly 15 km South of Phnom Penh, was the site of execution for many of those held at S-21. The site is comprised of 129 mass graves, around 40 of which have not been disinterred. Alongside Tuol Sleng, Choeung Ek became pivotal in the PRK’s construction of a coherent reading of the DK period. As Rachel Hughes has noted, following discovery, Choeung Ek was cast as ‘a centre for typical evidences’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1750698011405183">2006a</xref>: 258–9), providing further ‘proof’ about the ‘genocidal’ intentions of Pol Pot, thus attributing culpability for DK to senior KR leaders. Today clothing and shards of human bone can often be found whilst walking between these pits, contributing to the ‘shocking’ and ‘raw’ impression the site offers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1750698011405183">Bickford, 2009</xref>: 8). The central focus of the site is a memorial Buddhist <italic>stupa</italic> constructed in 1988 to display the remains of some 9000 of those killed there.</p>
<p>The memorial stupa at Choeung Ek materializes a tension between a politics of nation building and the imperative to create more subjective forums that could memorialize the loss of life during DK in accordance with Buddhist practice. As Hughes suggests, the public display of human remains within a memorial <italic>stupa</italic> represented an attempt to nationally reclaim, memorialize, or re-‘know’ victims that cannot be understood as having been ‘sacrificed’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1750698011405183">2006a</xref>: 259). Hughes’s analysis of Choeung EK reflects the concern that some Cambodians struggle to comprehend DK as Khmer-on-Khmer violence. Traditionally memorial <italic>stupa</italic> forms act as sacred spaces containing the cremated remains of one person, usually of venerable status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1750698011405183">Hughes, 2006b</xref>: 105). In contrast, the Choeung Ek memorial visibly interred the remains of many victims of the KR, the large numbers of unidentifiable skulls reinforcing the general and anonymous image of suffering under the KR. The tension between the Choeung Ek’s role as a religious and political site is further evidenced by the fact that, in the Buddhist tradition, deaths from inauspicious circumstance (such as murder) require urgent cremation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1750698011405183">Hughes, 2006b</xref>: 105–6). The continued display of mass-human remains therefore not only contravenes Buddhist funerary practice, but moreover makes some Cambodians uneasy and fearful about visiting the site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1750698011405183">Hughes, 2006b</xref>: 106). Compounding the tension in enmeshing the sacred and the profane at the Choeung Ek installation is the problematic issue of ‘ownership’. Today, the overwhelming majority of visitors to the site are non-Cambodian, and the site’s ticket concession has been awarded to a Japanese-Korean firm. The site therefore exists in a complicated state with the Cambodian moral imagination.</p>
<p>Following the visit to Tuol Sleng, the Pailin residents were taken on a tour of the Choeung Ek ‘killing field’. Rachel Hughes’s analysis of Choeung Ek as a site depicting ‘unsacrificed’ victims was corroborated when starting the tour. Whilst walking around the graves, one participant questioned how Khmers could commit such violence against Khmers. He compared the KR period of rule to Nazi Germany, whereby he rationalized the violence perpetrated there in the name of territory and sovereignty. In Cambodia, he could not understand how a government could ‘undercut’ its own people, in what he considered ‘non-sensical’ violence.</p>
<p>The difficulty the participants had in rationalizing the display of victims of Cambodian mass violence manifested itself through the lens of an offence to the Khmer ‘nation’. Yet this did not necessarily translate into anti-KR responses to the Choeung Ek displays. In fact, whilst the Choeung Ek site references a narrative of generalized suffering of the Cambodian nation at the hands of the KR, counter-claims resisting this narrative emerged on the tour. For example, one participant, claimed that ‘If only the KR had fed the people better and asked the people to join the army, we could have fought the Vietnamese invaders and won the battle’, contradicting the claims made at Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek about the nature of the Vietnamese intervention <italic>as salvation</italic> for the Cambodian people. This response eschews the narrative of the guilt of the ‘Pol Pot–Ieng Sary clique’ referenced at Choeung EK, but also disrupts a conceptualization of the memorial as means of deterring future violence (an expectation of many international visitors to the site; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1750698011405183">Bickford, 2009</xref>: 12).</p>
<p>As one former KR soldier remarked ‘Something happened here that I cannot understand … This place, it is not real – it’s politics. This violence was political.’ The former soldier was not necessarily denying the ‘truth’ of the site (that Cambodians died there) but clearly aligning his own experiences of DK to the collective violence represented was problematic, either through a lens of ‘perpetration’ or ‘victim hood’. This type of reaction is again dislocated from the ECCC as an authoritative moral response to the DK period because the reading of violence as ‘political’ could be seen as somewhat ambivalent toward culpability for the 1975–79 period when the claims made at Choeung Ek and the context of visitation explicitly link the ‘proof’ and nature of mass violence to the guilt and ‘cruel’ intentions of senior KR leaders.</p>
<p>The former soldier expressed further scepticism concerning the function of the Choeung Ek site. In his eyes, the site was ‘well established’, ‘good for attracting tourists and helping to develop the country, but it is very superficial’. This reflected his perception that Choeung Ek did not represent ‘the essence of the problem. The memorial is planned, made for a vision.’ These comments appear to show important links between the role and function of a site, knowledge and context of visitation, and the ways in which these feed into the ‘meanings’ read at that site.</p>
<p>The contested meaning and function of the Choeung Ek site is noteworthy because the Choeung Ek centre invites particular practices of observance, both ‘sacred’ and ‘profane’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1750698011405183">Hughes, 2006a</xref>). The display of mass graves and visible shards of bone and clothing littering the pathways between unfenced walkways provides an intimate and immediate encounter with a legacy of mass killing. The Pailin residents were very subdued whilst traversing between the pits, as the tour guide explained the role and scope of each section of the extermination centre. The circuit then looped back to the central memorial where human remains are displayed within a <italic>stupa</italic>, therefore as sacred. Yet these remains are organized in glass cases by age and gender, reflecting an imperative to classify and categorize the remains as evidence. Overlapping – but not necessarily complementary – discourses of nation, religion, and forensic truth or ‘proof’ played into the construction of the site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1750698011405183">Hughes, 2006b</xref>: Chapter 4). Arguably these translated in turn into particular responses from the Pailin residents; the younger attendees ascended the <italic>stupa</italic> before a sign reading ‘Please pay your respects to the millions of victims of the Pol Pot regime’, then knelt in prayer, before burning incense. The older attendees were not inclined to participate in religious observance at the site, but then would peer inquisitively at the human skulls in the display.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1750698011405183">
<title>Outreach at the ECCC building</title>
<p>Following the tours of Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek, the Pailin residents were taken by bus to visit the ECCC court building and attend a seminar with Reach Sambath, at the time an ECCC press officer. As noted above, the tours to Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek in part evidenced some dislocation between acceptance of the proof of KR atrocities and the perceived necessity and efficacy of the ECCC as the appropriate moral response to those atrocities. The seminar at the ECCC was framed in such a way as to consolidate this ‘proof’ and obviate the necessity of the ECCC as the <italic>only</italic> moral response to those atrocities. In this sense, outreach exercises at the court can be understood as a way of acting upon and reframing otherwise ambivalent or conflicting memory.</p>
<p>The seminar opened with a discussion of the displays at Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek, with Reach Sambath enquiring, ‘Those objects [at Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek] are real, everything is real. How closely did you watch the skulls?’ In response, one Pailin resident remarked ‘Close, very close, to ensure that they were real’. Such an exchange, that hinges on the accepted authenticity of the objects displayed, is illustrative of an anxiety held by practitioners within Cambodia’s transitional justice process that there are provincial groups within Cambodia that are not aware of Tuol Sleng or Choeung Ek, and do not trust the sites (for political or religious reasons). This is in conflict with the ECCC because Tuol Sleng and Cheonug Ek have been cast as crucial evidential and symbolic sites for understanding the KR period and the ECCC response to it. Moreover, it shows again that Cambodians do not necessarily remember the DK era through the lens of Tuol Sleng or Choeung Ek as representations of their experiences, despite past and present efforts to make the sites stand for those experiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1750698011405183">Hughes, 2006a</xref>: 154).</p>
<p>The problem of situating personal experience in relation to representations that generalize claims about collective memory was further broached in the seminar, with Reach Sambath asking ‘did you believe the killing was true?’ A woman from Pailin responded that relatives had told her about atrocities, but she had not witnessed anything. In reply, Sambath explained that ‘no one could see the killing, the killing was kept secret. And people were afraid of the killing sites so they would not go near them.’ In this sense, Tuol Sleng is used as an evidential premise of ‘secretive’ and ‘unfamiliar’ violence that can be extrapolated to generalize about experiences nationally. This locates the participant’s uncertainty about her local experience within a national explanatory framework.</p>
<p>By attempting to reinforce and establish the truth and authenticity of Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek, the seminar was able to refocus around the imperatives used to validate the ECCC. In the first instance, the proof of death plays to the need for justice, specifically thought through the lens of evidence and legal prosecution. As I have noted above, Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek lend themselves to this purpose because they portray culpability for DK crimes to senior leaders only whilst remaining ambivalent about lower level KR. This corresponds neatly to the current restricted ECCC prosecutions, and thus also fits with the politics of national reconciliation because there is a de facto blanket amnesty for lower level KR. Second, the truth of the sites plays to an educational imperative in that the younger Cambodian generation may learn about and take ownership of their history, purportedly helping to prevent future crimes. This second imperative implicitly cites the internationalized human rights call of ‘never again’, positioning younger Cambodian generations as obliged to take ownership of that history.</p>
<p>The truth presented at Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek was deployed in the seminar as justification for the ECCC, yet acceptance of the court’s necessity was not unanimous among attendees, even among those that had witnessed killings. One participant recalled that ‘I eye-witnessed some killing. But when I walked around Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek I felt that I didn’t want to see prosecutions. I wanted to see the five leaders live longer.’ Another former KR soldier explained that he had lost relatives, including brothers and uncles. ‘The killing happened continuously, from one to one to one. But why do we need this trial? I want to know why the regime killed people.’ Apprehension toward the ECCC as a response to atrocity can be understood as evidence for the fact that there may be memories and perspectives within Cambodia that remain in conflict with the ECCC project. Moreover, questions of ‘why the regime killed’ that are concerned with more contextual histories of violence raise concerns about the appropriateness of a legal mechanism that is governed by ascertaining the weight of proof to conclude only the guilt or innocence of a handful of individuals.</p>
<p>The Pailin attendees further pressed questions regarding atrocities committed before and after DK, challenging the delimited ECCC jurisdiction. Whilst Reach Sambath stressed that the court’s jurisdiction could only attend to the 1975–79 period, for some of the Pailin attendees ‘real’ history for future generations could not be documented without formal attention to the periods of violence outside of the ECCC mandate, which include bombing by the USA in the 1970s and violence perpetrated by the Vietnamese during the civil war after 1979. In the eyes of a number of the Pailin participants, acknowledgement and reckoning with these issues were also important to their understanding of reconciliation.</p>
<p>The seminar had noticeable effects in diffusing these points of conflict when explicitly addressing the role former lower level KR may play within the ECCC process. In this sense, the seminar worked to act upon and couch potentially conflicting memory in ‘reconcilable’ frames. ECCC outreach materials have been quick to emphasize that only senior leaders will be prosecuted and accordingly the seminar stressed that the restricted prosecution was a necessary element within the process of national reconciliation. CSD staff were also quick to point out that former KR may have lost relatives or suffered themselves and may therefore be ‘victims’ that could file complaints or join as civil parties. The tentative offer of enfranchisement within the ECCC process, in tandem with reassurance of the fact that lower level KR would not be prosecuted, appeared to assuage some of the Pailin attendees’ reservations about the trials. In this sense, it was clear that the stakes of reconciliation as defined by the ECCC – that 1975–79 was the ‘rupture’ around which to reconcile, and that only senior leaders are to blame – had gone some distance in positioning the court as a <italic>necessary and acceptable</italic> endeavour.</p>
<p>At one point a Pailin resident quizzed ‘Why do those five detainees receive such good treatment?’ to which Reach Sambath jokingly responded: ‘Are you jealous? We have some spare rooms.’ The seminar was characterized by this type of convivial exchange, and this certainly contributed to a far more positive mood among the Pailin residents than upon leaving Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek. This shows again how attention must be paid to both <italic>what</italic> is being remembered (meaning/message) and the specific contexts and modalities of memory (Tuol Sleng or Choeung Ek tours, ECCC seminars): they are at the same time relational, but also not necessarily mutually validating. On the one hand, the deployment of Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek as evidential agents that ‘licence’ the premise of the ECCC account (i.e. killing occurred, the senior leaders are to blame) still provoked specific types of resistance, potentially as a result of distrust of both their particular political histories and the technologies through which they articulate meaning (human remains, arguably ‘inauthentic’ Buddhist <italic>stupa</italic>, etc.). The attendees that were sceptical about Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek were not necessarily all against the ECCC; the attendees that were accepting of the ‘proof’ of Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek were not necessarily in agreement that the ECCC is the appropriate moral response to that ‘proof’. On the other hand, it should be stressed that the ECCC became less problematic for the Pailin residents as the day continued and they were exposed to more information about the court mechanism. This appears to show that individuals may resist a particular ‘story’, or struggle to align their experiences within a collective account of violence, but then may still accede to authoritative mnemonic responses. The ECCC mobilizes and is contingent upon a particular (mono-logical) account of the DK era that many participants could not completely accept as ‘valid’. Yet still the power of this account was increasingly felt during the seminar as attempts were made to render the ECCC intelligible. The seminar thus proved to be a powerful crucible within which the ‘moral meaning’ of memory was re-forged, and undoubtedly the ordering of the day’s schedule played to this, demonstrating sites of atrocity – or moral ‘wrong’ – to the site of moral resolution of those ‘wrongs’.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1750698011405183">
<title>The Pailin public forum</title>
<p>Following the tours to Phnom Penh, the Pailin public forum was held on 24 October 2008, with over 150 local residents in attendance to discuss issues of ‘justice and reconciliation’. ECCC staff, including co-prosecutors, co-investigating judges, domestic and international judges, and outreach personnel were all present to participate in the discussion. International court monitoring staff and representatives from donors groups were also present, including the British Ambassador, Stephen Mace. The local authorities were also represented with the attendance of Deputy Governor of Pailin, Mey Mak, a former KR official.</p>
<p>The morning session of the forum was intended to focus upon issues of justice and history. Participants were allowed up to three minutes to ask questions of the ECCC staff, which pre-disposed the format of the session to focus more on questions surrounding the ECCC mechanism itself, rather than history (the ECCC staff were generally reluctant to speak about anything other than the ECCC mechanism). Moreover, whilst each participant was able to introduce aspects of their own experiences of DK within their allotted three minutes, this did not provide enough time for them to elaborate in detail or greater length about either those experiences or their own perspectives about the ECCC. Whilst unstated, the CSD forum implicitly positioned questions on the history of DK to have been addressed during the visit to Phnom Penh at the museum and memorial sites. Moreover, the format of the dialogue became increasingly one of ‘question and answer’ rather than an exchange of ideas. In this sense, the ECCC staff were not (and could not be) attentive to questions outside of the framing of the ECCC jurisdiction. By focusing on questions about the detail of the ECCC apparatus, the explanations of the mechanism became quite indistinguishable from justifications for it: a process of rationalizing and validating the ECCC mechanism in a circular fashion emerged (it exists because it is important and it is important in its existence). This was in part reinforced by the highly authoritative positions the attending ECCC staff occupied within the court: judges, prosecutors, witness protection staff, etc. They therefore also occupied highly authoritative positions from which to speak about justice, necessarily implying the benefits of the ECCC as a means to that outcome.</p>
<p>Much as at the ECCC seminar, the Pailin attendees had not been exposed to any great level of information about the ECCC prior to the forum, and they were engaged by the details and process of court. This supports the findings of the Berkeley study suggesting that provincial Cambodian populations do not have information about the court process. As witnessed at the previous tour of Tuol Sleng, Choeung Ek, and to the court, it could be said that the more a ‘mode’ of remembering is rendered familiar, the more persuasive <italic>what</italic> it is remembering can become. The unfamiliarity of Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek maintained some degree of mistrust. In contrast, the convivial dialogue at the court seminar ending the tour was more persuasive. Again, though, this does not mean that knowledge of the ECCC process translated neatly into total acquiescence of the court’s purpose.</p>
<p>The strength of the ‘international’ imperatives to ‘do’ justice were very pronounced in rationalizing and validating the work of the ECCC at the public forum, with frequent references to other cases of intervention following atrocity. However, a specifically ‘national’ imperative to reconcile also dominated the discussion, particularly evident in the comments by the ECCC staff themselves. The Pailin residents were repeatedly encouraged to go back to their communes, tell their friends and spread the word that lower level KR have nothing to fear. The emphasis on assuaging the anxieties of lower level KR about the absence of lower level prosecutions must be understood as a reconciliatory endeavour as it is mobilized through a de facto blanket amnesty at the same time as positioning lower level Khmer Rouge (Pailin residents) as key parties to the reconciliation process. This is a close reproduction of the reconciliatory politics deployed during the civil war of the 1980s and 1990s, reflecting the articulation of blame of Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek to senior leaders only: that those who would live in peace are reconciled, and therefore that ‘peace’ equates to ‘reconciliation’.</p>
<p>Despite the ECCC’s restricted prosecutions, which tightly define the stakes of justice around the guilt of senior leaders whilst constructing moral lacunae for lower level KR (thus inviting reconciliatory politics), there are memories and beliefs manifest in communities such as Pailin that can be understood to remain in conflict with the ECCC project. As one former cadre remarked during the morning session on his own self-understanding as ‘Khmer Rouge’:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>When they hear the name KR they are scared. I am proud of what I went through but I am also sorry for the destruction in the period. These people [KR] were true nationalists, they protected the territory. We know there was destruction but we are not ashamed, we did not do any bad things. We tried to struggle, we made sacrifices for Cambodia</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The patriotic lens through which this former cadre understood his own experiences of the Cambodian conflict is at odds with the ECCC reading of the past, because on the one hand it acknowledges the suffering of the conflict but denies KR responsibility for ‘any bad things’. Moreover, the valorisation of the KR as ‘true nationalists’, or martyrs would not seem congruous to the ECCC explanation of the DK period, or that articulated at Tuol Sleng or Choeung Ek, despite the court’s ambivalence about the moral status of lower level KR. Another resident of Pailin remarked further that ‘…the KR leaders did good things. Without the leaders there would have been no agreement in Paris [1991 Peace Accords]. The KR leaders did not intend to kill people, this is our belief.’ Clearly this type of remark is a notable incongruity to the central ECCC reading of DK.</p>
<p>The afternoon session on ‘healing and reconciliation’ attempted to adopt a marked re- conceptualization of what reconciliation entails. As the host declared:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>These people are former KR. They are victims and they lost family. We need reconciliation. We don’t want to point the finger at anybody. We just want to look back to the past, and we need joint participation … You can contribute to justice, peace, and emotional healing.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The refocus upon individual trauma healing as a criterion of reconciliation – as opposed to peace equals reconciliation – shows the encroachment of psychological therapeutic assumptions into Cambodia’s transitional justice strategy. The casting of lower level KR as ‘victims’ – that must also know their own trauma in order to facilitate individual and community healing – borrows from an increasingly authoritative set of international therapeutic norms that are applied to transitional justice problems. Moreover, it plays out as a powerful reconciliation strategy because the construction of former soldiers and communities party to a conflict as ‘victims’ that require healing is exculpatory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1750698011405183">Moon 2009</xref>). Approaches that use a more ‘therapeutic’ understanding of reconciliation, borrowing from medicalized trauma concepts, could still comfortably operate in tandem with the construction of culpability mobilized by the ECCC (senior leaders are guilty) and alongside the existing politics of ‘national’ reconciliation mobilized by the Cambodian state (de facto blanket amnesties for lower level KR).</p>
<p>The afternoon session allowed greater licence for the attendees to speak in length about the issues they felt important for reconciliation and ‘healing’. What became evident was a notion among the participants that ‘truth’ was at stake. This did not consistently manifest itself around contestation over what had taken place during the DK period, but was more centrally concerned with ‘why violence had occurred?’ As one female resident of Pailin asked:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>During the KR I lost all my family members, I saw this with my own eyes. I saw people taken on trucks and then shot on the hillside. During the Pol Pot regime, why did they kill people, what was the purpose of the massacre, who backed the massacre, which countries?</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The attendee situates her memory of violent experiences within a contextual question about the origins of generalized violence. Moreover, the struggle to rationalize Khmer-on-Khmer violence is again manifest, evidenced in the fact that she seeks to locate culpability outside of Cambodia. This type of concern seems to point again to a tension between a legal mechanism, such as the ECCC, that relies on types of knowledge/memory that are factual/forensic, with a desire among sections of the Cambodian public to explore contextual questions about the nature of Cambodia’s history of political violence.</p>
<p>The demand for the recognition of unacknowledged memory also emerged among former KR cadre too:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>They assume KR is the most responsible offender. People need to understand the KR in order to not be scared of them. We have to understand what Pol Pot did. Of course they are responsible for the massacre and they must be held responsible. But why did they have so many followers? I was a willing follower. They need to understand us.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>For a number of the former soldiers, the civil war and violence perpetrated before and after the 1975–79 period was central to this ‘truth’, reflecting their concern that ‘legitimate’ memorial narratives in the national biography were being subordinated within a picture that did not address the ‘whole story’. Reconciliation and justice were considered problematic without acknowledgement of these broader periods of conflict. One exchange between the forum leader and a former-KR encapsulated this well:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>KR: I went through the regime, and each regime up to now. The killings happened in every regime. During the Pol Pot regime there was a massacre, and during the PRK, so the ECCC doesn’t bring real reconciliation, with those who commit crimes outside the regime. After 1979 a lot of people were killed too. People were killed by hunger, foreigners, and KR. If the trial cannot bring justice for people, we should give pardons, join hands and work for the people. Justice does not exist at the court – there is still injustice. There are problems today with injustice, the equality of poor and rich. We should concentrate on this not the trial.</p>
<p>Forum Leader: The size of the crimes was big and cruel. This court will not convict ideology. It will convict criminals. Now we have a lot of evidence to prove the massacres did happen.</p>
<p>KR: I am not worried that I will be convicted. The criminals should get real punishment. They are nationalists, but are responsible for the loss of life during that period. But you left after the regime, you didn’t suffer. Or see the suffering after that period, all my family were imprisoned. What we need is real reconciliation. The trial of senior leaders will not cause insecurity amongst the people. But there are many victims, and those who committed the crimes who are now in power.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This exchange is of particular interest because of how the former KR has disrupted the forum’s understanding of reconciliation as an ensuing and complimentary outcome of the ECCC. It is noteworthy that this person does not deny the factual basis of the ECCC claims about the 1975–79 violence (an outcome of senior leaders’ guilt). Rather, his re-conceptualization of victimhood as a substantive category for all of those involved in political violence within and outside 1975–79 contests the legitimacy of the ECCC as a reconciliatory strategy because it presents alternative sets of victims and perpetrators. The court is validated on a universal claim that demands accountability and redress for all perpetrators and victims of political violence. The ECCC is then challenged when communities such as Pailin present claims about the occurrence of serious political violence that the ECCC will not attend to.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1750698011405183">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Justice at the ECCC entails the prosecution of a ‘neat’ set of perpetrators in the name of a largely vague understanding of all Cambodians as ‘victims’ of the 1975–79 rupture (this is notwithstanding those Cambodians formally recognized by the court as civil parties, who remain only a small section out of the universe of possible DK victims). The ECCC prosecutions are reflective of the way blame for DK is represented at Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek and, as such, they are deployed to help persuade groups that participate in the ECCC outreach about the truth of the DK period and the need of the ECCC as a response to it. As this article has demonstrated, the success of these sites in disseminating a reading of the past in the name of the ECCC is mixed. Some of the forum attendees attempted to contest the meaning of the sites and some questioned whether they accepted the ECCC as a valid or necessary response to the suffering represented. Others among the visitors found Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek to correspond to their own experiences of DK and many considered the ECCC otherwise important. This shows that accepting the ECCC’s preferred past did not neatly translate into accepting the ECCC and vice versa. Moreover, The Pailin participants’ visit to Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek demonstrates that the meanings or moral imperatives arising from memory are rarely singular, unified, or completely shared, even within a localized community. Memory must be understood as constantly contested and renegotiated.</p>
<p>The ECCC prosecutions formalize an account of the DK period in which blame is placed at the hands of a few senior KR leaders. Such restricted prosecutions play to the politics of national reconciliation by (re)constructing a de facto blanket amnesty for lower level KR. A more transformative notion of reconciliation is invoked in the work of civil society groups that situate the ECCC within internationalized therapeutic imperatives for the ‘healing’ of a traumatized society, and casting lower level KR as victims of the DK period. Both of these approaches exculpate lower level KR, reframing memory of the DK period in ‘reconcilable’ terms. The ECCC seminar and public forum worked to soften potential conflicts by situating memory of DK in these terms. This was undoubtedly consolidated by the presence of authoritative voices and the arbiters of justice and reconciliation at the public forum. This further shows also that the personal and embodied – rather than ‘still’ – means of remembering violence were more strongly felt in these instances of mediating justice and reconciliation.</p>
<p>This article has explored how memory is governed through outreach work for the ECCC. As noted, outreach provides particular lenses for ‘knowing’ the DK period that at the same time imply the necessity of the ECCC as a response to it. Importantly, though, the Pailin forum shows mixed responses to these initiatives, evidencing memorial accounts and perspectives that remained in conflict with the ECCC sanctioned reading of Cambodia’s troubled past. Whilst acknowledging the numerous unique characteristic of the Pailin public forum, the case illuminates some of the more general means through which Cambodians question the ECCC: some look to contest the ECCC version of the past in its literal premises, whilst others demand answers to questions concerning the nature and origins of violence that the ECCC as a legal mechanism is poorly disposed to answer. Moreover, the concern among some participants regarding the truth of the DK period extends to the existence of alternative accounts of political violence that are silenced by the ECCC proceedings, particularly those memories of suffering that occurred before and after the ECCC’s temporal jurisdiction. These are important because they can make counter-claims about victimhood that challenge the ECCC privileging of the 1975–79 period. They are also disruptive because they necessarily involve counter-claims about perpetration too, bearing in mind that the creation of the court by the UN, Cambodian government and international community was contingent on a 1975–79 jurisdiction that could prosecute only senior leaders of the KR.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>I would like to thank the Department of Sociology at the London School of Economics for a generous award that funded this period of fieldwork.</p>
<p>I would also like to thank those staff working for the Centre for Social Development at the time of the fieldwork for their assistance over this period. The analyses offered here do not necessarily reflect their views. I am also very grateful for the comments and suggestions offered by the three anonymous reviewers of this article. I would also like to thank the Centre for Khmer Studies in Siem Reap for providing access to library resources and workspace, where the first drafts of this article were written.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1750698011405183">
<label>1.</label>
<p>This article is based upon data gathered whilst conducting doctoral research in Cambodia between September 2008 to May 2009.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1750698011405183">
<label>2.</label>
<p>I describe justice and reconciliation as ‘strategies’ because the terms imply both processes and outcomes that the ECCC purportedly administers. As Moon has explained in reference to South Africa’s Truth and Reconciliation Commission, such strategies of ‘political transition’ can work as a ‘template-script’ that maps and governs how the past is remembered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1750698011405183">2008</xref>: 54–5). Through the ECCC, these strategies work to organize what can and cannot be said (or ‘remembered’) about Cambodia’s past political violence. This is particularly visible through ECCC outreach initiatives. At the same time, I recognize that the terms justice and reconciliation are disputed and contested. The article can therefore be read to eschew an approach that presumes particular ‘essential’ properties of justice and reconciliation in favour of an understanding of each as negotiated and unstable. The article is rather interested in how each become meaningful in the specific ways that they are articulated, understood, accepted and/or contested between ECCC staff, civil society groups and the Cambodian public.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1750698011405183">
<label>3.</label>
<p>Audio files and English language transcripts of these radio adverts, as well as images from the poster series, are available on the ECCC website (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1750698011405183">ECCC, n.d.</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1750698011405183">
<label>4.</label>
<p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1750698011405183">Kiernan (2002)</xref> for an overview of these conflicts.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1750698011405183">
<label>5.</label>
<p>The ECCC published monthly ‘Court Report’ has a dedicated section in each issue to NGO and civil society ‘partner’ outreach that details ECCC endorsed initiatives. The Court Report is available on the ECCC website (ECCC. n.d.).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1750698011405183">
<label>6.</label>
<p>Details of the TPO outreach initiatives can be found on their website (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1750698011405183">TPO Cambodia, 2009</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1750698011405183">
<label>7.</label>
<p>In July 2009 CSD underwent significant restructuring and a change of leadership as a result of an internal dispute. The parts of the projects related to ECCC outreach on victim participation and a ‘National Dialogue on Justice and Reconciliation’ have been taken up by the Centre for Justice and Reconciliation (led by many former CSD staff).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1750698011405183">
<label>8.</label>
<p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1750698011405183">Hughes (2008)</xref> in particular on practices of visitation at Tuol Sleng by non-Cambodians.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1750698011405183">
<label>9.</label>
<p>A large number of this group were former KR and their families, although one resident of Phnom Penh was invited exceptionally as a former student of Tuol Sleng High School.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1750698011405183">
<label>10.</label>
<p>Personal interview, Phnom Penh, 7 October 2008.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1750698011405183">
<label>11.</label>
<p>All information at the site is in Khmer, English and French.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>BBC News</collab>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Khmer Rouge Leader ‘enacts role’</article-title>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/7264203.stm">news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/7264203.stm</ext-link></comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bickford</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Transforming a legacy of genocide: Pedagogy and tourism at the killing fields of Choeung Ek</article-title>. <comment>Report for the Memory, Memorials, and Museums Program, International Centre for Transitional Justice. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ictj.org/static/Asia/Cambodia/ICTJBickford_KHM_ChoeungEK_pa2009">www.ictj.org/static/Asia/Cambodia/ICTJBickford_KHM_ChoeungEK_pa2009</ext-link></comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Voices from S-21: Terror and History in Pol Pot’s Secret Prison</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ciorciari</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>The Khmer Rouge Tribunal</source>. <publisher-loc>Phnom Penh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Documentation Centre of Cambodia</publisher-name> .</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>States of Denial: Knowing about Atrocities and Suffering</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>ECCC</collab>. (<comment>n.d.</comment>) <article-title>Website</article-title>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eccc.gov.kh/english/publications.aspx">www.eccc.gov.kh/english/publications.aspx</ext-link></comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fawthrop</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Getting Away with Genocide? Elusive Justice and the Khmer Rouge Tribunal</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Cambodia after the Khmer Rouge: Inside the Politics of Nation Building</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Nationalism and memory at the Tuol Sleng Museum of Genocide Crimes, Cambodia</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hodgkin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Radstone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Contseted Pasts: The Politics of Memory</source>. <publisher-loc>London and New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006a</year>) <article-title>Memory and sovereignty in post-1979 Cambodia: Choeung Ek and local genocide memorials</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Genocide in Cambodia and Rwanda: New Perspectives</source>. <publisher-loc>New Jersey</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction</publisher-name>, <fpage>257</fpage>-<lpage>279</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="thesis">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006b</year>) <article-title>Fielding genocide: Post-1979 Cambodia and the geopolitics of memory</article-title>. <comment>PhD thesis</comment>, <publisher-name>Faculty of Arts, University of Melbourne</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Australia</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Dutiful tourism: Encountering the Cambodian genocide</article-title>. <source>Asia Pacific Viewpoint</source> <volume>49</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>318</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kiernan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Introduction: Conflict in Cambodia, 1945–2002</article-title>. <source>Critical Asian Studies</source> <volume>34</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage> .</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ledgerwood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The Cambodian Tuol Sleng Museum of Genocidal Crimes: National narrative</article-title>. <source>Museum Anthropology</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ly</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Conveying Khmer Rouge history to young people</article-title>. <source>Searching for the Truth</source> (<issue>1</issue>) (<publisher-loc>Phnom Penh, Cambodia</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Documentation Centre of Cambodia</publisher-name>): <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Narrating Political Reconciliation: South Africa’s Truth and Reconciliation Commission</source>. <publisher-loc>Lanham, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lexington Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Healing past violence: Traumatic assumptions and therapeutic interventions in war and reconciliation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Human Rights</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vinck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sokhom</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stover</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>So We Will Never Forget: A Population-Based Survey on Attitudes about Social Reconstruction and the Extraordinary Chambers in the Courts of Cambodia</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>TPO Cambodia</collab>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Website</article-title>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tpocambodia.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=48&amp;Itemid=60">www.tpocambodia.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=48&amp;Itemid=60</ext-link></comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1750698011405183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Witnessing genocide: Vigilance and remembrance at Tuol Sleng and Choeung Ek</article-title>. <source>Holocaust and Genocide Studies</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>