<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">WMR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spwmr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Waste Manag Res</journal-id>
<journal-title>Waste Management &amp; Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0734-242X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1096-3669</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0734242X12457119</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0734242X12457119</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Study on characteristics of printed circuit board liberation and its crushed products</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>Cui</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Aimin</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Ningbo</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0734242X12457119">School of Environmental Science and Technology, Dalian University of Technology, Dalian, P. R. China</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0734242X12457119">Aimin Li, School of Environmental Science and Technology, Dalian University of Technology, Dalian 116024, P. R. China Email: <email>leeam@dlut.edu.cn</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>30</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<issue-title>Special issue: Waste electrical and electronic equipment</issue-title>
<fpage>1178</fpage>
<lpage>1186</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">International Solid Waste Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Recycling printed circuit board waste (PCBW) waste is a hot issue of environmental protection and resource recycling. Mechanical and thermo-chemical methods are two traditional recycling processes for PCBW. In the present research, a two-step crushing process combined with a coarse-crushing step and a fine-pulverizing step was adopted, and then the crushed products were classified into seven different fractions with a standard sieve. The liberation situation and particle shape in different size fractions were observed. Properties of different size fractions, such as heating value, thermogravimetric, proximate, ultimate and chemical analysis were determined. The Rosin-Rammler model was applied to analyze the particle size distribution of crushed material. The results indicated that complete liberation of metals from the PCBW was achieved at a size less than 0.59 mm, but the nonmetal particle in the smaller-than-0.15 mm fraction is liable to aggregate. Copper was the most prominent metal in PCBW and mainly enriched in the 0.42–0.25 mm particle size. The Rosin-Rammler equation adequately fit particle size distribution data of crushed PCBW with a correlation coefficient of 0.9810. The results of heating value and proximate analysis revealed that the PCBW had a low heating value and high ash content. The combustion and pyrolysis process of PCBW was different and there was an obvious oxidation peak of Cu in combustion runs.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Printed circuit board waste</kwd>
<kwd>crushing</kwd>
<kwd>liberation</kwd>
<kwd>characterization</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0734242X12457119" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The amount of waste electric and electronic equipment (WEEE) is increasing rapidly. As printed circuit board waste (PCBW) are an essential part of almost all electric and electronic equipment, the increase in the generation of WEEE leads to an increase in the amount of printed circuit board waste (PCBW). Printed circuit boards can be classified according to the material used in its substrate, for example if it is paper-based (FR-1, FR-2, XPC), composite material-based or fiberglass-based (FR-4) printed circuit board, and so on. Recycling of PCBW is a challenge because of the fact that PCBW are diverse and complex in terms of the type, size and shape of materials and components. Many studies have been carried out with regard to the recycling of PCBW with a view to recovering resources and, at the same time, preventing environmental contamination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0734242X12457119">Flandinet et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X12457119">Hall and Williams, 2007a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0734242X12457119">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X12457119">Mou et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0734242X12457119">Park and Fray, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0734242X12457119">Wang et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0734242X12457119">Xiang et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0734242X12457119">Xiu and Zhang, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0734242X12457119">Yu et al., 2009</xref>). Mechanical and thermo-chemical methods are two traditional methods of recycling PCBW. For the mechanical process, liberation is the first step before separation can occur. After the liberation of the component materials, metallic concentrates are recovered through various mechanical processes, such as screening, specific gravity separation, magnetic separation, eddy current separation and electrostatic separation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0734242X12457119">Eswaraiah et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X12457119">Guo et al., 2011</xref> ; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0734242X12457119">Kumar et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0734242X12457119">Li et al., 2007b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0734242X12457119">Murugan et al., 2008</xref>; ). Particle size, shape and liberation degree play crucial roles in the mechanical recycling process. The liberation of metals and nonmetals is usually obtained by sequential particle size reduction being done in a crusher machine. Crushing is obviously the core process in mechanical treatment and the process of crushing may directly affect the efficiency of subsequent separation steps, which then can affect the recovery rate and the purity of the metal. The thermo-chemical process usually includes pyrolysis, thermometallurgy and combustion. Among them, pyrolysis can be considered as an alternative method for recycling PCBW because when pyrolysis is applied to PCBW the organic resin should decompose to form an oil and gas that can be subsequently used for chemical feedstock or fuel. Furthermore, the baseplate of PCBW after pyrolysis are very friable and prone to delamination, making the process of separating the organic, metallic and glass fiber fractions of PCBW much easier, and, therefore, making recycling of each PCBW fraction more viable. A number of studies on the pyrolysis of PCBW have been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0734242X12457119">Barontini et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0734242X12457119">Guan et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X12457119">Hall and Williams, 2007a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0734242X12457119">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0734242X12457119">Long et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0734242X12457119">Quan et al., 2010</xref>). In this aspect, a detailed knowledge of chemical and thermal degradation characteristics of PCBW which is very significant for both the design and the operation of PCBW thermal treatment facilities, is of great importance. However, dioxins and furan gases evolved from the pyrolysis process might induce environmental risk and should be considered in detail.</p>
<p>In the present investigation, characteristics of PCBW liberation and its crushed products were studied. First, the PCBW was pulverized in a process consisting of a coarse-crushing step and a fine-pulverizing step using a shearing machine and a hammer grinder together. A standard sieve is applied to screen crushed material to different size fractions. Characterization of different size fractions from the sieving operation was carried out using various methods of analysis, such as liberation degree analysis, size distribution analysis, elemental composition analysis, proximate analysis, heat value analysis and thermogravimetric analysis. These data could be used in the recycling process design and energy recovery of PCBW.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0734242X12457119" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="section3-0734242X12457119">
<title>Materials</title>
<p>PCBW feedstock without electronic elements was obtained from a local printed circuit board factory in Dalian city. The baseplates of the PCBW consisted of a woven fiberglass mat impregnated with thermoset resins with copper coating on the baseplates. The samples were cut into small pieces of about 1 cm × 1 cm by pliers before being subjected to crushing machines.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0734242X12457119">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>PCBW contains copper foil and are enforced by glass-fiber, so intensity, tenacity and rigidity are very high, making them hard to crush. In this study, a two-step crushing process was adopted. A CSJ-80B dust absorption crusher (Jiangyin Xinda Machinery Co., Ltd, Jiangyin, China), as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0734242X12457119">Figure 1(a)</xref>, was used as crude crusher. The crusher consisted mainly of a feeder, crushing chamber, output collector, electromotor and dust bag. The PCBW sample was fed into the crusher manually. The internal structure of the crushing chamber is presented in the top right of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0734242X12457119">Figure 1(a)</xref>. The crusher was driven by a three-phase AC induction motor at a fixed speed of 400 rpm, which was connected to the crusher by a triangular belt. The rated power of the motor was 1.5 kW. When the samples passed through the crushing chamber, the blades on rotor and stator throw intensive impact and shearing forces to the PCBW samples, which break them up into small pieces. The crushed PCBW was collected in output collector and the dust produced during crushing process was collected in a dust bag. A WF-18B dust absorption mill (Jiangyin Xinda Machinery), as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0734242X12457119">Figure 1(b)</xref> was employed as the second crusher. The internal structure of the milling chamber is presented in the top right of the <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0734242X12457119">Figure 1(b)</xref>. The mill was driven by a three-phase AC induction motor at a fixed speed of 5200 rpm, and the rated power of the motor was 2.2 kW. When the sample passed through the milling chamber, the intensive force caused by relative movement between the active of fluted disc and fixed fluted disc makes the PCBW samples break up into a small powder. After crushing and milling, the product was then subjected to size analysis by sieving. A standard vibrating screen (BD-300, Beijing Boda Machinery Co., Ltd, Beijing, China), as displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0734242X12457119">Figure 1(c)</xref> was used to screen the milled materials; all materials after screening were weighed. The milled products were classified into seven different fractions: &lt;0.15 mm, 0.15–0.18 mm, 0.18–0.25 mm, 0.25–0.42 mm, 0.42–0.59 mm, 0.59–0.84 mm and &gt;0.84 mm.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0734242X12457119" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Experimental equipment used in our studies: (a) crude crusher, (b) second crusher and (c) vibrating screen.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0734242X12457119">
<title>Characterization</title>
<p>The dissociation situation and morphology of PCBW after crushing were observed by a digital camera (Olympus 565uz, Tokyo, Japan) and scanning electron microscopy (SEM; JEOL JSM-5600LV, Tokyo, Japan). The fractions larger than 0.42 mm were observed by digital camera and the fractions smaller than 0.42 mm were observed by SEM.</p>
<p>In order to homogenize the sample for later elemental composition analysis, proximate analysis, calorific value analysis and thermogravimetric analysis, the coarser fractions (0.25–0.42 mm, 0.42–0.5 9 mm, 0.59–0.84 mm and &gt;0.84 mm) were first ground to a fine powder with a grinder (Retsch, ZM 200, Haan, Germany) separately and then each fraction was mixed uniformly by shaking. The analytical specimen of each fraction was taken using the quadrant sampling method. To verify the validity of the data, all experiments were performed twice and average values were listed.</p>
<p>The hydrogen (H), carbon (C) and nitrogen (N) content of PCBW samples in different size fractions was determined on a VarioEL III Elemental Analyzer, Elementar corporation, Hanau, Germany, and other elemental compositions were determined via X-ray fluorescence (XRF) spectrometers (XRF-1800, Shimadzu, Tokyo, Japan) which carried out qualitative analysis of elements from beryllium (Be) to uranium (U). Absolute errors of the analysis results conducted by the elemental analyzer and XRF were ≤0.1%.</p>
<p>The calorific values of PCBW samples in different size fractions were determined by burning a weighed sample in an oxygen bomb calorimeter (Hebi HongTai Electronic technology Co., Ltd, Hebi, China). The errors of heating values obtained in this study were about 1–2%. First, standard benzoic acid (C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>6</sub>COOH) was used to obtained the water equivalent of the calorimeter and then, according to the temperature rise of the calorimeter before and after the sample ignited, the calorific values of sample could be calculated by following <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0734242X12457119">equation (1)</xref>:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0734242X12457119">
<label>(1)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-0734242X12457119">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>Q</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>T</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1000</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>m</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0734242X12457119" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <italic>Q</italic> is heat of combustion of the sample, MJ/kg; Δ<italic>T</italic> is corrected temperature rise, °C; <italic>K</italic> is water equivalent of calorimeter, MJ/°C; <italic>e</italic> is correction for heat of combustion of firing wire, MJ; <italic>m</italic> is mass of the PCBW sample, g.</p>
<p>Ash content (Ad), moisture content (Md), volatile matter (Vd) and fixed carbon (FC) are considered as proximate analysis and they were conducted on a SDTGA5000 automatic proximate analyzer (Hunan Sundy Technology Development Industrial Co., Ltd, Changsha, China). The errors of proximate analysis were about 1%.</p>
<p>Thermal degradation of the milled PCBW samples was performed on a EXSTAR TG/DTA6300 Thermobalance at different atmospheres: nitrogen for the pyrolysis run and air for the combustion run. The sensitivity of the thermobalance was 1 µg. For each run, approximately 10 mg of sample was heated from room temperature to 800°C at 20°C/min with a flow rate of 200 ml/min. Thermogravimetry (TG) and differential thermogravimetry (DTG) curves were recorded continuously and presented as percentages of initial sample weight.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0734242X12457119" sec-type="results|discussion">
<title>Results and discussion</title>
<sec id="section7-0734242X12457119">
<title>Characteristics analysis of dissociation</title>
<p>Preceding physical and mechanical method, good liberation is the premise to further separation. The optimal crushing result is that each component in PCBW powders achieves monomer dissociation. In the present article, the degree of liberation was introduced to describe the dissociation situation of copper in milled PCBW, which can be expressed as <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0734242X12457119">equation (2)</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0734242X12457119">Zhang and Forssberg, 1999</xref>):</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0734242X12457119">
<label>(2)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math2-0734242X12457119">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>%</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0734242X12457119" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-eq2.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>in which LD denotes the liberation degree of copper; <italic>N</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> indicates the number of copper monomer particle; and <italic>N</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> indicates the number of intergrowth particles of copper and nonmetals. According to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0734242X12457119">equation (2)</xref>, the degree of liberation of copper at a certain size fraction could be determined by counting.</p>
<p>Through observing the crushed material by digital camera, the dissociation situation of PCBW after crushing can be initially determined. It could be seen from the photographs that, when particle size was larger than 0.84 mm (as presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0734242X12457119">Figure 2a</xref>), metals and nonmetals in PCBW were undissociated. In the size range 0.84–0.59 mm, metals began to strip from baseplates (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0734242X12457119">Figure 2(b)</xref>, indicated by arrows A and B), but there were still some intergrowth particles of copper and nonmetals, as indicated by arrow C in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0734242X12457119">Figure 2a</xref>. In the size range 0.59–0.42 mm, metals achieved approximately complete liberation, which is in agreement with the experimental results found by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X12457119">Guo et al. (2011)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0734242X12457119">Li et al. (2007a)</xref>. As shown by arrow D in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0734242X12457119">Figure 2c</xref>, the liberated metals included granular, rod-like copper.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0734242X12457119" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Digital photographs of milled printed circuit boards. (a) &gt;0.84 mm, (b) 0.84–0.59 mm, (c) 0.59–0.42 mm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The main components of the nonmetals in PCBW are thermoset resins and reinforcing materials. The shape and composition of nonmetals varied with particle size as seen through careful observation on SEM, as indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0734242X12457119">Figure 3</xref>. Particles in the size range 0.42–0.25 mm were present mainly as irregularly-shaped granules, with the majority of the glass fiber surface being encapsulated in epoxy resin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0734242X12457119">Figure 3a</xref>). The 0.25–0.18 mm fractions contained predominantly fiber-particulate bundles. The thermosetting resin got stuck inside the glass fibers, forming a large fiber-particulate bundle of loosely entangled fibers. Particles sized 0.18–0.15 mm contained both fiber bundles and single fibers, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0734242X12457119">Figure 3c</xref>. One part of the single fiber marked by the circle is enlarged in the top right of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0734242X12457119">Figure 3c</xref>. It is clearly seen that the fibers have a rough surface with a small quantity of resin. Fractions shorter than 0.15 mm, where the glass fibers are largely separated from the thermoset resin, were mainly in the form of single fibers and resin powder, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0734242X12457119">Figure 3d</xref>. Most of the single fibers in these fractions were of short length.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0734242X12457119" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Scanning electron microscope (SEM) micrographs of milled printed circuit boards with different particle sizes. (a) 0.42–0.25 mm, (b) 0.25–0.18 mm, (c) 0.18–0.15 mm, (d) &lt;0.15 mm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>PCBWs are heterogeneous samples, which usually contains glass fiber, reinforced resin and metals. The difference in shape and composition among crushed particles with different particle sizes could be determined by the intrinsic structure of PCBW and the two-step crushing process. Thin copper foils are attached to epoxy resin plates reinforced on each side by glass fibers; they become smaller as a result of simultaneous tearing when these brittle PCBW components are milled. Copper is easy to deform and hard to break under loads; as the size is reduced it might strip from the baseplates of PCBW. However, glass fiber and resin in raw material presented a stronger combination and most glass fiber surfaces were encapsulated by resin. The liberation of the resin from the glass fiber surface would leads to the formation of a large fiber-particulate bundle of loosely entangled fibers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0734242X12457119">Figure 3b</xref>). As the resin inside the glass fiber is liberated, the formed fiber bundle becomes single fibers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0734242X12457119">Figure 3c</xref>). These liberated single glass fibers are expected to be brittle; as the size reduced further, they were cut short and dispersed within the thermoset resin granules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0734242X12457119">Figure 3d</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0734242X12457119">
<title>Size distribution of the crushed products</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0734242X12457119">Figure 4</xref> shows the size distribution of PCBW after crushing. Materials in the complete dissociation sample (&lt;0.59 mm) were found to compose &gt;82.53% of the total particle weight. The weight percentage of particles &lt;0.15 mm constituted the largest portion, amounting to 37.15% of the total particle weight. However, too fine a size—which insures absolute metal/non-metal separation—may not be desired from an energetic perspective owing to the excessive energy required for size reduction. Additionally, based on visual observation, nonmetal particles in the fraction sized &lt;0.15mm is fine and liable to aggregate as presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0734242X12457119">Figure 5</xref>, leading to inefficient separation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0734242X12457119">Wu et al., 2009</xref>). Thus, the optimum particle size for mechanical dissociation of metals and nonmetals in PCBW should be controlled in the range of 0.15–0.59 mm. In order to avoid excessive fine generation and enhance the degree of liberation, some researchers carried out a study on cryogenic comminution and wet crushing of PCBW (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0734242X12457119">Tan et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0734242X12457119">Zou et al., 2006</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig4-0734242X12457119" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mass distribution of printed circuit board waste after crushing.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig5-0734242X12457119" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Aggregate of nonmetal powder in &lt;0.15 mm fraction.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0734242X12457119">
<title>Mathematical models of particle size distribution</title>
<p>Particle size distribution (PSD) is probably the most important physical characteristic of solids. Many distribution functions have been proposed to characterize the fraction of materials as a function of the particle size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0734242X12457119">González-Tello et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0734242X12457119">Macías-García et al., 2004</xref>). The Rosin–Rammler distribution function has long been used to describe the particle size distribution of powders of various types and sizes. The function is particularly suited to represent powders made by grinding, milling and crushing operations. The governing equation for the Rosin–Rammler particle size distribution may be expressed as shown in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-0734242X12457119">equation (3)</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0734242X12457119">Rosin and Rammler, 1933</xref>):</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0734242X12457119">
<label>(3)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math3-0734242X12457119">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>EXP</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-0734242X12457119" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-eq3.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <italic>R(x)</italic> is cumulative oversize mass, %; <italic>x</italic> is particle size, assumed to be equivalent to nominal sieve aperture size, mm; <italic>n</italic> is the size parameter or Rosin–Rammler geometric mean diameter, mm; and <italic>b</italic> is distribution parameter or Rosin–Rammler skewness parameter (dimensionless). A small <italic>b</italic> indicates a wide spread in PSD. The Rosin–Rammler function was linearized as shown in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-0734242X12457119">equation (4)</xref>:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0734242X12457119">
<label>(4)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math4-0734242X12457119">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>LNLN</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>LN</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>LN</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula4-0734242X12457119" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-eq4.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <italic>n</italic> is the slope and <italic>lnb</italic> is the intercept. Often, a least-square regression analysis is used to fit a line to the data point. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0734242X12457119">Figure 6</xref> shows the fits of experimental data to the Rosin–Rammler model. The correlation coefficient, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>, was 0.9810. The closer <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> is to 1 the better the fit of the experimental results to the model.</p>
<fig id="fig6-0734242X12457119" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Results of least-squares regression analysis of particle size distribution (PSD) fitting to the experimental data.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>After calculation, the values of <italic>b</italic> and <italic>n</italic> were found to be 2.585 and 0.846 respectively. The resulting distribution model for milled PCBW obtained by application of the Rosin–Rammler model was given by the <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula5-0734242X12457119">equation (5)</xref>:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0734242X12457119">
<label>(5)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math5-0734242X12457119">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>EXP</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>585</mml:mn>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>x</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>846</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula5-0734242X12457119" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-eq5.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0734242X12457119">Figure 7</xref> showed the cumulative oversized product data and its fitting curves. From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0734242X12457119">Figure 7</xref> it was deduced that the Rosin–Rammler model provided a good fit to the experimental PSD curve. As the speed of the mill used in our experiment has only a fixed value of 5200 rpm, and its speed can not be adjusted, we did not present the effect of grinding parameters in this article. However, the parameters of Rosin-Rammler model obtained at different grinding speeds have been reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0734242X12457119">Zhao et al. (2009)</xref>. Their results revealed that the values for both <italic>n</italic> and <italic>b</italic> increased with an increase in grinding speed.</p>
<fig id="fig7-0734242X12457119" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Cumulative oversized product data and fitting curves.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0734242X12457119">
<title>Elemental composition analysis</title>
<p>The C, H and N content in each fraction of milled PCBW determined by the elemental analyzer is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0734242X12457119">Figure 8a</xref> and the contents of other elemental compositions determined by XRF are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0734242X12457119">Figure 8b</xref>. The element composition analysis results conducted on the elemental analyzer and by XRF revealed that there was a total of about 21 elements in the PCBW. The major nonmetallic elements included H, C, oxygen (O), silicon (Si) and bromine (Br). The dominant metallic elements in PCBW included magnesium (Mg), aluminium (Al), calcium(Ca), iron (Fe), copper (Cu) and barium (Ba). A high content of Cu compared with the other metallic elements studied was observed. The concentrations of copper reached a maximum in the 0.42–0.25 mm size fraction—about 32.32%. Aside from the special case of precious metals, copper in PCBW is, economically-speaking, the most interesting metal for recovery and could be used as a secondary raw material because of its relatively high content compared with the corresponding content in explorable ores and its economic value. In addition, PCBW contained environmentally-harmful materials, such as chromium (Cr) and Br, which need to be recovered or removed before disposal.</p>
<fig id="fig8-0734242X12457119" position="float">
<label>Figure 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>Elemental compositions in each fraction of milled printed circuit board analyzed by (a) the elemental analyzer and (b) X-ray fluorescence (XRF).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-fig8.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0734242X12457119">
<title>Heating value and proximate analyses</title>
<p>Calorific value—the amount of energy released by each unit of combustible mass—is the most important property of a sample which determines the energy value of it. Direct combustion with energy recovery for PCBW waste is usually hindered by Br content and the need to prevent the formation of brominated dioxins; however, it is necessary to know the calorific value of PCBW as this value is usually used for the energy balance calculation during the pyrolysis process. The results of heating value and proximate analysis of each fraction in milled PCBW are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0734242X12457119">Table 1</xref>. The volatile matter was related to the organic matter in PCBW and the ash usually consisted of metal, glass fiber and other refractory oxides. It can be seen from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0734242X12457119">Table 1</xref> that the moisture content of the samples was between 0.34% and 0.85%, the ash content ranged from 53.87% in 0.18–0.15 mm fractions to 80.45% in the 0.42–0.25 mm fractions, the volatile matter content was in the range of 22.84% in the 0.59–0.42 mm particle size fractions and 39.62% in the 0.18–0.15 mm fractions, and the fixed carbon content varied between 0.16% in the 0.84–0.59-mm fractions and 7.92% in particle size fractions &lt;0.15 mm. The calorific values of the samples changed in the range of 8.07–11.69 MJ/kg. As can be seen from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0734242X12457119">Table 1</xref>, the proximate analysis and heating value of the milled PCBW samples varies over a broad range. PCBW samples had a low heating value and high ash content.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0734242X12457119" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Proximate analysis results and heating value of printed circuit board samples</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0734242X12457119" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Size fractions/mm</th>
<th align="left" colspan="4">Proximate analysis/wt% in dry basis<hr/></th>
<th align="left">Q MJ/kg</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Md</th>
<th align="left">Vd</th>
<th align="left">Ad</th>
<th align="left">FC</th>
<th/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>&gt;0.84</td>
<td>0.64</td>
<td>32.12</td>
<td>62.01</td>
<td>5.88</td>
<td>10.53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0.84–0.59</td>
<td>0.54</td>
<td>34.90</td>
<td>64.94</td>
<td>0.16</td>
<td>10.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0.59–0.42</td>
<td>0.34</td>
<td>22.84</td>
<td>79.96</td>
<td>2.8</td>
<td>8.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0.42–0.25</td>
<td>0.47</td>
<td>24.95</td>
<td>80.45</td>
<td>5.4</td>
<td>8.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0.25–0.18</td>
<td>0.75</td>
<td>36.11</td>
<td>60.52</td>
<td>3.37</td>
<td>10.96</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0.18–0.15</td>
<td>0.85</td>
<td>39.62</td>
<td>53.87</td>
<td>6.52</td>
<td>11.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>&lt;0.15</td>
<td>0.83</td>
<td>30.44</td>
<td>61.64</td>
<td>7.92</td>
<td>9.95</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0734242X12457119">
<p>Md, moisture content; Vd, volatile matter; Ad, ash content; FC, fixed carbon.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0734242X12457119">
<title>Thermal-chemical property analysis</title>
<p>The thermal stability of the non-metallic fractions is very important, both for the physical and chemical recycling methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0734242X12457119">Guo et al., 2009</xref>). The thermal behaviors of milled PCBW in the fractions of 0.59–0.42 mm, 0.42–0.25 mm and 0.25–0.18 mm were analyzed as a reference in this study. The corresponding TG and DTG curves for pyrolysis and combustion are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0734242X12457119">Figure 9a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0734242X12457119">b</xref>. As can be seen, there is little difference on the thermal stability of fractions with different sizes. The pyrolysis of PCBW only included one major step and DTG curves exhibited a single peak. Decomposition occurred mainly in the range of 299–391°C. The different behavior of the thermal decomposition in combustion runs can be observed. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0734242X12457119">Senneca et al. (2002)</xref> considered that two extreme pathways of solid fuel conversion in an oxidizing atmosphere are possible, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0734242X12457119">Figure 10</xref>. One is represented by the sequential steps of purely thermal degradation of the material (pyrolysis; reaction A ) followed by combustion of volatile matter and char generated by pyrolysis (reaction B).</p>
<fig id="fig9-0734242X12457119" position="float">
<label>Figure 9.</label>
<caption>
<p>Thermogravimetry (TG) and differential TG (DTG) curves during pyrolysis (a) and combustion (b) of milled PCBW in particle size fractions of 0.59–0.42 mm, 0.42–0.25 mm and 0.25–0.18 mm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-fig9.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig10-0734242X12457119" position="float">
<label>Figure 10.</label>
<caption>
<p>The possible pathways of solid fuel conversion in an oxidizing atmosphere.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X12457119-fig10.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0734242X12457119">Senneca et al. (2002)</xref>, there is a clear behavior of the type of pyrolytic decomposition with char formation and char combustion for PCBW combustion. However, an interesting phenomenon was observed in the combustion curve in that the weight increased with the temperature. The combustion behavior of pure copper appeared as a similar weight increase peak (as indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0734242X12457119">Figure 9b</xref>). This could be due to the interaction of oxygen with copper to form Cu-O and Cu-(O)-Cu species in the solid residues, in accordance with results reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0734242X12457119">Chien et al. (2000)</xref>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0734242X12457119" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The performed investigations showed that two-step crushing was an effective process in completely stripping metals from the baseplates of PCBW. PCBW could be fully dissociated between metal and nonmetals when particle size was &lt;0.59 mm. Material in the complete dissociation sample was found to constitute &gt;82.53% of the total particle weight. There are many kinds of metals in PCBW, such as Mg, Al, Ca, Fe, Cu and Ba. Among them, Cu is the primary metal and it mainly enriched in the 0.42–0.25 mm particle size fraction. The mathematical model of particle size distribution for crushing PCBW was in the form of <italic>R</italic>(<italic>x</italic>)=100 exp(−2.585<italic>x</italic><sup>0.846</sup>). The proximate analysis and heating value of the milled PCBW samples in each fraction were different. The calorific values of the samples changed in the range of 8.07 to 11.69 MJ/kg. The combustion and pyrolysis processes of milled PCBW are different. The pyrolysis of PCBW only included one major step. In combustion runs, owing to the interaction of O with Cu to form Cu-O and Cu-(O)-Cu species in the solid residues, there was an increase in weight with temperature in the combustion curve of PCBW.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The work cited in this paper was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 51006018) and the Geping GreenAid Project—Environmental Scientific Research “123 Project” of Liaoning, China.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barontini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marsanich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petarca</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cozzani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Thermal degradation and decomposition products of electronic boards containing BFRs</article-title>. <source>Industrial &amp; Engineering Chemistry Research</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>4186</fpage>–<lpage>4199</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Fate of bromine in pyrolysis of printed circuit board wastes</article-title>. <source>Chemosphere</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eswaraiah</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kavitha</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vidyasagar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Classification of metals and plastics from printed circuit boards using air classifier</article-title>. <source>Chemical Engineering and Processing</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>565</fpage>–<lpage>576</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flandinet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tedjar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghetta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fouletier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Metals recovering from waste printed circuit boards using molten salts</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hazardous Materials</source> <volume>213–214</volume>; <fpage>485</fpage>–<lpage>490</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>González-Tello</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vicaria</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>González</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A modified Nukiyama–Tanasawa distribution function and a Rosin–Rammler model for the particle-size-distribution analysis</article-title>. <source>Powder Technology</source> <volume>186</volume>: <fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M-X</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Product characterization of waste printed circuit board by pyrolysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Analytical and Applied Pyrolysis</source> <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>189</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Liberation characteristic and physical separation of printed circuit board</article-title>. <source>Waste Management</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>2161</fpage>–<lpage>2166</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Recycling of non-metallic fractions from waste printed circuit boards: A review</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hazardous Materials</source> <volume>168</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007a</year>) <article-title>Processing waste printed circuit boards for material recovery</article-title>. <source>Circuit World</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>W J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007b</year>) <article-title>Separation and recovery of materials from scrap printed circuit boards</article-title>. <source>Resources, Conservation and Recycling</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>691</fpage>–<lpage>709</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Review on mechanical recycling of end-of-life electrical and electronic equipments for recovery of metallic components</article-title>. <source>Korea Earth System Science and Engineering</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>608</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007a</year>) <article-title>Recycle technology for recovering resources and products from waste printed circuit boards</article-title>. <source>Environmental Science and Technology</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1995</fpage>–<lpage>2000</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007b</year>) <article-title>Application of corona discharge and electrostatic force to separate metals and nonmetals from crushed particles of waste printed circuit boards</article-title>. <source>Journal of Electrostatics</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Using vacuum pyrolysis and mechanical processing for recycling waste printed circuit boards</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hazardous Materials</source> <volume>177</volume>: <fpage>626</fpage>–<lpage>632</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Macías-García</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cuerda-Correa</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Díaz-Díez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Application of the Rosin-Rammler and Gates-Gaudin-Schuhmann models to the particle size distribution analysis of agglomerated cork</article-title>. <source>Materials Characterization</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A physical process for recycling and reusing waste printed circuit boards</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceeding of the international Symposium on Electronics and the Environment</conf-name>. <conf-loc>Washington, DC, USA</conf-loc>, <conf-date>1–4 August 2004</conf-date>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Murugan</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bharat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Varughese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haridoss</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Milling and separation of the multi-component printed circuit board materials and the analysis of elutriation based on a single particle model</article-title>. <source>Powder Technology</source> <volume>183</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fray</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Recovery of high purity precious metals from printed circuit boards</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hazardous Materials</source> <volume>164</volume>: <fpage>1152</fpage>–<lpage>1158</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Characterization of products recycling from printed circuit board waste pyrolysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Analysis and Applied Pyrolysis</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rammler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1933</year>) <article-title>The laws governing the fineness of powdered coal</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Institute of Fuel</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Senneca</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chirone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salatino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A thermogravimetric study of nonfossil solid fuels. 2. Oxidative pyrolysis and char combustion</article-title>. <source>Energy &amp; Fuels</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>661</fpage>–<lpage>668</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Size distribution of wet crushed waste printed circuit boards</article-title>. <source>Mining Science and Technology (China)</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Crushing performance and resource characteristic of printed circuit board scrap</article-title>. <source>Journal of Central South University of Technology</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>555</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Impact of nonconductive powder on electrostatic separation for recycling crushed waste printed circuit board</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hazardous Materials</source> <volume>164</volume>: <fpage>1352</fpage>–<lpage>1358</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhua</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Bioleaching of copper from waste printed circuit boards by bacterial consortium enriched from acid mine drainage</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hazardous Materials</source> <volume>184</volume>: <fpage>812</fpage>–<lpage>818</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xiu</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Materials recovery from waste printed circuit boards by supercritical methanol</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hazardous Materials</source> <volume>178</volume>: <fpage>628</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Review and prospects of recycling methods for waste printed circuit boards</article-title>. In: <conf-name>IEEE International Symposium on Sustainable Systems and Technology</conf-name>. <conf-loc>Tempe, AZ, USA</conf-loc>, <conf-date>18–20 May 2009</conf-date>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forssberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Intelligent Liberation and classification of electronic scrap</article-title>. <source>Powder Technology</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Physical Separation Theory and Technology of Electronic Waste</source>. <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Science Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0734242X12457119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>QZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Research on cryogenic comminution of discarded printed wiring boards</article-title>. <source>Journal of China University of Mining &amp; Technology</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>