<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">UEX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spuex</journal-id>
<journal-title>Urban Education</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0042-0859</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-8340</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0042085911431430</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0042085911431430</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Editorial</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lomotey</surname><given-names>Kofi</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>5</fpage>
<lpage>6</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Barrett, Ausbrooks, and Cosio look at how schools address the welfare of students, focusing on the role of schools in addressing the needs of middle and high school students displaced by Hurricane Katrina. In schools where (a) students sought assistance from teachers, (b) cooperation was facilitated, and (b) student needs were addressed in moderation, greater success was realized. The authors include recommendations for educators for addressing student needs.</p>
<p>Ellerbrock conducted a qualitative study in three high schools in which interdisciplinary teaming was explored as an alternative teaching strategy. Using observations, interviews, and archives, Ellerbrock found that increased teacher communication better addresses student and teacher needs. Students did not see the change as much of a benefit as did teachers. Implementation of the strategy was an “intervening variable.”</p>
<p>Ordonez-Jasis and Jasis look at Latino parent engagement at three California community and school-based parent participation projects. Using interviews, the authors address the activism of women and its relationship to parent participation and, ultimately, student success.</p>
<p>Sanchez and Salazar look at the way Latino immigrants acquire and use technology in the United States and in Mexico. In this 3-year ethnographic study, the authors uncover what is known about the digital divide as it relates to bilingual Latino immigrants. Suggestions for teaching are addressed by Sanchez and Salazar.</p>
<p>O’Malley, Roseboro, and Hunt conduct a two-part case study, looking at state financial oversight of an east St. Louis school district. Results show financial stability was achieved, but sustained student achievement was not. The oversight was also hierarchically structured. Recommendations of O’Malley, Roseboro, and Hunt include paying close attention to culture and other factors in future state–district partnerships.</p>
<p>Marvul looked at the impact of several factors—attendance monitoring, sports participation, and a moral character class—on student attendance. Studying high school students—with control and intervention groups—the author uncovered significant differences in the groups. Attendance was related to all predictor variables. Attendance, educational expectations, engagement, and student attitudes improved with the intervention.</p>
<p>Fairchild, Tobias, Corcoran, Djukic, Kovner, and Noguera study the impact of relational demography on teacher job satisfaction. In this secondary data analysis, findings indicate that some components of relational demography have an impact on teacher job satisfaction.</p>
<p>Archer-Banks and Behar-Horenstein, using Ogbu’s cultural ecological theory, examine how several factors—school policies and practices, caring adults, student negotiation of academic, and racial identities—contribute to the success of more successful African American high school students.</p>
<p>Taymans, Tindle, Freund, Ortiz, and Harris researched a professional development school partnership and its effect on the preparation of urban educators. Using interviews, surveys, focus groups, and observations, the authors found that the partnership prepared the candidates well. In discussion, the authors look at several factors that contribute to the success of the partnership.</p>
<p>Cholewa, Amatea, West-Olatunji, and Wright use grounded theory to look at the relational processes of a teacher and her fifth grade African American students. Emotional connectedness was found to be a significant dimension. Uncovered themes are discussed, as are important teacher practice and preparation implications.</p>
<p>Jupp and Slattery look at the impact of a predominantly White teaching force in diverse de facto segregated schools. Using narratives, the authors discuss the respondents’ professional identifications: race visibility, difference within difference, and relational-experiential pedagogy. Jupp and Slattery call for future studies addressing White teacher identity.</p>
<p>Thornberg conducted an investigation looking at collaborations between resource teams, teachers, principals, students, and parents. The aim was to address the academic and social behavior of students. Thornberg’s grounded theory study uncovered human resource synchronizing and human resource desynchronizing as two ideal challenges to students.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>Enjoy.<break/>
<italic>Kofi Lomotey</italic></sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>