<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MDM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmdm</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Med Decis Making</journal-id>
<journal-title>Medical Decision Making</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0272-989X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-681X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0272989X12468793</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0272989X12468793</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editorials</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Standardization and Regulatory Guidelines May Inhibit Science and Reduce the Usefulness of Analyses Based on the Application of Preference-Based Measures for Policy Decisions</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Feeny</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0272989X12468793">University of Alberta, Portland, Oregon, USA (DF)</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0272989X12468793">David Feeny, PhD, Professor Emeritus, Department of Economics, University of Alberta, 1209 SW Sixth Avenue, Unit 801, Portland, OR 97204-1030, USA; telephone: (971) 255-0187; e-mail: <email>dafeeny@comcast.net</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>33</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Health Technology Assessment to Inform Policy</issue-title>
<fpage>316</fpage>
<lpage>319</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>9</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>28</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>As Mavranezouli and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0272989X12468793">1</xref></sup> note, the use of a 10-y time horizon for health states for their time tradeoff (TTO) preference elicitation may have affected their results. So why did these authors choose a 10-y time horizon? Proximally, they probably chose this time horizon because one of the important objectives of the study on which the article is based was to generate evidence for a submission to the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) in England and Wales. NICE recommends the TTO and a 10-y time horizon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0272989X12468793">2</xref></sup>—the time horizon that was used in the Measurement and Valuation of Health (MVH) study on which the UK scoring function for EQ-5D is based.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0272989X12468793">3</xref></sup> Distally, the authors probably chose the 10-y time horizon to enhance the comparability between their results and results from other studies. Indeed, the 10-y time horizon has been very frequently used.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0272989X12468793">4</xref></sup></p>
<sec id="section1-0272989X12468793">
<title>MVH Protocol: 10-y Time Horizon</title>
<p>Why might the use of a 10-y time horizon pose a problem? A 10-y time horizon invites respondents to view the health state being described as chronic, a condition that will last for a considerable period of time. Indeed, it is often the case that researchers want to know the value attached to a variety of chronic health states. For many respondents in their 60s and 70s, 10 y is a plausible time horizon. But for respondents in their 80s, 10 y is, in general, too generous, and for those not yet in their 60s, it is much too stingy. The mean age in the sample for the Mavranezouli and colleagues study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0272989X12468793">1</xref></sup> was 49 y; thus, clearly, the 10-y time horizon was a poor match for many respondents. If you ask people to evaluate something that is unrealistic to them, respondents may not provide fully meaningful responses.</p>
<p>Could the 10-y time horizon matter quantitatively? Stiggelbout and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0272989X12468793">5</xref></sup> elicited TTO scores from 3 groups of cancer patients using 3 different time horizons: an approximation of the patient’s additional life expectancy and 2 shorter time periods. The TTO scores for the longer time periods were systematically lower than the scores for the shorter time periods.</p>
<p>Similarly, Lin and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0272989X12468793">6</xref></sup> investigated the effects of the duration of the time horizon in a study of patients with spinal cord injury. The study randomized patients to provide TTO and standard gamble (SG) scores based on 10-y and 20-y time horizons or 20-y and 30-y time horizons for the patient’s current health state. TTO scores, but not SG scores, declined as the time horizon was increased from 10 to 30 y.</p>
<p>In analyses of the MVH data (10-y time horizon), Dolan and Roberts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0272989X12468793">7</xref></sup> report a systematic quadratic relationship between the age of the respondents and their scores. Scores increase with the age of the respondents up to 45 y of age and then fall slowly, with a more rapid decline in the 70s. This may be evidence that respondents of different ages respond differently to the 10-y time horizon.</p>
<p>Van Nooten and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0272989X12468793">4</xref></sup> in an Internet survey asked respondents to provide an estimate of their subjective additional life expectancy (SLE). Respondents were asked to evaluate 3 hypothetical EQ-5D health states with varying levels of morbidity. For SLE &gt;10, results indicated that the number of years respondents were willing to trade was negatively affected by SLE; the longer the SLE, the fewer years they were willing to trade. The number of respondents with SLE &lt;10 was too few for statistical significance, but the sign on SLE &lt;10 was positive; the longer the SLE, the more years they were willing to trade. A possible implication of these results is that 10-y time horizon TTO scores are comparable across studies only if the age distributions of respondents in those studies are similar.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0272989X12468793">
<title>Choice of TTO</title>
<p>NICE strongly recommends the use of the TTO instead of the SG, the other major choice-based technique for eliciting preference scores for health states. Of course, in addition to the assumptions on which the SG is based, the TTO also assumes that individuals have utility functions that are linear in additional years; many criticize this assumption (see, for instance, Garau and others<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0272989X12468793">8</xref></sup>). Furthermore, in particular in patients with life-threatening conditions, many studies have reported an unwillingness by many patients to trade any time with the TTO.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0272989X12468793">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0272989X12468793">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0272989X12468793"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0272989X12468793"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0272989X12468793">12</xref></sup> In contrast, in similar situations respondents are often willing to trade risk on the SG.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0272989X12468793">
<title>Choice of Multiattribute Preference-Based Measure</title>
<p>NICE strongly recommends the use of the EQ-5D. In a pilot study done in the United Kingdom, the Patient-Reported Outcome Measures (PROMs) project in cataract surgery, the EQ-5D was quickly abandoned because EQ-5D scores did not change, whereas scores on a vision-specific measure did.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0272989X12468793">13</xref></sup> That the generic preference-based measure seemingly did not detect clinically meaningful change when it had occurred adversely affected the credibility of the PROMs program among clinicians. More generally, the proliferation of mapping studies (see, for instance, Brazier and others<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0272989X12468793">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0272989X12468793">15</xref></sup>)—the development of algorithms to predict EQ-5D scores using data from disease- or condition-specific measures—may be in part a results of investigators either having evidence that the EQ-5D is not responsive in that clinical context or suspecting that it will not be and therefore omitting it from the study. Of course, the relative lack of responsiveness of generic measures when compared with specific measures is not unique to the EQ-5D.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0272989X12468793">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0272989X12468793">17</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0272989X12468793">
<title>A Tradeoff between Comparability among Studies and the Best Available Science?</title>
<p>The guidelines promulgated by NICE and other health technology assessment regulatory agencies are meant to enhance comparability of utility scores across studies. NICE’s assumption is presumably that if all studies use the EQ-5D, or for those studies that engage in the direct elicitation of preference scores, the 10-y time horizon TTO, then if results differ it is because the health outcomes really differ. Indeed, using guidelines to enhance comparability and thus the interpretability of study results is a worthy goal. But there is a risk of premature and inappropriate standardization. If the 10-y time horizon is implausible for many respondents, the validity of the resulting scores may be in doubt. Furthermore, if a widely used generic preference-based measure is chosen to enhance the ability to make comparisons to other studies, but that measure has inferior measurement properties relative to other generic preference-based measures in the relevant area of application—say, because of substantial floor or ceiling effects or attenuated responsiveness—then neither internal validity nor external generalizability are well served.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0272989X12468793">18</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0272989X12468793"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0272989X12468793">20</xref></sup></p>
<p>Perhaps instead, measures should be chosen on the basis of relevance and their track record in the context of the study at hand. As noted above, using the EQ-5D instead of a preference-based measure that explicitly includes vision might lead to the underestimation of the gains in health-related quality of life associated with cataract surgery.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0272989X12468793">21</xref></sup> Because hearing is explicitly included in the Health Utilities Index Mark 3 (HUI3) and hearing is not included in EQ-5D, HUI3 has often been shown to be more useful in studies of cochlear implants.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0272989X12468793">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0272989X12468793">23</xref></sup> In a study of epilepsy, Langfitt and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0272989X12468793">24</xref></sup> indicate that despite the floor effects associated with the Short-Form 36 and Short-Form 6D, the inclusion of social interaction in the short-form measures makes them more useful than a number of other preference-based measures, including EQ-5D and HUI3.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0272989X12468793">
<title>How Important Is “Strict” Comparability?</title>
<p>Clearly, all other things being equal, comparability is desirable. The guidelines for the economic evaluation of health care services specified in a number of other jurisdictions, including Australia,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0272989X12468793">25</xref></sup> Canada,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0272989X12468793">26</xref></sup> and the United States,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0272989X12468793">27</xref></sup> are, in general, less prescriptive than the guidelines specified by NICE. For the direct elicitation of preference scores, a choice-based technique is recommended, typically the SG or TTO. In general, investigators can choose among established preference-based measures. In practice, this eclecticism does not appear to have adversely affected decision making and comparability. In reflecting on the experience of the Ontario Drug Benefit Program’s Drug Quality and Therapeutics Committee, Andreas Laupacis, MD, notes that “the subtleties of economic evaluation do not play an important role in decision making.”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0272989X12468793">28</xref>(p45)</sup> Instead, the evidence on effectiveness and estimates of the order of magnitude of cost-effectiveness are the focus of deliberations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0272989X12468793">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0272989X12468793">29</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0272989X12468793">
<title>How to Comply with Regulatory Guidelines and Serve Science Simultaneously?</title>
<p>There is a well-established tradition of sensitivity analyses in health technology assessment and economic evaluation. One approach might be for investigators to do one version of the study/analyses that is compliant with the regulatory guidelines and another version based on the best currently available science. Clearly, this is more feasible if both approaches call for the same type of primary data collection. If both approaches provide similar answers, decision makers can be more confident. If the answers diverge importantly, then decision making becomes more challenging. Furthermore, there may be clues on how the science can be improved. Of course, such an approach might invite gaming behavior by the advocates for new health care technologies. Nonetheless, if the science of evaluation is to improve over time, in the long run we are probably better served by using the best available science and then critically evaluating it. Higher-quality evidence will serve both decision making and science.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The author acknowledges the helpful comments provided by Dr. Louise Russell.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>It should be noted that David Feeny has a proprietary interest in Health Utilities Incorporated, Dundas, Ontario, Canada. HU Inc. distributes copyrighted Health Utilities Index (HUI) materials and provides methodological advice on the use of HUI.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0272989X12468793">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mavranezouli</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brazier</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barkham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Estimating a preference-based index from the Clinical Outcomes in Routine Evaluation-Outcome Measure (CORE-OM): valuation of CORE-6D</article-title>. <source>Med Decis Making</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>395</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0272989X12468793">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence</collab>. <article-title>Guide to the Methods of Technology Appraisal</article-title>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NICE</publisher-name>; <month>June</month> <year>2008</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0272989X12468793">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Modeling valuations for EuroQol health states</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>1095</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0272989X12468793">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van Nooten</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koolman</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brouwer</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The influence of subjective life expectancy on health state valuations using a 10 year TTO</article-title>. <source>Health Econ</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>549</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0272989X12468793">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stiggelbout</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kiebert</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kievit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leer</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Habbema</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Haes</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The “utility” of the time trade-off method in cancer patients: feasibility and proportional Trade-off</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1207</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0272989X12468793">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Examination of assumptions in using time tradeoff and standard gamble utilities in individuals with spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0272989X12468793">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <article-title>To what extent can we explain time trade-off values from other information about respondents?</article-title> <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>919</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0272989X12468793">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Garau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Towse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Using QALYs in cancer: a review of the methodological limitations</article-title>. <source>Pharmacoeconomics</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>673</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0272989X12468793">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elstein</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuzel</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prostate cancer patients’ utilities for health states: how it looks depends on where you stand</article-title>. <source>Med Decis Making</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0272989X12468793">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grann</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Panageas</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Antman</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neugut</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Decision analysis of prophylactic mastectomy and oophorectomy in BRCA1-positive or BRCA-2 positive patients</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>979</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0272989X12468793">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grann</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sundarajan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alberta</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Troxel</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neugut</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The quality of life associated with prophylactic treatments for women with BRCA1/2 mutations</article-title>. <source>Cancer J Sci Am</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0272989X12468793">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Valuing health status using VAS and TTO: what lies behind the numbers?</article-title> <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1289</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0272989X12468793">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feeny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <article-title>Using patient reported outcome measures to improve health and health care</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Noyes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <conf-name>Patient Reported Outcomes to Improve Performance, Value and Productivity: Symposium Proceedings</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Victoria</conf-loc>, <conf-date>December 9, 2010</conf-date>; pp <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>; published online 16 May 2012. Available from: URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.effectiveproductivity.info/resources/category/37-patient-reported-outcomes-measures">www.effectiveproductivity.info/resources/category/37-patient-reported-outcomes-measures</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0272989X12468793">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brazier</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yanag</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowen</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A review of studies mapping (or cross walking) non-preference based measures of health to generic preference-based measures</article-title>. <source>Eur J Health Econ</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>212</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0272989X12468793">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brazier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsuchyia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Preference-based condition-specific measures of health: what happens to cross programme comparability?</article-title> <source>Health Econ</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0272989X12468793">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feeny</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stubbing</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Generic and specific measurement of health-related quality of life in a clinical trial of respiratory rehabilitation</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0272989X12468793">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wiebe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matijevic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sidwell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparative responsiveness of generic and specific quality-of-life instruments</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0272989X12468793">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fryback</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunham</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>U.S. norms for six generic health-related quality of life indexes from the National Health Measurement Study</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1162</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0272989X12468793">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chew</surname><given-names>L-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>K-Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A comparison of the EuroQol-5D and the Health Utilities Index Mark 3 in patients with rheumatic disease</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>2268</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0272989X12468793">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feeny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparing Short Form 6D, standard gamble, and Health Utilities Index Mark 2 and Mark 3 utility scores: results from total hip arthroplasty patients</article-title>. <source>Qual Life Res</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1659</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0272989X12468793">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feeny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spritzer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Agreement about identifying patients who change over time: cautionary results in cataract and heart failure patients</article-title>. <source>Med Decis Making</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0272989X12468793">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cost-utility analysis of cochlear implants in Korea using different measures of utility</article-title>. <source>Acta OtoLaryngol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>817</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0272989X12468793">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>UK Cochlear Implant Study Group.</collab> <article-title>Criteria of candidacy for unilateral cochlear implantation in postlingually deafened adults II: cost-effectiveness analysis</article-title>. <source>Ear Hear</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>336</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0272989X12468793">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Langfitt</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vickrey</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Validity and responsiveness of generic preference-based HRQOL instruments in chronic epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Qual Life Res</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>899</fpage>–<lpage>914</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0272989X12468793">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <article-title>Economic analysis as an aid to subsidisation decisions: the development of Australian guidelines for pharmaceuticals</article-title>. <source>Pharmacoeconomics</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0272989X12468793">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Canadian Coordinating Office for Health Technology Assessment (CCOHTA). Guidelines for Economic Evaluation of Pharmaceuticals: Canada</collab>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Canadian Coordinating Office for Health Technology Assessment</publisher-name>; <month>November</month> <year>1997</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0272989X12468793">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <article-title>Cost-Effectiveness in Health and Medicine</article-title>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>1996</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0272989X12468793">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laupacis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Inclusion of drugs in provincial drug benefit programs: who is making these decisions, and are they the right ones?</article-title> <source>CMAJ</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>166</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0272989X12468793">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laupacis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <article-title>Incorporating economic evaluations into decision-making: the Ontario Experience</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<supplement>Suppl.</supplement>):<fpage>II-15</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>