<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PUS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppus</journal-id>
<journal-title>Public Understanding of Science</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0963-6625</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1361-6609</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0963662511415295</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0963662511415295</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Les Problèmes Théoriques de la Vulgarisation Scientifique</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Trench</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0963662511415295">Dublin City University, Ireland</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>777</fpage>
<lpage>778</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jurdant</surname><given-names>Baudouin</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>Les Problèmes Théoriques de la Vulgarisation Scientifique</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Editions des Archives Contemporaines</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>. <page-count count="248"/> pp. ISBN <isbn>978–2813000057</isbn></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This 1973 thesis by Baudouin Jurdant – a member of this journal’s editorial advisory board – has been frequently mentioned in French discussions of science communication. It has been circulated in photocopies and posted on the web. It appears here, unaltered, with a postscript in which Jurdant extends some of the arguments he outlined in his late twenties.</p>
<p>The thesis’s publication reveals the long roots of Jurdant’s more recent preoccupations. He has published several papers on notions of scientificity; a key chapter in the thesis is “The myth of scientificity.” The opening chapter of the thesis explores science popularisation in the context of positivism and scientism in the 1870s; a recent contribution to <italic>Alliage</italic> review argues that science popularisation can be considered a means of propagating the ideology of scientism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0963662511415295">Jurdant, 2007</xref>). Looking at science popularisation as literary genre, Jurdant suggested that it came closest to autobiography; he elaborated on this later in a contribution to this journal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0963662511415295">Jurdant, 1993</xref>). Reflexivity, however – a central theme of Jurdant’s writing – is touched on lightly in the thesis.</p>
<p>Publication of Jurdant’s thesis is itself an autobiographical project, but not just personal; the thesis tells a significant story about the emergence of science communication studies before “science communication” was the common label. Jurdant brought Anglophone work in communication theory, educational psychology and discourse studies into an avowedly “eclectic” but distinctly French framework of post-modern and Marxist sociology, structuralist anthropology and semiotics. Many of these studies and reflections remain remarkably relevant.</p>
<p>Jurdant’s critique of science popularisation was acutely observed and often strongly stated. He considered the model of transmission of knowledge to be “untenable,” science popularisation to be based on an “impossible” pedagogic relationship, and to constitute a “perfectly empty discourse.” But he does note in his postscript that some of the thesis’s judgements were “a little abrupt.”</p>
<p>The central novelty of the thesis was its approach to science popularisation as communication, according to “<italic>the</italic> model of communication” expressed in terms of sender-message-receiver. Jurdant enhances the reception element by reference to educational theory and psychology but communication studies more firmly rooted in concepts of society and culture were still some way off. It is surprising that he does not reflect on this in his postscript.</p>
<p>Almost in passing, Jurdant indicated that he preferred the opposition science / everyday to science / society. He was writing not long after Henri Lefebvre published his Critique of Everyday Life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0963662511415295">1961</xref>) with which I became familiar as a student in France just when Jurdant was studying in England. Our paths converged in the mid-1990s and we have conversed and co-operated in various ways since then. In the interest of the dialogue – particularly spoken – Jurdant actively promotes, I suggest that we can correct CP Snow’s binary distinction of literary and scientific cultures, prominent in this thesis, by considering how both cultures to different degrees and in different ways intersect with the everyday.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0963662511415295">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jurdant</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Popularization of science as the autobiography of science</article-title>. <source>Public Understanding of Science</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>373</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0963662511415295">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jurdant</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>La colonisation scientifique de l’ignorance</article-title>. <source>Alliage</source> <fpage>61</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0963662511415295">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1961</year>) <article-title>Critique de la vie quotidienne II, Fondements d’une sociologie de la quotidienneté</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>L’Arche</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>