<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmej</journal-id>
<journal-title>Music Educators Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0027-4321</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1945-0087</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0027432112451841</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0027432112451841</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Departments</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Take Note</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>99</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>4</fpage>
<lpage>4</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 National Association for Music Education</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">MENC: The National Association for Music Education</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0027432112451841">
<title>New Challenges: Orchestrating Success for Music Education</title>
<p>What if today was the first day of your music teacher career? What if you just walked into your first classroom?</p>
<p>Do you think that the environment would be different than it was five, ten, fifteen, or more than twenty years ago? Would the student population look different? Would the community be the same? Would the legislature or Congress have acted differently? I know that my answers to these questions would show some pretty stark differences from the day I started as a music educator in 1968.</p>
<p>Almost every element of the teaching profession in the United States over the past few decades has been affected by two large trends: technology and demographics. With the economic reset we face as a nation and individually pushing the process, we have no choice but to recognize that we are in the middle of fundamental change to our profession—and that change will continue for some time.</p>
<p>Like you, NAfME is undergoing adjustments and challenges. Like you, we plan to be a winner in the race. We know that music education orchestrates success for our students, institutions, and communities. Music education has a positive impact on learning, and our impact on students goes far beyond school.</p>
<p>Changes in the American public school system will persist, as will the passion we bring to our classrooms. Across the country, NAfME has devoted considerable resources to advocacy efforts in support of music education. In the past year, we created the Music Education Policy Roundtable, which has grown from one partner to fourteen in less than twelve months. While our national association works with Congress, our family of state federated associations has ramped up efforts with state legislators and regulators. This work may not always be seen, but if we intend to have high-quality sequential programs of music in our schools, we will need to participate in our nation’s and states’ political and regulatory processes at every level. This is essential: Remember that students have a voice in music education because we work on their behalf. They need to know that we take seriously continuing music education programs, or they will not take it seriously.</p>
<p>We are conducting a member satisfaction and marketing survey to better understand member needs and position our work on behalf of music education and educators. Simultaneously, we have reached out to others in the music community to better engage the various music interest groups in coordinated programs.</p>
<p>This year we will continue our work to update our website and grow online services for the membership. And work doesn’t stop with the virtual domain. Give a Note Foundation, in collaboration with Twentieth Century Fox Home Entertainment and the television show <italic>Glee</italic>, distributed $1 million this year to needy school music programs across the country. We provided advice and research to support teacher evaluation processes that respect the music educator. Our work with All American Games and the U.S. Army has created a masterful student experience that culminates in the U.S. Army All-American Marching Band.</p>
<p>And we plan over the next few years to reimagine our professional development efforts, working with our state federated associations in bringing high-quality in-service programs in new formats on topics of particular interest to music educators. We have coordinated and devoted significant resources to updating the National Standards, and that work continues in this year. And we’re building all of this on the basis of a strong, established voice for the profession: We are preparing to celebrate the one-hundred-year history of <italic>Music Educators Journal</italic> (<italic>MEJ</italic>) over the coming eighteen months.</p>
<p>We must embrace the new realities in which we work to ensure that music education will truly be treated as a core subject in the effort to provide America’s school children with college- and career-ready curricula. We know the value of music in students’ lives—and we must all work to spread that knowledge. We must work at this each day in our classrooms, with fellow teachers in every subject area, and with school administrators, parents, community leaders, and policymakers at every level. We came to our careers to teach music, and to do that, we need to promote the benefits of music education in the lives of students.</p>
<p>If you are at all like me, you walked into your first classroom full of enthusiasm, desire, and maybe a little trepidation. We looked into the eyes of our students and saw the future. The musical experiences and learning that we were about to provide to those students were a way to give back to our families and communities for the opportunities they provided us.</p>
<p>Students’ lives were, and continue to be, better for what we brought, and bring, to their school experience. From their earliest days in elementary classrooms with general music teachers through their middle school, high school, and college days, music plays a significant role in students’ development—academically, personally, and as citizens.</p>
<p>As we advance music education by encouraging the study and making of music by all, we advance the individual and collective life of our society. You and NAfME are in that business, and we should be proud of what we do. And every time you hear music play a steady role in a celebration of our nation’s achievements or in a ceremony reflecting on our nation’s tragedies, know that you are playing your part in making our culture and our nation possible.</p>
<p>Enjoy the new academic year.</p>
<graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_0027432112451841-fig1.tif"/>
</sec>
</body>
</article>