<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">amjsports</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Sports Med</journal-id>
<journal-title>The American Journal of Sports Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0363-5465</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3365</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0363546512461903</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0363546512461903</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
<subject>2</subject>
<subject>43</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Long-term Outcomes of Postoperative Septic Arthritis After Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Schub</surname><given-names>David L.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512461903">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>Leah M.</given-names></name>
<degrees>PA-C</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512461903">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>Flavia A.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0363546512461903">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Winalski</surname><given-names>Carl S.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0363546512461903">†</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0363546512461903">‡</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>Richard D.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512461903">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0363546512461903">§</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0363546512461903"><label>*</label>Orthopaedic &amp; Rheumatologic Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, Ohio</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0363546512461903"><label>†</label>Imaging Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, Ohio</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0363546512461903"><label>‡</label>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Lerner Research Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, Ohio</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0363546512461903">Investigation performed at Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, Ohio</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0363546512461903"><label>§</label>Richard D. Parker, MD, Cleveland Clinic, Department of Orthopaedics, A-41, 9500 Euclid Avenue, Cleveland, OH 44195 (e-mail: <email>parkerr@ccf.org</email>).</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>12</issue>
<fpage>2764</fpage>
<lpage>2770</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">American Orthopaedic Society for Sports Medicine</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0363546512461903">
<title>Background:</title>
<p>Septic arthritis is a rare but potentially devastating complication of anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) reconstruction surgery. Several studies, including one by this group, have reported short- and medium-term outcomes, but to our knowledge there are no long-term follow-up studies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0363546512461903">
<title>Hypothesis:</title>
<p>Postoperative septic arthritis after ACL reconstruction surgery will lead to diminished long-term outcomes compared with surgery without infectious complications, likely related to the development of arthritis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0363546512461903">
<title>Study Design:</title>
<p>Case series; Level of evidence, 4.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0363546512461903">
<title>Methods:</title>
<p>Four of 831 consecutive patients undergoing arthroscopically guided ACL reconstruction surgeries performed by 1 surgeon were previously reported on by this group at an average follow-up of 36 months. These same patients were contacted and reevaluated. Each patient underwent a physical examination, functional testing, and subjective evaluations with the SF-36, Lysholm, International Knee Documentation Committee (IKDC), and Tegner activity scale scores. Plain film radiographs and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans were analyzed by 2 musculoskeletal radiologists.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0363546512461903">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>Average follow-up time for this study was 17.9 years, and average age was 44.3 years. No other injuries or surgeries had occurred from the time of the previous study. Each patient had a decline in SF-36, Lysholm, and IKDC score, and the average Tegner score was unchanged. Average vertical hop test performance and Biodex dynamometry were both improved. The average side-to-side displacement measured via the KT-1000 arthrometer was increased. Radiographic and MRI studies revealed progression of arthritis in all patients and ACL graft rupture in 1 patient.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0363546512461903">
<title>Conclusion:</title>
<p>Patients who develop septic arthritis as a complication of ACL reconstruction surgery have diminished long-term subjective, functional, and radiographic outcomes compared with historical reports of uncomplicated cases, likely related to pain from advanced arthritis. As compared with their own earlier follow-up, these patients had declines in pain-related subjective measures but remained stable or improved in both functional testing and activity-related subjective scales.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>anterior cruciate ligament</kwd>
<kwd>septic arthritis</kwd>
<kwd>arthroscopy</kwd>
<kwd>arthritis</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Septic arthritis is a potentially devastating complication of all peri- and intra-articular surgical procedures, including arthroscopy. Persistent pain, dysfunction, diminished subjective outcomes, and development of early arthritis have all been associated with this diagnosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546512461903">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546512461903">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0363546512461903">27</xref></sup> The incidence of septic arthritis after arthroscopically guided anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) reconstruction surgery has been reported to be between 0.14% and 1.7%.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0363546512461903">‖</xref></sup> The functional, clinical, and subjective outcomes of the patients who have been diagnosed and treated for this condition have previously been reported by this group<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0363546512461903">20</xref></sup> and by others at various short-term and medium-term time periods. However, to our knowledge, there are no published results regarding a more distant follow-up interval. This study aims to report on the long-term follow-up of the patients previously reported on by the group led by the senior author (R.D.P.).</p>
<sec id="section7-0363546512461903" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>Institutional review board approval was granted for this study. The initial 4 patients from the previous study were contacted for reevaluation, and informed consent was obtained in each case. A 1-time stipend was paid to each patient for participation in this study. The previous testing protocol was then followed. Clinical interview and physical examination were performed by 1 physician assistant who is trained in sports medicine. Clinical outcomes were assessed with the MOS 36-item Short-Form Health Survey (SF-36).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0363546512461903">32</xref></sup> Functional outcomes were assessed with the modified Lysholm knee scoring scale,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0363546512461903">19</xref></sup> International Knee Documentation Committee (IKDC) form,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0363546512461903">11</xref></sup> and the Tegner activity score.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0363546512461903">28</xref></sup></p>
<p>Patients underwent functional testing with the KT-1000 arthrometer (MEDmetric, San Diego, California) and Biodex (Lumex Corp, Ronkonkoma, New York) isokinetic strength evaluation of quadriceps and hamstrings at 60 and 240 deg/sec. They also underwent performance testing by single-legged hop and vertical jump tests.</p>
<p>Imaging studies consisted of a series of radiographs including standing AP radiograph at 0° of extension, lateral, 45° of flexion posteroanterior weightbearing, and axial Merchant patellar views. The affected knees then underwent magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scanning with a 3-T magnet (Verio, Siemens Medical Systems, Erlangen, Germany). All patients had the following MRI acquisitions: coronal and sagittal fast spin echo (FSE) fat-saturated proton density-weighted, sagittal and axial fat-saturated FSE T2-weighted, and sagittal FSE T2-weighted and coronal FSE T1-weighted. Kellgren and Lawrence grade and a modified Osteoarthritis Research Society International (OARSI) grade were used to evaluate radiographic changes and to subsequently characterize OA progression on all available radiographs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0363546512461903">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0363546512461903">16</xref></sup> To score knee cartilage loss on MRI, the Boston-Leeds Osteoarthritis Knee Score (BLOKS) was used.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0363546512461903">13</xref></sup> All radiographs and MRI examinations were retrospectively reviewed independently by 2 musculoskeletal radiologists. Disagreements were resolved by consensus.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0363546512461903" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section9-0363546512461903">
<title>Summary of Initial Publication</title>
<p>Four of 831 patients who underwent arthroscopically guided ACL reconstructions performed by 1 surgeon between 1987 and 1998 developed septic arthritis postoperatively. The patients were all male, with an average age of 26 years (range, 20-34) at the time of diagnosis, and each patient was involved in either recreational or competitive sports on a regular basis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0363546512461903">20</xref></sup></p>
<p>Patient 1 sustained his knee injury during a noncontact moment in a baseball game. He was 28 years old at the time of this surgery, which consisted of an arthroscopically assisted ACL reconstruction that entailed hamstrings tendon autograft and medial meniscus repair. He had no history of prior knee surgery.</p>
<p>Patient 2 sustained his knee injury when he was impacted by another player in a football game. He was 20 years old at the time of this surgery, which consisted of arthroscopically assisted ACL reconstruction with bone–patellar tendon–bone (B-PT-B) autograft and medial meniscectomy. He had previously undergone an arthroscopic medial meniscectomy on the affected knee.</p>
<p>Patient 3 sustained his knee injury during a collision in a soccer game. He was 34 years old at the time of this surgery, which consisted of arthroscopically assisted ACL reconstruction with B-PT-B autograft. He had previously undergone an open partial medial meniscectomy on the affected knee.</p>
<p>Patient 4 had a history of open ACL reconstruction with arthrotomy on his affected knee that preceded this event. He had returned to sports and reinjured this knee during a collision in a wrestling match. He was 22 years old at the time of this revision surgery, which consisted of arthroscopically assisted revision ACL reconstruction that entailed B-PT-B autograft and medial meniscus repair.</p>
<p>Each patient received a diagnosis of septic arthritis within 24 hours of symptom onset, with an average presentation at 11.25 days after ACL reconstruction (range, 8-18 days). At the time of initial diagnosis of infection, all patients immediately underwent arthroscopic lavage with open wound debridement and partial synovectomy. Synovial fluid cultures grew methicillin-sensitive <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in all 4 patients. In each case, the ACL graft was determined to be intact and was retained. Each wound was packed, loosely closed over drains, and later repaired.</p>
<p>The average number of surgical procedures aimed at treating the initial infection at the time of the initial publication was 2.75 (range, 2-4). All 4 patients underwent a course of intravenous antibiotics (average, 4.75 weeks) followed by oral antibiotics (average, 3 weeks). Physical therapy was started postoperatively in all cases. While the patient was still in the hospital, physical therapy consisted of continuous passive motion; this was followed by outpatient therapy with toe-touch weightbearing in an unlocked hinged knee brace for the first 6 weeks. Three of the 4 patients (Nos. 1, 2, and 3) underwent subsequent hardware removal with negative cultures taken at the time. In 2 patients (Nos. 1 and 2), additional arthroscopic procedures were performed to address stiffness and arthrofibrosis.</p>
<p>For the previous study, these patients were reassessed at an average of 36 months (range, 28-42) after the initial diagnosis, and their clinical, functional, and subjective outcomes were reported. Of note, MRI scans for this study used 1- and 1.5-T magnets.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0363546512461903">
<title>New Results</title>
<p>The average patient age at the time of this study was 44.3 years (range, 37-53). The average interval between the index ACL reconstruction and this study was 17.9 years (range, 17.1-18.6). None of the patients had undergone any surgery on their knee since the time of the previous publication. The average time from the patients’ last surgery to this study was 17.2 years (range, 16.4-18.2).</p>
<p>The SF-36 Health Survey results indicated that each patient had experienced a decline in physical function, role physical, and bodily pain scoring (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0363546512461903">Table 1</xref>). Respectively, the average decline in points for each category was 44.7 (range, 26.1-56.9), 47.6 (range, 43.1-55.4), and 33.2 (range, 19.9-51.1). The average IKDC score was 58.9 (range, 37.9-74.7), with all patients demonstrating abnormal to severely abnormal results. This is lower than the average IKDC score of 64 reported in the previous study. The raw individual IKDC scores from the time of the initial publication were unavailable for comparison; however, it was reported that the final ratings of 3 of the 4 patients were abnormal and that the rating for 1 patient was severely abnormal (No. 4). In the current study, the average modified Lysholm knee score was 69.5 points (range, 60-84 of 100), which is nearly 9 points lower than reported in the previous study (average, 78.25 points; range, 73-88 points). The average Tegner activity score, in contrast, was unchanged from the score reported in the previous study (5.25; range, 3-7), with 2 patients (Nos. 2 and 4) having an increased score and 2 patients (Nos. 1 and 3) having a decreased score from that time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0363546512461903">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0363546512461903" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption><p>SF-36 Scores From Previous and Current Studies</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0363546512461903" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512461903-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Physical Function<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Role Physical<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Bodily Pain<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Initial</th>
<th align="center">Current</th>
<th align="center">Initial</th>
<th align="center">Current</th>
<th align="center">Initial</th>
<th align="center">Current</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Patient 1</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>33.9</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>44.6</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>42.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient 2</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>50.7</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>56.9</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>62.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient 3</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>38.1</td>
<td>93</td>
<td>49.5</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>41.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient 4</td>
<td>91</td>
<td>44.4</td>
<td>76</td>
<td>27.5</td>
<td>71</td>
<td>19.9</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig1-0363546512461903" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Preinjury, initial study, and current Tegner activity scores.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512461903-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>At the time of this study, all of the patients held relatively sedentary occupations, with 3 patients (Nos. 1, 2, and 4) holding sales jobs and 1 patient (No. 3) working as a teacher. Patients 1 and 2 reported that they continued to engage in some form of regular athletic activity, whereas patients 3 and 4 denied any participation in sports at this time. Regardless of their current level of activity, each patient reported that he was aware of his knee problems on at least a daily basis, and all had modified their lifestyles to avoid having issues with their knees. There were no reported incidents of reinjury in the interval between these 2 studies.</p>
<p>Physical examination of each patient did not reveal any chronic surgical wound issues. In all patients, the average active and passive range of motion arcs were slightly diminished on the surgical knee. Actively, the affected knees lacked an average of 12.5° of flexion (range, 6°-25°). There was an average deficit of passive motion of 12° of flexion (range, 3°-22°). Only 1 patient (No. 4) had a deficit of active and passive extension, measured at 3° and 1°, respectively. Pivot shift was negative in 2 of 4 patients and was weakly positive for a pivot glide in 2 patients (Nos. 3 and 4). Patellofemoral crepitus was noted in the operative knee of each patient. Crepitus was also noted in 2 of 4 patients during passive testing of each the medial and lateral compartments. Each patient denied any problematic or painful joints apart from the location of their operation. Only 1 patient (No. 2) currently used a brace during athletic activity.</p>
<p>KT-1000 arthrometer testing demonstrated that the average side-to-side difference of maximum manual displacement increased from 1.75 mm in the previous study to 4.6 mm in the current study (range, 2.5-7 mm). Performance testing with the single-legged hop test was performed in 3 of the 4 patients and was halted in 1 patient (No. 3), who exhibited poor control because of an exacerbation of his chronic low back pain. Results of single-legged hop tests in the affected leg were nearly identical to those in the unaffected leg in 2 patients (Nos. 1 and 4) and were substantially diminished in 1 patient (No. 2). In patients 1 and 4, the affected limb achieved a single-legged hop horizontal distance of 96.4% and 98.2% and a vertical distance of 96.6% and 89.1% of the uninjured leg, respectively. Patient 2 achieved a single-legged hop horizontal distance of 65.5% and a vertical distance of 49% of the unaffected leg. At the time of the previous study, the average single-legged hop horizontal and vertical distances were 81% and 89%, respectively, of the contralateral limb (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0363546512461903">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0363546512461903" position="float">
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption><p>Functional and Performance Test Results</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0363546512461903" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512461903-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Isokinetic Strength Evaluation: Quadriceps, %<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0363546512461903"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup><hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Isokinetic Strength Evaluation: Hamstrings, %<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0363546512461903"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup><hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Single-Legged Hop Test, %<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0363546512461903"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup><hr/></th>
<th align="center">KT-1000 Arthrometer</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Low Speed (60 deg/sec)</th>
<th align="center">High Speed (240 deg/sec)</th>
<th align="center">Low Speed (60 deg/sec)</th>
<th align="center">High Speed (240 deg/sec)</th>
<th align="center">Distance</th>
<th align="center">Vertical</th>
<th align="center">Side-to-Side Difference, mm</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Patient 1</td>
<td>−10.00</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>−19.70</td>
<td>−17.10</td>
<td>96.40</td>
<td>96.60</td>
<td>3.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient 2</td>
<td>−32.10</td>
<td>−20.80</td>
<td>3.30</td>
<td>18.20</td>
<td>65.50</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>5.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient 3<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0363546512461903"><italic>b</italic></xref></sup></td>
<td>−4.60</td>
<td>45.00</td>
<td>32.30</td>
<td>60.90</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>7.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient 4</td>
<td>−14.20</td>
<td>−28.20</td>
<td>−7.20</td>
<td>−0.50</td>
<td>98.20</td>
<td>89.10</td>
<td>2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average</td>
<td>−15.20</td>
<td>−0.63</td>
<td>2.18</td>
<td>15.38</td>
<td>86.70</td>
<td>78.20</td>
<td>4.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Previous study average (range)</td>
<td align="center">−27 (−17 to −30)</td>
<td align="center">−13 (−13 to −20)</td>
<td align="center">−4 (−4 to −31)</td>
<td align="center">8 (9 to −16)</td>
<td align="center">81</td>
<td align="center">89</td>
<td align="center">1.75 (0-3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Change from previous study</td>
<td>11.80</td>
<td>12.37</td>
<td>6.18</td>
<td>7.38</td>
<td>5.70</td>
<td>−10.80</td>
<td>2.85</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0363546512461903">
<label>a</label>
<p>Expressed as percentage of uninjured limb.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0363546512461903">
<label>b</label>
<p>Patient was unable to complete hop test because of back pain.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Testing with a Biodex dynamometer demonstrated that the average deficit of peak torque achieved by the quadriceps at low speed (60 deg/sec) was −15.2% (range, −4.6% to −32.1%). At high speed (240 deg/sec) there was an average deficit of −0.63% in peak torque, with 2 patients showing an increase (No. 1, 1.5%; No. 3, 45%) and 2 patients showing a deficit (No. 2, −20.8%; No. 4, −28.2%). In the previous study, average deficits of −27% at low speed and −13% at high speed were reported. In the current study, 2 patients (Nos. 1 and 4) showed a deficit in isokinetic testing of hamstrings muscle power at both low and high speeds when compared with the opposite leg, and the other 2 patients (Nos. 2 and 3) showed an increase. On average, the increases in hamstring power were 2.2% at low speed and 15.4% at high speed. Hamstring testing in the previous study was similarly varied, with deficits at low speed ranging from −4% to −31% and from 9% to −16% at high speed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0363546512461903">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<p>Patients 1, 2, and 3 had historical radiographs available for comparison, and historical MRIs were available for all patients. In each case, when these scans were compared with earlier ones, there was evidence of progression of cartilage loss on MRI and arthritic changes on radiographs. Based on the Kellgren and Lawrence classification, all 4 patients had at least some radiographic evidence of osteoarthritis in more than 1 knee compartment, and in all except 1 patient (No. 4), there was tricompartmental involvement. In patients 1, 3, and 4, the ACL graft was intact on MRI, whereas patient 2 had evidence of graft rupture. Meniscus abnormality was noted on MRI in all patients, with 2 having isolated medial meniscus tears (Nos. 3 and 4) and 2 having tears of both menisci (Nos. 1 and 2). These findings are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0363546512461903">Table 3</xref>, and current radiographs for each patient are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0363546512461903">Figures 2</xref> through <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0363546512461903">5</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0363546512461903" position="float">
<label>Table 3</label>
<caption><p>Radiographic and Magnetic Resonance Imaging Findings</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0363546512461903" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512461903-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Kellgren and Lawrence <sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0363546512461903"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup> and OARSI<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0363546512461903"><italic>b</italic></xref></sup><hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">MRI BLOK<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0363546512461903"><italic>c</italic></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0363546512461903"><italic>d</italic></xref></sup><hr/></th>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Meniscus Tear?<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Medial</th>
<th align="center">Lateral</th>
<th align="center">Patellofemoral</th>
<th align="center">Tibia (Medial, Lateral)</th>
<th align="center">Femur<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0363546512461903"><italic>e</italic></xref></sup> (Medial, Lateral)</th>
<th align="center">Patella (Medial, Lateral)</th>
<th align="center">ACL Intact?</th>
<th align="center">Medial</th>
<th align="center">Lateral</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Patient 1</td>
<td>3+</td>
<td>3+</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2b, 2c</td>
<td>2c, 2c</td>
<td>3d, 2c</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient 2</td>
<td>4+</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3c, 3c</td>
<td>2c, 3c</td>
<td>1a, 1a</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient 3</td>
<td>2+</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2b, 1b</td>
<td>2b, 2b</td>
<td>1b, 1a</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient 4</td>
<td>3+</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2b, 1a</td>
<td>2b, 1a</td>
<td>1a, 0a</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0363546512461903">
<label>a</label>
<p>Kellgren and Lawrence Arthritis Severity Scale<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0363546512461903">16</xref></sup>: 0 = none, 1 = doubtful, 2 = minimal, 3 = moderate, 4 = severe.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0363546512461903">
<label>b</label>
<p>Joint narrowing on Osteoarthritis Research Society International (OARSI) scale.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0363546512461903">2</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0363546512461903">
<label>c</label>
<p>MRI Boston-Leeds Osteoarthritis Knee Score (BLOKS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0363546512461903">13</xref></sup> Percentage of Surface Cartilage Loss Scale: 0 = none, 1 = &lt;10%, 2 = 10%-75%, 3 = &gt;75%.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0363546512461903">
<label>d</label>
<p>MRI BLOKS Percentage of Surface Full-Thickness Cartilage Loss Scale: a = none, b = &lt;10%, c = 10-75%, d = &gt;75%.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-0363546512461903">
<label>e</label>
<p>Weightbearing surface.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig2-0363546512461903" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption><p>Radiograph showing posteroanterior weightbearing for patient 1 at 45° of flexion.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512461903-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-0363546512461903" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption><p>Radiograph showing posteroanterior weightbearing for patient 2 at 45° of flexion.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512461903-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-0363546512461903" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption><p>Radiograph showing posteroanterior weightbearing for patient 3 at 45° of flexion.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512461903-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig5-0363546512461903" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption><p>Radiograph showing posteroanterior weightbearing for patient 4 at 45° of flexion.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512461903-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0363546512461903" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Although septic arthritis is relatively rare, it is an established and potentially devastating complication of arthroscopically assisted ACL reconstruction surgery. Several studies have illustrated diminished short-term outcomes and others have reported only minimal negative findings. To our knowledge there have been no reports of longer term follow-up of this entity.</p>
<p>From the time of the previous follow-up at 3 years after treatment, study patients demonstrated many changes in both the subjective and objective outcomes of this group. Although the results varied across patients, there were several aspects of individual patients’ current levels of function that were improved when compared with the previous study, such as the average single-legged hop and isokinetic muscle test results. This suggests that over time, patients may continue to build strength and learn to compensate for their previous deficits. This is also evidenced by the unchanged average Tegner score compared with the score at the time of the initial study. Activity level remained stable, but declines were seen in the Lysholm, IKDC, and SF-36 scores, likely as a result of the patients’ development of symptomatic arthritis. Although each patient did report pain, stiffness, and swelling, physical examination demonstrated only minimal instances of laxity and a slight deficit in average flexion compared with the previous study. There were no complaints of symptomatic instability.</p>
<p>When compared with patients in other studies of long-term (&gt;10 y) outcomes after ACL reconstructions reported in the literature who did not experience septic arthritis,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0363546512461903">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546512461903">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0363546512461903">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0363546512461903"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0363546512461903">24</xref></sup> our group had results that were either comparable or inferior in most measured categories. The average Lysholm scores reported in the above-cited studies were in the good (range, 84-100) or excellent (range, 95-100) categories. These are superior to our group, where the average Lysholm score was 69.5, which would be considered fair (range, 65-83), with a breakdown of our patient scores being 1 good (No. 4), 2 fair (Nos. 1 and 3), and 1 poor (No. 2). The study by Sajovic et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0363546512461903">24</xref></sup> was the only one of the above-cited studies to report average SF-36 scores that were slightly higher than those we observed in our patients in all 3 categories measured in this study. Similarly, the IKDC scores in previous studies were higher in patients who did not have septic complications<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0363546512461903">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0363546512461903">24</xref></sup> than in our group. Despite these results, the median Tegner scores reported by Oiestad et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0363546512461903">22</xref></sup> were slightly inferior to our group’s average score (4 vs 5.25).</p>
<p>The KT-1000 arthrometer testing in our group revealed a higher average maximal side-to-side displacement of 4.6 mm, whereas the majority of such measurements reported in the other studies were less than 3 mm. Isokinetic muscle testing and hop tests revealed a similar pattern to those reported by Oiestad et al,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0363546512461903">22</xref></sup> with slight average improvements noted with increased follow-up time. Imaging studies in our patients also coincided with the high prevalence of operative knee arthritis that was reported in the studies of nonseptic ACL reconstruction patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0363546512461903">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546512461903">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0363546512461903">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0363546512461903">24</xref></sup> All of the patients in our study had both plain film and MRI evidence of extensive arthritic changes throughout the knee joint, as well as degenerative changes of either 1 or both menisci. Although no patient in our group had less than level 2+ changes on the Kellgren and Lawrence scale, our small sample size was not sufficiently powered to compare the severity of our patients’ arthritis to arthritis severity in other studies.</p>
<p>Diminished subjective findings persisted when our group was compared with a cohort of 488 nonsurgical patients who were considered to have “normal” knees (average age, 41 years).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0363546512461903">5</xref></sup> These patients had an average Tegner score of 6 and an average Lysholm score of 94. Although both of these scores were superior to those of our patients, this difference in Tegner scores does not persist after age-matching, which indicates that our patients did return to a comparable level of activity despite their ACL abnormality.</p>
<p>In each of our patients, the decision was made to retain the ACL graft. Several studies have investigated the outcomes of ACL graft retention in patients with septic arthritis and have indicated that these patients often have more favorable outcomes compared with those who have had the graft removed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0363546512461903">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0363546512461903">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0363546512461903">33</xref></sup> This may be in part because untreated ACL deficiency has been associated with an increased sensation of instability as well as higher rates of meniscus abnormality and accelerated onset of arthritis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0363546512461903">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0363546512461903">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0363546512461903">18</xref></sup> At the time of this study, 1 patient in our group (No. 2) had MRI evidence of graft deficiency, but this did not correlate with his physical examination or KT-1000 arthrometer testing results. This patient had the most severe arthritis of the group as well as inferior results on isokinetic and hop testing; however, he reported no feelings of instability on his questionnaires and believed that the majority of his deficits were the result of pain. This was the most substantial complaint of all 4 patients, including the 2 patients (Nos. 3 and 4) with positive pivot glide and slightly increased laxity with Lachman testing on examination. Only patient 1 reported feelings of instability, although he described these feelings as rare and asymptomatic, and his physical examination was unremarkable in this regard. It is possible that these discrepancies among MRI findings, symptoms, and physical examination results were caused by an ankylosing-like effect of chronic arthritis and compensated neuromuscular control.</p>
<p>Although it is difficult to draw any overwhelming or generalizable conclusions from this small group, the long-term outcomes appear to be similar to reports of other patients who have been treated for septic arthritis of the knee as a complication of arthroscopy, without unique characteristics reflecting that our group all initially underwent ACL reconstructions. Late-term ACL graft rupture, although apparent in 1 of 4 patients, did not result in any symptomatic instability, which would support either the patient’s ability to compensate over time or the ankylosing effects of severe arthritis. The lack of complaints regarding instability from our patients lends support to graft retention when possible. Although each patient had diminished subjective outcomes, the predominant symptoms were related to knee pain, likely related to the significant chondral and meniscal lesions. Although the development of arthritis is frequently seen in those who have undergone an uncomplicated ACL reconstruction and after meniscectomy, arthritis is likely more advanced in our patients as a sequela of their septic arthritis. As a result, the diminished outcomes of these patients compared with those in other long-term follow-ups of ACL reconstructions are likely due to the severity of their arthritis. However, given our small sample size and lack of internal controls, we cannot lend statistical significance to this claim, and further research is warranted in this regard.</p>
<p>Although there are few published data on long-term outcomes of young, athletic patients treated for septic arthritis after arthroscopic surgery, our findings suggest that when the infection is eradicated with prompt surgical and antibiotic treatment, there is still an accelerated rate of symptomatic chondral injury. Despite this subjective decline, if adequately treated these patients can potentially show improvement in objective physical function testing and maintenance of activity level over time.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>One or more of the authors has declared the following potential conflict of interest or source of funding: Funding for this study was obtained through a grant from the National Football League Charities.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0363546512461903">
<label>‖</label>
<p>References <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546512461903">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546512461903">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0363546512461903">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0363546512461903">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0363546512461903">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0363546512461903">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0363546512461903">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0363546512461903">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0363546512461903">29</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0363546512461903"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0363546512461903">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0363546512461903">33</xref>.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0363546512461903">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aichroth</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zorrilla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The natural history and treatment of rupture of the anterior cruciate ligament in children and adolescents: a prospective review</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>38</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0363546512461903">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Atlas of individual radiographic features in osteoarthritis, revised</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthritis Cartilage</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<supplement>suppl A</supplement>):<fpage>A1</fpage>-<lpage>A56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0363546512461903">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Balabaud</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gaudias</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boeri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jenny</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kehr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Results of treatment of septic knee arthritis: a retrospective series of 40 cases</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>387</fpage>-<lpage>392</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0363546512461903">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Binnet</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Basarir</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Risk and outcome of infection after different arthroscopic anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction techniques</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>862</fpage>-<lpage>868</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0363546512461903">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steadman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hines</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Lysholm score and Tegner activity level in individuals with normal knees</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>898</fpage>-<lpage>901</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0363546512461903">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burks</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Friederichs</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Treatment of postoperative anterior cruciate ligament infections with graft removal and early reimplantation</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>414</fpage>-<lpage>418</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0363546512461903">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Septic arthritis after arthroscopic anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction</article-title>. <source>Ann Acad Med Singapore</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>228</fpage>-<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0363546512461903">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gillquist</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Messner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction and the long-term incidence of gonarthrosis</article-title>. <source>Sports Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>143</fpage>-<lpage>156</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0363546512461903">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fujisaki</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Landry</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saluja</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Anterior cruciate ligament tears in skeletally immature patients: meniscal pathology at presentation and after attempted conservative treatment</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>233</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0363546512461903">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hanypsiak</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spindler</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rothrock</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Twelve-year follow-up on anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: long-term outcomes of prospectively studied osseous and articular injuries</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>671</fpage>-<lpage>677</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0363546512461903">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hefti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jakob</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Staubli</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of knee ligament injuries with the IKDC form</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>3-4</issue>):<fpage>226</fpage>-<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0363546512461903">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oiestad</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Risberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aune</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>No difference in knee function or prevalence of osteoarthritis after reconstruction of the anterior cruciate ligament with 4-strand hamstring autograft versus patellar tendon-bone autograft: a randomized study with 10-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>448</fpage>-<lpage>454</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0363546512461903">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The reliability of a new scoring system for knee osteoarthritis MRI and the validity of bone marrow lesion assessment: BLOKS (Boston Leeds Osteoarthritis Knee Score)</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>206</fpage>-<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0363546512461903">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Indelli</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dillingham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fanton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schurman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Septic arthritis in postoperative anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>398</volume>:<fpage>182</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0363546512461903">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Judd</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bottoni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hooker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Infections following arthroscopic anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>375</fpage>-<lpage>384</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0363546512461903">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kellgren</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Radiological assessment of osteo-arthrosis</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>. <year>1957</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>494</fpage>-<lpage>502</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0363546512461903">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Treatment of septic knee arthritis: comparison of arthroscopic debridement alone or combined with continuous closed irrigation-suction system</article-title>. <source>J Trauma</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>454</fpage>-<lpage>459</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0363546512461903">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lohmander</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Englund</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The long-term consequence of anterior cruciate ligament and meniscus injuries: osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1756</fpage>-<lpage>1769</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0363546512461903">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lysholm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gillquist</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of knee ligament surgery results with special emphasis on use of a scoring scale</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>150</fpage>-<lpage>154</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0363546512461903">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McAllister</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Recht</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Outcomes of postoperative septic arthritis after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>562</fpage>-<lpage>570</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0363546512461903">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mouzopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fotopoulos</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tzurbakis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Septic knee arthritis following ACL reconstruction: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1033</fpage>-<lpage>1042</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0363546512461903">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oiestad</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aune</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Knee function and prevalence of knee osteoarthritis after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a prospective study with 10 to 15 years of follow-up</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2201</fpage>-<lpage>2210</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0363546512461903">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pinczewski</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lyman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A 10-year comparison of anterior cruciate ligament reconstructions with hamstring tendon and patellar tendon autograft: a controlled, prospective trial</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>564</fpage>-<lpage>574</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0363546512461903">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sajovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strahovnik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dernovsek</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skaza</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Quality of life and clinical outcome comparison of semitendinosus and gracilis tendon versus patellar tendon autografts for anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: an 11-year follow-up of a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2161</fpage>-<lpage>2169</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0363546512461903">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schollin-Borg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Michaelsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rahme</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Presentation, outcome, and cause of septic arthritis after anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a case control study</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>941</fpage>-<lpage>947</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0363546512461903">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gotze</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jurgens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Faschingbauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Septic arthritis of the knee after anterior cruciate ligament surgery: a stage-adapted treatment regimen</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1064</fpage>-<lpage>1069</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0363546512461903">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Studahl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalebo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Septic arthritis of the knee: a 10-year review and long-term follow-up using a new scoring system</article-title>. <source>Scand J Infect Dis</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0363546512461903">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tegner</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lysholm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rating systems in the evaluation of knee ligament injuries</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>198</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0363546512461903">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Van Tongel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stuyck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bellemans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vandenneucker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Septic arthritis after arthroscopic anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a retrospective analysis of incidence, management and outcome</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1059</fpage>-<lpage>1063</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0363546512461903">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Viola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marzano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vianello</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An unusual epidemic of Staphylococcus-negative infections involving anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction with salvage of the graft and function</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>173</fpage>-<lpage>177</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0363546512461903">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Septic arthritis after arthroscopic anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a retrospective analysis of incidence, presentation, treatment, and cause</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>243</fpage>-<lpage>249</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0363546512461903">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>The SF-36 Health Survey Manual and Interpretation Guide</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nimrod Press</publisher-name>, <year>1993</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0363546512461903">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Laurencin</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Septic arthritis after arthroscopic anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction. Diagnosis and management</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>261</fpage>-<lpage>267</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>