<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OPP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spopp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Oncol Pharm Pract</journal-id>
    <journal-title>Journal of Oncology Pharmacy Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1078-1552</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-092X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1078155212455445</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1078155212455445</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Isolated hypomagnesemia in a patient treated with capecitabine</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Rajapakse</surname><given-names>Senaka</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1078155212455445"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1078155212455445">Department of Clinical Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Colombo, Sri Lanka</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>Chaturaka</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-1078155212455445">Department of Clinical Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Colombo, Sri Lanka</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Rajapakse</surname><given-names>Anoja C</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff3-1078155212455445">Kings Mill Hospital, Sherwood Forest NHS Foundation Trust, Sutton-in-Ashfield, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1078155212455445">Senaka Rajapakse, Department of Clinical Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Colombo, 25 Kynsey Road, Colombo 08, Sri Lanka. Email: <email>senaka.ucfm@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>254</fpage>
<lpage>256</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Hypomagnesemia is known to occur for a variety of renal, gastrointestinal and other causes, and is often associated with other electrolyte and metabolic disturbances. We present a case of isolated hypomagnesemia in a patient who had been treated with the chemotherapy agent capecitabine. The approach to diagnosis and treatment is discussed. We postulate that capecitabine may cause isolated hypomagnesemia, possibly due to renal magnesium loss.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Hypomagnesemia</kwd>
<kwd>capecitabine</kwd>
<kwd>electrolyte disturbance</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1078155212455445" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Low serum magnesium levels occur in about 12% of hospitalized patients, and can be as frequent as 60% in patients receiving critical care.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1078155212455445">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1078155212455445">2</xref></sup> Many patients with hypomagnesemia are asymptomatic, or have non-specific symptoms; however, serious complications such as ventricular arrhythmias are known to occur.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1078155212455445">3</xref></sup> Capecitabine is an antimetabolite belonging to the novel fluoropyrimidine carbamate class, and has been reported to cause hypokalemia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1078155212455445">4</xref></sup> Hypomagnesemia has been reported with certain anti-cancer drugs,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1078155212455445">5</xref></sup> although we could find no reported cases of hypomagnesemia with capecitabine. We present a case of isolated hypomagnesemia likely to be due to capecitabine, and discuss the approach towards diagnosis and treatment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1078155212455445"><title>Case</title>
<p>A 55-year-old woman with a history of breast cancer treated with surgery followed by chemotherapy with capecitabine 2 months earlier was referred to the acute medical clinic because she was found to have persistently low serum magnesium levels by her general practitioner. She complained of general weakness and episodic dizziness, but did not report palpitations or seizures. She had no diarrhea or polyuria, and was on no medications. She had no other significant medical history, and was on no concomitant medications or herbal preparations. Clinical examination was unremarkable.</p>
<p>At the time of first review in the acute medical clinic (i.e. 2 months after completing chemotherapy), her serum magnesium was 0.55 mEq/L (NR 0.7–1.0). Other investigations were as follows: sodium 145 mEq/L, potassium 4.5 mEq/L, urea 3.0 mmol/L, creatinine 55 µmol/L, eGFR &gt; 90 mL/min, calcium 2.36 mmol/L (adjusted 2.38), phosphate 1.32 mmol/L. Full blood count, liver function and thyroid function tests were normal. PTH assay was normal. The 24-hour urinary magnesium excretion was high, but 24-hour urinary calcium excretion was normal. Magnesium levels had not been performed during capecitabine treatment, but had been normal prior to the commencement of treatment for breast cancer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1078155212455445" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>Hypomagnesemia is defined as a serum magnesium concentration below 0.7 mEq/L (normal range 0.7–1.2 mEq/L).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1078155212455445">3</xref></sup> Most patients with hypomagnesemia have no symptoms. Symptoms usually occur when the serum magnesium level drops below 0.5 mmol/L. Severe hypomagnesemia is often associated with other biochemical abnormalities such as hypokalaemia, hypocalcaemia and metabolic alkalosis, thus making it difficult to determine whether these clinical manifestations are entirely due to hypomagnesemia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1078155212455445">6</xref></sup> The following are commonly reported clinical features of hypomagnesemia:
<list id="list1-1078155212455445" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>muscle weakness, neuromuscular irritability (positive Chvostek sign and Trousseau sign), tetany.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1078155212455445">7</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>seizures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1078155212455445">8</xref></sup></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>ventricular arrhythmias (palpitations, transient loss of consciousness). The risk of ventricular arrhythmias is increased in patients with cardiac disease, especially myocardial infarction.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1078155212455445">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1078155212455445">10</xref></sup> Whether hypomagnesemia causes arrhythmias in individuals with no cardiac disease is controversial. Ventricular arrhythmias are the most serious complication of hypomagnesemia.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>The etiology of hypomagnesemia falls into one of three categories: renal loss of magnesium, which could be primary or secondary, gastrointestinal loss of magnesium (magnesium is absorbed mainly in the small bowel), and other miscellaneous causes. Many drugs are suggested to cause hypomagnesemia, through varying mechanisms: thiazides and loop diuretics, aminoglycosides, proton pump inhibitors, cyclosporine, pentamidine, amphotericin B, and chemotherapy agents (cisplatin). The mechanism through which drugs cause hypomagnesemia are variable. Drugs that cause vomiting or diarrhea can result in gastrointestinal magnesium loss. Certain drugs may have a direct effect on the renal tubules, resulting in increased renal magnesium loss.</p>
<p>A systematic approach helps to identify the cause of hypomagnesemia in many instances. Our patient had no gastrointestinal symptoms, i.e. diarrhea, features of malabsorption (steatorrhea), or vomiting. She had not had radiotherapy. She was on a normal diet. Dietary magnesium deficiency is unlikely in patients having a normal diet (dietary sources include green vegetables, fruits, fresh meat, fish and cereal). Alcoholics often have low magnesium levels due to nutritional deficiency. In both alcoholics and diabetics, in addition to nutritional deficiency, osmotic diuresis due to alcohol and glucose respectively increases renal magnesium loss. Our patient did not drink alcohol, and was not diabetic. She had no renal symptoms such as polyuria, frothy urine, hematuria, or any other features of chronic renal disease or urinary tract obstruction. She had no features of hyperthyroidism, hyperparathyroidism or primary aldosteronism; these endocrine abnormalities can cause renal potassium wasting and, potentially, magnesium wasting.</p>
<p>Standard investigations for evaluation of hypomagnesemia include urinary magnesium, serum creatinine, urea and electrolytes, urine creatinine, calcium, phosphate, serum proteins, liver function, thyroid function, blood glucose. Blood calcium levels maybe low in severe hypomagnesemia, and this is associated with low parathyroid hormone levels, which contribute to hypocalcaemia. Hypomagnesemia also results in PTH resistance, resulting in reduced release of calcium from bone, and hence we performed PTH levels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1078155212455445">3</xref></sup> However, these investigations were entirely normal in our patient. Records showed that her magnesium levels prior to commencement of chemotherapy were normal. The ECG may show a variety of changes in hypomagnesemia: tall, peaked T waves; flat T waves or depression in the precordium; U waves; ST depression, low voltage complexes, PR prolongation; and widened QRS. Arrhythmias may be detected on continuous ECG monitoring. Our patients 12-lead ECG was normal, and there was no indication for 24 ECG monitoring.</p>
<p>We calculated the fractional excretion of magnesium (FEMg). This is calculated from spot values of blood and urine magnesium and creatinine, using the following formula
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1078155212455445">
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math1-1078155212455445"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>FEMg</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>urine magnesium</mml:mtext><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mtext>serum creatinine</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>serum magnesium</mml:mtext><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mtext>urine creatinine</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>1 00</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-1078155212455445" xlink:href="10.1177_1078155212455445-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>FEMg over 4% suggests renal potassium loss, while FEMg below 2% suggests gastrointestinal loss or other causes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1078155212455445">11</xref></sup> If the FEMg is high, then further investigations may be needed to elucidate a cause. The urinary Ca/Cr ratio is of some use; a ratio &lt;0.3 suggests diuretic use or Gitelman syndrome.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1078155212455445">12</xref></sup> This patient’s FEMg was over 4%, suggesting renal loss of magnesium.</p>
<p>We postulate that capecitabine was the cause of her isolated hypomagnesemia, despite this being stopped 2 months ago. Hypokalaemia has been reported as a side effect of capecitabine, and is mentioned as a side-effect on the product insert. Saif et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1078155212455445">4</xref></sup> in a retrospective case series of patients treated with capecitabine for gastrointestinal malignancy, demonstrated isolated hypokalaemia in patients who had no diarrhea and were not on diuretics. It was been postulated that hypokalaemia occurred in these cases due to direct effects on the renal tubules. A similar phenomenon occurs with cisplatin, which causes renal potassium and magnesium wasting.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1078155212455445">5</xref></sup> We postulate that a similar effect on the renal tubules could result in hypomagnesemia with capecitabine. In a phase II study of capecitabine, oxaliplatin and cetuximab for advanced hepatocellular cancer, hypomagnesemia was observed in 41% of patients, though it was not possible to determine which agent was primarily responsible for this.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1078155212455445">13</xref></sup> We could not find any data comparing the incidence of hypomagnesemia in patients treated with capecitabine versus other anti-cancer drugs.</p>
<p>Treatment of hypomagnesemia is based on withdrawing drugs which can cause magnesium deficiency, and magnesium replacement. In symptomatic and severe hypomagnesemia (neuromuscular manifestations, arrhythmias) magnesium should be replaced intravenously. Such patients will typically need hospital admission. A dose 50 mEq of IV magnesium is given slowly over 8–24 h. The dose can be repeated to maintain plasma magnesium concentration above 0.8 mEq/L. Magnesium replacement should be done slowly, because a rapid rise in plasma magnesium concentration will result in an increase in magnesium excretion, without allowing for sufficient repletion of total body magnesium depletion. Magnesium should never be given as IV bolus therapy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1078155212455445">3</xref></sup> Asymptomatic patients should be given slow release magnesium oral tablets. There are several preparations of Magnesium tablets available. Magnesium oxide 400 mg twice or thrice daily will deliver 40–58 mmol of elemental Magnesium per day, and magnesium gluconate 500 mg four times daily will deliver 9–18 mmol of magnesium per day. Magnesium glycerophosphate tablets contain 4mmol of magnesium each. Magnesium containing antacids are poorly absorbed and should not be used to replace magnesium in hypomagnesemia.</p>
<p>Our patient had completed capecitabine treatment at the time of first review, and the drug was not introduced again as there was no oncological indication. She was commenced on oral magnesium replacement, i.e. magnesium glycerophosphate 2 tablets 4 times daily for 4 months, reduced gradually over another 2 months while monitoring magnesium levels. Magnesium levels returned to normal after 6 months and remained normal thereafter.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1078155212455445" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Capecitabine may cause isolated magnesium depletion, possibly through a direct effect on the renal tubules. This side effect has not been reported earlier. This effect may be prolonged, and remain after discontinuation of treatment. Given the potentially serious cardiac effects of hypomagnesemia (especially in patients with pre-existing cardiac disease), magnesium levels should be monitored in patients treated with chemotherapeutic agents such as capecitabine, and magnesium supplementation maybe required if levels are low.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec5-1078155212455445"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1078155212455445"><title>Conflict of interest</title>
<p>No conflicts of interest were declared.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1078155212455445"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Rude</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A high prevalence of hypomagnesemia and hypermagnesemia in hospitalized patients</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Pathol</source> <year>1983</year>; <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>348</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1078155212455445"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chernow</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bamberger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoiko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Hypomagnesemia in patients in postoperative intensive care</article-title>. <source>Chest</source> <year>1989</year>; <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1078155212455445"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agus</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hypomagnesemia</article-title>. <source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1616</fpage>–<lpage>1622</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1078155212455445"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saif</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Fekrazad</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ledbetter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Hypokalemia secondary to capecitabine: a hidden toxicity?</article-title> <source>Ther Clin Risk Manag</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1078155212455445"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Solanki</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Whang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Refractory potassium repletion due to cisplatin-induced magnesium depletion</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source> <year>1989</year>; <volume>149</volume>: <fpage>2592</fpage>–<lpage>2594</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1078155212455445"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Flink</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyckner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Magnesium depletion as a cause of refractory potassium repletion</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source> <year>1985</year>; <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>1686</fpage>–<lpage>1689</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1078155212455445"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vallee</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wacker</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ulmer</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The magnesium-deficiency tetany syndrome in man</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <year>1960</year>; <volume>262</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1078155212455445"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dharnidharka</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carney</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Isolated idiopathic hypomagnesemia presenting as aphasia and seizures</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Neurol</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1078155212455445"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dyckner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Serum magnesium in acute myocardial infarction. Relation to arrhythmias</article-title>. <source>Acta Med Scand</source> <year>1980</year>; <volume>207</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1078155212455445"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dyckner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Relation of cardiovascular disease to potassium and magnesium deficiencies</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source> <year>1990</year>; <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>44 K</fpage>–<lpage>46 K</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1078155212455445"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elisaf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Panteli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Theodorou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fractional excretion of magnesium in normal subjects and in patients with hypomagnesemia</article-title>. <source>Magnes Res</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1078155212455445"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaer</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bia</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gitelman’s syndrome revisited: an evaluation of symptoms and health-related quality of life</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>710</fpage>–<lpage>717</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1078155212455445"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanoff</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phase II study of capecitabine, oxaliplatin, and cetuximab for advanced hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Cancer Res</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>