<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">VCJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spvcj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Visual Communication</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1470-3572</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-3214</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1470357212453978</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1470357212453978</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Looking healthy: visualizing mental health and illness online</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>Riki</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1470357212453978">University of Washington Tacoma, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>395</fpage>
<lpage>420</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s), 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Through a historical case study of the mental health community website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, the author applies social semiotics and critical discourse analysis to interrogate the visual discourse surrounding mental health online. Web design transformations over the course of a decade demonstrate how visual imagery conveys a shift from a biomedical discourse focused on illness to a social-therapeutic discourse centered on health and wellness. Ultimately, the author argues that the utilization of faces in stock photography, stylized images, and social media platforms on HealthyPlace reflects a growing trend in <italic>virtual visual synthetic personalization</italic> on the internet to market mental health disorders as a concern for the everyday person while selling the promise of wellness through online participation. This article explores the visual language of mental health and wellness online to expanding on research in the field of visual communication, health communication, and new media studies.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>critical discourse analysis</kwd>
<kwd>disorder</kwd>
<kwd>image banks</kwd>
<kwd>mental health</kwd>
<kwd>new media</kwd>
<kwd>online communities</kwd>
<kwd>photography</kwd>
<kwd>social semiotics</kwd>
<kwd>websites</kwd>
<kwd>wellness</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In the midst of the battle over health care reform in the US, the subject of mental health reached center stage when the Obama administration extended the Mental Health Parity Act of 1996, issuing a new law requiring insurance companies to equate coverage for mental health disorders with that of standard medical cases. The US Secretary of Labor stated that: ‘The benefits will give these Americans access to greatly needed medical treatment, which will better allow them to participate fully in society’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1470357212453978">HHS, 2010</xref>, 29 January). Policies deeming mental health conditions worthy of as much attention as physical health care concerns point to changes in health discourse. Where conditions of the mind were once treated as insignificant problems, discursive shifts suggest that mental health disorders are increasingly viewed as detrimental to the social order at large.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1470357212453978">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>The narrative of the productive member of society and the imperative to attend to mental health as a path to social participation is a readily reproduced public discourse in many Western societies—and most recently on the internet. The World Health Organization website (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1470357212453978">WHO, 2008</xref>) defines mental health as ‘a state of well-being in which every individual realizes his or her own potential, can cope with the normal stresses of life, can work productively and fruitfully, and is able to make a contribution to her or his community’. Mental illness, conversely, disrupts well-being, hindering an individual’s ability to achieve, deal with the everyday, and participate fully in society.</p>
<p>In the new millennium, the internet has become a significant resource for health information in the lives of millions of people worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1470357212453978">Fox, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1470357212453978">Fox and Jones, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1470357212453978">Lewis, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1470357212453978">Mager, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1470357212453978">Wyatt et al., 2005</xref>). Despite the large numbers of people participating in online support groups and the ubiquity of health information online, research that examines mental health communication and virtual support communities is lacking. Expanding on research in the field of health communication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1470357212453978">Gwyn, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1470357212453978">Segal, 2005</xref>) and visual communication in virtual spaces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1470357212453978">Adami, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1470357212453978">Hohl, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1470357212453978">Killoran, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1470357212453978">Knox, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1470357212453978">Mohammed, 2004</xref>), this article applies social semiotics and critical discourse analysis to interrogate the shifting visual discourse surrounding mental health and wellness online.</p>
<p>A historical analysis of the mental health community website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1470357212453978">1999–2010</xref>) shows how web design and the emergence of new media converge, contributing to shifts in health communication. Web design transformations of HealthyPlace over a decade indicate a trend towards greater use of visual imagery and new media to convey ideological messages about wellness and disorder. Original web design in 1999 reproduced biomedical discourses and framed illness through stock photography and stylized images. Increased use of stock photography of smiling people on the 2003 revision of the website shifted the focus from illness to health. With the most recent overhaul of the website in 2008, an intensified perspective for highly stylized stock photographs along with the integration of social media and streaming videos of people talking to viewers concentrated attention on faces to promote mental health as a concern for the everyday person while selling the promise of wellness through virtual interaction. This case study provides much needed research on how visual resources are digitally deployed and commodified through web design to understand how ‘wellness’ is marketed as an ideal to pursue, and how ‘disorder’ is sold as the ‘normal’ state of affairs.</p>
<sec id="section1-1470357212453978">
<title>Theoretical Foundations</title>
<p>In the short time span of less than two decades, the internet has gone from a slow, unpopulated, computer-mediated space for information dissemination to a high-speed, heavily trafficked, virtual world where people from around the globe turn to find information and connect with others. Where web designers needed to be wary of including large image files or animation on websites in the 1990s, transformations in digital technology have allowed web designers to bring together visual, textual, and audio forms to communicate messages quite differently to the modern day internet audience.</p>
<p>With the evolution of new media forms, ‘texts are no longer just written, but “designed”, and multimodally articulated’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1470357212453978">Kress and Van Leeuwen, 1998</xref>). Suggesting that theories and tools are insufficient to account for and describe the semiotic conditions of the present, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1470357212453978">Kress (2009)</xref> throws down the gauntlet for scholars to re-examine and re-theorize visual communication, revisiting older terms and developing new ones that better fit the semiotic landscape. The use of visual imagery has increasingly become a significant resource for communicating mental health to website visitors. By combining a social semiotics and critical discourse analysis approach, I examine this website from a multimodal perspective, paying attention to how notions of health and wellness are visually and ideologically reproduced.</p>
<p>I draw on critical discourse analysis to extend the concept of <italic>synthetic personalization</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1470357212453978">Fairclough, 1989</xref>) to the semiotic environment of the web. When a message is contrived for a mass audience so individuals feel as if they are being spoken to personally, synthetic personalization is at work. Image types and photographic perspective also interact with viewers, performing visual speech acts. These <italic>image acts</italic> are realized through the gaze (or absence of it) that addresses the viewer. Visual ‘demands’ simulate social interaction, either through the eyes of the represented participant gazing at or gesturing towards the viewer. In ‘offer’ images, the gaze does not form a social connection between the viewer and the object pictured. Instead, ‘it “offers” the represented participants to the viewer as items of information, objects of contemplation, impersonally, as though they were specimens in a display case’ (p. 124). Through visual resources that communicate sociality,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1470357212453978">2</xref></sup> web design elides institutional voices by employing personal discourses to befriend the interlocutor, engaging in the business of <italic>virtual visual synthetic personalization.</italic></p>
<p>Web designers attempt to invoke behavior responses through the communicative power of design, producing messages rich with ideology that users may not be aware of. Image banks offer a wide range of context-free visual resources for web designers to work with. Research on image banks describes how the ability to interchange these images for a variety of marketing situations is made increasingly possible by the genericity of images that rely on stereotypes of ‘average’ people in the midst of ‘everyday’ activities in common places, reflecting a culture of branding—one in which a stylized, harmonized, commodified world is presented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1470357212453978">Machin, 2004</xref>). Stock photos of people, uploaded photos of bloggers, and screen captures depicting faces of people on downloadable <italic>YouTube</italic> videos are significant instruments of virtual visual synthetic personalization on HealthyPlace.</p>
<p>Design influences the symbolic potential available to meaning-makers. Social semiotic theory uses the concept of modality to explain the degree to which visuals represent a perceived sense of reality and ‘truth’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1470357212453978">Kress and Van Leeuwen, 1996</xref>). With the shift to digital photography and image banks, stock images allow for increasingly generic, decontextualized and highly stylized images to reproduce a ‘truth’ that corresponds to an ‘essence’ of what they represent, symbolizing concepts and moods rather than products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1470357212453978">Machin 2004</xref>). Stock images and modality on HealthyPlace show how design can be used to neutralize the seriousness of mental illness and naturalize disorder as a problem for everyday people. Stylized imagery and new media depict a lifestyle of health and wellness, selling online sociality as an intervention for mental health disorders.</p>
<p>By applying social semiotic theory to read visual space, information values of visual resources can be understood by their placement along a variety of axes ‘attached to the various “zones” of the image: left and right; top and bottom; center and margin’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1470357212453978">Kress and Van Leeuwen, 1996</xref>: 183). A prominent element placed in the ‘center’ is valued as more important than the surrounding elements in the ‘margins’. A polarized configuration can signal that information on the left is ‘known’ and that on the right is ‘new’, or that information placed on the bottom is ‘realist’ whereas the top corresponds to an ‘ideal’. By extending print-based design theory to new media environments, we can see how visual communication is shifting towards complex, intertwining modes of representation when content, placement, and design are overlaid. The deployment of images of people in the center of web pages as both ‘real’ and stylized to reflect an ‘ideal’ shows how new media can denote a ‘realistic ideal’ that blurs the divide when modality and layout are manipulated for specific ends (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1470357212453978">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Composition and modality reflect changing information values (adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1470357212453978">Kress and Van Leeuwen, 1996</xref>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>With increasing speed of browsers and decreasing costs for storage, websites are increasingly multimodal, employing dynamic interactive content to engage with end-users. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1470357212453978">Jenkins (2006)</xref> argues we are in an age of media transition and instability, a ‘convergence culture’ in which new and old media interact in a complex relationship, depending on active participation of consumers working in a social dynamic with media producers to influence the relationship among audiences, producers, and content. The inclusion of new media tools to deliver content and gain participation from site visitors demonstrates how HealthyPlace is participating in the convergence culture, encouraging members to fulfill the role of participants (not just consumers) on the mental health community website newly branded as ‘America’s Mental Health Channel’.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1470357212453978">
<title>Constructing a Healthy Place</title>
<p>On the website, homepage viewers are told that ‘HealthyPlace is the largest consumer mental health site, providing comprehensive, trusted information on psychological disorders and psychiatric medications from both a consumer and expert point of view’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1470357212453978">HealthyPlace, 1999–2010</xref>). HealthyPlace is a privately held company based in the US, with revenues generated through advertising sales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1470357212453978">‘About HealthyPlace and the People Behind It – Healthy Place’, 2009</xref>). HealthyPlace producers, claiming no affiliation with site advertisers, hail from a variety of professional backgrounds (i.e. business, journalism, psychiatry, and web-design). While articles on the site are reviewed for accuracy by the Medical Director, health-writing journalists (not medical professionals), and branded members of the community generate the content. Those who register for a free membership receive a weekly email newsletter and can view and post content throughout the site.</p>
<p>Visitors entering the new HealthyPlace will navigate through a variety of visual and textual signifiers. In the top left-hand corner, the logo, website name, and motto anchor the webpage. Next to the motto ‘American’s mental health channel’, the logo depicts a stylized image of a group of six people standing in a circle holding hands. To the right of the logo, a horizontal drop-down navigation menu leads visitors to: Communities, Other Info, Insight, Support, TV Show, Blogs, About, and Tools. Links for new users to register for membership, sign in, and bookmark the page are in the top right corner. In the same section of the page, there is a search box to locate information within the site and another box to sign up for the newsletter mailing list. In the center of the homepage just below the welcome message, a row of five embedded YouTube videos are visible. Below the videos, visitors will find a list of links to mental health communities. Continuing down the page, another section includes links to a list of recent blog titles, psychological tests, and audio message files created by bloggers and members. Further down the page, another section divider marks the area for HealthyPlace TV Show Blogs and links to YouTube videos featured on the site—mostly developed by professionals, bloggers, and members. Links to information about pharmaceutical products are at the bottom of the page, along with a secondary navigation menu. Advertisements for mental health pharmaceuticals can be found on all four sides of the homepage.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Comparison between HealthyPlace homepages. Copyright © 1999–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig2.tif"/></fig>
<p>Over the first 10 years, HealthyPlace has undergone a number of design changes, providing clues about the power of images to serve as strategic marketing resources to represent ‘disorder’ and ‘wellness’ in relation to circulating mental health discourses. Through imagery and linguistic messages, HealthyPlace have re-branded themselves a number of times. The design changes show intentional moves away from symbolic imagery depicting the disordered body and metaphors of transformation to iconic imagery of healthy people. Elements of modality and image-types demonstrate how visual resources semiotically construct ways of thinking about mental health disorder and wellness to operationalize self-improvement offered by it. The formula for achieving the ‘look’ of HealthyPlace has changed from a simple, pre-millennial website that visualized health through biomedical discourses to a site reflecting a corporate aesthetic that reifies the everyday, unremarkable individual as a symbol of health and wellness.</p>
<p>Image-types employed on the homepage and across HealthyPlace differ with each revision, suggesting new approaches to talking about illness and selling health. Upon entrance to the original homepage in 1999, visitors would have viewed an animated image of ‘the brain in action’ that visually enacted popular biomedical discourses selling the website as a place to improve one’s mind to get healthy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1470357212453978">Figure 2a</xref>). Unlike early animated images, newer images use a high degree of articulation, offering a sense of realness to viewers. Visual content of early pages is primarily symbolic abstract whereas newly designed pages present stylized iconic images of people as the dominant resource. Reflecting a shift towards discourses of sociality and talk psychotherapy, the symbolic imagery of the improving mind was replaced in 2003 by a stock photo of ‘girlfriends’ outdoors exuding health (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1470357212453978">Figure 2b</xref>). In 2009, the discipline of branding increases through a stock photo of a smiling woman standing in a sunny meadow with outstretched arms, signaling a lifestyle of wellness and freedom from disorder (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1470357212453978">Figure 2c</xref>).</p>
<p>Even though HealthyPlace remains rather text-heavy,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1470357212453978">3</xref></sup> there is a clear trend towards greater use of visual resources and rich media to communicate and draw an audience. In the welcome message on the homepage, a dialogue is created with visitors who are told, ‘We’re glad you found us’, beginning the linguistic process of synthetic personalization on HealthyPlace. Stylized stock images of ‘real’ people gazing back at website visitors set in motion the visual synthetic personalization process, and faces of real people captured in screen shots of streaming videos and social network profiles signal the virtual aspect of synthetic personalization. Increasing a sense of sociality, members are invited to watch the newly-branded HP TV streamed in real time and send questions or comments using synchronous chat. To contrive (and sell) a HealthyPlace, images of community members—both real and imagined— frame wellness through healthy-looking, socially engaged people.</p>
<p>A historical analysis of visual content, stylization, and presentation sheds light on changes surrounding health communication—a shift that new media forms intensify. Prior to the ascendancy of people as icons of health, imagery deployed on HealthyPlace consisted primarily of thematic representations of landscapes, clichés, and bodies constructing illness. With the re-launch of HealthyPlace in 2009, the addition of social media tools and embedded YouTube videos exploit the face, blurring the lines between health and sociality.</p>
<p>Since the inception of HealthyPlace, internet traffic has primarily come from the US, with a strong and varied international presence.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1470357212453978">4</xref></sup> The website consistently ranks within the Global Top 100,000 for internet traffic.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1470357212453978">5</xref></sup> In the US, HealthyPlace ranks 16,930 overall and is consistently a Top 10 ‘mental health’ website.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1470357212453978">6</xref></sup> Clearly, HealthyPlace has the potential to (re)produce ideological discourses and construct a narrative of health and wellness to a sizable audience of internet users around the globe.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1470357212453978">
<title>Constructing Communities</title>
<p>One of the areas on HealthyPlace where manufactured images are most prevalent, and therefore speak volumes about constructions of health and illness, are the community homepages. I begin with an analysis of the original 17 community homepages, showing how disorder served as the frame for visually communicating mental health from 1999–2002. Next, I discuss a small number of community homepages that were re-designed between 2003–2005 to show a shift from a symbolically-driven focus on disorder to an emphasis on ideal health for the everyday person. Finally, I examine the 2009 overhaul of all the community homepages (now numbering 20) to illustrate how generic stock images of people have been commodified to sell (online) sociality as the promise of mental health.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1470357212453978">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Mapping community homepages provides evidence of a transition surrounding how health and illness are visually communicated in the digital age. Although the move to use people to represent health is found across the website, a progression from symbolic images signifying disorder to literal depictions of the idealized community is salient through an analysis of stylized image types employed on community homepages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1470357212453978">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig3-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Image types on HealthyPlace community homepages.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig3.tif"/></fig>
<p>On the original 17 community homepages from 1999–2006, symbolic images that relied upon clichés, people representing disorder, surreal landscapes, and exaggerations of the disordered body were the primary means of visually communicating disorder communities. In 2002, photographs in which people gazed back at viewers began to appear, on specific community homepages. In 2009, stylized images of groups of healthy-looking people demanding engagement through eye contact, designed from generic stock photos, became the only image type employed for HealthyPlace communities (with the exception of two communities that included no image at all: dissociative disorders and self-injury). The move from objects of suffering (as symbols of disorder) to close-ups of faces gazing back at viewers (as icons of health) demonstrates how visual synthetic personalization can close social distance, creating a sense of fellowship and community through web design.</p>
<p>The layout and composition of webpages also serves a vital role in communicating meaning potential. With the original website design, disorder communities were marked by a symbolic image at the top-left corner, reinforcing ‘known’ ideological notions about mental illness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1470357212453978">Figure 4</xref>). In the second version of the site, a number of community homepages were redesigned<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1470357212453978">8</xref></sup> using a combination approach, with ‘known’ constructions of disorder in the top left corner and stock photos of ideal community members integrated into the center of the webpage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1470357212453978">Figure 5</xref>). In 2009, all community homepages were modified, creating a more uniform look, each page shared the same background and contained a similarly stylized close-up image of small group of three to four people (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1470357212453978">Figure 6</xref>). The newest site does not include symbols of illness, only generic stock photos depicting healthy people.</p>
<fig id="fig4-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>People as symbols of disorder to be gazed upon. Copyright © 1999–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig4.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig5-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>People as representatives of community. Copyright © 2000–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig5.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig6-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>People as icons of health that demand virtual engagement. Copyright © 2000–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig6.tif"/></fig>
<p>Stock photos of people represent a sense of realness and/or possibility for users, potential for wellness. This reframing of health shifts the discourse from disorder as the ‘known’ state of affairs to a focus on health as a ‘new’ realistic ideal. The centering of stylized groups of ‘everyday’ people suggests a new way of thinking—or at least representing—disorder as neither given nor new, but rather a manufactured ‘realistic ideal’ of wellness that is central in the lives of the average person, blurring the boundaries between disorder and wellness.</p>
<p>Changes to community homepages demonstrate how images project a ‘realistic’ sense of (un)wellness through representation, perspective, and contextualization. Details such as degrees of articulation in detail, background, and color saturation present in images provide additional information for analysis, whereby highly articulated images are used to represent the real, and images in soft-focus or less significant in size, such as small images in the background, represent an ideal or an object that is out of reach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1470357212453978">Kress and Van Leeuwen, 1996</xref>).</p>
<p>In early people-centered images posted on community homepages, the background (or lack thereof) created a generic scene in which a suffering person was the focus. ‘Offer’ images were most common—consequently, signaling detachment rather than involvement. In early community images, people rarely looked directly at viewers, but rather appeared posed with averted, closed, or covered eyes, often looking down or away from the viewer. People were often somewhat obscured from clear view or presented in less detail, making literal images appear less ‘real’ and more symbolic through perspective. Additionally, photographic perspective often presented people from an angle, rather than a frontal close-up that denotes maximum involvement. Commonly illustrated through attention to posture, facial expression, and gesture, meaning potentials about illness were also conveyed through generic stock photography that calls upon familiar motifs (such as the depressed person in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1470357212453978">Figure 4</xref>) by iconically communicating a distinctive emotional quality—or ‘mood’—of the disorder.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1470357212453978">
<title>Symbolizing Disorder</title>
<p>When the HealthyPlace website was first launched in 1999, images that relayed symbolic meaning potentials were the primary means of communicating mental illness and signaling specific communities. A multiplicity of meaning potentials is made possible by the simultaneous exploitation of symbolic and/or iconic representations, containing an array of visual content whose meaning potentials are generated through both literal and figurative images as well as the presentation and stylization of images (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1470357212453978">Thurlow and Aiello, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1470357212453978">Van Leeuwen, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Visual resources derived from generic images of surreal landscapes make up the first thematic image-type deployed on the original HealthyPlace community homepages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1470357212453978">Figure 7</xref>). For example, in 1999, visitors saw a desert landscape with rock formations in hues of magenta and orange when entering the Bipolar Community (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1470357212453978">Figure 7a</xref>), and a mystical looking mountain gorge in the moonlit night sky upon entrance to the Self-Injury Community (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1470357212453978">Figure 7b</xref>). These images, which offer highly stylized and exaggerated representations of the world, exhibit low degrees of modality with their ‘unrealistic’ depiction of nature. However, read through a ‘sensory coding orientation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1470357212453978">Kress and Van Leeuwen, 2006</xref>), these landscape images may be deemed to contain a high degree of truth value on account of their affective meaning potentials. Additionally, the rich and soothing colors of these landscapes provide affective meanings and consequently can convey high modality when coded by individuals valuing emotive/sensory truth.</p>
<fig id="fig7-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>New age landscapes: Bipolar (1); Self-Injury (b). Copyright © 1999–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig7.tif"/></fig>
<p>As symbolic or ‘figurative’, visual resources construct notions of HealthyPlace communities, surreal landscapes strategically provide non-controversial ways of thinking about the serious issue of mental health disorders through modality and genericity. Generic landscapes are, in and of themselves, icons with the added connotative meaning potential of the natural world and, in turn, ‘serenity’ and ‘peacefulness’. The figurative iconicity of the landscape makes the symbolic invocation of wellness possible.</p>
<p>The imagery of the landscape does not literally represent mental health disorders, but instead can be read as figuratively constructing idealized spaces that speak to a life without disorder. Despite the tenuous connection to the communities they represent, surreal landscapes have the symbolic potential to invoke ‘positive thinking’ and hint at the possibility of enlightenment through spirituality and simplicity. This is possible due to intertextual meaning potentials derived from New Age discourses, which emphasize a return to the ‘natural’ and ‘mythical’. The New Age imagery is an available visual resource that allows for the possibility of interpretations promising personal transformation. The utilization of generic stock bank images of surreal landscapes creates a complex web of intertwined meaning potentials, with iconicity and symbolism informing one another.</p>
<p>Clearly iconic and symbolic visual resources that rely upon clichés offer users a recognizable association and way of thinking about the identity of a given community. Employing the stylistic tool of metonymy to conjure meaning potentials closely associated with the particular disorder communities, a word or visual image may be substituted for a larger whole. For a number of HealthyPlace communities, visual resources that have come to symbolically represent concepts have been employed, to trigger the preferred translation and association between image and community (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1470357212453978">Figure 8</xref>). While metonymic suggestions may aim to invoke specific meaning potentials, such as the rainbow flag for the GLBT Community (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1470357212453978">Figure 8a</xref>) and a microscopic rendering of a sperm and egg as representative of the Sex/Sexuality Community (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1470357212453978">Figure 8b</xref>), the genericity and decontextualized nature of the images may also inadvertently signal unintended readings.</p>
<fig id="fig8-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>Clichés.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig8.tif"/></fig>
<p>Recognition value is highest when the gap between the image and the ideologically dominant meaning is small. Even though multiple meaning potentials exist, an image that is closer to the normalized discourse will meet the narrative expectations with visual language serving as a denotative marker. When an image meets the expectation of the viewer, it is less likely to confuse and more likely to lead to a dominant reading. Thus, abstract images with high recognition value serve as powerful—and effective—resources because the reader needs to do less work to interpret a possible meaning. Clichés are effective because they simplify the decoding process by providing regularly and widely used images and metaphors to depict a concept (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1470357212453978">Dillon, 2006</xref>). They also require little or no effort on behalf of the viewer for such decoding. Clichés related to particular mental health disorders facilitate ease of translation, yet clichés are helpful only in as much as they are universally understood and easily recognizable.</p>
<p>Visual resources that represent the disordered body were commonly used before 2009 to do this connotative work. The production and performance of a specific disorder was typified through images that were digitally distorted to exaggerate the effects of disorder on the body as with the Chronic Pain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-1470357212453978">Figure 9a</xref>) and OCD Communities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-1470357212453978">Figure 9b</xref>). With the focus on the body, iconic images create literal representations of disorder; people (or their body parts) serve as objects to be gazed upon while the disorder is performed as an interruption to normality. Hyper-stylization of images can be said to decrease modality and thus create a less perceptually truthful representation of disorder. However, the extreme modification of images can also be seen as increasing modality—in that they can be decoded as abstract—and thus designed to exaggerate reality to depict an ‘emotive’ truth about the experience of disorder as disruptive to everyday living.</p>
<fig id="fig9-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 9.</label>
<caption>
<p>Exaggerations of the disordered body: Chronic Pain (a); OCD (b). Copyright © 1999–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig9.tif"/></fig>
<p>The use of children in stock images can carry complex connotative power, adding connotative value, as they are often used as props to signal innocence and a sense that all is well with the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1470357212453978">Thurlow and Aiello, 2007</xref>). Conversely, children are also used as props to represent lost innocence, as seen in the image of a sad, neglected child associated with the Abuse Community (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-1470357212453978">Figure 10</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig10-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 10.</label>
<caption>
<p>Children as props signaling disorder on Abuse Community. Copyright © 1999–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig10.tif"/></fig>
<p>The difficulty of using images to encode and decode conceptual meaning has been discussed by visual theorists, who argue that while words and images serve an important role in creating a system of common understanding among groups of people, this system is not without problems as meanings are not fixed and thus require negotiation and interpretation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1470357212453978">Moscovici, 1973</xref>). Specifically, visual representations of conceptual meanings require even greater degrees of interpretation on the part of viewers. Culturally symbolic representations are especially problematic when websites draw a global audience, as the potential for failed meaning recognition increases, making literal imagery a more effective communicative tool. Unfortunately, literal imagery can be difficult to attribute to mental health disorders and health.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1470357212453978">
<title>Normalizing Disorder: Everybody’s Problem</title>
<p>With the continuous revisions to the HealthyPlace community homepages, symbolic imagery signaling disorder has been slowly replaced by manufactured stock photos representing diverse groups of people idealizing health. Despite an initial inclination to read the de-contextualization of people in stock images as having lower modality given the ‘falsification’ of the setting that happens in reproduction, modality is quite high because the visual resource simultaneously appeals to a ‘naturalistic’ and ‘abstract coding orientation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1470357212453978">Kress and Van Leeuwen, 1996</xref>). Stock images across community homepages employ models as generic icons to create typical examples of idealized HealthyPlace users who iconically and symbolically embody ideal health and wellness.</p>
<p>People model this genericity by appearing ‘average’ or ‘normal’. Models are attractive, but do not stand out in any way; hair and clothing styles are consistently conservative, so as not to draw attention to any one individual as falling outside of the norm. There is little range in clothing styles, expressions, and body posturing. Through the process of image decontextualization, truth value is connected to the way stylization ‘reduce[es] the individual to the general, and the concrete to its essential qualities’ (p. 170). Generic photos of individuals—due to their simplicity and plasticity—can readily serve as representatives of a larger group through genericity. ‘Photoshopping’ images of decontextualized people to create the appearance of uniform groups (rather than using actual photographs of groups that may differ stylistically) creates particular truth values about who HealthyPlace community members are (or have the potential to become). The ‘realistic’ depiction of ‘normal’ people as iconic figures embodying the HealthyPlace user and the stylized (re)production of these figures create a realistic ideal.</p>
<p>Group photos on community pages stylize an appearance of diversity through inclusion of people representing different ethnic, racial, gender, sexuality, and age groups. These images of ‘average’ people gazing back at viewers can enact visual synthetic personalization by contriving familiarity through relatability. While it may be true that community homepages as a whole give the impression of diversity, upon closer inspection however, stylized images actually reflect generic representatives of community members. Communities are visualized on the updated HealthyPlace community homepages to reflect categorical heterogeneity (or homogeneity).</p>
<p>The contrived attention to diversity is apparent through the absence and repetition of specific ‘types’ of people assigned to specific communities to reflect the ‘average’ visitor. Corresponding with statistics that women are the primary consumers of self-improvement products, HealthyPlace visualizes mental health as a greater concern for women through gender presence on community pages (and throughout the site overall). Similarly, the inclusion of a visibly overweight woman on the Eating Disorders Community homepages (marked by the exclusion on all other community pages) demonstrates a strategic move to appeal to a perceived demographic via a ‘realistic’ representation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-1470357212453978">Figure 11</xref>). Taken separately, each model appears common, but when grouped together, diverse body sizes and a group largely comprised of women indicates a generic—yet representative—group of people dealing with eating disorders.</p>
<fig id="fig11-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 11.</label>
<caption>
<p>Representing the group on Eating Disorders homepages. Copyright © 1999–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig11.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig12-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 12.</label>
<caption>
<p>Representing the group: Sex/Sexuality (a); Gender (b). Copyright © 1999–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig12.tif"/></fig>
<p>The distinction between heterosexual and homosexual couples on the Sexuality and Gender Communities demonstrates intentional design choices to create a montage that represents particular types of people. Here attention is paid to representing couples, not just individuals. Decontextualized stock photos are re-contextualized by linguistic disorder categories (through community labels) while simultaneously representing specific gender and sexuality norms through uniform images signaling representative types of ‘couple-ness’.</p>
<p>Imagery that relies on generic stock photos of everyday people on mental health websites and public discourses that claim mental health issues are widespread and common collectively contribute to an increasing normalization of disorder. Such a notion of mental health is reminiscent of a ‘a postmodern perspective of health that escapes the dualism that we are either sick or well’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1470357212453978">Harter et al., 2005</xref>), but rather that we all experience degrees of health and unwellness on a regular basis. This outlook on health is powerful because it opens up possibilities for the everyday person and removes stigma, making disorder acceptable and treatment possible. On the other hand, this broadening of ‘disorder’ effectively minimizes severe mental illness and feeds discourses that encourage everyday people to feel compelled to work on themselves to meet prescribed ideals of wellness ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1470357212453978">Illouz, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1470357212453978">McGee, 2005</xref>), potentially creating heightened anxiety and fueling constant regimes of self-care—including increased participation on mental health community websites such as HealthyPlace.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1470357212453978">
<title>The Changing Face(s) of Healthyplace</title>
<p>When users enter the new HealthyPlace, they are increasingly <italic>faced</italic> with a number of images—most of which include people (especially women) looking back at the visitor. After nearly a decade as a successful community website, HealthyPlace web designers have moved to capitalize on the iconic imagery that endeavors to capture the essence of healthy people rather than continue to metaphorically visualize mental illness and the disordered mind (and body). With each redesign of the HealthyPlace website, symbolic images representing disorder (or the disordered body) have been replaced by realistic stylized images of healthy people, as well as photos and videos of real people, personifying health. The images included on the different homepages, as well as other key pages on the website, provide vital information about the change in messaging at work on HealthyPlace.</p>
<p>At the top of the HealthyPlace homepage, where once a stylized image of the brain in action signaled mental activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-1470357212453978">Figure 13a</xref>), and later, butterflies flying in the clouds connoted transformation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-1470357212453978">Figure 13b</xref>), a new logo depicting a group of <italic>people</italic> holding hands now represents the HealthyPlace virtual community (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-1470357212453978">Figure 13c</xref>). Visual imagery reflects discursive shifts from biomedical models of the mind, to psychotherapeutic models of the transforming self, to a psycho-social model that relates health to sociality. Unlike the symbolic image of the mind at work that welcomed visitors on the original website, the homepage of second and third versions of the website relies upon images of women to signal ideal health (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-1470357212453978">Figure 14</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig13-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 13.</label>
<caption>
<p>Homepage logos reflect discursive shifts. Copyright © 1999–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig13.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig14-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 14.</label>
<caption>
<p>Women represent health on HealthyPlace homepages. Copyright © 1999–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig14.tif"/></fig>
<p>Modality markers that contextualize a type of reality of living with mental health disorder(s) influence meaning potentials in relation to wellness, often exemplifying wellness through their ‘naturalness’. Stock images that contextualize groups of people in outdoor environments promote lifestyles based on concepts such as ‘togetherness’ and ‘leisure’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1470357212453978">Emmons, 2010</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1470357212453978">Thurlow et. al. (2005)</xref> suggest in their analysis of visual resources in tourist postcards that people are often presented as spectacles in the service of constructing the ‘ethnoscape’ through what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1470357212453978">Goffman (1986)</xref> refers to as a ‘performance’ frame in which they ‘act out hospitability and friendliness’ while ‘engaged in mundane activities’ (p. 7).</p>
<p>On the Parenting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-1470357212453978">Figure 15a</xref>) and ADD/ADHD community pages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-1470357212453978">Figure 15b</xref>), mythologies about ‘good parenting’ and ‘father–son time’ are played out through images. These images reflect consumer categories that show a stylized, harmonized world of commodified health through the performance of sociality. Although the earlier version of the community images differ stylistically—people serve as objects of the gaze rather than demanding engagement from viewers—parents and children are depicted in social interaction, reflecting mythologies of wellness through relationship.</p>
<fig id="fig15-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 15.</label>
<caption>
<p>People in everyday activities perform wellness: (a) ADD/ADHD; (b) Parenting. Copyright © 1999–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig15.tif"/></fig>
<p>Photographic images of people demanding engagement from viewers have become the dominant visual resource across the site—enacting visual synthetic personalization to capture and maintain a web audience. In addition to the manufactured stock photos of ‘healthy’ people on community pages that have been discussed, photographs of people have been strategically employed on key sections of the website. This new incarnation of HealthyPlace illustrates the latest branding strategy. With images of people serving as icons of wellness rather than symbolic representations of disorder, faces of ‘real’ people have become the most significant visual resource to sell (online) sociality as the promise of mental health.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1470357212453978">
<title>Real People</title>
<p>Embedded videos on the HealthyPlace site add another dimension of people on display (and participating in the community) through visual design. When visitors enter the main homepage or the community homepages, they will see a table with five embedded YouTube video files linked below the welcome message (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig16-1470357212453978">Figure 16</xref>). With the technological transformations that allow individuals to embed a still frame from a YouTube video into another webpage, visual imagery that capitalizes on people in videos (rather than the concept of a video) has become a possibility. Still shots of people looking into the camera and talking about mental health serve as links to YouTube videos accessible by clicking on the photo (or the title just below). The addition of these embedded YouTube videos further the HealthyPlace mission to be the largest web community with content generated by both professionals and consumers while simultaneously employing new media as a tool of virtual visual synthetic personalization in web design.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1470357212453978">9</xref></sup></p>
<fig id="fig16-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 16.</label>
<caption>
<p>Faces of people on YouTube embedded videos. Copyright © 2000–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig16.tif"/></fig>
<p>Another area where HealthyPlace has capitalized on new media and participatory culture to improve the community website is the Support Network that replaced Forums in 2009. Centered on the support network page is a stylized image of community members waving hello, a visual resource that enacts the epitome of virtual visual synthetic personalization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig17-1470357212453978">Figure 17</xref>). The speech act ‘Join us now, it’s free!’ is positioned next to the image of the healthy looking group of community members, complementing the visual image to communicate a request for participation. Faces of community members look back at viewers from a variety of sections on the Support Network: Get Connected, Members, Who’s Online, Recent Activities, Latest Videos, Who’s Online, and New Photos. Similar to popular social network programs, uploaded photos of people in the network (or avatars representing people) are posted, along with activity and status updates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig18-1470357212453978">Figure 18</xref>). These sorts of visual communication moves mark a growing trend away from text-based organization on the web to a privileging of images—especially those that provide a shortcut to meaning potentials about what it means to be healthy.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1470357212453978">10</xref></sup></p>
<fig id="fig17-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 17.</label>
<caption>
<p>Faces of HealthyPlace members on social network. Copyright © 2000–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig17.tif"/></fig>
<p>With the re-launch of the site in 2009, journals written by community members were replaced by blogs written by professionals.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1470357212453978">11</xref></sup> Upon entry to the blog community, readers find abbreviated entries that include head shots of multiple bloggers looking back at them. Whereas journalers of the past posted entries without concern for deadlines or visual rhetoric, paid bloggers—elevated to the status of expert patients—are required to post one video blog (vlog) per month, write two traditional blog entries per week, and include a personal photograph as well as a complementary image (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig18-1470357212453978">Figure 18</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-1470357212453978">12</xref></sup></p>
<fig id="fig18-1470357212453978" position="float">
<label>Figure 18.</label>
<caption>
<p>Faces of HealthyPlace bloggers. Copyright © 2000–2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link>, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1470357212453978-fig18.tif"/></fig>
<p>The deployment of faces on health websites influences ideological notions about health and wellness—specifically linking wellness and sociality. Stylized generic stock photos of people and photos of hired bloggers serve as communicative devices that enact virtual visual synthetic personalization on websites like HealthyPlace. Moreover, with the addition of participatory new media tools, self-sponsored profile photos on social network platforms and YouTube videos generated by website producers and members reify the message of wellness and sociality through the proliferation of real people’s faces posted across health websites.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1470357212453978">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Stylized stock photos of imagined community members, photos of bloggers and members within the social support network reify the connection between sociality and health; the ‘faces’ of HealthyPlace thus serve as commodities to sell sociality as a sign of health and wellness. Unlike images that signaled detachment through perspective in the early version of this website, images on the new HealthyPlace website rely primarily on close-ups of people gazing back at viewers to close social distance and create intimacy with the user. In this way, the possibility of health and wellness is constructed as attainable and relatable through the strategic use of images that creates engagement with users.</p>
<p>This reframing of the discourse to one of achievable health appears optimistic and empowering compared to earlier discourses that concentrated communicative messages on the despair of illness. This is not to say that discourses of wellness are less problematic than discourses of illness; just as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1470357212453978">Sontag (1990)</xref> vehemently argued against illness discourses that relied upon metaphors of empowerment to suggest that people can fight physical illness through their will, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1470357212453978">Gwyn’s (2002)</xref> research on health communication has shown that a wellness focused approach has the ramifications of reproducing discourses of unattainable ideals of health.</p>
<p>Web design choices that rely upon stock photography images that depict all types of happy-looking people as representatives of the HealthyPlace community promote the normalization of disorder and a lifestyle of self-care in virtual communities. Visual discourse, with its symbolic and iconic availability, can function as a strategic communication form employed to communicate that mental health disorders are a common problem for the everyday person. This normalization of mental health disorders opens up the market for products and services no longer reserved for the extremely ill, allowing the everyday person to participate in a previously marginalized and stigmatized market. And while growing acceptance of mental health issues on society marks progress, the normalization of mental illness has the potential to pathologize normal experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1470357212453978">Conrad, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1470357212453978">Horwitz, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1470357212453978">Szasz, 2007</xref>) and fuel a consumerist model aimed at eradicating any signs of unhappiness that are part of the human condition. Mental health community websites like HealthyPlace provide evidence that self-care is not merely a dilemma to be solved, but also a commodified lifestyle to be capitalized on in the virtual marketplace.</p>
<p>In the global marketplace, the cost of health care has put a financial strain on many countries with socialized medicine, especially as the cost of attending to the health care needs of aging populations continues to increase. Even though many countries around the world already provide national health care that recognizes mental health conditions equitably, the advancement of mental health disorders as a valid health care problem in the US signals continuing shifts in discourse around caring for a nation’s citizenry. In conjunction with the Mental Health Parity legislation passed by the Obama administration at the beginning of 2010, the US Government launched the website HealthCare.gov to provide facts and explanations about Health Care Reform recently passed by congress. The Obama administration’s investment in the internet as a major channel to reach out to citizens about national health care policy changes signals that the internet is a vital space for health communication. Moreover, as old and new media converge, blurring the lines between information dissemination, consumerism, and socio-digital participation, research that investigates the impact of visual communication in online environments remains vital. This historical examination of the mental health website HealthyPlace contributes to the growing body of scholarship aimed at understanding the intersection between new media and visual health communication.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>I would like to thank Brandy Parris, Lei Lani Michel, Crispin Thurlow, the reviewers and editor of <italic>Visual Communication</italic> for their insightful comments throughout various stages of this project. I also wish to thank <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthyPlace.com">HealthyPlace.com</ext-link> Inc. for granting permission to reproduce images from the website.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1470357212453978">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Statistics compiled by the National Institute for Mental Health point to mental disorders as commonplace in the US and internationally, with 25 percent of adults suffering from a diagnosable mental disorder annually. From a global perspective, the negative impact of mental illness is more significant than cancer, accounting for 15 percent of the health burden in market economies. On a smaller scale, in the US and Canada, mental health disorders are said to be a leading cause of disability for people 15–44 years old (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1470357212453978">Nimh, 2010</xref>).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1470357212453978">
<label>2.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1470357212453978">Killoran (2002)</xref> theorizes that individuals take up a reciprocal practice on personal homepages, which he calls synthetic institutionalization, mimicking institutional voices to construct authority through marketing discourses.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1470357212453978">
<label>3.</label>
<p>In comparison to popular mental health websites (e.g. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://PsychCentral.com">PsychCentral.com</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="MentalHealth.com">MentalHealth.com</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://APA.org">APA.org</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://NIMH.org">NIMH.org</ext-link>), HealthyPlace is one of the most image-heavy.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1470357212453978">
<label>4.</label>
<p>HealthyPlace draws almost half of the audience from the UK, India, Australia, Canada, South Africa, Saudi Arabia, Sweden, Philippines, and China (Alexa internet, 24 June 2010).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1470357212453978">
<label>5.</label>
<p>From 2005–2010, HealthyPlace ranked at around 45,000 on the Global Top 100 (Alexa internet, 24 June 2010).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1470357212453978">
<label>6.</label>
<p>A category search for ‘mental health’ on <italic>Alexa internet</italic> generated a list of 4,500 to 5,300 websites. Over a 4-year period (2007–2010), HealthyPlace moved between ninth and twelfth on the list.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1470357212453978">
<label>7.</label>
<p>Even though advertisements play a significant role in communicating ideas about health and illness on this website, an analysis of these images is beyond the scope of this article. However, it should be noted that advertisements from the beginning of the decade relied upon symbolic and metaphoric notions of the disordered brain/body whereas advertisements from the second half of the decade shifted to iconic imagery of people representing health as a result of medication. See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1470357212453978">Emmons (2010)</xref> for a discussion of depression advertisements.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1470357212453978">
<label>8.</label>
<p>With this revision, only the five most heavily trafficked community homepages were updated (i.e. Anxiety, Biopolar, Depression, Eating Disorders, Sex).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1470357212453978">
<label>9.</label>
<p>Each time pages with embedded videos are refreshed, new videos appear, suggesting that videos are randomly selected using a filter that searches and pulls specific mental health topics from YouTube. Most of the embedded videos are mental health topics randomly selected from YouTube and <italic>not</italic> community member generated videos. I attempted to contact HealthyPlace producers on numerous occasions to ask about the selection process for embedded videos, but received no response.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1470357212453978">
<label>10.</label>
<p>Visitors to this part of the website encounter more imagery of everyday people (and stylized depictions of people in the form of generic avatars) and less text-based navigational options that existed with the bulletin boards on the earlier version of the site.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1470357212453978">
<label>11.</label>
<p>A number of bloggers confirmed HealthyPlace recruited them because of an already-established blog about a particular mental health issue. While writing professionally for HealthyPlace, bloggers maintained their personal blog and cross-promoted blogs to followers.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-1470357212453978">
<label>12.</label>
<p>Blogging requirements were confirmed through interviews with a number of bloggers.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Biographical Note</title>
<p>RIKI THOMPSON is an Assistant Professor of Rhetoric and Composition at the University of Washington Tacoma. Her work draws upon discourse analysis, social semiotics, narrative studies, and new media studies to explore the intersection of language, technology, and self-identity. Her research is based on understanding how language serves as a tool for meaning-making, sociality, and transformation, focusing on self-improvement discourse and health communication.</p>
<p><italic>Address</italic>: Interdisciplinary Arts and Sciences, University of Washington Tacoma, 1900 Commerce Street, Box 358436, Tacoma, WA 98402, USA. [email: <email>rikitiki@u.washington.edu</email>]</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>‘About HealthyPlace and the People Behind It – HealthyPlace’</collab> (<year>2009</year>). Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www./about-healthyplace/about-us/about-healthyplace-and-the-people-behind-it/">http://www./about-healthyplace/about-us/about-healthyplace-and-the-people-behind-it/</ext-link> (<access-date>updated 1 February 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adami</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>‘We/YouTube’: Exploring sign-making in video-interaction</article-title>. <source>Visual Communication</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>The Medicalization of Society: On the Transformation of Human Conditions into Treatable Disorders</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dillon</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Clipart images as commonsense categories</article-title>. <source>Visual Communication</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Emmons</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Black Dogs and Blue Words: Depression and Gender in the Age of Self-Care</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rutgers University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fairclough</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>Language and Power</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Longman</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Media and medicine in modern America</article-title>. <source>History of Medicine Lecture: Yale University</source>, <publisher-name>New Haven</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>CT</publisher-loc>, <day>18</day> <month>February</month>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The social life of health information</article-title>. <source>Pew Internet &amp; American Life Project</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pew Research Center</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goffman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <source>Frame Analysis: An Essay on the Organization of Experience</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Northeastern University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gwyn</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Communicating Health and Illness</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harter</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Japp</surname><given-names>P.M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Vital problematics of narrative theorizing about health and healing</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Harter</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (eds) <source>Narratives, Health, and Healing: Communication Theory, Research, and Practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="other"><collab>HealthyPlace</collab> (<year>1999–2010</year>) <article-title>Healthy Place: America’s Mental Health Channel</article-title>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>HHS</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Obama administration issues rules requiring parity in treatment of mental, substance use disorders</article-title>. <source>Press release</source>, <day>29</day> <month>January</month>, <publisher-name>US Department of Health &amp; Human Services</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hohl</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Beyond the screen: Visualizing visits to a website as an experience in physical space</article-title>. <source>Visual Communication</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>284</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Horwitz</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Creating Mental Illness</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Illouz</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Saving the Modern Soul: Therapy, Emotions, and the Culture of Self-Help</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Convergence Culture: Where Old and New Media Collide</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Killoran</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Private domains in the public domain: The synthetic institutionalization of personal web space</article-title>. <conf-name>Internet Research 3.0 Conference</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Maastricht, The Netherlands</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Visual–verbal communication on online newspaper home pages</article-title>. <source>Visual Communication</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Reading Images: The Grammar of Visual Design</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Multimodality: Exploring Contemporary Methods of Communication</source>. <publisher-loc>Abingdon</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Front pages: (The critical) analysis of newspaper layout</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Approaches to Media Discourse</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Reading Images: The Grammar of Visual Design</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Seeking health information on the internet: Lifestyle choice or bad attack of cyberchondria?</article-title> <source>Media, Culture &amp; Society</source> <volume>28</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>539</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Machin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Building the world’s visual language: The increasing global importance of image banks in corporate media</article-title>. <source>Visual Communication</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mager</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mediated health: Sociotechnical practices of providing and using online health information</article-title>. <source>New Media &amp; Society</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1123</fpage>–<lpage>1142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mcgee</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Self-help, Inc.: Makeover Culture in American Life</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Self-presentation of small developing countries on the world wide web: A study of official websites</article-title>. <source>New Media &amp; Society</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>486</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moscovici</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Foreword</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Herzlich</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Health and Illness: A Social Psychological Analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>NIMH</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Statistics</source>. <publisher-loc>Bethesda, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Institute of Mental Health</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Health and the Rhetoric of Medicine</source>. <publisher-loc>Carbondale</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Southern Illinois University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sontag</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>Illness as Metaphor and AIDS and Its Metaphors</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Doubleday</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Szasz</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>The Medicalization of Everyday Life: Selected Essays</source>. <publisher-loc>Syracuse, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Syracuse University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thurlow</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aiello</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>National pride, global capital: A social semiotic analysis of transnational visual branding in the airline industry</article-title>. <source>Visual Communication</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>344</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thurlow</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jaworski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ylänne-Mcewen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>‘Half-hearted tokens of transparent love’? ‘Ethnic’ postcards and the visual mediation of host-tourist communication</article-title>. <source>Tourism, Culture and Communication</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Introducing Social Semiotics</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>WHO</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <source>The Global Burden of Disease: 2004 Update</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1470357212453978">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wyatt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The digital divide, health information and everyday life</article-title>. <source>New Media &amp; Society</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>