<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EHQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spehq</journal-id>
<journal-title>European History Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0265-6914</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7110</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0265691411428783aa</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0265691411428783aa</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Heinz-Gerhard Haupt and Jürgen Kocka, eds, <italic>Comparative and Transnational History: Central European Approaches and New Perspectives</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0265691411428783aa">The George Washington University, Washington, DC</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>160</fpage>
<lpage>161</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0265691411428783aa"><title>Heinz-Gerhard Haupt and Jürgen Kocka, eds, <italic>Comparative and Transnational History: Central European Approaches and New Perspectives</italic>, Berghahn Books: Oxford, 2010; vi + 294 pp.; 9781845456153, £55.00 (hbk)</title>
<p>This book offers English readers a glimpse into one of the most important developments in the great tradition of German social history since the days when Hans-Ulrich Wehler and the Bielefeld School developed their original and innovative approaches to modern German history. While the important critiques of the way the Bielefeld School characterized a <italic>Sonderweg</italic>, or peculiar path, of German history (from the Kaiserreich to the Third Reich), discredited some aspects of that particular type of social history, its core social-theoretical and comparative methodology has remained an important part of the discipline. Perhaps to a greater extent than their colleagues in other countries, German historians have retained a commitment to comparative history, even if the comparison was only implied by the use of general social-scientific categories rather than worked out in the study of multiple cases. This comparative social history now finds itself in productive dialogue, and dissonance, with recent transnational approaches, and what once appeared as discreet national cases now turn out to be the co-productions of entangled histories.</p>
<p>The chapters in the first section of the book make available in English some of the core methodological arguments in these discussions about transnational and comparative history. After a sensible overview and commentary by Hartmut Kaelble, the volume translates two of the seminal articles in the debate, by Jürgen Osterhammel and Sebastian Conrad, both originally published in the flagship journal of German social history, <italic>Geschichte und Gesellschaft</italic>. Osterhammel’s chapter traces the gradual and sometimes reluctant embrace of global and transnational approaches by German social historians. Osterhammel discourages blanket rejections of national histories in favour of transnational approaches and instead maintains that varying objects of inquiry require varying frameworks, with the nation playing an enormous role in the late modern period but perhaps less so in other times and places. Conrad is more directly critical than Osterhammel of historiographies centred on the nation, citing studies that show the nation to be a product of prior transnational processes, and also recent developments in colonial history that point to the co-production of colony and metropole against Eurocentric accounts emphasizing the agency of colonizer and the passivity of colonized. The transnational thus relativizes the nation for Osterhammel and peripheralizes it for Conrad.</p>
<p>Perhaps it is not surprising that many of the texts foundational to this debate are by historians of colonialism, for the study of entangled histories is necessary to all non-Eurocentric accounts of empire. Andreas Eckart attributes the neglect, until recently, of colonial studies in Germany in part to the overwhelming interest in studying a national <italic>Sonderweg</italic> in order to explain National Socialism. Scholars have now begun to recognize that German colonies, like other colonies, functioned as ‘laboratories’ from which emerged many aspects of European modernity. Some historians have even begun to connect – carefully and with many qualifications – the history of overseas imperialism with that darkest endpoint of the German <italic>Sonderweg</italic>, the Holocaust, which had previously helped to marginalize colonial studies in Germany. The entangled and non-Eurocentric nature of modernity is persuasively illustrated by Shalini Randeria’s chapter on communitarian liberal democracy in postcolonial India. Randeria finds that, rather than pursuing a European path of state formation more or less successfully, as Eurocentric modernization theory might have it, India has, in fact, already addressed problems of civil society that Western states have only recently begun to consider. The liberalism so often regarded as a hallmark of the West is, Randeria suggests, neither particularly Western nor complete and stable, but rather continues to emerge transnationally, including on the terrain of the ‘uneven modernity’ of the postcolonial state.</p>
<p>The editors of this volume do not suggest with their selection of essays that transnational history is an entirely new approach or that it places a new methodological obligation on historians and invalidates comparative and other methodologies. Essays demonstrate the ongoing strength of more long-standing areas of transnational history, such as the history of migration, as well as the continued importance of comparative research that brackets out the entanglements that some might see as invalidating the comparisons.</p>
<p>The volume makes available to English readers an important ongoing discussion centred in Germany but having clear connections with international developments in historiography. I wish that these discussions would expand from methodology to theory, asking not only what and how historians have practiced or should practice, but also about the nature of historical knowledge and its objects. This would help connect the recent practice of historians to the long tradition of social and political theory with which it has always been – more or less consciously – entangled.</p>
<p><bold>Andrew Zimmerman</bold>, <italic>The George Washington University, Washington, DC</italic></p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>