<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjcc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0221</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-5422</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022022110395140</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0022022110395140</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Brief Reports</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Variable Preferences for Sexual Dimorphism in Stature (SDS) Might Not Be Universal</article-title>
<subtitle>Data From a Semi-Nomad Population (Himba) in Namibia</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Sorokowski</surname><given-names>Piotr</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0022022110395140">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sorokowska</surname><given-names>Agnieszka</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0022022110395140">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-0022022110395140">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>Bernhard</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0022022110395140">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0022022110395140">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Mberira</surname><given-names>Mara</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0022022110395140">4</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0022022110395140"><label>1</label>Institute of Psychology, University of Wroclaw, Wroclaw, Poland</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0022022110395140"><label>2</label>Department of Sociobiology/Anthropology, University of Goettingen, Göttingen, Germany</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0022022110395140"><label>3</label>Courant Research Center Evolution of Social Behavior, University of Goettingen, Göttingen, Germany</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0022022110395140"><label>4</label>University of Namibia</aff>
<aff id="aff5-0022022110395140"><label>5</label>Faculty of Management, Computer Science and Finance, Wroclaw University of Economics, Wroclaw, Poland</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0022022110395140">Piotr Sorokowski, University of Wroclaw, Dawida 1, Wroclaw 50-527 Poland. Email: <email>sorokowskipiotr@yahoo.co.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>43</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>32</fpage>
<lpage>37</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In Western societies women prefer relatively taller men as potential partners, whereas men prefer women to be slightly shorter than them. Here we report data on relative height preferences in a traditional ethnic group, i.e. the Himba, in which men and women do not show such a strong preference. Thus our data challenges the view of a universal preference for taller men, by suggesting that height preferences may be influenced by environmental and ecological conditions.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>body height</kwd>
<kwd>sexual dimorphism in stature (SDS)</kwd>
<kwd>mate preferences</kwd>
<kwd>Himba</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Evolutionary psychologists argue that body height is one of the most important characteristics of male physical attractiveness and may thus serve as an initial criterion for women to decide upon further interest and possible engagement in courtship. Body height is strongly sexually dimorphic across all human groups such that men are on average taller than women (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0022022110395140">Gray &amp; Wolfe, 1980</xref>). This sexual dimorphism is developed around puberty through the effect of testosterone on bone growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0022022110395140">Antoszewska &amp; Wolanski, 1992</xref>). Thus, the female preference for taller men might indicate that women derive certain cues from height that are associated with testosterone and that could provide them with certain fitness benefits. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0022022110395140">Pawlowski, Dunbar, and Lipowicz (2000)</xref> argue that there is active female selection for stature in male partners by showing that taller men are reproductively more successful than shorter men.</p>
<p>The association between male height and women’s perception of their attractiveness has been confirmed through both experimental studies (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0022022110395140">Graziano, Brothen, &amp; Berscheid, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0022022110395140">Shepperd &amp; Strathman, 1989</xref>) and the analysis of personal (“lonely hearts”) advertisements (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0022022110395140">Lynn &amp; Shurgot, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022022110395140">Salska et al., 2008</xref>). Men, in turn, at least in Western societies, seem to have a preference for women who are slightly shorter than them. Based on data of matrimonial offers in the United States, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0022022110395140">Cameron, Oskamp, and Sparks (1977)</xref> showed that men were searching for women who were smaller or around average height in the respective population, regardless of their own height. In a study of “lonely hearts” advertisements, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022022110395140">Pawlowski and Koziel (2002)</xref> found a negative correlation between women’s body height and the number of men (“candidates”) who were interested in these women (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0022022110395140">Shepperd &amp; Strathman, 1989</xref>).</p>
<p>Recent research has emphasized the significance of relative rather than absolute body height when studying men’s and women’s height preferences in a romantic relationship. Such research involves investigation of preferences towards the difference between one’s own height and the height of a preferred partner (sexual dimorphism in stature [SDS]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022022110395140">Fink, Neave, Brewer, &amp; Pawlowski, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022022110395140">Pawlowski, 2003</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022022110395140">Pawlowski (2003)</xref> studied SDS preferences in a Polish sample and found that both men and women adjust their SDS preferences according to their own body height. Moreover, no participant chose the option of a woman being slightly taller than a man. Similar results were reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022022110395140">Fink et al. (2007)</xref> in a study of German, Austrian, and British men and women, thus confirming the finding of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022022110395140">Pawlowski (2003)</xref>. Both studies argue that preference adjustment according to one’s own height could be regarded as a mechanism to increase the pool of potential partners. However, although these studies argue, to some extent, for a universal preference pattern with men being taller than women, they were only studied in Western societies.</p>
<p>To this date, only one study has reported data that challenge the universality of the “male-taller norm.” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0022022110395140">Sear and Marlowe (2009)</xref> reported that in the Hadza society (Tanzania), in 8.2% of 207 marriages the wife was taller than the husband. This is not different from the proportion of female-taller marriages than one would expect by chance, whereas the proportion of female-taller marriages in the United Kingdom, for example, is significantly lower than expected by chance. It is important to note, though, that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0022022110395140">Sear and Marlow’s (2009)</xref> study investigated height patterns in actual mate choice, not mate preferences like almost all of the other studies. This difference, as the authors note, may be important as preferences do not take into account the costs and constraints involved in acquiring a partner, such as availability of a partner and one’s own mate value.</p>
<p>Here we report data on men’s and women’s SDS preferences of a nomadic pastoral traditional ethnic group (i.e., the Himba of northern Namibia) that question the universality of the “male-taller norm.”</p>
<sec id="section1-0022022110395140" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section2-0022022110395140">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>The present study was conducted among the Himba (Ovahimba) tribe, a nomadic pastoral traditional ethnic group living in the northern part of Namibia (Africa). The Himba are one of few tribes in Africa who still preserve their traditional lifestyle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0022022110395140">Malan, 2004</xref>). Our participants were from Opuwo and villages around Opuwo, a region, which is only rarely visited by tourists.</p>
<p>Our sample comprised a total of 66 women aged between 15 and 80 years (<italic>M</italic> = 39.5, <italic>SD</italic> = 18.8) and 42 men between 17 and 76 years (<italic>M</italic> = 50.3, <italic>SD</italic> = 18). Age was provided by self-report (often the participants did not know exactly how old they were). The majority of the group was married (95% of males and 74% of females) and 72% of the men had more than one wife. Mean height of male participants was 174.8 cm (range: 161-186; <italic>SD</italic> = 7.33), and of female participants 165.8 cm (range: 154-182; <italic>SD</italic> = 5.54). All participants received a fee of some US$3 for their participation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0022022110395140">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>Participants were shown six pairs of silhouettes, depicting an opposite sex couple differing in SDS, calculated as the ratio of male height divided by female height. The SDS ratios ranged from 1.19 (i.e., the man being much taller than the woman) to 0.96 (i.e., the woman being slightly taller than the man), decreasing in steps of 0.05 (see for details on the material, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022022110395140">Fink et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022022110395140">Pawlowski, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>The participants were told that each pair represented partners in a romantic partnership where the partners differed in their relative body height. They were then asked to choose (a) the pair they would prefer as for their own (preferred) relationship and (b) the pair that corresponded to the actual size difference between them and their actual partner (if they were in a close relationship). Participants who were currently not in a close relationship were allowed to skip the second question, and men who had more than one partner were assessing the estimated average height of their partners. After completing this task, the participants were measured for their body height (in cm).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0022022110395140" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section5-0022022110395140">
<title>Men’s Preferences</title>
<p>Distribution of SDS choices was not random (χ<sup>2</sup> = 23.9, <italic>df</italic> = 5, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, <italic>V</italic> = .15). The largest proportion of male participants had a preference for an SDS of 1.0 (31%), i.e., that where men and women were of equal height, followed by a considerable number of males who preferred being partner in a romantic couple with an SDS of 0.96 (21.4%), i.e., where the woman was slightly taller than the man. SDS pairs where the men were taller than the women were less frequently preferred (SDS = 1.04 (16.6%), SDS = 1.09 (14.3%), SDS = 1.14 (11.9%), SDS = 1.19 (4.8%)) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0022022110395140">Figure 1</xref>). A two-way test for differences between two proportions indicated that the pair with an SDS = 1.0 was preferred significantly more frequently than the one with an SDS = 1.14 (<italic>p</italic> = .03, <italic>z</italic> = 2.1) and SDS = 1.19 (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01, <italic>z</italic> = 3.1). A close to significant difference was found for the pair with an SDS = 1.09 (<italic>p</italic> = .07, <italic>z</italic> = 1.8). Moreover the pair depicting an SDS = 0.96 was preferred more frequently than the one with an SDS = 1.19 (<italic>p</italic> = .02, <italic>z</italic> = 2.3). All other differences failed to reach statistical significance.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0022022110395140" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Percentages of SDS Figures Preferred by Men and Women</p>
<p>Note: SDS values &gt; 1 denote pairs with men being taller than women, and SDS of 1 refers to a pair where the man and the woman are of equal height, and an SDS &lt; 1 depicts a pair where the woman is taller than the man.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0022022110395140-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0022022110395140">
<title>Women’s Preferences</title>
<p>Like in men, the distribution of women’s SDS choices was not random (χ<sup>2</sup> = 25.9, df = 5, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .0001, <italic>V</italic> = .16). The largest proportion of female participants had a preference for an SDS = 1.0 (33,8%), i.e., for the figures where men and women were of equal height. The frequencies of choices of other SDS pairs were lower (SDS = 0.96 (13.8%), SDS = 1.14 (18.5%), SDS = 1.04 (13.8%), SDS = 1.19 (13.8%), SDS = 1.09 (6.2%)) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0022022110395140">Figure 1</xref>). Men who were of equal height to women (i.e., those with an SDS = 1.0) were preferred significantly more often in comparison to all other SDS figures (SDS = 0.96: <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01, <italic>z</italic> = 2.7; SDS = 1.04: <italic>p</italic> &lt;. 01, <italic>z</italic> = 2.7; SDS = 1.09: <italic>p</italic> &lt;. 001, <italic>z</italic> = 3.9; SDS = 1.14: <italic>p</italic> = 0.05, <italic>z</italic> = 2.0; SDS = 1.19: <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01, <italic>z</italic> = 2.7). Also, an SDS = 1.14 was preferred more often than an SDS = 1.09 (<italic>p</italic> = .03, <italic>z</italic> = 2.1). All the other differences failed to reach significance.</p>
<p>To test whether the preferred SDS was affected by one’s own body height, an ANCOVA was conducted, separately for males and females, with body height as the dependent variable, SDS preference as a factor, and weight and age as covariates. The adjustment of preferences in relation to own height was not significant (men: <italic>F</italic>5,34 = 0.18, <italic>p</italic> = .97; women <italic>F</italic>5,57 = 1.39, <italic>p</italic> = .24). However, we found that women who chose the highest SDS (woman considerably shorter than man) were shorter (162.4 cm) than other groups (from 165.9 to 170.3 cm). Still, the only significant difference in height was found in women that preferred SDS 1.19 and SDS 1.09 (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, Tukey’s LSD test). Considering age and weight, this did not significantly affect these results (all <italic>p</italic>s &gt; .05). Similar results were obtained with reports of SDS of actual partners as dependent variables. An analysis of correlations confirmed that the observed preferences were not significantly correlated with either own height (for males: <italic>r</italic> = −.09, <italic>p</italic> = .6; for females: <italic>r</italic> = .01, <italic>p</italic> = .9), age (for males: <italic>r</italic> = − .19, <italic>p</italic> = .2; for females: <italic>r</italic> = −.02, <italic>p</italic> = .8), or weight of the participants (for males: <italic>r</italic> = − .23, <italic>p</italic> = .2; for females: <italic>r</italic> = −.05, <italic>p</italic> =.7).</p>
<p>To check whether the observed preferences matched the ones in actual relationships in the Himba, the distributions of “choices of ideal partners” and “real partners” were compared. Among men and women who were in a relationship (<italic>N</italic> = 89), the distribution of choices of particular SDS figures representing dimorphism in their partnerships was as follows: SDS 1.19 (13%), SDS 1.14 (17%), SDS 1.09 (10%), SDS 1.04 (20%), SDS 1.0 (31%), and SDS 0.96 (11%). This distribution differed significantly from preferences of the male participants (χ<sup>2</sup> = 21, <italic>df</italic> = 5, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, <italic>V</italic> = .14), whereas it resembled preferences of the female participants (χ<sup>2</sup> = 4.5, <italic>df</italic> = 5, <italic>p</italic> = .48, <italic>V</italic> = .07).</p>
<p>We also tested whether the distribution of percentage of choices of each SDS pair obtained from the Himba people differed significantly from those of European samples reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022022110395140">Fink et al. (2007)</xref>. It was found that both male (χ<sup>2</sup> = 598.9, <italic>df</italic> = 5, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .0001, <italic>V</italic> = .77) and female participants (χ<sup>2</sup> = 593.6, <italic>df</italic> = 5, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .0001, <italic>V</italic> = .77) from Namibia had significantly different preferences towards presented SDS figures than the European sample.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0022022110395140" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our results show that Himba preferences for SDS differ from preferences in European samples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022022110395140">Fink et al., 2007</xref>). In the Himba tribe a significant percentage of participants (over 30%) preferred partners’ body height to be similar to their own, this being true for both men and women. However, in comparison to almost all previous findings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022022110395140">Fink et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022022110395140">Pawlowski, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0022022110395140">Pawlowski &amp; Koziel, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0022022110395140">Pierce, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0022022110395140">Salska et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0022022110395140">Shepperd &amp; Strathman, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0022022110395140">Swami et al., 2008</xref>), many Himba men preferred relatively taller women, which cannot be explained through the actual SDS in this tribe. The most common response in our sample (for both men and women) was a preference for the pair where men were taller than women (about 50% of participants). Some 30% of the sample preferred no height difference, and about 20% preferred the pair where the man is shorter than the woman. While this pattern basically follows the one reported in Western samples, it is noteworthy that in the Himba the “male-taller-norm” is less pronounced.</p>
<p>Moreover, and contrary to previous reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022022110395140">Fink et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022022110395140">Pawlowski, 2003</xref>), we found no evidence for an adjustment of SDS preferences in relation to one’s own height in women, as only the shortest women had preferences for a partner who was much taller than them. In men, even the tallest participants expressed preferences towards women taller than them, which is contrary to results obtained in Western cultures (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022022110395140">Fink et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022022110395140">Pawlowski, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>It is known that people’s variation in body height is affected not only by genetic differences but also by environmental influences. Lower height in humans can result from malnutrition, stress, or various infectious diseases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0022022110395140">Beard &amp; Blaser, 2002</xref>) and may therefore be a cue to low “quality” of an individual (in terms of health). This could be a reason why in adverse environmental conditions such as in the study site of the semi-desert areas of Kaokoland, northern Namibia, short women were not preferred. Men in Western countries choose female partners shorter than themselves possibly because they do not face the ecological constraints that are present in other societies, such as the Himba in Africa. Hence, height preferences of men and women in highly demanding environments, as in northern Namibia, may be shifted compared to the ones observed in Western cultures because of resources other than what is expressed through body height. This assumption seems to be supported also by the study on actual mate choice conducted among other indigenous society of the Hadza people (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0022022110395140">Sear &amp; Marlowe, 2009</xref>). Thus, the reported preferences of studies in Western societies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0022022110395140">Fink et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0022022110395140">Pawlowski, 2003</xref>) towards women shorter than men might be biased by a socioculturally affected stereotype that is altered by environmental and ecological conditions.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The authors declared that they had no conflicts of interests with respect to their authorship or the publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The first author (P.S.) was supported by Foundation for Polish Science and a grant of the University of Wroclaw.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Antoszewska</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolanski</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Sexual dimorphism in newborns and adults</article-title>. <source>Studies in Human Ecology</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beard</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blaser</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The ecology of height</article-title>. <source>Perspectives in Biology and Medicine</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>475</fpage>-<lpage>498</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oskamp</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <article-title>Courtship American style: Newspaper ads</article-title>. <source>The Family Coordinator</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neave</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pawlowski</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Variable preferences for sexual dimorphism in stature (SDS): Further evidence for an adjustment in relation to own height</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>2249</fpage>-<lpage>2257</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Height and sexual dimorphism of stature among human societies</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Physical Anthropology</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>441</fpage>-<lpage>456</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Graziano</surname><given-names>W. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brothen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berscheid</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <article-title>Height and attraction: Do men see women eye to eye?</article-title> <source>Journal of Personality</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>128</fpage>-<lpage>145</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shurgot</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>Responses to lonely hearts advertisements: Effects of reported physical attractiveness, physique, and coloration</article-title>. <source>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>349</fpage>-<lpage>357</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Malan</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Peoples of Namibia</source>. <publisher-loc>Windhouk</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rhino Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Body height and romantic attraction: A meta-analytic test of the male-taller norm</article-title>. <source>Social Behavior and Personality</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>143</fpage>-<lpage>149</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pawlowski</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Variable preferences for sexual dimorphism in height as a strategy for increasing the pool of potential partners in humans</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B</source>, <volume>270</volume>, <fpage>709</fpage>-<lpage>712</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pawlowski</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunbar</surname><given-names>R. I. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lipowicz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Evolutionary fitness: Tall men have more reproductive success</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>403</volume>, <fpage>156</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pawlowski</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koziel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The impact of traits offered in personal advertisements on response rates</article-title>. <source>Evolution and Human Behavior</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>139</fpage>-<lpage>149</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salska</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frederick</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pawlowski</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>K. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Conditional mate preferences: Factors influencing preferences for height</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>203</fpage>-<lpage>215</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sear</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marlowe</surname><given-names>F. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>How universal are human mate choices? Size doesn’t matter when Hadza foragers are choosing a mate</article-title>. <source>Biology Letters</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>606</fpage>-<lpage>609</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shepperd</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strathman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Attractiveness and height: The role of stature in dating preference, frequency of dating and perceptions of attractiveness</article-title>. <source>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>617</fpage>-<lpage>627</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0022022110395140">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swami</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Furnham</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balakumar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Canaway</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stanistreet</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Factors influencing preferences for height: A replication and extension</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>395</fpage>-<lpage>400</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>