<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">UAR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spuar</journal-id>
<journal-title>Urban Affairs Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1078-0874</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-8332</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1078087411428121</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1078087411428121</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Note</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reframing Regional Governance for Research and Practice</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>Kathryn A.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1078087411428121">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>William R.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1078087411428121">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1078087411428121"><label>1</label>University at Buffalo Regional Institute, State University of New York, Buffalo, NY, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1078087411428121"><label>2</label>National League of Cities, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1078087411428121">Kathryn A. Foster, University at Buffalo Regional Institute, c/o Brookings Institution, Metropolitan Policy Program, 1775 Massachusetts Avenue, NW, Washington, DC 20036 Email: <email>kafoster@buffalo.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-1078087411428121">
<p>Kathryn A. Foster is a Visiting Fellow in the Metropolitan Policy Program of The Brookings Institution and Senior Fellow and Immediate Past Director of the UB Regional Institute, a research and public policy center of the University at Buffalo, State University of New York. A member of the MacArthur Foundation Research Network on Building Resilient Regions, she is the author of <italic>The Political Economy of Special-Purpose Government</italic> (Georgetown University Press, 1997), <italic>Regionalism on Purpose</italic> (Lincoln Institute for Land Policy, 2001), and numerous articles, chapters, and reports on regional governance.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio2-1078087411428121">
<p>William R. Barnes is Director for Emerging Issues at the National League of Cities in Washington, D.C. He earned his PhD from the Maxwell School at Syracuse University and a BA from Oberlin College. He coauthored, with Larry C. Ledebur, <italic>The New Regional Economies: the U.S. Common Market and the Global Economy</italic> (SAGE, 1998). In May 2005, the <italic>Urban Affairs Review</italic> published his “Beyond Federal Urban Policy,” a 40th Anniversary Featured Essay. He is a member of the MacArthur Foundation’s Research Network on Building Resilient Regions, the Executive Council of the Urban Politics Section of the American Political Science Association, and the Editorial Board of <italic>Economic Development Quarterly</italic>.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>48</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>272</fpage>
<lpage>283</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The article proposes a framework to clarify and specify regional governance, a concept widely used but as yet inadequately formulated for research and practice. Using capacity and purpose rather than governance or governmental forms as a foundation, the framework identifies five dimensions—actor group, agenda, internal capacity, external capacity, and implementation experience—that together describe regional governance for a time, place, and policy goal.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>regions</kwd>
<kwd>governance</kwd>
<kwd>capacity</kwd>
<kwd>regional governance</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Over recent decades, interlocal and regional experience in the United States has changed in significant ways. The amount of such activity increased substantially. The focus shifted from government to governance and from governmental consolidation to problem solving. More recently, the Obama Administration avowed an interest in regional-scale policy and put money into relevant programs. Searches for interjurisdictional responses to the financial crisis and the recession have also brought new urgency to the topic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1078087411428121">Barnes 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1078087411428121">Peirce 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1078087411428121">Staley 2010</xref>). These accumulated changes fundamentally challenge the dominant ways of thinking about regional governance and highlight the need for more useful analytic frameworks.</p>
<p>Specifications of regional governance have typically comprised a range of forms that are used to implement collective action at the regional scale. Emblematic of this approach is <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1078087411428121">Walker’s (1987)</xref> classic 17-level typology of regional service delivery approaches ranging from relatively easy interventions (informal cooperation, private contracting) through modestly difficult interventions (functional transfers, annexation, multipurpose special districts) to the hardest interventions (structural change through consolidations or two-tier federations). In a voluminous literature spanning nearly a quarter century, other authors have elaborated elements of Walker’s typology in pieces spanning models of regional growth management to case studies of metropolitan regionalism. (For a representative sampling, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1078087411428121">McKinney and Johnson 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1078087411428121">Feiock and Carr 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1078087411428121">Kemp 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1078087411428121">Katz 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1078087411428121">Greenstein and Wiewel 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1078087411428121">Oakerson 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1078087411428121">Rothblatt and Sancton 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1078087411428121">Downs 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1078087411428121">Peirce 1993</xref>.)</p>
<p>Although the longstanding argument among metropolitan government, public choice, and new regionalist approaches has made a substantial contribution to understanding the relative benefits of alternative governmental arrangements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1078087411428121">Foster 2001</xref>), the debate over the <italic>forms</italic> of regional governance has probably taken us as far as it can. Continuing an evolution of thought increasingly emphasizing collaborative approaches to region-scale problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1078087411428121">Cooke and Morgan 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1078087411428121">Mason 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1078087411428121">Pastor, Benner, and Matsuoka 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1078087411428121">Visser 2002</xref>), we propose a reframing of regional governance, one that focuses less on structure and more on capacity and purpose. Capacity, in our formulation, is the attributes of regional governance that reflect how actors make decisions to organize, determine means of action, accumulate appropriate resources, and act on a specific regional problem or issue. Purpose is the goal regarding the problem or issue. We conceive regional governance as a complex, multifaceted politics, part of historical processes of adaptation in the political economy to changing environments and vicissitudes. This evolution manifests in various decision-making structures, modes of governing, attitudes, and outcomes across space and time.</p>
<p>We thus define regional governance as <italic>deliberate efforts by multiple actors to achieve goals in multi-jurisdiction environments</italic>. By this definition, regional governance</p>
<list id="list1-1078087411428121" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>crosses borders, by definition jurisdictional, and also often sectoral (public, private, nonprofit, academic) and/or functional (e.g., environment, economic, social);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>encompasses, but goes beyond, the institutions, tools, or structures that may establish and implement regional action; and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>involves purposes and goals—for example, solving a regional problem or seizing a regional opportunity—as the object of a regional governance effort.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>This definition builds on the insights derived from looking at politics in a place as a “regime.” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1078087411428121">Stone (2005)</xref> defines “an urban regime . . . as the informal arrangements through which a locality is governed.” While regime analysis has been useful to us in highlighting and analyzing the way that governance occurs, its focus on informal structures and processes aimed at actions within a single jurisdiction makes it incomplete for illuminating regional governance in the cross-boundary, multijurisdictional way that we define it. In a region, boundaries vary by the scope of the functional purpose. Further, there is no single government or an automatically authoritative institution for carrying out decisions; there is no formal entity at whose actions the “informal arrangements” are aimed. The process of regional governance is more tenuous, complex, and risky than it would likely be within a single jurisdiction.</p>
<p>By this definition, regional governance includes formal and informal actors in the private and civic sectors as well as governmental units that organize, engage, and act with others—in concert or in conflict—to seek a goal. Working toward a goal does not imply that multiple entities have the same motivations or aims. Regional governance entails the whole set of actors interacting to assess alternative courses of action and navigate their differences in addressing a problem or opportunity.</p>
<p>Our proposed framework will support analyses of regional governance as a dependent variable (<italic>Why do regions have different regional governance?</italic>) or independent variable (<italic>What effects does regional governance have?</italic>). Our primary focus in this article, however, is neither of these explanatory questions. Rather, we focus on the precursor descriptive question of <italic>What is regional governance?</italic></p>
<p>Our view is that regional governance varies by place, time, and goal, reflecting issue differentiation and evolution of alternative political economies and cultures. Regional governance is not necessarily effective or successful in achieving the goals of regional collective actors, and the analytic framework we present allows for such variety of outcomes.</p>
<sec id="section1-1078087411428121">
<title>A Regional Governance Framework</title>
<p>We hypothesize five dimensions and underlying indicators to measure regional governance for a particular place, time, and goal, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1078087411428121">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1078087411428121" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Dimensions and indicators of regional governance</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1078087411428121-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>Following a lineage of political analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1078087411428121">Long 1958</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1078087411428121">Dahl 1961</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1078087411428121">Stone 1993</xref>), the first dimension gauges characteristics of the <bold>Actor Group</bold> engaged on a goal. The actor group may vary from a formal entity with authority to a loose ad hoc set of individuals tackling a specific regional problem. Regardless of structure or formality, the salient measure is the wherewithal of actors to achieve their goal. This is gauged by three indicators. The first is <italic>actor group composition</italic>, measured by whether the set of people and organizations involved includes stakeholders needed for success in realizing the group goal. Determining which stakeholders are “needed to succeed” is case specific for a time, place, and goal; what constitutes an appropriate actor group will vary. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1078087411428121">Kooiman (2003</xref>, 11) notes, “day to day governance occurrences appear to be complex, layered interaction processes enacted between a variety of unpredictable actors with discrepant interests and ambitions.” Inclusiveness in the sense of including all stakeholders potentially affected by or interested in the goal—is not presumed. The second indicator gauges <italic>leadership</italic> for the group purpose, which may range from unacceptable—as could occur if no leadership structure is defined or if leadership is not widely sanctioned or recognized—to acceptable, as occurs when the leadership arrangement is widely known and satisfactory. The third actor group indicator assesses the degree of <italic>commitment to group and purpose</italic>. This does not imply that members of the group will or must have mutual regard, high degrees of consensus, and low levels of conflict. Although there is evidence that individuals may self-select into groups whose members and agenda are sympathetic with their own views (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1078087411428121">Henry, Lubell, and McCoy 2010</xref>) and that ideological differences within a group are positively associated with intragroup conflict (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1078087411428121">Grissom 2010</xref>), other findings suggest that such conflict is better managed and channeled in groups with high social capital and trust (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1078087411428121">Jehn and Mannix 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1078087411428121">Watson, Kumar, and Michaelsen 1993</xref>). Our view is that common commitment to work together, to stay at the table, toward a purpose over the relevant duration and despite differences is a core attribute of regional governance.</p>
<p>The second dimension captures the group <bold>Agenda</bold>, assessed by the purposefulness of its formulation and assessment and its popular understanding. Students of government have long noted that the articulation of an issue is critical to its achievement (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1078087411428121">Deutsch 1963</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1078087411428121">Greer 1963</xref>). Preventing mission creep, framing questions appropriately, understanding relevant choices, and presenting the agenda to achieve popular comprehension are core elements of agenda effectiveness. Relevant to this dimension are three indicators. The first captures the <italic>agenda framing</italic>, how effectively formulated are the vision, goals, alternatives, and priorities for the nature and severity of the regional goal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1078087411428121">Warriner 1965</xref>). Not all goals warrant a regional approach; pursuing a fundamentally trivial or local issue through a regional agenda can hamper progress on the issue. Moreover, an effective agenda framing need not be wholly clear or comprehensive. For some contexts and issues, limiting the options or purposefully keeping details vague could improve success in achieving the regional goal. A second indicator captures the <italic>agenda assessment</italic> by the actor group, ranging from incomplete or poor vetting to a thorough and deliberate consideration of agenda issues, scope, strategy, and tactics for goal achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1078087411428121">O’Leary-Kelly, Martocchio, and Frink 1994</xref>). The third agenda indicator gauges the degree to which there is <italic>popular comprehension of the agenda</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1078087411428121">Greer 1963</xref>). This does not imply popular support, which may be withheld, but rather widespread popular understanding of the topic and the regional nature of the agenda.</p>
<p>The third dimension, <bold>Internal Capacity</bold>, gauges the sufficiency of resources to achieve success on the specific goal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1078087411428121">Foster 2000</xref>). There are three kinds of internal capacity. One captures the sufficiency of <italic>money and resources</italic> to effect regional action. A second assesses whether the actor group has the necessary and sufficient <italic>information and expertise</italic>—data, people, insights, wisdom—to act effectively on the issue. A third gauges the degree to which the group has sufficient <italic>authority and legitimacy</italic> to make decisions and act (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1078087411428121">Pierre and Peters 2005</xref>, 46-48). Indicators of internal capacity do not necessarily track one another. A business-led group addressing regional economic development challenges may have money and information, but insufficient legitimacy or authority to achieve its aims. In contrast, a government-led group may have legitimacy and authority to decide on a course of action, but lack financial or information resources to act effectively.</p>
<p>The dimension of <bold>External Capacity</bold> captures the skills and reach of the actor group to connect to and secure external resources to support the group goal. This includes having sufficient political, economic, or intellectual influence to shape policy or program outcomes in favor of group aims at both the <italic>state</italic> and <italic>federal</italic> levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1078087411428121">Abbott 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1078087411428121">Orfield 1997</xref>). Such influence may come through the seniority or power of a region’s elected state or federal delegation as well as from inter-personal relationships between regional leaders and key elected, appointed, or professional players in the policy area. External capacity also measures a region’s <italic>connectedness</italic> through formal and informal channels to constituencies, organizations, peer regions, national and international foundations, and other connections useful in formulating, obtaining resources for, and achieving the regional goal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1078087411428121">Provan and Kenis 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>A final hypothesized dimension of regional governance is <bold>Implementation Experience</bold>. Presuming that experience increases the chances of effective region-scale action, one indicator is the sheer <italic>level of region-scale activity</italic> for the region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1078087411428121">Abbott 2000</xref>). A parallel indicator assesses the <italic>level of region-scale activity on this goal</italic>. Regions with experience addressing a regional goal—even if they have failed in the past—can draw insights and knowledge from prior efforts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1078087411428121">Savitch and Vogel 2004</xref>). A third indicator is the degree to which a region <italic>institutionalizes its experience</italic> in policies and processes, thus “normalizing” its habits of effective regional governance. A caution is that institutionalizing practices or structures does not automatically enhance regional governance. Irrelevant or inappropriate institutions can lock in a region to practices that ultimately hinder regional governance.</p>
<p>This proposed framework has several implications. First, it emphasizes factors of capacity and purpose in assessing regional governance, a focus that we believe is constructive for regional leaders and policy makers. By this emphasis, the framework deliberately shifts the conversation from the number or arrangement of local governments and regional entities to the concern with capacity to act at the regional scale across time and a range of issues. The framework still recognizes that governmental and governance structures constitute the forms, arrangements, and rules within which governance capacity operates, factors incorporated in indicators for the authority or legitimacy of the regional actors to act and the institutionalization of regional governance experience.</p>
<p>Second, the framework reinforces that regional governance for a specific region, time, and issue will vary. Because actors, conditions, and technologies change over time, a region’s governance of water resource management in 2012 might well differ from its governance of water resources in 1960. Regional governance for water resource management may likewise differ from governance for economic development, affordable housing, or other regional issues. And regional governance for economic development in 2012 is expected to vary for Chicago, Charlotte, and Cheyenne.</p>
<p>Third, although we hypothesize that for many regions regional governance will vary regularly and widely, the framework may reveal regions that tend toward a single style of regional governance across time or policy goal. Regions exhibiting consistent tendencies toward a particular regional governance style may have a governance “mode.” If so, the framework can contribute to ongoing debates about the nature and importance of political culture to regional outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1078087411428121">Hooghe 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Fourth, the regional governance framework permits examination of internal dynamics within and across the five dimensions. Researchers and policy leaders will be able to glean, for example, the relationship, if any, between actor group composition and its common commitment, to what degree having high external capacity may accord with high internal capacity, and how linked implementation experience is to having federal and state capacity. Follow-up empirical analysis may also reveal dimension- or indicator-level regional governance patterns and trends generally and by issue area. Plausible findings might be, for example, that a region’s track record matters for regional governance only rarely, that appropriate framing of the agenda always matters, or that acceptable leadership trumps other indicators of governance. Such discoveries will refine the framework.</p>
<p>Fifth, the proposed dimensions and indicators of capacity are not typically available in national databases. Perhaps imaginative proxies can be developed; for now, we assume measurements of regional governance will require assessments from people deeply knowledgeable about a region, its history, actors, and circumstances.</p>
<p>Finally, while our primary purpose is description of regional governance, we hypothesize that empirical applications would link stronger regional governance capacity with more positive regional outcomes. Future tests might also reveal combinations of regional governance indicators that are especially favorable for achieving certain regional goals. For example, regional governance marked by low state and federal influence and high popular comprehension may prove conducive to action on key regional economic goals, even while these characteristics of governance might hamper action in other circumstances. Illuminating such nuance would be an important aim of empirical analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1078087411428121">
<title>Concluding Note</title>
<p>We offer a regional governance framework to facilitate analysis and provide a platform that consolidates the movement of practitioner and research discussion beyond a focus on governmental and governance forms to questions of capacity and purpose. Our hypothesized specification contains five dimensions, each with three indicators.</p>
<p>For researchers, the proposed framework highlights patterns in regional governance by goal, differences in regional governance within a single region across goals, and regional governance trends over time for a region, group of regions, or goals. A more clearly specified and measurable concept of regional governance opens the way for hypothesis testing regarding regional governance as a dependent or independent variable.</p>
<p>For regional practitioners, the proposed framework highlights key aspects of regional governance and facilitates strategic discussion about regional capacity. The framework could help local actors address such questions as: How does my region compare to others in general and with regard to specific dimensions and indicators? On the various indicators of my region’s governance capacity, which ones are likely to change in the near future? How will that affect the potential for effective action? Which dimensions or indicators might our region enhance for best effect? We believe that some such analysis is already practiced, at least informally, by proficient regional governance actors. Feedback loops from practice to research would also hone the framework.</p>
<p>In the end, we intend the framework to inspire fresh thinking about regional governance. We invite refinements and applications to advance this work.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article:</p>
<p>Funding for work on this paper was provided by the MacArthur Foundation through the Research Network on Building Resilient Regions.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>Carl</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1983</year>. <source>Portland: Planning, politics, and growth in a twentieth century city</source>. <publisher-name>Univ. of Nebraska Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>Carl</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2000</year>. The capital of good planning: Metropolitan Portland, Oregon since <year>1970</year>. In <source>The American planning tradition: Culture and policy</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Woodrow Wilson Center and Johns Hopkins Univ. Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>William</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>Emerging issues: Obama’s urban policy ideas</article-title>. <source>Nation’s Cities Weekly</source>, <month>July</month> <day>27</day>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National League of Cities</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>Philip</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1998</year>. <source>The associational economy: Firms, regions and innovation</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford Univ. Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>Robert A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1961</year>. <source>Who governs? Democracy and power in an American city</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale Univ. Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deutsch</surname><given-names>Karl W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1963</year>. <source>The nerves of government: Models of political communication and control</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>Anthony</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1994</year>. <source>New visions for metropolitan America</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brookings Institution and Lincoln Institute of Land Policy</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Feiock</surname><given-names>Rick</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>Jered</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <year>2004</year>. <source>Reshaping the local landscape: Perspective on city county consolidation and its alternatives</source>. <publisher-loc>Armonk, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>M.E. Sharpe</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>Kathryn A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2000</year>. <article-title>Regional capital</article-title>. In <source>Urban-suburban interdependencies</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Greenstein</surname><given-names>Rosalind</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wieviel</surname><given-names>Wim</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lincoln Institute of Land Policy</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>Kathryn A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2001</year>. <source>Regionalism on purpose</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lincoln Institute of Land Policy</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Greenstein</surname><given-names>Rosalind</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wim</surname><given-names>Wiewel</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds., <year>2000</year>. <source>Urban-suburban interdependencies</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lincoln Institute of Land Policy</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>Scott</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1963</year>. <source>Metropolitics: A study of political culture</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grissom</surname><given-names>Jason A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2010</year>. <article-title>The determinants of conflict on governing boards in public organizations: The case of California school boards</article-title>. <source>Journal of Public Administration Research and Theory</source> <volume>20</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>601</fpage>-<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>Adam Douglas</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lubell</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Belief systems and social capital as drivers of policy network structure: The case of California regional planning</article-title>. <source>Journal of Public Administration Research and Theory</source>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jpart.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2010/08/20/jopart.muq042.abstract">http://jpart.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2010/08/20/jopart.muq042.abstract</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed January 6, 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hooghe</surname><given-names>Marc</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>Why there is basically only one form of political trust</article-title>. <source>The British Journal of Politics &amp; International Relations</source> <volume>13</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jehn</surname><given-names>Karen A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mannix</surname><given-names>Elizabeth A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2001</year>. <article-title>The dynamic nature of conflict: A longitudinal study of intragroup conflict and group performance</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Journal</source> <volume>44</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>238</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>Bruce J.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ed. <year>2000</year>. <source>Reflections on regionalism</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brookings Institution Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>Roger L.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ed. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>Regional government innovations</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Jefferson, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MacFarland &amp; Company</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kooiman</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>Governing as governance</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Norton E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1958</year>. <article-title>The local community as an ecology of games</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source> <volume>64</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>251</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>Robert J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2008</year>. <source>Collaborative land use management: The quieter revolution in place-based planning</source>. <publisher-loc>Lanham, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rowman &amp; Littlefield</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McKinney</surname><given-names>Matthew J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Shawn</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <source>Working across boundaries: People, nature, and regions</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lincoln Institute of Land Policy</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oakerson</surname><given-names>Ronald J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1999</year>. <source>Governing local public economies: Creating the civic metropolis</source>. <publisher-loc>Oakland, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ICS Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Leary-Kelly</surname><given-names>Anne M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martocchio</surname><given-names>Joseph J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frink</surname><given-names>Dwight D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1994</year>. <article-title>A review of the influence of group goals on group performance</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Journal</source> <volume>37</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>1285</fpage>-<lpage>1301</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Orfield</surname><given-names>Myron</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1997</year>. <article-title>Metropolitics: A regional agenda for community and stability</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lincoln Institute of Land Policy and Brookings Institution</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pastor</surname><given-names>Manuel</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Benner</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>Martha</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>This could be the start of something big: How social movements for metropolitan equity are reshaping metropolitan America</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell Univ. Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peirce</surname><given-names>Neal R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> with <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Curtis W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>John Stuart</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1993</year>. <source>Citistates: How urban America can prosper in a competitive world</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Seven Locks Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peirce</surname><given-names>Neal</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>An era of federal opportunity for cities and regions?</article-title> <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.Citiwire.net">www.Citiwire.net</ext-link></comment>, <month>February</month> <fpage>13</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pierre</surname><given-names>Jon</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>B. Guy</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <source>Governing complex societies: Trajectories and scenarios</source>. <publisher-loc>Hampshire, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Provan</surname><given-names>Keith G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kenis</surname><given-names>Patrick</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>Modes of network governance: Structure, management and effectiveness</article-title>. <source>Journal of Public Administration Research and Theory</source> <volume>18</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Rothblatt</surname><given-names>Donald N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sancton</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <year>1998</year>. <source>Metropolitan governance revisited: American/Canadian intergovernmental perspectives</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Univ. of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Savitch</surname><given-names>H.V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>Ronald K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2004</year>. <article-title>Suburbs without a city: Power and city-county consolidation</article-title>. <source>Urban Affairs Review</source> <volume>39</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>758</fpage>-<lpage>90</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Staley</surname><given-names>Willy</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Urban nation</article-title>. <source>Next American City</source> <volume>29</volume> (<issue>Winter</issue>). <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://americancity.org/magazine/article/urban-nation/">http://americancity.org/magazine/article/urban-nation/</ext-link></comment> (<access-date>accessed April 15, 2011</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>Clarence</given-names></name>
</person-group> .<year>1993</year>. <article-title>Urban regimes and the capacity to govern: A political economy approach</article-title>. <source>Journal of Urban Affairs</source> <volume>15</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>Clarence</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <article-title>Looking back to look forward: Reflections on urban regime analysis</article-title>. <source>Urban Affairs Review</source> <volume>40</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>James A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2002</year>. <article-title>Understanding local government cooperation in urban regions</article-title>. <source>American Review of Public Administration</source> <volume>32</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>40</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>David B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1987</year>. <article-title>Snow White and the 17 Dwarfs: From metro cooperation to governance</article-title>. <source>National Civic Review</source> <volume>76</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>14</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Warriner</surname><given-names>Charles K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1965</year>. <article-title>The problem of organizational purpose</article-title>. <source>Sociological Quarterly</source> <volume>6</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>139</fpage>-<lpage>143</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1078087411428121">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>Warren E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Kamalesh</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Michaelsen</surname><given-names>Larry K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1993</year>. <article-title>“Cultural diversity’s impact on interaction process and performance: Comparing homogenous and diverse task groups</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Journal</source> <volume>36</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>590</fpage>-<lpage>602</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>