<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GCQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spgcq</journal-id>
<journal-title>Gifted Child Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0016-9862</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1934-9041</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0016986211429169</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0016986211429169</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Forced Choice Dilemma</article-title>
<subtitle>A Model Incorporating Idiocentric/Allocentric Cultural Orientation</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Jae Yup</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0016986211429169">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0016986211429169">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>Miraca U. M.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0016986211429169">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0016986211429169"><label>1</label>The University of New South Wales, Sydney, New South Wales, Australia</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0016986211429169"><label>2</label>University of Wollongong, Wollongong, New South Wales, Australia</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0016986211429169">Jae Yup Jung, School of Education, The University of New South Wales, Sydney, New South Wales 2052, Australia Email: <email>jae.jung@unsw.edu.au</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-0016986211429169">
<p>Jae Yup Jung, PhD, is a lecturer in the School of Education at The University of New South Wales, Australia. His major research interest is in the decision making of both gifted and nongifted adolescents on topics such as careers, university entrance, and friendships, usually incorporating motivational and cultural perspectives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio2-0016986211429169">
<p>John McCormick, PhD, is an associate professor in the Faculty of Education at the University of Wollongong, Australia. His primary research interests are focused on human motivation, including motivation to learn, social cognition, decision making, and cross-cultural differences in educational and organizational settings.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio3-0016986211429169">
<p>Miraca U. M. Gross, PhD, is the director of the Gifted Education Research, Resource and Information Centre at The University of New South Wales, Australia. Her research in gifted education centers on socioaffective development, the highly gifted, and the academic and socioaffective outcomes of ability grouping and acceleration.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>56</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>15</fpage>
<lpage>24</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 National Association for Gifted Children</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">National Association for Gifted Children</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This study developed and tested a new model of the forced choice dilemma (i.e., the belief held by some intellectually gifted students that they must choose between academic achievement and peer acceptance) that incorporates individual-level cultural orientation variables (i.e., vertical allocentrism and vertical idiocentrism). A survey that had previously been administered to a sample of intellectually gifted Australian adolescents was modified and then administered to a new sample of 450 intellectually gifted Australian students enrolled in Grades 7 through 12. The data were analyzed using structural equation modeling procedures. The major findings of the study were that: (a) motivation for academic success and need for peer acceptance generally predict the experience of the forced choice dilemma, and (b) vertical allocentric and vertical idiocentric orientations strongly predict motivation for academic success. The findings of the study provide insights that may assist educators, psychologists, counselors, and family members to better understand, and guide, intellectually gifted students affected by the forced choice dilemma.</p>
<p><bold>Putting the Research to Use</bold></p>
<p>Educators, psychologists, counselors, and families may be able to use the model developed and confirmed in this study to better understand how some intellectually gifted students experience the dilemma arising from a perceived conflict between academic achievement and peer acceptance. The model provides insights on how specific cultural orientations of students may play a part in how the dilemma is experienced. It appears that intellectually gifted students who value human inequality and interdependence are more able to resolve the dilemma; hence, attention in this realm should be focused on those students who place greater importance on human equality and/or independence, for whom the dilemma may be a more difficult issue.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>gifted education</kwd>
<kwd>forced choice dilemma</kwd>
<kwd>cultural orientation</kwd>
<kwd>idiocentrism</kwd>
<kwd>allocentrism</kwd>
<kwd>Australia</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The <italic>forced choice dilemma</italic> refers to the choice that some intellectually gifted students believe they must make between the needs for acceptance by peers and the pursuit of high-level academic achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0016986211429169">Gross, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0016986211429169">1998</xref>). The focus of the study reported here was the development and testing of a model that examined the role of idiocentric/allocentric cultural orientation on the experience of the phenomenon. The research was motivated by evidence suggesting that people with different cultural orientations may place different emphases on one element of the forced choice dilemma: the importance of academic achievement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0016986211429169">Boykin et al., 2005</xref>). The study addresses the existing deficiency in the literature in the area (a concentration on intellectually gifted students of particular backgrounds and orientations) while attempting to gain a clearer understanding of how cultural orientation is related to the phenomenon for intellectually gifted students.</p>
<sec id="section1-0016986211429169">
<title>Forced Choice Dilemma</title>
<p>Some intellectually gifted students appear to perceive a conflict between the pursuit of academic success and the maintenance of friendships with, or acceptance by, their average-ability peers. Such students may feel that high levels of academic performance may lead to negative or hostile attitudes toward them from their peers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0016986211429169">Benbow &amp; Stanley, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0016986211429169">Buescher &amp; Higham, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0016986211429169">Cross, Coleman, &amp; Terhaar-Yonkers, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0016986211429169">Gross, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0016986211429169">1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0016986211429169">Hollingworth, 1926</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0016986211429169">Janos &amp; Robinson, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0016986211429169">Swiatek, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0016986211429169">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0016986211429169">Swiatek &amp; Dorr, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0016986211429169">Tannenbaum, 1983</xref>). Researchers have investigated the responses of intellectually gifted students toward such perceived conflicts under various labels, including “social adjustment” and “social coping strategies” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0016986211429169">Buescher &amp; Higham, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0016986211429169">Chan, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0016986211429169">Cross et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0016986211429169">Swiatek, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0016986211429169">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0016986211429169">Swiatek &amp; Dorr, 1998</xref>). An intellectually gifted student’s perceived need to use social adjustment or coping strategies in the face of possible social difficulties was conceptualized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0016986211429169">Gross (1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0016986211429169">1998</xref>) as giving rise to the “forced choice dilemma.” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0016986211429169">Gross (1989)</xref> described the phenomenon as a dilemma faced by intellectually gifted students “through the interaction of the psychosocial drives for (acceptance) and achievement, which complement each other in students of average ability, but which place the gifted student in a forced choice situation” (p. 189).</p>
<p>Most of the research related to the forced choice dilemma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0016986211429169">Benbow &amp; Stanley, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0016986211429169">Buescher &amp; Higham, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0016986211429169">Cross et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0016986211429169">Foust, Hertberg-Davis, &amp; Callahan, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0016986211429169">Gross, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0016986211429169">1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0016986211429169">Hollingworth, 1926</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0016986211429169">Janos &amp; Robinson, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0016986211429169">Rudasill, Foust, &amp; Callahan, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0016986211429169">Swiatek, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0016986211429169">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0016986211429169">Swiatek &amp; Dorr, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0016986211429169">Tannenbaum, 1983</xref>) has been undertaken in Western societies where substantial segments of the population may have anti-intellectual attitudes. Some Westerners have been noted, on occasion, to show rejection and hostility toward students engaging in intellectual activities with high levels of success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0016986211429169">Hofstadter, 1964</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0016986211429169">Winner, 1996</xref>); this may take the form of indifference, stereotyping, taunting, and/or intimidation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0016986211429169">Janos &amp; Robinson, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0016986211429169">Schroeder-Davis, 1983</xref>) unless the pursuit of intellectual activities is accompanied by (and mediated by) peer-approved activities such as sport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0016986211429169">Carrington, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0016986211429169">Tannenbaum, 1983</xref>). Intellectually gifted students living in Western societies may thus find the need for acceptance by peers to be in opposition to the need for academic achievement. These conflicts or tensions may result in intellectually gifted students believing that instead of being able to pursue both needs synchronously, it is necessary to exercise a “forced choice” between them.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0016986211429169">
<title>Need for Peer Acceptance/ Motivation for Academic Success</title>
<p>Most of the existing literature on the forced choice dilemma has focused mainly on the conceptualization of the phenomenon; few studies have investigated the decision-making processes used by intellectually gifted students in their attempts to resolve the dilemma. We propose that insight into this process may be gained by examining the phenomenon through the interplay of two constructs that have been labeled <italic>need for peer acceptance</italic> and <italic>motivation for academic success</italic>. The constructs were derived from elements (i.e., “motivation” and “peers”) of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0016986211429169">Gagné’s (2004)</xref> Differentiated Model of Giftedness and Talent.</p>
<p>The forced choice dilemma may not arise if the average ability peers of intellectually gifted students accept, or tolerate, high levels of academic achievement. In such situations, intellectually gifted students may feel permitted to simultaneously pursue both their motivation for academic success and need for peer acceptance. In contrast, if the average-ability peers of intellectually gifted students have negative attitudes toward high-level academic achievement, either the intellectually gifted students’ motivation for academic success or their need for peer acceptance may have to be compromised. The ultimate choice may depend on the relative importance placed on the two alternatives. Some students may adopt the strategy of “masking” their giftedness and developing identities that are acceptable to their anti-intellectual peers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0016986211429169">Cross et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0016986211429169">Gross, 1989</xref>). Others may choose to pursue their academic interests even with the risk of not attaining peer acceptance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0016986211429169">Gross, 1998</xref>).</p>
<p>The forced choice dilemma may be problematic for gifted students as “often neither [need] is [fully] satisfied” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0016986211429169">Gross, 1989</xref>, p. 193). For those who respond to the dilemma by masking their giftedness, meeting the need for acceptance by peers may be associated with emotional frustration resulting from portraying identities at odds with their true identities and levels of development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0016986211429169">Gross, 1998</xref>). For those who respond by pursuing academic achievement, the possible lack of intimate peer relationships may have detrimental social impacts, which could then reduce their ability to fully realize their academic potential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0016986211429169">Gross, 1989</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0016986211429169">
<title>Culture</title>
<p>As most existing research related to the forced choice dilemma has focused on intellectually gifted students with Anglo-Saxon/Celtic or European backgrounds living in Western societies, the current understanding of the phenomenon may not necessarily reflect the experience of intellectually gifted students from other cultures, cultural backgrounds, or cultural orientations. Culture is complex and has been defined in different ways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0016986211429169">Triandis, 1996</xref>). Nevertheless, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0016986211429169">Triandis (1996)</xref> noted that “there is wide agreement that culture consists of <italic>shared</italic> elements that provide the standards for perceiving, believing, evaluating, communicating, and acting among those who share a common language, a historic period, and a geographical location” (p. 408).</p>
<p>A widely accepted model for studying culture, using a classification system based on values, was developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0016986211429169">Hofstede (2001)</xref>. Hofstede identified five interrelated dimensions of culture: individualism/collectivism, power distance, uncertainty avoidance, masculinity/femininity, and long-term/short-term orientation. The model has endured repeated applications and tests over a substantial period of time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0016986211429169">Dimmock &amp; Walker, 2005</xref>). Each dimension of culture identified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0016986211429169">Hofstede (2001)</xref> reflects different issues faced by a range of cultures, for which different solutions may exist.</p>
<p>Extensive research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0016986211429169">Coon &amp; Kemmelmeier, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0016986211429169">Gaines et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0016986211429169">Hartung, Fouad, Leong, &amp; Hardin, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0016986211429169">Shuluf, Hattie, &amp; Dixon, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0016986211429169">Singelis, Triandis, Bhawuk, &amp; Gelfand, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0016986211429169">Triandis, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0016986211429169">1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0016986211429169">1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0016986211429169">Triandis, Chan, Bhawuk, Iwao, &amp; Sinha, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0016986211429169">Triandis &amp; Gelfand, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0016986211429169">Triandis, Leung, Villereal, &amp; Clack, 1985</xref>) has been conducted using the dimension of individualism/collectivism. Individualism was defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0016986211429169">Triandis (1995)</xref> as follows:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>A social pattern that consists of loosely linked individuals, who view themselves as independent of collectives; are primarily motivated by their own preferences, needs, rights, and the contracts they have established with others; give priority to personal goals over the goals of others; and emphasize the rational analyses of the advantages and disadvantages to associating with others. (p. 2)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Collectivism, on the other hand, was defined as follows:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>A social pattern consisting of closely linked individuals who see themselves as being part of one or more collectives (family, co-worker, tribe, or nation); are primarily motivated by the norms of, and duties imposed by, those collectives; are willing to give priority to the goals of these collectives over their own personal goals; and emphasize their connectedness with members of these collectives. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0016986211429169">Triandis, 1995</xref>, p. 2)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>These definitions reflect several important attributes of individualism and collectivism, including (a) the definition of the self (interdependent in collectivism and independent in individualism), (b) the priority of goals (priority given to group goals by collectivists and to personal goals by individualists), and (c) determinants of social behavior (emphasis on social norms by collectivists and personal attitudes by individualists; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0016986211429169">Triandis, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0016986211429169">Triandis &amp; Gelfand, 1998</xref>).</p>
<p>Several researchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0016986211429169">Singelis et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0016986211429169">Triandis, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0016986211429169">Triandis &amp; Gelfand, 1998</xref>) have identified two distinct dimensions of individualism/collectivism: a <italic>horizontal</italic> dimension emphasizing equality and the need for people to be similar in all characteristics, and a <italic>vertical</italic> dimension emphasizing hierarchy between individuals and an assumption that each individual is different. Support for the validity of these dimensions has been demonstrated through research conducted in both Western and Eastern societies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0016986211429169">Hartung et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0016986211429169">Singelis et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0016986211429169">Triandis &amp; Gelfand, 1998</xref>).</p>
<p>Individualism and collectivism combine with the horizontal and vertical dimensions to produce four different cultural constructs: <italic>horizontal individualism</italic>, <italic>horizontal collectivism</italic>, <italic>vertical individualism</italic>, and <italic>vertical collectivism</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0016986211429169">Triandis &amp; Gelfand, 1998</xref>). These cultural constructs reflect different combinations of the cultural characteristics of equality/inequality and independence/interdependence. It is important to note that the terms <italic>individualism</italic> and <italic>collectivism</italic> are usually confined to defining phenomena at the level of culture and groups of individuals in societies rather than at the individual level, which is arguably more relevant to this study.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0016986211429169">Triandis (1995)</xref> suggested the terms <italic>idiocentrism</italic> and <italic>allocentrism</italic> to represent individualism and collectivism, respectively, at the level of the individual. As with individualism and collectivism, idiocentrism and allocentrism may have horizontal and vertical dimensions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0016986211429169">Alavi &amp; McCormick, 2007</xref>). <italic>Horizontal idiocentrism</italic> refers to the valuing of equality and independence, <italic>horizontal allocentrism</italic> refers to the valuing of equality and interdependence, <italic>vertical idiocentrism</italic> refers to the valuing of inequality and independence, and <italic>vertical allocentrism</italic> refers to the valuing of inequality and interdependence.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0016986211429169">
<title>Theoretical Framework and Hypotheses</title>
<p>Intellectually gifted students of different horizontal and vertical idiocentric and allocentric orientations may experience the forced choice dilemma differently, as these orientations may influence attitudes toward peers and academic achievement. For example, students with either horizontal <italic>allocentric</italic> or vertical <italic>allocentric</italic> orientations may be more likely than those with either horizontal <italic>idiocentric</italic> or vertical <italic>idiocentric</italic> orientations to place importance on connectedness with peers, have concerns about responsibilities to peers, and attempt to preserve relationships with peers, as they are likely to be concerned about maintaining close linkages with others. Additionally, students with <italic>vertical</italic> dimensions in their idiocentric or allocentric orientations may be more likely than those with <italic>horizontal</italic> dimensions to be more comfortable with having superior intellectual ability and academic performance compared with peers, as they are likely to be comfortable with inequality among individuals.</p>
<p>A theoretical framework based on the arguments developed above was devised to guide the study. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0016986211429169">Figure 1</xref> schematically depicts the theoretical framework and identifies the constructs to be investigated. First, we propose that the forced choice dilemma is predicted by intellectually gifted students’ motivation for academic success and need for peer acceptance.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0016986211429169" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Theoretical framework</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0016986211429169-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<list id="list1-0016986211429169" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 1:</italic> Motivation for academic success will positively predict the experience of the forced choice dilemma.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 2:</italic> Need for peer acceptance will positively predict the experience of the forced choice dilemma.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>In turn, we propose that intellectually gifted students with vertical idiocentric/allocentric orientations are likely to be more comfortable with superior academic performance than students with horizontal dimensions and, consequently, may maintain strong motivations for academic success.</p>
<list id="list2-0016986211429169" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 3:</italic> Vertical allocentricism will positively predict motivation for academic success.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 4:</italic> Vertical idiocentrism will positively predict motivation for academic success.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Finally, we propose that intellectually gifted students with allocentric orientations (i.e., both vertical allocentrics and horizontal allocentrics) are likely to value interdependence and interconnectedness with salient social groups such as peers at school and are, consequently, likely to maintain strong needs for peer acceptance.</p>
<list id="list3-0016986211429169" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 5:</italic> Vertical allocentrism will positively predict need for peer acceptance.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Hypothesis 6:</italic> Horizontal allocentrism will positively predict need for peer acceptance.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Note that horizontal idiocentrism was not included in the theoretical framework, as unlike vertical allocentrism, vertical idiocentrism, and horizontal allocentrism, we did not identify any a priori argument for the existence of positive relationships between horizontal idiocentrism and the noncultural orientation variables of interest to the study. That is, intellectually gifted students with horizontal idiocentric orientations may not have strong motivations for academic success because of their expected discomfort with superior academic performance and human inequality. Simultaneously, such students may not have strong needs for peer acceptance because of the importance they are likely to place on personal independence.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0016986211429169" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section6-0016986211429169">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>The population of interest was intellectually gifted students attending secondary schools (Grades 7 to 12) in Australia. The investigators used a database maintained by the Gifted Education Research, Resource, and Information Centre at The University of New South Wales of past participants of two talent searches that used above-level assessment in mathematics, science, English vocabulary, and reading comprehension: the Australian Secondary Schools Educational Talent Search (ASSETS) and the Australian Primary Talent Search (APTS). Students qualify for ASSETS/APTS testing through a range of admission criteria, including a score at or above the 95th percentile in an IQ or standardized achievement test or being in receipt of an academic scholarship. The students who participated in these talent searches in 2007, and who would be in Grades 7 through 12 in the year of data collection (2009), were selected by the investigators for the study.</p>
<p>A written questionnaire and information package was mailed to all participants for self-administration. Two weeks after the original mailing, the package was resent with a reminder to those participants who had not responded. Of the 1,058 high school students who were sent the package, 502 participants returned written parental/guardian consent forms <italic>and</italic> completed questionnaires. Nevertheless, 49 questionnaires were discarded, as they were returned by students attending fully academically selective schools—an environment in which the forced choice dilemma is logically less likely to be experienced. Three others were discarded, as the students were homeschooled. Consequently, the sample submitted to analysis comprised 450 participants. These were aged between 11 and 17 years (<italic>M</italic> = 13.96; <italic>SD</italic> = 1.59), slightly more were male (59%; <italic>n</italic> = 264), more were in the earlier grades (i.e., 131 in Grade 7, 105 in Grade 8, 55 in Grade 9, 78 in Grade 10, 68 in Grade 11, and 13 in Grade 12), and most were Australian born (92%; <italic>n</italic> = 410). Approximately 71% had Anglo-Saxon/Celtic ancestry, 5% had East Asian ancestry, 4% had non–Anglo-Saxon/Celtic Western European ancestry, 3% had South Asian ancestry, 2% had Southeast Asian ancestry, and 12% had mixed ancestry. It is likely that there was an overrepresentation of participants with higher socioeconomic backgrounds, as they may have been more able to meet the costs associated with ASSETS and APTS.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0016986211429169">
<title>Instrument</title>
<p>The instrument was a modified version of the one used in a previous related study undertaken by the authors on the forced choice dilemma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0016986211429169">Jung, Barnett, Gross, &amp; McCormick, 2011</xref>). The items used in the original instrument, and adapted for this study, came from a number of well-established instruments with proven psychometric properties (i.e., the Network of Relationship Inventories [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0016986211429169">Furman &amp; Buhrmester, 1985]</xref> to assess need for peer acceptance, an untitled instrument developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0016986211429169">Singelis et al. [1995]</xref> to assess idiocentrism/allocentrism, and the Social Coping Questionnaire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0016986211429169">Swiatek, 1995</xref>] to assess other constructs, including the forced choice dilemma). The Cronbach alpha values of the scales used in the previous study ranged from .46 to .81.</p>
<p>During the process of modifying the instrument, items that were retained in the factor analysis and multiple regression analysis of the previous, related, study were carefully reexamined. First, items designed to assess constructs that were not considered essential for this study (e.g., horizontal idiocentrism) were discarded. Second, items retained were supplemented with new items developed by the authors to ensure that at least six items were designed to assess each construct. The procedure was necessary to improve scales for constructs such as vertical allocentrism (α = .46, and only two loading items). Finally, some of the items were slightly modified to more appropriately assess the constructs of interest.</p>
<p>The final modified instrument comprised a total of 51 items. Of these, 8 items were designed to assess horizontal allocentrism (e.g., “It is important to maintain harmony with my group of friends”), 6 items were designed to assess vertical idiocentrism (e.g., “It is important that I do better at school than others”), 6 items were designed to assess vertical allocentrism (e.g., “I usually sacrifice my self-interest for the benefit of my group of friends”), 6 items were designed to assess motivation for academic success (e.g., “Doing well academically at school is important to me”), 7 items were designed to assess need for peer acceptance (e.g., “I don’t worry about whether or not I am popular; 5 of the 7 items assessing this construct were phrased in this direction), and 10 items were designed to assess the forced choice dilemma (e.g., “I would fit in better at school if I were not academically gifted”). Participants responded to these items using a 7-point Likert-type scale, ranging from 1 = <italic>strongly disagree</italic> to 7 = <italic>strongly agree</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0016986211429169">
<title>Method of Analysis</title>
<p>PASW Statistics (Version 18.0) was used to enter, screen, and clean the data. Thereafter, the data were imported into LISREL (Version 8.80) to specify and estimate measurement and structural equation models. The small number of cases with missing data (i.e., 68 cases, or 0.25% of total data) justified the use of the listwise deletion method.</p>
<p>The theoretical framework that guided the study was tested using a two-step process: (a) the estimation and optimization of a full measurement model and (b) the estimation and optimization of a structural equation model of the theoretical framework. The diagonally weighted least squares method of estimation was used for all models, as it has been acknowledged to be the most appropriate for the ordinal-type data that were collected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0016986211429169">Hair, Black, Babin, &amp; Anderson, 2010</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0016986211429169" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section10-0016986211429169">
<title>Measurement Models</title>
<p>Initially, a full measurement model that comprised the instrument items designed to assess the six constructs of interest was estimated. Thereafter, the model was optimized by the progressive removal of items when the following criteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0016986211429169">Byrne, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0016986211429169">Weston &amp; Gore, 2006</xref>) were not met:</p>
<list id="list4-0016986211429169" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The <italic>t</italic> statistic of each measurement equation was at least 1.96.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> value of each measurement equation was between .30 and 1.00.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Most of the prespecified goodness-of-fit statistics were “good” (i.e., small values of root mean square error of approximation [RMSEA] and standardized root mean square residual [SRMR], and normed fit index [NFI], nonnormed fit index [NNFI], comparative fit index [CFI], goodness-of-fit index [GFI], and adjusted goodness-of-fit index [AGFI] values close to 1; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0016986211429169">Martens, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0016986211429169">Quintana &amp; Maxwell, 1999</xref>).</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The procedure resulted in the removal of a total of 10 items (i.e., 2 items each that were designed to assess Horizontal Allocentrism and Vertical Idiocentrism, and 3 items each that were designed to assess Vertical Allocentrism and Need For Peer Acceptance). The final full measurement model had good general fit (χ<sup>2</sup> = 1,119.98, degrees of freedom [<italic>df</italic>] = 480, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; χ<sup>2</sup>/<italic>df</italic> = 2.33; RMSEA = .06, 90% confidence interval = .05, .06; NFI = .94; NNFI = .96; CFI = .96; SRMR = .07; GFI = .97; AGFI = .96). <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0016986211429169">Table 1</xref> shows the factors, factor loadings, and error variances of this model.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0016986211429169" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Full Measurement Model: Means, Standard Deviations, Factor Loadings, and Error Variances</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0016986211429169" xlink:href="10.1177_0016986211429169-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Factors/items</th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="center">Loading</th>
<th align="center">Error variance</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Horizontal Allocentrism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> B5: The well-being of my school friends is important to me.</td>
<td>6.27</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>.82</td>
<td>.33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> B9: I feel good when I cooperate with others.</td>
<td>5.50</td>
<td>1.23</td>
<td>.60</td>
<td>.64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> B13: It is important to maintain harmony with my group of friends.</td>
<td>5.65</td>
<td>1.24</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> B17: If a school friend gets a prize, I would feel proud.</td>
<td>5.63</td>
<td>1.30</td>
<td>.66</td>
<td>.57</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> B21: I like sharing little things with my friends.</td>
<td>5.42</td>
<td>1.37</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>.66</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> B25: If a relative were in trouble, I would help him or her.</td>
<td>6.32</td>
<td>0.95</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Vertical Idiocentrism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> B2: It is important that I do better in school than others.</td>
<td>3.86</td>
<td>1.70</td>
<td>.75</td>
<td>.44</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> B6: It annoys me when other people perform better than I do.</td>
<td>3.50</td>
<td>1.65</td>
<td>.80</td>
<td>.36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> B10: When another person does better than I do, I get tense and aroused.</td>
<td>2.61</td>
<td>1.49</td>
<td>.79</td>
<td>.38</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> B14: Winning is everything.</td>
<td>2.30</td>
<td>1.56</td>
<td>.67</td>
<td>.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Vertical Allocentrism</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> B4: Whatever the price, friends should look after one another.</td>
<td>5.88</td>
<td>1.15</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td>.68</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> B16: It is important to me that I respect the desires of my group of friends.</td>
<td>5.57</td>
<td>1.16</td>
<td>.73</td>
<td>.47</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> B24: The welfare of my friends is important to me.</td>
<td>6.11</td>
<td>1.00</td>
<td>.82</td>
<td>.33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Motivation for Academic Success</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> C1: Academic success makes me happy.</td>
<td>6.11</td>
<td>1.05</td>
<td>.82</td>
<td>.32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> C2: Doing well academically at school is important to me.</td>
<td>6.03</td>
<td>1.11</td>
<td>.90</td>
<td>.19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> C3: I feel a sense of accomplishment from getting good marks at school.</td>
<td>6.28</td>
<td>0.99</td>
<td>.83</td>
<td>.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> C4: Getting good marks is the most important thing at school.</td>
<td>4.06</td>
<td>1.65</td>
<td>.65</td>
<td>.58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> C5: People should make the most of their academic abilities.</td>
<td>6.26</td>
<td>1.04</td>
<td>.72</td>
<td>.48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> C6: It is essential that I perform well in school exams.</td>
<td>5.56</td>
<td>1.44</td>
<td>.77</td>
<td>.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Need for Peer Acceptance</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> D2: I don’t try to act very much like other students act.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0016986211429169">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>3.43</td>
<td>1.53</td>
<td>.62</td>
<td>.61</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> D3: I try to look very similar to other students.</td>
<td>5.36</td>
<td>1.46</td>
<td>.64</td>
<td>.59</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> D4: I don’t worry about whether or not I am popular.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0016986211429169">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>3.34</td>
<td>1.71</td>
<td>.72</td>
<td>.48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> D6: It doesn’t matter what other students think about me.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0016986211429169">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>3.72</td>
<td>1.68</td>
<td>.65</td>
<td>.57</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Forced Choice Dilemma</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> E1: I would fit in better at school if I were not academically gifted.</td>
<td>2.49</td>
<td>1.74</td>
<td>.75</td>
<td>.44</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> E2: It is difficult to decide whether academic success or gaining acceptance from other students is more important to me.</td>
<td>2.83</td>
<td>1.66</td>
<td>.65</td>
<td>.57</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> E3: Being academically gifted hurts my popularity.</td>
<td>2.51</td>
<td>1.78</td>
<td>.86</td>
<td>.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> E4: I have had to spend a lot of time and energy deciding between the relative importance of academic success and acceptance by other students.</td>
<td>2.17</td>
<td>1.47</td>
<td>.74</td>
<td>.45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> E5: Other students like me less because I am academically gifted.</td>
<td>2.47</td>
<td>1.74</td>
<td>.83</td>
<td>.32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> E6: I sway between thinking that acceptance by other students is more important than academic success and thinking that academic success is more important than peer acceptance.</td>
<td>2.50</td>
<td>1.65</td>
<td>.74</td>
<td>.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> E7: If I were not academically gifted, other kids’ attitudes toward me would be different to what they are now.</td>
<td>3.92</td>
<td>2.07</td>
<td>.68</td>
<td>.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> E8: It is unfair that I can’t excel academically and be accepted by other students.</td>
<td>2.74</td>
<td>2.09</td>
<td>.73</td>
<td>.47</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> E9: I feel a strong degree of tension between achieving academic success and being accepted by other students.</td>
<td>2.28</td>
<td>1.60</td>
<td>.88</td>
<td>.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> E10: I feel that I have to choose between fitting in with other students and achieving academic success.</td>
<td>2.05</td>
<td>1.59</td>
<td>.83</td>
<td>.32</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0016986211429169">
<label>a.</label>
<p>Reverse scored.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>All factor loadings in the full measurement model exceeded .50; hence, convergent validity was established for these factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0016986211429169">Hair et al., 2010</xref>). Thereafter, to assess discriminant validity, correlations between factors were examined; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0016986211429169">Table 2</xref> presents these factor correlations with Cronbach’s alpha values on the diagonal.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0016986211429169" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Factor Correlations With Cronbach’s Alpha Values on the Diagonal</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0016986211429169" xlink:href="10.1177_0016986211429169-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">1</th>
<th align="center">2</th>
<th align="center">3</th>
<th align="center">4</th>
<th align="center">5</th>
<th align="center">6</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1. Horizontal Allocentrism</td>
<td><bold>.75</bold></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2. Vertical Idiocentrism</td>
<td>−.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0016986211429169">**</xref></td>
<td><bold>.80</bold></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3. Vertical Allocentrism</td>
<td>.88<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0016986211429169">**</xref></td>
<td>−.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0016986211429169">**</xref></td>
<td><bold>.72</bold></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4. Motivation for Academic Success</td>
<td>.32<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0016986211429169">**</xref></td>
<td>.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0016986211429169">**</xref></td>
<td>.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0016986211429169">**</xref></td>
<td><bold>.85</bold></td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5. Need for Peer Acceptance</td>
<td>−.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0016986211429169">**</xref></td>
<td>.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0016986211429169">**</xref></td>
<td>−.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0016986211429169">**</xref></td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td><bold>.72</bold></td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6. Forced Choice Dilemma</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0016986211429169">**</xref></td>
<td>−.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0016986211429169">**</xref></td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>−.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0016986211429169">**</xref></td>
<td><bold>.90</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0016986211429169">
<label>**</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Most noteworthy was the relatively strong correlation (.88) between Horizontal Allocentrism and Vertical Allocentrism. Consequently, additional analyses were undertaken to determine whether Horizontal Allocentrism and Vertical Allocentrism were distinct factors. The approach taken was to establish whether a better fitting measurement model would result if the items of the two factors were combined into a single factor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0016986211429169">Hair et al., 2010</xref>). The chi-square difference statistic (Δχ<sup>2</sup>) of 6.30 (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0016986211429169">Table 3</xref>) suggested that the two-factor model was significantly superior to the combined one-factor model at the .05 level. Moreover, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0016986211429169">Table 3</xref> shows that the two-factor model had superior fit to the combined one-factor model on many of the goodness-of-fit indicators.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0016986211429169" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Goodness-of-Fit Indices of Individual Measurement Models of the Observed Variables Loading Onto the Factors “Horizontal Allocentrism” and “Vertical Allocentrism”</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0016986211429169" xlink:href="10.1177_0016986211429169-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Model</th>
<th align="center">χ<sup>2</sup></th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>df</italic></th>
<th align="center">χ<sup>2</sup>/<italic>df</italic></th>
<th align="center">RMSEA</th>
<th align="center">NFI</th>
<th align="center">NNFI</th>
<th align="center">CFI</th>
<th align="center">SRMR</th>
<th align="center">GFI</th>
<th align="center">AGFI</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Combined model</td>
<td>74.782</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>2.770</td>
<td>.063</td>
<td>.977</td>
<td>.980</td>
<td>.985</td>
<td>.043</td>
<td>.993</td>
<td>.989</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Two-factor model</td>
<td>68.380</td>
<td>&lt;.01</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>2.630</td>
<td>.061</td>
<td>.979</td>
<td>.982</td>
<td>.987</td>
<td>.043</td>
<td>.994</td>
<td>.989</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0016986211429169">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. RMSEA = root mean square error of approximation; SRMR = standardized root mean square residual; NFI = normed fit index; NNFI = nonnormed fit index; CFI = comparative fit index; GFI = goodness-of-fit index; AGFI = adjusted goodness-of-fit index; <italic>df</italic> = degrees of freedom. <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 for Δχ<sup>2</sup>.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>All six factors in the full measurement model had acceptable Cronbach’s alpha values ranging from .72 to .90, as noted in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0016986211429169">Table 2</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0016986211429169">
<title>Structural Models</title>
<p>The initially estimated structural equation model of the theoretical framework had generally good fit (i.e., χ<sup>2</sup> = 1,201.19, <italic>df</italic> = 486, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; χ<sup>2</sup>/<italic>df</italic> = 2.47; RMSEA = .06, 90% confidence interval = .05, .06; NFI = .93; NNFI = .95; CFI = .96; SRMR = .08; GFI = .96; AGFI = .96). Nevertheless, a minor issue needed to be addressed through the removal of Horizontal Allocentrism, as the path from this to Need For Peer Acceptance was statistically nonsignificant.</p>
<p>The resulting structural equation model had generally good fit (i.e., χ<sup>2</sup> = 971.50, <italic>df</italic> = 318, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; χ<sup>2</sup>/<italic>df</italic> = 3.06; RMSEA = .07, 90% confidence interval .06, .07; NFI = .93; NNFI = .95; CFI = .95; SRMR = .08; GFI = .96; AGFI = .96), and all the remaining paths were statistically significant. Moreover, the modification indices and standardized residuals did not suggest freeing additional paths. Consequently, the modified model was accepted as the final model, which is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0016986211429169">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0016986211429169" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Final structural model</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0016986211429169-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Mediation effects in the model were tested, at the recommendation of a reviewer, by (separately) introducing an additional path from both cultural orientation variables to the forced choice dilemma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0016986211429169">Hair et al., 2010</xref>). In both cases, (a) the newly added path was statistically significant, (b) there was a statistically significant decrease to the chi-square value (Δχ<sup>2</sup> of between 43.14 and 76.64), and (c) the other goodness-of-fit statistics improved slightly (i.e., GFI increased to .97; the path addition from Vertical Idiocentrism to the Forced Choice Dilemma also resulted in an increase to the CFI [.96] and a decrease to the SRMR [.07]). Nevertheless, partial mediation was only established for the relationship between Vertical Allocentrism and the Forced Choice Dilemma, as the path from Motivation for Academic Success to the Forced Choice Dilemma was not statistically significant in the model that introduced a path from Vertical Idiocentrism to the Forced Choice Dilemma. A significant indirect effect through a confirmed mediating variable was therefore only found to exist between Vertical Allocentrism and the Forced Choice Dilemma.</p>
<p>Broadly, two path sequences in the final model linked the cultural orientation variables that remained with the variable Forced Choice Dilemma. In the first path sequence, both Vertical Allocentrism and Vertical Idiocentrism were found to positively predict Motivation for Academic Success (γ = 0.87, <italic>t</italic> = 3.60 and γ = 0.94, <italic>t</italic> = 6.12, respectively), which positively predicted the Forced Choice Dilemma (β = 0.19, <italic>t</italic> = 3.00). In the second path sequence, Vertical Allocentrism negatively predicted Need for Peer Acceptance (γ = 0.55, <italic>t</italic> = −4.56), which in turn positively predicted the Forced Choice Dilemma (β = 0.48, <italic>t</italic> = 4.69). The most substantial paths in the final accepted model were from Vertical Idiocentrism to Motivation for Academic Success and from Vertical Allocentrism to Motivation for Academic Success. The final model provided support for Hypotheses 1, 2, 3, and 4, but not for Hypotheses 5 and 6.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0016986211429169" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The final structural equation model provided support for the propositions that, in intellectually gifted students, (a) the forced choice dilemma may be conceptualized as a phenomenon that is predicted by both motivation for academic success and need for peer acceptance, and (b) cultural orientations that emphasize hierarchy among individuals may allow a strong motivation for academic success.</p>
<p>Surprisingly, the proposed relationships between the two allocentric dimensions of culture (i.e., horizontal allocentrism and vertical allocentrism) and the need for peer acceptance were not supported. Instead, vertical allocentrism was found to be a negative predictor of the need for peer acceptance. The relationship suggested that intellectually gifted students who value both hierarchies and interdependencies among friends are unlikely to have a need for peer acceptance. One speculative interpretation of the result is that the “allocentrism” component of vertical allocentrism is restricted to “close” friends and may not necessarily extend to peers at school for the participants of the study. Another possibility is that intellectually gifted students who are vertically allocentric are already likely to have achieved high levels of peer acceptance and are therefore unlikely to have a “separate” or additional need for it. Other interpretations are possible, and further investigations may be necessary to gain a clearer understanding of the relevant issues.</p>
<p>Of the two cultural orientation variables in the final accepted model, vertical allocentrism was the only one with a significant indirect effect on the experience of the forced choice dilemma through a mediating variable. The result suggested that vertical allocentrism may be more important than vertical idiocentrism in explaining or accounting for adolescent experiences of the phenomenon. Vertical idiocentric orientation may only be relevant to the forced choice dilemma in terms of its role in predicting one variable that is closely related to the phenomenon, or may be considered to be one element of the phenomenon (i.e., motivation for academic success). To explain the findings, it may be argued that although both vertical idiocentrics and vertical allocentrics have motivation for academic success (because of the “vertical” components of their cultural orientations), only vertical allocentrics are able to readily translate this contribution or “input” of cultural orientation on their motivation into an experience or otherwise of the forced choice dilemma. Vertical allocentrism, more so than vertical idiocentrism, does appear to have a strong relationship (i.e., positive and negative) with <italic>both</italic> variables that predict, and may potentially be described as elements of, the experience of the forced choice dilemma.</p>
<p>The finally accepted model was consistent with the original theoretical framework, except for the predictive relationships between the two allocentric cultural orientation constructs (i.e., horizontal allocentrism and vertical allocentrism) and need for peer acceptance. One other possible point of difference between the theoretical framework and the final accepted model is the tentative inference from the final accepted model that students high on vertical allocentrism may have <italic>resolved</italic> the forced choice dilemma by giving priority to academic achievement (i.e., the positive path from vertical allocentrism to motivation for academic success <italic>and</italic> the negative path from vertical allocentrism to need for peer acceptance). However, this requires further investigation before any definitive conclusions are made.</p>
<p>The findings of the study have a number of implications for both research and practice. In terms of research, it may be valuable to further investigate the relationship between vertical allocentrism and the need for peer acceptance. Interviews, case studies, or other qualitative approaches could be used to gain richer insights. Furthermore, a longitudinal study that assesses the need for peer acceptance of intellectually gifted students from a young age may provide the necessary information to confirm whether it may indeed be considered a “fundamental” and/or “ingrained” need of vertically allocentric students, such that it is unlikely to be “separately” pursued in later adolescence. Additionally, it may be worthwhile to conduct separate investigations on the experience of the forced choice dilemma for different age, grade, ancestral, and gender groups.</p>
<p>Future research may also be directed at examining how other cultural orientations may predict, directly or indirectly, the experience of the forced choice dilemma. Of the cultural orientations proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0016986211429169">Hofstede (2001)</xref>, power distance, or “the extent to which the less powerful members of organizations and institutions accept and expect that power is distributed unequally” (p. xix), and masculinity/femininity, or the different degrees to which individuals adopt “tough” or “tender” roles in societies, may have some relationship to the experience of the phenomenon. The cultural values/dimensions proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0016986211429169">Schwartz (1999)</xref>, including hierarchy, egalitarianism, intellectual autonomy, and affective autonomy, are other possibilities.</p>
<p>In terms of practice, educators, psychologists, counselors, and families may be able to use the model to better understand how intellectually gifted students experience the forced choice dilemma. As the model provides insights on how idiocentric/allocentric cultural orientations influence the experience of the phenomenon, a more complete understanding of intellectually gifted students’ experiences of the forced choice dilemma may be gained by considering the nature of their idiocentric/allocentric orientations. If it is the case that intellectually gifted students with high levels of vertical allocentrism are able to readily resolve the forced choice dilemma, educators, psychologists, counselors, and families may be advised to direct their focus to intellectually gifted students of the other cultural orientations (i.e., vertical idiocentrics, horizontal idiocentrics, and horizontal allocentrics), for whom the forced choice dilemma may present itself to be a more difficult issue.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0016986211429169">
<title>Limitations of the Research</title>
<p>The study has some limitations that need to be taken into consideration when its findings are interpreted. First, the participants were not all formally identified as gifted and, therefore, verification of intellectual level was not possible. Second, as the data collected relied exclusively on self-reports, there is potential for single-source bias. Other data sources, such as the perceptions of significant others and peers at school, and interview data from the participants, may have provided additional validation to the findings. Third, causal inferences should not be made about the relationships in the structural equation models that were estimated, as the conditions for establishing causality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0016986211429169">Hair et al., 2010</xref>) were not fully met. A longitudinal or experimental study may be required before any causal inferences may be made with any degree of confidence. Fourth, we acknowledge that this study has not investigated all the variables that may be related to the forced choice dilemma of intellectually gifted students. Therefore, we are unable to claim that the model provides a complete picture of the experience of the forced choice dilemma. Finally, although it is necessary to acknowledge that the model is one of many possible models of the forced choice dilemma, we stress that it was based firmly on theory and logical argument.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alavi</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Measurement of vertical and horizontal idiocentrism and allocentrism in small groups</article-title>. <source>Small Group Research</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>556</fpage>-<lpage>564</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benbow</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Inequity in equity: How “equity” can lead to inequity for high potential students</article-title>. <source>Psychology, Public Policy and Law</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>249</fpage>-<lpage>292</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boykin</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albury</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Culture-based perceptions of academic achievement among low income elementary students</article-title>. <source>Cultural Diversity &amp; Ethnic Minority Psychology</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>339</fpage>-<lpage>350</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Buescher</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>A developmental study of adjustment among gifted adolescents</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>VanTassel-Baska</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Olszewski-Kubilius</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Patterns of influence on gifted learners: The home, the self and the school</source> (pp. <fpage>102</fpage>-<lpage>124</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Teachers College Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Structural equation modeling with LISREL, PRELIS and SIMPLIS: Basic concepts, applications and programming</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Australian academic attitudes toward academic brilliance</article-title>. <source>Australasian Journal of Gifted Education</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>10</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The structure of social coping among Chinese gifted children and youths in Hong Kong</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Education of the Gifted</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coon</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kemmelmeier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Cultural orientations in the U.S.: Re-examining differences among ethnic groups</article-title>. <source>Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>348</fpage>-<lpage>364</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Terhaar-Yonkers</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>The social cognition of gifted adolescents in schools: Managing the stigma of giftedness</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Education of the Gifted</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>44</fpage>-<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dimmock</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Educational leadership: Culture and diversity</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foust</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hertberg-Davis</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>“Having it all” at sleep’s expense: The forced choice of participants in Advanced Placement courses in International Baccalaureate programs</article-title>. <source>Roeper Review</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>121</fpage>-<lpage>129</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Furman</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buhrmester</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Children’s perceptions of the personal relationships in their social networks</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychology</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1016</fpage>-<lpage>1024</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gagné</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Transforming gifts into talents: The DMGT as a developmental theory</article-title>. <source>High Ability Studies</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>119</fpage>-<lpage>147</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gaines</surname><given-names>S. O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marelich</surname><given-names>W. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bledsoe</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steers</surname><given-names>W. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Granrose</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Page</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Links between race/ethnicity and cultural values as measured by racial/ethnic identity moderated by gender</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>1460</fpage>-<lpage>1476</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>M. U. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>The pursuit of excellence or the search for intimacy? The forced choice dilemma of gifted youth</article-title>. <source>Roeper Review</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>189</fpage>-<lpage>194</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>M. U. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The “me” behind the mask: Intellectually gifted students and the search for identity</article-title>. <source>Roeper Review</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>174</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hair</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Babin</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Multivariate data analysis: A global perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Upper Saddle River, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hartung</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fouad</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>F. T. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hardin</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Individualism-collectivism: Links to occupational plans and work values</article-title>. <source>Journal of Career Assessment</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>34</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hofstadter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1964</year>). <source>Anti-intellectualism in American life</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jonathan Cape</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hofstede</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Culture’s consequences</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hollingworth</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1926</year>). <source>Gifted children: Their nature and nurture</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Janos</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Psychological development in intellectually gifted children</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Horowitz</surname><given-names>F. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The gifted and talented: Developmental perspectives</source> (pp. <fpage>149</fpage>-<lpage>195</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>M. U. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Levels of intellectual giftedness, culture, and the forced choice dilemma</article-title>. <source>Roeper Review</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>182</fpage>-<lpage>197</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Future directions of structural equation modelling in counseling psychology</article-title>. <source>The Counseling Psychologist</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>551</fpage>-<lpage>558</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Quintana</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Implications of recent developments in structural equation modeling for counseling psychology</article-title>. <source>The Counseling Psychologist</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>485</fpage>-<lpage>527</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rudasill</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Foust</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The Social Coping Questionnaire: An examination of its structure with an American sample of gifted adolescents</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Education of the Gifted</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>353</fpage>-<lpage>371</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schroeder-Davis</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Brains, brawn, or beauty: Adolescent attitudes toward three superlatives</article-title>. <source>Journal of Secondary Gifted Education</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>134</fpage>-<lpage>147</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>A theory of cultural values and some implications for work</article-title>. <source>Applied Psychology: An International Review</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shuluf</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hattie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Development of a new measurement tool for individualism and collectivism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Psychoeducational Assessment</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>385</fpage>-<lpage>401</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Singelis</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Triandis</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhawuk</surname><given-names>D. P. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gelfand</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Horizontal and vertical dimensions of individualism and collectivism: A theoretical and measurement refinement</article-title>. <source>Cross-Cultural Research</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>240</fpage>-<lpage>275</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swiatek</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>An empirical investigation of the social coping strategies used by gifted adolescents</article-title>. <source>Gifted Child Quarterly</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>154</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swiatek</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Social coping among gifted high school students and its relationship to self-concept</article-title>. <source>Journal of Youth and Adolescence</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swiatek</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dorr</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Revision of the social coping questionnaire: Replication and extension of previous findings</article-title>. <source>Journal of Secondary Gifted Education</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>252</fpage>-<lpage>259</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tannenbaum</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <source>Gifted children: Psychological and educational perspectives</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Triandis</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Cross-cultural studies of individualism and collectivism</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <conf-name>Nebraska symposium on motivation</conf-name>, <conf-date>1989</conf-date> (pp. <fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>133</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Lincoln</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Nebraska Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Triandis</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>Individualism and collectivism</source>. <publisher-loc>Boulder, CO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Westview</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Triandis</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The psychological measurement of cultural syndromes</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>407</fpage>-<lpage>415</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Triandis</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhawuk</surname><given-names>D. P. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iwao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>J. B. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Multimethod probes of allocentrism and idiocentrism</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Psychology</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>461</fpage>-<lpage>480</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Triandis</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gelfand</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Converging measurement of horizontal and vertical individualism and collectivism</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>, <volume>74</volume>, <fpage>118</fpage>-<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Triandis</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Villereal</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clack</surname><given-names>F. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Allocentric versus idiocentric tendencies: Convergent and divergent validation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Research in Personality</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>395</fpage>-<lpage>415</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weston</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>A brief guide to structural equation modeling</article-title>. <source>The Counseling Psychologist</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>719</fpage>-<lpage>751</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0016986211429169">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Winner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Gifted children: Myths and realities</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>