<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">WOX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spwox</journal-id>
<journal-title>Work and Occupations</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0730-8884</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-8464</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0730888411415601</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0730888411415601</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Dual Earners Preparing for Job Loss</article-title>
<subtitle>Agency, Linked Lives, and Resilience</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0730888411415601">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Moen</surname><given-names>Phyllis</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0730888411415601">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0730888411415601"><label>1</label>Ithaca College, Ithaca, NY, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0730888411415601"><label>2</label>University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0730888411415601">Stephen Sweet, Department of Sociology, Muller Faculty Center, Ithaca College, Ithaca, NY 14850, USA Email: <email>ssweet@ithaca.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-0730888411415601">
<p>Stephen Sweet is an associate professor of sociology at Ithaca College, Ithaca, New York. He has published widely on work-family concerns. His most recent books include <italic>Changing Contours of Work</italic> (2012) and <italic>The Work and Family Handbook: Interdisciplinary Perspectives, Methods and Approaches</italic> (2005). His current research focuses on the intersecting concerns of job security, talent retention, and the changing composition of the workforce.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio2-0730888411415601">
<p>Phyllis Moen holds the McKnight presidential chair in sociology at the University of Minnesota, Minneapolis. She studies occupational careers, gender, families, and well-being over the life course and has published numerous books and articles on work and family concerns, including <italic>Women’s Two Roles: A Contemporary Dilemma</italic> (1992), <italic>It’s About Time: Couples and Careers</italic> (2003), and <italic>The Career Mystique: Cracks in the American Dream</italic> (2005).</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>39</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>35</fpage>
<lpage>70</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We draw on a two-wave panel survey and a third wave of in-depth interviews to study how 78 dual-earner couples prepared for job loss and the implications of preparation for resilience. We find personal and social resources predict preparation: those displaced workers who prepared had higher energy and higher incomes prior to job loss and also worked for employers who provided advance notification. Couples’ egalitarian career strategies are associated with lower levels of preparation as well as limited options in the face of displacement. Less preparation is associated with less favorable career adjustments following job loss as well as more severe health and emotional challenges.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>insecurity</kwd>
<kwd>dual careers</kwd>
<kwd>unemployment</kwd>
<kwd>risk</kwd>
<kwd>planning</kwd>
<kwd>life course</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Job security has declined markedly in the transition from the “old economy” to the “new economy” and, when replacement work is not found quickly, the impact of job loss can be profound (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0730888411415601">Hacker, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0730888411415601">Sweet, Moen, &amp; Meiksins, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0730888411415601">Warren &amp; Tyagi, 2003</xref>). Whereas sporadic economic crises escalate the risks and consequences of job loss, in the new economy, other factors contribute to these concerns, including the reliance on flexible technologies, new organizational configurations, new managerial philosophies, and increased employment in industry sectors that have historically provided less secure employment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0730888411415601">Cappelli, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0730888411415601">Kalleberg, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0730888411415601">Smith, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0730888411415601">Sweet &amp; Meiksins, 2008</xref>). The recomposition of the labor force itself, from workers in predominantly single-earner family arrangements to those in dual-earner households, complicates the planning for job loss and the adjustment following displacement. This article considers why some couples prepare more for job loss, and others less, as well as the impact that preparation might have on the adjustment to job loss.</p>
<sec id="section1-0730888411415601">
<title>Theoretical Framework: Preparation, Agency, Control, and the Life Course</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0730888411415601">Kalleberg (2009)</xref> proposed the need for scholarship to promote understandings of the connections between employees’ sense of agency and their increasingly precarious employment. Our goal is to contribute to this literature by considering how <italic>preparation</italic> for job loss might explain worker responses to the contours of the new economy. By assessing the contexts that might enhance or discourage agentic response to job insecurity, we consider the extent that workers anticipate job loss and plan their lives accordingly. We then consider if those acts of preparation make meaningful differences in their lives. In essence, to what extent do workers exert agency in the context of insecurity and, when they do, does it make a difference?</p>
<p>Preparation for an event such as job loss can involve multiple types of physical, social, and cognitive components. With respect to physical effort, it can require the accrual of savings as well as the securing of documents and information that might help one pursue new work, should the current position be terminated. On a social level, preparation might involve consciously embedding oneself within networks that expand opportunities so as to consciously take advantage of both strong and weak ties. In addition, as we discuss in detail in this article, this can also involve proactively coordinating a career with one’s spouse/partner to maximize dual-career stability/mobility in turbulent contexts. Moreover, preparation might also take the form of proactive emotional responses, in which one has predesignated a way of interpreting how the event is to be interpreted and its reflection on the self. These components share in common the deliberate effort to identify and position oneself in anticipation of future career contingencies and all involve the application of agency.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0730888411415601">Emirbayer and Mische (1998)</xref> define agency as “the temporally constructed engagement by actors of different social environments—which, through the interplay of habit, imagination, and judgment, both reproduces and transforms those structures in interactive response to the problems posed by changing historical situations” (p. 971). Although the capacity to exert agency is variable, its application is a key component in securing dignity in the workplace and establishing the terms of employment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0730888411415601">Hodson, 2001</xref>). By studying preparation for job loss, we advance the theoretical development and empirical analysis of agency with respect to the capacity to exert control over one’s career via “projective activities”—meaning anticipating future scenarios and adjusting actions accordingly. These projective capacities can vary remarkably and are contingent not only on social positioning with respect to resources and constraints but also on the meanings actors ascribe to actual and prospective events. We develop our model with respect to four aspects of projective action: (a) the interpretation of jobs and job loss, (b) constraints that limit the capacity to prepare, (c) resources that enhance the capacity to prepare, and (d) the likely impact of preparation in the wake of job loss. We review the evidence on each concern below.</p>
<sec id="section2-0730888411415601">
<title>Agency and Interpretation</title>
<p>Social psychological studies have shown that response to hardship (or potential hardship) can be predicted from enduring personality/dispositional orientations—including control-oriented coping abilities and psychological hardiness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0730888411415601">Armstrong-Stassen, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0730888411415601">Crowley, Hayslip, &amp; Hobdy, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0730888411415601">Fouad &amp; Bynner, 2008</xref>). However, beyond these personal capacities, symbolic interactionist theory underscores the importance of subjective interpretation, that is, the way individuals define their situations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0730888411415601">Blumer, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0730888411415601">Mead, 1934</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0730888411415601">Stryker &amp; Serpe, 1982</xref>). Research shows that the meanings individuals accord to their jobs have powerful effects on career development over the life course, not only with respect to their career choices (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0730888411415601">Johnson &amp; Monserud, 2010</xref>) but also the ways jobs are performed and prioritized with respect to other commitments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0730888411415601">Burawoy, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0730888411415601">Hodson, 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>When workers operate in precarious work situations, their definitions of these conditions can vary remarkably. These understandings, in turn, shape the preparation for job loss and the experiences that follow. For example, an ethnographic study found that some displaced workers interpreted their job loss as fate and beyond their control, whereas others did not. Those who created narratives emphasizing their own personal heroism in the face of adversity were more inclined to persist in their efforts to find replacement work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0730888411415601">Ezzy, 2000</xref>). As numerous studies indicate, perceptions of procedural justice in the ways jobs were actually terminated predict subsequent favorable social-psychological outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0730888411415601">Appelbaum, Simpson, &amp; Shapiro, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0730888411415601">Armstrong-Stassen, 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0730888411415601">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0730888411415601">Brockner, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0730888411415601">Grunberg, Anderson-Connolly, &amp; Greenberg, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0730888411415601">Latack, Kinicki, &amp; Prussia, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0730888411415601">Mishra &amp; Spreitzer, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0730888411415601">Naumann, Bennett, Beis, &amp; Martin, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-0730888411415601">Wanberg, Bunce, &amp; Gavin, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr88-0730888411415601">Wiesenfeld, Brockner, &amp; Martin, 1999</xref>). Thus, although there are objective realities (such as job loss), the impacts of dislocation can vary depending on the ways individuals interpret the experience and how organizational practices shape definitions of situations.</p>
<p>A life-course perspective highlights how ostensibly bad events (such as job loss) or good events (such as getting a new job) can have differing outcomes, ranging from negligible impacts (positive or negative) to major turning points, depending on the narratives constructed. Subjective assessments of events are considerate not only of the new conditions but also of the previous contexts as well as the anticipation of future contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0730888411415601">Clausen, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0730888411415601">Strandh, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-0730888411415601">Wethington, Pixley, &amp; Kavey, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-0730888411415601">Wheaton, 1990</xref>). In other words, job loss could potentially be interpreted favorably if the employee did not like the previous work environment and viewed his/her new situation (even if unemployed) as favorable compared with the negative conditions that they were forced to exit. The timing at which a job loss occurs (early, mid, or late in one’s career) can affect not only the prospects of finding replacement work but also the interpretation of the event within a personally constructed career narrative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0730888411415601">Mendenhall, Kalil, Spindel, &amp; Hart, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>As workers do not equally attach their identities to their jobs, their motivation to prepare for job loss and their subjective experiences of actual job loss vary as well. As an extreme example, consider the attitudes of substance abusing temporary workers, whose agency is devoted to obtaining the means for the next fix, not toward negotiating career stabilities embraced by most other segments of the labor force (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr89-0730888411415601">Williams, 2009</xref>). This orientation stands in marked contrast to the attitudes of middle-class workers, who tend to identify strongly with their jobs and for whom job loss has a greater negative impact on subjective well-being (as compared with those in the upper and lower classes; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0730888411415601">Andersen, 2009</xref>). Last, understanding the interpretative component of agency has had considerable impact on strategies for establishing the terms of employment. For example, the union movement rested on beliefs in shared interests and shared experiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0730888411415601">Clawson, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0730888411415601">Hodson, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0730888411415601">Kalleberg, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>In sum, the act of preparation depends on internalized beliefs that view planning as being important and effective. In addition, how people plan and respond to job loss depends on the strategies that they believe will likely help them cope in the face of career changes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0730888411415601">
<title>Agency and Constraints</title>
<p>Constraints can be understood as impediments that limit the pursuit of alternate paths of action. For example, considerable research documents the ways that time binds can drain the capacity to engage in activities other than tending to the immediate demands of work and family responsibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0730888411415601">Hochschild, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0730888411415601">Jacobs &amp; Gerson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0730888411415601">Moen &amp; Roehling, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0730888411415601">Presser, 2003</xref>). As preparation requires effort, we expect that deficits in time and energy resources will undermine the capacity to prepare for job loss as these resources have been shown to negatively impact capacities for resilience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0730888411415601">Schieman &amp; Glavin, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0730888411415601">Sonnentag, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>In the new economy, couples are increasingly the strategic decision-making unit. By virtue of needing to accommodate two careers, the logistics of obtaining and maintaining employment are complex and commonly pit one spouse’s career interests against the other’s (but usually for the benefit of the collective household interests). As dual-earning partners’ career paths are inextricably linked, planning likely corresponds with previous efforts to manage career hierarchies. These adaptive strategies can affect the short-term and long-term outcomes for the careers of <italic>both</italic> partners, but not necessarily in consistent ways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0730888411415601">Crosnoe &amp; Elder, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0730888411415601">Pixley, 2008</xref>; Swisher, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0730888411415601">Sweet, &amp; Moen, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>In this article, we examine the possibility that professional couples who adopt egalitarian career strategies (those who report favoring neither partner’s career or who say they take turns in whose career to favor) face greater challenges in preparing for job loss. This prediction stems from studies documenting the difficulties of finding mutually satisfying jobs, especially for professionals laboring in scarce job markets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0730888411415601">Schiebinger, Henderson, &amp; Gilmartin, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0730888411415601">Sweet &amp; Moen, 2004</xref>). To prepare for job loss, egalitarian couples may take both partners’ interests into account as they plan their next steps, such as moving to a new geographic location. As the risks of job loss are often unknown, it may be impossible to plan for all potential contingencies to optimize both partners’ situations. This, in turn, might prompt a “cross the fingers” approach that results in less preparation.</p>
<p>Gender templates also likely constrain preparation for job loss. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0730888411415601">Hakim (2001)</xref> argues that many women move out of the labor force or into careers that are secondary to those of their spouse because they have a preference for home-centered or adaptive positions with respect to work and family roles. While Hakim may overestimate the explanatory power of preferences as predicting women’s career choices (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0730888411415601">Stone, 1997</xref>), there is some support that (constrained) preferences are a contributing factor in women’s career trajectories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0730888411415601">Kan, 2007</xref>). We expect, therefore, that planning for job loss may be influenced by gendered values as well as the gender of the worker.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0730888411415601">
<title>Agency and Resources</title>
<p>Perceptions of control or a sense of mastery can be a valuable resource in shaping response to job insecurity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0730888411415601">Pearlin, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0730888411415601">Pearlin, Lieberman, Menaghan, &amp; Mullan, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0730888411415601">Pearlin, Schieman, Fazio, &amp; Meersman, 2005</xref>). Furthermore, jobs themselves may socialize individuals or provide resources that may facilitate the navigation of career changes. For example, even when time pressures exist, the intrinsic qualities of jobs matter as high-quality roles (even if demanding) are associated with increased vitality and energy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0730888411415601">Barnett &amp; Gareis, 2006</xref>). These observations suggest that workers who labor in the types of jobs that provide or sustain higher levels of levels of energy (a resource) will be better positioned to prepare for job loss. In addition, because high-income jobs enable the purchase of services (such as child care, household cleaning, etc.), they might reduce time binds and increase employees’ capacity to prepare as well as ease the need to obtain immediate replacement work. Relationships with coworkers likely matter as well, as they have the potential to provide support with respect to the performance of work tasks as well as provide network ties that expand career options (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0730888411415601">Granovetter, 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0730888411415601">McGuire, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Conversely, some work environments may undercut resources and the development of agentic capacities. For example, toxic work environments, such as those in which bullying takes place, can diminish the capacity to cope under strain. Research shows that organizations that provide secure work are also the least likely to exemplify bullying (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0730888411415601">Hodson, Roscigno, &amp; Lopez, 2006</xref>), suggesting that workers in those organizations are both at lower risk of job loss and possibly better prepared for it in terms of a supportive work environment. Similarly, organizations with less complex hierarchies and less rigidly formalized practices tend to extend more autonomy to their workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0730888411415601">Choi, Leiter, &amp; Tomaskovic-Devey, 2008</xref>). This autonomy, in turn, might transfer to a greater capacity to prepare for, plan, and cope with job loss.</p>
<p>Another key resource is access to information about where the organization (and one’s own job) may be heading as the capacity to exert control in environments of risk is nested within the ability to access and process information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0730888411415601">Kahneman &amp; Tversky, 1983</xref>). One might expect that working in an economy characterized by increasingly taken-for-granted generalized risk would be sufficient to compel workers to engage in planning for job loss. Nevertheless, most American workers do not accrue sufficient savings to sustain them through a prolonged job search. A study of workers in a declining industry found few workers that could be classified as “active career planners,” who charted out next steps in advance of impending job loss. It was far more common for workers facing potential redundancy to be “triggered career changers” and to engage in career reshaping <italic>after</italic> experiencing job loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0730888411415601">Gardiner et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Even close social proximity to job loss may not be sufficient to catalyze preparation. For example, one study found that even after witnessing friends and associates lose jobs, the organizational commitment of “survivors” (individuals who witnessed layoffs but who did not lose their own jobs) remained unchanged (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0730888411415601">Grunberg et al., 2000</xref>). A complementary finding is offered with respect to other forms of preparatory behavior as perceptions of job insecurity have not been found to be accompanied by corresponding changes in spending (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0730888411415601">Stephens, 2004</xref>). What does seem important is knowledge of specific risk as it applies to one’s own career, which has a considerable impact on how individuals plan for job loss. For example, contract workers typically include preparation for job loss as part of an overarching career strategy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0730888411415601">Osnowitz, 2010</xref>). When employers provide workers with information and resources during downsizing, this should theoretically increase preparation for job loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0730888411415601">Armstrong-Stassen, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>Finally, it is important to recognize that the availability of a resource, in and of itself, does not necessarily change behavior. Studies of the use of work–family programs, for instance, indicate that they need to be perceived (an interpretive act) as being usable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0730888411415601">Barnett, Gareis, Gordon, &amp; Brennan, 2009</xref>). Moreover, when employees are strongly devoted to their work, it can limit their inclination to take advantage of work-reduction programs even when they are present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-0730888411415601">Wharton, Chivers, &amp; Blair-Loy, 2008</xref>). It would follow that those heavily invested in their jobs may postpone thinking about and planning for future possible dislocations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0730888411415601">
<title>Agency and Adjustment to Insecure Work</title>
<p>Our approach to studying agency considers the preparatory aspect of anticipating change, performing advanced work to favorably position oneself to “hit the ground running” in advance of, or after, job loss. If preparation has a positive impact on adjustment, this should be evident in minimized impacts of being laid off on financial, career, health, and emotional well-being—all of which have been documented to be negatively affected by job loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0730888411415601">Burgard, Brand, &amp; House, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0730888411415601">Dooley, Catalano, &amp; Wilson, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0730888411415601">Grzywacz &amp; Tucker, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0730888411415601">Jahoda, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0730888411415601">Kelvin &amp; Jarrett, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0730888411415601">Leana &amp; Feldman, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0730888411415601">Pavalko &amp; Smith, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0730888411415601">Perrucci, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0730888411415601">Perrucci, Perrucci, &amp; Targ, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-0730888411415601">Uchitelle, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-0730888411415601">Vosler &amp; Page-Adams, 1996</xref>). To our knowledge, no study has specifically used level of preparation as a means to predict relational outcomes following job loss.</p>
<p>We theorize engagement in preparation as a signifier of self-efficacy (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0730888411415601">Bandura, 1982</xref>), which should facilitate resilience (in the form of career, health, and emotional adjustment in the wake of job loss). It is important to recognize that this is not the only possible outcome. For example, the literature on anticipatory grieving (which occurs in advance of the death of a loved one) indicates that knowledge of impending loss can add to the stress experienced by caregivers and does not necessarily result in reshaping the grieving process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0730888411415601">Caitlin &amp; Mast, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0730888411415601">Gilliland &amp; Fleming, 1997</xref>). If these findings are transferrable to the process of job loss, preparation might not produce salutary outcomes.</p>
<p>In sum, to understand both the process of preparing for job loss and how it shapes subsequent experiences requires not only gauging the objective conditions in which job loss occurs but also individuals’ subjective interpretations of their circumstances in terms of their jobs and careers. This includes perceptions of work situations and the sense of mastery or control over one’s life. The social context may shape planning as well, as some workers may receive clearer signals about impending layoffs. Understanding the variation in preparation also requires attention to other dimensions of the social context, including job expectations, family demands, and social linkages. It remains an open question as to whether planning affects adjustment following actual job loss.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0730888411415601">
<title>Data and Measures</title>
<sec id="section7-0730888411415601">
<title>Study Design and Sample</title>
<p>This study draws on data collected at three points in time: a baseline quantitative study of middle-class, dual-earner couples in upstate New York, a follow-up survey of these same couples 2 years later (1998, 2002 Ecology of Careers Panel Study), and a third qualitative survey of a subsample of couples identified as having experienced job loss or that have continued to work in insecure jobs between the two survey waves (2002 Couples Managing Change Study). This third study was performed in the same year as the second wave of the Ecology of Careers Panel Study.</p>
<p>Participants in the Ecology of Careers Panel Study engaged in hour-long telephone interviews, first in April 1998-March 2000 (<italic>N</italic> = 4,637) and again approximately 2 years later in January 2001-April 2002 (<italic>N</italic> = 3,893). The goal of these surveys was to collect information from a representative sample of middle-class, dual-earner couples on the challenges, contexts, and strategies of bridging work and family. The surveys were designed so that both spouses in dual-earner families were interviewed (separately), generating extensive information on job histories, family histories, current family dynamics, current work experiences, and future plans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0730888411415601">Moen, 2003</xref>). Fully 84% of the participants in the baseline survey participated in the second wave of interviews. The high response rate can be attributed to the interest participants expressed in the goals of the study as well as the compensation they received (US$25-US$35/participant). To generate the sample, an initial pool of participants was recruited through a random sample in 11 different places of employment (representing a diversity of occupations and economic sectors), and another group of participants was recruited in a random sample from three communities in which the initial pool of participants resided (an average of 27 respondents were recruited in each of 57 census block groups in upstate New York; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0730888411415601">Swisher et al., 2004</xref>). Although it is not possible to calculate an exact response rate for the organizational-based portion of the sample, it is likely comparable with the 68% response rate achieved for the community-based portion of the sample.</p>
<p>These panel data were subsequently used to identify a sample of vulnerable couples who either experienced job loss or had at least one partner working in conditions of low security over the 2 years between the panel survey waves. Low security was operationalized as a score of less than 80 in response to the question “think of a scale of 0 to 100, where 0 means you are certain you will lose your present job and 100 means you are certain you will be able to keep it. . . . on this scale, how certain is it that during the next couple of years you will be able to keep it?” (modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0730888411415601">Galinsky, Bond, &amp; Friedman, 1993</xref>). This threshold was selected as it was the median level of job security reported at the first interview wave.</p>
<p>This subsample of displaced workers and those feeling at risk of job loss was used to launch the Couples Managing Change Study (conducted May to July 2002), a survey that involved hour-long telephone interviews in which participants answered detailed open- and closed-ended questions concerning their preparation for, experiences during, and outcomes following job loss. This in-depth study achieved a 95% positive response rate and yielded interviews with 260 husbands and wives (in nearly every case, both partners were interviewed but, owing to interviewer errors, five interviews had to be discarded). Interviews were taped and transcribed verbatim, producing more than 8,000 pages of text that was subsequently coded and analyzed using the text management system askSam. In this article, we focus on couples who participated in all three surveys and who experienced a job loss. These data represent the experiences of 41 middle-class, dual-earner couples in which the husband had lost his job, 32 couples in which the wife had lost her job, and 5 couples in which both partners had lost their jobs.</p>
<p>We operationalize displaced workers as individuals who lost their jobs in the 2 years between surveys in the Ecology of Careers Study. These workers may or may not have been working in new jobs at the time they were reinterviewed in Wave 3. In fact, most (60.2%) of those who had lost jobs were working at the time of the third interview, but others defined themselves as “retired and working” (2.4%), “retired and not working” (3.6%), or “neither retired nor working” (33.7%). One in ten of the spouses of displaced workers was out of the labor force by the third interview. As a point of comparison, we also explored the characteristics of “survivors,” individuals who labored in insecure jobs at Wave 1 and Wave 2 but did not lose their jobs between these survey waves. When considering the factors that predict preparation, as well as how preparation predicts adjustment following job loss, we restrict our analysis to the experiences of couples in which one or both partners had lost their job(s).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0730888411415601">
<title>Measures and Analysis</title>
<p>To examine the factors associated with preparation, we use logistic regressions to predict preparing “a lot” or “some” for job loss. With the exception of the variable assessing advanced notification, all of these measures were captured in Wave 1 prior to when couples lost jobs. The following survey items offer quantitative data concerning predictors of preparation and are included in binary logistic regression.</p>
<list id="list1-0730888411415601" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Egalitarian career strategy:</italic> Those who report “neither” or “took turns” to the following question: “Think about all of the major decisions that you and your spouse/partner have made since you have been together, such as changing jobs, having children, going back to school, or moving. Overall, whose career was given more priority in these decisions, yours or your spouse’s/partner’s?” (Ecology of Careers Wave 1).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Notification:</italic> “How much advance notice were you given that your job was being eliminated?” Days, weeks, and months were recoded to indicate no notification, less than one month, one, or greater than one month notification (Couples Managing Change Study).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Energy:</italic> “Think of a scale from zero to ten where zero is a person who never has any energy and ten is a person who is always full of energy. On this scale of zero to ten, what number best indicates how much pep or energy you have had lately?” (Ecology of Careers Wave 1).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Workload:</italic> An index based on the average of a 4-point Likert-type scale response to three individual items: “My job requires working very fast”; “My job requires working very hard”; “I am asked to do excessive amounts of work” (α = .65; Ecology of Careers Wave 1).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Household income:</italic> The income from all sources (Ecology of Careers Wave 1). To reduce skew in multivariate analyses, a log transformation was performed on this variable.</p></list-item></list>
<p>To assess the outcomes of preparing “a lot” for job loss, we rely on both quantitative and qualitative data drawn from the third wave. Although the information from entire interviews was taken into account, in this study, we focus primarily on the following items:</p>
<list id="list2-0730888411415601" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>“Are you currently looking for work or a new job?”</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>“What kind of work or employment situation are you seeking?”</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>“How difficult is it to find work in your profession (easy, a little difficult, difficult, very difficult)?” “Can you tell me more about this?”</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>“Has the experience of losing this job changed any of the ways you manage your career?”</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>“In terms of your financial situation, how big of an impact did this job loss have on your life (a lot, some, a little, not at all)? Can you tell me more about that?” This same question structure was replicated to assess changes in “physical health” and “emotional well-being.”</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>“In comparison to when you (your spouse) had that previous job, would you say that your financial situation is (better, worse, about the same)?” (if better or worse) “Can you tell me some of the ways your financial situation has changed?” This same question structure was replicated to assess changes in “career,” “health,” and “emotional well-being.”</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>“Following your (your spouse’s) job loss, did you seriously consider (a) retraining or returning to school, (b) moving or relocating, (c) changing careers or lines of work, or (d) retiring?” Each item was asked separately and follow-up probes were asked about reasons for pursuing (or not) this change and satisfaction with the outcomes.</p></list-item></list>
<p>The level of preparation for job loss was assessed by responses to the question in the third interview: “How prepared would you say you were for this job loss: a lot, some, a little, or not at all?” This question was followed by probes inquiring about the types of preparation performed and any acts of preparation the participant believed they should have done differently. Before determining the final statistical models, we performed a variety of analyses on this variable in its original coding, including multinomial regressions on the entire sample as well as regressions performed separately by gender, life stage, and job loss status, including interactions among these and other potential predictors. We compared this retrospective account with the prospective evaluations of those at risk who did not lose their jobs (survivors) on how prepared they feel for the potential loss of their current job and their appraisal of the difficulty in finding work if they were to lose that job (reported below and in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0730888411415601">Table 1</xref>). Exploratory analyses revealed that the strongest distinctions post job loss were between those who prepared “a lot” for job loss and those who prepared “some,” “a little,” or “not at all.”</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0730888411415601" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sample Characteristics of Displaced Workers and Their Spouses</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0730888411415601" xlink:href="10.1177_0730888411415601-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Displaced workers</th>
<th align="center">Spouses of displaced workers</th>
<th align="center">Survivors</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Gender</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0730888411415601">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Men</td>
<td>55.4%</td>
<td>43.5%</td>
<td>49.1%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Women</td>
<td>44.6%</td>
<td>56.5%</td>
<td>50.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Life stage (W2)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0730888411415601">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Nonparent &lt; Age 40</td>
<td>2.4%</td>
<td>2.9%</td>
<td>7.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Preschool child in household</td>
<td>19.3%</td>
<td>20.3%</td>
<td>17.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> School-age child in household</td>
<td>39.8%</td>
<td>40.6%</td>
<td>38.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Age 40+ no children in household</td>
<td>38.6%</td>
<td>36.2%</td>
<td>36.1%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Current work status (W3)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0730888411415601">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Working</td>
<td>60.2%</td>
<td>88.4%</td>
<td>83.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Retired working</td>
<td>2.4%</td>
<td>1.4%</td>
<td>1.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Retired not working</td>
<td>3.6%</td>
<td>2.9%</td>
<td>13.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Not retired not working</td>
<td>33.7%</td>
<td>7.2%</td>
<td>1.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Currently looking for new job (W3)</td>
<td>36.1%</td>
<td>4.3%</td>
<td>6.5%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0730888411415601">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Perceived difficulty in finding work (W3)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0730888411415601">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Very easy</td>
<td>6.3%</td>
<td>14.9%</td>
<td>9.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Easy</td>
<td>23.8%</td>
<td>44.8%</td>
<td>39.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Difficult</td>
<td>41.3%</td>
<td>35.8%</td>
<td>43.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Very difficult</td>
<td>28.8%</td>
<td>4.5%</td>
<td>6.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Income (W1)</td>
<td>US$54,419</td>
<td>US$55,974</td>
<td>US$54,402</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Income (W2)</td>
<td>US$55,675</td>
<td>US$60,698</td>
<td>US$64,871</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Income (W3)</td>
<td>US$42,632</td>
<td>US$58,771</td>
<td>US$64,947<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0730888411415601">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Preparation (W3)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0730888411415601">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> A lot</td>
<td>32.5%</td>
<td>33.3%</td>
<td>35.1%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Some</td>
<td>31.3%</td>
<td>39.1%</td>
<td>45.7%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> A little</td>
<td>16.3%</td>
<td>10.1%</td>
<td>13.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Not at all</td>
<td>20.0%</td>
<td>17.4%</td>
<td>5.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Advance notification (W3)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No notice</td>
<td>51.9%</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Less than 1 month</td>
<td>10.4%</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1-3 months</td>
<td>16.9%</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 3+ months</td>
<td>20.8%</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>N</italic></td>
<td>83</td>
<td>69</td>
<td>108</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0730888411415601">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .10. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>It is important to highlight here a critical limitation in our measure of preparedness. The design of the first wave of the Ecology of Careers Study did not include a prospective measure of preparedness, and once we identified the level of job insecurity within that sample and the frequency of job loss as it had occurred between waves of that study, the only available option was to generate retrospective appraisals of preparation. However, it is possible that these retrospective assessments are colored post hoc by the experiences of participants after their job loss, such that those who experienced a more smooth adjustment might have reported being more prepared than those who experienced a more rough adjustment. This undermines the capacity to establish causal relationships to the extent that we wish we could. However, to our knowledge, no existing survey has measured preparation prior to the loss of jobs (i.e., “how prepared would you be if you lost this job?”) in such a manner that it would enable documentation of dual-career responses to job loss. If these data were available, this would be a superior approach than that used here. We discuss this concern further in the conclusion.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0730888411415601">Table 1</xref> summarizes the demographic characteristics of the sample. As the Ecology of Careers Study set out to examine the experiences of middle-class, dual-earner couples, it is not surprising that the personal and household incomes of these professionals and managers are substantially higher than the average for the nation. Therefore, findings cannot be generalized to the experiences of low-wage workers. The sample also reflects the aging workforce, with most participants either raising school-age children or are older than age 40 and with children no longer in the household.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0730888411415601">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section10-0730888411415601">
<title>How Much Preparation Do Insecure Workers Perform?</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0730888411415601">Table 1</xref> shows remarkable variation in the amount of preparation for job loss reported by displaced workers. One in five displaced workers and their spouses reported having engaged in no preparation for job loss and only one in three reported “a lot” of preparation. The primary planning strategies displaced workers and spouses mentioned were financial preparation (typically cutting back on spending and accruing savings), preparing for and initiating job searches, and emotional preparation.</p>
<p>To gauge the level of preparedness of the couples who lost jobs as compared to other workers who continue to labor in insecure positions, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0730888411415601">Table 1</xref> includes data of “survivors”—couples in which one or both partners continued to labor in jobs they rated as only 80% confident that they would be able to keep for the next 2 years (as measured at Wave 1). This threshold is proximate to the mean level of security as measured in the original Ecology of Careers Study and is consistent with the standard used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0730888411415601">Sweet et al. (2007)</xref>. Comparisons of survivors with displaced workers and their spouses shows that displaced workers were more likely to report “having not prepared at all” than survivors (20.0% versus 5.3%). They were also more likely to report that finding work in their profession is “very difficult” than survivors (28.8% vs. 6.9%). These findings suggest that retrospective accounts of preparation are likely shaped by the challenges experienced in the wake of job loss. In other words, it is only after couples actually lose jobs that they realize the limitations of their preparation, while couples who labor in insecure jobs may overestimate their level of preparedness for job loss.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0730888411415601">
<title>Preparation as a Dual-Career Activity</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0730888411415601">Table 2</xref> shows the level of preparation for job loss among dual earners. After accounting for previous patterns of career prioritization (which normatively favored the husband’s career over that of the wife’s), we find no difference in the level of planning based on the gender of the displaced worker. However, career prioritization is significantly associated with preparing for job loss, indicating that the act of preparation corresponds with preestablished career strategies. Among couples who lost at least one spouse’s job, only a minority had previously reported favoring the wife’s career over that of the husband’s (17% according to the reports of husbands, 19% according to the reports of wives), while approximately half (53% according to reports of either spouse) favored the career of the husband. Because of thin representation of the wife’s-career-favored hierarchy, we were not able to establish if gender of the favored partner related to planning levels. However, couples who had adopted egalitarian career strategies were about half as likely to have prepared job loss, compared with couples who prioritized one partner’s career over that of the other (odds ratio .44, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0730888411415601">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0730888411415601" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Logistic Regression of Factors Predicting “A Lot” or “Some” Preparation for Job Loss</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0730888411415601" xlink:href="10.1177_0730888411415601-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">Exp <italic>B</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Gender (1 = <italic>Women</italic>)</td>
<td>−0.06</td>
<td>0.56</td>
<td>0.94</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Husband is the displaced worker (W2)</td>
<td>−0.17</td>
<td>0.60</td>
<td>0.84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Egalitarian career strategy (W1)</td>
<td>−0.81</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>0.44<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Notification (W3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No notification (Reference)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> &lt;1 month notification</td>
<td>1.16</td>
<td>0.76</td>
<td>3.18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1+ months notification</td>
<td>1.49</td>
<td>0.48</td>
<td>4.44<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0730888411415601">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Work load prior to job loss (W1)</td>
<td>−0.57</td>
<td>0.39</td>
<td>0.56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Energy scale prior to job loss (W1)</td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td>1.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0730888411415601">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Log household income (W1)</td>
<td>3.44</td>
<td>1.28</td>
<td>31.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0730888411415601">***</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constant</td>
<td>−16.64</td>
<td>6.57</td>
<td>0.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0730888411415601">***</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0730888411415601">
<p>Note: <italic>N</italic> = 149.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0730888411415601">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .10. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Qualitative data further affirm the ways that career hierarchies correspond with preparation for job loss as well as how the formation of these strategies is predicated by decisions made earlier in the life course. In addition, they show that perceptions of adaptation to insecurity and the role preparation plays are not uniformly shared by partners. We illustrate this dynamic with comments from “Owen” and his wife “Naomi.” Owen is a reemployed displaced optical engineer who lost his job of 23 years (along with 300 other workers) and reported having engaged in a lot of preparation.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>My spouse and I talked and decided that I definitely had to find another job. And her job situation happened to be that she was dissatisfied with her present position so she was willing to quit at any time, so that opened up the geographic horizons—so we could go anywhere. It made it easier.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In contrast to Owen’s perception of having engaged in a lot of preparation and that this opened “opportunities,” his wife Naomi reports that she engaged in “little” preparation and she was dissatisfied with the move because she remained out of work at the time of the interview. This same dynamic is observed in the contrasting visions of another couple. “Terrance,” a reemployed displaced senior engineer who lost his job (along with 300 other workers), reported having engaged in a lot of preparation and that his new job in a new community would provide an opportunity for his wife to pursue her career. His wife “Jocelyn,” an insurance manager who resigned her position and moved to follow Terrance, offers a very different appraisal of the impact as she now works in a position comparable with those held by her subordinates in her previous job:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>My salary’s cut in half . . . my benefits are not as good . . . Obviously I [lost] vacation and I had, uh, gosh, a good health insurance program, which I now have . . . really a terrible program. . . . Um (long pause) my 401K was devastated between company stock . . . I lost a huge amount of money. And my retirement, basically, my fund for my retirement is a fraction, a pittance of what it was. After 28 years with the company . . . [My career is ] definitely worse off. . . . I’m very, very concerned that I have spent over a year, in a position that is really almost a entry level position. I’m very concerned about having this even on my resume.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Like Owen and his wife Naomi, Terrance and Jocelyn made a hierarchical career decision as a couple well in advance of the job loss. However, unlike Naomi, Joceyln was initially able to establish a satisfying career as a trailing spouse, only to see it dismantled with the move that followed Terrance’s job loss. Although their husbands both rated their levels of preparation as being high, that perception was not held by their spouses, and both of the women’s careers suffered from geographical moves.</p>
<p>In contrast, consider the response of “Patty,” who found a position at the same manufacturing company as her husband “Frank.” This couple had previously adopted an egalitarian career strategy, with both reporting that neither partner’s career had taken priority. With the corporate restructuring at their company, Frank lost his job, but Patty retained her employment.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>In hindsight, I think we both thought probably having us work in the same department probably wasn’t a good thing to be doing. We probably should have been working in different, maybe different companies or at least different departments you know, so we weren’t so vulnerable, we came pretty close to both of us losing our jobs at the same time and that would have been really devastating.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>As we have discussed elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0730888411415601">Sweet et al., 2007</xref>), the adoption of coworking arrangements such as this are often in response to the challenges of maintaining dual careers. Patty and Frank’s egalitarian career strategy contributed to the formation of their coworking arrangement, but it also compounded their risks and complicated their ability to plan. It is particularly informative that, despite having planned less than couples who adopted hierarchical strategies, few of the couples who adopted egalitarian career strategies reported that they would have done anything different with respect to planning for job loss, other than to secure a larger savings.</p>
<p>For dual-earner couples, the problem of preparing for job loss is a concern not just for the insecure worker but also for his/her spouse. Even when one partner is able to demonstrate agency by planning for his/her career change, these plans can operate on the assumption that the other partner’s career will have to be dislodged. In some couples, this results in one spouse being “agentic” and the other not or agency being enacted in a manner that undermines the career options of one partner. Although agency can be demonstrated with respect to a job loss event, it also manifests itself with respect to preexisting strategies of managing dual careers, tending to favor one spouse’s career (most commonly the husband’s) over that of the spouse. Moreover, when two careers are placed on the same level of priority, the capacity to plan is undermined by uncertainty and the prospect of losing returns on investments in both partners’ careers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0730888411415601">
<title>How Resources Predict the Capacity to Plan for Job Loss</title>
<p>While dual-earner arrangements can constrain the capacity to plan for the loss of one or both partners’ jobs, other resources can facilitate planning. Contrary to what we expected, in our quantitative models, workload does not predict level of preparation (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0730888411415601">Table 2</xref>). However, a number of laid-off workers expressed that they were “too focused on the job” to prepare for its loss. The qualitative data indicated that combined demands on both the work and family fronts have an impact on energy and the capacity to engage in the additional work needed to prepare for job loss. The effects of this dynamic are brought home in this account by “Marie,” mother of an 8-year-old boy and formerly a lead engineer in a manufacturing company, describing why she did little planning:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>. . . at the time and the situation I was in . . . I felt like I was doing just about all I could do.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Quantitative results show that psychological energy is positively associated with preparation. This relationship is strong as individuals who had (in Wave 1) rated their energy at 9 (on the 10-point scale) prior to job loss were more than twice as likely to have prepared for job loss than individuals with scores of 7 or below. Collectively, these findings suggest that the capacity to prepare is not predicted by workloads but may potentially be predicted by workloads as they intersect with the resources of time and energy. As expected, those with higher household incomes were also more likely to plan for job loss.</p>
<p>Advance notification of job loss strongly predicts the level of preparation. It bears emphasizing that those who received more than one month of prior notification were four times (odds ratio 4.44, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0730888411415601">Table 2</xref>) more likely to have prepared for job loss than those who did not receive any advance notification. Given its strong association with preparedness, it is sobering to observe that only one in two couples who lost jobs received <italic>any</italic> advance notice from employers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0730888411415601">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<p>Few couples actively pursued obtaining specific information about their employer’s intents, even when they suspected that their jobs might be at risk. For example, “Oswald” (a displaced technical writer for a software company) reported that he had suspicions that the owners were considering moving their operations. When asked what he could have done differently to prepare his job loss, he reflected,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Well, I think I . . . probably [should have] talked to them . . . maybe a couple months before it happened to find out how much longer they were going to have me there, and then really start a job search. That would have been the smart thing to do.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The fact that most displaced workers had not pushed for clarity on the future of their relationship with their employers reflects that they lacked a key resource—the information needed to plan their careers. Lacking the capacity to obtain this knowledge, their agentic potential was undermined.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0730888411415601">
<title>Does Preparation Predict Dual-Career Resilience?</title>
<p>We expected that those couples who engaged in a lot of preparation would experience less negative dual-career outcomes following job loss and this would be reflected in reports of changes in employment, quality of employment, and financial considerations. We also expected that these outcomes would be evidenced not only in the careers of displaced workers but also in the careers of their spouses.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0730888411415601">Table 3</xref> reveals no differences between those who prepared a lot and those who prepared less in their success in securing work following displacement. However, the quality of employment of those who prepared less was considerably worse than for those who prepared more, indicating that preparation may play a key role in limiting the prospect of being forced to accept jobs that are mismatched to experiences or expectations. Only one in four displaced workers who prepared a lot (23.1%) were currently looking for work, compared with nearly one in two (42.6%) of those who prepared less. Although not reaching the point of statistical significance for the subanalysis of displaced workers and their spouses, when those two groups are combined, the data indicate that those who prepared a lot were more likely to report that their career had changed for the better (48.9%) compared with those who prepared less (38.0%). Fully, one in four (25%) of those who prepared less reported that their careers had changed for the worse, compared with only one in ten (10.6%) of those who had prepared a lot.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0730888411415601" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Career Differences Between Those Who Prepared “A Lot” and Those Who Prepared Less for Job Loss</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0730888411415601" xlink:href="10.1177_0730888411415601-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">All</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Displaced workers</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Spouses</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Prepared less</th>
<th align="center">Prepared a lot</th>
<th align="center">Prepared less</th>
<th align="center">Prepared a lot</th>
<th align="center">Prepared less</th>
<th align="center">Prepared a lot</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Current work status (%) (W3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Working</td>
<td>74.0</td>
<td>73.5</td>
<td>63.0</td>
<td>57.7</td>
<td>87.0</td>
<td>91.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Retired working</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>4.1</td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>3.8</td>
<td>0.0</td>
<td>4.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Retired not working</td>
<td>3.0</td>
<td>4.1</td>
<td>3.7</td>
<td>3.8</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>4.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Not retired not working</td>
<td>22.0</td>
<td>18.4</td>
<td>31.5</td>
<td>34.6</td>
<td>10.9</td>
<td>0.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Currently looking for work (%) (W3)</td>
<td>25.0</td>
<td>14.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
<td>42.6</td>
<td>23.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
<td>4.3</td>
<td>4.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Finding work difficult or very difficult (%) (W3)</td>
<td>58.3</td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td>73.1</td>
<td>60.0</td>
<td>40.9</td>
<td>39.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Change in career (%) (W3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Better</td>
<td>38.0</td>
<td>48.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
<td>50.0</td>
<td>58.3</td>
<td>23.9</td>
<td>39.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Worse</td>
<td>25.0</td>
<td>10.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
<td>29.6</td>
<td>12.5</td>
<td>19.6</td>
<td>8.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> About the same</td>
<td>37.0</td>
<td>40.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
<td>20.4</td>
<td>29.2</td>
<td>56.5</td>
<td>52.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Job loss changed the way career is managed (%) (W3)</td>
<td>56.1</td>
<td>36.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0730888411415601">**</xref></td>
<td>75.0</td>
<td>41.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0730888411415601">***</xref></td>
<td>34.8</td>
<td>30.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Considered changing career, retraining, or retiring (%) (W3)</td>
<td>38.0</td>
<td>30.6</td>
<td>44.4</td>
<td>38.5</td>
<td>30.4</td>
<td>21.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pursued career, retraining or retirement (%) (W3)</td>
<td>15.0</td>
<td>20.4</td>
<td>16.7</td>
<td>23.1</td>
<td>13.0</td>
<td>17.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Considered relocating (%) (W3)</td>
<td>30.0</td>
<td>24.5</td>
<td>31.5</td>
<td>34.6</td>
<td>28.3</td>
<td>12.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Actually relocated (%) (W3)</td>
<td>3.0</td>
<td>6.1</td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>11.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
<td>4.3</td>
<td>0.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>N</italic></td>
<td>100</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0730888411415601">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .10. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Detailed personal accounts provide a window of explanation for the quantitatively measured differences observed. In some circumstances, higher levels of preparation were identified by workers as enabling a seamless transition into new opportunities. For example, “Matilda” engaged in a lot of preparation while she worked as a senior security analyst and found employment elsewhere in same company, even as it eliminated the jobs of 300 other workers. She explained her preparation in the following way:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>The phrase I like to use is, you can do what they ask you to do, and the best job at it, but they can still decide tomorrow they don’t want you, or want your job. . . . so you’ve got to always be prepared to assess what is of interest to you, either moving into the same thing somewhere else, or changing jobs.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>When we asked about how individuals prepared for job loss and their experiences of losing a job, many reported modest impacts because they had experienced prior job losses in the past. As one participant, “Jennifer”—recently reemployed as an engineering manager and someone who engaged in a lot of preparation—explained,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>[Did I plan?] Oh, yes I was flatfooted and conk cold [the first time I lost a job] (laughs). [Now I] keep working with friends . . . keep my resume extremely current and . . . mail them occasionally to very reliable sources.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Participants reported that these prior experiences shaped their strategies of managing careers as well as subjective interpretations of events, as another one participant “Priscilla”—an unemployed manager—explained,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>[Did it affect my feeling about myself?] No. You know, if you had talked to me when I was a lot younger, and I’d lost my first job, I would tell you I would be devastated. But this is not the first time that I was even laid off.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Preparation also predicts some changes in career management strategies, but not others. Less prepared displaced workers were most apt to report that their career strategies changed as a result of their job displacement (75%). No differences were identified in the proportions of those who prepared a lot and those who prepared less in terms of their consideration of changing careers, retiring, or retraining. Although no difference was observed on the level of preparation and whether relocating was considered, displaced workers who planned more (11.5%) were more likely to actually move than those who prepared less (1.9%).</p>
<p>Although not significant for every variable, and not equally important for the displaced worker and his/her spouse, these findings support our overarching expectation that prospects for achieving successful career adjustment in the wake of a job loss can be enhanced by preparation. It is also possible that causality works in the opposite direction, however, and that retrospective accounts of preparedness may be shaped by outcomes, as those who landed on their feet (some perhaps simply by chance) may rate their preparedness more favorably than those who did not. Moreover, it is possible that this relationship might be partially spurious as those who are best positioned to satisfy their new career needs may also be simultaneously positioned to prepare. Thus, some caution should be used in concluding that advance preparation alone is responsible for the differences observed here.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0730888411415601">
<title>Does Preparation Predict Financial Returns from Work?</title>
<p>Assessing changes in individual and household incomes is complicated by the observation that individuals who prepared a lot also tended to have higher household incomes at Wave 1 than those who prepared less for job loss (nearly US$15,000 more). <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0730888411415601">Table 4</xref> shows that those who had prepared less were considerably more likely to report that their financial situation had changed for the worse in Wave 3 (49.0%) compared with those who had prepared more (30.6%), and much of this difference can be explained by the perspective of the spouses of displaced workers who prepared less, with more than half (54.3%) reporting that their financial situation had worsened. Although not statistically significant, the assessment of the impact on finances by displaced workers trended in the same direction.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0730888411415601" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Financial Differences Between Those Who Prepared “A Lot” and Those Who Prepared Less for Job Loss</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0730888411415601" xlink:href="10.1177_0730888411415601-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">All</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Displaced workers</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Spouses</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Prepared less</th>
<th align="center">Prepared a lot</th>
<th align="center">Prepared less</th>
<th align="center">Prepared a lot</th>
<th align="center">Prepared less</th>
<th align="center">Prepared a lot</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Change in financial situation (%) (W3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Better</td>
<td>22.4</td>
<td>26.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
<td>26.9</td>
<td>26.9</td>
<td>17.4</td>
<td>26.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Worse</td>
<td>49.0</td>
<td>30.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
<td>44.2</td>
<td>38.5</td>
<td>54.3</td>
<td>21.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> About the same</td>
<td>28.6</td>
<td>42.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
<td>28.8</td>
<td>34.6</td>
<td>28.3</td>
<td>52.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Impact on financial situation “a lot” or “some” (%) (W3)</td>
<td>65.0</td>
<td>57.1</td>
<td>64.8</td>
<td>65.4</td>
<td>65.2</td>
<td>47.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Change in individual income (mean) (W3 – W1)</td>
<td>−2,791.4</td>
<td>−3,661.3</td>
<td>−3,972.4</td>
<td>−15,329.8</td>
<td>−988.8</td>
<td>8,525.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Standard deviation</td>
<td>28,183.9</td>
<td>31,700.1</td>
<td>23,651.9</td>
<td>36,393.6</td>
<td>34,615.3</td>
<td>19,906.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Household income (W1)</td>
<td>93,710.0</td>
<td>118,602.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0730888411415601">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Standard deviation</td>
<td>35,881.7</td>
<td>48,101.6</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Household income (W3)</td>
<td>91,266.6</td>
<td>100,314.2</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Standard deviation</td>
<td>50,399.0</td>
<td>46,732.5</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Change in household income (mean) (W3 – W1)</td>
<td>−2,524.5</td>
<td>−8,382.0</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Standard deviation</td>
<td>36,005.5</td>
<td>43,034.3</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Husband–wife income difference (mean) (W1)</td>
<td>10,768.3</td>
<td>23,924.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Standard deviation</td>
<td>29,763.0</td>
<td>41,543.2</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Husband–wife income difference (mean) (W3)</td>
<td>21,371.7</td>
<td>33,685.8</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Standard deviation</td>
<td>43,947.3</td>
<td>52,494.2</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Change in husband–wife income difference (mean) (W3 – W1)</td>
<td>9,220.2</td>
<td>6,533.3</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Standard deviation</td>
<td>37,662.8</td>
<td>48,001.2</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>N</italic></td>
<td>100</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-0730888411415601">
<p>Note: Couples in which one or both partners are retired and not working are excluded from the analysis of income.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0730888411415601">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .10. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Consistent with the earlier analysis of how preparation fits within gendered career strategies and prospects, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0730888411415601">Table 4</xref> also shows that couples who prepared the most for job loss were also more likely to have significantly higher husband–wife income disparities prior to their job loss (US$10,768 for lower preparers; US$23,925 for high preparers). The average husband–wife income gaps expanded between the waves of this study, indicating the impact that job loss can have on gender disparities in earnings. However, the impact of preparation for job loss is not significantly associated with either the narrowing or the expanding of the gap between husbands’ and wives’ incomes between survey waves. As we discuss below, preparation also predicts the ways that changes in financial circumstances are interpreted.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0730888411415601">
<title>Is Preparation Associated With Health and Emotional Resilience?</title>
<p>Perhaps as important as monetary changes are the ways displaced workers interpret their changing career situations and how that corresponds to subsequent agentic responses to the hardships that can follow job loss. We expected that those who prepared a lot would report more favorable changes in health and emotional well-being following job loss compared with those who prepared less and that this would be evident in the experiences of both the displaced worker and his/her spouse. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0730888411415601">Table 5</xref> provides support for some but not all of these expectations.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-0730888411415601" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Health and Emotional Well-Being Differences Between Those Who Prepared “A Lot” and Those Who Prepared Less for Job Loss</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0730888411415601" xlink:href="10.1177_0730888411415601-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">All</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Displaced workers</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Spouses</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Prepared less</th>
<th align="center">Prepared a lot</th>
<th align="center">Prepared less</th>
<th align="center">Prepared a lot</th>
<th align="center">Prepared less</th>
<th align="center">Prepared a lot</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Impact on health “a lot” or “some” (%) (W3)</td>
<td>43.3</td>
<td>28.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
<td>48.1</td>
<td>51.9</td>
<td>37.8</td>
<td>22.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Change in physical health (%) (W3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Better</td>
<td>23.0</td>
<td>30.6</td>
<td>31.5</td>
<td>42.3</td>
<td>13.0</td>
<td>17.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Worse</td>
<td>15.0</td>
<td>8.2</td>
<td>11.1</td>
<td>15.4</td>
<td>19.6</td>
<td>0.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> About the same</td>
<td>62.0</td>
<td>61.2</td>
<td>57.4</td>
<td>42.3</td>
<td>67.4</td>
<td>82.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Impact on emotional well-being “a lot” or “some” (%) (W3)</td>
<td>66.3</td>
<td>41.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0730888411415601">***</xref></td>
<td>69.8</td>
<td>50.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0730888411415601">*</xref></td>
<td>62.2</td>
<td>31.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0730888411415601">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Change in emotional well-being (%) (W3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Better</td>
<td>37.0</td>
<td>35.4</td>
<td>46.3</td>
<td>44.0</td>
<td>26.1</td>
<td>26.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Worse</td>
<td>18.0</td>
<td>16.7</td>
<td>20.4</td>
<td>20.0</td>
<td>15.2</td>
<td>13.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> About the same</td>
<td>45.0</td>
<td>47.9</td>
<td>33.3</td>
<td>36.0</td>
<td>58.7</td>
<td>60.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>N</italic></td>
<td>100</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn7-0730888411415601">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .10. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Nearly one in two (43.3%) of those who engaged in lower levels of preparation report that the job loss had significant impact on their health, in contrast to one in four (28.3%) of those who prepared a lot. Although we found no differences in the direction of the impact (health improving or deteriorating) for displaced workers, spouses who prepared more were less likely to report health declines and more likely to report health improvements. We were surprised that a greater proportion of displaced workers (both those who prepared and those who did not) reported health improvements than reported health declines following their job losses. One recurrent theme in the qualitative data is that the loss of the job (for both those who prepared and those who did not) freed individuals to “take care of myself” and redefine their priorities as well as to disentangle financial aspects of careers from the larger construct of “life.” This reorientation to work is reflected in the response of “Fritz,” a man with 23 years with his employer prior to being laid off with 1,000 other workers. Fritz remained unemployed at Wave 3 (despite reporting high levels of preparation) and assessed the impact on his career as follows:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>It depends on what aspect you’re talking about. Financially, I was obviously much better off [in my old job]. Physically, emotionally, happiness, I was much worse off. So was my sanity . . . I’m happier, sleep better, and enjoy life a heck of a lot more.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Fritz had a lot going for him in that he received 18 months severance pay which in turn buffered some of the financial strains experienced more severely by displaced workers who were less prepared and less favorably situated. Survey data show that 56% of the sample received some severance pay but qualitative comments indicated that few received more than a little compensation.</p>
<p>Even when financial assessments worsened, other aspects of their lives often improved following the loss of jobs and this was predicted by preparation for job loss. For some, the changes were dramatic and suggest job displacement as a real turning point, especially in terms of renewed attention to health concerns and the initiation of exercise routines. Jennifer (who engaged in a lot of preparation and was recently reemployed as an engineering manager) offers a perspective reflected in many other interviews:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>[When I was in my old job] I couldn’t do a simple curl I now curl with twenty pound weights. I could not bike or walk, but now I click off twenty minutes at a time and can walk nine miles. . . . [now I am engaged in] weightlifting, joining a course in the gym and am becoming much more physical.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Those who had prepared a lot for job loss are also less likely to report substantial negative impacts on their emotional well-being (41.3%) in comparison with those who prepared less (66.3%). Those who transitioned immediately into retirement tended to have more positive appraisals as did empty nesters whose children had already exited the household and were no longer financially dependent. This observation corresponds with expectations from what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0730888411415601">Elder (1998)</xref> terms <italic>the life stage principle</italic>—that the ramifications of an event depend on its timing within the person’s life course.</p>
<p>How can an ostensibly aversive event (job loss) be associated with reports of improved emotional well-being? It is important to remember that many of the participants in our target group had spent years working in environments of low security and low morale, environments that they called “bad,” “really bad,” and even “toxic.” Transitions out of these environments were followed by a sense of relief—not only in exiting stressful jobs but also in alleviating the worry of the prospect of job loss. Second, some job losses removed constraints of demanding schedules, which translated into new opportunities to engage in “psychic work,” to “mellow,” and to “reprioritize values.” Those who had greater financial resources were the most likely to report benefits of being able to rest and recover as well as the least desperation in finding new work.</p>
<p>Both the quantitative and qualitative evidence indicated that preparation predicts less severe emotional or health changes, especially for the one in six displaced workers who said that their emotional well-being was worse after their job loss. Among those who reported emotional tolls, the impact was sometimes profound, as interviews revealed consideration of suicide, diminished capacities for trust, and decreased motivation to work. These types of changes were commonly traced by participants to both the nature of the new economy and their perceived lack of control. For example, “Ethel” (a currently unemployed displaced public relations manager who engaged in no preparation) reports that,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I’ve never had an employer say “sayonara—get out of here” before. That was pretty tough. (Pause) The longer [my job search] goes on, the harder it is in terms of your self esteem.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The narratives offered by the displaced workers and their spouses indicated that internalized feelings of control contributed to their capacities to cope with job loss. For example, Maurice (who engaged in a lot of preparation) began searching for work 4 months before his job as an operations manager was eliminated. He had yet to find work nearly a year later. Note that even though he experienced serious difficulties in locating a replacement job, his agentic disposition remained intact:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I have a high ego, I think highly of myself (laughs). I think I am very good, and like I told you, I am listening to what my boss said, I was not let go for performance or anything. Ours was a business case of support and they targeted our crew. So I sit there and say I am an “a player,” and being an “a player” can know that I should be able to get a job. You just have to have the right market timing. And I feel good about myself and I go to these interviews, and the thing that is killing me is that I’m interviewing excellent and I talk to human resource people. What’s killing me is that there are people with more experience than I have at the levels I am trying to get into.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This type of attitude stands in stark contrast to other workers who prepared less. For example, Jonathan (a displaced health safety coordinator who only prepared “a little”) explains his perspective on his job loss,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>You question the process itself. And, you question leadership and then, above all, you question yourself. And that leads to this self doubt where, you know, sometimes it’s difficult to—to get anything done. Because you don’t know what’s right anymore, or that’s the feeling that started to happen.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Tobias (who engaged in no preparation and who received no advance notification before being displaced as an information specialist) appraises his sense of control in this manner,</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>My whole work ethic was rattled by the situation. It’s not what they did, it’s how they did it. Um, I think there were a lot of options they could’ve looked at if they would’ve given me a heads-up. I could’ve easily left the company and gone to another company and not gone into the period of shock that I was in. I think it was a very poor management style.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In sum, our findings indicate that one reason why physical and emotional well-being does not uniformly decline following job loss (even if preparation did not take place) has to do with the toxic work environments that many displaced workers are exiting. Some see job loss as a new opportunity to redefine themselves and their careers. Preparation for job loss does not appear to altogether eliminate negative health and emotional impacts following job loss, but the evidence presented in this article supports a conclusion that it likely contributes to resilience. This indicates that emotional readiness is an important component of planning for job loss, and yet the way many individuals lose jobs undermines this component of preparation.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0730888411415601">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In today’s global risk economy, job loss is a commonplace event—for the middle-class as well as less for advantaged members of the workforce. Moreover, it increasingly takes place in a dual-earner environment, which compounds the logistics of preparing for and rescuing careers. We showed that the process of preparing for job loss happens at both the individual and couple level but that not everyone prepares in the same way or to the same extent. Although our goal was to predict respondents’ interpretations of having prepared and to examine correlates of preparation, our most important contribution may be identifying a considerable <italic>lack</italic> of preparation for job loss as a key context of vulnerability.</p>
<p>The complexities of managing two careers that are locked in tandem significantly increase the challenges of navigating work in insecure contexts. Our analysis shows an association that sits uncomfortably with the creation of power/career equality within dual-career families. Egalitarian couples, those who give equal consideration to both partners’ careers, turn out to be among the least prepared for job loss, and we believe this indicates something important about the structure of jobs and careers in the risk economy. Even if egalitarian arrangements present the ideal dual-earner family arrangement, this association suggests that the current risk economy operates with barriers to the implementation of this couple-level strategy. Moreover, because an association between preparedness and advanced notification is identified, this suggests that preparation may be undermined by the limited capacity of employees to ask for (or expect) clear indications of their employers’ intents.</p>
<p>We also investigated associations between preparation and career and financial outcomes, finding that couples who engage in higher levels of preparation are less likely to report their financial situation worsened following job loss. They are also more likely to find new satisfying jobs. By contrast, members of dual-career couples who prepare less for job loss are more apt to change their career management strategies and are less satisfied with their new employment situation. The psychological framing of job loss is also associated with preparation; those who prepare are more likely to report that their lives improve following the loss of their jobs and are less likely to report the most injurious situations (such as feelings of deep depression). This suggests that preparation helps individuals to anticipate the challenges that lay ahead, to redefine their career expectations, and to locate new opportunities.</p>
<p>Before discussing policy implications, it is important to address some limitations in our study and how these might direct future research. A key strength of our study is its reliance on both quantitative and qualitative panel data. However, the sample size limited the types of statistical analysis we could perform. As our study was limited to primarily White, middle-class, dual-earner couples, our findings cannot speak to the severity and adaptation to risk as it is influenced by a variety of factors including race, disability, immigrant status, socioeconomic status, and other factors that intersect with vulnerability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0730888411415601">Andersen, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0730888411415601">Dominguez &amp; Watkins, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0730888411415601">Kmec, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0730888411415601">Pollert &amp; Charlwood, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0730888411415601">Spalter-Roth &amp; Deitch, 1999</xref>). Future research could address these issues as well as how single-parent families prepare for, and respond to, job loss. In this study, we asked participants to indicate how much preparation they performed, and then, in qualitative analysis, we identified three types of preparation: financial (e.g., savings and budgeting), career (e.g., job searches), and emotional (e.g., being psychologically set for the transition). In addition to financial and career preparation, our study indicates that emotional readiness may be important to facilitating resilience, a finding consistent with studies of other life-course events beyond job loss. Creating and analyzing quantifiable measures of each type of preparation, and measuring these dimensions prior to life major career events, could be a productive path for future studies.</p>
<p>A strength of our study was the use of panel data to identify an appropriate sample and to use Wave 1 measures (obtained prior to the job loss) to predict levels of preparedness identified after the job loss. Some causal relationships are more strongly established with our longitudinal methodology than others. Most limiting, though, is the reliance on retrospective accounts on preparedness, which may be influenced after the fact by the level of success in adjusting to job loss. It is possible that the retrospective appraisals we used to assess preparedness have been swayed by the very things we hypothesized as being affected by preparation. In defense of our conclusions, however, we point to the detailed accounts offered through our qualitative data, but the consideration remains nonetheless. To address this concern, future longitudinal studies will need to assess appraisals of preparation as evaluated prior to job loss and then use those prospective accounts to predict longer term consequences of job loss on career, social-psychological, and family well-being observed at later points in time.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0730888411415601">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>An ongoing discussion concerns who should bear the burden of risk in the new economy and what roles various social institutions might play in reconfiguring existing arrangements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0730888411415601">Bernstein, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0730888411415601">Hacker, 2006</xref>). In comparison with their counterparts throughout most other advanced economies, the “ownership” workers have of their lives and careers in the United States is accompanied by far fewer entitlements or protections. Although the discourse of ownership stresses the power of agency, the conditions in which career transitions occur in a risk economy impose blinders that make preparation difficult to perform. Our study suggests that employers can facilitate preparation by providing advance notice, and this in turn can facilitate resilience. However, this remedy (and especially so long as it is voluntary) is not sufficient to address workers’ needs in the new risk economy. Our findings suggest that cultivating personal capacities to prepare for job loss requires reconfiguring wider sets of expectations concerning jobs designs and employer–employee commitments to one another. So long as workers are overextended and underinformed, their capacity to prepare for job loss will be limited.</p>
<p>In comparison with most other economic powers, the United States provides scant support in the wake of job loss from either employers (in terms of severance pay) or the government (in terms of unemployment compensation or support for retraining). Yet these types of institutionalized arrangements can have major impacts on resilience to job loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0730888411415601">Gangl, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0730888411415601">Kochan, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0730888411415601">Root, 2006</xref>). Given the challenge of finding suitable replacement work, so long as workers need to plan careers under these types of conditions, many will not be able to develop viable plans for adjustment to job loss.</p>
<p>Our study suggests that when individuals or couples labor are positioned to plan and prepare, they can make meaningful adjustments in their lives and careers. Although it is beyond the scope of this study to recommend specific policy initiatives, our findings indicate inherent problems in assuming that individuals or families can effectively bear the burden of risk in a turbulent global economy through acts of personal preparation. Indeed, many existing institutional arrangements may discourage preparation rather than enhance it.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The authors declared receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: Support was extended through the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation for the collection and analysis of data with the expressed intent of having this work published in scholarly journals. The Ecology of Careers Study and the Couples Managing Change Study were supported by grants from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Unemployment and subjective well-being</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Appelbaum</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>The tough test of downsizing</article-title>. <source>Organizational Dynamics</source>, <volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>68</fpage>-<lpage>79</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Armstrong-Stassen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Survivors’ reactions to a workforce reduction</article-title>. <source>Revue Canadienne des Sciences de Administration</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>334</fpage>-<lpage>344</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Armstrong-Stassen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Determinants of how managers cope with organisational downsizinig</article-title>. <source>Applied Psychology: An International Review</source>, <volume>55</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>The self and mechanisms of agency</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Suls</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Psychological perspectives on the self</source> (pp. <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gareis</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Role theory perspectives on work and family</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Pitt-Catsouphes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kossek</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Work and family handbook: Multidisciplinary perspectives, methods and approaches</source> (pp. <fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>222</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gareis</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Usable flexibility, employee’s concerns about elders, gender, and job withdrawal</article-title>. <source>The Psychologist-Manager Journal</source>, <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>50</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>All together now: Common sense for a fair economy</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Berrett-Koehler</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blumer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969</year>). <source>Symbolic interactionism: Perspective and method</source>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brockner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Scope of justice in the workplace: How survivors react to co-worker layoffs</article-title>. <source>Journal of Social Issues</source>, <volume>46</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burawoy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <source>Manufacturing consent: Changes in the labor process under monopoly capitalism</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burgard</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>House</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Toward a better estimation of the effect of job loss on health</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health and Social Behavior</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>369</fpage>-<lpage>384</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Caitlin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mast</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The impact of anticipatory grief on caregiver burden in dementia caregivers</article-title>. <source>The Gerontologist</source>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>388</fpage>-<lpage>396</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cappelli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>The new deal at work</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard Business School Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leiter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tomaskovic-Devey</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Contingent autonomy: Technology, bureaucracy, and relative power in the labor process</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>422</fpage>-<lpage>455</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clausen</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Gender, contexts, and turning points in adults’ lives</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Moen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elder, Jr.</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luscher</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Examining lives in context: Perspectives on the ecology of human development</source> (pp. <fpage>365</fpage>-<lpage>392</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clawson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>The next upsurge: Labor and the new social movements</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ILR Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crosnoe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elder</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Successful adaptation in the later years: A life course approach to aging</article-title>. <source>Social Psychology Quarterly</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>328</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayslip</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hobdy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Psychological hardiness and adjustment to life events in adulthood</article-title>. <source>Journal of Adult Development</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>248</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Creating networks for survival and mobility: Social capital among African-American and Latin-American low-income mothers</article-title>. <source>Social Problems</source>, <volume>50</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>111</fpage>-<lpage>135</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dooley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Depression and unemployment</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Community Psychology</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>745</fpage>-<lpage>765</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elder</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The life course and human development</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lerner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Handbook of child psychology, Vol.1: Theoretical models of human development</source> (pp. <fpage>939</fpage>-<lpage>991</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Emirbayer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mische</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>What is agency?</article-title> <source>American Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>103</volume>, <fpage>692</fpage>-<lpage>1023</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ezzy</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Fate and agency in job loss narratives</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Sociology</source>, <volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>121</fpage>-<lpage>134</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fouad</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bynner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Work transitions</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>-<lpage>251</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Galinsky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>The changing workforce: Highlights of the national study</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Families and Work Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gangl</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Scar effects of unemployment: An assessment of institutional complementarities</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>986</fpage>-<lpage>1013</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forde</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perrett</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Redundancy as a critical live event: Moving on from the welsh steel industry through career change</article-title>. <source>Work, Employment and Society</source>, <volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>A comparison of spousal anticipatory grief and conventional grief</article-title>. <source>Death Studies</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>541</fpage>-<lpage>569</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Granovetter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <article-title>The strength of weak ties</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>78</volume>, <fpage>1360</fpage>-<lpage>1380</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grunberg</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Anderson-Connolly</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Surviving layoffs: The effects on organizational commitment and job performance</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grzywacz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Work-family experiences and physical health: A summary and critical review</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wfnetwork.bc.edu/encyclopedia_entry.php?id=6410&amp;area=All">http://wfnetwork.bc.edu/encyclopedia_entry.php?id=6410&amp;area=All</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hacker</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>The great risk shift: The assault on American jobs, families, health care and retirement and how you can fight back</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hakim</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Work-lifestyle choices in the twenty-first century</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hochschild</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>The time bind: When work becomes home and home becomes work</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Metropolitan Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hodson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Dignity in the workplace under participative management: Alienation and freedom revisited</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>719</fpage>-<lpage>738</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hodson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Dignity at work</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hodson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roscigno</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Chaos and the abuse of power: Workplace bullying in the organizational and institutional context</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>382</fpage>-<lpage>416</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gerson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>The time divide: Work, family, and gender inequality</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jahoda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <source>Employment and unemployment: A social psychological analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Monserud</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Judgments about work and the features of young adult’s jobs</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>194</fpage>-<lpage>224</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kahneman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tversky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Choices, values, and frames</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>341</fpage>-<lpage>350</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kalleberg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Precarious work, insecure workers: Employment relations in transition</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>74</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>M. Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Work orientation and wives’ employment careers: An evaluation of Hakim’s preference theory</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>430</fpage>-<lpage>462</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelvin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jarrett</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <source>Unemployment: Its social psychological effects</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kmec</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Ties that bind? Race and networks in job turnover</article-title>. <source>Social Problems</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>483</fpage>-<lpage>503</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kochan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The American worker: Disposable or indispensible</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>377</fpage>-<lpage>381</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Latack</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kinicki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prussia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>An integrative process model of coping with job loss</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>311</fpage>-<lpage>334</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leana</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <source>Coping with loss: How individuals, organizations and communities respond to layoffs</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lexington Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Intimate work: A typology of the social support that workers provide to their network members</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>125</fpage>-<lpage>147</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1934</year>). <source>Mind, self and society</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mendenhall</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalil</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spindel</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Job loss at mid-life: Managers and executives face the “new risk economy.”</article-title> <source>Social Forces</source>, <volume>87</volume>, <fpage>184</fpage>-<lpage>209</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spreitzer</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Explaining how survivors respond to downsizing</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>567</fpage>-<lpage>588</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>It’s about time: Couples and careers</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roehling</surname><given-names>P. V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>The career mystique</source>. <publisher-loc>Boulder, CO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rowman &amp; Littlefield</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Naumann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beis</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Laid off, but still loyal</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Conflict Management</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>356</fpage>-<lpage>368</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Osnowitz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Freelancing expertise: Contract professionals in the new economy</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ILR Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pavalko</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The rhythm of work: Health effects of women’s work dynamics</article-title>. <source>Social Forces</source>, <volume>77</volume>, <fpage>1141</fpage>-<lpage>1162</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pearlin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>The study of stress</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health and Social Behavior</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>-<lpage>256</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pearlin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Menaghan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mullan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>The stress process</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health and Social Behavior</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>337</fpage>-<lpage>356</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pearlin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schieman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fazio</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meersman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Stress, health, and the life course: Some conceptual specifications</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health and Social Behavior</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>-<lpage>219</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Perrucci</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Economic strain, family structure and problems with children among displaced workers</article-title>. <source>Journal of Sociology and Social Welfare</source>, <volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Perrucci</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perrucci</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Targ</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Gender differences in the economic, psychological and social effects of plant closings in an expanding economy</article-title>. <source>Social Science Journal</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>217</fpage>-<lpage>233</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pixley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Life course patterns of career-priorizing decisions and occupational attainment in dual earner couples</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>163</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pollert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charlwood</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The vulnerable worker in Britain and problems at work</article-title>. <source>Work, Employment and Society</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>-<lpage>362</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Presser</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Working in a 24/7 economy: Challenges for American families</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Russell Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Root</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Job loss, the family, and public policy</article-title>. <source>Marriage and Family Review</source>, <volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schiebinger</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gilmartin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Dual-career academic couples: What universities need to know</source>. <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schieman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glavin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Trouble at the border? Gender, flexiblity at work, and the work–home interface</article-title>. <source>Social Problems</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>590</fpage>-<lpage>611</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Crossing the great divide: Worker risk and opportunity in the new economy</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sonnentag</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Recovery, work engagement, and proactive behavior: A new look at the interface between nonwork and work</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Psychology</source>, <volume>88</volume>, <fpage>518</fpage>-<lpage>528</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Spalter-Roth</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deitch</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>“I don’t feel right sized; I feel out-of-work sized”: Gender, race, ethnicity, and the unequal costs of displacement</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>446</fpage>-<lpage>482</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Job loss expectations, realizations, and household consumptive behavior</article-title>. <source>Review of Economics and Statistics</source>, <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>253</fpage>-<lpage>269</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Opting out? Why women really quit careers and head home</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strandh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Different exit routes from unemployment and their impact on mental well-being: The role of the economic situation and the predictability of the life course</article-title>. <source>Work, Employment and Society</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>459</fpage>-<lpage>479</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stryker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Serpe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Committment, identity, salience and role behavior: Theory and research</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ickes</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Personality, roles and social behavior</source> (pp. <fpage>199</fpage>-<lpage>218</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meiksins</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Changing contours of work: Jobs and opportunities in the new economy</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pine Forge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Intimate academics: Coworking couples in two universities</article-title>. <source>Innovative Higher Education</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>252</fpage>-<lpage>274</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meiksins</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Dual earners in double jeopardy: Preparing for job loss in the new risk economy</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Workplace temporalities</source> (<volume>Vol. 17</volume>, pp. <fpage>437</fpage>-<lpage>461</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swisher</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The family-friendly community and its life course fit for dual-earner couples</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marriage and Family</source>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>281</fpage>-<lpage>292</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Uchitelle</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>The disposable American: Layoffs and their consequences</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Knopf</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vosler</surname><given-names>N. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Page-Adams</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Predictors of depression among workers at the time of a plant closing</article-title>. <source>Journal of Sociology and Social Welfare</source>, <volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wanberg</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bunce</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Perceived fairness of layoffs among individuals who have been laid off</article-title>. <source>Personnel Psychology</source>, <volume>52</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr84-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>The two-income trap: Why middle-class mothers and fathers are going broke</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr85-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wethington</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pixley</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kavey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Turning points in work careers</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Moen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Its about time: Couples and careers</source> (pp. <fpage>168</fpage>-<lpage>182</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr86-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chivers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blair-Loy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Use of formal and informal work-family policies on the digital assembly line</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>327</fpage>-<lpage>350</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr87-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wheaton</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Life transitions, role histories, and mental health</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>223</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr88-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wiesenfeld</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brockner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>A self-affirmation analysis of survivors’ reactions to unfair organizational downsizing</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>441</fpage>-<lpage>460</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr89-0730888411415601">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Grounding the regine of precarious employment: Homeless day laborers’ negatiation of the job queue</article-title>. <source>Work and Occupations</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>246</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>