<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CPJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcpj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Pediatr (Phila)</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical Pediatrics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0009-9228</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1938-2707</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0009922812440840</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0009922812440840</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Early Pediatric Emergency Department Return Visits</article-title>
<subtitle>A Prospective Patient-Centric Assessment</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Alliyia B.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812440840">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Place</surname><given-names>Rick</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812440840">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, FACEP, FAAEM</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812440840">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Malubay</surname><given-names>Sienna M.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MS</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0009922812440840">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0009922812440840"><label>1</label>Inova Fairfax Hospital, Falls Church, VA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0009922812440840">Alliyia B. Ali, Inova Fairfax Hospital, 3300 Gallows Road, Falls Church, VA 22042, USA Email: <email>alliyia.ali@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>51</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>651</fpage>
<lpage>658</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0009922812440840">
<title>Background</title>
<p>A substantial percentage of emergency department (ED) patients return within 72 hours of their initial evaluation. Quality reviews typically demonstrate that most revisits do not seem to be directly related to problematic care provided on the first evaluation. We examined the possibility that return visits are related to nonmedical issues on the first visit, most notably patient discharge education.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0009922812440840">
<title>Objective</title>
<p>We prospectively surveyed a convenience sample of caregivers in a pediatric ED to determine why they returned with their children within 72 hours of their initial ED visit.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0009922812440840">
<title>Design/Methods</title>
<p>All patients who returned within 72 hours of a previous visit were identified and prospectively interviewed using a survey instrument with nominal (multiple choice) and brief descriptive responses.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0009922812440840">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Caregivers of 124 children were prospectively surveyed; 93 children (75%) returned because their symptoms had not improved or worsened. Only 50 (53%) had contacted their primary medical doctor (PMD) prior to the second visit; of these, 14 (28%) could not get an appointment, and 32 (64%) were told to return to the ED. Discharge instructions were felt to be informative by 94% (n = 86) of caregivers with the same number (94%) reported being satisfied with the first ED physician. Twenty-nine children (30%) were admitted on the second visit.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0009922812440840">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Among children who are discharged from the emergency department and return within 72 hours, most caregivers are satisfied with the care and instructions provided on their first visits. Though most patients have a PMD, many do not call them prior to their return ED visit, and those who do either cannot schedule an appointment or are told to return to the ED. The majority of patients return for clinical progression of illness.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>return visits</kwd>
<kwd>emergency department</kwd>
<kwd>administration</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section6-0009922812440840" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>A substantial percentage of emergency department (ED) patients are seen for a return visit (RV) within 72 hours of their initial evaluation. Standard return rates in the United States are between 2.2% and 3.5%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922812440840">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0009922812440840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0009922812440840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0009922812440840"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0009922812440840">5</xref></sup> These unanticipated repeat visits have been used as quality indicators in medical care, with this population characterized as being at high risk for errors in diagnosis or physician management.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922812440840">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0009922812440840">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0009922812440840">6</xref></sup> Etiologies and trends of avoidable RVs were investigated in the hope of changing medical practice and improving care.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922812440840">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0009922812440840">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0009922812440840">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Many institutions and hospital committees continue to use RV rate as the benchmarking tool for quality of care provided. Many studies in the past 2 decades have looked at the perceived medical necessity of RVs, with a focus on identifying problematic medical care provided on the initial visit.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922812440840">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0009922812440840">6</xref></sup> Others have analyzed RVs from the perspective of patient demographics, demonstrating that many unnecessary RVs are to the result of a lack of care continuity and availability of timely outpatient follow-up.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0009922812440840">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0009922812440840">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0009922812440840"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0009922812440840">10</xref></sup> Recently, pediatric ED investigators examined RVs associated with subsequent admission and found that 90% of initial ED evaluations were considered appropriate, and admissions were primarily for progression of illness.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0009922812440840">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>Most published literature investigating the root causes of RVs is based on retrospective chart review. Consequently, analysis of each visit and conclusions regarding the quality of care were made retrospectively, often through chart review, increasing the risk of bias in the evaluation process.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922812440840">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0009922812440840">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0009922812440840">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0009922812440840">5</xref></sup> Furthermore, the process of retrospective evaluation is almost always from the perspective of the physician evaluator.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0009922812440840">7</xref></sup> Very few articles focus on the caregivers’ perceptions of what occurred during the initial medical encounter.</p>
<p>Care provided by the initial physician may seem perfectly sound to the physician evaluator, whereas the patient or caregiver may have an entirely different perception of the quality of care initially provided. Our research hypothesis was that patient return within 72 hours of an initial ED visit was a result of either ineffective doctor–patient rapport or poor discharge education.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0009922812440840" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section8-0009922812440840">
<title>Study Design</title>
<p>This was a prospective survey of a convenience sample of patients arriving in the pediatric ED within 72 hours of a previous visit to the same ED. The hospital institutional review board approved the study. The authors developed the survey tool using the modified Delphi approach after reviewing literature addressing survey tools used in the ED. We determined that nominal and descriptive responses were most useful in obtaining precise responses. Questions were reviewed by physicians in the department, and a pilot study was run from March to April 2008. The responses were used to further refine survey questions, and this was then reviewed by the IRB prior to distribution.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0009922812440840">
<title>Study Setting and Population</title>
<p>The setting was a dedicated suburban pediatric ED in a tertiary care, level I trauma center, operating 24 hours a day. The annual census recorded approximately 30 000 patient visits. We selected 4 nonconsecutive months (May, June, August, and September) to distribute a RV survey, based on the principle investigator’s availability.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0009922812440840">
<title>Study Protocol</title>
<p>The unit secretary identified each patient who had returned within 72 hours of the initial visit. During the active study periods, this was done 24 hours a day, 7 days a week. ED technicians, specifically trained to administer the survey, then conducted a brief, 2-part interview of each caregiver, using a survey instrument consisting of questions with nominal (multiple choice) and brief descriptive responses. In-house interpreters were available for Spanish speaking caregivers, and all other languages were accessed on a telephone language line. All study participants provided verbal consent.</p>
<p>Children who returned for a scheduled visit or who arrived with an unrelated chief complaint were excluded from analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0009922812440840">
<title>Measurements</title>
<p>Most questions were framed as nominal multiple-choice questions, which were then tallied into a composite result for analysis. Each family had an opportunity to provide additional descriptive comments for each question. Questions were written and presented in a manner such that they provided as much flexibility in answering as possible because the primary goal was to understand the family’s perception of the previous visit and the need for the subsequent follow-up visit.</p>
<p>Demographic data for each visit, including age, race, type of insurance, diagnosis, need for an interpreter, and final disposition were abstracted from the medical record by the principle investigator.</p>
<p>Because of limited and intermittent availability of interviewers, who were also serving in a clinical role during the study period, not all eligible patients were captured. Charts of nonsurveyed patients were analyzed, and the surveyed group was compared with the nonsurveyed group to assess the risk of inclusion bias (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0009922812440840">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0009922812440840" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Demographics and Diagnosis Comparing Those Surveyed With Those not Surveyed</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0009922812440840" xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812440840-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Surveyed</th>
<th align="center">Not Surveyed</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Total number</td>
<td>124 Caregivers</td>
<td>122 Caregivers</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Median age (in years)</td>
<td><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>3.0</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>First quartile: 1.1</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Third quartile: 12</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>2.6</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>First quartile: 1.0</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Third quartile: 11</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gender: male</td>
<td>n = 64 (52%)</td>
<td>n = 59 (49%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Common diagnosis</td>
<td><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Fever/Infectious: n = 57 (31%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>GI: n = 27 (15%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Respiratory: n = 34 (18%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Seizure disorder: n = 7 (4%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Trauma: n = 32 (17%)</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Fever/Infectious: n = 45 (23%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>GI: n = 24 (13%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Respiratory: n = 29 (15%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Seizure disorder: n = 3 (2%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Trauma: n = 22 (12%)</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ESI (1-5)</td>
<td><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Median: 3 First quartile: 3</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Third quartile: 4</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Median: 3</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>First quartile: 3</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Third quartile: 4</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Insurance</td>
<td><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Private: n = 53 (43%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Medicaid: n = 52 (42%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>None: n = 19 (5%)</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Private: n = 62 (51%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Medicaid: n = 46 (42%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>None: n = 14 (5%)</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Interpreter requested</td>
<td><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Spanish: n = 23 (18%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Other: n = 3 (2%)</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Spanish: n = 20 (16%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Other: n = 0 (0%)</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Disposition</td>
<td><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Discharged home: n = 95 (77%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Admitted total: n = 29 (23%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Admitted wards: n = 29 (23%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Admitted ICU: n = 0 (0%)</p></list-item>
</list></td>
<td><list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Discharged home: n = 103 (84%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Admitted total: n = 19 (16%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Admitted wards: n = 16 (33%)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Admitted ICU: n = 0 (0%)</p></list-item>
</list></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0009922812440840">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>Data were entered into an Excel v.11.8 (Microsoft Inc, Redmond, WA) spreadsheet and analyzed with Prism v. 4.0 (Graphpad Inc, San Diego, CA). Descriptive statistics and confidence intervals were calculated. Nominal outcomes were analyzed using χ<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0009922812440840">2</xref></sup> tests. Nonparametric comparisons were evaluated using the Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test. The α value was set at .05 for all comparisons.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0009922812440840" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>During our study period, 8742 patients were seen in the ED. Of those, we prospectively identified that 246 patients had returned within 72 hours of their initial visit. This gave us an RV rate of 2.8%. We were able to survey half of these patients (n = 124) in our study period, which left half (n = 122) unsurveyed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0009922812440840">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0009922812440840" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Study patients</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812440840-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The comparison of demographics of surveyed patients versus those that were not surveyed is noted in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0009922812440840">Table 1</xref>. The age, sex, patient acuity (Emergency Service Index [ESI code]) and type of insurance were all found to be similar between these 2 groups. There were no significant differences in ethnicity between patients either surveyed or not surveyed. It was found that the number of patients who returned was reflective of the general ED population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0009922812440840">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig2-0009922812440840" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Comparison of ethnicity between study patients and general emergency department (ED) population</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812440840-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Differences were identified among diagnoses for the 2 cohorts. There was a significant increase in the number of people surveyed who were diagnosed with fever, trauma, and seizure disorders. The remaining demographics between the 2 groups were similar. All patients who returned within 72 hours were included in this comparison (n = 246).</p>
<p>Of the 124 patients who were prospectively surveyed, scheduled revisits accounted for 14% (n = 17), and 11% (n = 14) returned for a completely different reason. These patients were excluded from analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0009922812440840">Figure 1</xref>). The remaining 75% of patients (n = 93) constituted the study population.</p>
<p>Reported satisfaction with the first ED physician encounter was 94% (n = 87). Of the 6 caregivers who were not satisfied, 5 chose the phrase “the doctor didn’t give the help that I expected” and did not choose an optional phrase specifically critical of the physician (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0009922812440840">Figure 3</xref>). Similarly, 94% (n = 87) reported that they were comfortable with their discharge instructions and felt that they were clear and informative (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0009922812440840">Figure 4</xref>). Those that had discharge instructions “not in my language” included Vietnamese (2) and Mandarin (1).</p>
<fig id="fig3-0009922812440840" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Satisfaction with emergency department (ED) physician</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812440840-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-0009922812440840" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Satisfaction with discharge instructions</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812440840-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Of 93 patients surveyed, only 53% (n = 50) contacted their primary medical doctor (PMD) prior to the second visit. Of these 50 caregivers, 28% (n = 14) could not get an appointment, and 64% (n = 32) were told by the office staff (nurse or physician) on the telephone to return to the ED. There were 6% (n = 3) of patients who were seen by their PMD that same day and sent back to the ED for reevaluation. Only 4 children did not have a PMD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0009922812440840">Figure 5</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig5-0009922812440840" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Primary care follow-up</p>
<p>Abbreviations: PMD, primary medical doctor; ED, emergency department.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812440840-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In assessing patient disposition, we found that 30% (n = 29) were admitted on the second visit to the pediatric ward, though none to the pediatric intensive care unit. Continued gastrointestinal abnormalities (31%), recurrent seizures in a child with a known seizure disorder (24%), febrile illnesses (17%), or respiratory illnesses (14%) were the most common conditions in children admitted at their second visit.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0009922812440840" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>This project evolved out of our anecdotal experience with returning patients who we felt “didn’t need to be back.” This belief arose out of the perception that, for many patients, conservative management (eg, no antibiotics for a viral illness) failed to meet the patient’s initial expectations. We suspected that although patients received a quality medical evaluation, they may not have received adequate discharge instructions, or they may not have trusted the diagnosis or opinion of the initial managing physician in the ED. Contrary to our expectations, the results of this survey suggest that most repeat pediatric ED visits are not the result of poor patient education or ineffective doctor–patient rapport and patient dissatisfaction.</p>
<p>Our research differs from prior ED studies on RVs, which focus primarily on the evaluation of medical management through retrospective chart review by physician reviewers. Such evaluation is inherently subjective, and results are likely subject to the initial bias of the investigator (much as clinicians are biased about the necessity of a patient’s RV in real time).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922812440840">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0009922812440840">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0009922812440840">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0009922812440840">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0009922812440840">12</xref></sup> Investigators with 20/20 hindsight, who are looking for evidence of physician mismanagement or inadequate discharge instruction, are likely to find it.</p>
<p>Keith et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0009922812440840">1</xref></sup> judged that 40% of patients experienced medical management deficiencies, and 35% were given inappropriate discharge or follow-up instructions. Pierce et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0009922812440840">2</xref></sup> found that physician-related factors were responsible for RVs in only 18% of cases “contrary to [their] expectations.” More recently, however, DePiero et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0009922812440840">11</xref></sup> judged that 90% of RVs resulting in admission were caused by progression of illness. In neither of these studies is the appropriateness of medical care or the provision of discharge medical education evaluated from a patient’s perspective.</p>
<p>We chose to explore the reason for the follow-up visit from the point of view of the patient and their family because their concerns and beliefs ultimately drive the decision to seek further care in the ED. Of our surveyed patients, 94% were comfortable with the care they received on their first visit. The same number reported clear, informative, and helpful (verbal and/or written) discharge instructions. Written survey comments included statements such as, “The instructions were clear and we were told exactly what to return for,” and “The nurse and doctor explained them to me (in my language) and then asked me to repeat what they said to make sure I understood.” The same percentage reported that they were satisfied with the first ED physician in response to a question assessing doctor–patient rapport. Other written comments included, “She took the time to really listen to what I had to say,” and “He answered all my questions and wasn’t rushed.”</p>
<p>Barely half of our patients contacted their PMD prior to the second visit, even though the vast majority identified a primary source of medical care. This is likely a reflection of structural deficiencies within our primary care health system.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0009922812440840">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0009922812440840">14</xref></sup> Patients may have previously experienced difficulty with scheduling same-day appointments, as reflected in survey comments such as, “I didn’t even bother calling because he can never fit me in.” Two thirds of primary care offices that were actually contacted by the patient’s family referred them back to the ED without an office evaluation.</p>
<p>Other families simply may not meet their acute care needs through their primary care physician but, instead, through the ED.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0009922812440840">8</xref></sup> Many caregivers are unable to take off from work during office hours to take their children to the PMD for reevaluation. Additionally, some families simply may not trust their primary care physicians for what they perceive as a more serious illness. This is reflected in the fact that 16 of the 39 patients who did not call their primary care physician chose the answer in our survey, “I didn’t trust my doctor/wanted a second opinion.”</p>
<p>A number of studies among pediatric and adult ED patients have been conducted to analyze the barriers to obtaining primary care follow-up and improve appointment adherence.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0009922812440840">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0009922812440840">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0009922812440840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0009922812440840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0009922812440840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0009922812440840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0009922812440840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0009922812440840"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0009922812440840">22</xref></sup> Strategies have included scheduling the follow-up appointment during the initial ED visit,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0009922812440840">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0009922812440840">18</xref></sup> receiving scheduling assistance from a health care professional,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0009922812440840">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0009922812440840">23</xref></sup> or providing a convenient location for the follow-up visit.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0009922812440840">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0009922812440840">25</xref></sup> Unfortunately, in reviewing the literature, it is clear that these strategies have had limited success in promoting more consistent follow-up.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0009922812440840">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>We found these barriers to be major factors influencing RVs in our study as well. However, this study sheds additional light on why such interventions fail to improve follow-up; they may be addressing the wrong barriers. Failure to follow-up goes beyond barriers of access. Patients frequently declare a clear preference to meet their acute care needs in the ED. Although this is not specifically the focus of the study, these findings may also have significant implications for ED use, with the anticipated expansion of health care insurance over the next decade.</p>
<p>Whether a RV to the ED is medically necessary is an inherently subjective question. Much has been written about ED overcrowding and nonurgent visits.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0009922812440840">26</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0009922812440840"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0009922812440840">28</xref></sup> From a patient’s perspective, it may be less important that a physician reviewer believes that a patient should not have returned for reevaluation. It may be impossible to fully educate a family on a single visit, and it is probably safer for the family to return if they think that their child continues to exhibit signs of significant illness versus actual progression, as evidenced by our relatively high admission rate. In truth, many of these RVs may be more of a reflection of the inadequacy of the primary care system than whether a patient needed to be seen back in the ED.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0009922812440840">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0009922812440840">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0009922812440840">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0009922812440840">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0009922812440840">21</xref></sup> Nevertheless, the literature suggests that frequent use of the ED for nonemergent care is not the primary cause of overcrowding.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0009922812440840">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0009922812440840">27</xref></sup></p>
<p>We noted a relatively high admission rate on the second visit. DePiero et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0009922812440840">11</xref></sup> looked at children admitted on the second visit to a PED and found that 90% had an appropriate ED evaluation, and admission was for progression of illness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0009922812440840">Figure 6</xref>). Though our study did not specifically focus on the medical evaluation of these patients, it is noteworthy that there was no change in diagnosis from the first visit, and none of them was admitted to the ICU. Chart review identified progression of illness, unreliable social situations, and other complicating factors as reasons for admission; some physicians made specific notations regarding a lower threshold for admission, given that it was a repeat visit.</p>
<fig id="fig6-0009922812440840" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Diagnoses of children admitted on second visit</p>
<p>Abbreviations: UTI, urinary tract infection; GI, gastrointestinal infection.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0009922812440840-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0009922812440840">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>We recognize that there are several limitations to this study. We distributed surveys during 4 nonconsecutive months and collected a convenience sample based on the availability of the technician surveyor. However, when we analyzed and compared the demographics of nonsurveyed versus surveyed patients, we found no evidence of inclusion bias.</p>
<p>This study was an assessment of patient perception and did not specifically evaluate the adequacy of the initial medical evaluation or the actual effectiveness of the discharge education. Patients may have received cursory discharge instructions that they felt were clear and yet returned because they did not fully understand them.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0009922812440840">29</xref></sup> Furthermore, a family may return for a reason such as the persistence of a high fever and perceive this to be a continuation or progression of illness rather than a failure of discharge education as the physician reviewer might. However, we feel that the patient’s perspective on the adequacy of the instruction they received is a more reliable indicator than retrospectively reviewing and judging the often minimal written instructions in the chart (or the more verbose prepopulated instructions more commonly used with computer-generated printouts), which may have little relationship with the actual discharge discussion.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0009922812440840" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In this prospective evaluation of pediatric ED repeat visits, most caregivers were satisfied with both their initial physician care and their discharge instructions. Even though most patients had a PMD, many did not call their physician prior to returning to the ED, and those who did either could not get an appointment or were simply sent back to the ED without a medical evaluation. The majority of children returned either because of clinical progression of their illness or a failure to improve during the interval period. Retrospective chart review of RVs cannot reliably be used as a quality indicator for patient satisfaction with the initial medical encounter or quality of discharge instructions. Despite clear and informative discharge instructions and high patient satisfaction, many families return for repeat evaluations, with many citing real or perceived barriers to primary care follow-up.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authorws received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0009922812440840">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Keith</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bocka</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kobernick</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Emergency department revisits</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>964</fpage>-<lpage>968</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0009922812440840">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kellerman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>“Bounces”: an analysis of short-term return visits to a public hospital emergency department</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>752</fpage>-<lpage>757</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0009922812440840">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>An</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Initial emergency department diagnosis and return visits: risk versus perception</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>569</fpage>-<lpage>573</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0009922812440840">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCarten-Gibbs</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeNoble</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Repeat pediatric visits to a general emergency department</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>467</fpage>-<lpage>473</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0009922812440840">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alessandrini</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lavelle</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grenfell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Return visits within 48 hours to a pediatric emergency department</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Emerg Care</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>166</fpage>-<lpage>171</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0009922812440840">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Risk Management in the Emergency Medicine</source>. <publisher-loc>Dallas, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American College of Emergency Physicians</publisher-name>; <year>1985</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0009922812440840">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weinstock</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Factors impacting on return visits to a pediatric emergency department</article-title>. <source>Am J Dis Child</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>425</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0009922812440840">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gregor</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mahajan</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maio</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Piette</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
</person-group>; <collab>Great Lakes Emergency Medical Services for Children Research Network</collab>. <article-title>Caregiver adherence to follow-up after an emergency department visit for common pediatric illnesses: impact on future ED use</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>326</fpage>-<lpage>333</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0009922812440840">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>LeDuc</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosebrook</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rannie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pediatric emergency department recidivism: demographic characteristics and diagnostic predictors</article-title>. <source>J Emerg Nurs</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>-<lpage>138</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0009922812440840">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rimsza</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effects of access to pediatric care and insurance coverage on emergency department utilization</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>483</fpage>-<lpage>487</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0009922812440840">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DePiero</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ochsenschlager</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chamberlain</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of pediatric hospitalizations after emergency department release as a quality improvement tool</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>-<lpage>163</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0009922812440840">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lerman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kobernick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Return visits to the emergency department</article-title>. <source>J Emerg Med</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>359</fpage>-<lpage>362</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0009922812440840">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goepp</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malia</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poordabbagh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nonurgent use of a pediatric emergency department: a preliminary qualitative study</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Emerg Care</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>-<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0009922812440840">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Halfon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newacheck</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>St Peter</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Routine emergency department use for sick care by children in the United States</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>28</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0009922812440840">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barlas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Homan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rakowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>How well do patients obtain short-term follow-up after discharge from the emergency department?</article-title> <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>610</fpage>-<lpage>614</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0009922812440840">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chande</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wyss</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Exum</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Educational interventions to alter pediatric emergency department utilization patterns</article-title>. <source>Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>150</volume>:<fpage>525</fpage>-<lpage>528</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0009922812440840">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kallis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonzalez del Ray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruddy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Linking emergency department patients to PC: phone vs. face-to-face interaction</article-title>. <source>Acad Emerg Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>817</fpage>-<lpage>822</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0009922812440840">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Komorski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A comparison of interventions to improve clinic follow-up compliance after a pediatric emergency department visit</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Emerg Care</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>90</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0009922812440840">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vanko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Follow-up compliance after emergency department evaluation</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>560</fpage>-<lpage>567</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0009922812440840">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Cleve</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Improving the use of early follow-up care after emergency department visits</article-title>. <source>Am J Dis Child</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>145</volume>:<fpage>440</fpage>-<lpage>444</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0009922812440840">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barlas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Homan</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Radkowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Houck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thode</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>How well do patients obtain short-term follow-up after discharge from the emergency department?</article-title> <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>610</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0009922812440840">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vieth</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thodes</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nonprice barriers to ambulatory care after an emergency department visit</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>607</fpage>-<lpage>613</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0009922812440840">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Decreasing nonurgent emergency department utilization by Medicaid children</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0009922812440840">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vivier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewander</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Is continuity of care preserved in children who utilize the pediatric emergency department?</article-title> <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0009922812440840">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Teach</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quint</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Improved asthma outcomes in a high morbidity pediatric population</article-title>. <source>Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>535</fpage>-<lpage>541</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0009922812440840">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Minkovitz</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of pediatric emergency department use at an urban medical center</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Emerg Care</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>84</fpage>-<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0009922812440840">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moskop</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sklar</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Geiderman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schears</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bookman</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Emergency department crowding, part 1: concept, causes, and moral consequences</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>605</fpage>-<lpage>611</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0009922812440840">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schull</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Szalai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of low-complexity patients on emergency department waiting times</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>257</fpage>-<lpage>264</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0009922812440840">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heisler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ubel</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Patient comprehension of emergency department care and instructions: are patients aware of when they do not understand?</article-title> <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>454</fpage>-<lpage>461</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>