<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DIJ</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdij</journal-id>
         <journal-title>Drug Information Journal</journal-title>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">0092-8615</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0092861512445792</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0092861512445792</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Commentary</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Editor’s Commentary: Assessing Worst-Case Scenarios in Regulatory Science</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Turner</surname>
                  <given-names>J. Rick</given-names>
               </name>
               <degrees>PhD</degrees>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0092861512445792"/>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff1-0092861512445792">Editor-in-Chief</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
            <month>5</month>
            <year>2012</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>46</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <fpage>283</fpage>
         <lpage>285</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder content-type="society">Drug Information Association</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Last year we introduced several new categories of submissions, including Letters to the Editor. The first two letters were published in the September 2011 issue of the Journal, one from Dr Norman Stockbridge (FDA) and the other from Dr Larry Satin (Cardiocore). Both letters addressed an Expert Commentary on ambulatory blood pressure measurement (ABPM) by Professor Eoin O’Brien entitled “Why ABPM Should Be Mandatory in All Trials of Blood Pressure–Lowering Drugs.”<sup>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0092861512445792">1</xref>
         </sup> Of note is that one comment contained in Dr Stockbridge’s letter has already been highlighted by speakers at several international conferences, and has therefore generated ongoing discussion.</p>
      <p>This issue of the Journal contains two Commentary pieces, one from Associate Editor Peter Pitts (president, Center for Medicine in the Public Interest, New York) and the other from Dr Michael Weber (professor of medicine at SUNY Downstate College of Medicine and chairman of the Center for Medicine in the Public Interest). They discuss issues of central importance to the practice of medicine in the United States, and Letters to the Editor from readers in response to these issues are encouraged.</p>
      <sec id="section1-0092861512445792">
         <title>Assessing Worst-Case Scenarios in Regulatory Science</title>
         <p>In many randomized, concurrently controlled, double-blind phase III clinical trials, a subject sample is chosen from the population of all possible subjects, and this sample is then randomized to the drug treatment group or the control treatment group. Analysis of the trial’s data provides a precise result for that particular sample. While this sample can contain several thousand subjects, this is likely to be a (very) small percentage of the population from which it was chosen, in other words the population of individuals in the general population who might be prescribed the drug in the future should it be approved. The primary goal of the trial is not to observe what responses were shown by the subjects who participated, but to use the results obtained to gain insight into what would likely be seen in the population of potential future patients.</p>
         <p>If a different sample of subjects had been chosen, the chance of the data obtained being identical is so infinitesimally small that we can safely say that they would be different. The question of interest becomes: How different would they likely be? Ideally, we would like them to be similar, thus generating a result that is similar to the result of the original trial: The more similar the results from a second trial, the more confidence we could reasonably place in the results from the original trial.</p>
         <p>The word <italic>confidence</italic> in the previous sentence occurs in the general language use of the word. In contrast, in the discipline of Statistics the word is used in a specific way when discussing confidence intervals. While one-sided confidence intervals are legitimately used in some circumstances, present discussions focus on two-sided confidence intervals. A two-sided confidence interval constitutes a range of values defined by the lower limit and the upper limit of the confidence interval. These limits are placed around the treatment effect calculated from a trial’s results, which in this context is referred to as the <italic>treatment effect point estimate</italic>. The confidence interval represents a range of values that is likely to cover the true but unknown population treatment effect with a specified degree of certainly. While this degree can theoretically take any percentage value greater than zero and less than 100, three levels are commonly used: the 90%, 95%, and 99% levels. Discussions here focus on the 95% confidence level, but they are generalizable to any other level.</p>
         <p>Placing a two-sided 95% confidence interval (95% CI) around a treatment estimate (from a single trial or from a meta-analysis of more than 1 trial; see later) allows the following statement to be made:</p>
         <list list-type="simple">
            <list-item>
               <p> The lower limit and upper limit of the confidence interval placed around the treatment effect point estimate delineate a range of values that we are 95% confident will cover the true but unknown population effect.</p>
            </list-item>
         </list>
         <p>The treatment effect point estimate in question can be either an <italic>efficacy point estimate</italic> or a <italic>safety point estimate</italic>. In the former case, the efficacy treatment effect is ideally large enough to provide compelling evidence of statistically and clinically significant therapeutic benefit and to outweigh any safety concerns, thus leading to a favorable benefit-risk profile. In the latter case, ideally the safety treatment effect is as small as possible, and, when compared with the therapeutic benefit of the drug, it is an “acceptable” adverse event in that the benefit-risk profile is also favorable.</p>
         <sec id="section2-0092861512445792">
            <title>Employment of Confidence Intervals in Efficacy Analyses</title>
            <p>Consider a randomized, double-blind, concurrently controlled phase III clinical trial involving a new investigative drug intended to raise high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol (HDLc), the “good cholesterol.” One group of subjects receives the investigational drug, and a second group receives a control drug (in this case a placebo). The magnitude of the drug’s treatment effect in this particular trial (its efficacy) is calculated by subtracting the mean magnitude of change in HDLc for subjects in the placebo group from its mean magnitude for subjects in the drug treatment group. When gaining insight into the likely response of the general patient population should the drug be approved, the treatment effect is now referred to as the treatment effect point estimate, and a two-sided 95% CI is placed around this point estimate. The computations involved in the calculation of the lower and upper limits are not necessary here; it is sufficient to note that they will lie equidistantly from the treatment effect point estimate, since a value X is first subtracted from the point estimate to determine the lower limit, and then added to the point estimate to determine the upper limit.</p>
            <p>Imagine a point estimate of 8.00 mg/dL, and lower and upper limits of the two-sided 95% CI of 1.50 mg/dL and 14.50 mg/dL, respectively. (The unit of measurement for cholesterol employed in this example is one of several possibilities, but the logic is the same for all such units.) This information is often presented as: 8.00 mg/dL (95% CI, 1.50-14.50). The following statement can now be made: </p>
            <list list-type="simple">
               <list-item>
                  <p> The data obtained from this single trial are compatible with a treatment effect in the general population as small as 1.50 mg/dL and as large as 14.50 mg/dL, and our best estimate is 8.00 mg/dL. </p>
               </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>When regulators examine these results at the time of the drug’s marketing application, the important question is this: Is the increase represented by the worst-case scenario clinically significant? The worst-case scenario is provided by the lower limit of the confidence interval. That is, an increase of only 1.50 mg/dL is (still) compatible with the data from this trial. While all increases are theoretically beneficial, it might be decided that this increase is too small to warrant approving the drug, especially if there are already drugs on the market with good (or better) safety profiles and that confer greater therapeutic benefit. This outcome is possible even though the upper limit of the confidence interval, which here represents the best-case scenario, provides evidence that a therapeutic benefit of 14.50 mg/dL is (still) compatible with data from this trial.</p>
            <p>The worst-case scenario is therefore the one influencing the regulatory decision. </p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="section3-0092861512445792">
            <title>Employment of Confidence Intervals in Safety Analyses</title>
            <p>Many analyses conducted while assessing a drug’s safety profile are not inferential; descriptive statistics are by far the most common (this avoids multiplicity issues associated with multiple inferential tests). However, in several circumstances, an inferential analysis is needed, and confidence intervals play a central role. One example is contained in the December 2008 FDA Guidance for Industry entitled “Diabetes Mellitus—Evaluating Cardiovascular Risk in New Antidabetic Drugs to Treat Type 2 Diabetes.”<sup>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0092861512445792">2</xref>
               </sup> At the end of a drug’s preapproval development program, a meta-analysis is conducted using essentially all phase II and phase III data to compare the number of centrally adjudicated cardiovascular adverse events in the drug group with those in the control group. This is done by calculating a <italic>relative risk ratio</italic>, with the number of events in the drug treatment group as the numerator and the number in the control group as the denominator. If the numbers were to be identical (a vanishingly small probability), the relative risk ratio would be unity, expressed here as 1.00. If the number of events in the drug treatment group were greater than those in the control treatment group, the relative risk ratio would be greater than unity, indicating a greater cardiovascular risk being associated with the drug (a relative risk ratio less than unity indicates that the drug is cardioprotective). The guideline requires demonstration that any increased risk must be below a designated threshold of regulatory concern: If so, and the drug shows sufficient efficacy, its overall benefit-risk profile may be deemed favorable, and the drug approved. (See Caveney and Turner<sup>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0092861512445792">3</xref>
               </sup> for a more detailed exposition, including additional evidence that most likely will be required from a postmarketing cardiovascular outcomes trial.) </p>
            <p>The threshold of regulatory concern is an upper limit of a two-sided 95% confidence interval placed around the relative risk point estimate given by the meta-analysis of 1.80: values of 1.8 or greater breach this threshold. Given that division is involved in the calculation of a relative risk ratio, the lower and upper limits of a confidence interval do not lie equidistant from the point estimate: the upper limit will always be further away from it than the lower limit. Therefore, imagine the hypothetical example of a relative risk point estimate of 1.20, a lower limit of 1.10, and an upper limit of 1.35. This can be written as 1.20 (95% CI, 1.10-1.35). In combination with the relative risk ratio point estimate, these confidence limits allow the following statement to be made:</p>
            <list list-type="simple">
               <list-item>
                  <p> The data obtained from this meta-analysis are compatible with as little as a 10% increase and as much as a 35% increase in the risk of cardiovascular events in the general population, and our best estimate is an increase of 20%.</p>
               </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>Of course, any increase in risk is not ideal, which is why regulators must use a benefit-risk analysis, balancing any risk against likely therapeutic benefit, all in the context of the seriousness of the disease of interest and the extent of availability of other therapeutic agents. In the case of the present example, if there is sufficiently compelling evidence of a therapeutic benefit afforded by the antidiabetic agent, it may receive marketing approval even though it is associated with up to a 35% greater risk of cardiovascular events. </p>
            <p>Note that in this scenario, it is the upper limit of the confidence interval placed around the treatment effect (relative risk ratio) point estimate that captures the worst-case scenario; the lower limit, which here represents the best-case scenario, indicates that there may be as little as a 10% increase in the risk of cardiovascular events. </p>
            <p>Before moving to the final section of this commentary, another point should be addressed here. While the approach taken by regulators in the prospective exclusion of unacceptable cardiovascular risk requires such a threshold to be made explicit, relative risk alone does not capture the whole picture of interest to individual patients and their physicians. If the risk of an event is 1.00 in 10 in one group and 1.35 in 10 (ie, 35% greater) in a second group, it can be correctly stated that the risk in the second group is 35% greater. However, the same statement can be made for a risk of 1.00 in a million in one group and 1.35 in a million in the second group. While the increase in relative risk is the same in both of these scenarios, in contrast to the first scenario the absolute risk has changed extremely slightly in the second scenario. Therefore, wherever possible, a difference in risk between two situations is always best addressed by presenting information concerning both relative risk and absolute risk.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="section4-0092861512445792">
            <title>The Confidence Limit of Primary Interest</title>
            <p>From the perspective of regulatory decision making (always intended to protect and promote public health), the worst-case scenario is always of primary interest. This is true for both efficacy and safety assessments. For efficacy assessments, the worst-case scenario represents the least likely benefit. For safety assessments, the worst-case scenario represents the greatest likely risk.</p>
            <p>In contrast to this similarity, the worst-case scenario in efficacy assessments (ie, the least likely therapeutic benefit) is represented by the lower limit of a confidence interval placed around the treatment effect point estimate, whereas the worst-case scenario in safety assessments (ie, the greatest likely risk) is represented by the upper limit of a confidence interval placed around the treatment effect point estimate. Regulatory science therefore employs worst-case scenarios to protect public health from risks considered too great, and to promote public health by ensuring that sufficient therapeutic benefit is provided by approved drugs.</p>
         </sec>
      </sec>
      <sig-block>
         <sig>J. Rick Turner, PhD<break/>
            <italic>Editor-in-Chief</italic>
         </sig>
      </sig-block>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="bibr1-0092861512445792">
            <label>1</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>O’Brien</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Why ABPM should be mandatory in all trials of blood pressure–lowering drugs</article-title>. <source>Drug Information Journal</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr2-0092861512445792">
            <label>2</label>
            <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
               <collab collab-type="author" xlink:type="simple">Guidance for industry: diabetes mellitus—evaluating cardiovascular risk in new antidiabetic therapies to treat type diabetes</collab>. <article-title>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services Food and Drug Administration Center for Drug Evaluation and Research (CDER)</article-title>. <comment>December 2008. Available at</comment> 
               <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/downloads/drugs/guidancecomplianceregulatoryinformation/guidances/ucm071627.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.fda.gov/downloads/drugs/guidancecomplianceregulatoryinformation/guidances/ucm071627.pdf</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed March 6, 2012</comment>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="bibr3-0092861512445792">
            <label>3</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Caveney</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Turner</surname>
                     <given-names>JR</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>. <article-title>Regulatory landscapes for future antidiabetic drug development (Part I): FDA guidance on assessment of cardiovascular risk</article-title>. <source>J Clin Studies</source>. <year>2010</year>:<fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>