<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSW</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjsw</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Social Work</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1468-0173</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-296X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1468017312457945</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1468017312457945</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Tom Keenan, <italic>‘Crossing the Acts’: The support and protection of adults at risk with mental disorder; across the Scottish legislative frameworks</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Roger</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1468017312457945">Open University in Scotland, Edinburgh, Scotland</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>226</fpage>
<lpage>227</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1468017312457945"><title>Tom Keenan, <italic>‘Crossing the Acts’: The support and protection of adults at risk with mental disorder; across the Scottish legislative frameworks</italic>. Birmingham: Venture Press, 2011, 231 pp., £17.95(pbk), ISBN 9 781661780867.</title>
<sec id="sec2-1468017312457945"><title><bold>Reviewed by</bold>: Roger Davis, <italic>Open University in Scotland, Edinburgh, Scotland</italic></title>
<p>In her foreword Professor Atkinson notes that this book ‘tackles the unenviable task of leading us through the Acts’ – these being the Adults with Incapacity (Scotland) Act 2000, the Mental Health (Care and Treatment) (Scotland) Act 2003 and the Adult Support and Protection (Scotland) Act 2007. This unenviable and, indeed, ambitious work takes us on a journey through the complicated interrelationships between these Acts and which face the practitioner in providing support and protection for adults at risk with mental disorder. At its heart lies the belief that adults at risk, most of whom are adults affected by mental disorder, are presently not best served by practitioners where a dearth of a creative use of the three main Acts exists. It suggests that practitioners may be more familiar with, and therefore more likely to make inquiries and intervene through, the lens of one or other of these Acts.</p>
<p>Cutting straight to the chase the author in the first few pages provides an outline of the background to the Acts supported by a myriad of Mental Welfare Commission statistics. The casual reader will by now have moved off elsewhere but for the key practitioners that this book is aimed at the rewards of staying the course soon emerges.</p>
<p>This is not an academic book – with only a few exceptions all its references are drawn from the Mental Welfare Commission and the Scottish Executive/Government – and also, on occasion, the author relies on unattributed anecdotal evidence. Nor does it attempt to set the Scottish legislation and practice in a UK or international context with no reference, for example, to the impending and world leading Mental Capacity (Health, Welfare and Finance) Bill in Northern Ireland or to any of the discussion that lies in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1468017312457945">Mackay (2012)</xref> on the diverging nature of mental health social work in the light of the new Acts in Scotland, and in England and Wales. Nor still is this a handbook for practitioners, but rather what it does attempt is an opening up of a discussion of how best the key practitioners who are involved in the lives of adults at risk with mental disorder can, through a close understanding of the inter relationships between the three Acts, become more adept at finding the most appropriate line of inquiry and intervention.</p>
<p>The book is set out in four parts and takes the reader through the risk environment, the detail of the provisions of the Acts themselves, the powers and duties that the Acts convey and finally how the Acts intertwine – the ‘crossing of the Acts’ of the title. To help the reader the author usefully provides seven case studies which thread themselves through the work and help to bring aspects of the Acts’ interrelations to life. There are also some 41 appendices designed to assist the reader relate the discussion to practice and 15 tables built into the text fulfilling a similar objective. In looking at the risk or harm environment facing adults with mental disorder the author teases out the range of difficulties practitioners face in utilising the relevant legislations, using the middle two parts to fully explore the Acts in detail. It is Part 4 though that draws the reader back into the mix with Chapters 10 and 11 in particular tying the Acts together into practice. The author here offers a good perspective on the pragmatic approach often required to manage risk whilst maintaining a flexible and creative view of how the intertwining Acts can be used to maximise the principles of participation, empowerment and advocacy that underpin all three Acts, helpfully listing key questions the practitioner could be asking themselves.</p>
<p>By its own admission this book has a rather narrow audience – they being the key practitioners from the professions working with adults at risk with mental disorder. That however should not detract from the important questions this book asks of its audience and the debates that it should stimulate. Credit goes to the author for opening up the discussion.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>Reference</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1468017312457945"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The parting of the ways? The diverging nature of mental health social work in the light of the new Acts in Scotland, and in England and Wales</article-title>. <source>Journal of Social Work</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>