<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="news">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SJP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsjp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Scand J Public Health</journal-id>
<journal-title>Scandinavian Journal of Public Health</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1403-4948</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1651-1905</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1403494812460448</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1403494812460448</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>News from the National Institutes of Public Health</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>News from the National Institutes of Public Health</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>582</fpage>
<lpage>582</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 the Nordic Societies of Public Health</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Associations of Public Health in the Nordic Countries Regions</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1403494812460448">
<title>The National Institute for Health and Welfare in Finland (THL)</title>
<p>The National Institute for Health and Welfare (THL) is a research and development institute under the Finnish Ministry of Social Affairs and Health.</p>
<p>The institute works to promote the well-being and health of the population, to prevent diseases and social problems, and to develop social and health services. It is the statutory statistical authority in health and welfare and maintains a strong knowledge base within its own field of operation. THL is also responsible for the application of this knowledge.</p>
<p>The institute has a wide range of tools to carry out its responsibilities: research, follow-up and evaluation, development, expert influence, official tasks and international cooperation. It serves the scientific community, actors in the field, and decision-makers in central government and municipalities, as well as serving the broader society.</p>
<p>The institute started operating on 1 January 2009, after the merger of the National Public Health Institute (KTL) and the national Research and Development Centre for Welfare and Health (STAKES).</p>
<p>The institute’s functions are:</p>
<list id="list1-1403494812460448" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>To promote the welfare and health of the population</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>To prevent diseases and social problems</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>To develop social and health services</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The institute’s headquarters are located in Helsinki. It also has satellite offices in Jyväskylä, Kuopio, Oulu, Tampere, Turku and Vaasa. THL has a total staff of about 1,300 and is subject to the performance guidance of the Ministry of Social Affairs and Health.</p>
<sec id="section2-1403494812460448">
<title>Physical inactivity has a major health effect worldwide</title>
<p>A recent study ranks physical inactivity among smoking and obesity as the major risk factors for chronic diseases. The study reveals that lack of physical activity accounts for 6% of the global heart disease morbidity, 7% of type 2 diabetes, and 10% of breast and colon cancers. Physical inactivity caused as many as 5.3 million of the 57 million deaths that occurred worldwide in 2008.</p>
<p>These findings are partly based on THL research data. The article “Effect of physical inactivity on major non-communicable diseases worldwide: an analysis of burden of disease and life expectancy” was published in the <italic>Lancet</italic> in July 2012.</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736%2812%2961031-9/fulltext">www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736%2812%2961031-9/fulltext</ext-link></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1403494812460448">
<title>Milder lager for sale in Finland to cut down alcohol intake</title>
<p>Whether or not the freshly launched milder beer will break through in Finland will depend on consumers. THL’s director general, Pekka Puska, is pleased with the decision taken by two Finnish breweries to introduce a milder lager beer with an alcohol content of 3.5% (known as “folköl” in Sweden).</p>
<p>Alcohol use has quadrupled in Finland over the past decades, and adverse alcohol-related effects have multiplied. Beer accounts for almost half of all alcohol consumed by Finns today. As mass-produced beer is sold everywhere and the marketing is forceful, the most health promoting measure, proposed by THL, would be to reduce the alcohol content of beer. Now, the brewing companies have met the health experts halfway and the need to regulate the alcohol content of beer by law is less urgent.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
</article>